<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->
<!-- Olga A. Hernandez Papers -->
<!-- Created: Sat May 26 12:19:36 2018 -->
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vif00106">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">

<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViF">
PUBLIC "-//Fairfax County Public Library//TEXT (US::ViF::vif00106::A Guide to the Olga A. Hernandez Papers)//EN" "vif00106.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Olga A. Hernandez Papers, <date>2003-2013</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Olga A. Hernandez Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">MSS 06-97</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<!-- This puts in text for the boilerplate information about FCPL - address, phone number, etc.
     Text lives in a separate file. -->
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/fairfax_address.xi.xml"/>
 
<!-- This must be here so that the publication date appears in search results -->
<date type="publication">© 2018 Fairfax County Public Library. All rights reserved.</date>
</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Ross Landis, <date>May 26, 2018</date>
</creation>

<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langusage>

</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>

<titleproper>A Guide to the Olga A. Hernandez Papers, <date>2003-2013</date></titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in The Fairfax County Public Library<lb/>
<num type="Record Group Number">MSS 06-97</num>
</subtitle>

<!-- This puts in the JPEG of the logo. -->
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
 xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/FairfaxCoPL.jpg"/>
</p>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<archdesc level="collection">

<runner placement="footer">Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</runner>

<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Fairfax County Public Library</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">The Olga A. Hernandez Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2003-2013</unitdate></unittitle>
<unitid label="Record Group Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MSS 06-97</unitid>

<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">
<extent>
0.75 linear feet
</extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>

<abstract label="Abstract" encodinganalog="520$a">
The Olga A. Hernandez Papers consist of 0.75 linear feet and span the years 2003-2013. The collection contains correspondence; committee and commission member lists; meeting agendas and summaries; work plans; working papers, and reports; newsletters; and other working papers from her involvement with the Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee and Fairfax County Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission.
</abstract>

<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
Hernandez, Olga A.
</origination>

</did>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information</head>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions</head>
<p>None</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions</head>
<p>Consult repository for information</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Olga A. Hernandez Papers, MSS 06-97, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</p>
</prefercite>

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information</head>
<p>Donated by Olga A. Hernandez in February 2018</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Jessica Koenig, April 2018<lb/>EAD generated by Ross Landis, 2018</p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical and Biographical Information</head>
<p>Born in Cuba, but raised in Miami, Florida, Olga A. Hernandez became a naturalized citizen at 18. She graduated from the University of Florida with a degree in broadcast journalism. She moved to Virginia in 1995, and has been involved with the League of Women Voters of Virginia for more than 20 years.  She became a board member of the League of Women Voters of the Fairfax Area in 1996, and served as its president from 2000 to 2005. From 2005 to 2007, she served as the vice president and director of the League of Women Voters of Virginia. In 2007, she was elected president of the League of Women Voters of Virginia, an office held for four years. During her role as president, she moderated the Women's Roundtable meetings during the General Assembly sessions. She has organized statewide televised gubernatorial and US Senate debates as well as debates and forums for local elections in the Fairfax area.</p>
<p>In 2005, Hernandez was appointed to the Fairfax County Virginia 2007 Community Citizen Planning Committee, acting as the representative from the League of Women Voters of the Fairfax Area and served on the Public Information Subcommittee.  The committee was formed as part of the Virginia 2007 Community Program, a statewide initiative launched as part of the Jamestown 2007 project commemorating the 400th anniversary of the founding of Jamestown. The committee was tasked with developing and implementing projects and activities to enhance awareness of the county’s role in the history of Virginia and the nation. Signature projects resulting from the committee’s efforts included publication of Fairfax County Stories 1607-2007, a legacy book of essays written by county residents on events, localities, and subjects of historical significance in the county from 1607 to 2007; production of a series of 10 one-minute public service announcements in collaboration with Fairfax County Government Television Channel 16, highlighting important events and figures in the county’s history; planting of several cherrybark oak seedlings on the grounds of the Fairfax County Government Center, grown from seeds collected on Jamestowne Island; and a Jamestown exhibit displayed at the Fairfax County Government Center.</p>
<p>Hernandez was actively involved in the fight for non-partisan redistricting in Virginia for decades. Most recently, she worked with the non-profit OneVirginia2021 as a representative of the League of Women Voters of the Fairfax Area to educate the public about “gerrymandering,” the process by which the sitting legislature draws district lines to pack voters into districts in a way that ensures incumbents keep their seats.</p>
<p>Hernandez was also involved in a number of efforts to prevent restrictions and barriers to voter registration and access, including serving as the representative for the League of Women Voters of the Fairfax Area on the Fairfax County Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission. The commission was created by the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors following the November 2012 election, which experienced long voting lines and other issues that can restrict voter access. The commission was charged with improving the county’s election process by evaluating voting precinct locations, size, parking, and space; equipment number, type, and compliance with industry standards; number and processes for identification and training of election workers; processes for approval and assignment of election officials; and the county’s absentee voting policy. The commission presented a final report to the Board of Supervisors on March 19, 2013.</p>
<p>Hernandez served on the Help America Vote Act committee for Virginia, the Virginia State Board of Elections Residency Task Force, and state Census Complete Count Committee. She was an officer of the Virginia Coalition for Open Government and the League of Women Voters of the National Capital Area and served on various community committees. She worked extensively with Girl Scouts USA, various PTA organizations, military community groups, and other non-profit and volunteer efforts. Hernandez was recognized by the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations as the 2015 Fairfax County Citizen of the Year for her extensive and diverse volunteer efforts, including efforts to make Fairfax and Virginia residents more informed voters.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$b">
<head>Scope and Content</head>
<p>The Olga A. Hernandez Papers consist of 0.75 linear feet and span the years 2003-2013. The collection contains correspondence; committee and commission member lists; meeting agendas and summaries; work plans; working papers, and reports; newsletters; and other working papers from her involvement with the Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee and Fairfax County Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission. Subjects include Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee participation in the Virginia 2007 Community Program and Jamestown 2007; Fairfax County Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission; and events and statistics of the November 2012 election in Fairfax County.</p>
<p><emph render="boldunderline">Series 1: Virginia 2007 Community Program - Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee, 2003-2007, Box 1</emph></p>
<p>This series contains materials relating to Hernandez’s involvement with the Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee as part of the Virginia 2007 Community Program. Items include committee meeting agendas and summaries; committee membership lists; committee work plans and timelines; the final committee report; correspondence; newsletters, background information, and brochures for the Jamestown 2007 and Virginia 2007 programs; press releases; news articles and coverage; a program from the Reston Chorale “Foundations of Freedom” Program; materials from the Virginia 2007 Community Program annual meeting; a photocopy of the Virginia 2007 Community Program Certificate of Recognition; and a list of Virginia 2007 themed months.</p>
<p><emph render="boldunderline">Series 2: Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission, 2012-2013, Box 2</emph></p>
<p>This series contains materials relating to Hernandez’s involvement with the Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission. Documents include background information on topics related to voting issues, including statistics, procedures, and summaries on election officers, provisional ballots, absentee voting, voter registration, voting machines, pollbooks, and election returns; a brochure on laws about voting in Fairfax County; comments received from the public, poll workers, and election officers and chiefs on issues encountered or witnessed while voting during the November 2012 election; the letter and introduction packet appointing Olga Hernandez to the commission; a list of commission members; agendas and summaries of commission meetings; draft and final versions of the commission’s report to the Board of Supervisors; the commission’s work plan and schedule; the Fairfax County Electoral Board’s report documenting their response to the commission’s recommendations; background information on election officers, such as duties, recruitment efforts, training, and salary; background information on the use of school as polling places, such as relevant regulations and building statistics for high schools and middle schools in the county; background information on and recommendations from the Office of Elections; agendas and attached information for public hearings related to amendments to county codes on election precincts and absentee voting satellite locations; and a Quick Reference to Problems guide issued by the State Board of Elections.  </p>
</scopecontent>


<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>The Fairfax County Stories 1607 - 2007 Manuscript Papers, MSS 08-12, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>None</p>
</separatedmaterial>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- Index/Search terms go here - categorized appropriately

See page 38-39 for information on differentiated vs. undifferentiated lists.

Going to do undifferentiated.

<persname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</persname>
<famname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</famname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">^%term%</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">^%term%</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">^%term%</geogname>
<title encodinganalog="630$a">^%term%</title>
<function encodinganalog="657$a">^%term%</function>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">^%term%</genreform>
<occupation encodinganalog="656$a">^%term%</occupation>
-->

<!-- Example:
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Oak Hill</subject>
__index__terms_25__
</controlaccess>
-->

<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Elections - Virginia - Fairfax County</subject>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Fairfax County 2007 Community Citizen Planning Committee</corpname>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Fairfax County Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission</subject>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hernandez, Olga A.</persname>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Jamestown 2007</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Virginia 2007 Community Program</subject>
</controlaccess>

<!-- Begin Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<dsc type = "combined">
<head>Container List</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 1:  Virginia 2007 Community Program - Fairfax County Citizen Planning Committee,
<unitdate>2003-2007</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">1
</container>
<unittitle>2007 Legacy Book Submissions, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">2
</container>
<unittitle>Committee Meeting Agendas and Summaries, 
<unitdate>2005 January-2007 October
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">3
</container>
<unittitle>Committee Membership Lists, 
<unitdate>2006 January-2006 April
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">4
</container>
<unittitle>Committee Report to Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, 
<unitdate>2007 November
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">5
</container>
<unittitle>Committee Work Plans, 
<unitdate>2005 July-2006 January
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">6
</container>
<unittitle>Committee Work Plan Timelines, 
<unitdate>2004 July-2006 January
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">7
</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence, 
<unitdate>2006 February-2006 October
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">8
</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence - Appointment as Committee Member, 
<unitdate>2005 June-2006 July
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">9
</container>
<unittitle>Jamestown 2007 and Virginia 2007 Background Information, 
<unitdate>2005 January
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">10
</container>
<unittitle>Jamestown 2007 and Virginia 2007 Brochures, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">11
</container>
<unittitle>Jamestown 2007 Newsletters, 
<unitdate>2003-2004
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">12
</container>
<unittitle>Jamestown 2007 Steering Committee Annual Report, 
<unitdate>2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">13
</container>
<unittitle>News and Media, 
<unitdate>2003 September-2007 July
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">14
</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases, 
<unitdate>2003 October-2006 April
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">15
</container>
<unittitle>Reston Chorale “Foundations of Freedom” Program, 
<unitdate>2007 May
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">16
</container>
<unittitle>Virginia 2007 Community Program Annual Meeting Materials, 
<unitdate>2006 January
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">17
</container>
<unittitle>Virginia 2007 Community Program Certificate of Recognition [photocopy], 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">18
</container>
<unittitle>Virginia 2007 Themed Months, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 2: Bipartisan Election Process Improvement Commission,
<unitdate>2012-2013</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">1
</container>
<unittitle>Background Information on Voting Issues, 
<unitdate>2013 February
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">2
</container>
<unittitle>Brochure on Laws about Voting in Fairfax County, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">3
</container>
<unittitle>Comments on Voting Issues during November 2012 Election, 
<unitdate>2012 November-2013 February
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">4
</container>
<unittitle>Commission Appointment Information, 
<unitdate>2012 November-2012 December
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">5
</container>
<unittitle>Commission Members, 
<unitdate>2012 December
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">6
</container>
<unittitle>Commission Meeting Agendas and Summaries, 
<unitdate>2013 January-2013 March
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">7
</container>
<unittitle>Commission Report to the Board of Supervisors (Draft and Final), 
<unitdate>2013 March
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">8
</container>
<unittitle>Commission Work Plan and Schedule, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">9
</container>
<unittitle>Fairfax County Electoral Board Response to Commission Recommendations, 
<unitdate>2014 May
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">10
</container>
<unittitle>Information on Election Officers, 
<unitdate>2013 February
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">11
</container>
<unittitle>Information on Schools as Polling Places, 
<unitdate>Undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">12
</container>
<unittitle>Office of Elections Background and Recommendations, 
<unitdate>2013 February
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">13
</container>
<unittitle>Public Hearing Agendas, 
<unitdate>2012 January; 2012 July
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">2
</container>
<container label = "Folder" type = "folder">14
</container>
<unittitle>State Board of Elections Quick Reference to Problems Guide, 
<unitdate>2012 September
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

</archdesc>
</ead>