<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->
<!-- Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books -->
<!-- Created: Sat Dec  8 12:48:50 2018 -->
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vif00122">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">

<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViF">
PUBLIC "-//Fairfax County Public Library//TEXT (US::ViF::vif00122::A Guide to the Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books)//EN" "vif00122.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books, <date>1895-1902</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books
<num type="collectionnumber">MSS 06-103</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<!-- This puts in text for the boilerplate information about FCPL - address, phone number, etc.
     Text lives in a separate file. -->
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/fairfax_address.xi.xml"/>
 
<!-- This must be here so that the publication date appears in search results -->
<date type="publication">© 2018 Fairfax County Public Library. All rights reserved.</date>
</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Ross Landis, <date>December 8, 2018</date>
</creation>

<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langusage>

</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>

<titleproper>A Guide to the Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books, <date>1895-1902</date></titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in The Fairfax County Public Library<lb/>
<num type="Record Group Number">MSS 06-103</num>
</subtitle>

<!-- This puts in the JPEG of the logo. -->
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
 xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/FairfaxCoPL.jpg"/>
</p>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<archdesc level="collection">

<runner placement="footer">Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</runner>

<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Fairfax County Public Library</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">The Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1895-1902</unitdate></unittitle>
<unitid label="Record Group Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MSS 06-103</unitid>

<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">
<extent>
0.75 linear feet
</extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>

<abstract label="Abstract" encodinganalog="520$a">
The Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books collection consists of three inscribed Hornbook Series books from 1895, 1896, and 1902, and were found in the Love House, also known as Coombe Cottage, located in the City of Fairfax, Virginia when Lyman B. Kirkpatrick, Jr. purchased the house in 1945.
</abstract>

<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
Love, James Monroe, Jr. (1875-1957)
</origination>

</did>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information</head>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions</head>
<p>None</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions</head>
<p>Consult repository for information</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books, MSS 06-103, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</p>
</prefercite>

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information</head>
<p>The inscribed books in this collection belonged to Col. James M. Love Jr. Love’s father, Judge James M. Love, purchased Coombe Cottage in the City of Fairfax in 1879. In November 1945, Lyman B. Kirkpatrick Jr. purchased Coombe Cottage from the Love family, which still included many contents of the house, including these books. Kirkpatrick passed these books down to his son Paull T. Kirkpatrick, who donated them to the Virginia Room in August 2018.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Chris Barbuschak, December 2018<lb/>EAD generated by Ross Landis, 2018</p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical and Biographical Information</head>
<p>James Monroe Love Jr. was born on February 12, 1875 in Fairfax, Virginia to Maria and Judge James M. Love Sr. (1842-1933). His father, a son of Thomas R. Love, was a judge of the courts at Fairfax County and Alexandria. He also was a Confederate Civil War veteran and fought with the “Black Horse” Fourth Virginia Calvary. Love was a founder of the Marr Camp of Confederate Veterans of Fairfax County.</p>
<p>On February 15, 1879, Judge James M. Love purchased from the heirs of E.R. Ford 10.5 acres of land adjacent to Truro Church containing Coombe Cottage. In 1845, Dr. Frederick Baker had purchased this same tract of land and built a collection of buildings including a residence and a private school for young women. He named the academy Coombe Cottage which operated until the Civil War. Love resided there for over 50 years, and Coombe Cottage became known locally as the “Love House”. Love died at the home of his other son, Thomas B. Love, at 1925 S Street, NW at age 91 on June 12, 1933.</p>
<p>After Love’s death, the chancery case Love v. Love forced the sale of the property. On November 13, 1945, Lyman B. Kirkpatrick, Jr. (1916-1995) purchased the Love House for $18,000. The sale included original furnishings and other belongings of Judge Love’s, of which the three books found in this collection were included. In 1955, the Kirkpatricks sold the property, and developers demolished Coombe Cottage in 1962 to make way for the Mosby Apartments, presently known as Mosby Tower at 10560 Main Street.</p>
<p>On March 17, 1898, James M. Love Jr. married Rebecca Fowle Daingerfield of whom he had two daughters with. He joined up with the U.S. Army and was appointed a Second Lieutenant with the 21st Infantry in September 1898. On October 8, 1899, he was appointed as a First Lieutenant of the 5th Infantry and went on to fight in the Spanish-American War. He was severely wounded in the right arm while serving with General Henry Ware Lawton near Manila in the Philippines.</p>
<p>After the war, Love returned home and in 1899 saw duty as adjutant general of the District of Columbia National Guard with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. On July 16, 1900, he applied and later received permission to be relieved of that assignment desiring to see active service in China due to the Boxer Rebellion. He was transferred to the 21st Infantry on February 27, 1902. Afterwards, he attended the Infantry and Calvary School at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas where he studied law and graduated in 1905. He received the rank of Captain of the 15th Infantry on August 21, 1905.</p>
<p>During World War I, he was in command of the 3rd Officers Training Camp at Camp Lee (now Fort Lee) in Prince George County, Virginia. He saw action on the French front, and served as a Lieutenant-Colonel in the 318th Infantry and commanded Fairfax County soldiers in the Meuse-Argonne Offensive. Upon returning home from World War I, Love was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal for his meritorious service with the U.S. Army in France.</p>
<p>Love went on to attend the Army War College at Washington. After his graduation, the Army assigned him to be an instructor at the Fort Leavenworth, Kansas army college in August 1921. Love finished his career at Fort Sam Houston, Texas, and he received orders to retire in October 1922. After retiring, he moved to the Far East, and married for a second time on January 6, 1927, to Elizabeth A. “Bessie” Tobin.</p>
<p>During World War II, the Japanese captured him while living in Manila, Philippines and placed him in an internment camp. He was released in February 1945, and returned to the United States in May, living at the Army and Navy Club until his death on March 18, 1957 at Walter Reed Army Hospital. He is buried near his father at the Fairfax City Cemetery. </p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$b">
<head>Scope and Content</head>
<p>The Col. James M. Love Jr. Law Books collection consists of three inscribed Hornbook Series books from 1895, 1896, and 1902, and were found in the Love House, also known as Coombe Cottage, located in the City of Fairfax, Virginia when Lyman B. Kirkpatrick, Jr. purchased the house in 1945. Two of the books were used by Col. Love and inscribed by him while he studied law at the Infantry and Calvary School at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas in 1904-1905. The third book, Shipman’s Common Law Pleading Book belonged to Washington attorney Christopher B. Garnett (1875-1955), a partner in the firm Barbour, Garnett, Pickett and Keith and includes handwritten notes throughout.</p>
</scopecontent>


<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>None</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>None</p>
</separatedmaterial>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- Index/Search terms go here - categorized appropriately

See page 38-39 for information on differentiated vs. undifferentiated lists.

Going to do undifferentiated.

<persname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</persname>
<famname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</famname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">^%term%</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">^%term%</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">^%term%</geogname>
<title encodinganalog="630$a">^%term%</title>
<function encodinganalog="657$a">^%term%</function>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">^%term%</genreform>
<occupation encodinganalog="656$a">^%term%</occupation>
-->

<!-- Example:
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Oak Hill</subject>
__index__terms_25__
</controlaccess>
-->

<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Coombe Cottage (Fairfax, VA)</subject>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Garnett, Christopher B. (1875-1955)</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Love, James Monroe, Jr. (1875-1957) </persname>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">United States Infantry and Calvary School (Fort Leavenworth, KS)</subject>
</controlaccess>

<!-- Begin Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<dsc type = "in-depth">
<head>Container List</head>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container type = "folder">&#160;
</container>
<unittitle>Shipman’s Common Law Pleading Book, 2nd edition [inscribed by C.B. Garnett in 1909], 
<unitdate>1895
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container type = "folder">&#160;
</container>
<unittitle>Smith’s Elementary Law [inscribed by Love], 
<unitdate>1896
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<container label = "Box" type = "box">1
</container>
<container type = "folder">&#160;
</container>
<unittitle>Clark’s Criminal Law, 2nd edition [inscribed by Love], 
<unitdate>1902
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

</archdesc>
</ead>