<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->
<!-- Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection -->
<!-- Created: Sun May 12 16:20:22 2024 -->
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx -->

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vif00160">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">

<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViF">
PUBLIC "-//Fairfax County Public Library//TEXT (US::ViF::vif00160::A Guide to the The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection)//EN" "vif00160.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, <date>1962-1971</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection
<num type="collectionnumber"></num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<!-- This puts in text for the boilerplate information about FCPL - address, phone number, etc.
     Text lives in a separate file. -->
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/fairfax_address.xi.xml"/>
 
<!-- This must be here so that the publication date appears in search results -->
<date type="publication">© 2024 Fairfax County Public Library. All rights reserved.</date>
</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Ross Landis, <date>May 12, 2024</date>
</creation>

<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langusage>

</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>

<titleproper>A Guide to the The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, <date>1962-1971</date></titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in The Fairfax County Public Library<lb/>
</subtitle>

<!-- This puts in the JPEG of the logo. -->
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
 xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/FairfaxCoPL.jpg"/>
</p>

</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<archdesc level="collection">

<runner placement="footer">Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</runner>

<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Fairfax County Public Library</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1962-1971</unitdate></unittitle>

<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">
<extent>
0.5 linear feet
</extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>

<abstract label="Abstract" encodinganalog="520$a">
The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection contains 141 photographs and six negatives from 1962-1971. The images depict a quickly developing Fairfax County suffering from erosion and other environmental problems, and conservation efforts to combat them.
</abstract>

<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District
</origination>

</did>

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information</head>

<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions</head>
<p>None</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions</head>
<p>Consult repository for information.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library</p>
</prefercite>

<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information</head>
<p>Gift of Dan Schwartz, Northern Virginia Soil &#38; Water Conservation District, December 2023.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Chris Barbuschak, May 2024<lb/>EAD generated by Ross Landis, 2024</p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical and Biographical Information</head>
<p>In July 1945, the Virginia Soil Conservation Committee approved the establishment of the Northern Virginia Soil Conservation District which included Loudoun, Prince William and Fairfax counties. Those three counties voted for its creation in a referendum held on April 26, 1945. Renamed the Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District (NVSWCD) on July 1, 1964, it was established to develop a public understanding of the need for planning and action to preserve natural resources; to encourage landowners to use the most effective practices and procedures in the conservation of soil and natural resources; and to assist landowners and operators with conservation. The District was also concerned about the consequences of erosion, flooding and sedimentation caused by the sudden increase in land development and construction.</p>
<p>A board of five supervisors directed the work of the District assisted by professional personnel of the Soil Conservation Service of the Department of Agriculture. The offices were originally located in Manassas, then at 114 East Main Street at Fairfax Circle, and later in January 1970, the District moved to 3945 Chain Bridge Road in Fairfax. Today, its offices are in the Fairfax County Government Center.</p>
<p>Following World War II, the rural character of Fairfax County was rapidly changing due to the influx of people seeking housing and the related expansion of shopping centers, roads, schools, and recreation. The hasty development brought about staggering damage and destruction to many irreplaceable natural resources and it caused abundant soil and water conservation problems.</p>
<p>Originally orientated toward agriculture, the District undertook a pilot urban conservation program in Fairfax County beginning in July 1962, with the intent of minimizing and preventing further destruction. Glenn B. Anderson of the Soil Conservation Service was assigned to the District to assist with the pilot project over the next decade. Subsequently, the District undertook many initiatives including developing a conservation policy for the county, conducted field tours outlining major conservation problems and the techniques used to alleviate them, various planting projects, conducted environmental studies and assessments at the request of county agencies, provided consultation services, assisted farmers with conservation practices and projects, and provided conservation outreach to the public. The District celebrates 80 years of promoting soil and water conservation in Fairfax County in 2025.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$b">
<head>Scope and Content</head>
<p>The Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Photograph Collection contains 141 photographs and six negatives from 1962-1971. The images depict a quickly developing Fairfax County suffering from erosion and other environmental problems, and conservation efforts to combat them. The photographs were taken to increase public understanding of the conservation needs and problems in Fairfax County. Some of these images were originally published in the District’s annual reports and were mostly photographed by Glenn B. Anderson, the District Conservationist; Gordon S. Smith, an information specialist of the Soil Conservation Service based in Upper Darby, PA; and Clarence Deland, a field photographer for the Soil Conservation Service. Locations featured include Annandale, Burke, Centreville, Chantilly, Fairfax, Falls Church, McLean, Seven Corners, Springfield, Tysons Corner, and Vienna, VA.</p>
</scopecontent>


<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>None</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<p>None</p>
</separatedmaterial>

</descgrp>
<!-- xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

<!-- Index/Search terms go here - categorized appropriately

See page 38-39 for information on differentiated vs. undifferentiated lists.

Going to do undifferentiated.

<persname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</persname>
<famname encodinganalog="600$a">^%term%</famname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">^%term%</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">^%term%</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">^%term%</geogname>
<title encodinganalog="630$a">^%term%</title>
<function encodinganalog="657$a">^%term%</function>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">^%term%</genreform>
<occupation encodinganalog="656$a">^%term%</occupation>
-->

<!-- Example:
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Oak Hill</subject>
__index__terms_25__
</controlaccess>
-->

<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Anderson, Glenn B. (1926-2008)</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Smith, Gordon S. (1899-1978)</persname>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Soils -- Virginia.</subject>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District</corpname>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Soil erosion - Virgina </subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Soil erosion -- Virginia -- Fairfax County</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650$a">Soil conservation -- Virginia -- Fairfax County</subject>
</controlaccess>

<!-- Begin Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->
<dsc type = "in-depth">
<head>Container List</head>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 1">
Annandale Woods Subdivision, Annandale, VA: An area of land where high density urban development is being permitted on slopes that exceed 15%. The roadbank in the foreground is over 25 feet high, and individual sewage lines are often excavated to a depth of 20 feet. This type of land use results in excess cost to developers and compounds soil and water conservation problems.  (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 September 3</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 2">
Annandale Woods Subdivision, Annandale, VA: This picture shows development of residential subdivision on steep land. The units under construction will have a 15 to 20" fill when completed. Development of steep slopes often results in excessive cost to builders and compounds soil and water conservation problems. [2 copies] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 September 3</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 3">
Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: [No caption] Men sitting in front of "Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve" sign. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 October ?</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 4">
Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Dwarf sorghum is one of the big crops on the Mitchell's hunting farm. This variety has a strong stem that withstands winter wind and snow to provide wildlife food during the winter. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 October 22</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 5">
Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Most of Phillip Mitchell's open land is laid out in contour strips 25 feet wide with 200 feet between strips. Strips are planted with corn, sorghum, buckwheat, flax or other cover and food-producing plants. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 October 22</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 6">
Bull Run Ranch Hunting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Mr. and Mrs. Phillip Mitchell and son - A family scene on this 255 acre recreation development where approximately 100 acres of crop land has been converted to the reduction of wildlife feed and cover crops. Mrs. Mitchell and son are displaying two neatly processed ring-necked pheasants.  (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 October 27</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 7">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Initial planting of special wildlife feed and cover plants on converted farm croplands. The plantings are arranged in strips for conservation purposes and hunter and dog accessibility. This farm consists of 265 acres and will be open for hunting for the first time this season. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 May</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 8">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: A 40' x 200' holding pen for ring neck pheasants. This pen is located in a convenient but secluded area of this 265 acre shooting preserve. Several thousand birds are stocked in this pen during the shooting season. Most of the structural materials were harvested from the farm. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 October</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 9">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: A 40' x 200' holding pen for ring neck pheasants. This pen is located in a convenient but secluded area of this 265 acre shooting preserve. Several thousand birds are stocked in this pen during the shooting season. Most of the structural materials were harvested from the farm. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 October</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 10">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Use of regular farming equipment for maintenance and other work on this 265 acre shooting preserve. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 October</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 11">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Young bird dog being trained. This 265 acre commercial shooting preserve will offer a wide variety of outdoor recreation activities, such as; shooting lessons, training dogs, boarding dogs, organized hunts for ringnecked pheasants, quail, and other upland game. [2 copies] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 October 4</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 12">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Part of the facilities and land use on a 265 acre commercial shooting preserve. The holding pen located in the clearing has capacity for several thousand ring-neck pheasants. Both field and contour strips located in the background contain plantings of special wildlife food and cover plants. Perennial wildlife borders are located along fence rows, woodlands and roadways. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 13">
Bull Run Shooting Preserve, Centreville, VA: Portions of a 265 acre commercial shooting preserve that has recently been taken out of crop production. Emphasis is placed on sound conservation use and treatment of the land. Wildlife food and cover plantings are arranged in field and contour strips. Perennial wildlife borders are located along the edge of wooded areas and road ways. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 14">
Congressional School, Falls Church, VA: A newly landscaped and eroded playground that has well prepared for seeding. The application of a simple mechanical conservation measure (diversion terraces) would have prevented much of this erosion and waste. The surface water could have been led to a safe outlet and a potential drainage problem prevented on the playground below. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 July 20</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 15">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: This high altitude, vertical photo covers most of the 10,000 acres involved in the new jetport. The floodwater dam and reservoir are not shown. The lake near the center of the photo serves as part of the landscaping and a drainage area for the terminal building area today. (photographer: FAA), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 November</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 16">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: The portion of the flood control impoundment on the Horsepan Run. The picture shows the top of the conduit during flood stage. This dam impounds water from a 15,000 acre watershed.  (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 March 6</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 17">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 18">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 19">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: FAA supervising horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin and SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson studying soil and agronomy problems on the 10,000 acre airport. Sound soil and water conservation planning and application is a must on urban areas like this. Urbanization of agricultural lands frequently compounds soil, water and related conservation problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 20">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Glenn Anderson, SCS technician for Fairfax County, left, and Gilbert J. Tobin, horticulturalist for Dulles Airport, examine new growth on loblolly pines planted on the outer fringes of the airport. The tree plantings are part of the 1000-foot-wide buffer zone around the airport. Over two million trees have been planted in this zone. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 21">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Now part of the landscaping near the terminal buildings, this 10-acre lake served as a de-silting basin during the construction period. The main terminal building's catch-basin roof and surrounding acreage keep the lake full. Prolonged dry spells in the past two years have made this lake a valuable source of irrigation water. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 22">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Part of the Dulles International Airport installation. This airport is located on approximately 10,000 acres of land most of which was in woodland and pasture land prior to urbanization. A basic conservation plan was employed during and after construction of this airport. Cooperation between SCD, Federal, State and County agencies often save the taxpayer thousands of dollars. [7 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 23">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: SCS Conservationist Glenn B. Anderson and FAA horticulturalist Gilbert Tobin discussing agronomy problems on the Dulles Airport grounds. The adverse soil conditions found in this area, coupled with tremendous land disturbance due to construction work, compounds the soil, water and plant material problems. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 24">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Two airport workers spread mulch in a planting of azalea shrubs near the terminal building. In the background are a few Washington hawthorne trees that form part of the new landscaping. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 25">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Up-stream aerial view at the Horse Pen Run flood control dam. This conservation structure provides flood protection to hundreds of down-stream land owners on Broad Run during and following periods of heavy rainfall. In the background can be seen the Dulles Administration Building and runways. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 June 25</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 26">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: [No caption] Dulles Airport construction. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 September</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 27">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: [No caption] Tractor in front of terminal building. (photographer: FAA), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 September</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 28">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Construction scene, building foundation. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 29">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Laying cornerstone for taxiway at Dulles International Airport. (photographer: FAA), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 30">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Pictured at the flood control dam at Dulles Airport during the suburbia conservation tour sponsored by the Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Tuesday (May 2) are these assistants to members of the House of Representatives, left to right: Jack McKee (Rep. Vigorito, Pa.); Jerr James (Rep. Belcher, Okla.); Mickey Holmes (Rep. Poage, Tex.); Ray Marbles (Rep. Marsh, Va.); Wayne Trotter (Rep. Wampler, Va.); and Bill Williams (Rep. Scott, Va.). (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 31">
Dulles Airport, Chantilly, VA: Taken during the November 22nd Conservation Field Tour. Shows group looking at FAA Dulles Flood Prevention Dam. (photographer: Ted James), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 32">
George Mason College, Fairfax, VA: [No caption]. Man looking at drain. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 33">
George Mason College, Fairfax, VA: A twelve foot gully caused by uncontrolled storm runoff. An underground storm sewer no longer functions because it is completely blocked by silt from the unprotected and eroding areas. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 34">
Glen Burnie Park, Glen Burnie, MD: Erosion problems of this community area. The pool has been constructed by the community. (photographer: Bob Halstead), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 July 19</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 35">
Green Acres Elementary School, Fairfax, VA: Serious erosion damages on the Green Acres Elementary School construction site. Application of simple erosion control practices would greatly reduce damage to both the construction site and the down-stream properties located along Pohick Creek. (Pohick Creek Watershed) (photographer: Clarence Deland), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968 June 26</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 36">
James W. Robinson Secondary School, Fairfax, VA: Heavy sediment deposits that has been conveyed through the storm sewer and deposited below outlet. No effective erosion control practices have been installed on this 79 acre site. Construction started in November 1969. The area drains into impoundment site #4. (Pohick Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1970 February</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 37">
James W. Robinson Secondary School, Fairfax, VA: Heavy silt deposits that have been conveyed through the storm sewer and deposited down below outlet. No effective erosion control practices have been installed on this 79 acre development. Construction started in November 1969. The area drains into impoundment site #4. (Pohick Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1970 February</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 38">
Lake Braddock, Burke, VA: [No caption] Proof prints and negatives of Lake Braddock. (Pohick River Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1971</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 39">
Lake Fairfax, Reston, VA: Some of the recreational facilities found on this 100-acre converted farm are a 30-acre lake, two large swimming areas, large picnicking area, camping area, restaurant, and many other facilities. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 September</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 40">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: This 200 year old Elm tree was the first the bulldozer assaulted. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 41">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965 March</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 42">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965 March</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 43">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: Langley High School construction. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965 March</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 44">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 45">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 46">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 47">
Langley High School, McLean, VA: [No caption]. View of front of Langley High School. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 48">
Montgomery Ward - Seven Corners, 6100 Arlington Boulevard, Seven Corners, VA: Use of semi-permanent vegetative cover for erosion control on a commercial development. Land Grading was completed on this area during August 1963. This practice has proven to be both economical and effective for the control of accelerated soil erosion on urban developments where construction has been delayed. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 September</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 49">
Montgomery Ward - Seven Corners, 6100 Arlington Boulevard, Seven Corners, VA: Diversion ditch above a 40' high cut. A concrete flume conveys the water to an underground storage sewer below. [3 copies and negative] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 50">
Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Conservation Awards, Unknown:  [No caption] Award Ceremony: Dr. Stephen I. Granger, Stanley Lickey, Chairman Nelson Craun, Kettler Brothers Inc., House Brothers. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 51">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 52">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 53">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 54">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 55">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 56">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Two men inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 57">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Two men inspecting the site. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 58">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Houses at 5505 Ravenel Lane and 5507 Ravenel Lane. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 59">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: [No caption] Houses in Ravensworth subdivision. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 60">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Portions of a 28 acre Industrial Development where temporary vegetation is being established for erosion control. Vegetation is effective for the control of erosion on urban developments when application is done immediately following rough grading.  (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 61">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 62">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 63">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 64">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Typical erosion scene occurring on this 28 acre Industrial Development where area has been exposed for 14 months. This construction site has over 4,000 linear feet of steep cut and fill slopes. Accelerated soil erosion has caused serious damage to parkland and lake areas. Conservation practices were not planned until downstream property owners complained. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 65">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Unprotected soil from the 100-acre industrial development has washed out under new curbing flooding backyards of homes with silt. Proper protective measures could solve this situation. [2 copies] (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 16</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 66">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. A section of newly seeded bank that partially surrounds this 109-acre industrial park. This fill slope was seeded to crown vetch and rye grass during early May 1968. About 4,000 linear feet of cut and fill slopes are located on this industrial complex. Some of these slopes are 40 feet in height. A stream valley park is located along the Flag Run, below this bank. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968 June 26</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 67">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. Conservationist examining vegetative mulch for erosion control. The bare subsoil was seeded to temporary vegetation in the spring of 1966, following rough grading. This is part of a 109 acre industrial development which will be built on at a later date. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968 June 26</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 68">
Ravensworth Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Glenn B. Anderson and Hugh Mackey. Excellent erosion control by use of temporary vegetation. This is the 2nd year's growth of temporary vegetation which was seeded on rough graded subsoil for erosion control. It is a most effective and economical erosion control practice if used immediately after rough grading is done. This is part of a 109-acre industrial park which is to be built on a later date. (photographer: Clarence Deland), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968 June 26</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 69">
Reston Nursery, Reston, VA: An area of native dogwood trees that have been salvage from urban construction areas. These same trees will be replanted on the urban developments after construction is completed. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 October</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 70">
Seven Corners Area, Seven Corners, VA: A debris basin that is effectively storing heavy silt-laden storm water from the above construction area. Approximately 13 acres of highly erodible soil material in the above area. This type of structure is designed to prevent heavy sedimentation damages in off-sight drainage areas. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 March 8</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 71">
Shirley Industrial Park, Springfield, VA: Stand pipe and perforated pipe for siltation basin. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 72">
Shouse Village Subdivision, Vienna, VA: This picture shows where developer installed jute erosion matting only after earlier seeding has been lost due to severe erosion. Jute is one of a number of erosion control practices that will greatly retard erosion and help insure establishment of protective vegetation on criticial areas. (Wolf Trap Creek Watershed) (Kenton Inglis pictured) [2 copies] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1969 September 10</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 73">
Sleepy Hollow United Methodist Church, Falls Church, VA: This picture shows the construction of a new church where a conservation plan is being developed for the purpose of controlling erosion and beautification of the surrounding landscape. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 February 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 74">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Shopping Center, Early Summer '65. [photo and negative] (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 75">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Shopping Center, Early Summer '65. [photo and negative] (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 76">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Shopping Center, Early Summer '65. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) [photo and negative] (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 77">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Shopping Center, Early Summer '65. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) [photo and negative] (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 78">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Debris basin at Tysons Corner International Shopping Center shown- Graham Munkitt Vick(?), Glenn B. Anderson. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 79">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] Men gathered around siltation basin. [Negative] (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 80">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] Debris basin at Tysons Corner International Shopping Center. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 81">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: A functioning debris basin used as a temporary erosion and flood control structure on the Tysons Corner International Shopping Center construction site. This structure is located on an 86 acre watershed where 46 acres is subjected to accelerated erosion during construction. The structure has 2.1 surface acres; 18.5 acre feet of temporary storage and will store approximately 4.4 inches of sediment per acre of disturbed area. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 82">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: A functioning debris basin used as a temporary erosion and flood control structure on the Tysons Corner International Shopping Center construction site. This structure is located on an 86 acre watershed where 46 acres is subjected to accelerated erosion during construction. The structure has 2.1 surface acres; 18.5 acre feet of temporary storage and will store approximately 4.4 inches of sediment per acre of disturbed area. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 83">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Portions of a newly constructed debris basin on this 86 acre urban construction site. This basin is located on a 46 acre watershed with 33 acres of disturbed area. The structure has 3 surface acres' 42 acre feet of storage capacity; and approximately 11.2 inches of storage per acre of erodible area. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 84">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Tour of Fairfax. Sediment basin, originially 18' deep, now near the top. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 85">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Shopping Center silting basin. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 86">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 87">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond.  (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 88">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 89">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 90">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond. (Tysons Corner International Shopping Center sign pictured) (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 91">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond, outfall near Quick property. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 92">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Silt Pond, Storm Drainage. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 May 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 93">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] Man inspecting site.  (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 94">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] View of site. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 95">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] View of site. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box  Folder 96">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: [No caption] View of site. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 97">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Pictured at the Tysons Corner International Shopping Center where conservation measures are protecting against silting and erosion during construction, during the suburbia conservation tour sponsored by the Northern Virginia Soil and Water Conservation District Tuesday (May 2) are these assistants to members of the United States Senate, left to right: Earl Nishimura (Senator Fong, Hawaii); Charles Ganadt (Senator Byrd, Virginia); John Holum (Senator McGovern, South Dakota); Neal Bjornson (Senator Young, North Dakota); and Jim Meeker (Senator Burdick, North Dakota). (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 98">
Tysons Corner International Shopping Center, Tysons Corner, VA: Tysons Corner Energy dissipator.  (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 99">
W. T. Woodson High School, Fairfax, VA: A portion of a 100 acre construction site that has been stabilized and beautified by the application of sound agronomic conservation practices. The area on the left has been prepared for seeding after lying exposed for 2 years. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 July 3</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 100">
W. T. Woodson High School, Fairfax, VA: The successful establishment of a permanent vegetative cover on part of the Woodson High School playground. The background shows a large exposed area that has not been seeded. The application of sound agronomic and engineering conservation measures is a must in areas like this. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1962 August 14</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 101">
Wakefield Forest Elementary School, Fairfax, VA: Uncontrolled erosion on school ground where land was left bare over winter. This area drains into Turkey Run where an 8 acre privately-owned lake has recently become choked with silt. (Turkey Run Watershed) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1970 March</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 102">
Westgate Industrial Park, McLean, VA: [No caption] Man photographing drain. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 103">
Westgate Industrial Park, McLean, VA: Severe gully erosion on an Industrial Development site where thirty-foot banks have been exposed for about 12 months. Lack of conservation planning often causes serious damages to construction sites, however, the most serious damages occur to downstream resource areas. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 104">
Westgate Industrial Park, McLean, VA: Severe gully erosion on an Industrial Development site where thirty-foot banks have been exposed for about 12 months. Lack of conservation planning often causes serious damages to construction sites, however, the most serious damages occur to downstream resource areas. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 105">
Westgate Industrial Park, McLean, VA: Severe gully erosion on an Industrial Development site where thirty-foot banks have been exposed for about 12 months. Lack of conservation planning often causes serious damages to construction sites, however, the most serious damages occur to downstream resource areas. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 106">
Westgate Industrial Park, McLean, VA: Severe gully erosion on an Industrial Development site where thirty-foot banks have been exposed for about 12 months. Lack of conservation planning often causes serious damages to construction sites, however, the most serious damages occur to downstream resource areas. (photographer: Gordon Smith), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1966 March 15</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 107">
Wexford Subdivision, Vienna, VA: Erosion damage in new subdivision due to improper location of sewer (storm) and lack of proper seeding. The outlet to storm sewer is located on upper elevation of steep bank. Large quantities of sediment has been transported in to nearby stream due to lack of erosion control measures. (Glenn B. Anderson and Joe Vaden pictured) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1969 July 30</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 108">
Wexford Subdivision, Vienna, VA: Lack of effective sediment control measures on eroding subdivision. Developer merely placed a row of baled straw below erosion problem in an attempt to trap the sediment. Large quantities of sediment was carried onto adjacent property and into the nearby stream. (Wolf Trap Run Watershed) (Kenton Inglis pictured) (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1969 July 30</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 109">
Willston Elementary School, Seven Corners, VA: The use of a thin veneer of asphalt on a construction site that contains highly erodible micaschist soil material. This asphalt blanket provides temporary protection from sheet and rill erosion. Economical conservation measures like this gives temporary protection to downstream property owners during critical periods of construction.  (photographer: Clarence Britt), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 February 5</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 110">
Willston Shopping Center, Seven Corners, VA: The application of erosion netting the face of a steep cut. This material helps control erosion and enables young seedlings to become established. (photographer: Glenn B. Anderson), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1964 February</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 111">
Unidentified, Unknown: [No caption] Dredge in operation. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 112">
Unidentified, Unknown: [No caption] Man speaking through bullhorn to children. (photographer: Ted Jones), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level = "file">
<did>
<unittitle label="Box 1 Folder 113">
Unidentified, Unknown: [No caption] Man pointing out ditch. (photographer: Unknown), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End Container List xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx-->

</archdesc>
</ead>