<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY transcript SYSTEM "http://spec.lib.vt.edu/civwar/memoirs.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY bioginfo SYSTEM "http://spec.lib.vt.edu/civwar/encyccw.htm" NDATA html>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl"?>
<ead id="viblbv00568">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00568::Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir, c.1890s)//EN"
            "viblbv00568.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir, <date>c.1890s</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Atkinson, Archibald, Jr., Memoir <num type="collectionnumber"
                        >Ms1994-022</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By
                    Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in oXygen by Kira A. Dietz,
                    <date>12/7/2009</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir, <date>c.1890s</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number"
                    >Ms1994-022</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2009 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: </label>
                    <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir,
                    <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f"
                    >c.1890s</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms1994-022</unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 folder; 0.1 cu.
                ft.</physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract label="Abstract">The collection consists of a partial memoir of Atkinson's
                Civil War experiences. Atkinson served as a surgeon for the 10th Regiment, Virginia
                Cavalry, followed by appointments with the 31st Regiment, Virginia Infantry, and the
                Second Army Corps, Army of Nothern Virginia.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Archibald Atkinson,
                Jr.</origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Permission to publish from the Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir must be obtained
                    from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir, Ms1994-022, Special Collections,
                    Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>The Archibald Atkinson, Jr., Memoir was purchased by Special Collections in
                    1993.</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <altformavail>
                <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
                <p>A transcription of the <extref entityref="transcript">memoir</extref> is
                    available on the Special Collections website.</p>
            </altformavail>
            <processinfo>
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Archibald Atkinson, Jr.
                    Memoir commenced and was completed in 1994.
                    <!--"The document was in such fragile condition that it was taken
                    to a conservation studio in the Washington, D.C. area where it was expertly
                    washed and deacidified, loose parts reattached and tears mended, and each page
                    encapsulated in a plastic film. The transcription of the document presented here
                    was made from a photocopy of the original. Special Collections staff Dorthy
                    Bodell and Stephen Zietz transcribed the text and work on the electronic edition
                    as time permits. The transcription will be updated from the original document as
                    time permits." <-the previous note comes from the online inventory, replaced in Dec. 2009. 
                    The transcription available online is complete. -->
                </p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Information</head>
            <p>Atkinson, Archibald, Jr., M.D., Professor of Materia Medica and Therapeutics in the
                College of Physicians and Surgeons, Baltimore, was born February 23, 1832, near
                Smithfield, on the James River, Isle of Wight County, Virginia. His father was an
                eminent lawyer, and represented the Second Congressional District of Virginia in the
                United States Congress from 1844 to 1848. Dr. Atkinson received his education at the
                University of Virginia, and graduated in medicine at the University of Pennsylvania
                in the spring of 1854. After receiving his diploma he went abroad and enjoyed the
                advantages of the clinics of the most famous hospitals of Paris for eighteen months,
                and a six months' residence in the Rotunda Lying-in Hospital of Dublin, Ireland.
                Returning to America in 1856 he located in Baltimore, where he practiced his
                profession until the outbreak of the late civil war, when he returned to his native
                State and was appointed Assistant Surgeon in the Wise Legion in West Virginia, and
                assigned to the charge of the Lewisburg Hospital.</p>
            <p>In 1862, Dr. Atkinson was selected as the Surgeon of the Tenth Regiment, Virginia
                Cavalry, belonging to General J.E.B. Stuart's command, and in autumn of 1863 was
                assigned to the Thirty-first Virginia Regiment of Infantry. Subsequently he was
                appointed Brigade-Surgeon in General John Pegram's Brigade, Early's Division, Second
                Army Corps, of the Army of Northern Virginia. At the termination of the war he
                established himself in the practice of his profession in his native town of
                Smithfield, Virginia, continuing there until the spring of 1873, when he removed to
                Baltimore and located on North Charles Street. In the fall of 1875 Dr. Atkinson was
                elected to the chair of Materia Medica and Therapeutics in the College of Physicians
                and Surgeons of Baltimore, a position he has filled with rare ability and eminent
                success as an imparter of medical knowledge. His maternal ancestors were the Powells
                and Chiltons of Loudon County, Virginia, whose progenitors originally came from
                Scotland and Wales. His ancestors on the paternal side were English.</p>
            <p>He has a brother, Dr. Robert Chilton Atkinson, who is practicing medicine at St.
                Louis, Missouri. On November 2, 1858, Dr. Atkinson married Mary Elizabeth Thomas, of
                Smithfield, Virginia, daughter of Samuel Thomas, whose wife was Frances Harrison
                Woodley, daughter of Major Woodley, of Smithfield. The issue of the marriage is two
                children, Mary Chilton and Louis Woodley Atkinson, both of whom are living.</p>
            <p>Source: pgs. 603-604 in <title render="italic">The Biographical Cyclopedia of
                    Representative Men of Maryland and District of Columbia</title>. Baltimore:
                National Biographical Publishing Co., 1879.</p>
            <p>Additional <extref entityref="bioginfo">biographical information</extref> is
                available on the Special Collections website.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>Written sometime around 1900, the document recounts the military career of Archibald
                Atkinson, Jr. as a doctor in the Confederate Army. The memoir was writen in a
                commercially prepared notebook (printed, lined paper) on a total of 58 pages. The
                transcription preserves the page and line breaks as they appear in the original.
                Links throughout the transcript point to additional information on relevent people and
                places.</p>
            <p>The memoir seems to begin in the middle of the text; there is no introductory
                material or conclusion. There may well have been another notebook with the first
                part of the narrative; if so, there is no indication anywhere on the notebook
                preserved at Virginia Tech of its existence.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged by material type.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Memoir, <unitdate type="inclusive">c.1890s.</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Folder" type="folder">1</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
