<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00653">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00653:: Henry Kyd Douglas Letter, 1871)//EN" "viblbv00653.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Kyd Douglas Letter, <date>1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Douglas, Henry Kyd Letter
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-023
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>5/25/2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Kyd Douglas Letter, <date>1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2010-023
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henry Kyd Douglas Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1871
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-023
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">: Letter from Henry Kyd Douglas, Hagerstown, Maryland attorney and former Confederate staff officer, to William P. Maulsby, of Frederick, Maryland, regarding the case of Fiery et al v. Emmert et al.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Henry Kyd Douglas Letter must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: : Henry Kyd Douglas Letter, Ms2010-023 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Henry Kyd Douglas Letter was found by Special Collections staff in March 2010, in a book that was among a collection donated to Special Collections in 2001. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the Henry Kyd Douglas Letter commenced and was completed in May 2010. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Henry Kyd Douglas, son of Rev. Robert and Mary Robertson Douglas, was born near Shepherdstown, (West) Virginia on September 29, 1838. He graduated from Franklin and Marshall College in Lancaster, Pennsylvania in 1858, then attended law school in Lexington, Virginia. At the outbreak of the Civil War, Douglas was a practicing attorney in St. Louis. He returned to Virginia to join the Confederate Army and enlisted as a private in Company B of the 2nd Virginia Infantry. Rising through the ranks, Douglas eventually earned an officer's commission and was appointed to a position on the staff of General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson. Following Jackson's death in May 1863, Douglas served successively on the staffs of Confederate generals Edward Johnson, John B. Gordon, Jubal Early, John Pegram and James Walker. Douglas was seriously wounded at the Battle of Gettysburg and was held prisoner for nine months at Johnson's Island. In 1865, he was exchanged and appointed commander of the Light Brigade, a position he held through the end of the war. Following the war, Douglas established a law practice in Winchester, Virginia, but soon moved to Hagerstown, Maryland and in 1891 was appointed a circuit court judge. He died in 1903 and was buried in Elmwood Cemetery of Shepherdstown, West Virginia. His wartime experiences were chronicled in the book <title render="italic">I Rode with Stonewall</title>, published in 1940. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of a letter written by Henry Kyd Douglas, a Hagerstown, Maryland attorney and former Confederate staff officer, to William P. Maulsby of Frederick, Maryland. Douglas writes of the case of Fiery et al v. Emmert et al, a suit between two groups of stockholders in the Antietam Manufacturing Company, in which Maulsby has been named a defendant. Douglas explains that an appeal filed by the plaintiffs will soon be heard by the court of appeals. He doubts that the court will overturn an earlier decision but requests Maulsby's assistance in preparing his brief.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive">Dec 30 1871
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
