<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01873">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01873::Tyler-Wilson Family Papers, 1899-1960)//EN" "viblbv01873.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Tyler-Wilson Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1899-1960</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Tyler-Wilson Family Papers <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2017-014</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2017 By Virginia Tech. All rights
          reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace <date era="ce"
        calendar="gregorian">2017-08-23 14:01:21-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Tyler-Wilson Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1960</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
        Ms2017-014</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
        Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Tyler-Wilson Family Papers, <unitdate normal="1899/1960" type="inclusive">1899-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2017-014</unitid>
      <physdesc altrender="whole" label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.5 Cubic Feet</extent>
        <extent altrender="carrier">1 box</extent>
      </physdesc>      
      <abstract id="aspace_cbe251003d7d0141af02e778cdb03815">Papers, consisting
        largely of correspondence, of Virginia Governor James Hoge Tyler; Tyler's wife, Sue Hammet
        Tyler; their children Edward H. Tyler, James Hoge Tyler Jr., Stockton Heth Tyler, Lucy Belle
        Norwood Tyler McConnell, Sue Hampton Tyler Jopling, Hal C. Tyler, and Lily Tyler Wilson; and
        Lily Tyler Wilson's children: J. Hoge Tyler Wilson, Lily Norwood Wilson, and Henry Harrison
        Wilson II. Also includes a 1925 European travel diary maintained by Nancy E. Lukens. </abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
    <userestrict id="aspace_06c0408ece9a214dc77b4c9505ec9ab7">
      <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
      <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_a06b297a16d21922aa14470ff81eee63">
      <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
      <p>Permission to publish material from the Tyler-Wilson Family Papers must be obtained from
        the Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_b969e8525d5a912f020f24e2dd710077">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information:
        Tyler-Wilson Family Papers, Ms2017-014, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg,
        Va.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_f4ad75455c5ac78993a00df2a34b704a">
      <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head>
      <p>The Tyler-Wilson Family Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2016.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="aspace_e6d2dfe40181da9db84d1888e028ac79">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processing of the Tyler-Wilson Family Papers commenced in June 2017 and was completed in
        July 2017.</p>
    </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="aspace_09106e133d2a01a6d7f3b5157aa1ca68">
      <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
      <p>James Hoge Tyler (1846-1925), Virginia governor from 1898 to 1902, was born in Caroline
        County, Virginia in 1846. He was the son of George and Eliza Hoge Tyler but was reared by
        his grandparents, James and Eleanor Howe Hoge, in Pulaski County, Virginia. </p>
      <p>Tyler joined the Confederate army and served as a private in the Signal Corps throughout
        the Civil War. After the war, he returned to Pulaski County, where he had inherited the Hoge
        farm. He renamed the farm "Belle Hampton" and become a successful farmer and businessman. </p>
      <p>Tyler married Sue Montgomery Hammet (1845-1927) in 1868. While living at Belle Hampton, the
        Tylers had eight children: Edward H., James H. Jr., Stockton Heth, Lucy Belle, Sue H., Henry
        C. ("Hal"), Eliza ("Lily") and Eleanor Howe Tyler (died in infancy). In 1891, the family
        moved to "Halwick," their home in Radford.</p>
      <p>Tyler was elected to the state senate in 1877 and served one term. He also served on the
        board of visitors and as rector of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College (now
        Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University). He served as Virginia's lieutenant
        governor 1890 to 1894 and as governor from 1898 to 1902. Tyler remained somewhat active in
        state politics in his later years and also served as food administrator for Radford and
        Montgomery County during World War I.</p>
      <p>Eldest child of James H. and Sue Hammet Tyler, Edward Hammet ("Ned") Tyler (1869-1939)
        graduated from Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College. He managed the family farm at
        Belle Hampton and also owned Kirkland Farm near Dublin (Pulaski County), Virginia. </p>
      <p>James Hoge Tyler Jr. (1871-1937) attended Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and
        graduated from Hampden-Sidney College. He worked in the governor's office during his
        father's administration and later for the Virginia-Carolina Chemical Company. He married
        Evelyn Gray Bell (1879-1924) in 1908, and the couple lived in Roanoke. </p>
      <p>Stockton Heth Tyler (1874-1943) was a graduate of the Washington and Lee School of Law.
        During the Spanish-American War, he was a major in the U. S. Army, serving as an additional
        paymaster. He married Nelle Louise Serpell in 1904; the couple had five children. Tyler
        served as mayor of Norfolk, Virginia from 1924 to 1932. </p>
      <p>Lucy Belle Norwood Tyler (1876-1955) married Colonel Frank Percy McConnell (1870-1941) in
        1908. The couple, with their son, James Hoge Tyler McConnell, lived in Fort Smith, Arkansas,
        where Frank McConnell was engaged in several business enterprises, before returning by 1927
        to Radford. </p>
      <p>Sue Hampton Tyler (1877-1949) married Rev. Robert Ware Jopling (1865-1944), a Presbyterian
        minister, in 1915. The couple had two children, Sue Tyler and James Robert Jopling, and
        resided in Texas and South Carolina. Following her husband's death, Sue Jopling made her
        home in Norfolk, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Henry Clement ("Hal") Tyler (1878-1941) graduated from the University of Virginia School of
        Law in 1901. He established a law practice in Radford, where he was appointed commonwealth
        attorney in 1906. He continued in that position through successive elections until 1922. In
        1909, he was elected city attorney and served in that position until his death. He served in
        the Virginia House of Delegates from 1924 to 1925. </p>
      <p>Known to her family and friends as "Lily," Eliza Lillian Tyler (1882-1974) married Henry
        Harrison Wilson (1882-1933) in 1915. The Wilsons eventually made their home in Harrisburg,
        Pennsylvania and had three children: James Hoge Tyler (1916-1994), Lily Norwood (1919-2008),
        and Henry Harrison Wilson II (1923-2016). Following her husband's death, Lily Wilson
        returned to Virginia and by 1948 was living at the Tyler family home.</p>
      <p>Born in 1902, Nancy E. Lukens was the daughter of Charles S. Lukens of Roanoke, Virginia.
        She graduated from Randolph-Macon Woman's College and later obtained a master's degree from
        Columbia University. Her obituary indicates that Lukens began teaching at Roanoke's
        Jefferson High School in 1925. She also served on Roanoke's library board and as president
        of the Roanoke Rescue Mission. She is listed in Jefferson High annuals as Nancy Lukens as
        late as 1945 but later married Dr. Clarence William Hamilton. Nancy Lukens Hamilton retired
        from teaching in 1950 and died in Roanoke in 1959. Her relationship (if any) to the Tylers
        is unknown. </p>
      <p>(More detailed biographical information on the J. Hoge Tyler family may be found in the
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00220.xml"
            xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">finding aid</extref> for the J. Hoge Tyler Family
        Collection.)</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_adf63014b0fbbbc45ad4f175619d0975">
      <head>Content Description</head>
      <p>This collection contains personal papers of Virginia Governor James Hoge Tyler; his wife
        Sue Hammet Tyler; their children Edward H. Tyler, James Hoge Tyler Jr., Stockton Heth Tyler,
        Lucy Belle Norwood Tyler McConnell, Sue Hampton Tyler Jopling, Hal C. Tyler, and Lily Tyler
        Wilson; and Lily Tyler Wilson's children J. Hoge Tyler Wilson, Lily Norwood Wilson, and
        Henry Harrison Wilson II. The collection consists largely of correspondence and advertising
        / promotional materials. </p>
      <p>The correspondence of Governor Tyler represented here is mostly devoted to his efforts in
        having a heating system installed in "Halwick," the Tylers' home in Radford, Virginia. The
        folder includes correspondence, contracts, and printed material from the Peck-Hammond
        Company relating to the Moline System. Also included is a Halwick floor plan. Apart from two
        pieces of personal correspondence, the remainder of Tyler's material consists of advertising
        material, including items from the Advanced Agricultural Publishing Company; White Enamel
        Refrigerator Company; F. S. Royster Guano Company; and the Toggery Shop (Radford, Virginia).
        Most of the folders devoted to other family members contain just a few pieces of personal
        correspondence, personal financial documents, and ephemera. The materials for Lily Tyler
        Wilson and her daughter, Lily Norwood Wilson, are somewhat more extensive, each consisting
        of a number of pieces of personal correspondence, much of this written during the younger
        Lily's 1935 trip to Europe. </p>
      <p>The collection also contains the 1925 European travel diary of Nancy E. Lukens, whose
        relationship (if any) to the Tylers and Wilsons is unknown. The diary commences on June 5
        with Lukens' arrival in New York City; proceeds through her trans-Atlantic cruise aboard the
        Ms <emph render="bolditalic">Rotterdam</emph>; and continues with her tour of Great Britain,
        Ireland, Holland, Belgium, and France. The diary ends on August 2, with a description of
        Lukens' visit to the Louvre Museum. </p>
      <p>The various advertising and promotional materials completing collection had undoubtedly
        been sent to various members of the Tyler family, but because they could not be associated
        with any individual, they are collected together separately. Of possible particular interest
        among these items are promotional materials from the Frank E. Davis Fish Company (including
        price lists), the Dreamland Theatre of Radford, the Miss Radford beauty pageant of 1934, and
        the Radford Chatauqua. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_0d59ab3f07add8e4a11f7fa04cc93331">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by family group, in order of birth, followed by the Nancy Lukens
        diary, and ending with a set of advertising/promotional materials not associated with any
        particular family or individual.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
    <separatedmaterial id="aspace_1efdb7106584a5b94c62ce9087e1041f">
      <head>Separated Materials</head>
      <p>The following items were removed from the collection, to be added to the University
        Archives:</p>
      <p><title>The Blacksburg Sun</title>, March 28, 1973. <title>The Blacksburg Sun</title> (NIT
        souvenir edition), April 4, 1973.</p>
    </separatedmaterial>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_fd7855f953d92c380a72b5c9dc93ccc1">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>See also the finding aid for the <extref xlink:type="simple"
        xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00220.xml" xlink:show="new"
        xlink:actuate="onRequest">J. Hoge Tyler Family Collection (Ms1967-002)</extref>. The materials
        in this collection undoubtedly originated from the same source and somehow been separated
        from the larger collection before it was donated to Special Collections in 1967.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="aspace_e9ad24e58d743fb17d94c135dc157bfe" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. Hoge Tyler - home heating system,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1909-1910, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_f9b77e79f1b0d198a12ed70621ddba7a" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_139f5e4a1076010b98c22a8a7826fdbd"
            parent="aspace_f9b77e79f1b0d198a12ed70621ddba7a" type="folder">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_4bd28d8cd4dac2a7b37c371043734e59" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. Hoge Tyler - correspondence, notes, advertising materials,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1921, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_0bf5d2478d4910fa4e6b85b85aa5e91b" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_f0113df3bf66732739126697711c3a99"
            parent="aspace_0bf5d2478d4910fa4e6b85b85aa5e91b" type="folder">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_0910e34190bd995fdb49c4941f45ca30" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Sue Hammet Tyler,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1916-1926, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_736d35b2e092405e49938acd255be0e6" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_849286dd6622dcff94ebf7375d2b071d"
            parent="aspace_736d35b2e092405e49938acd255be0e6" type="folder">3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ba5753ea8af0dc199278b9dc649006f9" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edward Hammet Tyler,
          <unitdate normal="1903/1933" type="inclusive">1903-1933</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_0c4b56271796689adf05c3705af664b5" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_188e2e477dbbf2b590a6f77850bbd6fd"
            parent="aspace_0c4b56271796689adf05c3705af664b5" type="folder">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d5132367b04fd80d931517b4b8e904ed" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. Hoge Tyler Jr.,
          <unitdate normal="1923/1923">1923</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_d0d3507476c46e3dfd1cadc36efd1537" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_c1189dd1300d5fe153d8a056155afa8c"
            parent="aspace_d0d3507476c46e3dfd1cadc36efd1537" type="folder">5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_8b8af5e6000d1e7e41bea4b71b66b6da" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Stockton Heth Tyler,
          <unitdate normal="1899/1925" type="inclusive">1899-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_1555a0e9c324a298d03ed0aeb2d0089a" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_5afd36cb8842c7fcf15480a3b6b68dcb"
            parent="aspace_1555a0e9c324a298d03ed0aeb2d0089a" type="folder">6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_72d3b8a3637996032a94ec73c3fa7bf6" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lucy Belle Norwood Tyler,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1907-1927, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_34086a88dceb4c444e9f13fcc94ca1b5" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_edce07e4c53231312b794a41c6e8c6fd"
            parent="aspace_34086a88dceb4c444e9f13fcc94ca1b5" type="folder">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d6c8a40ad7b1c6db4e5afb5dadccd629" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Sue Hampton Tyler Jopling,
          <unitdate normal="1914/1925" type="inclusive">1914-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_79872ec1c2a625b6abc4c11bc85e599d" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_b2f06baa617ba8da0acc2c3476beab83"
            parent="aspace_79872ec1c2a625b6abc4c11bc85e599d" type="folder">8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ca2d1202acfed5a9d1a1bb85b12a998f" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Hal C. Tyler,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1911-1926, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_34abe8dbf5aac851e615792afc9509c3" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_d5ce5c5c13d251fe0da735cdc83d5dfa"
            parent="aspace_34abe8dbf5aac851e615792afc9509c3" type="folder">9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_c192c8f1d865ff8a506fddbb57b9cb71" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lily Tyler Wilson,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1911-1954, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_c4dd265a26df05d5afc44f85019b5c30">[2
            folders]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_d25d9c95e014a57da4b101e2fd60f692" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_02b297ea99fed541359014237fa88fca"
            parent="aspace_d25d9c95e014a57da4b101e2fd60f692" type="folder">10</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ade4fc09442da6665d2b950778d5afe4" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. Hoge Tyler Wilson,
          <unitdate normal="1935/1939" type="inclusive">1935-1939</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_17d4c731ded74d724c223aac1a71bbf6" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_933783c72f1d124df2834d2274eabe9c"
            parent="aspace_17d4c731ded74d724c223aac1a71bbf6" type="folder">11</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_90c252effa175636a977643625e6c66d" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lily Norwood Wilson - incoming correspondence,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1935-1960, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_6eb20b2b81bb0f39b29e2b5e83697937">[2
            folders]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_75b7451384c46968d28b5af35b3a6ef4" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_4a8b1c2d63a0fa54d124e5f990493301"
            parent="aspace_75b7451384c46968d28b5af35b3a6ef4" type="folder">12</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_549790951cc7fbfed1fab7ee5a3cd298" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lily Norwood Wilson - Italian travel guides and brochures,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1935, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_1fd28682665fd0e75f818146ade58826" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_aaf0994b98b3272ffea1dbae76e102d3"
            parent="aspace_1fd28682665fd0e75f818146ade58826" type="folder">13</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_a241eece96ae45e59013e6f171df484b" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Henry H. Wilson Jr.,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1942-1958, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_279ae077d8ceabfc15110e6751263d75" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2aee19b96f9248b97fc4dda74de87f5b"
            parent="aspace_279ae077d8ceabfc15110e6751263d75" type="folder">14</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_b6b183fa035379ef0521f88abd00d317" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Nancy E. Lukens travel diary
          <unitdate normal="1925/1925">1925</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_663cddd1570ba6ff2a4feabbbcacb7a2" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_fab50b2c08dd13050f47e845145c3219"
            parent="aspace_663cddd1570ba6ff2a4feabbbcacb7a2" type="folder">15</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_3d7c57a44377a4b8c58e213fedb6dd75" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Advertising and promotional materials,
          <unitdate type="inclusive">1915-1934, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_58d6d414e307a747fa46985d5d006f2d" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_bf3126b898d81104ef68d0ce628b0d14"
            parent="aspace_58d6d414e307a747fa46985d5d006f2d" type="folder">16</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_cb38480224be0d4e822a437a88f5e32f" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>American Law Book Company</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_79a269e335afb6a89a3cd8ae0f12e820" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Art Collectors Club </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_82fc7edda3b63602e87c76cb8ffcbb89" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Berol Mail Course in Memory Training</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_4cd5bbd645cd53546a41fb56b1d53e2b" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>British Imperial Relief Fund</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_f0063ed4df77f1cae9c55d871229d78c" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>D. H. Russell Distilling Company</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_bedfa63240cfad5eac20679f1d28a2f6" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dreamland Theatre (Radford, Virginia) - "Judith of Bethulia"</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_3df07d79ea8d4336bbfb5bc52324f230" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Frank E. Davis Fish Company / Frank E. Davis Company</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_222e820bc61dbb5bf0d9f6f62547af3e" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Funk and Wagnalls Company - "The Wit and Humor of America"</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_2d644e6624a2100551a224fa476868e6" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miss Radford Beauty Pageant</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_5c79818dfcbece9b1cf046214a26e2ae" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>National Cloak and Suit Company</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_49769ceb0623c71a5b1d525573207fad" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Public Speaker's Tool Chest</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_858e9eb4bab4a29f6e91724d74fdc4b9" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Radford, Virginia Chatauqua</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_fab1de4cd699175da1f5fa8d5280e60d" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Southern Realty and Auction Company - Blair Farm (Wytheville, Virginia)
              auction</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_8431f51108436f2c28e91f487881d114" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Vogue - ladies' ready-to-wear store (Roanoke, Virginia)</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
