<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv018060">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv018060::Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, 1916-1924, n.d.)//EN" "viblbv018060.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1916-1924, n.d.</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Anderson, Sherwood Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2015-044</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2015 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2015-08-06T16:30-0400</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916-1924, n.d.</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2015-044</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz, Archivist,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    
               
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, <unitdate>1916-1924, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2015-044</unitid>

            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc label="DIGITAL CONTENT">
                <emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available 
                    <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://omeka.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/84">online</extref></emph>.</physdesc>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.1 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 folder</extent>
            </physdesc>
           
            <abstract id="ref18" label="Abstract">This collection consists of eight letters written by American author Sherwood Anderson to Llewellyn Jones between 1916 and 1924 with three undated (but likely from the same period). Jones was the literary editor for the Chicago Evening Post. The correspondence primarily discusses the reviews of Anderson's works by Jones and other critics.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator">
                <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref11">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref12">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones must obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref15">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, Ms2015-044, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <altformavail id="ref17">
            <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
            <p>The <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/84">collection</extref> has been digitized and is available online.</p>
        </altformavail>
        <acqinfo id="ref14">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones was purchased by Special Collections in April 2015.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref13">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones was completed in August 2015.</p>
        </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection consists of eight letters written by American author Sherwood Anderson (1876-1941) to Llewellyn Jones (1884-1961) between 1916 and 1924 with three undated (but likely from the same period). Jones was the literary editor for the Chicago Evening Post. The correspondence primarily discusses the reviews of Anderson's earlier works by Jones and other critics. Anderson and Jones appear to have also been friends and a number of the letters include queries about Jones' wife and personal updates on Anderson and his second wife, Tennessee Claflin Mitchell (1874-1929). In the "Contents List" below, items showing as "c." are the date from the postmark on the envelope. In these cases, the letters themselves did not have dates.</p>
            <p>Although Anderson never mentions specific titles, the 1916 letters refer to <title render="italic">Windy McPherson's Son</title>. The note from April 1918 probably refers to Anderson's collection of poetry published that year, <title render="italic">Mid-American Chants</title>. The letter dated only "October 3" was likely written in 1918, since records indicate that was the fall in which Anderson had Spanish influenza. He writes, "Have made the draft of a new novel and writen some fifty thousand words of it," probably referring to early work on the novel <title render="italic">Poor White</title>, which was published in 1920. This typed letter also describes a recent visit to Anderson by Carl Sandburg. The two letters from 1924 both include Anderson's comments on reviews of his 1923 novel, <title render="italic">Many Marriages</title>.</p>
            <p>The collection also includes two undated letters, both of which can be placed in an approximate timeline. One was written from New York City. Although short, it mentions he will be there until the end of the year. This likely places the letter in in either late 1922 or 1923, during which time he was living there (before he moved to New Orleans with his third wife in 1924). The other undated letter laments that the reactions "I have seen, for the most part, [are] not intelligent criticism but long dissertations on someone’s notion of labor, writing, or intellectuality." This could place the letter in 1917, after the publication of Marching Men, which dealt with themes of labor issues and the intellectual figure in society.</p>
            <p>Transcripts of the letters are available in print with collection and online with the digitized copies.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist id="ref20">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p>Sherwood Anderson (1876-1941) was born in the small town of Camden, Ohio, to a large and impoverished family. An outstanding student, Anderson quit school at 14 to help support his family. In 1895 he volunteered for the Spanish-American War, then spent one year in Wittenburg College. He worked as a laborer in Chicago and later as a writer in an advertising agency. Unable to resist the urge to write and live a bohemian lifestyle, Anderson suffered an emotional breakdown and walked away from his family and his mail-order paint business. He had three children (two sons and a daughter) from his first marriage. Anderson eventually married three more times.</p>
            <p>Anderson published 27 books, plays, and volumes of short stories, along with numerous articles in periodicals. Often controversial, he wrote about issues as diverse as the sexual awakening of adolescence to the alienation caused by industrialization. He was very active in the intellectual community of the day and was instrumental in helping both Faulkner and Hemingway to be published for the first time.</p>
            <p>Anderson wrote to his daughter from Kansas City in March, 1933, "As you know, my dear, I never did domesticate well," but he always maintained relationships with his children. Later in life, Anderson embarked on his fourth--and only successful--marriage, to Eleanor Copenhaver, a native of Marion, Virginia. They traveled extensively and spent summers on their rural farm, "Ripshin," near Marion. Anderson bought and operated both of Marion's local newspapers and eventually passed ownership along to his eldest son, Robert.</p>
            <p>Sherwood Anderson died on the first leg of a long-anticipated trip to South America. He developed peritonitis and was hospitalized in Panama, where he passed away on March 8, 1941.</p>
            <p>See the Sherwood Anderson Foundation website for additional <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://sherwoodandersonfoundation.org/2010/02/sherwood_anderson_a_brief_biog_1.php">biographical information</extref> and a <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://sherwoodandersonfoundation.org/2006/07/sherwood_andersons_major_books.php">chronology of his major works</extref>.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <bioghist id="ref19">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p>Llewellyn Jones (July 13, 1884-July 1, 1961) was an American editor and author. He served as the literary editor of the Chicago Evening Post from 1914-1932. He later worked for book publisher Willett, Clark, and Company. He authored three books on writing, criticism, and reading. His personal and professional papers are held by the Beinecke Rare Book and Mansuscript Library at Yale University. A <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/beinecke.jonesl">guide to the collection</extref>, including a brief biography, can be found online.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <arrangement id="ref21">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The correspondence in the collection is arranged in chronological order. In the "Contents List" below, items showing as "c." are listed by the date from the postmark on the envelope. In these cases, the letters themselves did not have dates. Undated letters that cannot be clearly placed in the timeline are at the end, with a note about the possible year(s).</p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref16">
            <head>Related Materials</head>
            <p>Special Collections houses several collections containing materials by or about Sherwood Anderson: 
                <list>
                    <item>Sherwood Anderson Collection, 1912-1938, Ms1973-002. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00247.xml">Finding aid</extref> available online. </item>
                    <item>Sherwood Anderson Photograph and Postcard, 1929, 1939, Ms2011-004. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00773.xml">Finding aid</extref> available online. </item>
                    <item>Welford D. Taylor Collection on Sherwood Anderson, 1927-1992, Ms2015-045. This collection is currently being processed and a finding aid is forthcoming. The collection is accessible to researchers, who should contact Special Collections for additional information. </item>
                </list></p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        </descgrp>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Persons:</head>
            <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</persname>
            <persname source="local">Jones, Llewellyn, 1884-1961</persname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">American Literature--Virginia</subject>
                <subject source="lcsh">Authors, American--20th century</subject>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Occupations:</head>
            <occupation source="lcsh">Authors</occupation>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">Correspondence</genreform>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <blockquote>
                <p><emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://omeka.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/84" xlink:actuate="onRequest">online</extref></emph>. </p>
            </blockquote>
            <c01 id="ref2" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Correspondence,<unitdate>1916-1924, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid2075001" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref3" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>July 26, 1916</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref4" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>c. September 9, 1916</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref5" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>c. April 26, 1918</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref6" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>October 3, [1918]</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref7" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>c. July 22, 1924</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref8" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>c. December 11, 1924</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref10" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Undated [possibly after the publication of <title render="italic">Marching Men</title> (1917)]</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref9" level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Undated, from New York City [possibly 1922 or 1923]</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
