<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01729">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01729::Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, 1928-1947)//EN" "viblbv01729.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1928-1947</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2013-094</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2014 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2014-07-21T14:45-0400</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1947</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2013-094</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Betsy Reed, Graduate Assistant, and Kira A. Dietz, Archivist,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>

    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, <unitdate normal="1928/1947" type="inclusive">1928-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2013-094</unitid>
               <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 box</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>            
            <abstract id="ref3" label="Abstract">This collection contains a book of meeting minutes for the Art League of Philadelphia recorded primarily by secretaries Margaret Nefferdorf and Elsa Hofheinz. The collection also includes Elsa Hofheinz's diary from 1928 when she was in high school.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator">
                <persname source="local" role="Creator (cre)">Hofheinz, Elsa Marie Rupp, 1912-2012</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref4">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref5">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref6">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia and Diary of Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, Ms2013-094, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref8">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>This collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2013.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref9">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philadelphia with Manuscript Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz was completed in May 2014.</p>
        </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref10">
            <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
            <p>Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz Wurtz (1912-2012) became the secretary for the Art League of Philadephia in 1944. Elsa was enthusiastic about art from a young age as evidenced from her high school journal. She was a cartoonist for her school's newspaper and her diary contains many sketches and doodles. Little is known about Elsa's later life outside of the Art League, but it is known that she met her husband Charles Wurtz through the Art League.</p>
            <p>The Art League of Philadelphia aimed to present and promote the work of member artists, both male and female. Their work included painting, watercolors, ceramics, photography and a variety of printmaking techniques. The League held exhibitions of members' work, lectures, and studio classes. Many members were graduates of art institutions including the Pennsylvania Museum and School of Industrial Art, the Pennsylvannia Academy of the Fine Arts, the Woodmere Art Museum, and the Barnes Foundation.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref11">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection contains a book of minutes from the meetings of the Art League of Philadelphia from October 21, 1936 to October 21, 1947 as recorded by the League's secretaries over those years. The Art League of Philadelphia aimed to present and promote the work of member artists, both male and female. Their work included painting, watercolors, ceramics, photography and a variety of printmaking techniques. The League held exhibitions of members' work, lectures, and studio classes. Many members were graduates of art institutions including the Pennsylvania Museum and School of Industrial Art, the Pennsylvannia Academy of the Fine Arts, the Woodmere Art Museum, and the Barnes Foundation. The minutes record plans for upcoming events, the group's monthly monetary balance, and yearly lists of members.</p>
            <p>The collection also contains the diary of Art League member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz from 1928. Elsa Hofheinz later became Art League secretary in 1944. Her diary details her comments on fashion, her experiences learning to drive, her daily activities at school and around the house, as well as her artistic endeavors. The diary also contains many of Elsa's doodles.</p>
            <p>In 2015, the following biographical information was submitted by family of Elsa Wurtz. This and additional information from the family has been included with the collection:</p>
            <p>A Philadelphian, Mrs. Wurtz was awarded a four-year scholarship to Moore College of Art. She designed greeting cards for Norcross in New York City before learning to read blueprints and then illustrating them for Fleetwings (an aircraft supplier or manufacturer outside Philadelphia) during World War II.</p> 
            <p>Early in her career, she painted in watercolor and exhibited at numerous venues, including the Rittenhouse Square Clothesline Exhibit. As time went on, she painted Impressionistic works in acrylic. She also created silkscreen art, prints, and worked in stained glass.</p> 
             <p>Her future husband always said that he picked out his mother-in-law and married her only single daughter. Elsa preferred to put it that she picked out her father-in-law (a fellow member of the Art League) and married his only single son!</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref12">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is in its original order.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Corporate Names:</head>
            <corpname source="local">Art League of Philadelphia.</corpname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Persons:</head>
            <persname source="local">Hofheinz, Elsa Marie Rupp, 1912-2012</persname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">Diaries</genreform>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="local">History of Women in Architecture</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Women</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref1" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Diary of Art League Member Elsa Marie Rupp Hofheinz, <unitdate>1928</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid1870004" type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref2" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Meeting Minutes of the Art League of Philasdelphia, <unitdate normal="1936/1947" type="inclusive">1936-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid1870005" type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
