<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00362">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00362:: William H. Collier Ledger, 1856-1887)//EN" "viblbv00362.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William H. Collier Ledger, <date>1856-1887</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Collier, William H.
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-027
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>02/25/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William H. Collier Ledger, <date>1856-1887</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-027
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William H. Collier Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1856-1887
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-027
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.3 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Farm and household expense ledger of William H. Collier of Northampton County, North Carolina. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the William H. Collier Ledger must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: William H. Collier Ledger, Ms2009-027 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The William H. Collier Ledger was purchased by Special Collections in 2009. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the William H. Collier Ledger commenced and was completed in February 2009. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William H. Collier, son of Joseph and Sarah C. Mangum Collier, was born in Northampton, North Carolina in 1822. He married Sarah Parham (1824-1857) in 1843. The couple had eight children, including Joseph H. (mentioned frequently within the ledger). Following the Sarah's death, Collier in 1860 married Elizabeth Rebecca Bonner Garner, by whom he fathered another seven children. William H. Collier died in 1906. 
</p>
<p>Within his ledger, Collier provides the year of birth of a woman named Charity--likely a slave--and the names and birth years of her children and grandchildren, including: Mary (1841), Lieuanna (1847), Henry (1849), Susan (1851), Julia (1853), Ben (1855), Sarah Ann (1857), twins Charles and Ned (1859), and George (1860). In later entries, Collier makes frequent mention of hiring and paying members of the Moody family. The 1870 census for Northampton County lists 45-year-old African American Charity Moody living with her husband, Burton and children Henry, 21; Sarah, 16; Ben, 17; and Charles and Edward, 12. No further record could be found on the Moody family.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of a ledger maintained by William H. Collier, a farmer from Northampton County, North Carolina during the latter half of the nineteenth century. Collier's ledger lists in detail his expenses--for household goods as well as farm supplies and equipment--during a 30-year period. (Although the ledger contains data for the years 1857-1860, the years 1862-1864 are lacking, and more frequent entries commence with 1866.) Many of the entries, made regularly, relate to farm labor.  Recorded for both long-term and day laborers are wages, work performed, provisions issued, and wages withheld. Appearing after the names of several workers are the initials "FM" and "FW," likely describing individuals as freedmen and freedwomen. Members of the Moody family are mentioned frequently among the laborers, as are members of the Nolley, Woodruff, Jordan and Hodges families. Collier often used child laborers, hired from their parents or other relatives.
</p>
<p>Collier also lists within the ledger the amount of cotton produced on his farm as well as the amount of corn produced and sent to mill. He makes special mention of the amount of his trade in late 1865, "after the surrender of Lee's Army" and "sales of cotton soald this fall after the serender of the Southern Army." He details his trades and purchases with various merchants in North Carolina's Halifax and Northampton counties--as well as Petersburg, Virginia--for such items as clothing, medicine, foodstuffs, and farming supplies and equipment. Also within the ledger are notations regarding Collier's account as administrator of his father's will and copies of agreements for obtaining credit against future crops and for sharecropping on his land.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive">1856-1887
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
