<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00658">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00658:: W. J. Bryan Account Ledger, 1860-1911)//EN" "viblbv00658.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the W. J. Bryan Account Ledger, <date>1860-1911</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Bryan, W. J. Account Ledger
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-027
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>06/08/2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the W. J. Bryan Account Ledger, <date>1860-1911</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2010-027
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">W. J. Bryan Account Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1860-1911
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-027
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.5. cu. ft. 
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Account ledger of W. J. Bryan, a Greene County, Pennylvania farmer, listing sales and property rental transactions, as well as royalty payments received for coal and oil removed from properties in Marion County, West Virginia and Greene County, Pennsylvania.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the W. J. Bryan Account Ledger must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: W. J. Bryan Account Ledger, Ms2010-027 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The W. J. Bryan Account Ledger was donated to Special Collections in 2009. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the W. J. Bryan Account Ledger commenced in May 2010 and was completed in June 2010. The volume had been accessioned as an unidentified railroad ledger but upon closer inspection during processing was found to be the personal ledger of W. J. Bryan, and the title was changed accordingly. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>According to census records, Weden J. Bryan was born in Pennsylvania in November 1825. He was married around 1849. In the 1860 census, he appears as a 33-year-old farmer residing in Greene County, Pennsylvania, together with his wife, 28-year-old Cecelia Bryan. The couple had one daughter, Sarah, born around 1852. W. J. Bryan seems to have died prior to 1910, though Cecelia is listed in the 1910 census.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of a 408-page ledger belonging to W. J. Bryan, a farmer in Greene County, Pennsylvania. The ledger lists transactions which seem to be related to sales and rental payments. Though the ledger details a few transactions for farm rentals or sales of farm commodities, many of the entries consist only of page numbers and money amounts which have been carried over from an earlier ledger (an entry of "6/2.25/22/.50" apparently representing "page 6, $2.25; page 22, $.50" and so forth). On opposing pages, Bryan notes account payments. Payment seems often to have been made in the form of labor, with Bryan noting what work was performed. The entries begin in 1860 and end in 1904, and run through the ledger's first 336 pages. The remaining pages are devoted to bank account records and to money received as royalty payments on coal and oil removed from property in Marion County, West Virginia and Greene County, Pennsylvania. 
</p>
<p>Also included is a folder containing papers which had been placed within the ledger. These papers consist largely of letters from the Fairmont Coal Company (Fairmont, West Virginia), concerning the payment of mineral royalties during the first decade of the twentieth century.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive">1860-1911
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence and notes
<unitdate type="inclusive">1903-1908
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
