<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00130">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00130::Hotel Roanoke
Architectural Drawings)//EN" "viblbv00130"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1890-1983 </date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Hotel Roanoke, Architectural Drawings.
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2000-093
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Tamara Kennelly
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. 68 Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by Clayton McGahee.<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1890-1983 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2000-093
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Tamara Kennelly
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Tamara Kennelly
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1983
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">Ms2000-093
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">22 containers, 132 cu. ft, 1,992 drawings.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings collection includes information about Hotel Roanoke in the form of original drawings, blueprints and photocopies dating from 1890 to 1983. The
collection contains foundation, floor, and framing plans, elevations; ventilation, plumbing, heating and cooling plans; external and internal details for various rooms, stairways, and features; alterations;
landscaping details; and exterior features, such as swimming pool and stables.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings, Ms2000-093, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Part 1 of the Hotel Roanoke drawings was acquired at an unknown date. Part 2 of the Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings was donated to the Special Collections in 2001 through the Office of the Vice
President for Administration and Treasurer at Virginia Tech.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
        <p>The Special Collections <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu">Imagebase</extref> contains two digital images under Hotel Roanoke, Southwest Virginia.
</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings were processed at two different periods. The processing, arrangement, and description of the Part 2 accession of Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings commenced in
October, 2003 and was completed in November, 2003. The drawings in Part 1, which were an earlier accession, were processed in 2001. Because of the size of the collection and staff limitations, it was not possible
to reprocess the drawings in Part 1 so that they conform to the standards used in Part 2.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The original Hotel Roanoke was built in 1882 by the Norfolk Western Railroad for $60,000. The hotel started with 34 rooms and quickly grew to 94 rooms in 1890. It was severely damaged by a fire in 1895 and was
rebuilt. It continued to expand through wars and the depression. By the 1950s, it had over 384 rooms within its distinctive half-timber English Tudor style facade.
</p>
      <p>As the public began to use interstate highways rather than passenger rail for travel, the Hotel Roanoke experienced a decline in business. Unable to compete with the national hotel chains located near the
interstate highway, the Norfolk Western Railroad decided to concentrate on the transportation aspects of their corporation and closed the Hotel Roanoke in the fall of 1989. James McComas, then president of
Virginia Tech, was approached by city leaders to accept the hotel as a gift and develop a first class hotel and conference center. The Virginia Tech Foundation accepted and renovated the Hotel Roanoke, while the
City of Roanoke constructed the adjacent conference center.
</p>
      <p>The $27.8 million renovation of the Hotel Roanoke was financed through a mixture of funding sources: a consortium of local financial institutions loaned the project $6.5 million, a $6.0 million loan through
section 108 HUD loan program with the City of Roanoke Redevelopment and Housing Authority for the creation of 300 new jobs, $3.0 million from the sale of land surrounding the hotel, $4.0 million loan from the
Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc., $1.3 million loan from Doubletree hotels, $1.0 million loan from a local Roanoke foundation, and $6.0 million from local citizens and companies in a local fund drive to save the
historic hotel. The Hotel Roanoke is privately owned by a for-profit subisidiary of the Virginia Tech Real Estate Foundation, Inc.
</p>
      <p>Since reopening in the spring of 1995 as the Hotel Roanoke &amp; Conference Center, the 332-room facility has received many historic preservation and architectural awards. It was placed on the prestigious
National Register of Historic Places and on the Virginia Landmarks register, and it received the 1996 National Trust for Historic Preservation Honor Award for restoration and preservation.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings consist of an extensive set of drawings, blueprints, and photocopies. Original perspective drawings mounted on presentation boards and a file with specifications for the
remodeling of 24 east wing bathrooms in the hotel are also part of the collection. The drawings in the collection span the years 1890-1983. The bulk of the drawings are from 1937-53.
</p>
      <p>Part 1 includes blueprints for the swimming pool, motor inn, and laundry; floor plans; heating, cooling, and plumbing plans; elevations; finish schedule; kitchen, ballroom, office, beauty shop, and parking
plans; details of entrance and back porch, and various interior and exterior details and alterations.
</p>
      <p>Part 2 includes structural steel drawings; heating, cooling, ventilation and plumbing systems; external and internal details for various rooms and features; floor plans, framing plans, elevations and sections;
foundation plans; blueprintss for alterations; and various landscape details.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The drawings were divided into two parts depending on the time of accession. Part 2 was further subdivided into series depending on serial numbers, overall subject matter, and chronological sequence. Part 1 was
arranged somewhat chronologically. The drawings span 1890-1983.
</p>
      <p>Part 1 is arranged in thirteen series, housed in portfolios 1 to 13. Individual drawings in Part 1 were assigned numbers in the inventory available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://drive.google.com/a/vt.edu/file/d/1-A-PI3h825diSvp2atmoXfRBvtAVXHX5/view?usp=sharing">online</extref>. However, these
numbers indicate only the position in the portfolio relative to the other drawings. The assigned numbers have not been written on the drawings.
</p>
      <p>Part 2 is arranged in nine series by job number and subject matter. It is further arranged in chronological order. Each series is housed in a portfolio ranging from A-I.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
      <otherfindaid>
        <head>Other Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Individual drawings in Part 1 were assigned numbers in the inventory available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://drive.google.com/a/vt.edu/file/d/1-A-PI3h825diSvp2atmoXfRBvtAVXHX5/view?usp=sharing">online</extref>.</p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>

    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
    <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
    <subject source="local">Hotel Roanoke</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>

    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Hotel Roanoke Architectural Drawings
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1983
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>SERIES I
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-80
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 50
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 1, portfolio 1
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">1
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of proposed swimming pool, motor inn, laundry, air conditioning study, and floor plans.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 50
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 2, portfolio 2
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">2
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of track level plan heating, site plan and riser diagram, door and window details, elevations, interior elevations, terrazzo plans, door and finish schedule.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 149
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 3, portfolio 3
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">3
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of door and finish schedule, waiting room, coffee shop plan, preliminary floor plans, electric light, power and bell system, valve control schedules, foundation plans, and roof and penthouse
machinery drawings.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 149
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 4, portfolio 4
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">4
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of details of swimarium, gable wall column setting, sections through fiberglass and plexiglass, kitchen equipment layouts, heating and cooling risers, air conditioning study, coffee shop kitchen
plans, electric lights and power circuits, ballroom plan, beauty shop office, Shenandoah room details and sections.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 72
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 5, portfolio 5
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">5
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of floor plans, alterations and additions of basement study, fountains room, kitchen details, furring window stools, marble details, floor plans and elevations.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 56
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 6, portfolio 6
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">6
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of office for traffic department, steel ladders and access doors, space for Pullman company in Hotel Roanoke, floor plans, and diagram for water drainage.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 57
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 7, portfolio 7
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">7
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of elevations, wiring drawing, and fire pump and riser details.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 236
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 8, portfolio 8
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">8
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of renovations of shops, health centers, passenger station, elevator shafts, waiting room, laundry room, penthouse plans and details, ice water circulation diagram, and foundation room counter
bakery.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 70
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 9, portfolio 9
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">9
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of service station, parking lot, pneumatic temperature and electric sequence, and roof sections.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 164
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 10, portfolio 10
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">10
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of details of entrance vestibule, drawings of back porch, store room and refrigerating room, cigar counter, mail box and chute, cupola details, enlarged garage parking, column schedule, situation
plan, electric diagram and wing wall placing plan.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 64
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 11, portfolio 11
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">11
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of steam generating plant, exterior details, sections, AC-b and AC-p controls and restaurant details.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 89
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 6, portfolio 12
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">12
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Elevations, door and window schedules, alterations and additions, piping layout plan, oriel windows, stair and station details and beam details.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 234
</unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/4, drawer 7, portfolio 13
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">13
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Details of handrails, light cove details, exhibition room plans, spandrel details, footing and foundation pans, roof and attic framing plan, toilets and exhaust ducts, room service checkers ducts, cashiers
counters, telephone shelf, and location of tunnel for foundation plan.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>SERIES II
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-83
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job 37.935
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 5, portfolio E
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">E
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 12
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints of structural steel drawings for all floors, ranging from 08.1937-09.1937
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job 37.935
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 6, portoflio A
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">A
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 17
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprint drawings for heating, ventilation and plumbing, all dated 10.5.1937
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 19
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 11, portfolio C
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">C
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>drawings for external and internal details, bathroom details, beauty parlor, palm room, cigar room details, and internal details of cornice, gable and stairs.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 44
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 12, portfolio B
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">B
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprint drawings for all floor plans, framing plans, elevations and sections.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Portfolio F
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/6, drawer 6, portfolio F
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">F
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 78
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Job 450-1A
</unittitle>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Blueprints of drawings showing details of typical bedrooms, bathrooms, and beauty parlor; footing and foundation plans; floor framing plans; column schedule; electrical plans and riser details.
</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Job 450-1B
</unittitle>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Blueprints of drawings showing key plans for all floors, kitchen floor base details, door schedules and room finishing schedule, pantry details, and penthouse details. Also includes drawings showing alterations
and additions to the main building.
</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job 450-1B
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945-46
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 7, portfolio G
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">G
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 84
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Details of windows, floor plans, elevations, spandrel details, air conditioning systems, pipe gallery, heating venting and plumbing details.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job 450-3
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/6, drawer 6, portfolio D
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">D
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 49
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Blueprints drawings of alterations and additions, including floor plans, elevations, details, floor framing plans, mechanical plans, and electrical plans.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job 450-1, 450-1B
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-80
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>Set of drawers in first floor in Special Collections, portfolio H
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">H
</container>
              <physdesc>Total number of drawings: 213
</physdesc>
            </did>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Job 450-1
</unittitle>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Original drawings of grating for paved areas, equestrian door, underground doors, installation of screens and laundry plans, fountain room details, unit enclosures, rack in engineer's office and additional
stairs No. 2. Original drawings of exit stairs No 2, bench support letter rack and cashier window. Also includes original drawings of additional Exit stairs, masonry boilers, soiled linen hamper, health club,
mirrors in corridor, fire protection, ventilation, deep well pump house, sprinkler system catch basin, wrought iron balcony, and garage ceiling plan.
</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Job 450-1B
</unittitle>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Original drawings of lifts (Otis), doors, front elevator, bath details, driveway, enclosure between ballroom and corridor, fire ladder, reflector signs, electric drawings, ventilation, marquee details,
reflector signs, refrigerator for meats, water pump, external wood details, writing room, ice converter chute, locking device for accordion and original boards of diagram, display cases, tunnel details.
</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Job number unlisted, total number of drawings: 26
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-83
</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physloc>B/MC/5, drawer 5, portfolio I
</physloc>
              <container label="Folio" type="folio">I
</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Copies of drawings of floor plans dated 1983. Blueprints of drawings showing fire protection, air conditioners, elevations and renovation of beauty shop.
</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
