<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00664">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00664:: Moore Family Papers, 1847-1948)//EN" "viblbv00664.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Moore Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847-1948</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Moore Family Papers <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-033
                    </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
                </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia Polytechnic
                    Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Julia Viets,
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6/15/2010</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Moore Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847-1948</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">Ms2010-033 </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Julia Viets </label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Moore Family Papers <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847-1948 </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-033 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 box; 1.4 cu. ft. </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">A collection of photographs, correspondence, and other
                documents created by members of the Moore family that span three generations between
                1847 and 1948. Most of this collection is comprised of letters that relate family
                news. </abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Moore family </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>There are no restrictions. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Moore Family Papers, Ms2010-033, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The Moore Family Papers were acquired by Special Collections prior to 2009. </p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information </head>
      <p>The Moore family papers include letters and other documents from Moore family members
                that span three generations. </p>
      <p>John Moore (I) is a member of the oldest generation represented in this collection.
                His parents were immigrants from Europe: his mother, Catherine, came from England
                and his father, Garret Moore, came from Ireland. Although much of John Moore's
                extended family lived in Ireland, he grew up in Louisiana on a plantation run by
                slaves. John's first job was teaching. He then became an army surgeon. In 1853, his
                first post was at Fort Myers, Florida, during the Third Seminole War. Later, John
                was employed in the United States Army expedition against the Mormons and in the
                Union Army during the Civil War. He had three other siblings named Mary, Robert, and
                Richard (who died in 1908). His two children were named children John and Juliet. </p>
      <p>John Moore (II) is the elder John Moore's son. He was born on April 12, 1866 in
                Eutaw, Alabama and was 5'11. From December 5, 1890 to October 3, 1902, he worked in
                the treasury department of the Internal Revenue Service. There, he started out as a
                substitute clerk, class D, but was promoted on May 7, 1895. In 1904, he worked for
                Central Union Telephone Co. In 1895, he married Elizabeth and they had two children:
                Robert and Mary. He separated from his wife and lived with Mary Kelly, his aunt, in
                Indiana because of his alcoholism. </p>
      <p>Elizabeth "Lizzie" Moore was John Moore's (I) wife; her maiden name was Ford. Born in
                1873, she was 5'7, 136 pounds, and had pale brown hair. Mary was twenty-two when
                first courted by her husband. She had many brothers, including one named Will. </p>
      <p>Mary Mead Moore was John and Lizzie Moore's daughter. She was born on September 29,
                1906,and graduated from Randolph Macon Women's College in 1929. She kept in contact
                with Betty, a college friend who lived in Charleston, for the rest of her life. Mary
                worked in Roanoke as a schoolteacher and was deeply religious and interested in
                radios. </p>
      <p>Robert Garrett Moore was Mary's elder brother. He was born in 1897 and was a clumsy
                child. As a young man, he was estranged from his father and wanted to become an
                engineer. In June of 1925, he died at the age of 28: during a reserve officers
                training camp, he drowned from either cramps or a heart spasm. On the day of his
                death, he had complained about heart pain and vertigo to his drill sergeant. He is
                buried in Timber Ridge Church Yard, located outside of Lowery, Virginia. </p>
      <p>Juliet Moore is the daughter of John Moore (I). She lived on a cattle farm in Iowa
                and her husband's name was Burt. They had two sons, John and Gaylord, who both
                studied medicine at Iowa State University. </p>
      <p>Gaylord is the eldest son of Juliet Moore. In addition to attending Iowa State
                University, he also went to Rush College in Chicago. There, he played trombone in
                the college band and sang soprano in the choir. In 1938, he became a medical officer
                for the US Naval Air Station in Pensacola, Florida. Gaylord was close with his
                cousin, Robert Garrett Moore. </p>
      <p>Mary Moore Kelly was John Moore's (I) sister. She died in late 1921. Based in
                Bloomington, Indiana, she was a member of Daughters of the American Revolution and
                interested in family genealogy. In the early 1900s, she tried to construct a family
                tree with Arthur Walters Cameron Moore and Henry Percival Moore, two distant cousins
                from Australia. She was married to Captain James R. Kelly, who worked in railroads
                before serving in the Indiana's fourteenth regiment during the Civil War; he was
                mortally wounded in battle and died in a Virginia hospital. </p>
      <p>Henry Percival Moore "HP" was born on November 8, 1860 to Robert Walters Moore. He
                lived in Adelaide, Australia. In 1885, he married his wife Eleanor and they had
                three children. In 1912, his eldest Robert was stationed in India, his other son
                Brian was seventeen, and his daughter Mary was nine. </p>
      <p>Arthur Walters Cameron Moore was Henry Percival Moore's brother and lived in St.
                Claire, Australia. He had several daughters and a wife named Sophy, all of which
                belonged to the Women's Liberal League. In addition to Henry, he had a widowed
                sister named Louise Gardner. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection consists of fourteen folders of photographs, correspondence, and
                other documents relating to the Moore family between 1847 and 1948. </p>
      <p>The first folder, Australia Moore family and genealogy papers, contains
                correspondence between Mary M. Kelly and her cousins, Arthur Walters Cameron Moore
                and Henry Percival Moore during the early 1900s. In addition to relaying family news
                and bemoaning the onset of World War I, the letters discuss Moore family ancestry,
                tracing roots back to Ireland and an abandoned Catholic faith. A partial family tree
                is included in a letter written on January 17, 1911. </p>
      <p>The second folder, Captain James R, Kelly and Mary Moore Kelly papers, contains
                photocopies and a transcript of letters and papers written by the couple during the
                Civil War. It includes James R Kelly's notice of promotion to Captain of the Union
                Rifles on June 5, 1861 and a partial memoir of his Civil War service as written by
                his daughter. The correspondence ranges from July 20, 1861 to March 1, 1862 and
                gives a lot of insight into Civil War soldier conditions. In a notable letter dated
                July 23, 1861, James tells Mary, "Our scouts surprised a secessionist camp
                consisting of forty-four men armed and a lot of women. All of the men were killed
                but ten. They have been brought into our camp; they are hard looking wretches. It is
                thought they will all be hung." In another dated January 28, 1862, he says, "The
                Indiana regiments here are regarded as the most reliable on the Potomac while I
                feel proud of Indiana, and her brave soldiers, at the same time I can plainly see
                and feel that in order to maintain that proud position, we will most likely be
                exposed to the most dangerous positions in the army." On February 19, he laments: "I
                have just been out among the men's tents, and in their quarters, the mud and water
                is full shoe-top deep. It is most painful to see the poor men cooking in the mud and
                rain but then it can't be helped, they must cook and eat while they live."</p>
      <p>The third folder, Elizabeth Moore correspondence, contains family news as well as
                condolences about her son's death in 1925. Many of the letters are written to her
                from her husband; they lament about his estranged relationship with Robert, her cold
                behavior towards him, and his unhappiness with himself. In a letter date August 12,
                1909, he tells her:</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>I feel that my life is wholly broken-maybe forever. I'm sorry for it all as it
                    has been and has turned out. It has greatly saddened and soured me to see it
                    thus-but maybe there is yet one more turn in life's ever changing kaleidoscope
                    that will bring us together as one again. But fate is sometimes so cruel and
                    unkind-but with me off life's checkerboard you'll be free and happy I hope, and
                    will find someone who more nearly deserves your love and devotion than I do. I
                    have richly earned your contempt and don't wonder you inwardly despise me when
                    you recall the past and the horrors that lurk in its deepening shadows. The
                    awful thoughts and the pangs of regret haunt me every hour of the course will be
                    the burden of my torment in hell. Oh! That I never been born! I am afraid
                    to be alone. Sometimes I wonder if I am going insane! I deserve it.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The fourth folder, Gaylord pictures, contains three pictures: one of him as a little
                boy and two of him dressed in Navy uniform.</p>
      <p>The fifth folder, John Moore (I) correspondence, includes photocopies and a
                transcript of letters written between 1847 and 1862 that chronicle his career
                transition from a teacher in Louisiana to an army surgeon in the Third Seminole War,
                Army expedition against the Mormons, various Native American battles, and the Civil
                War. The letters hold strong opinions and their subjects include the famine in
                Ireland, slavery, and his Army experiences. On October 20, 1854, he wrote about
                meeting Billy Bowlegs: "I was out in the woods some distance about a week ago, with
                the Indian agent, to see King Bowlegs and twenty or thirty of his warriors. He was
                very polite, spread skins for us on the ground and an awning overhead to keep off
                the sun. When Billy spoke all the others kept a respectful silence." On July
                24, 1859, he wrote the following about the Mormons: "The details of their domestic
                life are disgusting and revolting beyond anything you can imagine. How long are such
                a people to be not only tolerated but furnished with the means of growing rich
                beyond that of any proportion of the people in the States?" On Dec 13, 1862 he was
                in the midst of the Battle of Fredericksburg and penned, "One of the most bloody
                battles of the war will probably come off here today. I don't know what will happen
                to me. If you fancy the approach of such a battle depressed the spirits of men
                or officers you are greatly mistaken. I have never seen more mirth and joking than
                among the hundreds of officers assembled about this building, which is used as the
                HD. Quarters of General Burnside, and within range of the revel guns."</p>
      <p>The sixth folder, John R. Moore (II) correspondence, contains letters written to
                family. His main recipients were his sister, Juliet, and aunt, Mary Kelly. He wrote
                about family news, his disappointment in his son, his alcoholism, his separation
                from his wife, and his work. A notable letter is one penned on March 2, 1895 to his
                future in-laws asking them for Elizabeth's hand in marriage. In another, written in
                Nov 1898, he tells his aunt: "I cannot suck happiness out of a bottle." On July 14,
                1919, he laments about his son to his sister, "He has a fat chance to become an
                engineer. He should be a preacher- they don't do any work." In a sobering letter
                written to his aunt on June 20, 1925, John reveals that he first learned about his
                son's death from a newspaper clipping, after the funeral had already occurred. </p>
      <p>The seventh folder, John R. Moore (II) documents &amp; pictures includes items such
                as account books, tintype portraits, Homestead papers, and Civil Service Commission
                papers. </p>
      <p>The eighth folder, General Moore family photographs, contains sixteen photographs of
                various generations of Moore family members. It includes pictures of the family at
                the beach, posing in front of slave workers, and a portrait Robert Moore taken on 25
                December 1894. </p>
      <p>The ninth folder, Mary M. Kelly papers, contains correspondence relating family news
                and other documents such as real-estate warranty deeds, tax receipts, and a list of
                ancestry for Daughters of the American Revolution membership requirements. </p>
      <p>The tenth and eleventh folders, Mary Mead Moore correspondence, include letters she
                received between 1902 and 1948. They mainly relate news of family and friends,
                information on radios, and advice about finances. Many letters written during the
                summer of 1925 convey condolences for her brother's death. Mary's main correspondent
                was her college friend, Betty.</p>
      <p> The twelfth folder, Mary Mead Moore pictures, holds twenty-six photographs, mainly
                portraits, of Mary taken throughout her life. Included is a portrait of her posing
                in a college graduation gown with her mother and a stark black and white picture of
                middle-aged Mary with a serious expression and the word "soul" penciled on the back. </p>
      <p>The last two folders, other correspondence and additional papers and ephemera,
                include materials created between 1880 and 1921. The letters talk about family news.
                One interesting letter addressed to Robert Moore in Blacksburg from an unknown
                sender on February 1, 1922, contains two lines: "If a body write a body, and meet
                with no reply; might a body write a body, and ask a body why? Bob Moore, you're such
                a mess!!!" Documents include such items as calling cards, receipts, newspaper
                articles, and report cards. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by creator and material type. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Australia Moore family genealogy papers <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Captain James R. Kelly papers (photocopies &amp; transcript)
                            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Elizabeth Moore correspondence <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Gaylord pictures <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John Moore (I) correspondence (photocopies &amp; transcript)
                            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John R. Moore (II) correspondence <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John R. Moore (II) documents &amp; pictures <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>General Moore family photographs <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mary M. Kelly papers <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mary Mead Moore correspondence (1902-1931) <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mary Mead Moore correspondence (1932-1948) <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mary Mead Moore pictures <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Other correspondence <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Additional papers &amp; ephemera <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
