<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00526">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00526:: Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers, 1985-1997, 2013)//EN" "viblbv00526.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers, <date>1985-1997, 2013</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Harkness, Sarah Pillsbury, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms1997-024
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Lora Settle, <date>10/21/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers, <date>1985-1997, 2013</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms1997-024
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1985-1997, 2013
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms1997-024
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 box, 1 oversize folder; 2.25 cu. ft. 
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers consist of a book written by her in 1985, a booklet documenting the presentations given on November 21, 1991, and architectural drawings and photographs for her 1996-97 design of a house in Essex, Massachusetts.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Sarah Pillsbury Harkness, Ms1997-024 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1997.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Sarah Pillsbury Harkness Papers commenced and was completed in April 1998.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Born 1914. Sarah Pillsbury Harkness, an architect of Lexington, Massachusetts, received her Master of Architecture degree from the Smith College Graduate School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture in 1940. She was a founder, in 1945, and now Principal Emeritus of the Architects Collaborative (TAC). She was President of the Boston Society of Architects, a chapter of the AIA, in 1985. She was a Distinguished Visiting Lecturer and Guest Lecturer at the University of Arizona, Tucson, a lecturer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and a thesis advisor, lecturer, critic, and honorary member of the Boston Architectural Center.
</p>
<p>Harkness's most noteworthy designs include the New Main Library and the Olin Arts Center at Bates College in Lewiston, Maine; the Anita Tuvin Schlechter Auditorium at Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania; the Art School Addition at the Worcester Art Museum in Worcester, Massachusetts; and the C. Thurston Chase Learning Center of the Eaglebrook School in Deerfield, Massachusetts.</p>
<p>Harkness has received many awards in her career, including the Boston Society of Architects Prize (1941), the American Association of School Administrators Award for her design of the Fox Middle School in Bedford, New York (1967), the American Institute of Architects Honor Award for her design of the Chase Learning Center of the Eaglebrook School (1967), the American School and University Louis I. Kahn Citation for her design of the Olin Arts Center at Bates College (1987), and the Boston Society of Architects 1991 Award of Honor.</p>
<p>Harkness was elected as a fellow of the American Institute of Architects in 1979. She is a registered architect of Massachusetts and Tennessee. Harkness died May 22, 2013.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Sarah Pillsbury Harkness papers consist of a book written by her in 1985, <title render="italic">Sustainable Design for Two Maine Islands</title>; a booklet documenting the presentations given on November 21, 1991, at an awards dinner by the Boston Society of Architects, where Harkness was presented with the 1991 Award of Honor; and architectural drawings and photographs for her 1996-1997 design of a house in Essex, Massachusetts.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Separated Material
</head>
<p>The following book has been removed and cataloged for the Special Collections Rare Book Collection:
</p>
<p>
<bibref>Harkness, Sarah P. <title render="italic">Sustainable Design for Two Maine Islands</title>. Boston, Boston Architectural Center, 1985. This book is cataloged for the Rare Book Room, Special Collections. <title render="bold">Rare Book Collection HT393 M2 S9 1985 Spec Large</title></bibref></p>
</separatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Biographical Information, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1991, 1997, 2013.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:1 </container>
</did>
</c01>
    
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Audiocassette of a lecture given by Harkness at Virginia Tech on October 29, 1986, about sustainable design,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1986.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Booklet documenting the presentations given at the awards dinner when Harkness was presented with the Boston Society of Architects 1991 Award of Honor, November 21, 1991. Includes photographs of many of Harkness's designs and biographical information about her,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1991.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:3
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Photographs of the Shaw House in Essex, Massachusetts,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1997.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:4
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Architectural drawings of the Shaw House in Essex, Massachusetts (23 drawings),
<unitdate type="inclusive">1996-1997.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
