<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00285">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00285:: Virginia Republican Party Flyer, 1921)//EN" "viblbv00285.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Republican Party Flyer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Virginia Republican Party Flyer
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-058
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Emily Cook, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">08/13/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Republican Party Flyer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-058
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:  Emily Cook, 
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia Republican Party Flyer,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-058
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.  
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The Virginia Republican Party Flyer lists the African American Republican candidates for Virginia elected offices in 1921 and includes Maggie L. Walker, the first American female bank president, as the candidate for Superintendent of Public Instruction and John Mitchell, Jr., the editor of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Planet</title>, as the candidate for Governor.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Virginia Republican Party Flyer must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Virginia Republican Party Flyer, Ms2008-058 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Virginia Republican Party Flyer was purchased by Special Collections. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing and description of the Virginia Republican Party Flyer occurred in August, 2008.  
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>The <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Lily Black</title> Republican ticket of 1921 was in response to the all white (<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Lily White</title>) ticket put forward by the Republican party of Virginia.  Neither Republican ticket won in 1921, as the Democratic party swept the elections.  Although several names appear on the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Lily Black</title> Republican ticket, biographical information exists only for Maggie L. Walker, John Mitchell, Jr., and Joseph Thomas ( J.T. ) Newsome. 
</p>
      <p>Maggie Lena Mitchell was born on July 15, 1864 in Richmond, Virginia, and married Armstead Walker, Jr. in 1886.  At age fourteen Maggie joined the local chapter of the Independent Order of St. Luke, a fraternal and cooperative insurance society.  Eventually, Maggie achieved the title of Right Worthy Grand Secretary in 1899, created <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href=""> The St. Luke Herald</title> in 1902, and founded the St. Luke Penny Savings Bank in 1903&#8212;thus making her the first woman to charter a bank in the United States.  Maggie also devoted time to promoting African American women's rights.  This civic concern eventually expressed itself in an unsuccessful bid for the office of Superintendent of Public Instruction in 1921.  Maggie Lena Walker died on December 15, 1934.  
</p>
      <p>John Mitchell, Jr. was born July 11, 1863.  Mitchell was the editor of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Planet,</title> a paper that exposed racial injustice, and the President of the National Afro-American Press Association.  Elected to Richmond's Board of Alderman from Jackson Ward in 1892, Mitchell eventually made an unsuccessful bid for the governor's office in 1921.  Mitchell also founded, and was president of, the Mechanics Savings Bank which fell into legal trouble and was eventually rechartered by the state in July, 1924.  Due to the bank's failure, Mitchell lost his assets and eventually died on December 3, 1929.
</p>
      <p>Joseph Thomas ( J.T. ) Newsome was born on June 2, 1869 in Sussex County, Virginia, to Joseph and Anne Newsome.  After attending Virginia Normal and Collegiate Institute in Petersburg, Newsome received his law degree from Howard University in 1898.  Newsome married Mary Beatrice Winfield and moved to Newport News where he became a successful lawyer, the editor of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Newport News Star</title>, a public speaker, and a politician.  In 1921 Newsome unsuccessfully ran for state attorney general and the first congressional district seat.  Joseph Thomas Newsom died on March 9, 1942.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Virginia Republican Party Flyer is a list, titled <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">The Republican Ticket</title> and printed on newsprint, of the so-called <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href=""> Lily Black</title> Republican ticket of 1921 (an African American offshoot of the Republican party).  Sought-after offices include:  Governor, Lieutenant-Governor, Attorney-General, Treasurer, Secretary of Commonwealth, Superintendent of Public Instruction, Corporation Commissioner, and Commissioner of Agriculture.  Maggie L. Walker of Richmond, Virginia, an African-American philanthropist and the first American female bank president, is listed as the Republican candidate for the Superintendent of Public Instruction.  John Mitchell, Jr. of Richmond Virginia, the editor of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Planet,</title> is listed as the Republican candidate for Governor.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Flyer,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
