<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00715">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00715::Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, 1848-1939)//EN"
            "viblbv00715.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1939</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-067</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010-10-15T11:49-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1939</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-067</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
          <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection,
                    <unitdate normal="1848/1939" type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1939</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-067</unitid>
      <physdesc id="ref5" label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.3 cu. ft.
                1 box; 1 oversize folder</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language" encodinganalog="546">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract id="ref93" label="Abstract">Family papers of President John Tyler, his second
                wife, Julia Gardiner Tyler, and descendants, mostly through the couple's daughter,
                Pearl Tyler Ellis. Letters written to the Tylers from family and friends; a letter
                written by the Tyler's son, David G. Tyler; an autograph book used at the 1868
                Democratic National Convention; a published memorial to Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner
                Horsford; photographs of Pearl Tyler Ellis; Ellis and Marye family-related newspaper
                clippings; photographs and Civil War prisoner parole of Confederate Major William
                Gordon Anderson.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="dacs" source="local">Marye, Madison</persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref9" encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref11" encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection must be
                    obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref94" encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, Ms2010-067, Special
                    Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg,
                    Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref95" encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection was donated to Special Collections in
                    2007.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo id="ref96" encodinganalog="583$a">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family
                    Collection commenced and was completed in October 2010.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="ref92" encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>John Tyler, tenth president of the United States, was born in Charles City County,
                Virginia in 1790, the son of John and Mary Armistead Tyler. Admitted to the Virginia
                bar in 1809, Tyler established a practice in his native county. He was elected the
                the Virginia House of Delegates in 1811. In 1813 he married Letitia Christian (also
                born in 1790), and the couple would have eight children. Elected to Congress in
                1816, Tyler served until 1821, then returned to the Virginia House of Delegates,
                then was elected Virginia governor in 1824, then served in the U. S. Senate from
                1827 until 1836, when he resigned. Elected vice-president as William Henry
                Harrison's running mate in 1840, Tyler became president soon after taking office,
                following Harrison's death on April 4, 1841. Letitia Christian Tyler died the
                following year, and in 1844, Tyler married Julia Gardiner, making her First Lady of
                the United States. John Tyler died in 1862.</p>
      <p>Born on Gardiner's Island, New York in 1820, Julia was the daughter of David and
                Juliana McLachlan-Gardiner. Together, the John and Julia Gardiner Tyler had seven
                children: David, John, Julia, Lachlan, Lyon, Robert and Pearl. After Tyler's
                presidency, the couple moved to Sherwood Forest, their Charles City County estate.
                Following President Tyler's death, Julia Tyler moved to Staten Island, New York,
                though her sympathies lay with the Confederacy. In the 1870s, she returned to
                Virginia, her finances largely depleted, and lived with the aid of her children. She
                died in Richmond in 1872.</p>
      <p>Pearl Tyler, the youngest child of John and Julia Gardiner Tyler, was born on June
                20, 1860. She married William Munford Ellis, a member of the Virginia House of
                Delegates, in 1884. Born in Richmond in 1846, Ellis was the son of Powhatan Lewis
                Ellis and Elvira Henry Munford. His father died while Ellis was still a boy, and he
                moved with his mother and stepfather, Howard Peyton, to Montgomery County, Virginia
                in 1853. In 1864, William Ellis enlisted in the 4th Regiment, Virginia Reserves at
                Christiansburg, Virginia. He was elected second lieutenant in Company A in early
                1864 and later appointed adjutant. Ellis first married, in 1870, Margaret Kent
                Langhorne, with whom he had four children before she died in 1882. Married in 1884,
                William and Pearl Tyler Ellis lived for many years in the Shawsville, Virginia area
                and had eight children: Pearl, John, Leila, Cornelia, Gardiner, William, Julia, and
                Lyon. Pearl Tyler Ellis served in the U. S. Army Nurse Corps during World War I and
                World War II, eventually attaning the rank of lieutenant colonel. Pearl Tyler Ellis
                died in Richmond in 1947; William Mumford Ellis had died in 1921.</p>
      <p>Among the children of William and Pearl Tyler Ellis was Leila MacLachlan Ellis
                (1888-1968). She married Ambrose Madison Marye (1887-1972). The couple lived in the
                Shawsville, Virginia area. Ambrose Marye was the son of Alfred J. Marye and Nancy A.
                Anderson, whose brother, William G. Anderson, had served as a major in the 54th
                Virginia Infantry.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="ref7" encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains papers of Julia Gardiner Tyler, wife of President John
                Tyler, and some of her descendants, mostly through daughter Pearl Tyler Ellis.
                Though small, the collection is comprised of a wide array of items, including
                correspondence, printed material, photographs and ephemera. Among the papers
                relating directly to the John and Julia Tyler family is an 1844 letter to President
                Tyler from an anonymous woman, offering congratulations on his recent marriage. Also
                included are several letters addressed to Julia Tyler, among which is a war-time
                letter from a soldier named Douthat, a Confederate prisoner-of-war at Point Lookout,
                Maryland. Also included are a letter from nephew John C. Tyler regarding timber
                interests; a letter from son John Alexander Tyler, written from Baden, Germany; a
                letter from William A. Galbraith, enclosing tickets to the 1868 National Democratic
                Convention; two letters from Pearl Tyler Ellis (including an 1885 letter written
                from Shawsville, Virginia); and an undated letter from F. W. Thomas, addressed to
                "Lady Presidentiss" and regarding invitations to be issued to the Beeckmans and
                Colegates for an unidentified event. Also among the Tyler correspondence is a letter
                from David G. Tyler (oldest child of John and Julia Gardiner Tyler) to Harry
                Beeckman and accompanied by an envelope addressed to Mrs. David Gardiner and
                free-franked by John Tyler. Included also is an autograph book used by Julia Tyler
                at the 1868 Democratic National Convention (containing the autographs of delegates
                from Virginia, North Carolina, and Arkansas, and accompanied by a delegate ribbon);
                an invitation to the 1848 National [Washington's] Birth-night Ball; and a published
                memorial to Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford (including studio portrait). The
                Tyler-related papers also contain several empty envelopes, among which are three
                envelopes free-franked by Tyler and two black-edged mourning envelopes addressed to
                Tyler as president.</p>
      <p>Among the items in the collection related to the Ellis family are photographs of
                Pearl Tyler Ellis (including one with husband William Munford Ellis), several
                family-related newspaper clippings, and a lock of hair from Carlton Munford (brother
                of Elvira Munford Ellis Peyton, William Munford Ellis's mother). A property map of
                the Shawsville, Virginia area is included in an oversize folder.</p>
      <p>From the Marye family, the collection contains several family-related newspapers
                clippings, a letter from W. Carter Wormeley to Bob Marye, a report on the Works
                Progress Administration's Engineering and Construction Division by Ambrose M. Marye,
                two photographs of scenes on the Virginia Tech campus, and a copy of an 1862 letter
                from Nannie E. Kent to Mrs. James McGavock Kent. Also included here are two
                20th-century studio portraits of Major William Gordon Anderson, who served with the
                54th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War and was the brother of Nancy Anderson
                Marye. Accompanying the portraits is Anderson's 1865 military parole.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="ref97" encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged according to family unit, then by document type.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
      <separatedmaterial id="ref12" encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Separated Materials</head>
        <p>The following books were removed from the Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection and
                    cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:</p>
        <p>Adams, Daniel, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Arithmetic: in which the principles of
                        operating by numbers are analytically explained, and synthetically
                        applied...</title> (Keene, NH: J. and J. W. Prentiss, 1833). QA101 A24 1833
                    Small Spec</p>
        <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Affection's gift: a Christmas and New Year's present for
                        youth</title> (Philadelphia: Thomas T. Ash, 1835). AY11 P4 1835 Small
                    Spec</p>
        <p>Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Songs and scenes from
                        Goethe's Faust</title> (Boston: Estes and Lauriat, 1884). PT2026 F2 M47 1884
                    Large Spec</p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Local Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="local">Local/Regional History</subject>
        <subject source="local">Montgomery County (Va.)</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="ref14" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter to [John Tyler] from anonymous (Norfolk, Virginia), <unitdate normal="1844/1844" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid300001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref15" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Julia Gardiner Tyler, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864-1885,
                        n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid300002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref16" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>From Douthat (Point Lookout, [Maryland]), <unitdate normal="1864/1864" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref17" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from Jn [John] C. Tyler (Sherwood Forest), <unitdate normal="1866/1866" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from A. Winant (Rossville, New York), <unitdate normal="1864/1864" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref99" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from William Watson (New York, New York) to Gurdon Bradley,
                                <unitdate normal="1867/1867" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref20" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from J. Alex Tyler (Baden, Germany), <unitdate normal="1867/1867" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref21" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from [William] A. Galbraith (New York, New York), <unitdate normal="1868/1868" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref23" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from Pearl Tyler (Richmond, Virginia), <unitdate normal="1884/1884" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1884.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from Pearl T. Ellis ("Madison," [Shawsville, Virginia p.m.]),
                                <unitdate normal="1885/1885" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref25" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>from F. W. Thomas, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref26" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter from David G. Tyler (Sherwood Forest) to Harry Beeckman,
                            <unitdate normal="1859/1859" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid309003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref28" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Julia Tyler autograph book, <unitdate normal="1868/1868" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid309001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref78" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Envelopes.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid309008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-5</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref86" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To Mrs. Juliana Gardiner, Staten Island, New York (postmarked
                            Richmond, Virginia), <unitdate normal="1859/1859" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref87">[free-franked by John
                            Tyler]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref80" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To John Tyler, president (postmarked New York, Nov. 2),
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref81">[on mourning
                            stationery]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref82" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To "His Excellency, the President of the United States"
                            (postmarked New York, Aug. 3), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref83">[on mourning
                            stationery]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref79" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To Ex-president Tyler (postmarked May 7, New York),
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref84" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To Margaret G. Beeckman, Staten Island, New York (postmarked
                            Norfolk, Virginia, June 13),</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <physdesc id="ref85">[free-franked by John
                            Tyler]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref88" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>To Mrs. Juliana Gardiner, Saratoga Springs, New York (postmarked
                            Norfolk, Virginia, Jul 5), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref91">[free-franked by John
                            Tyler]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref32" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed material.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid309004" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-6</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref33" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Invitation to National Birth-night Ball, <unitdate normal="1848/1848" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref29" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford memorial, <unitdate normal="1872/1872" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1872.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="cid309002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref34" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ellis family papers, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1922, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid309005" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-7</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref35" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Munford Ellis and Pearl Tyler Ellis studio portrait,
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref36" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Pearl Ellis snapshot, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref38" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Pearl Tyler Ellis] studio portraits
                            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref40">[2 items]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref59" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lock of hair from Carlton Munford, brother of Elvira H. Peyton,
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref100" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper clippings.</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 id="ref57" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>death of Lt. Carlton R. Munford (unidentified newspapers),
                                    <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1847?].</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref58">[photocopies][2
                                items]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref48" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Death announcement and obituary for Benjamin Howard Peyton
                                (unidentified newspapers), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1868].</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref50">[photocopies] [2
                                items]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref43" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"'Victory Girl,' Carnival Prize Win[ner]" ( <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Evening Star</title>), <unitdate normal="1919/1919" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref55">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref47" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Major William Munford Ellis (a Tribute)" (unidentified
                                newspaper), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1921?].</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref51">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref46" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Major W. M. Ellis is buried at Shawsville" (unidentified
                                newspaper), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1921?].</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref52">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref42" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photograph of William M. Ellis and children Munford, John,
                                Gardiner and Pearl in military uniforms ( <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">American Legion
                                    Weekly</title>, <unitdate normal="1922/1922" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922.</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref41" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Mrs. Pearl Ellis is Critically Ill" (unidentified
                                newspaper), <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref56">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref44" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Senatorial Nomination" (unidentified newspaper),
                                    <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref54">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref45" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Veterans to Play: Champoin 'Fiddler' and Banjo Player to
                                Entertain press Club" (unidentified newspaper),
                                    <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref53">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref60" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Marye family papers, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865-1939, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid309006" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-8</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref70" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to Bob [Marye] from [W. Carter Wormeley], <unitdate normal="1930/1930" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref101" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper clippings.</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 id="ref64" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"First at Gettysburg and Last at Appomattox" (unidentified
                                newspaper) <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref67">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref65" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Alfred James Marye" (unidentified newspaper) <unitdate normal="1920/1920" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref66">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="ref68" level="item">
            <did>
              <unittitle>"Poetic Veteran's Check Was Sent" (unidentified newspaper)
                                    <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <physdesc id="ref69">[photocopy]</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref74" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Engineering and Construction Division, the Work Projects
                            Administration: Its Handicaps, Mistakes, and Accomplishments" by A. M.
                            Marye, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref71" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Virginia Tech airport and agricultural building,
                                <unitdate normal="1939/1939" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref72">[2 items]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref63" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William G. Anderson Civil War prisoner parole, <unitdate normal="1865/1865" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref61" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William G. Anderson studio portraits,
                            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc id="ref62">[2 items]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref73" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcription of 1862 letter from Nannie E. Kent to Mrs. James
                            McGavock Kent, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref75" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid309007" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref76" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Shawsville, Virginia area map,
                            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
