<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00425">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00425:: William Roane Aylett Letters, 1852-1887, n.d.)//EN" "viblbv00425.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the William Roane Aylett Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1887, n.d.</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Aylett, William Roane, Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms1992-033
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Kira A. Dietz, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/15/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the William Roane Aylett Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1887, n.d.</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms1992-033
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William Roane Aylett Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1887, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms1992-033
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 folder; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains seven letters written to Aylett between 1852 and 1887, as well as five undated letters and four envelopes. The collection includes letters from family and friends, as well as business correspondence.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the William Roane Aylett Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: William Roane Aylett Letters, Ms1992-033 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The William Roane Aylett Letters were purchased by Special Collections in 1992. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the William Roane Aylett Letters commenced and was completed in 1992. Additional description was completed in May 2009. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information</head>
      <p>William Roane Aylett was born in May 1833 to Colonel Philip and Judith Page (Waller) Aylett on the family plantation, Montville, in King William County, Virginia.  His paternal great-grandfathers were influential Revolutionary War figures Patrick Henry and William Aylett. Aylett was the second of three sons and one of seven children. His early education consisted of private tutors and attending the Rumford Academy. He went to college at the University of Virginia, from which he graduated with degrees in French language and literature and in moral philosophy in 1854. He was admitted to the bar in 1854 and began practicing law privately. His reputation had spread throughout a number of Virginia counties by 1860.</p>
      <p>In 1860, Aylett married Alice R. Brockenborough (1838-1985). Between 1861 and 1880, they had twelve children, seven of whom lived past infancy: Sarah (Sallie) (b. 1861), Martha (Pattie) Waller (b. 1862), twins, names unknown (1866?-1869?), Philip (b. 1867), Alice Page (b. 1868), Patrick Henry (1870?-1871?), William Roane (b. 1871), Elizabeth (Bessie) (1873-1948), Patrick Henry (1876-1943), Eugenia (1878?-1879?), and Moore Brockenborough (1880?-1881?).</p>
      <p>In December of 1861, he helped organize the Confederate 53<emph render="super">rd</emph> Regiment, Virginia Infantry, and was elected as captain. He was quickly promoted through the ranks, eventually becoming a colonel in 1863. He continued service with the regiment after being wounded at Gettysburg. He attempted to resign in 1864, disappointed at not being promoted to General, despite shining recommendations, but was denied. At Sayler's Creek, he was captured on April 6, 1865 and was later paroled from Johnson's Island, Ohio, on July 15, 1865. He returned to his home and to the practice of law, rebuilding his business and the ruined family plantation. From 1870-1886, he was a Commonwealth's Attorney. Aylett died in at Montville, King William County, Virginia, in August 1900.</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <head>For additional information, see:</head>
        <item>Kneebone, John T., and Sara B. Bearss. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title> Richmond: Library of Virginia, 1998.</item>
        <item>Tyler, Lyon Gardiner. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Encyclopedia of Virginia Biography, Under the Editorial Supervision of Lyon Gardiner Tyler.</title> New York: Lewis Historical Pub. Co, 1915.</item>
      </list>
      <list type="simple">
        <head>For other Virignia institutions with Aylett Family Collections, see:</head>
        <item><extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/">Library of Virginia</extref>, Richmond</item>
        <item><extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/small/">Small Special Collections Library</extref>, Alderman Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville</item>
        <item><extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vahistorical.org/research/main.htm">Virginia Historical Society</extref>, Richmond</item>
      </list>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection contains seven letters written to Aylett between 1852-1887, as well as five undated letters and four envelopes. The collection includes letters from family and friends, as well as business correspondence. Although the letters span the Civil War-era, there is no war-time correspondence in this collection. Most of the letters are from the 1850s. </p>
      <p>Family correspondents include Aylett's mother, his brother, Patrick, his sister, Rosalie, and his cousin, Margaret, mostly containing news about other family members. There are two letters from his friend, James (Jack) Alexander, mostly explaining why he has not written to Aylett lately, and one from R. Hawy(?), explaining his inability to attend an upcoming party. Business correspondence includes a request for Aylett's counsel by George Taylor; a request for a copy of arguments Aylett made relating to the Thomas Cluverius murder case (1885) by Dr. John Finchcomb(?); and an anonymous note (that apparently accompanied a picture) by someone unhappy with Aylett's law practice. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters and envelopes,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1887, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
