<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00303">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00303:: Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters, 1849)//EN" "viblbv00303.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters, <date>1849</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-077
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Emily Cook, <date>9/17/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters, <date>1849</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-077
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:  Emily Cook,
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1849
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-077
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.  
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Letters to William S. Archer discussing his election as delegate to the July, 1849, convention of the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company.  Correspondence also discusses the plan to connect the Atlantic and Pacific oceans via railroads. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters, Ms2008-077 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters were purchased by Special Collections. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters occurred in September, 2008.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>After years of proposals from Lynchburg citizens, the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad was chartered in 1849.  Built in the 1850s, the V&amp;T connected Southwestern Virginia, from Lynchburg to Bristol.  With V&amp;T rail lines came expanded economic markets and new industry.  During the Civil War, the V&amp;T served as a Confederate lifeline by moving supplies, weapons, and troops.  The Confederate reliance on the V&amp;T resulted in the partial destruction of lines by Union forces.  In 1870, the V&amp;T joined the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad and the City Point Railroad to create the Atlantic, Mississippi, and Ohio Railroad.  The AM&amp;O later became the Norfolk and Western.
</p>
<p>William S. Archer was born in 1841 at "The Lodge" in Amelia County, Virginia.  Archer studied law, passed the bar in 1810, and practiced law in Powhatan and Amelia counties.  From 1812 to 1819, Archer served four terms in Virginia's House of Delegates.  Archer represented the Whig Party in the U.S. House of Representatives from 1819 to 1834 and in the Senate from 1841-1846.  After his political career, Archer resumed his law practice.  William Segar Archer died on March 28, 1855.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Letters are two manuscript missives informing former Senator William S. Archer of his election as delegate to the July, 1849, convention of the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company held in Memphis, Tennessee.  Other elected delegates included:  William C. Riley, John Mason, and Lieutenant M. F. Maury.   The letters predate the railroad's construction and thus discuss only the proposed improvement.  Also mentioned is the plan to connect the Atlantic and Pacific oceans via railroads.  The letter of May 4, 1849, was written by the chairman of the electoral meeting, Rich J. Morris, while the letter of May 17, 1849, was written by the committee of correspondence.  Signatures of committee members also appear. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
