<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00241">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00241:: Charles O. Poland Diary, 1864)//EN" "viblbv00241.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Charles O. Poland Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Poland, Charles O. Diary
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-013
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>4/3/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Charles O. Poland Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-013
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Charles O. Poland Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-013
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Diary of Charles O. Poland, a private in Company B, 142nd Ohio Infantry (National Guard), written while serving for six weeks near the front during the early siege of Petersburg.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Charles O. Poland Diary must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Charles O. Poland Diary, Ms2008-013 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Charles O. Poland Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the Charles O. Poland Diary commenced and was completed in April 2008. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Charles O. Poland, a private in Company B, 142nd Ohio Infantry (National Guard) during the Civil War, was a resident of Knox County, Ohio. Born around 1836, he was the husband of Angeline Disney (daughter of William A. and Mary Jane Lampson Disney) and the father of several children. Census records indicate that Poland was a farmer; documents within this collection indicate that Poland was also certified to teach in Morrow and Knox counties prior to the war. 
</p>
<p>The 142nd Ohio National Guard was organized at Camp Chase, Ohio and mustered into service for 100 days on May 12, 1864. On May 14, the regiment proceeded to Martinsburg, West Virginia, where it drilled until May 19, when ordered to Fort Lyon, Virginia, from which it served guard duty in the Washington D. C. area. On June 5, the regiment was ordered to the front and arrived on June 9 at White House Landing, Virginia, where it was dispatched to guard a supply train through the Wilderness to Cold Harbor. From there, the 142nd proceeded to Point of Rocks, about five miles from Petersburg, Virginia. The regiment participated in the early siege of Petersburg through August 19, when it was ordered back to Washington, D.C., thence to Camp Chase, where it was mustered out on September 2, 1864. </p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains the diary of Charles O. Poland, a private in Company B, 142nd Ohio Infantry (National Guard) during the Civil War. The diary's entries commence on June 15, 1864, with Knox already in the rifle pits before Petersburg. He writes of being detailed to destroy Confederate breastworks, erect fortifications, and fell trees as battles raged nearby. Elsewhere he mentions having seen generals Grant and Burnside, the gunboats on the James River, the discovery of a cache of buried silver and gold by a New York regiment while hunting for fishing worms, and the trading of hardtack for tobacco between the lines. Throughout the diary, Poland notes many days on picket, and the state of the fighting around Petersburg. On July 20, Poland developed a fever, and the final four entries, concluding with July 31, are devoted to the condition of his health. 
</p>
<p>Also within the diary are a few entries regarding pre- and post-war personal financial transactions; the diary is accompanied by two 1855 documents certifying Poland as qualified to teach in Knox and Morrow counties. </p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive">1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
