<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv00240">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00240::Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook, 1881-1882)//EN" "viblbv00240.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1881-1882</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Wickham, Williams Carter Letterbook <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-011</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 CC0.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace <date era="ce"
        calendar="gregorian">2018-09-25 14:23:10-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881-1882</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
        Ms2008-011</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook</unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="dacs" source="local">Wickham, Williams Carter, 1820-1888</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2008-011</unitid>
      <physdesc altrender="whole" label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.2 Cubic Feet</extent>
        <extent altrender="carrier">1 box</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1881/1882" type="inclusive">1881-1882</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_f25627149ee78fa02b4f54ce84336dd1">Letterbook of Williams Carter Wickham,
        attorney, farmer, Virginia state senator, Hanover County supervisor, Chesapeake and Ohio
        Railway Company official, and Confederate brigadier general, containing copies of letters
        regarding farm, business, political and personal matters.</abstract>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_a4038f4ecbadd91954f11bfe48a3dfcb">
      <head>Access Restrictions</head>
      <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_2e3f3e688167a34d4ea62f32297ec0b1">
      <head>Use Restrictions</head>
      <p>Permission to publish material from the Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook must be obtained
        from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_ce3ed3c90b80ce6c2ce038bb7947b508">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information:
        Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook, Ms2008-011 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic
        Institute and State University.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_d47707a3a05d963e60af913258e3a1bb">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>The Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook was purchased by Special Collections in 2008.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="aspace_09b5406fa2d1c092823c3783fb1fcb63">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Williams Carter Wickham Letterbook
        commenced and was completed in March 2008.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <bioghist id="aspace_254c01fa287f46a488dd74ecdbf15165">
      <head>Biographical Information</head>
      <p>Williams Carter Wickham, attorney, farmer, politician, Confederate brigadier general and
        president of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company (the C&amp;O), was born September 21,
        1820. The son of William Fanning and Anne Butler Carter Wickham, Williams Wickham was born
        in Richmond, Virginia but reared on his father's plantation, Hickory Hill, in Hanover
        County. He graduated from the University of Virginia and was admitted to the Virginia bar in
        1842 but seems to have devoted much of his time to managing Hickory Hill. He married Lucy
        Penn Taylor, and the couple had four children. Wickham was elected to the Virginia House of
        Delegates in 1849 and also served as the presiding justice on the Hanover County court. In
        1858, he became captain of a unit of Virginia militia cavalry, and in 1859 was elected as a
        Whig to the state senate. </p>
      <p>Wickham voted against the ordinance of secession in the 1861 Virginia convention, but once
        secession had been effected, he and his company, the Hanover Dragoons, joined the
        Confederate Army. After First Manassas, Wickham was commissioned colonel of the Fourth
        Virginia Cavalry. At the Battle of Williamsburg, Wickham was wounded and captured but soon
        paroled and healed. Wounded again after the Battle of Antietam, Wickham had rejoined his
        regiment by late 1862 and participated in the battles of Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville
        and Gettysburg. He was promoted to brigadier general on September 9, 1863. Wickham resigned
        his commission on October 4, 1864, and assumed the Confederate Congress seat to which he had
        been elected in the spring of 1863.</p>
      <p>Just weeks after the cessation of hostilities, Wickham joined the Republican Party,
        providing his reasons in an open letter which estranged many of his colleagues. The former
        general was elected president of the Virginia Central Railroad Company in November 1865, and
        when that line merged with the Covington &amp; Ohio Railroad in 1868 to become the C&amp;O,
        Wickham was retained as the new company's president. He served as vice-president of the
        company from 1869 to 1878, when the company went into foreclosure, with Wickham as receiver.
        Under reorganization of the company, Wickham served as second vice-president. During this
        time, he maintained an active political life, being elected chairman of the Hanover County
        board of supervisors in 1871 and a state senator in 1883. He held all of these positions at
        the time of his death on July 23, 1888. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_dbd269055251a40ad5ab748d32149cfc">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains a letterbook maintained by Williams Carter Wickham, attorney,
        farmer, Virginia state senator, Hanover County supervisor, president of the Chesapeake and
        Ohio Railway Company, and Confederate brigadier general. The book contains copies of letters
        written by Wickham from November 25, 1881 to December 29, 1882, while serving as second
        vice-president of the C&amp;O. Comprising 472 pages, the letters relate to matters both
        personal and professional. Though copied on C&amp;O letterhead, the vast majority of the
        letters do not seem to relate directly to the railroad's business. (Many of the letters
        regard payments on accounts which could be for the railway but appear more likely to be
        personal.) Much of the correspondence relates to farming matters, especially cattle, sheep,
        tobacco and wheat. Letters within the book seem to indicate that in addition to managing the
        family's Hickory Hill plantation, Wickham rented property on the North Wales plantation from
        his friend Charles Carter in Caroline County, Virginia. Other letters relate to the Virginia
        Agricultural Society, of which Wickham served as president during this time period. </p>
      <p>Other letters relate to Wickham's service on the Hanover County board of supervisors. A
        number of these letters relate to smallpox vaccinations within the county; others concern
        road precincts and the commitment of a local African American woman to a state hospital.
        Wickham's political interests are documented in a number of letters mentioning Virginia
        issues, especially the settlement of the state debt. Other letters touch on the temperance
        question, the condition of Virginia's state Republican Party, and attempts to assist friends
        and acquaintances in obtaining government and other positions.</p>
      <p>Very few of the letters within the book are of a purely personal nature. Two exceptions are
        letters of August 21 and September 1, 1882, in which Wickham provides lengthy details
        regarding his family and his military service. </p>
      <p>The letterbook is accompanied by an index, arranged by name of recipient, and several
        pieces of miscellanea, including three (1882) Virginia, Kentucky &amp; Ohio Railroad
        construction account summaries; a photograph of an unidentified train wreck; and a letter
        from [H.?] Kinsey of Richmond to Wm. C. Sampon of Ivy Depot, Virginia.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_a09ced999af11d1375d82e3e7bd50650">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by type, then chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_2ea8dbf2611a0eaccd9a4e89fa7f4cd4">
      <head>Related Materials</head>
      <p>William C. Wickham Order, Ms2018-020. <extref xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv01925.xml">Finding aid
          available online</extref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
      <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
      <subject source="local">Railroad</subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref11_9wl" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letterbook,
          <unitdate>1881-1882</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_2b38a9d40dfe97a67725f3db6e907ff7" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_3f0c2aa9cb5f3cc469919a78cb40eae6"
            parent="aspace_2b38a9d40dfe97a67725f3db6e907ff7" type="folder">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref12_y99" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Index,
          <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_c556b82dbffe8ee9eacb6be6d7b1537a" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_21ecf94001d1fea890c8efcf4497834f"
            parent="aspace_c556b82dbffe8ee9eacb6be6d7b1537a" type="folder">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref13_jol" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellanea,
          <unitdate>1881-1896, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_9e3084600adadf1d1901419c790b42ef" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_a26f7aa3e49d14c5c9e05c5d1421d34b"
            parent="aspace_9e3084600adadf1d1901419c790b42ef" type="folder">3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
