<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00242">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00242:: Daniel A.
Lowber Diary, 1864)//EN" "viblbv00242.xml" </eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Daniel A. Lowber Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Lowber, Daniel A. Diary <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-015 </num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
University. All rights reserved. </date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>April
7, 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Daniel A. Lowber Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-015 </num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
<date type="publication">2008 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: </label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff </item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary </head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic
Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Daniel A. Lowber Diary <unitdate type="inclusive"
label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1864 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-015 </unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft. </physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English </language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War diary of Captain Daniel A. Lowber, Company A, 37th Wisconsin
Infantry, which served in the siege of Petersburg, Virginia. </abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information </head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions </head>
<p>Collection is open to research. </p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions </head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Daniel A. Lowber Diary must be obtained from Special
Collections, Virginia Tech. </p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation </head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Daniel A.
Lowber Diary, Ms2008-015 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information </head>
<p>The Daniel A. Lowber Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. </p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information </head>
<p>The processing and description of the Daniel A. Lowber Diary commenced and was completed in April
2008. </p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information </head>
<p>Daniel A. Lowber, captain of Company A, 37th Wisconsin Infantry during the Civil War, was born in
New York in February 1844. By 1864, he was living in Columbus, Wisconsin, where he enlisted as a
private in the 13th Independent Battery of Wisconsin Light Artillery. Lowber transferred to the 37th
Wisconsin Infantry on March 7, 1864. Serving as a lieutenant in Company A, he was wounded on June 18
at Petersburg. He received a promotion to first lieutenant on July 28, then to captain on September
27, 1864. He was wounded again at Petersburg on April 2, 1865, and mustered out with his regiment on
July 27. </p>
<p>Post-war records show Lowber living in Waupun, Wisconsin from 1868 through 1880, his occupation
listed variously as operator of a variety store and restaurant (1868), a news dealer and
confectionary (1870, 1872) and a miner (1880). He had married before 1870, his wife Susan [Morse?]
having been born in Wisconsin in 1850. By 1900 Lowber had returned with his wife to New York; they
lived in a boardinghouse in Brooklyn, where Lowber was occupied as a railroad supplier. Daniel A.
Lowber died on November 3, 1902.</p>
<p>The 37th Wisconsin Infantry was organized at Camp Randall in Madison and mustered into service on
April 9, 1864. The regiment departed for Washington at the end of April. A month later, the 37th was
ordered to the front. The regiment was assigned to the Ninth Army Corps and participated in the
assault against the Confederate lines before Petersburg on June 17 and 18, experiencing heavy fire.
The regiment generally remained at Petersburg until the Confederate surrender the following spring,
participating in numerous battles (including the Battle of the Crater) around Petersburg and
Richmond. The 37th participated in the Grand Review in Washington D. C., where it remained until
July 27, when it was mustered out of the service.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content </head>
<p>This collection contains the Civil War diary of Captain Daniel A. Lowber of Company A, 37th
Wisconsin Infantry. The diary entries commence with July 25, 1864, with Lowber apparently in transit
to his regiment after a temporary furlough. He joins the regiment the day after the Battle of the
Crater and takes command on August 1, noting that his new command has only 18 men fit for duty. In
daily entries spanning the next five months, Lowber mentions frequent picket and fatigue duty and
notes his routine administrative duties as well. He also mentions trading papers with a Confederate
soldier between the lines, his living quarters, church services, news of Sheridan's victories in the
Shenandoah Valley, the regiment's tally in the 1864 presidential election, and Thanksgiving. Lowber
also describes actions during several battles, including perhaps most significantly the Battle of
Peeble's Farm. The diary entries cease with December 31, 1864. </p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List </head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Diary <unitdate type="inclusive">1864 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1 </container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
