<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
    type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
    title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01790">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01790::Adin B. Underwood Papers, 1861-1926)//EN" "viblbv01790.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Adin B. Underwood Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1861-1926</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Underwood, Adin B., Papers <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2015-025</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2015 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2015-08-24T14:28-0400</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Adin B. Underwood Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1926</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2015-025</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Ryan Mair,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
                
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">Adin B. Underwood Papers, <unitdate normal="1861/1926" type="inclusive">1861-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2015-025</unitid>

            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 folder</extent>
            </physdesc>
           
            <abstract id="ref6" label="Abstract">This collection comprises the papers of Brigader General Adin. B Underwood. The papers contain photocopies of Civil War-era correspondence written to Underwood by his wife and sister-in-law and Underwood's written requests to his superiors for leave from duty. The collection also consists of Underwood's pension records, his pay and muster sheets from his time in the Union Army, and his wife's applications for a widow's pension after his death in 1888. This collection includes a short history of the Thirty-Third Massachusetts Infantry, Union Army, a unit with which Underwood served during the Civil War.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator">
                <persname source="naf">Underwood, Adin B., (Adin Ballou)</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref7">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref8">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from the Adin B. Underwood Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref11">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Adin B. Underwood Papers, Ms2015-025, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref9">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The Adin B. Underwood Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2004.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref12">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Adin B. Underwood Papers was completed in July 2015.</p>
        </processinfo>
            </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref13">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p>Adin B. Underwood (1828-1888) graduated from Brown University, studied Law at Harvard School of Law, and settled in Boston, Massachusetts, with his wife Jane. He joined the Union Army at the start of the Civil War and was made a Captain in the 2nd Massachusetts Infantry. Promoted to Major, he transferred to the 33rd Massachusetts Infantry and rose to the rank of Colonel. Underwood was wounded at the Battle of Wauhatchee in 1863 and appointed Brigader General of Volunteers. He later became a brevet Major General in 1865. Underwood officially mustered out in 1866 and returned to Boston. He was surveyor for the port of Boston for 20 years and wrote <emph render="doublequote">Three Years' Service of the Thirty-Third Massachusetts Infantry </emph> in 1881.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection contains photocopies of the papers of Brigader General Adin B. Underwood. The papers include personal correspondence with transcriptions, Underwood's Union Army pension records, and a detailed history of the 33rd Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, Union Army, in which Underwood served.</p>
            <p>Dating 1861 to 1865, the correspondence includes photocopies and transcriptions of letters written to General Underwood in Tennessee and Washington, D.C., by his wife Jane in Newtonville, Massachusetts, and his sister-in-law Maria, who resided in Brooklyn, New York. The letters written to Underwood pertain mostly to family matters and well wishes. Also in the correspondence are personal letters sent to Jane Underwood from her sister Maria, a Mrs. J. McQuesten, and an unknown sender regarding Adin's health and updates about friends and family. Lastly, the correspondence includes requests by General Underwood for leave of duty and the subsequent replies from his commanding officers, which are not transcribed.</p>
            <p>The pension records span from 1861 to 1926. The records include photocopies of muster sheets for the 2nd and 33rd Massachusetts Infantry Regiments, USA, casualty and wounded reports, and pension forms and affidavits regarding Underwood. Orders from Adjutant General E.D. Townsend of the Union Army Headquarters request removal of Underwood's name from the 33rd Massachusett's regimental muster roll after he accepted his appointment to Brigader General. The pension records also contain forms completed by Underwood establishing his retirement pension. Lastly, forms and affidavits completed by Jane Underwood request her widow's pension following the death of Adin Underwood in 1888.</p>
            <p>The Thirty-Third Massachusetts Infantry Regimental History details the recruitment and organization of the regiment in 1862. The document lists all forty-five battles and actions the regiment took part in for the duration of the war. The document also details the total wounded and killed as well as the mustering out and discharge of the surviving men of Thirty-Third after the end of the Civil War.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref14">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged by type of material.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Persons:</head>
            <persname source="naf">Underwood, Adin B., (Adin Ballou)</persname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
                </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref2" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1861/1865" type="inclusive">1861-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid2054001" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref4" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Pension Records, <unitdate normal="1861/1926" type="inclusive">1861-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid2054002" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref5" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>
                        <emph render="doublequote">Thirty-Third Massachusetts Infantry</emph> Regimental History, <unitdate>1887</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid2054003" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
