<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv00343">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00343::Montgomery Female College Collection, 1875-1892)//EN" "viblbv00343.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Montgomery Female College Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1875-1892</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Montgomery Female College Collection <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-013</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2014 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2014-10-28T15:17-0400</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Montgomery Female College Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1892</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2009-013</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">Montgomery Female College Collection, <unitdate normal="1875/1892" type="inclusive">1875-1892</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2009-013</unitid>

            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.1 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 folder</extent>
            </physdesc>
           
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">Ephemera relating to Montgomery Female College in Christiansburg, Virginia, including programs and certificates.</abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Infomration</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref3">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref4">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from the Montgomery Female College Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref5">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Montgomery Female College Collection, Ms2009-013, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref6">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The Montgomery Female College Collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. An additional item was donated in 2014.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Montgomery Female College Collection commenced and was completed in January 2009.</p>
        </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref8">
            <head>Historical Information</head>
            <p>Founded as a companion to the Montgomery Male Academy, the Montgomery Collegiate Institute opened in Christiansburg Virginia on November 1, 1852. Under the auspices of the Montgomery Presbytery, the school was first located in what had been the old Presbyterian Church on Franklin Street. In 1860, the college moved into a new building, but it was used as a hospital during the Civil War and the school endured harsh economic conditions. In 1870, Dr. Samuel K. Cox purchased the school (by then known as Montgomery Female Academy); though it retained its prestige, the school failed to regain its antebellum prosperity. The school was sold at public auction to Oceana S. Pollock, a teacher at the school, in 1876.</p>
            <p>With Pollock serving as principal, the school--by then known as Montgomery Female College--once again thrived. In 1887, Pollock deeded the college to Ebenezer T. and Anna Susan McDannold Baird but continued to serve as principal. The school closed for a year in 1890, then reopened under a series of principals. In 1903, Pollock's niece, Virginia Wardlaw was named principal of Montgomery Female College. She was soon joined on the staff by her older sisters, Mary Snead and Caroline Martin. Under the sisters' operation, the school declined and gained local notoriety as the scene of strange events. The Wardlaws became known as "the black sisters" for their practice of appearing always in black dresses and heavy veils. The sisters fell deeply into debt, local sentiment turned against them, and the school's reputation suffered. Montgomery Female College closed in 1908, and the Wardlaws left Christiansburg for New Jersey. (Within a year, the sisters would become implicated in events surrounding the mysterious death of Caroline Wardlaw Martin's daughter, Ocey.) The building formerly housing the Montgomery Female College operated under new owners as a boarding house and health resort for several years, then was sold to the Montgomery County School Board. In 1935, the building was demolished to make space for construction of a new Christiansburg High School.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref9">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection contains five pieces of ephemera relating to Montgomery Female College in Christiansburg, Virginia. The collection includes a program for exercises of the "Eureka Class," also listing the class' individual members. Also included is an 1892 program of entertainment including recitations, music and songs. Two undated certificates, awarded to Annie V. and Eugenia V. Sullivan for "purity and correctness in the use of the English language" are included as well (Eugenia V. Sullivan is listed elsewhere as a member of the class of 1886.). An additional item was donated in 2014: the 1875-1876 Annual Announcement.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref10">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
        <relatedmaterial id="ref11">
            <head>Related Material</head>
            <p>Zierold, Norman J., <title render="italic">Three sisters in black</title> (Boston: Little, Brown, 1968). HV6533 .N3 Z5 1968 Large Spec</p>
        </relatedmaterial>
        </descgrp>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
            <subject source="local">Montgomery County (Va.)</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref12" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Ephemera, <unitdate>1875-1892, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid58823" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>                   
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
