<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00629">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00629:: Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers, 1958-1997)//EN" "viblbv00629.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers, <date>1958-1997</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Choneva, Krasimira Architectural Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2007-003
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Dayne Mauney, <date>4/08/2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers, <date>1958-1997</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2007-003
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Dayne Mauney, 
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2007-003
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">3.1 cu. ft.; 1 map case; 1 box 
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers include conceptual and working drawings as well as supporting documents for six projects.  The projects range in date from 1958-1997 and were all designed and completed in Bulgaria by Krasimina Choneva.  The collection also includes one biographical sketch written by Choneva herself as well as an additional biography written by Milka Bliznakov in 2007.  
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Krasimira Choneva
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers, Ms 2007-003 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. , Ms2007-003, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2007. The collection was obtained in two accessions both in 2007.  
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers commenced in March, 2010 and was completed in April, 2010.  Some preliminary processing including a detailed inventory was completed in March 2007.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Krasimira Zheliazkova Choneva was born on September 23, 1935 in Varna, Bulgaria.  Her father, Zheliaazko Maldjiev (b.1901) was an insurance agent and her mother Elena Ivanova Maldjieva (b.1898) was a middle school teacher who moved with her family to Varna from Macedonia after the Llinden uprising in 1903.  
</p>
<p>
Choneva's family emphasized hard work and education, as a result Choneva's brothers attained university diplomas in electronics and technology and her cousins studied architecture.  At the encouragement of her family Choneva enrolled in a Construction and Technological High School where she began her study of architecture.  In addition to academia, Krasimira participated in sports, specifically swimming, eventually taking second place at a national competition in Bulgaria.  
</p>
<p>
"This sport helped me to aim at being the best, to follow the prescribed rules and to organize my time and activities.  I didn't continue my architectural education in the university for the following reasons," Krasmira states, "First, because I was in training to reach the international standards in swimming.  Second, university entrance in the architecture program required contacts within the ruling communist party." 
</p>
<p>
Choneva's professional architectural experience began in 1958 when she started working in the construction office of Varna's ship building industrial complex.  The experience cemented her "love and commitment for architecture." In 1959, Choneva's won a draftsman competition in the design organization for the town of Varna.  
</p>
<p>
Choneva worked for this state organization until her mandatory retirement in 1990, calling this period her "university training."  The work experience provided Choneva with the opportunity to work with several architects including, Marin Marinov; Simeon Dimitrov; Kosio Khristov; Julia Angelova; Daniel Ognianov; and Philio Ginev on multiple design projects.   
</p>
<p>
In 1961 Choneva married Marin Choveve (b.1932) a conductor of the leading Bulgarian choir "Morski Zvutzu" (The Sounds of the Sea).  The choir performed abroad giving her the opportunity to visit multiple countries and familiarize herself with their architecture.  "During the years of the 'Iron Curtain' such knowledge gave me considerable advantage," Choneva recalls.  
</p>
        
<p>
In 1971 Choneva became involved with construction of mass-housing utilizing prefabricated panels.  The system developed after WWII in Western Europe and was later imported by the Soviet Union.  "Regardless of the persistent endless criticism of prefabricated multi-family apartment housing," Krasmiria insists, "it was justified by the large migration of people from the agricultural sector (small towns and villages) to cities with large industrial developments.  The prefabricated system gave to almost all urban dwellers the option to reside in their own apartment with adequate space and sanitary facilities.  The modular panels (5.10 meters x 3.60 meters) allowed for functional arrangement of the required spaces.  Speedy construction, however, allowed for sloppy finishes and shoddy appearance of the apartment buildings.  I am glad to have responded to the societies demand for improved quality and to my personal desire to give the ugly panels a more attractive fa&#x00E7;ade appearance."
</p>
<p>
In the latter part of the 1980's the Union of Bulgarian Architects (SAB) invited Choneva to join their organization.  This was a distinct honor giving Choneva the right to open a private practice after the change in Bulgarian government between 1989 and 1990.  Choneva opened a private office where she designed residential houses and apartment buildings for twelve years from 1990-2002.  
</p>
<p>
Choneva had three children, two daughters and one son.  Her daughter, Liuliana Marinova Chonevea (b. Oct. 14, 1962) joined her at the practice when she graduated Sofia Polytechnic in 1990.  Upon her retirement Choneva transferred the practice to her daughter.  Her son Kalin Tchonev (b.1971), also a choral conductor and piano performer, resides in North Carolina.  
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Krasimira Choneva Architectural Papers span the year's 1958 to 1997 and cover projects Choneva completed in Bulgaria.  The collection includes conceptual drawings, working drawings and supporting documents for six projects including, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola; Apartment building for B. Mikhov on Llinden St. in Varna; Pavilion with changing rooms to the Euxinograd Palace near Varna; Vacation house for Burov in the subdivision of Briz, Varna; Vacation house for Manasiev in Euxinograd near Varna; and a Vacation house for Shulekov on the Monastikski Rd. area.  The collection also includes one biographical sketch written by Choneva herself, as well as an additional biography written by Milka Bliznakov in 2007.  
</p>
<p>
The majority of Choneva's work includes architectural drawings of residential apartment buildings and vacation homes.  Items of particular distinction in the collection include Choneva's early work on the Pavilion for Euxinograd Palace and her apartment designs utilizing prefabricated panels and accent colors.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged chronologically according to project.  
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>14 Photographs. Photos of unidentified apartment buildings with prefabricated panel housing and colorful elements.
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>7 Photographs; 1 black and white image, exterior elevations for multi-family housing; 2 photos, apartment building in Varna, Bulgaria; 1 photo, single family home near Varna; 3 photos, sports pavilion at Euxinograd Palace,1958.  
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>11 handwritten slides of biography written in Bulgarian by Krasimira Choneva. 
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 1-5; Conceptual Drawings, Pavilion with Changing Rooms, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1958
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 1
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 6-14; Working Drawings, Vacation House for Manasiev in Euxinograd near Varna, Bulgaria, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1991
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 1
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 15-23; Conceptual Drawings, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola near Varna, Bulgaria, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1991
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 2
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 24-35; Working Drawings, Hotel "Victor" in St. Nikola near Varna, Bulgaria,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1992
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 3
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 36-47; Conceptual Drawings, Apartment Building for B. Mikhov on "Ilinden" Street in Varna, Bulgaria, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1993
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 4
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 48-62; Working Drawings, Apartment Building for B. Mikhov on "Ilinden" Street in Varna, Bulgaria, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1993
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 5
</container>
</did>
</c01>


<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 63-75; Working Drawings, Vacation House for Burov in subdivision of Briz in Varna, Bulgaria, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 6
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Paper 76; Site Plan, Vacation House for Shulevov in "Monastikski" Road area, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 7
</container>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers 77-83; Conceptual Working Drawings, Vacation House for Shulevov in "Monastikski" Road area,  
<unitdate type="inclusive">1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Map-case" type="drawer">32: Drawer 10: Folder 7
</container>
</did>
</c01>


</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>








