<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00126">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00126::Yellow Sulphur
Springs Hotel Account Book)//EN" "viblbv00126"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Register of the Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1887-1895 </date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms1940-033
</num></subtitle>
        <author>John M. Jackson
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by John M. Jackson.<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Register of the Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1887-1895 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms1940-033
</num></subtitle>
      <author>John M. Jackson
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887-1895
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Ms1940-033
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="DIGITAL CONTENT">
        <emph render="bold">This item has been digitized and is available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Appalachia/Ms1940_033">online</extref></emph>.
      </physdesc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 container; 1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Guest register from Yellow Sulphur Springs, a resort which operated in Montgomery County, Virginia, from 1810 to 1923. Register spans the years 1887 to 1895.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictionss
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book, Ms1940-033 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book was donated to Newman Library in 1940.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternate Form Available
</head>
        <p>This item has been digitized and is <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Appalachia/Ms1940_033">available online</extref> as a pdf.
</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book commenced and was completed in April 2004.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Yellow Sulphur Springs resort, located between the towns of Blacksburg and Christiansburg, Virginia, commenced operation as a health spa in 1810, when David and Nancy Robinson hired Charles Taylor to
construct cabins and a sixty-room hotel on their family's property. Known initially as Yellow Springs, the resort benefited from a popular belief in the restorative powers of mineral waters and catered to a new
leisure class seeking healthy and entertaining diversions. In doing so, the resort joined such other nearby establishments as the Greenbrier White, Old Sweet, and Montgomery White Sulphur Springs.
</p>
      <p>The resort passed through a series of owners (Charles Taylor, 1812; Armistead Forrest, 1842; Foulkes, Gardner and Edmundson, 1853; John and James Wade, 1871) throughout the nineteenth century. In 1852, the
resort's name was changed to Yellow Sulphur Springs. The Yellow closed during the Civil War, but re-opened in 1868 to heightened popularity. A second, larger hotel was built in 1871, but was destroyed by fire in
1873. In 1886, Ridgeway Holt acquired the property; he rebuilt the second hotel in 1888.
</p>
      <p>Easy access to the nearby Virginia-Tennessee Railroad ensured the springs' success. Though not one of the larger spas, the resort could house as many as 400 guests in its hotel and adjacent cottages. Offering
such amenities as a ballroom, a billiard room, a bowling alley, and a gazebo, the resort attracted visitors from throughout the United States and several foreign countries. Former Confederate generals Jubal Early
and P. G. T. Beauregard each had rooms permanently reserved for their stays. The hotel became a favorite place for students at Virginia Agricultural and Mechanics College (later Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
State University) after the college's founding in 1872.
</p>
      <p>With the advent of the automobile and scientific skepticism of the value of spring baths, however, the popularity of such resorts began to decline by the early twentieth century. The economic panic of 1893
hastened the resort's demise. The resort property was sold by auction in 1929. During the Great Depression, the Virginia Transit Bureau leased the resort as a camp for transients, who engaged in restoring the
buildings and grounds.
</p>
      <p>The original hotel and several other buildings remain standing today (2004), having been placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1979. The buildings have been partially restored, and a guest house
and healing arts studio now operate there.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel Account Book, which might more accurately be described as a guest register, includes the names of guests, their place of residence, the time of their arrival, and their room
numbers. While the resort played host to guests from all areas of the United States--and a few from foreign countries--a number of guests were local residents. Each register page features advertisements for a
variety of businesses in Lynchburg, Virginia. The register's entries commence on August 26, 1887 and end on July 10, 1895.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Appalachia/Ms1940_033">Register</extref>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887-1895
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
