<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY hawkins-pearce-navarro SYSTEM "http://www.pearcecollections.us/civilwar/fa_ind.php?fid=285" NDATA html>
]>
<ead id="viblbv00251">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00251:: James P. Hawkins Papers, 1864-65)//EN" "viblbv00251.xml" </eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the James P. Hawkins Papers, <date>1864-1865</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Hawkins, James P., Papers <num type="collectionnumber"
                        >Ms2008-025 </num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
                </publisher> &address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic
                    Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Jared
                Camins-Esakov, <date>5/27/2008</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the James P. Hawkins Papers, <date>1864-1865</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number"
                    >Ms2008-025 </num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
            <date type="publication">2008 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: </label>
                    <item>Jared Camins-Esakov, Special Collections Staff; new material added by Marc
                        Brodsky, Public Services and Reference Archivist </item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">James P. Hawkins Papers <unitdate
                    type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1864-1865 </unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-025 </unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu.
                ft. </physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract label="Abstract">Collection includes a bound expense/account notebook of James
                P. Hawkins, agent of the Southern Express Company, which also contains diary entries
                from 2 April - 10 April 1865. Also included are a collection of loose pages with
                Hawkins's diary entries for 11 April - 11 May 1865. Related documents, including
                special orders, exemption from military service, receipts, Oath of Allegiance,
                letters (2), envelopes, and a photograph complete the collection. </abstract>
            <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">James P. Hawkins </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information </head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions </head>
                <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions </head>
                <p>Permission to publish material from the James P. Hawkins Papers must be obtained
                    from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. </p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation </head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: James P. Hawkins Papers, Ms2008-025, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information </head>
                <p>The James P. Hawkins Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 2004. </p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo>
                <head>Processing Information </head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the James P. Hawkins Papers
                    commenced and was completed in May, 2008. Additional description was added in
                    November 2011. </p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Information </head>
            <p>James P. Hawkins was born in Albemarle Co., Virginia in 1845. The 1850 census shows
                James, then 5 years old, living with his father, Richard, listed as a harnessmaker,
                and his mother, Elizabeth, in Charlottesville. By 1860, the family was in Staunton,
                VA and included daughters Mary and Kate. Also by that year, Richard, James's father,
                was working as a Stage Agent. The 29 September 1865 issue of the <title render="italic">Staunton
                Vindicator</title> reports that "office of the Adam's Express Company has been refurbished"
                and that "company agent, Richard Hawkins, has again taken up business in the old
                quarters." In 1870 and 1880, respectively, Richard Hawkins's profession is listed as
                Express Agent and Adams Express Agent. The Adams Express Company was the parent
                company of the Southern Express Company, the company for which James P. Hawkins
                worked during the war. </p>

            <p> James P. Hawkins was never mustered into the Confederate Army and was exempt due to
                his service with Southern Express, a civilian transport company that worked in
                conjunction with the avenues of Confederate military transportation. He did,
                apparently, have an affinity for the West Augusta Guard, often referring to the
                "West A Guard" as "his company." (See Holcomb in Related Materials Note, below). The
                West Augusta Guard was one of the oldest of the Staunton companies, organized in the
                summer of 1858, first attached to the 160th Regiment Virginia Militia, and then, in
                June 1861, becoming Company L, 5th Virginia Infantry.</p>

            <p> Hawkins's work for Southern Express lasted at least through May 1865 and took him on
                routes throughout Virginia and North Carolina. On 2 April 1865, he returned to
                Richmond from North Carolina and found himself in the midst of the evacuation of the
                city. The events of this and following days are described in his diary. </p>

            <p> As reported by the <title render="italic">Staunton
                Vindicator</title> (23 December 1870), James P. Hawkins,
                resident of Danville, VA and Pheilipina Behn McDowell, formerly of Charleston, SC,
                were married in Staunton on 19 December 1870 at the residence of Richard Hawkins by
                the Rev. William H. Williams. The 1880 census shows them living as boarders in
                Danville, with James's occupation listed as tobacconist. In 1900, James and
                Pheilipina were living in Millboro, Bath Co., Virginia, along with their 17 year-old
                daughter, Palma. The Staunton Spectator of 21 February 1902 reported that Mrs. James
                P. Hawkins died on 12 February of that year at their home near Millboro and that
                three children, two sons and a daughter, survived her, along with her husband. In
                1910, James was still in Millboro, living with his now-married daughter, Parma Dill,
                her husband, James, and their children. James P. Hawkins died on 27 January 1931 and
                is buried at Windy Cove Presbyterian Church in Millboro Springs, VA. </p>

        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content </head>
            <p>The principle part of the collection consists of a bound expense/account notebook of
                James P. Hawkins, agent of the Southern Express Company, which also contains diary
                entries from 2 April - 10 April 1865, and a collection of loose pages with Hawkins's
                diary entries for 11 April - 11 May 1865.</p>

            <p> During this time, Hawkins was responsible for protecting the valuables of the
                Richmond office of Southern Express. He arrived in Richmond on April 2, the day the
                city was evacuated, and writes that he had heard nothing of the evacuation until
                arriving in the city. He describes the chaos of the city; the rumors "thick as
                flies"; the "ruling rates" for goods; and "burning at Treasury, Capitol, War Dept,
                etc." He would spend the next several weeks escorting a number of the Company's
                safes and records to Charlotte by way of Danville and Greensboro, NC. During that
                time, he reports on 10 April, "Hear for first time of 'Surrender of Lee and his
                Army'" and on 18 April, of the assassination of Lincoln and the wounding of Seward.
                On 10 May, Hawkins is appointed Southern Express agent at Danville. </p>

            <p> In addition to the diary entries, the bound notebook contains notes on his expenses
                and accounts during his travels, memoranda of various kinds (some entirely crossed
                out). The loose diary pages--written in the same hand as the bound diary, but,
                perhaps, copied over at a later date--pick up where the bound diary ends. The loose
                pages continue with descriptions of each day and news of military developments. </p>

            <p> Related documents, including special orders, exemption from military service,
                itemized expenses and receipts, Hawkins's signed Oath of Allegiance to the United
                States, two letters written to Hawkins, envelopes, and a photograph of an
                unidentified man taken in a New Orleans studio complete the collection.</p>

        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement </head>
            <p>Hawkins's diaries, bound and unbound, are arranged at the beginning of the
                collection, followed by the related material, with the unidentified photograph at
                the end. </p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>


            <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
                <head>Related Materials</head>

                <p>See also Holcomb, Julie. <title render="italic">America's Civil War,</title> "Confederate Express Agent James P.
                    Hawkins Got Caught Up in the Evacuation of Richmond," May 2003, Vol. 16, Issue
                    2, page 58. </p>

                <p> Three of James P. Hawkins' diaries spanning January 1862 - April 1863,
                    and a letter from James to his mother dated 15 May 1865 can be
                    found in the Hawkins (James P.) Papers in the Pearce Civil War Collection at
                    Navarro College in Corsicana, Texas. </p>

                <p> A finding aid is available on the <extref
                        href="http://www.pearcecollections.us/fa_ind.php?fid=285"
                        title="Pearce Museum at Navarro College website">Pearce Museum at Navarro College website</extref>. </p>
            </relatedmaterial>
        </descgrp>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Bound diary and expense/account notebook, <unitdate>2 Apr. 1865 - 10 Apr. 1865</unitdate> </unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962008" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref15" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Loose diary folios, <unitdate>11 Apr. 1865 - 11 May 1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962007" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref17" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Itemized expense sheets <unitdate> Mar. 1865 - May 1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962006" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref18" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Exemptions/furloughs permitting Hawkins to continue his work for Southern Express, <unitdate>23 Jun. 1863 - 31 Dec. 1864</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962005" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref20" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>James P. Hawkins' Oath of Allegiance and envelope, <unitdate>15 May 1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962004" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref21" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Envelopes addressed to James P. Hawkins.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962003" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref23" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Letters addressed to James P. Hawkins, <unitdate>20 Sep. 1864 - 10 Jan. 1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962002" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref25" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Unidentified photograph</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid962001" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                    
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>