<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00594">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00594::J. Hoge Tyler Diary, 1846-1925, 2009)//EN"
            "viblbv00594.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the J. Hoge Tyler Diary, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846-1925, 2009</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Tyler, J. Hoge, Diary <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-001</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011-02-07T14:35-0500</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>J. Hoge Tyler Diary, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846-1925, 2009</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-001</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz, Acquisitions and Processing Archivist, and
                        Isidoro Rodriguez-Hazbun, Student Assistant,</label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">J. Hoge Tyler Diary, <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846-1925, 2009</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms2010-001</unitid>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
        <extent>1 box</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Tyler, James Hoge, 1846-1925</persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref11" encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref12" encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the J. Hoge Tyler Diary must be obtained from
                    Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref13" encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: J. Hoge Tyler Diary, Ms2010-001, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref14" encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The J. Hoge Tyler Diary was donated to Special Collections in January 2010</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail id="ref10" encodinganalog="530$a">
        <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
        <p>In addition to the original diary, this collection also includes a bound
                    transcript and searchable pdf version of the transcript on CD.</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo id="ref15" encodinganalog="583$a">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the J. Hoge Tyler Diary was
                    completed in February 2011.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="ref7" encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>James Hoge Tyler, Virginia governor from 1898 to 1902, was born at the Tyler family
                farm, "Blenheim," in Caroline County, Virginia on August 11, 1846. He was the son of
                George Tyler (1817-1889), a representative of Caroline County, and Eliza Hoge
                (1815-1846), daughter of General James Hoge. His mother having died during his
                birth, the young James Hoge Tyler was reared by his grandparents, James and Eleanor
                Howe Hoge at "Hayfield," their Pulaski County home. Tyler was educated in Pulaski
                County before attending the school of Franklin Minor in Albermarle County.</p>
      <p>Tyler left school at the age of 16 to join the Confederate army and served as a
                private in the Signal Corps throughout the Civil War. (His later rank of "major" was
                apparently a post-war honorific.) After the war, Tyler returned to Pulaski County,
                where he had inherited the Hoge farm. He would rename the farm "Belle Hampton" and
                become a successful farmer, raising Durham cattle and serving as president of the
                Virginia Stock Farmers' Institute and of the Southwest Virginia Live Stock
                Association. His other business interests would come to include a store, a
                gristmill, a sawmill, the Belle Hampton Coal Mining Company (sold in 1902 to a New
                York company), and the Radford Development Company.</p>
      <p>Tyler married Sue Montgomery Hammet (daughter of Edward and Clementina Craig Hammet,
                who built the first home in what it now Radford, Virginia), a native of Radford, on
                November 16, 1868. While living at Belle Hampton, the Tylers had eight children:
                Edward H., James H. Jr., Stockton H., Lucy Belle, Sue H., Henry C. ("Hal"), Eliza
                ("Lily") and Eleanor Howe, who died in infancy. In 1891, the family moved to
                "Halwick," their home in Radford.</p>
      <p>In 1877, Tyler was elected to the state senate, serving one term and advocating
                retrenchment and reform. He maintained an active role in civic affairs, serving on
                the board of visitors and as rector of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical
                College (now Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University) and on the state
                debt commission. During the 1880s, he mounted two unsuccessful congressional
                campaigns. Tyler also launched an unsuccessful bid for governor in 1889 but secured
                the second place on the Democratic ticket that year and served as lieutenant
                governor from 1890 to 1894. While serving as lieutenant governor, Tyler again ran
                for the governorship in 1893, losing to Charles T. O'Ferrall. In 1897, Tyler
                successfully campaigned for governor and served from 1898 to 1902.</p>
      <p>Tyler's gubernatorial administration was marked by a concern with adjustment of
                Virginia's state debt. He was a strong supporter of bi-metallism, and was a personal
                friend of William Jennings Bryan. The American Historical Society's History of
                Virginia (1926) summarized Tyler's governorship thus:</p>
      <p>
        <blockquote>
          <p>Governor Tyler's administration was marked by the settlement of the long
                        vexed oyster question, for it was largely through his efforts that the
                        LeCato bill was made effective and the oyster beds of the state made to
                        yield an income to the state instead of an annual deficit. As governor he
                        secured the reduction of taxes and the state debt and the increase of the
                        public school fund and the literary fund. Other measures credited to his
                        administration are the establishment of the Farm Bureau, the reorganization
                        of the agricultural department, a conditional pardon system and the
                        settlement of the Virginia-Tennessee boundary question.</p>
        </blockquote>
      </p>
      <p>While serving as governor, Tyler launched an unsuccessful campaign for the U. S.
                Senate seat of incumbent Thomas S. Martin. His unsuccessful 1899 campaign would be
                Tyler's last, though he would continue to be somewhat active in state politics,
                playing the role of elder statesman and considering various pleas that he again seek
                office. During World War I, he served as food administrator for Radford and
                Montgomery County.</p>
      <p>A Presbyterian, Tyler served as a ruling elder and moderator of the Synod of
                Virginia. He founded the Presbyterian church in East Radford, the area's first brick
                church. Three times he represented his church in the Presbyterian General Assembly.
                He also served twice as a delegate to the Pan-Presbyterian Council--once in Toronto,
                Canada and once in Glasgow, Scotland. He also served on the boards of trustees of
                the church-affiliated Hampden-Sidney College, Union Theological Seminary, and
                Synodical Orphans Home at Lynchburg.</p>
      <p>James Hoge Tyler died on January 3, 1925; Sue Hammet Tyler, born July 16, 1845, died
                on April 24, 1927.</p>
      <p>For additional biographical information on the Tyler family, see the J. Hoge Tyler
                Family Collection <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00220.xml.frame">finding aid</extref>.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection includes the original diary, records, and family genealogy of James
                Hoge Tyler (1846-1925) of Pulaski County, Virginia, as well as new transcription
                with genealogy in print and a CD which incorporates all materials. The diary not
                only includes information about daily activities but also genealogical information.
                Most of the diary is written by James Hoge Tyler. He also includes in his writing
                some passages written by his mother (Eliza Hoge), poems, and songs. Some of the
                entries in the diary are written by his wife Sue Hammet Tyler while James Hoge Tyler
                was in office as Governor of Virginia (1898-1902). Later entries were written by
                Tyler's daughter, Eliza (Lily), who used the diary as her own for some time.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="ref8" encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by type of material.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
      <relatedmaterial id="ref6" encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Materials</head>
        <p>J. Hoge Tyler Family Collection, Ms67-002. <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Finding aid" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00220.xml.frame">Finding aid</extref> available on the Virginia Heritage
                    database. </p>
        <p>Tyler, James Hoge, and James F. Hoge. 1927. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Family of
                        Hoge</title>. Greensboro, N.C.: J.J. Stone &amp; Co., printers]. CS71 .H715
                    1927 Spec Genealogy</p>
        <p>Virginia, and James Hoge Tyler. 1902. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Letters and Public
                        Papers of Governor J. Hoge Tyler, 1898-1902</title>. F231 .T94 A4 1902 Spec
                    Large</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <separatedmaterial id="ref5" encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Separated Materials</head>
        <p>Gay, Thomas Edward. 1979. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Life and Political Career of
                        J. Hoge Tyler, Governor of Virginia, 1898-1902</title>. Thesis--University
                    of Virginia. This copy also contains a searchable pdf of the text on CD. F 231
                    .T98 G28 c.3. Spec Large</p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname source="local">Tyler, Eliza Hoge, 1815-1846</persname>
        <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Tyler, James Hoge, 1846-1925</persname>
        <persname rules="dacs" source="local">Tyler, Sue Hammet, 1845-1927</persname>
        <persname source="local">Wilson, Eliza (Lily) Tyler, b.1882</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Local Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Local/Regional History</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="ref3" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Diary, <unitdate normal="1846/1925" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846-1925</unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid505001" type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref4" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound transcription with searchable pdf version, <unitdate normal="2009/2009" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009</unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid505002" type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
