<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00388">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00388:: John Henry Johnson Scrapbook, 1918-1958)//EN" "viblbv00388.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the John Henry Johnson Scrapbook, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1958</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Johnson, John Henry Scrapbook
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-053
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">03/31/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the John Henry Johnson Scrapbook, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1958</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-053
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John Henry Johnson Scrapbook
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1958
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-053
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.3 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Scrapbook of John Henry Johnson, a Scott County, Virginia politician, including letters signed by other politicians (including William Jennings Bryan and other members of the Bryan family), newspaper clippings, certificates, invitations, original poetry, and a photograph. 
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the John Henry Johnson Scrapbook must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: John Henry Johnson Scrapbook, Ms2009-053 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The John Henry Johnson Scrapbook was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing and description of the John Henry Johnson Scrapbook commenced in February 2009 and was completed in March 2009.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>John Henry Johnson, a Southwest Virginia politician, farmer and businessman, was born in Turkey Cove (Lee County), Virginia on June 22, 1889. The son of John M. and Mannie Morrison Johnson, he attended school at Shoemaker College, Washington and Lee University and the University of Virginia. Johnson was appointed a Virginia delegate to the National Good Roads Congress in 1911. By 1914, Johnson was living in Scott County, from which he was elected as a Democrat to a single term in the Virginia House of Delegates. A farmer and businessman, Johnson also served in a number of local civic posts and managed the statewide campaign of Benjamin Franklin Buchanan in his race for lieutenant governor. During World War I, he was a "four-minute man," delivering short speeches--while reels were exchanged at film showings--in support of the war effort. In 1923, Johnson was elected to the Virginia Senate, representing the Sixteenth Senatorial District, composed of Lee and Scott counties. He also served as a delegate to the Democratic National Convention the following year. Reelected to the state senate in 1925, Johnson lost his bid for a third term in 1927. John Henry Johnson died on September 27, 1956. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of a scrapbook compiled by John Henry Johnson, a Southwest Virginia politician, farmer and businessman. The scrapbook includes such items as correspondence from other state and national figures, newspaper clippings, invitations, certificates, and other assorted ephemera. 
</p>
      <p>Among the political correspondents represented are William Jennings Bryan, Nebraska Governor Charles W. Bryan and other members of the Bryan family; Adlai Stevenson; Virginia Congressman Carter Glass; Democratic National Committee Chair Stephen A. Mitchell; Virginia Senator Thomas S. Martin; 1924 Democratic Party presidential nominee John W. Davis; Henry St. George Tucker, and former Virginia Lieutenant Governor Benjamin F. Buchanan.
</p>
      <p>Most of the newspaper clippings relate to local, state and national politics--including Virginia vote tabulations--and Johnson's own political career. Other clippings include a number of obituaries of Johnson's family members and acquaintances, as well as articles on Johnson's general personal interests, including various short poems (some written by Johnson); county, state and national history; and newsmakers of the day. Among the invitations are items relating to the fourth inauguration of Franklin D. Roosevelt. Included among the ephemera are a booklet of Washington and Lee songs, yells for a 1908 football game against Virginia Tech, and political handbills. The scrapbook contains a lone photograph, a studio portrait of Virginia Lieutenant Governor Benjamin F. Buchanan.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The scrapbook retains its original format and arrangement. At the rear of the scrapbook is a set of loose materials, at least some of which seem to have been detached from various pages within the scrapbook.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Scrapbook
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1958
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
