<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00698">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00698::John Harville Diaries, 1861-1864, 1913, 2010)//EN"
            "viblbv00698.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the John Harville Diaries, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864, 1913,
                        2010</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Harville, John, Diaries<num type="collectionnumber">
                        Ms2010-053</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in oXygen by Kira A. Dietz, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August
                    2010</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-23">2014-01-23</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>John Harville Diaries, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864, 1913, 2010</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">Ms2010-053</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz,</label>
          <item>Acquisitions and Processing Archivist, Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John Harville Diaries, <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864, 1913, 2010
                </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-053</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.4 cu. ft.; 2
                boxes</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains eight handwritten diaries chronicling
                John Harville's experiences during the Civil War. From August of 1861 to January of
                1864 Harville served with the 7th Wisconsin Regiment, Company F. He then transferred
                to the Veteran Reserve Corps for the remainder of his term, ending in July 1864. His
                diaries include details and stories from camp life, largely around Washington, DC,
                and Baltimore, MD. Suffering from chronic "congestion of the lungs," Harville spent
                Autumn 1862 to Spring 1864 in hospitals. He continued to document this period with
                stories of daily life, chores, staff and volunteers at the hospitals, and war news. </abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Harville, John McBride,
                1839-1913</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the John Harville must be obtained from the
                    donors. Please contact Special Collections for more information.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: John Harville Diaries, Ms2010-053, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The John Harville Diaries were donated to Special Collections by the family of
                    Edward Ferguson in June 2010.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
        <p>Transcripts of all eight diaries are available as part of the collection. Links
                    to the transcripts as pdf files are available in the "Contents List" below. </p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the John Harville Diaries
                    commenced and was completed in August 2010. Some transcripts were provided by
                    the donors. Additional transcripts were completed by Kira Dietz, Josh Howard,
                    John Jackson, Jennifer Mitchell, and Melissa Smith, Special Collections Staff,
                    in June, July, and August 2010.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>John McBride Harville (also spelled Harvill) was born in Illinois on January 29,
                1839. His family seems to have moved to Beetown, Wisconsin, around 1843, though
                other records indicate this may have occurred later. Before the early death of his
                mother when he was five, his parents appeared to have had three other children:
                Caroline (later Young), who Harville refers to as "Carrie" or
                "Cary" in his diaries; William; and Elizabeth (later Nickerson), who
                Harville calls "Lib." For several years, he lived with a foster family
                (the Sargents). His father, William, remarried and had five more children. By the
                start of the Civil War, Harville was living with the Batie family in Tafton,
                Wisconsin. </p>
      <p>Although Tafton did not have enough men to raise its own company, volunteers from the
                area, including Harville, joined others to form Company F, 7th Regiment Wisconsin
                Infantry in Lancaster during the summer of 1861. Harville served primarily in and
                around Washington, DC, Virginia, and Maryland. Chronic health problems resulted in
                his spending most of September 1862-August 1864 in hospitals in Baltimore, Maryland,
                though he continues to report on his personal experiences, as well as war news. In
                January of 1864, he transferred to the Veteran Reserve Corps until he mustered out
                in August 1864.</p>
      <p>In October 1864, he married Harriet E. Trine (1846-1916), who he had known since
                before the war. As early as his first diary in 1861, he records having received
                letters from Hattie and Lizzie (presumably her sister) Trine. They settled in
                Wyalusing and had five children: William A. (1865-1894), Annie Laure (b. 1867),
                Frank D. (1869-1883), Edgar R.(b. 1872), and John M., Jr. (b. 1879). Following the
                war, Harville was both a farmer and a newspaperman. He died from pneumonia in
                Wisconsin at age 74 in June 1913.</p>
      <p>The 7th Regiment, Wisconsin Volunteers, along with the 2nd Wisconsin, 6th Wisconsin,
                and 19th Indiana, formed the "Iron Brigade" in the autumn of 1861. In
                October 1862, the 24th Michigan joined the brigade. The Iron Brigade was under the
                immediate command of Brig. Gen. Rufus King and made up a part of the 3rd Brigade of
                the Army of Potomac, under Major General McDowell. Near the front of the battle at
                Gettysburg, Antietam, The Wilderness, Second Bull Run, and several other major
                campaigns, over the course of the war, the Iron Brigade suffered the greatest losses
                in proportion to its numbers. </p>
      <p>Additional biographical information is available in the collection. More information
                on Wisconsin Regiments can be found on the Wisconsin Historical Society website:
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/research.asp" xlink:href="http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/research.asp">
                    http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/research.asp</extref>. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection contains eight original diaries, as well as transcripts and additional
                biographical information. Harville's diaries chronicle his experiences with the 7th
                Wisconsin Regiment during 1861 and 1862. He spent much of 1863 and 1864 in Newton
                University Hospital, and later Jarvis Hospital, in Baltimore, MD, facing chronic
                illness.</p>
      <p>Clearly intended for an audience, the diaries contain short addresses to the
                "Reader" at the beginning and end, often including an apology for his poor
                grammar and spelling. Largely self-educated, Harville's diaries are surprisingly
                legible and his phonetic spellings are easy to decipher. Most of the diaries also
                include a list of letters received and written, as well as Harville's cash and
                barter accounts with friends. Several diaries are indexed and/or paginated.</p>
      <p>Harville's early entries detail the formation of Company F in Lancaster, Wisconsin,
                travel to Washington, DC, and life in camp outside Alexandria, Virginia. Like many
                farmers in the war, he keeps consistent notes on the weather. He recounts stories of
                his own adventures which more than once landed him in trouble, as well as the
                exploits of others. He also writes of picket and guard house duty, the occasional
                scouting mission, frequent drills and dress parades, and war news. He remains
                relatively well-informed about the war, at least in as much as it related to his
                experiences and his regiment.</p>
      <p>While spending time in Jarvis and Newton University Hospitals, the content of his
                entries begins to change some. He continues to records war news of note during this
                period, but the emphasis is on the work he does and the social life he develops. His
                illness is intermittent and so he also does chores around the hospital, including
                cleaning inside and outside the buildings, cooking and serving, and running errands.
                Harville spends a good deal of time helping the local women who volunteer at the
                hospitals, too, which he appears to thoroughly enjoy. At least two diaries contain a
                list of women and young ladies with whom he is acquainted.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged is two series: Series I: Diaries, 1861-1864 and Series II:
                Transcripts and Biographical Information, 1913, 2010, undated. </p>
      <p>Series I: Diaries, contains all eight original diaries, arranged in chronological
                order. There is some slight overlap of dates in diaries #7 and #8—both diaries
                contain different entries from the Summer of 1864.</p>
      <p>Series II: Transcripts and Biographical Information, includes transcripts of the
                diaries and copies of biographical material (obituaries, family records, and two
                newspaper columns). Transcripts are arranged in chronological order, followed by the
                biographical material. Wherever possible, first names and/or corrected spellings
                have been added to names Harville mentions throughout his diaries, due in large part
                to the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Roster of Wisconsin Volunteers, War of the Rebellion,
                    1861-1865</title> available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="online" xlink:href="http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/roster/search.asp">online</extref>.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data </head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material </head>
        <p>John Harville is mentioned briefly in: Ray, William R., Lance J. Herdegen, and
                    Sherry Murphy. <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Four Years with the Iron Brigade: The
                        Civil War Journals of William R. Ray, Co. F, Seventh Wisconsin
                        Infantry</title>. [Cambridge, Mass.]: Da Capo Press, 2002. Newman 2nd Floor,
                    E 537.5 7th R39 2002.</p>
        <p>Special Collections houses several publications on the Iron Brigade. A list of
                    these publications, with links to catalog records, is available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="here" xlink:href="http://addison.vt.edu/search~S1/?searchtype=Y&amp;searcharg=%22iron+brigade%22&amp;searchscope=5&amp;sortdropdown=-≈SORT=DZ&amp;extended=0&amp;SUBMIT=Search&amp;searchlimits=&amp;searchorigarg=Y%22iron+brigade%22%26SORT%3DDZ">here</extref>.</p>
        <p>Newman Library houses additional publications on the Iron Brigade, available for
                    circulation. A list of these publications, with links to catalog records, is
                    available <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="here" xlink:href="http://addison.vt.edu/search~S5/?searchtype=Y&amp;searcharg=%22iron+brigade%22&amp;searchscope=2&amp;sortdropdown=-&amp;SORT=DZ&amp;extended=0&amp;SUBMIT=Search&amp;searchlimits=&amp;searchorigarg=Y%22iron+brigade%22%26SORT%3DDZ">here</extref>.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental Histories--Wisconsin</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Diaries, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #1, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 1861 - January
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #2, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January - March
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #3, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March - May 1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #4, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May - August
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #5, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 1862 - May
                                1863.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #6, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June - November
                                1863.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #7, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1863 - August
                                1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary #8, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July - August
                                1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Transcripts and Biographical Information, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913, 2010, undated.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #1, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 1861 -
                                January 1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary1.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #2, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January - March
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary2.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #3, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March - May
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary3.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #4, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May - August
                                1862.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary4.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #5, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 1862 -
                                May 1863.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary5.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #6, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June - November
                                1863.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary6.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #7, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1863 -
                                August 1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary7.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcript, Diary #8, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July - August
                                1864.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="Transcript (pdf)" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/harville/diary8.pdf">Transcript
                                (pdf)</extref>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Biographical Information, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913,
                                undated.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2-9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
