<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00738">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00738::Paul H. Farrier Family Papers, 1936-1970)//EN"
            "viblbv00738.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Paul H. Farrier Family Papers, <date>1936-1970</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Farrier, Paul H., Family Papers <num type="collectionnumber"
                        >Ms2010-084</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date>2010-11-17T12:12-0500</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Paul H. Farrier Family Papers, <date>1936-1970</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-084</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2010 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Julia Viets,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Paul H. Farrier Family Papers, <unitdate
                    normal="1936/1970" type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f"
                    >1936-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms2010-084</unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
                <extent>0.6 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 box; 2 oversized folders</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">This collection contains materials relating to Paul
                H. Farrier and his daughter Pence Farrier, a former VPI Director of Admissions and a
                VPI alumnus, respectively, during the years of 1936 to 1970. Included are
                administrative papers such as business correspondence and admissions reports as well
                as general VPI memorabilia for campus events and activities, such as newspaper
                clippings, invitations, programs, and tickets.</abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Adminstrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict id="ref6" encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="ref8" encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Permission to publish material from the Paul H. Farrier Family Papers must be
                    obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite id="ref13" encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Paul H. Farrier Family Papers, Ms2010-084, Special Collections,
                    Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo id="ref10" encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>This collection was donated to Special Collections in 2010.</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo id="ref12" encodinganalog="583$a">
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Paul H. Farrier Family Papers
                    was completed in November 2010.</p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref5" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Information</head>
            <p>Paul H. Farrier was the Director of Admissions at Virginia Tech during the 1950s. He
                received his B.A. from Emory and Henry College in 1919, his M.A. from the University
                of Virginia in 1927, and his PhD also from UVA in 1929. Farrier then worked as an
                assistant English professor at Kentucky Wesleyan College before working as a
                Virginia Tech English professor for nine years, starting in 1936.</p>
            <p>Farrier was the Director of Admissions at VPI for ten years before he became the
                Executive Secretary for the Virginia State Council of Higher Education for two years
                in 1956. During his time in the Virginia State Council of Higher Education, Farrier
                worked on such projects as comparing public university meal prices, restructuring
                the home economics programs at VPI and Radford, and setting up an accredited school
                of forestry at Virginia Tech. In October of 1958, Farrier was reinstated as Director
                of Admissions at VPI and shared his duties with Landon Fuller, who had assumed the
                position during Farrier's two years leave.</p>
            <p>In addition to being in charge of admitting students, Farrier was also involved in
                the hiring of new faculty positions, student honor court proceedings, gathering
                student financial aid, working closely with high school officials, and dropping
                students based on poor behavior or academics. He was deeply passionate about being
                generous and inclusive with admissions, often admitting unqualified but motivated
                students to a 'basic program.' Farrier often referenced the value of this 'basic
                program' in his correspondence with President Newman; the program allowed unprepared
                freshman students to be admitted as undeclared majors if they took a lighter course
                load and received close counseling. Farrier believed that under-performing students
                should not be barred from receiving a higher education or be dropped, but instead
                should be kept in closer contact with. This generous attitude invited criticisms
                throughout Farrier's career; one high school principal even told him, "the VPI
                graduate murders the King's English and lets it lie in its gore." Such negative
                attitudes were further perpetuated by the fact that VPI offered practical, less
                refined degrees, such as those in agriculture and business. Later in his career,
                Farrier implemented a more selective admissions process, eliminating the bottom ten
                percent of the applicant pool and phasing out the 'basic' program.</p>
            <p>Receiving criticism and opposition were not the only difficulties Farrier faced
                in his career as Director of Admissions at VPI. The college application process was
                an evolving landscape that he had to continually adjust to. Because he received
                applications from students from a variety of backgrounds, Farrier was instrumental
                in increasing the use of college aptitude tests as to better screen students beyond
                those that came from out of state. Farrier was also continually worried about
                admitted students' maturity levels and the college adjustment process; thus, he
                helped set up student counseling programs to solve such worries. Additionally,
                Farrier was plagued by the departure of some of the best VPI students as they
                transferred elsewhere on scholarships; he worked hard to increase financial aid
                opportunities to keep such students. Other difficulties included facing applicant
                opposition towards the military aspects of VPI and battling the lack of dorm space
                available for increasingly enlarged freshman classes. For all these difficulties,
                Farrier maintained that increasing good public relations was part of the
                solution.</p>
            <p>Pence Farrier, the daughter of Paul H. Farrier, graduated from Virginia Tech in 1953.
                She also attended Randolph-Macon Women's College. At Virginia Tech, Pence attended
                many dances and was a YMCA cabinet member and the secretary of Maroon Mask in her
                senior year. Shortly after graduation, she married Roy Howard Ellis, another VPI
                alumnus.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection contains materials dated from 1936 to 1970 relating to Paul Farrier
                during his time as Director of Admissions at VPI and his daughter, Pence Farrier,
                during her time as an undergraduate student at VPI. Administrative materials include
                business correspondence, admissions reports, and newspaper clippings. Various VPI
                memorabilia items are also included in this collection and largely pertain to Pence
                Farrier's college days: most items are invitations, programs, and tickets relating
                to such activities as athletics, dances, memorials, and commencements.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref7" encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>This collection is arranged by material type into two series: Series I:
                Administrative Files and Series II: VPI Memorabilia.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Series I: Administrative Files</emph>, 1936-1966, contains three
                folders arranged by subject matter; within each topic, materials are arranged
                chronologically whenever possible. Materials in this series include business
                correspondence, newspaper clippings relating to Farrier's appointment as Executive
                Secretary for the Virginia State Council of Higher Education, and VPI admissions
                reports.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Series II: VPI Memorabilia</emph>, 1941-1970, contains twelve
                folders as well as two oversized folders arranged by subject matter; within each
                topic, materials are arranged chronologically whenever possible. Materials within
                this series consist of artifacts, invitations, tickets, programs, and news clippings
                relating to campus events and activities such as sports, dances, memorials,
                concerts, retirements, plays, and commencements.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
            <relatedmaterial id="ref11" encodinganalog="544$a">
                <head>Related Materials</head>
                <p>
                    <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                        title="Records of the Office of the President, Walter S. Newman, 1947-1962 (Bulk 1947-1961)"
                        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00086.xml.frame"
                        >Records of the Office of the President, Walter S. Newman, 1947-1962 (Bulk
                        1947-1961)</extref> (RG 2/10)</p>
                <p>
                    <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new" title="Wayne Morse Letter"
                        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00741.xml.frame"
                        >Wayne Morse Letter, 1947</extref> (Ms1947-001)</p>
            </relatedmaterial>
        </descgrp>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="lcsh">Virginia Polytechnic Institute</subject>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Local Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="local">University Archives</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref14" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series I: Administrative Files, <unitdate normal="1936/1966"
                            type="inclusive">1936-1966.</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Mr. &amp; Mrs. Paul Farrier Correspondence &amp; Papers,
                                <unitdate normal="1936/1966" type="inclusive"
                            >1936-1966.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385002" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of Admissions, <unitdate normal="1955/1964"
                                type="inclusive">1955-1964.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385017" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-2 to 1-3 (2
                            folders)</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref15" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series II: VPI Memorabilia, <unitdate normal="1941/1970"
                            type="inclusive">1941-1970.</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Dedications &amp; Memorials, <unitdate normal="1941/1969"
                                type="inclusive">1941-1969.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385005" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-4</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Proms/YMCA Dances, <unitdate normal="1945/1951" type="inclusive"
                                >1945-1951.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385008" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-5</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cotillion Club, <unitdate normal="1949/1957" type="inclusive"
                                >1949-1957.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385009" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-6</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Community Concert Association, <unitdate normal="1950/1953"
                                type="inclusive">1950-1953.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385010" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-7</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref23" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>New Student Information Materials, <unitdate normal="1950/1970"
                                type="inclusive">1950-1970.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385011" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-8</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>VPI Artifacts, <unitdate>1951.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385012" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-9</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Commencement, <unitdate normal="1951/1953" type="inclusive"
                                >1951-1953.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385013" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-10</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Maroon Mask Productions, <unitdate normal="1952/1953"
                                type="inclusive">1952-1953.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385014" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-11</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>German Club Dances, <unitdate>1952-1953,
                            1955.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385015" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-12</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref28" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Corps of Cadets/ROTC, <unitdate>1964.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385016" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-13</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref29" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Omicron Delta Kappa, <unitdate normal="1952/1966"
                                type="inclusive">1952-1966.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385007" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-14</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Retired Faculty in the News,
                            <unitdate>1964,1966.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385006" type="Box-folder" label="Folder">1-15</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>VPI Athletics, <unitdate normal="1950/1965" type="inclusive"
                                >1950-1965.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385003" type="Oversize" label="Oversize">Folder
                            1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Ring Dance, <unitdate normal="1951/1952" type="inclusive"
                                >1951-1952.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid385004" type="Oversize" label="Oversize">Folder
                            2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
