<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00127">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Digital Library and Archive//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00127::Department of
Biochemistry Oral History Collection)//EN" "viblbv00127"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection <date> 2001-05 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Department of Biochemistry, Oral History Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2003-009
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Tamara Kennelly
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">[ca. 58 Kilobytes]
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by Clayton McGahee. (Modified by Kimberli Weeks, 2007)<date>2004</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection <date> 2001-05 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Digital Library and Archive
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2003-009
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Tamara Kennelly
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Tamara Kennelly
</label>
<item>Digital Library and Archive Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">2001-05
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">Ms2003-009
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2 containers, 0.8 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The oral history interviews in the Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection were conducted by current and retired faculty as part of the department's 50th anniversary
celebration. Interviews were conducted in the period from October 2001 to June 2002 with department heads, faculty, and staff who played an important role in the founding and development of the Department of
Biochemistry at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Oral history interviews were done with the following: Juel Albert by Robert R. Schmidt, Bruce M. Anderson by Thomas O. Sitz, Ruben W. Engel by George Edwin Bunce, Robert Smibert by John L. Hess, Everett L. Wisman by Lewis Barnett, and Roderick Young by Robert R. Schmidt. In addition an oral history interview of Cecil Cummins about the Anaerobe Lab was conducted by John Hess.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection, Ms2003-009, Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection was donated to the Digital Library and Archives in 2001-2003. Individual interviews and oral history transcripts were donated as they were completed and
became available.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Department of Biochemistry was established at Virginia Polytechnic Institute through the leadership of Dr. H. N. Young, director of the Agricultural Experiment Station. In 1952, he recruited Dr. R. W. Engle
from Auburn University. As the first department head (1952-1966) of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, Engel pulled together faculty from existing departments with interests in agricultural chemistry
and nutrition. Facilities in Price and Smyth Halls soon became inadequate, and with Engel's leadership, funds were acquired from the National Institutes of Health and matched by funds from the Commonwealth of
Virginia for construction of the building now called Engel Hall. From 1962, when the building was occupied, through 1967, additions to the faculty broadened the research expertise of the department. Significant
impact on basic and applied nutrition and analytical service to the Commonwealth characterized these initial fifteen years.
</p>
<p>Kendall King served as head from 1966 to 1968. The department awarded only graduate degrees until the undergraduate biochemistry curriculum was established in 1968. A faculty committee comprised of Clemens
Ackerman, Robert R. Schmidt, and Ryland Webb led the department from 1968 to 1970. Bruce M. Anderson provided stable leadership as head from 1970 to 1982. During this period, significant changes in facilities and
services accompanied the emphasis on basic research. Thomas W. Keenan (head, 1982-1988) shepherded careers of faculty and growth in the undergraduate program. In 1988, Judith S. Bond, the fifth department head
(1988-1992), established significant changes in laboratories, supported new faculty, and facilitated faculty efforts in the successful dedication of the biochemistry building to honor R. W. Engel.
</p>
<p>During the 1990s, the university sustained huge reductions in operating funds while undergraduate enrollments increased. Under William E. Newton's leadership (1992-1998), faculties were merged between the
Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition and the Anaerobe Lab. Subsequently, the present Department of Biochemistry was identified. In 1994, the department was recognized as University Exemplary Department for its
commitment to employing research successfully, as a foundation for undergraduate education.
</p>
<p>Four new faculty members joined the department since 1998. Faculty in spring of 2003 included a complement of seventeen scientists and educators with John L. Hess as department head (1998-). Two faculty members
had laboratories in the Fralin Biotechnology Center, a state-of-the art research and teaching facility adjoining Engel Hall. Faculty employed a broad spectrum of research tools to explore how organisms function
and to assess unique attributes which many be developed to serve humankind. Faculty research programs and collaborations were in core areas: functional genomics and proteomics, molecular microbiology, and
molecular mechanisms of response to stress and disease. In 2002-2003, faculty provided education and training for 25 graduate and 300 undergraduate majors.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Department of Biochemistry Oral History Collection spans the years 1952 to 2005 (bulk 2001-2005, the period during which the oral histories were collected). It includes interviews with R.W. Engel, founding
head of the department; Juel Albert, early faculty member; Bruce Anderson, department head, 1970-1982; Cecil Cummins, professor emeritus of microbiology and faculty in the Anaerobe Lab; Robert Smibert, faculty in the Anaerobe Lab, Everett L. Wisman, first faculty member; and Roddy Young, early
faculty member. The founding of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition including faculty, facilities and equipment, instruction, and research is given special attention. The founding of the Anaerobe Lab is
also discussed.
</p>
<p>In the interview of Juel Albert by Robert S. Schmidt, Albert discussed planning for the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, including facilities and apparatus, such as the Kjeldahl apparatus; department
faculty; and research projects, including forage testing and analyses and a multi-state project on nutrition of pre-adolescent girls.
</p>
<p>In his interview by Thomas O. Sitz, Bruce M. Anderson spoke of his charge as Head of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition to convert the department into an independent research oriented department
rather than an analytical tool for other agricultural sciences at the university. The interview covered claiming the biochemistry building for the Department of Biochemistry so that it could expand in numbers of
faculty and research laboratories. This involved relocating people that were not in the department. Anderson also set up the mass-spectroscopy facility and developed the undergraduate program. The interview also
touched on Anderson's research in enzymology.
</p>
<p>The R. W. Engel interview by George Edwin Bunce explored Engel's vision for the new department, early faculty, inter-departmental relationships, background on how the department obtained grants and other
funding for the new building, and Engel's work with Kendall King on the Mothercraft Centers in the Philippines.
</p>
<p>The Robert Smibert interview by John Hess explored the establishment of the Anaerobe Lab at Virginia Tech. Smibert also talked about his work with anaerobes; the Anaerobe Manual; laboratory equipment and
techniques; research focus on ruminant disease, nutrition and human health; projects, including working with campylobacter; and achievements of the Anaerobe Lab.
</p>
<p>In his oral history interview by Lewis Barnett, Everett L. Wisman discussed the beginnings of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, including courses, faculty, and facilities; Virginia Tech in the
1940s; and various changes in Virginia Tech and the campus.
</p>
<p>The interview of Roderick Young by Robert Schmidt dealt with the groundwork behind starting the Department of Biochemistry including the role played by his father, Dr. Harold Newell Young; selection of faculty
for the new department; the column Roderick Young developed for separating amino acids; research interests of the department; the department's teaching program; the first black female graduate student on campus;
and the pesticide program.
</p>
<p>The interview of Cecil Cummins by John Hess focuses on the history of the Anaerobe Lab and on some of the research that was conducted in that facility.
</p>
<p>Full text of most of the interviews and selected sound clips as well as images and other documents about the history of the Department of Biochemistry and its faculty are available in the Internet site, 50-
Year Celebration of the Department of Biochemistry, 1952-2003: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/archives/depthistory/biochem/
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged alphabetically by interviewee.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Interviewees
</head>
<p>Juel Albert first joined the Department of Agricultural Chemistry in 1941 as Laboratory Technician before the Department of Biochemistry was established. As Laboratory Specialist in the Department of
Biochemistry and Nutrition, he served as head of the Analytical Laboratory (forage testing) and assisted Dr. Engel in starting the new department. Albert worked for approximately 30 years in the Departments of
Agricultural Chemistry and Biochemistry and Nutrition and then approximately another 13 years in the Forage Testing Laboratory after transfer of his unit to Litton-Reaves Hall.
</p>
<p>Bruce M. Anderson was educated at Ursinus College (B.S., 1964), Purdue (M.S., 1965), and Johns Hopkins (Ph.D., 1958). He helped set up the new biochemistry department at Brandeis University and later accepted
an assistant professorship at the University of Louisville Medical School. In 1963, he helped set up the new biochemistry department at the University of Tennessee in Knoxville. He was the Head of the Department
of Biochemistry at Virginia Tech from 1970-1982 and then continued on as faculty in the department until he retired in 1998. He was appointed Emeritus Professor in 1998.
</p>

<p>An expert in the cell wall, Cecil Cummins joined the anaerobic bacteria laboratory of the veterinary science department at Virginia Tech in 1967. A native of Cork, Ireland, Cummins received his M.D. and Doctor of Science degree from Trinity College, University of Dublin. His major was bacteriology. During World War II, he served as a medical officer in the Royal Army Medical Corps. As a reader in bacteriology at the London Hospital Medical College, he taught bacteriology to medical, dental, and nursing students and supervised the activities of graduate students in bacteriology. 
</p>

<p>Ruben W. Engel earned the Ph.B. and the Ph. D. (1939) from the University of Wisconsin. He was the founding Head of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition in 1952 and served in that position until 1966.
He was Professor of Biochemistry and Nutrition and Nutritionist, Agricultural Experiment Station, 1952-1956. He was then Professor of Biochemistry and Associate Dean of Research and Graduate Studies, College of
Agriculture. He maintained an aggressive research program in nutrition, and in 1967, he became fully committed to the application of basic nutritional knowledge in the USAID-sponsored projects in the Philippines
until he retired in 1978. His many honors include the Elvehjem award for Distinguished Public Service in Nutrition and the dedication of Engel Hall in recognition of his service to the university and his
contributions as scientist and humanitarian.
</p>
<p>Robert M. Smibert was educated at the University of Connecticut (B.S., M.S.) and the University of Maryland (Ph.D.). He worked at Temple University Medical School and came to Virginia Tech in the Department of
Veterinary Science in 1960. He was in the group of faculty that founded the Anaerobe Lab, headed by W. E. C. Moore. He was Professor of Veterinary Science and Professor of Bacteriology. After his retirement in
1990, he was appointed Emeritus Professor.
</p>
<p>Everett Lee Wisman was the first faculty member hired by Dr. Engel in the new Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition. Wisman was educated at Virginia Tech (B.S., 1946), Cornell University (M.S.), and Penn
State (Ph.D.). In addition to his work in biochemistry, he was Associate Poultry Nutritionist, Agricultural Experiment Station, 1952-1956 and Associate Professor of Poultry Nutrition, 1956 to 1958.
</p>
<p>Roderick Whiter Young was the son of Harold Newell Young, head of the Department of Agricultural Economics and of the Department of Rural Sociology and later Director of the Agriculture Experiment Station.
Roderick Young was educated at Virginia Tech (B.S., M.S.). He was Assistant Chemist, Agricultural Experiment Station, 1949-1956, Associate Professor of Poultry Nutrition 1956-1958 and then Assistant Professor of
Biochemistry and Nutrition. After his retirement, he was appointed Associate Professor Emeritus, Department of Biochemistry.
</p>
<p>Source: John Hess, "Celebrating 50 Years of Accomplishment: Department of Biochemistry, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University," in Department of Biochemistry reunion booklet, Blacksburg, Virginia
Polytechnic Institute and State University, 2003.
</p>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Information about the faculty and history of the Department of Biochemistry
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Juel Albert Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bruce M. Anderson Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-3
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>R. W. Engel Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-4
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Robert M. Smibert Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-5
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>E. L. Wisman Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-6
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Roderick Young Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-7
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Cecil Cummins Oral History Interview Transcript
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-8
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Tapes
<unitdate type="inclusive">2001-02
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Juel Albert interview microcassette,
<unitdate type="inclusive">February 14, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bruce M. Anderson interview cassette, copy 1
<unitdate type="inclusive">February 7, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bruce M. Anderson interview cassette, copy 2
<unitdate type="inclusive">February 7, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-3
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bruce M. Anderson interview DAT master,
<unitdate type="inclusive">February 7, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-4
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>R. W. Engel interview cassette, copy 1
<unitdate type="inclusive">October 3, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-5
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>R. W. Engel interview cassette, copy 2
<unitdate type="inclusive">October 3, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-6
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>R. W. Engel interview DAT master,
<unitdate type="inclusive">October 3, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-7
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Robert M. Smibert interview cassette,
<unitdate type="inclusive">June 19, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-8
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Robert M. Smibert DAT master,
<unitdate type="inclusive">June 19, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-9
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Robert M. Smibert DAT safety copy,
<unitdate type="inclusive">June 19, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-10
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>E. L. Wisman interview cassette, copy 1
<unitdate type="inclusive">January 22, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-11
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>E. L. Wisman interview cassette, copy 2
<unitdate type="inclusive">January 22, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-12
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>E. L. Wisman interview DAT master
<unitdate type="inclusive">January 22, 2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-13
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Roderick Young interview cassette, copy 1
<unitdate type="inclusive">November 20, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-14
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Roderick Young interview cassette, copy 2
<unitdate type="inclusive">November 20, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-15
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Roderick Young interview DAT master
<unitdate type="inclusive">November 20, 2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-16
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Cecil Cummins interview cassette, copy 1
<unitdate type="inclusive">March 17, 2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-17
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Cecil Cummins interview cassette, copy 2
<unitdate type="inclusive">March 17, 2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-18
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Cecil Cummins interview DAT master
<unitdate type="inclusive">March 17, 2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-19
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Cecil Cummins interview DAT copy
<unitdate type="inclusive">March 17, 2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2-20
</container>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
