<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00291">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00291:: Wright Gilbert Papers, 1865-1907)//EN" "viblbv00291.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wright Gilbert Papers, <date>1865-1907</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Gilbert, Wright Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-064
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>08/20/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wright Gilbert Papers, <date>1865-1907</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-064
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Wright Gilbert Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1865-1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-064
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Papers of Captain Wright Gilbert, 6th New York Heavy Artillery, including Civil War diary, family photos, and correspondence. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Wright Gilbert Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Wright Gilbert Papers, Ms2008-064 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Wright Gilbert Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Wright Gilbert Papers commenced and was completed in August 2008. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Wright Gilbert was born in New York around 1836. He enlisted as a private in Company E of the 168th New York Infantry on January 23, 1863, and mustered out as a sergeant on October 31 of that year. In 1864, Gilbert enlisted in the 6th New York Heavy Artillery at Peekskill. He was mustered in as a first lieutenant in Company B on April 23, 1864. On February 14, 1865, he was mustered in as captain of Company G, then transferred back to Company B on March 5. He mustered out with the company at Washington D. C. on August 24, 1865. In post-war New York census records, Gilbert is listed as a grocer, living in Putnam and Westchester counties. He was a member of the Crosby Post (302) G.A.R. in Brewster, serving for a time as senior vice-commander. He married twice; with his first wife, Margaret Perry, he had three children: Alice, Herbert and Percy. He fathered four additional children with his second wife, Marion. Wright Gilbert died in 1906.
</p>
<p>The 168th New York was mustered into service at Newburgh, New York on January 23, 1863 for nine months' service. The regiment saw action at Walkerton and Yorktown, Virginia in early June and was mustered out at Newburgh upon completion of its term on October 31, 1863.</p>
<p>The 6th New York Heavy Artillery had been organized as the 135th New York Infantry in September 1862. The regiment was converted to an artillery unit later that year. Within the Railroad Division of the 8th Corps, Middle Department, the 6th served in the defense of the Upper Potomac beginning in January 1863. Later, the 6th participated in several battles, including the Wilderness, Spotsylvania Court House, and Cold Harbor before participating in the siege of Petersburg. The regiment was mustered out of the service on August 24, 1865 near Washington D. C.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains the papers of Wright Gilbert, a captain in the 6th New York Heavy Artillery during the Civil War. The collection includes Gilbert's Civil War diary, a few pieces of correspondence (including one wartime letter), a collection of family photos, and ephemera.
</p>
<p>Gilbert's diary spans the entire year of 1865. The diary commences with Gilbert noting the regiment's position ("Bermud[a] front Va near the Dutch Gap"). In very brief entries, Gilbert proceeds to record the activities of the day, such as picket and court-martial duties, together with observations on the weather and camp health. He notes military engagements (January 25, 1865: "Rebel Gun Boats com down the James an try to get by the obstructions") and significant events of the day, such as receiving word of Lee's surrender and Lincoln's death. He frequently records small financial transactions in the diary. Following the end of combat, Gilbert frequently mentions his work, cleaning the streets of Petersburg and completing the company's paperwork, as well as recreational activities such as baseball. Beginning in September, most of the entries seem to relate to the construction of Gilbert's house and store.</p>
<p>Accompanying the diary are several letters, including one written by Gilbert at Bermuda Hundred, Virginia on February 8, 1865. Gilbert describes weather conditions and his living quarters and mentions the many Confederate deserters crossing the lines. In an 1893 letter to his daughter, Gilbert describes some of his experiences in battle. The collection also contains a 1900 letter to Gilbert from fellow veteran of the 6th New York Artillery Henry Irving, in which Irving describes his home on the edge of the South Mountain battlefield  (the building having once served as General McClellan's headquarters) and a recent trip to Petersburg, comparing it to the city they had known in after the war. Also included are several letters received from M. W. Sutton following Gilbert's death and recounting experiences with Gilbert in the war. </p>
<p>Together with these materials is a brief description of Gilbert's service with the 6th and an inspirational printed circular letter regarding Colonel J. Howard Kitching and addressed to the 6th New York Artillery. Completing the collection is a set of 10 photos of members of the Gilbert family</p>
<p>The collection also contains a small collection of seemingly unrelated materials, including: an 1835 letter from H. Goddard of Portland, Maine to John S. [Barron?]; an 1823 letter to Captain Jamie Drysdale, of the 23rd Bengal Native Infantry in India, from a relative in Jerviston, Scotland, regarding his uncle's estate and other financial matters; an 1845 letter to Messrs. Lindsay &amp; Blackiston, of Philadelphia, from Jacob Ernst, of Cincinnati, regarding the purchase of books; an 1829 letter from C. Cushing of Newburyport, New Hampshire, to Thorndike Putnam, of Hampstead, New Hampshire, regarding a stone for the grave of Putnam's brother; an 1853 letter from E. Matson, of Wrightsville, Pennsylvania, to H. James, of Baltimore, regarding timber business; an 1853 letter from Partridge &amp; Goold, of New York to Mr. Waldron, regarding the sale of rollers; and an 1855 letter from J. H. Bumstead &amp; Company to William Waldron, of New Brunswick, New Jersey, regarding an order for a grounding machine part.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged by material type, then chronologically. Miscellaneous letters not directly related to the Gilbert family are found at the end of the collection.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive">1865-1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diary
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1865
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letters
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Wright Gilbert to Mrs. Miller
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1865
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Wright Gilbert to [Alice Gilbert]
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1893
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Henry Irving to [Wright Gilbert]
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1900
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>M. [Michael] W. Sutton to [Wright Gilbert]
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1905
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Frances Miller to Mr. Gilbert
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1907
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>M. [Michael] W. Sutton to [Percy] Gilbert
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Feb-Apr 1907
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<physdesc>[2 items]
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Circular addressed to the 6th New York Heavy Artillery
	<unitdate type="inclusive">[1865]
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Description of Wright Gilbert's military service
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="series">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Photographs
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Alice Gilbert Williams
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Carrie Lawrence
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Martha Smith
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Thurmul McMahon
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Margaret Perry Gilbert
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<physdesc>[2 items]
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>"Aunt Daisy"
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Wright Gilbert
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Wright Gilbert in G.A.R. uniform
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<physdesc>[2 items]
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Ann Maria Wright 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>"Helen and Leslie"
		<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous letters
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1823-1855
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
				<c03 level="item">
				<did>
				<unittitle>[J?] Drysdale to Captain Jamie Drysdale
				<unitdate type="inclusive">1823
				</unitdate>
				</unittitle>
				</did>
				</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>C. Cushing to Thorndike Putnam				
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1829
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>H. Goddard to John S. [Barron?]
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1835
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Jacob Ernst to Lindsay &amp; Blackiston
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1845
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>E. Matson to H. James
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1853
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Partridge &amp; Goold to Mr. Waldron
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1853
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>J. F. Bumstead &amp; Company to William Waldron
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1855
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
