<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00308">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00308:: William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography, ca. 1995)//EN" "viblbv00308.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1995</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Phillips, William Hewitt Autobiography
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-080
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10/6/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1995</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-080
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1995
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-080
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Autobiography (typescript draft) of William Hewitt Phillips, NACA and NASA Langley Research Center aerospace engineer; chief of Flight Dynamics and Control Division from 1970 to 1979. 
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography, Ms2008-080 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography was donated to Special Collections in 1997.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing and description of the William Hewitt Phillips Autobiography commenced and was completed in October 2008. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>William Hewitt Phillips, known more familiarly as Hewitt Phillips, was born in Merseyside, England, in 1918, but moved with his parents at age two to the United States. He studied aeronautical engineering at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), obtaining an S. B. degree in 1939 and an S.M. in 1940. 
</p>
      <p>In July 1940, Phillips entered commenced service with the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA), where he was assigned to the Flight Research Division at Langley Research Center (Hampton, Virginia), specializing in the study of aircraft flying qualities and stability. Within this broader assignment, Phillips' task involved the improvement of World War II military aircraft flying qualities. Following the war, Phillips' research related to the development of jet-powered fighter airplanes, supersonic airplanes, stability augmentation and its effect on pilot control, automatic control, and gust alleviation. In 1947, Phillips had married Viola Ohler, then head of Langley's editorial office. The couple had three children.</p>
      <p>As the U. S. space program commenced, Phillips became chief of the Space Mechanics Division, supervising research in the areas of space rendezvous, navigation, and lunar landing and developing flight simulators for the Gemini and Apollo programs. To train astronauts for lunar landings, Phillips developed the Lunar Landing Facility. He later served as an analyst and consultant in the development of the space shuttle.
</p>
      <p>Phillips retired from NASA in February 1979 but continued in the position of distinguished research associate, performing original research on solar-powered aircraft, propellers, airfoil design and wind-tunnel studies of the use of canard surfaces for the space shuttle. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains an autobiographical typescript draft by William Hewitt Phillips, an aerospace engineer for the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) and National Air and Space Administration (NASA) at Langley Research Center and chief of the Flight Dynamics and Control Division from 1970 to 1979. The text is a preliminary draft for Phillips' <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Journey into Aeronautical Research: a Career at NASA Langley Research Center</title>. The manuscript briefly follows Phillips' early life, interest in aviation, and education, then describes in more depth the author's work at NACA. Among the chapter headings are "Problems Encountered as a Result of Wartime Developments," "Accident Investigations," "NACA Flight Research on the Vought F8U-1 Airplane," and "Administration of the Langley Research Center." A final brief chapter, "Dawn of the Space Age," provides background on the formation of NASA in 1958.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Phillips, W. Hewitt, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Journey in Aeronautical Research: a Career at NASA Langley Research Center</title> (Washington, D.C.: NASA History Office, 1998). TL540 P54 J687 1998 Large Spec</p>
        <p>William Hewitt Phillips Papers. Lecture notes, reports, and memoranda, tracing the development of Phillips' theories while at Langley, spanning from his work on World War II-era aircraft to the early U. S. space program and beyond. Ms2005-019. 
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Autobiography
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1995
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
