<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-viblbv">viblbv00247</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Collection, <date era="ce"
            calendar="gregorian">1912-1938</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Anderson, Sherwood, Collection <num type="collectionnumber">Ms1973-002
          </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic
          Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Amy S. Vilelle, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4/15/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2019-05-01"/>
        <item>Notes added, formatting of series and subseries fixed. kad</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1912-1938</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">Ms1973-002
        </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Joyce Nester and Amy Vilelle, Special Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
      University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
        Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sherwood Anderson Collection, <unitdate
          type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1912-1938 </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms1973-002 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="DIGITAL CONTENT"> Some items in this collection have been digitized and are
          <extref xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Ms1973_002_AndersonSherwood_" xlink:show="new"
          >available online</extref>.</physdesc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 containers; 1.0 cu. ft. </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Correspondence among author Sherwood Anderson and family members,
        most notably letters written by Anderson to his daughter Marian, as well as some of his
        professional correspondence. Also includes research material about Anderson gathered by Ray
        White and notecards--compiled by Dr. Charles Modlin--documenting the annotations in the
        books within Special Collections' Anderson book collection. </abstract>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="100$a">Marian Anderson Spear, Ray White,
        Charles Modlin </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>Most materials have no restrictions. Some photographs cannot be reproduced, as they are
          copies from collections at other institutions such as the Newberry Library in Chicago,
          Illinois. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information:
          Sherwood Anderson Collection, Ms1973-002 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic
          Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The Sherwood Anderson Collection was created through various donations and purchases in
          1973, 1980, and 1997. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information </head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Sherwood Anderson Collection took
          place from October to December 2006. </p>
      </processinfo>
      <altformavail id="aspace_fe342602447b2036497e55c228eaf6d5">
        <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
        <p>Some items in this collection have been digitized and are <extref xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Ms1973_002_AndersonSherwood_" xlink:show="new"
            >available online</extref>.</p>
      </altformavail>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="aspace_2c2c69bae10b76befaa1d0ab75381ee7">
      <head>Biographical Information</head>
      <p>Sherwood Anderson (1876-1941) was born in the small town of Camden, Ohio to Irwin McClain
        Anderson (d.1919) and Emma Jane Smith (d.1895). While Anderson excelled as a student, he
        quit school at the age of 14 to help support his family, taking on a wide variety of jobs.
        After his mother’s death, he relocated to Chicago for the first time, working and taking a
        few night classes. He served briefly in Cuba during the Spanish-American War, but was sent
        there after combat had ended. A few months later, he returned to Clyde, then moved to
        Springfield, Ohio, in 1899, where he completed his senior year at Wittenburg Academy, a prep
        school. His graduation speech resulted in his being offered a job as an advertising
        solicitor and he moved to back to Chicago.</p>
      <p>In 1903, work travels took him to Toledo, Ohio, where he met Cornelia Pratt Lane, his first
        wife. The couple married in 1904 and had three children: Robert Lane (1907-1951), John
        Sherwood (1908-1995) and Marion (Mimi) (1911-1996). In 1906, they relocated to Cleveland
        when Anderson became the president of the United Factories Company, a mail-order firm. The
        following year he departed the company, took his family to Elyria, Ohio, and started the
        Anderson Manufacturing Co., another mail-order business.</p>
      <p>In 1912, Anderson suffered a nervous breakdown. He returned to Chicago yet again and began
        work writing advertising copy, as well as becoming part of the writer and artist scene of
        the city. In 1916, he divorced Cornelia Pratt and married Tennessee Mitchell, a sculptor. He
        also published his first novel, Windy McPherson’s Son, the first of three books in a deal
        with publisher John Lane. It was the beginning of his writing career. 1919 saw the
        publication of his short story collection, <title render="italic">Winesburg, Ohio</title>, one of his most well-known
        works. In 1924, he divorced Tennessee Mitchell and married Elizabeth Prall. They lived in
        New York and New Orleans, and traveled in Europe. With profits from his 1925 novel Dark
        Laughter, Anderson bought Ripshin Farm, later just Ripshin, of Troutdale, Virginia, as a
        summer home in 1926. He also acquired both local newspapers, the <title render="italic">Smyth County News</title> and the
        <title render="italic">Marion Democrat</title>. His son, Robert, helped with, and eventually took over management of the
        newspapers in 1929. Around the same time, Anderson began a tour of the south and its factory
        towns with Eleanor Copenhaver, which shaped several of his later non-fiction
        publications.</p>
      <p>In 1932, Anderson divorced Elizabeth Prall and the following year, married Eleanor
        Copenhaver (1896-1985). Southwest Virginia was a powerful influence on his later stories and
        novels. His life in and around Marion and Troutdale was the focus of his writing for the
        newspapers, as well. At the same time, he was still writing novels and short stories for
        magazines. In 1941, Sherwood and Eleanor Anderson left for a trip to South America. During
        the trip, after ingesting a toothpick, Anderson developed peritonitis and was hospitalized
        in Panama, where he passed away on March 8, 1941. He is buried in Round Hill Cemetery in
        Marion, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Over his lifetime, Anderson published 8 novels, 4 collections of short stories, 2
        collections of poetry, 1 collection of plays, and 12 works of non-fiction. Following his
        death, publishers and scholars have produced memoirs, critical editions, and several volumes
        of his collected letters. During his life, he was influential on the careers of William
        Faulkner and Ernest Hemingway, and maintained extensive correspondence and friendships with
        authors, artists, publishers, and critics (though he later wrote that he had given up
        reading reviews).</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection contains materials relating to author Sherwood Anderson. The collection is
        notable for the personal letters written by Anderson to family members. The largest group of
        letters (about 78 of them) were written to his daughter, Marian Anderson ("Mimi") Spear,
        between 1912 and 1938. While discussing personal and family matters, Anderson often speaks
        of his difficulties, failures and successes in publishing, and his interactions with other
        notable authors of the period. Transcripts of the letters, probably made by Anderson scholar
        and retired Virginia Tech English Department faculty member Dr. Hilbert Campbell, are
        invaluable as Anderson's handwriting can be very difficult to read. Additional
        correspondence includes letters between Anderson and other family members. Other
        correspondence reflects Anderson as a writer and includes a typescript of a speech delivered
        by Anderson to striking workers at Danville, Virginia in 1931.</p>
      <p>Supporting sets of documents include two researchers' work on Sherwood Anderson. Material
        donated by Anderson scholar Ray Lewis White, author of more than a dozen titles related to
        Anderson, includes photographs of Anderson and his family members, book covers from a
        project to gather covers (or reproductions of covers) not already in his collection, pages
        that were prepared for publication, and other materials used by White in his Anderson books.
        Notes made by Dr. Charles Modlin, a retired professor from the English Department at
        Virginia Tech and author of seven books about Anderson, are also included. The notes mostly
        concern the Anderson book collection in Virginia Tech's Special Collections and the books
        related to Anderson.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in two series. Each series is further subdivided by subject.</p>
      <p>Series I contains original personal and professional Sherwood Anderson documents as well as
        Anderson family materials. Included in the series are letters (both handwritten and typed)
        from Anderson to daughter Marian ("Mimi"), 1912-1938. These letters mostly relate to
        personal and family matters, though Anderson sometimes mentions interactions with other
        authors of the day, his travels, and the current state of his works in progress. (Notable is
        the affectionate tone of the letters.) Also included in this series are letters to Marian
        from other family members, as well as letters among other members of Anderson's family.
        Contained here among Anderson's professional correspondence are letters to John Road;
        correspondence with Lee Brian concerning Brian's effort to publish a short story;
        correspondence with Helen Candill regarding her request for an editorial for the Marion
        College <title render="italic">Squib</title>, December 1940; and an editorial titled "Chance
        Rules Us All," penned by Anderson on the verso of a letter. Also included is a typescript of
        a speech Anderson gave to striking cotton mill workers of Danville, Virginia in 1931.</p>
      <p>Series II contains research materials about Anderson collected by two researchers. Included
        are research and publication materials used in <title render="italic">Sherwood Anderson's
          Winesburg, Ohio</title>, edited and annotated by Ray Lewis White (Ohio University Press,
        1997). The materials consist mostly of undated reproductions of photographs of people and
        documents from the Newberry Library and other sources, and book dust jackets. (Included is a
        list of 39 microfilm reels and four reprinted theses and dissertations regarding Anderson's
        work that were transferred to the general library collection. Also in this series are a set
        of notes compiled by Charles Modlin on the annotations found in the Anderson book collection
        in Virginia Tech's Special Collections. The project was not completed and notes have been
        preserved in their original order within seven envelopes.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data </head>
      <relatedmaterial id="aspace_f0b4069f2efccd970d8ff93a4eb504cb">
        <head>Related Material</head>
        <p>Books by and about Sherwood Anderson stored in Special Collections and the general
          collection of Newman Library are cataloged and can be located using the library's <extref
            xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://addison.vt.edu/" xlink:title="catalog"
            >catalog</extref>.</p>
        <p>Microfilmed and bound theses and dissertations about Sherwood Anderson and his work that
          were collected by researcher Ray White are cataloged and can be located using the
          library's <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://catalog.lib.vt.edu/"
            xlink:title="catalog">catalog</extref>.</p>
        <p>A 1904 wedding dress that belonged to Sherwood Anderson's wife, Cornelia Platt Lane, is
          part of the <extref xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.ahrm.vt.edu/oris_glisson_costume_and_textiles_collection/index.html"
            xlink:title="Glisson Historic Costume and Textiles Collection">Glisson Historic Costume
            and Textiles Collection</extref> located in Virginia Tech's Wallace Hall.</p>
        <p>Special Collections houses multiple manuscripts relating to Anderson, including: </p>
        <p>Ms2011-004, Sherwood Anderson Photograph and Postcard, 1929, 1939. <extref
            xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
            xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv00773.xml"
            xlink:show="new">Finding aid available online</extref>. </p>
        <p>Ms2015-020, Welford D. Taylor Collection on Sherwood Anderson, 1918-2006, n.d. <extref
            xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
            xlink:href="http://search.vaheritage.org/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv01837.xml">Finding
            aid available online.</extref></p>
        <p>Ms2015-044, Sherwood Anderson Correspondence with Llewellyn Jones, 1916-1924, n.d.
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
            xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv01807.xml">Finding
            aid available online</extref>. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new"
            xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="https://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/84"
            >Digital images with transcripts </extref>available online. </p>
        <p>Ms2017-005, James T. Farrell Letters to Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson, 1952. <extref
            xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=vt/viblbv01848.xml"
            xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Finding aid available online</extref>. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname rules="aacr" source="naf">Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</persname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <blockquote>
        <p><emph render="bold">Some items in this collection have been digitized and are <extref
              xlink:type="simple"
              xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/Ms1973_002_AndersonSherwood_" xlink:show="new"
              >available online</extref>.</emph></p>
      </blockquote>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="SERIES I">Sherwood Anderson and Anderson Family Correspondence
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Family Correspondence</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to Daughter Marian ("Mimi") from Sherwood Anderson </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Postcard, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912
                  </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927
                  </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2 </container>
                <physdesc> [11 items] </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1929-1934 </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3-8 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938
                  </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Transcripts of letters </unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to Marian from Family Members </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>From Cornelia, John, and Robert Anderson, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                    era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927, 1932, n.d. </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Anderson Family Members </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Cornelia Anderson from John Anderson, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                    era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930 </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Russel Spear from John Anderson, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
                    calendar="gregorian">1932 </unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Mary Anderson from Sherwood Anderson, n.d. </unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Sherwood Anderson from Robert Anderson, n.d. </unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14 </container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Professional Correspondence </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letter to John Road, n.d. </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Brian Lee, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
                  calendar="gregorian">1931 </unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Helen Candill, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
                  calendar="gregorian">1930 </unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letter on The Royalton (New York) letterhead; salutation unintelligible,
                n.d. </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Typescript of speech delivered by Sherwood Anderson to striking cotton mill
                workers of Danville, Virginia, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
                  calendar="gregorian">Jan 13 1931 </unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="SERIES II">Research Materials about Sherwood Anderson</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Material from Ray White</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos and negatives of Anderson from boyhood through 1920s </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Anderson from 1930s and 1940s </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Eleanor Anderson </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Anderson's mother and father </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photocopies from father's and mother's diaries, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                  era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1872 </unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson's father and step-brother </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with siblings </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with his sons </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with the Copenhavers </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of Anderson article "Business Types" in <title
                  render="italic">Agricultural Advertising</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of "My Word to You," written by Anderson as an
                advertisement for his company, the United Factories Company </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos and tourist brochures for Clyde, Ohio; color photos of paintings by
                local artist Kenn Bower (commissioned by Robert Good) of the characters in <title
                  render="italic">Winesburg, Ohio</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12 </container>
              <physdesc> [26 items] </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copies of manuscript pages for <title render="italic"
                  >Winesburg, Ohio</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copies of maps of Clyde, Ohio and Winesburg, Ohio </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Sherwood Anderson, Gertrude Stein, maps of and buildings in Ohio
                towns, copies of Anderson's signature, and other items for use in the publication of
                White's book </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic plates removed from a copy of Anderson's <title
                  render="italic">Hello Towns</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of a document written by Anderson in New York, July 26,
                [19]32 </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Book dust jackets </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18 </container>
            </did>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Original dust jackets for <title render="italic">Sherwood Anderson's
                    Notebook,</title><title render="italic">Perhaps Women,</title><title
                    render="italic">The Face of America,</title> and <title render="italic">Home
                    Town</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Photographic copies of dust jackets for <title render="italic">Winesburg,
                    Ohio</title> and <title render="italic">Marching Men</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Photocopies of dust jackets for <title render="italic">Puzzled
                    America,</title><title render="italic">The Triumph of the Egg,</title><title
                    render="italic">Mid-American Chants</title> and <title render="italic">Death In
                    the Woods and Other Stories</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence about White's dust jacket project </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographs of interior and exterior of Anderson's home, <title
                  render="doublequote">Ripshin,</title> includes a photographic copy of a painting
                of Ripshin by Karl Anderson </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of a wood carving by Buck Fever </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:21 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson's grave monument </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:22 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo identified as <title render="doublequote">Labor
                parade</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:23 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous photographic negatives </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:24 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>List of dissertations and theses on Anderson (most cataloged and available
                in Newman library general collection) </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:25 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Material from Charles Modlin</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Notes by Modlin on annotations within Special Collections' Anderson book
                collection </unittitle>
              <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">2:26-32 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
