<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00311">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00311:: Christian Case Papers, 1905-1906)//EN" "viblbv00311.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Christian Case Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905-1906</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Christian Case Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms96-026
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10/21/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Christian Case Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905-1906</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms96-026
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Katie Cox, Special Collections Student Assistant; and John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Christian Case Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905-1906
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms96-026
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.2 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Collection of materials about accusations in student hazing incident at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, subsequent disciplinary actions by the university's faculty, actions taken by the board of visitors, appeal by Judge George L. Christian (father of one of the accused), and proceedings of a joint legislative committee investigating the incident and the college's faculty and administrative practices and policies.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Christian Case Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Christian Case Papers, Ms 96-026 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Christian Papers were donated to Special Collections.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Christian Case Papers commenced and was completed in February 2007. The materials had been previously housed within the McBryde Presidential Papers but were deemed to be more appropriately processed as a separate collection. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>On September 24, 1905, four cadets at Virginia Polytechnic Institute were accused of having violated college rules by hazing a freshman cadet named Bowly. The four upperclassmen were caught by Lieutenant-Colonel William Mayo Brodie in the act of "bucking" Bowly in his dorm room. A faculty meeting was called immediately to level charges of hazing against the students and to question them on the matter. Shortly after the incident, one of the boys, J. L. Brown, left the college. The other three students, William B. Christian, Julian M. Salley, and Rowland P. Eubank, were found guilty by the faculty and asked to leave the campus and barracks immediately.  Christian's father, Judge George L. Christian, appealed to the school's board of visitors, asking the board to persuade the faculty to reverse its decision. The board agreed to hold a hearing in December. Judge Christian presented a strong appeal, and the Virginia General Assembly appointed a joint committee of the house and senate to investigate the case. 
</p>
      <p>The committee met on campus on July 23, 1906. Claiming that he had obtained new information, Judge Christian acknowledged that his son and the others had been guilty of hazing and therefore withdrew his request for an investigation of the matter. As rumors and allegations against the school had become so widespread, however, the committee had been instructed to "investigate any other matter at the college which may seem proper." The committee dropped the Christian case from its agenda but proceeded for the next six days to examine and review the university's faculty and administrative practices. In issuing its final report, the committee ultimately vindicated the college's administration.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
 </head>
      <p>This collection contains materials regarding allegations of hazing perpetrated against a Virginia Polytechnic Institute freshman named Bowly by upperclassmen J. L. Brown, William B. Christian, Julian M. Salley, and Rowland P. Eubank. Most of the materials relate to the appeal by Judge George L. Christian to have the four students reinstated following their expulsion from the school and the many charges he leveled against the college's administration. The collection includes correspondence, as well as published copies of Christian's appeal to the Virginia Assembly and the faculty's response to Christian's allegations. Also included is a report from the college's board of visitors, requesting a legislative investigation. The collection also contains the lengthy proceedings and findings of a joint legislative committee that convened in Blacksburg to investigate not only the hazing incident but all aspects of the college's administration.
 </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
 </head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by document type, then chronologically. 
 </p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
 </head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence and transcripts
 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905-1906
 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-1
 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Answer of the Faculty of Virginia Polytechnic Institute to a Printed Letter of Hon. George L. Christian" 
 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905
 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-2
 </container>
          <physdesc>[2 copies]
 </physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Appeal from a Judgment of the Board of Visitors of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Affirming a Judgment of the Faculty, Refusing to Allow William B. Christian, Rowland P. Eubank and Julian M. Salley to Matriculate at Said Institute" 
 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 11 1906
 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-3
 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Board of visitors request for legislative investigation
 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1906?]
 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-4
 </container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Proceedings Had Before the Committee Appointed by the General Assembly of Virginia, to Investigate Charges Against the Virginia Polytechnic Institute" 
 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Jul 1906
 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-5
 </container>
          <physdesc>[2 copies]
 </physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
