<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00247">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00247:: Sherwood Anderson Collection, 1912-1938)//EN" "viblbv00247.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1938</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Anderson, Sherwood, Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms73-002
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Amy S. Vilelle, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4/15/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1938</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms73-002
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: 
</label>
          <item>Joyce Nester and Amy Vilelle, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sherwood Anderson Collection,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1938
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms73-002
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 containers; 1.0 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Correspondence among author Sherwood Anderson and family members, most notably letters written by Anderson to his daughter Marian, as well as some of his professional correspondence. Also includes research material about Anderson gathered by Ray White and notecards--compiled by Dr. Charles Modlin--documenting the annotations in the books within Special Collections' Anderson book collection. 
</abstract>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="100$a">Marian Anderson Spear, Ray White, Charles Modlin
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Most materials have no restrictions. Some photographs cannot be reproduced, as they are copies from collections at other institutions such as the Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Sherwood Anderson Collection, Ms73-002 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Sherwood Anderson Collection was created through various donations and purchases in 1973, 1980, and 1997.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Sherwood Anderson Collection took place from October to December 2006. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Sherwood Anderson (1876-1941) was born in the small town of Camden, Ohio to a large and impoverished family. An outstanding student, Anderson quit school at 14 to help support his family. In 1895 he volunteered for the Spanish-American War, then spent one year in Wittenburg College. He worked as a laborer in Chicago and later as a writer in an advertising agency. Unable to resist the urge to write and live a bohemian lifestyle, Anderson suffered an emotional breakdown and walked away from his family and his mail-order paint business. He had three children (two sons and a daughter) from his first marriage. Anderson eventually married three more times.</p>
      <p>Anderson published 27 books, plays, and volumes of short stories, along with numerous
articles in periodicals. Often controversial, he wrote about issues as diverse as the sexual awakening of adolescence to the alienation caused by industrialization. He was very active in the intellectual community of the day and was instrumental in helping both Faulkner and Hemingway to be published for the first time.</p>
      <p>Anderson wrote to his daughter from Kansas City in March, 1933, "As you know, my dear, I never did domesticate well," but he always maintained relationships with his children. Later in life, Anderson embarked on his fourth--and only successful--marriage, to Eleanor Copenhaver, a native of Marion, Virginia. They traveled extensively and spent summers on their rural farm, "Ripshin," near Marion. Anderson bought and operated both of Marion's local newspapers and eventually passed ownership along to his eldest son, Robert.</p>
      <p>Sherwood Anderson died on the first leg of a long-anticipated trip to South America. He developed
peritonitis and was hospitalized in Panama, where he passed away on March 8, 1941.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains materials relating to author Sherwood Anderson. The collection is notable for the personal letters written by Anderson to family members. The largest group of letters (about 78 of them) were written to his daughter, Marian Anderson ("Mimi") Spear, between 1912 and 1938. While discussing personal and family matters, Anderson often speaks of his difficulties, failures and successes in publishing, and his interactions with other notable authors of the period. Transcripts of the letters, probably made by Anderson scholar and retired Virginia Tech English Department faculty member Dr. Hilbert Campbell, are invaluable as Anderson's handwriting can be very difficult to read. Additional correspondence includes letters between Anderson and other family members. Other correspondence reflects Anderson as a writer and includes a typescript of a speech delivered by Anderson to striking workers at Danville, Virginia in 1931.</p>
      <p>Supporting sets of documents include two researchers' work on Sherwood Anderson. Material donated by Anderson scholar Ray Lewis White, author of more than a dozen titles related to Anderson, includes photographs of Anderson and his family members, book covers from a project to gather covers (or reproductions of covers) not already in his collection, pages that were prepared for publication, and other materials used by White in his Anderson books. Notes made by Dr. Charles Modlin, a retired professor from the English Department at Virginia Tech and author of seven books about Anderson, are also included. The notes mostly concern the Anderson book collection in Virginia Tech's Special Collections and the books related to Anderson.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in two series. Each series is further subdivided by subject.</p>
      <p>Series I contains original personal and professional Sherwood Anderson documents as well as Anderson family materials. Included in the series are letters (both handwritten and typed) from Anderson to daughter Marian ("Mimi"), 1912-1938. These letters mostly relate to personal and family matters, though Anderson sometimes mentions interactions with other authors of the day, his travels, and the current state of his works in progress. (Notable is the affectionate tone of the letters.) Also included in this series are letters to Marian from other family members, as well as letters among other members of Anderson's family. Contained here among Anderson's professional correspondence are letters to John Road; correspondence with Lee Brian concerning Brian's effort to publish a short story; correspondence with Helen Candill regarding her request for an editorial for the Marion College <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Squib</title>, December 1940; and an editorial titled "Chance Rules Us All," penned by Anderson on the verso of a letter. Also included is a typescript of a speech Anderson gave to striking cotton mill workers of Danville, Virginia in 1931.</p>
      <p>Series II contains research materials about Anderson collected by two researchers. Included are research and publication materials used in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Sherwood Anderson's Winesburg, Ohio</title>, edited and annotated by Ray Lewis White (Ohio University Press, 1997). The materials consist mostly of undated reproductions of photographs of people and documents from the Newberry Library and other sources, and book dust jackets. (Included is a list of 39 microfilm reels and four reprinted theses and dissertations regarding Anderson's work that were transferred to the general library collection. Also in this series are a set of notes compiled by Charles Modlin on the annotations found in the Anderson book collection in Virginia Tech's Special Collections. The project was not completed and notes have been preserved in their original order within seven envelopes.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Various materials related to the Sherwood Anderson Collection are available in other locations.</p>
        <p>Books by and about Sherwood Anderson stored in Special Collections and the general collection of Newman Library are cataloged and can be located using the library's <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://addison.vt.edu/">catalog</extref>.</p>
        <p>Microfilmed and bound theses and dissertations about Sherwood Anderson and his work that were collected by researcher Ray White are cataloged and can be located using the library's <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://addison.vt.edu/">catalog</extref>.</p>
        <p>A 1904 wedding dress that belonged to Sherwood Anderson's wife, Cornelia Platt Lane, is part of the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ahrm.vt.edu/oris_glisson_costume_and_textiles_collection/index.html">Glisson Historic Costume and Textiles Collection</extref> located in Virginia Tech's Wallace Hall.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="SERIES I">
            <emph render="bold">SHERWOOD ANDERSON AND ANDERSON FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE</emph>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
	</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to Daughter Marian ("Mimi") from Sherwood Anderson
		</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Postcard, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
			</container>
                <physdesc>
			[11 items]
			</physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1934
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3-8
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Letters, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Transcripts of letters 
			</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to Marian from Family Members
		</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>From Cornelia, John, and Robert Anderson,  
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927, 1932, n.d.
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Anderson Family Members
		</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Cornelia Anderson from John Anderson,
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Russel Spear from John Anderson,			
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1932
			</unitdate></unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Mary Anderson from Sherwood Anderson, n.d.				
			</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>To Sherwood Anderson from Robert Anderson, n.d.	
			</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14
			</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE
	</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letter to John Road, n.d.
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Brian Lee,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931
		</unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Helen Candill,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930
		</unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Letter on The Royalton (New York) letterhead; salutation unintelligible, n.d.
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Typescript of speech delivered by Sherwood Anderson to striking cotton mill workers of Danville, Virginia,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Jan 13 1931
		</unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="SERIES II">
            <emph render="bold">RESEARCH MATERIALS ABOUT SHERWOOD ANDERSON</emph>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>MATERIAL FROM RAY WHITE
	</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos and negatives of Anderson from boyhood through 1920s
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Anderson from 1930s and 1940s
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Eleanor Anderson
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Anderson's mother and father
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photocopies from father's and mother's diaries,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1872
		</unitdate></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson's father and step-brother
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with siblings
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with his sons
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson with the Copenhavers
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of Anderson article "Business Types" in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Agricultural Advertising</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of "My Word to You," written by Anderson as an advertisement for his company, the United Factories Company
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos and tourist brochures for Clyde, Ohio; color photos of paintings by local artist Kenn Bower (commissioned by Robert Good) of the characters in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winesburg, Ohio</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12
		</container>
              <physdesc>
		[26 items]
		</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copies of manuscript pages for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winesburg, Ohio</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copies of maps of Clyde, Ohio and Winesburg, Ohio
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photos of Sherwood Anderson, Gertrude Stein, maps of and buildings in Ohio towns, copies of Anderson's signature, and other items for use in the publication of White's book
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic plates removed from a copy of Anderson's <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Hello Towns</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographic copy of a document written by Anderson in New York, July 26, [19]32
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Book dust jackets
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18
		</container>
            </did>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Original dust jackets for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Sherwood Anderson's Notebook,</title><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Perhaps Women,</title><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Face of America,</title> and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Home Town</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Photographic copies of dust jackets for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winesburg, Ohio</title> and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Marching Men</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="item">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Photocopies of dust jackets for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Puzzled America,</title><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Triumph of the Egg,</title><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Mid-American Chants</title> and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Death In the Woods and Other Stories</title></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence about White's dust jacket project
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographs of interior and exterior of Anderson's home, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Ripshin,</title> includes a photographic copy of a painting of Ripshin by Karl Anderson
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of a wood carving by Buck Fever
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:21
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo of Anderson's grave monument
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:22
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photo identified as <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Labor parade</title></unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:23
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous photographic negatives
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:24
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>List of dissertations and theses on Anderson (most cataloged and available in Newman library general collection)
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:25
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>MATERIAL FROM CHARLES MODLIN
</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Notes by Modlin on annotations within Special Collections' Anderson book collection
	</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">2:26-32
	</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
