<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00397">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00397:: John H. Myers Memoir, 1888)//EN" "viblbv00397.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Myers Memoir, <date>1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Myers, John H. Memoir
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-061
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>04/13/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Myers Memoir, <date>1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-061
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John H. Myers Memoir
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1888
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-061
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War reminiscences of John H. Myers, a corporal in Company G, 55th Illinois Infantry, providing an overview of the common soldier's life, focusing particularly on the behavior of officers; food, water and clothing rations; marches; encampments; battle preparation; picket duty; battle and its aftermath. Accompanied by post-war carte-de-visite identified as Myers
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the John H. Myers Memoir must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: John H. Myers Memoir, Ms2009-061 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The John H. Myers Memoir was purchased by Special Collections.  
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the John H. Myers Memoir commenced and was completed in April 2009. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>John Henry Myers was born in Allegheny County, Pennsylvania around 1841. Census records indicate that Myers was the son of Henry H. and Maria Myers, and that he was living with his parents and siblings in Fulton County, Illinois by 1860. Myers enlisted in Company G of the 55th Illinois Infantry and was mustered in with the company on October 31, 1861. He reenlisted as a veteran at Chicago on April 12, 1864, and mustered out as a corporal with his regiment on August 14, 1865. After the war, Myers returned to Pennsylvania. By his own account, Myers began practicing medicine around 1871, though he did not obtain a degree in medicine until graduating from the Baltimore Medical School in 1883. John Henry Myers died at his home in Lewiston (Mifflin County), Pennsylvania on March 6, 1919.
</p>
<p>The 55th Illinois Infantry was organized at Chicago, Illinois and mustered into Federal service on October 31, 1861. The regiment, part of the Army of Tennessee, participated in many of the larger battles in the western theater of operations, including Shiloh, Champion's Hill, and the Siege of Vicksburg, as well as the Atlanta Campaign and Sherman's "march to the sea." The 55th Illinois was mustered out of service on August 14, 1865.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of a Civil War memoir written by John H. Myers, a corporal in Company G, 55th Illinois Infantry. Rather than a strictly personal narrative, Myers' memoir provides an overview of military operations as he experienced them. He writes at length on military personnel (never naming individuals, however), likening officers to monarchs and privates to serfs, detailing several instances of injustices and incompetence committed by the former. Also discussed, often in a somewhat humorous manner, are army rations. (The writer particularly describes the soldiers' experiences with hardtack and the worms with which one shipment became infested.) Myers relates several anecdotes about foraging and the procurement of food, water and clothing. In subsequent sections, the former corporal describes the day-to-day experiences of the soldiers within an invading army--marches, encampments, picket duty, and battle preparation--providing specific details on army procedures. In the final section, Myers takes the reader step-by-step through the experience of battle, then its aftermath, as the dead and wounded are removed from the field.
</p>
<p>Accompanying the memoir is a carte-de-visite, the verso containing--in modern-day ink pen--the name of Dr. J. H. Myers, Lewistown, Pa. The portrait was executed in the studio of F. R. M'Carthy of Philadelphia.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Memoir
<unitdate type="inclusive">1888
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
