<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00729">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00729::Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book,
            1897-1947)//EN" "viblbv00729.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book,
                        <date>1897-1947</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book <num
                        type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-077</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date>2010-10-26T11:33-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book,
                    <date>1897-1947</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-077</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2010 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Norfolk and Western Railway Company
                Mortgage Bond Book, <unitdate normal="1897/1947" type="inclusive" label="Date"
                    encodinganalog="245$f">1897-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms.2010.077</unitid>
            <physdesc id="ref6" label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
                <extent>1.0 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 box</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref5" label="Abstract">Ledger containing register of sales and transfers
                of the company's mortgage bonds, including names of purchasers with dates and bond
                numbers purchased.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
                <corpname source="naf">Norfolk and Western Railway Company.</corpname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict id="ref7" encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="ref8" encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Permission to publish material from the Norfolk and Western Railway Company
                    Mortgage Bond Book must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite id="ref10" encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book, Ms2010-077,
                    Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University,
                    Blacksburg, Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo id="ref12" encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>The Norfolk and Western Railway Company Mortgage Bond Book comprised part of a
                    larger railroad-related collection purchased by Special Collections in 2009. The
                    remainder of the acquisition of which this volume was a part was divided among
                    the Chapman J. French Papers (Ms2009-034), the Norfolk &amp; Western Railway and
                    Associated Companies Collection (Ms2009-037), the Norfolk and Western Railroad
                    Account Ledgers (Ms2010-075), and the Wayne Perkins Collection (Ms2009-078).</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo id="ref2" encodinganalog="583$a">
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing and description of the Norfolk and Western Railway Company
                    Mortgage Bond Book commenced and was completed in October 2010.</p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref4" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Historical Note</head>
            <p>The Norfolk &amp; Western Railway was established through a reorganization of the
                bankrupt Norfolk and Western Railroad in 1896, the latter company itself having
                arisen from the Atlantic, Mississippi &amp; Ohio Railroad, a successor to the
                Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad. In order to raise capital to pay off debt, meet its
                payroll and other obligations, and make continued improvements to the line, the new
                company issued $23 million in preferred stock, $66 million in common stock, and
                $62.5 million gold bonds paying four percent, secured through a consolidated
                mortgage to the Mercantile Trust Company of New York.</p>
            <p>Through expansion and various mergers, the N&amp;W grew to become a major U.S.
                carrier, serving 14 states. The company manufactured steam locomotives at its own
                Roanoke Machine Works (established in Roanoke, Virginia in 1882), and among the
                railroad's affiliated holdings were several hotels. In 1982, the N&amp;W combined
                with the Southern Railway to form Norfolk Southern Corporation.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref3" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection consists of a single ledger volume bearing the title "Norfolk &amp;
                Western Railway Co. Transfer Book No. 1 Register &amp; Ledger: Coupon First
                Consolidated Mortgage Four Per Cent Gold Bonds." The volume is dedicated to the sale
                and transfer of the company's gold bonds, secured through a consolidated mortgage to
                the Mercantile Trust Company of New York.</p>
            <p>The ledger is divided into several sections. The first section consists of a register
                of sales and transfers of coupon bonds--arranged in chronological order--bearing the
                names of purchasers, the numbers of the individual bonds purchased, and the dates of
                purchase in chronological order. Also affixed in this section are correspondence and
                legal documents relating to the transfer of indivdidual bonds. The second section
                appears to be an abstract of the first, listing in chronological order the date of
                purchase, name and residence of bondholder, amount paid for each bond, and date of
                transfer. The third section consists of an accounting record, providing dates,
                descriptions and amounts of transactions. The final section is arranged by name of
                bondholder and includes dates and amounts of bond transfers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Corporate Names:</head>
                <subject source="naf" encodinganalog="100$a">Norfolk and Western Railway Company</subject>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Local Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="local">Railroad</subject>
            </controlaccess>          
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Bond book, <unitdate normal="1897/1947" type="inclusive">1897-1947.</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid342001" type="Box" label="Box">1</container>                    
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
