<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00261">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00261:: Sue R. Preston Diary, 1907)//EN" "viblbv00261.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sue R. Preston Diary, <date>1907</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Preston, Sue R., Diary
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-034
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Emily K. Bibby, <date>07/02/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sue R. Preston Diary, <date>1907</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-034
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Emily K. Bibby,
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sue R. Preston Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-034
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Diary of Sue R. Preston, a young middle-class woman of Detroit, Michigan and later nurse-in-training at Sarah Leigh Hospital in Norfolk, Virginia, dated January 7, 1907 to October 13, 1907.  Describes her daily activities in Detroit, including shopping, reading, watching her favorite stage personalities at the Temple Theatre, and following the famous Thaw Murder Trial.   Enclosed are numerous newspaper clippings that pertain to the trial and theater gossip. 
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Dealer
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Sue R. Preston Diary must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Sue R. Preston Diary, Ms2008-034 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Sue R. Preston Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 1994. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Sue R. Preston was a middle-class woman born around 1885.  She spent much of her youth in Detroit, Michigan, where she lived with her parents and sister, Mary.  In late 1907, she enrolled as a nurse-in-training at Sarah Leigh Hospital in Norfolk, Virginia, the forerunner to Sentara Norfolk General Hospital. Following her graduation from nursing school, she continued to to work at Sarah Leigh Hospital and was employed there as late as 1930.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The diary of Sue R. Preston, kept between January 7 and October 13, 1907, primarily documents the day-to-day activities of a young, middle-class woman, her family, and friends, living in Detroit, Michigan.  Preston describes shopping, reading, household activities, and going to church and to the theater.  She names many of the popular stage personalities, melodramas, music, and novels of the day.  Descriptions include personal sightings of actresses such as Gertrude Coghlan and Julia Sanderson as they enter and exit the Temple Theater.  She also repeatedly mentions the Thaw Murder Trial, the "Trial of the Century," and at one point echoes public sentiment when she writes that she hopes Harry K. Thaw will be judged innocent.  Enclosed are numerous newspaper clippings of the trial, including several photographs and drawings of Evelyn Nesbit.  Also featured are gossip columns reporting marriages between actresses and society millionaires and picturing a variety of famous stage personalities such as Ethel Barrymore, Bessie Wynn, and Valerie Bergere.
</p>
<p>Beginning in October 1907, Preston's diary entries document her first few days as a nurse-in-training at Sarah Leigh Hospital in Norfolk, Virginia, the forerunner to Sentara Norfolk General Hospital.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Sue R. Preston Diary,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder"> 1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>

