<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00287">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00287:: Henry Howland Letter, 1862)//EN" "viblbv00287.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Howland Letter, <date>1862</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Howland, Henry Letter
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms91-016
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>08/13/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Howland Letter, <date>1862</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms91-016
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henry Howland Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1862
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms91-016
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft. 
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War letter of Henry Howland, quartermaster of the 51st Illinois Infantry, to his mother in Chicago. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Henry Howland Letter must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Henry Howland Letter, Ms91-016 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Henry Howland Letter was purchased by Special Collections in 1991, under the title "Mississippi River Letter." With new information regarding the author's identity, the item was renamed the Henry Howland Letter at the time of processing. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the Henry Howland Letter commenced and was completed in August 2008. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Henry Howland, the son of William Avery and Hannah Morton Howland, was born in Conway, Massachusetts, on March 20, 1827. A carpenter, Howland moved to Chicago in 1854 and worked in the lumber industry. He married Jane Elizabeth "Eliza" Gray in 1856; the couple would eventually have three children: Allen, Grace and George. 
</p>
<p>In September 1861, Howland joined the 51st Illinois and was commissioned the regiment's quartermaster. He left Chicago with the regiment on February 14, 1862. By the end of the war, Howland was a captain, serving as quartermaster for the Union Army's Department of Kentucky. His military service ended on January 19, 1867. </p>
<p>Howland returned to the lumber industry, then engaged in a short-lived mining operation in Leadville, Colorado. Howland apparently left Leadville around 1881 and fell into what his obituary described as "unsettled habits." He seems to have moved frequently, occasionally working for various Chicago businesses while his wife returned to live with her parents. In April 1883, Howland traveled from Buffalo to Rochester, New York on business for the National Blue Book of the shoe and leather trade of Chicago. Howland drowned in a canal there on May 6. He was buried in Chicago's Rosehill Cemetery. </p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains a letter written by Henry Howland, quartermaster for the 51st Illinois Infantry while aboard the the steamer <title render="italic">D. G. Taylor</title> on the Mississippi River. Writing on April 17, 1862 to his mother in Chicago, Howland makes general comments about his health, then notes that his regiment had captured 5,000 Confederates near Tiptonville, Tennessee. He then describes General Paine as "a most excellent man and a very fine officer," notes his division's position, and describes the fleet on which the troops embarked to journey southward on the Mississippi from New Madrid, Missouri. The army, Howland writes, is under orders to "proceed up the Tennessee to aid our troops at Pittsburg." He anticipates a journey of three to four days, followed by "one of the hardest fought battles that has yet been fought," and expresses his readiness to die in battle. He then relates a few anecdotes about his young son, including one in which the boy prayed, "Please God send some big Bears to eat the Rebels up." Howland concludes by stating the hopelessness of receiving a furlough and the likelihood of a lengthy war.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>"Col. Henry Howland" <title render="italic">Chicago Daily Tribune</title>, May 8, 1883.
</bibref>
<bibref>Fitch, John, <title render="italic">Annals of the Army of the Cumberland</title> (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1864).
</bibref>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive">1862
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
