<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv01030">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01030::Orrin Rankin Magill Papers, 1945-1972)//EN" "viblbv01030.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Orrin Rankin Magill Papers, <date>1945-1972</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Magill, Orrin Rankin Papers
                    <num type="collectionnumber">Ms1975-010</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2012 By Virginia
                        Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2012-06-21T16:15-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Orrin Rankin Magill Papers, 
                <date>1945-1972</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms1975-010</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2012 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Orrin Rankin Magill Papers, <unitdate normal="1945/1972" type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" label="Date">1945-1972 (Bulk, 1960-1972)</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms1975-010</unitid>
            <physdesc id="ref56" label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
                <extent>2.5 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>5 boxes</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref55" label="Abstract">Papers--including correspondence, memoranda, subject files, and printed materials--of Orrin Rankin Magill, graduate of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (class of 1913), VPI professor of philosophy and religion, and active participant in civic and political affairs of Blacksburg and Montgomery County, Virginia. Materials document Magill’s community activities, particularly as a member of the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors and the New River Valley Planning Commission.</abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref57" encodinganalog="506$a">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref58" encodinganalog="540$a">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from the Orrin Rankin Magill Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref59" encodinganalog="524$a">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Orrin Rankin Magill Papers, Ms1975-010, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref60" encodinganalog="541$a">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The Orrin Rankin Magill Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1975.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref61" encodinganalog="583$a">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Orrin Rankin Magill Papers commenced and was completed in June, 2012.</p>
        </processinfo>
            </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref54" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p>Orrin Rankin Magill, son of Robert N. and Ella F. Doty Magill, was born in Dayton, Tennessee on November 21, 1887. Magill later moved with his family to Alabama, and he graduated from Mississippi State University. While attending graduate school at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI) in 1911 and 1912, Magill served as secretary of the university's YMCA. Later, after obtaining a master's degree in education from Columbia University, Magill moved to China, where he served on the staff of the Chinese National YMCA. In September, 1915, he briefly returned to Southwest Virginia to marry Ellen Howe Bell (1893-1968), the daughter of Francis Bell. The Magills, who would eventually have six children, both worked in establishing a YMCA in Manchuria. Beginning around 1917, they lived for 25 years in Shanghai, where Magill served on the staff of the National Chinese YMCA and Ellen Magill worked as a teacher fo the American Community Church and worked with refugees. The Magills lived in New York during World War II then returned to China for a few years. After retiring from the YMCA in 1950, Magill served for five years as public relations director of the International Missionary Council.</p>
            <p>In 1955, the Magills moved to Blacksburg, Virginia, where Magill became active in civic, educational, and religious affairs. Magill served on the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors from 1959 to 1971 and is generally credited with leading efforts in passing several ordinances to govern the orderly development of the county during its period of rapid growth in the 1960s. During these years, Magill also served in numerous other boards and commissions, some as a direct result of his position on the board of supervisors, while others were separate from his work there. Among the other bodies on which Magill served were the New River Valley Industrial Commission, Mountain Empire Board of Mental Health Clinic, Virginia Polytechnic Institute Centennial Planning Committee, Associaiton of Virginia Counties, Showalter Memorial Hospital board of directors, New River Valley Airport Commission, and New River Valley Planning District Commission. (Ellen Magill also remained active in the community, working with the university's foreign students and serving on the board of directors of Showalter Memorial Hospital. In 1962, she was named Virginia's Mother of the Year.) Orrin Rankin Magill died on September 3, 1976, and was buried at New Dublin Presbyterian Church, Dublin, Virginia.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains the papers of Orrin Rankin Magill, a graduate student at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (1911-1912), long-time YMCA officer, and active local community leader in Blacksburg and Montgomery County, Virginia during the 1960s. The papers, containing correspondence, administrative documents, subject files, and printed materials, document Magill's many community activities, particularly his service on the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors and the New River Valley Planning District Commission.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref63" encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged in three series:</p>
            <p>Series I. Personal and Community Activities, 1945-1972. This series contains materials relating to the personal life of Orrin and Ellen Magill, as well as Orrin Magill's public activities apart from his official duties on the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors and the New River Planning District Commission. Included is a folder of personal photographs, correspondence, notes, and newspaper clippings; as well as folders relating to Magill's service in other organizations. Also included is a file of materials relating to Virginia Tech, where Magill served on the Derring Retreat Planning Committee and the Virginia Tech Centennial Committee. A folder labeled "Community and Political Activity" contains materials relating to Magill's political campaigns as well as notes, speeches, correspondence, and certificates relating to his other public activities. Among these are a few items relating to the Blacksburg Area Committee for Public Schools, formed in 1959 to address Virginia's public school desegregation controversy.</p>
            <p>Series II. Montgomery County Board of Supervisors, 1958-1972. The files in this series relate largely to issues confronting Montgomery County during Magill's service on the board of supervisors. Many of these issues relate to rapid growth in the county during the 1960s and Magill's advocacy for various ordinances to govern that growth. Broad topics include public health concerns, commercial and residential development, public services, planning and zoning, schools, taxes, and transportation. The files include such materials as correspondence, reports, notes, and printed materials. The series also includes materials relating to the board's routine administrative maintenance as well as county governance, including budgets. The series also includes files devoted to other bodies on which Magill had a seat due to his position on the board of supervisors. These include the New River Valley Airport Commission and the New River Valley Industrial Commission.</p>
            <p>Series III. New River Valley Planning District Commission, 1968-1972. This series largely consists of subject files maintained by Magill during his service on the New River Valley Planning District Commission. Included are files on health, housing, land use, law enforcement, and water/sewer services, represented in correspondence, reports, notes, and printed materials. The series also contains administrative files relating to the commission's work, as well as meeting minutes and financial records.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
        <separatedmaterial id="ref62" encodinganalog="544$a">
            <head>Separated Materials</head>
            <p>The following item was removed from the collection and added to the Historical Map Collection:</p>
            <p>
                <title render="italic">Montgomery County, Virginia, showing Primary and Secondary Highways</title>. Virginia Department of Highways, 1969. 19 x 24 in.</p>
        </separatedmaterial>
            </descgrp>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">Blacksburg (Va.)</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">Faculty</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">Montgomery County (Va.)</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">University Archives</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="local">University History</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Virginia Polytechnic Institute</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</subject>
                </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref5" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series I. Personal and Community Activities,
                    <unitdate normal="1945/1972" type="inclusive">1945-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref2" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Personal papers, <unitdate>1962-1970, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref3" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Community and personal activity, <unitdate>1945-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref4" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Council on Alcoholism, Delinquency, Crime and Poverty, <unitdate>1966-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref6" level="series">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Mountain Empire Mental Hygiene Service, <unitdate normal="1962/1968" type="inclusive">1962-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190004" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref7" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Showalter Memorial Hospital, <unitdate>1967-1970, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190005" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-5</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref8" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Virginia Tech, <unitdate>1958-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190006" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-6</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref9" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series II. Montgomery County Board of Supervisors,
                    <unitdate normal="1958/1972" type="inclusive">1958-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref10" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Administrative file, <unitdate>1960-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190007" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-7</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref11" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Air pollution, <unitdate>1964-1965, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-8</container>
                       
                        <physdesc id="ref12" label="Physical Characteristics">[2 folders]</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref13" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Annexation, <unitdate>1964-1970, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190009" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-1</container>
                        
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Budgets, <unitdate normal="1961/1972" type="inclusive">1961-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190010" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-2-3</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Census, <unitdate normal="1960/1971" type="inclusive">1960-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190011" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-4</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Civil defense, <unitdate>1961-1963, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190012" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-5</container>
                        
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Community Action Program, <unitdate>1965-1968, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190013" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-6</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Courthouse, <unitdate>1962-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190014" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-7</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Dogs, <unitdate>1962-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190015" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-8</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Electrical and plumbing ordinances, <unitdate>1970-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190016" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-9</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Financial statements, <unitdate normal="1965/1971" type="inclusive">1965-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190017" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-10</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Fire departments, <unitdate>1962-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190018" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-11</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref23" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Health Department, <unitdate>1963-1965, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190019" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-12</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Insurance, <unitdate normal="1965/1971" type="inclusive">1965-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190020" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-1</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>League of Virginia Counties, <unitdate>1961-1965, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190021" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-2</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Library, <unitdate>1962-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190022" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-3</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Magisterial districts, <unitdate>1965-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190023" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-4</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref28" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Miscellaneous local issues, <unitdate>1960-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190024" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-5</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref29" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>New River Valley Airport Commission, <unitdate>1960-1965, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190025" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-6</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>New River Valley Industrial Commission, <unitdate>1962-1971, n.d. </unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190026" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-7</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Planning Commission, <unitdate>1961-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190027" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-8</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Public Service Authority, <unitdate>1969, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190028" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-9</container>
                        
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Real estate tax appraisal, <unitdate>1960-1972, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190029" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-10</container>
                        
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Roads and bridges, <unitdate>1961-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190030" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-11</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Roanoke River watershed project, <unitdate>1959-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190031" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-12</container>
                      
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref36" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sales tax, <unitdate>1966, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190032" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-13</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Schools, <unitdate>1959-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190033" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-1</container>
                       
                        <physdesc id="ref38" label="Physical Characteristics">[2 folders]</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subdivision ordinances, <unitdate>1961-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190034" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-2</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Trailer ordinance, <unitdate>1962-1969, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190035" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-3</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref41" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Virginia Association of Counties, <unitdate>1966-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190036" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-4</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref42" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Welfare, <unitdate normal="1961/1971" type="inclusive">1961-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190037" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-5</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref43" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Zoning ordinances, <unitdate>1958-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190038" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-6</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref44" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series III. New River Valley Planning District Commission,
                    <unitdate normal="1968/1972" type="inclusive">1968-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref45" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Administrative file, <unitdate>1968-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190039" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-7</container>
                       
                        <physdesc id="ref46" label="Physical Characteristics">[2 folders]</physdesc>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref47" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Health Planning Advisory Council, <unitdate>1969-1970, n .d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190040" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-1</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref48" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Housing Committee, <unitdate>1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190041" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-2</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref49" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Land use plan, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190042" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-3</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref50" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Law enforcement plan, <unitdate>1970-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190043" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-4</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref51" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Water/sewer services, <unitdate>1969-1971, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190044" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-5</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Financial records, <unitdate normal="1970/1972" type="inclusive">1970-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190045" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-6</container>
                        
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref53" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Minutes, <unitdate normal="1969/1971" type="inclusive">1969-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1190046" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-7-8</container>
                       
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
