<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00713">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00713::Umbarger Family Correspondence, 1863-1867, 1870-1883)//EN"
            "viblbv00713.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Umbarger Family Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1867,
                        1870-1883</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Umbarger Family Correspondence <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-066</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010-10-18T12:29-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Umbarger Family Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1867, 1870-1883</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-066</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Julia Viets,</label>
          <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Umbarger Family Correspondence,
                    <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1867,
                    1870-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-066</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
        <extent>0.3 cu. ft.</extent>
        <extent>1 box</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language" encodinganalog="546">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">This collection contains correspondence relating to
                the Umbarger family from 1863-1867 and 1870-1883. Letters detail the family's
                experiences in the Civil War and their migration from Jonesville, Lee County,
                Virginia, to Coss County, Indiana, shortly after the war's close.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <famname source="local">Umbarger family</famname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref3" encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref4" encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from Umbarger Family Correspondence must be
                    obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref5" encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Umbarger Family Correspondence, Ms2010-066, Special Collections,
                    Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref7" encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Umbarger Family Correspondence was purchased by Special Collections in
                    2010.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo id="ref9" encodinganalog="583$a">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Umbarger Family
                    Correspondence was completed in October 2010.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="ref11" encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information</head>
      <p>In the decade following the Civil War, the Umbarger family moved from Jonesville in
                Lee County, Virginia to Cass County, Indiana. Lee County, VA, was founded in 1793
                and named after former Virginia Governor "Light Horse Harry," who was the
                father of Confederate General Robert E. Lee; the Umbargers left this county because
                of the lack of work opportunities.</p>
      <p>The letters of Martha or "Mattie" Umbarger to her brother represent a large
                portion of this collection. She was born in 1857 in Tennessee. At the time of the
                1880 US Census, she was 22 years old and resided in Deer Creek in Cass County,
                Indiana. One of her hobbies was writing poetry.</p>
      <p>Martha's father, Jonas Umbarger, was born in 1822 in Virginia. He was a farmer and
                married to a native of Tennessee. Despite his southern origins, he was a Union
                supporter during the Civil War, but disliked both Negroes and abolitionists.</p>
      <p>John D. Umbarger was a 2nd Sergeant in Company G of Virginia's 64th Mounted Infantry;
                later, he was a prisoner of war. John enlisted in the Confederate army on August
                3rd, 1862. He became briefly ill in June of 1863 and was given his sergeant status
                on May 16th, 1863. On September 9th, 1863, he was taken as a prisoner of war at
                Cumberland Gap. On the 24th, he was transferred to Camp Douglas, where he stayed
                until he took the oath on June 15th, 1865.</p>
      <p>Camp Douglas, where John was incarcerated by the Union army, was located in Chicago,
                Illinois. Founded in 1861, it originally was a training camp for Union soldiers, but
                was hastily adapted into a Confederate prison in 1862. Conditions were poor in terms
                of sanitation, camp construction, and weather. By the end of the war, about 26,060
                total rebels were imprisoned, 4,000 of which perished.</p>
      <p>1880 United States Census, Deer Creek, Cass County, Indiana; p.469A, Umbarger;
                familysearch.org; 1254268.</p>
      <p>Weaver, Jeffrey C. <title render="italic">64th Virginia Infantry</title>. The
                Virginia Regimental Histories Series. Lynchburg, VA: H.E. Howard, 1992. Print.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="ref13" encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains forty-five letters pertaining to the Umbarger family that
                migrated from Lee County, Virginia to Coss County, Indiana shortly after the Civil
                War. The dates of these letters range from 1863-1867 and 1870-1883, and are grouped
                into the following six sections of Civil War correspondence, correspondence between
                siblings John and Mattie Umbarger, general family correspondence, business
                correspondence, poems, and empty envelopes.</p>
      <p>The Civil War correspondence includes nine letters written between Umbarger family
                members and two letters written by Virginian confederate soldiers during the years
                of 1863-1867. Of the family letters, three are written between John Umbarger, a
                confederate soldier and his sister back home; four others are penned by Jonas
                Umbarger, a union supporter. In general, these letters discuss family and war news,
                food prices, the lack of work opportunities in Wythe County, and the hardships of
                soldier camp life. In a letter dating April 25, 1863, John Umbarger tells his sister
                that he has been barefoot for three weeks because of the difficulties involved in
                obtaining shoes. The letters also express a range of sentiments, from homesickness
                to the more unpleasant-- such as those found racist remarks. In a letter dated May
                6th, 1866, Jonas Umbarger remarks to his sons and sister: "I am a union man [...]
                Lord save us from the abolitionist and from negro equality but I hope meanwhile have
                peace and constitution."</p>
      <p>The general Umbarger family correspondence includes 38 letters written between
                siblings, John and Mattie, as well as letters between other family members and
                friends. These letters discuss family events, visits and other current events. In a
                letter to brother dated October 24th, 1880, Mattie complains about current politics:
                "ever man and woman and child that is bige enough to talk goes to Buraleyes &amp;
                hollow for garfield and hancock I get tired enoough having them hollow-going along."
                Another interesting letter in this section contains a prose poem about a love gone
                sour in which various ingredients are given relationship attributes, such as
                "domestich industry forget me not true love" denotes "flax."</p>
      <p>There are three letters in business correspondence. Written in 1870, the first is
                written by a Margaret Reder and addressed to John Umbarger at Bunker Hill, Virginia;
                it discusses the terms of renting a farm. The second one is written in Howard,
                Indiana in 1880 by Daniel Mcbolle and talks about terms of rent and job prospects.
                The third is a notice of a debt repaid and was written in Illinois a year later.</p>
      <p>Of the seven short and simple poems in this collection, four are written in 1881 by
                Mattie Umbarger and focus on religious and romantic themes. One poem dated May 27th
                reads: Press forward, press forward <blockquote><p>The Prize is in view, A crown of bright glory is waiting for you.</p></blockquote> The other three poems are all undated and composed by non-family
                members.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="ref14" encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged by material type into six sections: Civil War
                correspondence, correspondence between siblings John and Mattie Umbarger, general
                family correspondence, business correspondence, poems, and empty envelopes.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms:</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="ref17" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Civil War correspondence, <unitdate normal="1863/1867" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1867.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid294007" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref18" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John &amp; Mattie Umbarger correspondence, <unitdate normal="1877/1883" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1877-1883.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid294008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref19" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>General family correspondence, <unitdate normal="1876/1883" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876-1883.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid294009" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref20" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Business correspondence, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870,
                        1880-1881.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid294010" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref21" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Poems, <unitdate normal="1881/1881" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid294011" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref22" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Empty envelopes.</unittitle>
          <container id="cid294012" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
