<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00674">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00674:: R. Baxter Brown Diary, 1864)//EN" "viblbv00674.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the R. Baxter Brown Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Brown, R. Baxter Diary
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-043
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>06/22/2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the R. Baxter Brown Diary, <date>1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2010-043
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">R. Baxter Brown Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2010-043
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War Diary of R. Baxter Brown, lieutenant in Company I, 11th New Hampshire Infantry. 
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Creator
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the R. Baxter Brown Diary must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: R. Baxter Brown Diary, Ms2010-043, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The R. Baxter Brown Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2010. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the R. Baxter Brown Diary commenced and was completed in June 2010. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>R. Baxter Brown was born in Candia, New Hampshire. On August 15, 1862, he enlisted in Company I of the 11th New Hampshire Infantry, which mustered into Federal service on September 2. Appointed a first sergeant, the 21-year-old Brown was wounded in the right breast and shoulder at the Battle of Fredericksburg. After convalescing at Washington D.C. and Philadelphia, Brown received a medical discharge from the service. He rejoined his regiment at Knoxville, however, and at the Battle of the Wilderness temporarily assumed command of Company I following the wounding of the company's captain. At the Battle of Spotsylvania, Brown was wounded in the left hand and was sent to St. John's Hospital in Annapolis, Maryland. He was commissioned a second lieutenant on July 25, 1864 and rejoined his regiment on September 11. At the Battle of Pegram Farm (September 30), he received a serious wound to his left thigh and a slight wound to  his neck. He rejoined the regiment in mid-November and served until the regiment was mustered out of service on June 4, 1865. Following the war, Brown worked as a shoemaker. The 1870 census records 29-year-old Baxter Brown living in Haverhill, Massachusetts with 28-year-old Nancy Baxter, and a four-month-old baby, Bertha L. Baxter. In the 1880 census, Richard B. Baxter, a 39-year-old shoe contractor, is listed among the residents of Haverhill. Also in the household is 10-year-old daughter Bertha and a six-year-old son, Lutten. Baxter was still living in Haverhill as of 1891 and is reported among those attending regimental reunions as late as 1896. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of the Civil War diary of Lieutenant R. Baxter Brown of Company I, 11th New Hampshire Infantry. Brown's diary notes weather conditions; his regiment's movements through Tennessee, Kentucky, Maryland, and northern Virginia; the departure of some regiments; the re-enlistment of others; and the arrival of new recruits. During July, Brown's diary entries frequently mention actions relating to Jubal Early's raid on Washington D.C. On July 13 he writes, "All business suspended and citizens called to defend the city which is under Martial law." The following day, he reports the presence of three gunboats in the Potomac River. The diary proceeds through the remainder of the year and is appended with a two-page description of his regiment's actions at the Battle of Pegram's Farm.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Cogswell, Leander W., <title render="italic">A History of the Eleventh New Hampshire Regiment, Volunteer Infantry in the Rebellion War, 1861-1865</title> (Concord, N.H.: Republican Press Association, 1891).
</bibref>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
<subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive">1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
