<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00366">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00366:: Charles F. McKenna Collection, 1861-1998)//EN" "viblbv00366.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Charles F. McKenna Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1998</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">McKenna, Charles F. Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-031
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Kira A. Dietz, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">03/10/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-23">2014-01-23</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Charles F. McKenna Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1998 (Bulk 1861-1913)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-031
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Charles F. McKenna Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1913
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-031
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 box; 0.3 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Diaries, papers, and published materials related to Charles F. McKenna's service in the 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers, during the Civil War.  
</abstract>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Donor
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Charles F. McKenna Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Charles F. McKenna Collection, Ms2009-031 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Charles F. McKenna Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2009. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Charles F. McKenna Collection commenced and was completed in March 2009. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Charles F. McKenna was born in Pittsburgh, PA, on October 1, 1844 to James and Anna McKenna. He and his twin brother were the youngest of six children, born shortly before their father's death in 1846. McKenna attended schools in Pittsburgh until, at age 14, he apprenticed to a lithographer, due to his interest in sketching. He would continue to sketch throughout his life, even providing illustrations for a published history of the 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers he edited.
</p>
      <p>McKenna attempted to enlist in the 63<emph render="super">rd</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers, in August of 1861, but was forced to postpone, owing to his mother's disapproval and her subsequent poor health. In July 1862, at the age of 16, he joined Company E, 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers. Less than a month after enlisting, McKenna's regiment was on the front lines at Antietam. Over the next three years, he would participate in some of the most pivotal battles of the Civil War: Gettysburg, Chancellorsville, Mine Run, Fredericksburg, and Appomattox. During the long winter encampments, he continued his education with Sergeant George P. Fulton who, folllowing the war, would serve as principal of the Highland Public Schools in Pittsburgh. McKenna served nearly three full years, obtaining leave only once, in January 1865. After his discharge in June 1865, he returned home to Pittsburgh.</p>
      <p>
In 1869, following several years work in a Pittsburgh law firm, Charles McKenna was admitted to the Allegheny County bar. He was an early memeber of the Allegheny County Bar Association, as well as a charter member of the Pennsylvania State Bar Association. On October 1, 1872, he married Miss Virginia White. The couple never had any children.</p>
      <p>
While serving as a Pennsylvania Supreme Court judge in 1904, he was offered the Judgeship of the United States District Court of Porto Rico [sic]. McKenna initially declined the offer, but soon changed his mind. He established the first Elks lodge in Porto Rico [sic] while living in San Juan. He returned to Pittsburgh in late 1906, unable to adapt to the climate. In addition to practicing law again, this time with his nephews, McKenna began to work extensively with Civil War organizations.</p>
      <p>
First appointed to the Gettysburg Battlefield Commission, he went to to serve as its president for many years. He wrote articles for the Western Pennsylvania Historical Society on topics in local history and the Civil War. In 1910, he edited and illustrated a detailed history of the 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, titled <title render="italic">Under the Maltese Cross, from Antietam to Appomattox, the Loyal Uprising in Western Pennsylvania, 1861-1865; Campaigns 155th Pennsylvania Volunteers Regiment, Narrated by the Rank and File</title>. He also created an index of Pennsylvania soldiers who participated in the Battle of Gettysburg for the Pennsylvania Historical Society. At the Battle of Gettysburg 50<emph render="super">th</emph> Reunion in 1913, he and other survivors received commemorative Congressional Medals of Honor for service.</p>
      <p>
In 1911, then-Pennsylvania Governor John K. Tener appointed McKenna to the newly established County Court of Allegheny County. In 1921, he was elected to complete a second ten-year term. His service was cut short by his death on December 3, 1922.</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <head>
Additional information from:</head>
        <item>Fleming, George Thornton. <title render="italic">History of Pittsburgh and Environs, from Prehistoric Days to the Beginning on the American Revolution</title>. 4 vols. New York: The American Historical Society, 1922.</item>
        <item>Eastman, Frank M. <title render="italic">Courts and Lawyers of Pennsylvania: A History</title>. 3 vols. New York: The American Historical Society, 1922.</item>
        <item>"Charles Francis McKenna." United States District Court of Puerto Rico. <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.prd.uscourts.gov/CourtWeb/bios_judge_McKenna.aspx">http://www.prd.uscourts.gov/CourtWeb/bios_judge_McKenna.aspx</extref>.</item>
      </list>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>
The Charles F. McKenna Collection contains diaries, personal papers, and published materials relating to McKenna's Civil War service. The materials date from 1861 to 1998 (bulk 1861-1913). The collection is divided into two series: Personal Papers and Published Materials.</p>
      <p>The Personal Papers include McKenna's original diaries (1862-1865); bound photocopies of the diaries; transcriptions on CD-rom; McKenna's discharge papers; photographs of two generals; and a letter regarding the publication of <title render="italic">Under the Maltese Cross, from Antietam to Appomattox, the Loyal Uprising in Western Pennsylvania, 1861-1865; Campaigns 155th Pennsylvania Volunteers Regiment, Narrated by the Rank and File</title>. The Published Materials include two articles featuring McKenna's letters; a map of McKenna's travels; an issue of <title render="italic">Civil War News</title>; and Civil War sheet music.</p>
      <p>Elements within the diaries suggest they may not have been recorded at the time of the war, but instead, written down at a later date. The loss of chronology and the absence of entries for large periods of time in 1864 hint at this. Several notes in the text also imply additions at another date. After the entry for June 23<emph render="super">rd</emph>, the following appears: "[N.B. Here my notes ceased, as well as my dates and for the remainder of June and July I will be obliged to record the dates as well as facts from memory][C.F. McKenna. Aug. 1863]." In a lengthy entry for November 30<emph render="super">th</emph>, an asterisk note reads, "Have since learned that it was Genl. Warren made this report to Genl. Meade." At the very least, it appears additions were made to the diaries over time.</p>
      <p>Additional materials in this collection include two published titles which are cataloged and located in the Rare Book Collection, a Tower rifle and bayonet, and a Solingen cavalry saber. See the "Separated Materials" section of this finding aid (below) for further information.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged in the following series:</p>
      <p>Series I: Personal Papers</p>
      <p>
The Personal Papers largely surround the diaries and McKenna's service in the 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers. McKenna's regiment was present at many noteworthy Civil War battles and the diaries mention several, including Gettysburg and Appomattox. The diaries contain details of McKenna's daily life as a soldier and his self-proclaimed "adventures," news from home, stories about the people he met, the loss of friends, and the treatment of soldiers in different parts of the mid-Atlantic region. He also comments frequently on changes in leadership of his regiment and the reception of various generals and officers in camp. Both diaries contain sketches by McKenna of people and places he encountered. While he does mention being near or taking part in some significant battles, details of the battles themselves are limited.</p>
      <p> The final pages of the first diary present a record of the dead, wounded, discharged, transferred, sick, deserters, and promoted in the regiment. The final pages of the second diary focus on McKenna's money spent on clothing, money received from home, and other financial information. Some of the second diary loses its linear chronology, and there are only a few entries for the entire year of 1864.</p>
      <p> The photographs are of Major General John Buford and Brigadier General David McMurtrie Gregg. The letter comes from Brigadier General David McMurtrie Gregg, upon the receipt of a gift copy of McKenna's regimental history. This series is arranged chronologically.</p>
      <p>Series II: Published Materials</p>
      <p>
The Published Materials include two articles from <title render="italic">Soldier Life</title>, Alexandria, VA: Time-Life Books, 1996, featuring McKenna's letters; a 1962 map with McKenna's Civil War travels marked in pen; a 1998 issue of <title render="italic">Civil War News</title>; and a collection of bound sheet music from before 1870. One article talks about boxing for recreation in camp and other talks about the relationship between soldiers, sutlers, and paymasters. The collection of music has a number of names inscribed on the inside cover and initial pages. This series is arranged chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material</head>
        <p>For information on the 155<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Pennsylvania Infantry, see:</p>
        <p><list>
          <item>Smith, Robin, and William Younghusband. <title render="italic">American Civil War Zouaves</title>. Elite series, No. 62. London: Osprey, 1996.</item>
          <item>United States. <title render="italic">Under the Maltese Cross, Antietam to Appomattox, The Loyal Uprising in Western Pennsylvania, 1861-1865; Campaigns 155th Pennsylvania Regiment</title>. Pittsburg, Pa: 155th Regimental Association, 1910. <lb/>E527.5 155th .P466 1910 Spec Civil War</item>
        </list></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Separated Material</head>
        <p>The following items were transferred to the Rare Book Collection:</p>
       <p> <list>
          <item>McKenna, Charles F., ed. <title render="italic">Under the Maltese Cross, from Antietam to Appomattox, the Loyal Uprising in Western Pennsylvania, 1861-1865; Campaigns 155th Pennsylvania Volunteers Regiment, Narrated by the Rank and File</title>. Pittsburg, PA: The 155th Regimental Association, 1910. This title is also available online at the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/text-idx?idno=00aee8379m;view=toc;c=pitttext">Historic Pittsburgh Full-Text Collection</extref>.<lb/>E527.5 155th .P466 c.2 Spec Civil War. </item>
          <item>Walton, William. <title render="italic">The Army and Navy of the United States, from the Period of Revolution to the Present Day</title>. Edition de Luxe. 11 vols. Philadelphia: George Barrie, 1890. Edition is numbered 185 and subscribed to "Mr. Charles F. McKenna."<lb/> UA23 .W243 Spec Folio </item>
        </list></p>
        <p>The following items are located in Oversize:</p>
        <p><list>          
          <item>Tower rifle and bayonet</item>
          <item>Solingen cavalry saber with leather harness </item>
        </list></p>
        <p>The following item is located in the Accession File:</p>        
        <p><list>
          <item>A second copy of the diary transcriptions on CD-rom.</item>
        </list></p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Personal Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1913</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles F. McKenna diaries, September 3, 1862 to September 3, 1863 and September 2, 1963 to June 5, 1865.
              </unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Spiral bound photocopy of first diary, 1862-1863.</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="series">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Spiral bound photocopy of second diary, 1863-1865.</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>CD-rom copies of diaries in Microsoft Word (.doc) and Rich Text Format (.rtf).</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>McKenna's discharge papers, June 2, 1865.</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Major General John Buford, 1863, and Brigadier General David McMurtrie Gregg, n.d.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter from General David McMurtrie Gregg regarding receipt of a copy of <title render="italic">Under the Maltese Cross, from Antietam to Appomattox</title>, May 24, 1913.</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Published and Printed Materials
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Bound Civil War sheet music, 1869(?).</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, and West Virginia map with McKenna's Civil War travels marked in pen, 1962.</unittitle>
	
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Two excerpts from: <title render="italic">Soldier Life</title>. Alexandria, VA: Time-Life Books, 1996. Features McKenna's letters.	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><title render="italic">Civil War News</title>, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February-March 1998.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
