<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01863">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01863::John Taylor Wood Correspondence, 1865)//EN" "viblbv01863.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the John Taylor Wood Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1865</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Wood, John Taylor Correspondence <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2017-016</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2017 By Virginia Tech. All rights
          reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace <date era="ce"
        calendar="gregorian">2017-06-23 12:48:51-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>John Taylor Wood Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
        Ms2017-016</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz, Archivist,</label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
        Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">John Taylor Wood Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1865/1865">1865</unitdate></unittitle>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname source="naf">Wood, John Taylor, 1830-1904</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2017-016</unitid>
      <physdesc altrender="whole" label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.1 Cubic Feet</extent>;
        <extent altrender="carrier">1 folder</extent>
      </physdesc>      
      <abstract id="aspace_cc5f3445ff1fda8d2ad28ff974d1e5e4">The John Taylor Wood Correspondence
        consists of ten letters written by John Taylor Wood between April and July of 1865. Nine of
        the letters were written to his wife, Lola, who was living in and around Richmond at the
        time; the tenth item is a small note requesting that enclosed letters be forwarded to Lola.
        Wood was the nephew and military aide to Confederate President Jefferson Davis.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
    <accessrestrict id="aspace_ac940948867e359adb3b9e85e3a68a25">
      <head>Access Restrictions</head>
      <p>The collection is open for research.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="aspace_53b1c2418429a35378b469e43830e50b">
      <head>Use Restrictions</head>
      <p>Permission to publish material from John Taylor Wood Correspondence must be obtained from
        Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="aspace_0e09465e58fb6b3b8988c48fad36105c">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: John
        Taylor Wood Correspondence, Ms2017-016, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg,
        Va.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="aspace_927a711ad953ba315aa1715fae5e842e">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>The John Taylor Wood Correspondence was purchased by Special Collections in April 2016.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="aspace_5f9eb4a0c9d7ff3f814856c7ad908d8f">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the John Taylor Wood Correspondence was
        completed in June 2017.</p>
    </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_841a305790b085afbb816dc496c7388a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The John Taylor Wood Correspondence consists of ten letters written by John Taylor Wood
        between April and July of 1865. Nine of the letters were written to his wife, Lola, who was
        living in and around Richmond at the time; the tenth item is a small note requesting that
        enclosed letters be forwarded to Lola. Wood was the nephew and military aide to Confederate
        President Jefferson Davis. His letters chronicle his flight with Davis from Richmond to
        points further south and later, his establishing a home in Halifax. Wood was captured with
        Davis and others in May of 1865, but was able to bribe a captor and flee to Cuba. He made
        his way from Havana to Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada, in June, where Lola and their two
        children eventually met him. </p>
      <p>The majority of Wood's date to April of 1865 and include news of himself, his uncle, and
        the officers around them. He shared opinions on his fellow officers and Confederates, whose
        loyalty begins to wane before his, as he wrote on April 24th from Charlotte, North Carolina: </p>
      <p><emph render="italic">If I have understood correctly the terms of the negotiation now pending it is a
        eventual surrender of what we have been contending for during the past four years, our
        independence: I care not what side issues may be granted. or what else they may concede,
        with out freedom it amounts to nothing. If I know myself, I never will consent to these
        terms &amp; Uncle never will, but we are almost alone. Cabinet ministers, generals,
        soldiers, citizens &amp; indeed 99 out of a hundred are in favor of these.</emph></p>
      <p>He tells Lola of their travels further south and write extensively about their children,
        how she should read his letters to them (in particular their eldest, Zachary Taylor Wood),
        and how much he misses them. He also keeps her updated on the whereabouts of family and
        friends, when he knows it. Shortly after the last letter written in April, Wood was captured
        with Davis in Georgia. As the story goes, with his uncle's permission, he bribed a Union
        officer to escape, and was able to flee to Cuba. In a small note, dated June 1865, he wrote
        to a friend, Jim (referenced later), asking him to forward an enclosed letter to Lola. </p>
      <p>The last two letters were written in mid-July from Montreal. Both talk about his own
        travels through Canada from Halifax to Montreal (though they would eventually settle in
        Halifax). He also writes on rumors of his own escape: </p>
      <p><emph render="italic">I hope my name will not appear again at present in the papers, I am sorry to see
        it &amp; will avoid it if possible, I am almost tempted to assume some other name, but will
        not do it, I have done nothing yet to be ashamed of. However I am told there is an account
        of my escaping from a Yankee Cruiser in some of the papers, where I am represented as having
        shown false or bogus papers and thus avoided capture, I have not seen it, but it is not
        necessary to tell you dear that it is not true.</emph></p>
      <p>Part of the penultimate letter surrounds logistics and plans for her travels to meet him
        and both of the final letters contain much of his concerns for her welfare and that of the
        children.</p>
      <p>Transcripts of the letters are included with the collection.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <bioghist id="aspace_b9f365a81edce70d9371792c5e68ac1e">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>John Taylor Wood (1830-1904) was born at Fort Snelling, Northwest Territory (modern day
        Minnesota, near St. Paul), on August 13, 1830. His father, Robert Crooke Wood, was an army
        surgeon. His mother, Anna Mackall Taylor Wood, was the daughter of Zachary Taylor (who would
        later become the 12th President of the United States). John Taylor Wood was the oldest of
        their children. His mother's sister, Sara Knox Taylor (1814-1835), was Jefferson Davis'
        first wife. Wood would later serve as the military aide to his uncle during the Civil War. </p>
      <p>Wood was raised in parts of the Midwest and in 1847, joined the U. S. Navy as a midshipman,
        serving around South America and Mexico during the Mexican War. He graduated from the U. S.
        Naval Academy in 1852 and continued to serve in the military, receiving several promotions.
        IN 1855, he met Lola MacKubin (1835-1909) and they married in November 1856. </p>
      <p>Just prior to the Civil War, Wood taught at the Naval Academy, but he resigned in April
        1861. In October 1861, he was commissioned in the Confederate Navy. By 1865, he was promoted
        to the rank of captain and in the last few months of the war, he accompanied his uncle in
        his flight south. Wood was taking prison with Davis and others in Georgia in early May 1865,
        but was able to escape (likely by bribing his captors), making his way to Havana, Cuba, and
        from there to Halifax, Nova Scotia. In July of 1865, Lola and their two children met him
        there. </p>
      <p>In Canada, Wood established himself as a merchant and business man, in partnership with a
        former blockade runner, John Wilkenson. Wood and his wife lived the rest of their lives in
        Canada, dying in 1904. Lola died in 1909 and they are buried together in the Camp Hill
        Cemetery in Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada. </p>
      <p>John and Lola had their first child, a daughter Anne, in 1857. She died in 1859. They would
        go on to have eight more children. Zachary Taylor Wood (1860-1915) was born when his parents
        were in Annapolis, Maryland. He grew up in Canada and served in the Royal Canadian Mounted
        Police from 1885 until his death in 1915 in Asheville, NC. In 1998, "Mount Wood" in the
        Yukon was renamed by tin his honor. Lola Wood (1864-1956) was born when her mother was
        likely in the Richmond, Virginia, area. As far as records indicate, she grew up in Canada,
        and was still living with her parents in 1901. She died in Maryland in 1956 and was buried
        with her younger sister, Nina. Eleanor M. Wood (later Campbell) was born about 1869. She
        died in Canada in 1953. John Taylor Wood was born about 1871, but little other information
        about him was available. George M. Wood was born about 1872/1873. He was a prospector in
        Canada for many years, and he died in Victoria, Canada, in 1927. Nina Wood was born about
        1874. She, like Lola, was still living with her parents in 1901 and appears to have never
        married. She died in Maryland in 1955. Mary Wood was born about 1876. Little information
        about her was found. Charles Carroll Wood was born about 1878. In 1896, he graduated from
        the Royal Military College of Canada and served in the Boer War, where he was killed in
        1899. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname source="local">Wood, Lola MacKubin, 1835-1909</persname>
        <persname source="naf">Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
      <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 id="aspace_d04aec701a99b8b1f3eebef206755962" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters,
            <unitdate normal="1865-04-06/1865-07-13" type="inclusive">1865-04-06-1865-07-13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_5fd0292bca6fad706dc1e6a15092dea9" label="Folder" type="folder"
            >1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
