<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01292">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01292::Black History Pamphlet Collection, 1920s-1970s)//EN" "viblbv01292.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Black History Pamphlet Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >1920s-1970s</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Black History Pamphlet Collection <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2012-066</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2014 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2014-04-01T10:38-0400</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Black History Pamphlet Collection <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920s-1970s</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2012-066</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Hannah Bochain, Student Assistant and Kira A. Dietz, Archivist,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">Black History Pamphlet Collection, <unitdate>1920s-1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2012-066</unitid>
               <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>10.0 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>18 boxes</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>           
            <abstract id="ref392" label="Abstract">This collection consists of pamphlets relating to a variety of specific topics in black history, as well as pamphlets relating to both black history and Africa, the West Indies, Communism, and Asia. Materials date from the 1920s through the 1970s.</abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref393">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref394">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from Black History Pamphlet Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref395">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Black History Pamphlet Collection, Ms2012-066, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref396">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The collection was acquired by Special Collections prior to 2007.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref397">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing and arrangement of the Black History Pamphlet Collection was completed in 2012. Additional description was completed in April 2014.</p>
        </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <scopecontent id="ref398">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection consists of pamphlets relating to a variety of specific topics in black history, as well as pamphlets relating to both black history and Africa, the West Indies, Communism, and Asia. Materials date from the 1920s through the 1970s. The contents list below includes a bibliography of pamhplet/publication titles at the folder level.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref399">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged in six series. For the most part, the series reflect the arrangement in which the collection was found in 2009. Please note: Many series overlap, i.e. there are materials on communism in series other than Series IV.</p>
            <p>Series I: Topics in Black History consists pamphlets on subjects including (but limited to) Civil Rights and Civil Rights organizations, arts and culture, discrimination, legal issues, drugs, and education. It also includes issues of publications. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.</p>
            <p>Series II: Africa contains pamphlets primarily relating to issues in different countries and regions. Other publications are about European colonialism in Africa and individual people. This series is arranged alphabetically by country/topic.</p>
            <p>Series III: West Indies includes pamphlets about islands and countries. Other pamphlets relate to culture, education, and political issues. This series is arranged into two subseries: Countries/Islands and Social and Political Topics. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by place/topic.</p>
            <p>Series IV: Communism contains publications primarily about communism in the United States, with some pamphlets on communism in South America, Africa, and Russia, as well. This series is in its original order, by the numbers assigned to publications.</p>
            <p>Series V: Asia includes a small number of publications divided into two subseries. One subseries contains publications about China; the second contains publications about Vietnam.</p>
            <p>Series VI: Other Topics includes materials about dating and marriage, financial issues, and the loss of rights of indigenous groups.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref186" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series I: Topics in Black History</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref1" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>ACLU</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref2">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>American Civil Liberties Union. Work Ahead in Hope. 39th Annual Report, July 1, 1958 to June 30, 1959.</item>
                        <item>American Civil Liberties Union. Defense of Liberty by the People. 40th Annual Report, July 1, 1959 to June 30, 1960.</item>
                        <item>American Civil Liberties Union. Testing Whether That Nation. 41st Annual Report, July 1, 1960 to July 30th, 1961. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>American Civil Liberties Union. What is the American Civil Liberties Union? 1960.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref4" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Afro-American Studies</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref93">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Waffen Leslie, Nolan Nancy, Thomas Charles. Draft Prepared for the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for the Study of Negro Life and History. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Faculty of Arts and Sciences Harvard University. Report of the Faculty Committee on African and Afro-American Studies. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Daniel P. Biebuyck. Letter for Black Studies Program at University of Delaware. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref5" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Arts</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref94">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Arthur A. Schomburg. The Schomburg Collection. undated.</item>
                        <item>Paul Breman Limited. The Heritage Series. Catalogue 23. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Cuadernillos De Poesia. Antalogia de la Poesia Negra Latinoamericana. undated.</item>
                        <item>Congress of Black Writers Towards the Second Emancipation. The Dynamics of Black Liberation. October 11th-14th, 1968.</item>
                        <item>League of Revolutionary Black Workers. Fine Revolutionary Art &amp; the Kcalb Gniw by Aaron Ibn Pori Pitts. June 21st-July 19, 1970(?)</item>
                        <item>Jessie Allison Butler. Humor in the Dark. 1935.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref6" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Black Cultural Conference</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319004" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref95">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Nyx Publications. First Annual Black Cultural Conference. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref7" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Black Nationalism</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319005" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref96">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>George Breitman. Jim Crow Murder of Mr. and Mrs. Harry T. Moore. 1952.</item>
                        <item>Socialist Workers Party. The Case for a Black Party. 1968. (2 Copies)</item>
                        <item>Hakim A. Jamal. From the Dead Level: Malcolm X and Me. 1971, 1972.</item>
                        <item>Tony Thomas. In Defense of Black Nationalism. 1971.</item>
                        <item>George Brietman and George Novack. Black Nationalism and Socialism. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Robert Vernon and George Novack. Watts and Harlem: The Rising Revolt in the Black Ghettos. 1965.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref9" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Black Power</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319007" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref98">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>James E. Jackson. The Meaning of Black Power. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Jacques Amalric. Chicago &amp; Black Power. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Stokely Carmichael. Power and Racism. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Black Power. Oberbaumverlag, undated.</item>
                        <item>Stokely Carmichael. Toward Black Liberation. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Stokely Carmichael. University of California At Berkely Speech. undated.</item>
                        <item>Deutsche Kommunistische Partei (DKP). Freiheit Fur Angela Davis.</item>
                        <item>Radical Education Project. Earl Ofari. Black Liberation (Cultural and Revolutionary Nationalism). undated.</item>
                        <item>National Association of Black Students. James Forman. Control, Conflict, and Change. undated.</item>
                        <item>Young Socialist Discussion Bulletin. Black Youth and the Struggle for Self Determination. Volume 14, No. 2. November 17, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Universal Coloured People's Association. Black Power in Britain. undated.</item>
                        <item>Sufi Abdull Hamid. The Black CHallenger to White Supremacy. undated.</item>
                        <item>Robert L. Allen. Dialects of Black Power. 1968.</item>
                        <item>James E. Jackson. The Meaning of Black Power. 1966.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref8" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Black Panther Party</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319006" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref97">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Julian E. Williams. Christian Crusade Publications. The Black Panthers Are Not Black...They Are Red!1970.</item>
                        <item>Merit Publishers. The Black Panther Party. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Murray Kempton and David Shimkin. Panther 21: Strangers to Justice. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Charter Group For a Pledge of Conscience. The Black Panther Party and the Case of the New York 21. 1965. (2 Copies)</item>
                        <item>Aaron Dixon Defense Fund. Hands Off Aaron Dixon. September 1968.</item>
                        <item>The John Brown Society. An Introduction to the Black Panther Party. May 1969.</item>
                        <item>Computer People for Peace. Clark Squire and the Panther 21. 1971.</item>
                        <item>Black Panther Party. Essays From the Minister of Defense Huey Newton. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Black Panther Party. The Genius of Huey P. Newton. October 1966.</item>
                        <item>Elridge Cleaver. On the Ideology of the Black Panther Party. Part One. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Terry Cannon. All Power to the People: The Story of the Black Panther Party. 1970. (2 Copies)</item>
                        <item>Students for a Democratic Society. Huey Newton Talks to the Movement About the Black Panther Party, Cultural Nationalism, SNCC, Liberals and White Revolutionaries. Undated.</item>
                        <item>Elridge Cleaver. The Black Man's Stake in Vietnam. undated.</item>
                        <item>Jean Genet. Here and Now for Bobby Seal. undated.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Lonnie McLucas: A True Revolutionary. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ovid P. Adams. The Adventures of Black Eldridge. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Peter Schumacher. Elridge Cleaver. September 1969.</item>
                        <item>Angela Davis &amp; Die Anderen. Werkstatt Manuskript Nr. 3. 1971.</item>
                        <item>Rising Up Angry. We the People. The Revolutionary People's Constitutional Convention. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref10" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Brownsville, Tex.</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref182">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Sun. Brownsville Again. May 17, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Brownsville Inquiry. May 21, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. It Is Cruelty to Animals to Throw Soft Rubber Balls at a Monkey-Owner Fined $20 in Washington.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Says Negro Soldiers Fired the Shots at Brownsville-The Editor Who Was Hit Testifies. May 21, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. The Brownsville Inquiry. May 22, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Light at Last on Brownsville. May 23, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Against the Negro Soldiers. June 6, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Brownsville Invites Senators. June 8, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Sure of Negro Troops Guilt. June 4, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. The Brownsville Inquiry. June 10, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. President Approves Death Sentence of Negro Soldier. June 13, 1907.</item>
                        <item>he Sun. The Brownsville Shooting. June 13, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. End of the Brownsville Inquiry. June 14, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Kills Enemy of His Stepfather. June 15, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. The End of the Brownsville Hearing. June 18, 1907.</item>
                        <item>The Sun. Foraker Stirs the Negroes. June 20, 1907.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref11" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Church</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319009" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref99">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Hoernle Memorial Lecture. Jan H. Hofmeyr. Christian Principles and Race Problems. 1945.</item>
                        <item>Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America. Action of the Churches on Race Relations. December 1923.</item>
                        <item>Dr. Wesley A. Swift. God, Man, Nations and the Races. January 27, 1963.</item>
                        <item>Sam Dalton. Sin, Not Skin. undated.</item>
                        <item>National Lutheran Council-Division of American Missions. Alf M Kraabel. Grace and Race in the Lutheran Church. 1957.</item>
                        <item>National Catholic Welfare Conference. Seminar on Negro Problems in the Field of Social Action. February 1947.</item>
                        <item>Rev. George F. Bragg, JR., D.D. Virginians and Church Woek Among the Colored Race. 1937.</item>
                        <item>The National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church. The Negro Today. 1936.</item>
                        <item>Martin De Porres Walsh. The Ancient Black Christians. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Adrian Hastings. The Pattern of African Mission Work. undated.</item>
                        <item>John LaFarge, S.J. A Catholic Interracial Program. 1939.</item>
                        <item>Life Messengers. Sam Dalton. The Quest of the Rebel. undated.</item>
                        <item>Knights of the Klan Versus Knights of Columbus. undated.</item>
                        <item>Real Life Stories. M. O. Olagundoye. My Life-So Far. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref12" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Civil Rights</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319010" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref100">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government. The Civil Rights Cases. undated.</item>
                        <item>Committee on Civil Rights. United Steelworkers of America. Human Relations. October 7, 1951.</item>
                        <item>Judge Hubert T. Delany. Defend Our Civil Rights. undated.</item>
                        <item>U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Equal Opportunity in Farm Programs. March 1965.</item>
                        <item>Aldrich Blake. Civil Rights or Civil Wrongs. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Blickpunkt Weltpolitik. Freedom Now. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The American Jewish Committee. The People Take the Lead. A Record of Progress in Civil Rights. 1948 to 1959.</item>
                        <item>The American Jewish Committee. The People Take the Lead. A record of Progress in Civil Rights. 1954 to 1963.</item>
                        <item>Theodore Leskes. The Civil Rights Story. A Year's Review. 1960.</item>
                        <item>Jewish Labor Committee. Bayard Rustin. The New Crisis in Civil Rights. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Woman's Division of Christian Service. Here's the Way to Secure These Rights. undated.</item>
                        <item>The American Jewish Committee. The Civil Rights Story. A Year's Review. Volume 65. 1964.</item>
                        <item>American Opinion. The Founder of the American Civil Rights Movement. undated.</item>
                        <item>Jewish Labor Committee. Labor Looks at the Crisis in Civil Rights. January 1959.</item>
                        <item>Marvin Rich. Civil Rights Strategy After the March. 1963.</item>
                        <item>The New York Chamber of Commerce. The Civil Rights Act. November 19, 1964.</item>
                        <item>A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund. Civil Rights: The Movement Re-examined. 1967.</item>
                        <item>The Civil Rights Congress. Mrs. McGee's Own Story. April 1, 1951.</item>
                        <item>Public Law 88-352. 88th Congress, H. R. 7152. July 2, 1964.</item>
                        <item>Lyndon B. Johnson. To Fulfill These Rights. Remarks of the President at Howard University. July 4, 1965.</item>
                        <item>Industrial Union Department. Charles Zimmerman. Justice When It Counts Most. 1958.</item>
                        <item>Save the 31 Flyer. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Pittsburgh Courier. Edwin R. Embree. 50 Years of Progress in Human Relations. 1950.</item>
                        <item>California State Association of Colored Women's Clubs, Inc. Viola M. Brooks. Freedom Schools. January 1965. (2 Copies)</item>
                        <item>Washington Gocernment Printing Office. Speech of Hon. George S. Boutwell of Massachusetts. February 18, 1875.</item>
                        <item>Marion A. Wright. The Positive Approach. February 4, 1961.</item>
                        <item>International Pamphlets. James S. Allen. Negro Liberation. Pamphlet No. 29. 1935.</item>
                        <item>League of Struggle for Negro Rights. Equality, Land, and Freedom. undated.</item>
                        <item>Socialist Workers Party. A Transitional Program for Black Liberation. October 1970.</item>
                        <item>Homes County F.D.P. Holmes County, Mississippi. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref13" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319011" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref101">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>St. Louis Post-Dispatch. Communist Forces Behind Negro Revolution in This Country. January 12, 1964.</item>
                        <item>Dr. W. E. B. DuBois' Application to join the Communist Party and Gus Hall's Reply. undated.</item>
                        <item>National Non-Partisan Committee. George W. Crockett, Jr. Freedom is Everybody's Job! undated.</item>
                        <item>Committee on Un-American Activities. The American Negro in the Communist Party. December 22, 1954.</item>
                        <item>Foreign Languages Press. Statement Made by Comrade Mao Tse-Tung, Chairman of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China, In Support of the Afro-American Struggle Against Violent Repression. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Hill. The Communist Party-Enemy of Negro Equality. undated.</item>
                        <item>American Opinion. Rex T. Westerfiel. Now It's the Brown Revolution. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Claude Lightfoot. The Negro Question in the U.S.A. March 1960.</item>
                        <item>Lightfoot Defense Committee. The Case of Claude Lightfoot. undated.</item>
                        <item>Claude Lightfoot. An American Looks at Russia. November 10, 1950.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. Character Building and Education in the Spirit of Socialism. 1939.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. What It Means To Be a Communist. February 1951.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. Build The Communist Party. Report to the 19th National Convention, COmmunist Party. April 10-May 4, 1969. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Workers Library Publishers. The Communist Election Platform. July 1936.</item>
                        <item>The Daily Worker. Election Platform of the COmmunist Party. 1940.</item>
                        <item>The Election Platform of the Communist Party. June 28, 1936.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin J. Davis. The Negro People on the March. Report to the National Committee of the Communist Party. 1956.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin J. Davis. Why I Am a Communist. December 1947.</item>
                        <item>Ben Davis, Jr. The Negro People and the Communist Party. March 1943.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin J. Davis. The Negro People in the Struggle For Peace and Freedom. Report to the 15th, Convention Communist Party. February 1951.</item>
                        <item>Julia Brown. An Anti-Communist Negro Makes This Appeal: Please Don't Help Glorify Martin Luther King. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pettis Perry. The Party of Negro and White. January 13, 1953.</item>
                        <item>Pettis Perry. White Chauvinism and the Struggle for Peace. 1952.</item>
                        <item>Pettis Perry. The November Elections and the Fight For jobs, Peace, Equal Rights, Democracy. 1954.</item>
                        <item>New Century Pulbishers. Pettis Perry Speaks to the Court. Opening Statement to the Court and Jury in the Case of the Sixteen Smith Act Victims in the Trial at Foley Square. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref14" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Convict Labor</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319012" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref102">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Sasha Small. Hell In Georgie. August 1935.</item>
                        <item>The Committee of 100. An AMerican Tragedy: The Story of Jesse Dukes. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref15" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Courts</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319013" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref103">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>League of Struggle For Negro Rights. The Story of Scottsboro in Pictures. March 1932. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Angelo Herndon. The Scottsboro Boys. August 1937.</item>
                        <item>The Scottsboro Defense Committee. The Scottsboro Case. Opinion of Judge James E. Horton. January 1936.</item>
                        <item>International Labor Defense. Decision of the United States Supreme Court in the Case of Angelo Herndon. April 1937.</item>
                        <item>Elizabeth Lawson. Angelo Herndon Must Go Free. May 1935.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend Resistance to Ghetto Life. We Accuse. Bill Epton Speaks to the Court. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Martin Sostre Defense Committee. Martin Sostre in Court. July 1969.</item>
                        <item>Fort Hood Three Defense Committee. The Fort Hood Three. July 1966.</item>
                        <item>Elwood Dean. The Story of the Trenton Six. December 1949.</item>
                        <item>NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc. The Fantastic Case of the Trenton Six. January 1951.</item>
                        <item>NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc. "Assault" at 75 Feet. undated.</item>
                        <item>Harry Raymond. The Ingrams Shall Not Die. undated.</item>
                        <item>Joint Committee to Aid the Herndon Defense. The Case of Angelo Herndon. October 1935.</item>
                        <item>Fact Sheet in the Case of the Harlem Six. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Lightfoot Defense Committee. The Case of Claude Lightfoot. undated.</item>
                        <item>Mike Newberry. The Cruel and Unusual Punishment of Henry Winston. undated.</item>
                        <item>Guardian Independent Radical Newsweekly. Angela Davis Speaks From Prison. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Gene Tournour. Henry Winston Meets Angela Davis. undated.</item>
                        <item>John Abt. On the Defense of Angela Davis. November 22, 1970.</item>
                        <item>James Baldwin. An Open Letter to My Sister , Miss Angela Davis. November 19, 1970.</item>
                        <item>The New York Committee to Free Angela Davis. People's Petition Demanding Bail For Angela Davis. undated.</item>
                        <item>Charlene Mitchell. The Fight to Free Angela Davis. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Student Nonviolent Coordinate Committee. Let Rap Rap. January 18, 1969.</item>
                        <item>New York Committee to Free Angela Davis. Bail for Angela Davis. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pettis Perry and Claudia Jones. This, Too, Is Lynch Law. undated.</item>
                        <item>NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc. Stop This Murder. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Groveland U.S.A. August 1949.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council, Inc. Racial Discrimination in the Southern Federal Courts. April 1965.</item>
                        <item>The Story of Winfred Lynn. undated.</item>
                        <item>National Putnam Letters Committee. The Evers Opinion. July 6, 1964.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. No. 290. October Term, 1947.</item>
                        <item>Britons Publishing Company. Not Guilty. March 1968.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref16" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 1-10</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319014" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref104">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>North Carolina Council on Human Relations. Annual Meeting. January 23, 1965.</item>
                        <item>Walter White. The American Negro and His Problems. 1927. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Elmer A. Carter. Practical Considerations of Anti-Discrimination Legislation: Experience Under the New York Law Against Discrimination. 1954.</item>
                        <item>Report of the New York State Temporary Commission Against Discrimination. 1945.</item>
                        <item>John P. Davis. Let Us Build a National Negro Congress. January 1936.</item>
                        <item>Bureau of Applied Social Research. Columbia University. A Controlled Study of the Impact of Anti-Discrimination Car Cards. 1953.</item>
                        <item>The CIO Committee to Abolish Discrimination. A "Turnover" Talk For Fair Practices. undated.</item>
                        <item>International Labor Defense and National Negro Congress. It is Against the Law. April 1945.</item>
                        <item>A Petition to the united Nations on Behalf of 13 Million Oppressed Negro Citizens of the United States of America. 1946.</item>
                        <item>Sons of Liberty. The Unconstitutionality of the 14th Amendment. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref17" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 11-20</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319015" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref105">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>NAACP. The Ilgwu Today-The Decay of a Labor Union. undated.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. The Racial Practices of Organized Labor0In the Age of Gompers and After. 1965.</item>
                        <item>A. Bruce Hunt. The Proposed Fair Employment Practice Act; Facts and Fallacies. December 1945.</item>
                        <item>NPA COmmittee of the South. Selected Studies of Negro Employment in the South. September 1953.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Hill. Labor Unions and the Negro. December 1959.</item>
                        <item>Negro Labor News Service. True Freedom for Negro and WHite Labor. undated.</item>
                        <item>Negro Labor News Service. When Will It End? November 30, 1929.</item>
                        <item>United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Side by Side. undated.</item>
                        <item>Claude Lightfoot. Turning Point in Freedom Road. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Art Shiels. The Killing of William Milton. September 1948.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref18" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 21-30</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319016" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref106">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Harry Raymond. Dixie Comes to New York. February 1946.</item>
                        <item>Angelo Herndon. You Cannot Kill the Working Class. undated.</item>
                        <item>National Negro Congress and the Michigan Negro Congress. Henry Ford and the Negro People. undated.</item>
                        <item>Leslie Stephens. Employment of Coloured Workers. Occasional Papers No. 10. 1956.</item>
                        <item>National Negro Labor Council. Let Freedom Ride the Rails. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pennsylvania Fair Employment Practice Commission. Employment at Your Highest Skill. undated.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Roy Wilkins. No Harvest for the Reaper. undated.</item>
                        <item>Herbert R. Northrup. Will negroes Get Jobs Now? November 1945.</item>
                        <item>Rob Fowler Hall. FEPC. February 1950.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Hill. Racial Inequality in Employment: The Patterns of Discrimination. January 1965.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref19" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 31-40</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319017" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref107">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Herbert Hill. Buffalo Law Review. Volume 14, No. 1. Fall 1964.</item>
                        <item>Robert Dudnick. Black Workers in Revolt. March 1969.</item>
                        <item>Radical Education Project. To the Point...of Production. July 1969.</item>
                        <item>Peter Noble. The Cinema and the negro. 1905-1948.</item>
                        <item>American Civil Liberties Union. Black Justice. April 1938.</item>
                        <item>Max Bedacht. Complete Equality. undated.</item>
                        <item>International Pamphlets. J. S. Allen. The American Negro. 1932.</item>
                        <item>Council for Democracy. The Negro and Defense. No. 3. 1941.</item>
                        <item>Chester Bowles. The Negro-Progress and Challenge. February 7, 1954.</item>
                        <item>National Negro Congress. Democracy and the Negro People Today. October 16, 1940.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref20" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 41-50</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319018" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref108">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>National federation for Constitutional Liberties. Everybody's Business. 1946.</item>
                        <item>International Students Conference. Racial Discrimination in the United States. 1965-1966.</item>
                        <item>Andrew B. Humphrey. Race Discrimination. undated.</item>
                        <item>March on Washington Movement. "Master Race" Vs. "White Supremacy". undated.</item>
                        <item>Executive Department State Commission Against Discrimination. undated.</item>
                        <item>Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies. The Impact of Race on Neighborhood in the Metropolitan Setting. April 27, 1961.</item>
                        <item>Earl B. Schulst. Race and Housing: The Basic American Dilemma. undated.</item>
                        <item>Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc. Homes for Blacks. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pamphlet Advocating Sharkey-Brown-Isaacs Bill. undated.</item>
                        <item>E. R. Braithwaite. Reluctant Neighbors. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref21" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 51-60</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319019" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">2-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref109">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>SPonsors of Open Housing Investment. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Journal of Negro History. The Negro in the United States Navy During World War II. undated.</item>
                        <item>Charles G. Bolte and Louis Harris. Our Negro Veterans. Public Affairs Pamphlet No. 128. 1947.</item>
                        <item>American Servicemen's Union. Black Marines Against the Brass. September 1969.</item>
                        <item>Committee For GI Rights. Kangaroo Court-Martial. March 10, 1969. (2 Ccopies).</item>
                        <item>Claudia Jones. Jim Crow in Uniform. July 1940.</item>
                        <item>Jim Crow "Justice" In Korea. The Case of Lieutenant Leon Gilbert. undated.</item>
                        <item>Wade Defense Committee. They Broke the Unwritten Law. undated.</item>
                        <item>Carl Hirsch. Terror at Trumbull. October 1955.</item>
                        <item>Howard Mayhew. Racial Terror at Trumbull Park, Chicago. August 1954.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref22" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 61-70</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319020" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref110">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>James Wallace. Segregation on Common Carriers. 1947.</item>
                        <item>Committee of Editors and Writers in the South. Voting Restrictions in the 13 Southern States. undated.</item>
                        <item>Virginia Commission on Constitutional Government. Voting Rights and Legal Wrongs. undated.</item>
                        <item>Flyer Encouraging Voter Participation in Mississippi. undated.</item>
                        <item>A Lesson for Delegates Who Don't Know About the Regular Mississippi Democratic Delegation. undated.</item>
                        <item>W. E. B. DuBois Clubs of America. Comlumbia, Inc. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Rev. A. Clayton Powell, Jr. A Big Stride Forward. Undated.</item>
                        <item>Claudia Jones. lift Every Voice For Victory. June 1942.</item>
                        <item>A.B. Magil. Battle for America. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref23" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Discrimination No. 70</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319021" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref111">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Herbert Aptheker and James E. Jackson. Riding to Freedom. June 1961.</item>
                        <item>Pettis Perry. Negro Representation. July 1952.</item>
                        <item>Text of Proposed Voting Rights Act. undated.</item>
                        <item>ERAP/ Students for a Democratic Society. undated.</item>
                        <item>Louis Redding. Louisville Travesty. undated.</item>
                        <item>Della Rossa. Why Watts Exploded. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Louis Burnham. Behind the Lynching of Emmet Louis Till. December 1955.</item>
                        <item>Congress of Racial Equality. Sit Ins. The Student Report. May 1960. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>S. Andhil Fineberg. Deflating the Professional Bigot. January 1960.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Summary of the PEP report on Racial Discrimination. February 1970.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Prejudice in the Community. undated.</item>
                        <item>27thh Congress, 2nd Session. Doc. No. 119. Colored Mariners in Ports of South Carolina.</item>
                        <item>Gordon W. Allport. ABC's of Scapegoating. undated.</item>
                        <item>Freedom Press Julius Lewin. Britain's Colour Bar in Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>Chris de Brogolia. South Africa: Racism in Sport. 1970.</item>
                        <item>The Economist. Elizabeth Burney. Black in a White World. Brief 5. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Disinherited Speak: Letters From Sharecroppers. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref24" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Drugs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319022" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref113">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Michael "Cetewayo" Tabor. Capitalism Plus Dope Equals Genocide. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Michael "Cetewayo" Tabor. Harlem: Kapitalismus &amp; Heroin=Volkermord.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref25" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Economics</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319023" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref112">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Eldridge Cleaver. Education and Revolution. undated.</item>
                        <item>The American Assembly. Black Economic Development. Report of the Thirty-fifth American Assemblt. April 24-27, 1969.</item>
                        <item>U.S. Department of Labor. The Economic Situation of Negroes in the United States. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Political Development. Politics in Command. November 1969.</item>
                        <item>Victor Perlo. Trends in the Economic Status of the Negro People. 1952.</item>
                        <item>United States Department of Labor. Negroes in the United States: Their Employment and Economic Status. December 1952.</item>
                        <item>Dick Roberts. The Fraud of Black Capitalism. October 1970.</item>
                        <item>Frank Riessman. New Careers: A Basic Strategy Against Poverty. undated.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council. The South: America's Opportunity Number One. 1945.</item>
                        <item>American Family Series. A Negro Community Works In Behalf of Its Families. Vol. 1. Undated.</item>
                        <item>American Family Series. A Negro Rural Family Learns To Use the Consumer Services of Its Government. Volume 2. undated.</item>
                        <item>The National Emergency Council. Report on Economic Conditions of the South. 1938.</item>
                        <item>A. Philip Randolph Institute. A "Freedom Budget" For All Americans. January 1967.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref26" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Education</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319024" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref114">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Marjorie V. Wilkins. Pioneer in Human Relations. undated.</item>
                        <item>Doxey A. Wilkerson. The People Versus Segregated Schools. February 1955. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Sir Edward Boyle. Race Relations and Education. 1970.</item>
                        <item>John W. Caughey. Segregation Blights Our Schools. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Rev. Robert Q. Patton, D.D. An Inspiring Record in Negro Education. February 14, 1940.</item>
                        <item>C. L. R. James. Black Studies and the Contempory Student. June 6, 1969. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>John Egerton. The Black Public COlleges. June 1971.</item>
                        <item>Charles H. Thompson. Fifty Years of Progress in Higher Education. 1950.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. A Bibliography For Teachers of Immigrants. March 1970.</item>
                        <item>Howard University. Chemistry at Howard University. 1951.</item>
                        <item>The Commission on the Black Colleges of the United Methodist Church. Black Colleges: The Call to Renew a Commitment. 1972.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. The Jim Crow School-North and West. July 1962.</item>
                        <item>David D. Jones. Cultural Obligations of the Faculty in a Negro Liberal Arts College. March 1939.</item>
                        <item>Albert Shanker. Some Comments on "Community Control". undated.</item>
                        <item>Association of Colleges for Negro Youth. November 12-13, 1914.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council. The Schools and the Courts. undated.</item>
                        <item>Harold C. Fleming and John Constable. What's Happening in School Integration. Public Affairs Pamphlet No. 244. December 1956.</item>
                        <item>Alvin J. Neely. Tuskegee's New Principal. April 1922.</item>
                        <item>Department of Christian Social Relations, United Church Women, National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America. Save Our Schools: A Roundup of Southern Press Opinion. August 1959.</item>
                        <item>Wisconsin Council of Teachers of English. Two Approaches to the Culturally Disadvantaged Student. June 1966.</item>
                        <item>Radio Interview. Martha Dean and Dr. James M. Hester. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Richard Bobbins. The Future of Negro Colleges. undated.</item>
                        <item>United Negro College Fund, Inc. Letter Seeking Donations. undated.</item>
                        <item>New york Civil Liberties Union. The Burden of Blame: A Report on the Ocean Hill-Brownsville School Controversy. undated.</item>
                        <item>Congress of Racial Equality. A First Step Toward School Integration. June 1958.</item>
                        <item>Doxey A. Wilkerson. The Historic Fight to Abolish School Segregation in the United States. 1954.</item>
                        <item>United States Department of the interior. Fundamentals in the Education of Negroes. 1935.</item>
                        <item>Margaret Burroughs. Identity For the Negro Child. 1966.</item>
                        <item>R. B. Eleazer. School Books and Racial Antagonism. 1937.</item>
                        <item>The School Crisis Hotline. Newspaper. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Lehman Education Fund Flyer. undated.</item>
                        <item>Institute for Developmental Studies. SChool of Education. New York University. A Program for Young Children. undated.</item>
                        <item>Angela Davis. Lectures on Liberation. undated.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Colored People: Education and Status. 1971.</item>
                        <item>Robert Birler. Some Educational Programs of Africa. November 1968.</item>
                        <item>J.R. Kwegyin Aggrey. Pioneers Who Served. 1957.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref27" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Freemasons, Negro</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319025" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref115">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Committee on Masonic Information. Free Masonry Among Men of Color in New York State. 1954.</item>
                        <item>Harry A. Williamson. The Prince Hall Primer. 1946.</item>
                        <item>Harry A. Williamson. The Story of Carthaginian Lodge. October 1, 1949.</item>
                        <item>Harold V. B. Voorhis. Our Colored Brethren. 1960.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref28" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Lincoln Folder</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319026" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref116">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Abraham Lincoln. Selections From His Writings. 1944.</item>
                        <item>William Pickens. Abraham Lincoln: Man and Statesman. 1930.</item>
                        <item>William E. Barton, D.D., LL. D. The Influence of Illinois in the Development of Abraham Lincoln. 1921.</item>
                        <item>D. J. Richards. The Story of Abraham Lincoln's Assassination. 1929.</item>
                        <item>Marguerite Bartlett Hamer. The Presidential Campaign of 1860 in Tennessee. 1931.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref29" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Man</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319027" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref117">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Matthew Ravenshaw. The Origin of the White and Black Races. undated.</item>
                        <item>Linda Samuels. An Exhibit on the Races of Mankind. June 1946.</item>
                        <item>Ruth Benedcit and Gene Weltfish. The Races of Mankind. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319028" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref118">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Harper's Ferry Souvenier Book. undated.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Commonwealth Immigration Report. September 25, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Labour Research Department. Immigration. Facts vs. Myth. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Department of Public Information. What the United Nations is Doing for Self-Governing Territories.</item>
                        <item>Christian Crusade. George C. Wallace Speech. August 1, 1969.</item>
                        <item>Cheddi Jagan. The Role of the C.I.A. in Guyana and Its Activities Throughout the World. October 1967.</item>
                        <item>Housing and Home Finance Agency. Urban Renewal. September 1955.</item>
                        <item>Wm. B. Hogg. The Old South. 1930.</item>
                        <item>Shakedown. Vol. 2, No. 3. Newspaper. June 7, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Jean Boyd. The Flame of Islam. 1969.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Music</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319029" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">3-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref119">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>H.T. Burleigh. Negro Spirituals. 1917.</item>
                        <item>Lily Strickland. Mah Lindy Lou. 1920.</item>
                        <item>George Hoefer. The Dixieland New Orleans. Folio No. 3. 1950.</item>
                        <item>University of Pittsburg. Stephen Collins Foster. 1939.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Lynching</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319030" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref120">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Marcet Haldeman-Julius. The Story of a Lynching. 1927.</item>
                        <item>Commission on Interracial Cooperation. The Mob Still Rides: A Review of the Lynching Record 1931-1935.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Lynching List. 1929.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Lynching List. 1933.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. The Lynching of Claude Neal. February 1937.</item>
                        <item>Hearings Before the Committee on the Judiciary House of Representatives. Anti Lynching. January 29, 1920.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>NAACP (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319031" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref121">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Mary White Ovington. How the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Began. 1951.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. An American Organization. June 1956.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. NAACP 43rd Annual Conference Resolutions. June 24-29, 1952.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. NAACP 51st Annual Convention Resolutions. June 21-26, 1960.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. "We Never Claimed It to be Authentic". October 1956.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. The Fight for Freedom in a Transition Year. NAACP Annual Report. 44th Year. 1952.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Hints for Better Branch Administration. 1959.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Invest in Freedom Brochure. December 1953.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes No. 1-20</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319032" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref122">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Prince George's County Memorial Library. Selective List of Government Publications About the American Negro. February 1969.</item>
                        <item>University Place Book Shop. Negro Life and Culture. undated.</item>
                        <item>Albert Parker. Negroes in the Post-War World. undated.</item>
                        <item>J.P. Holcombe, Esq. An Address Delivered Before the Seventh Annual Meeting of the Virginia State Agricultural Society. November 4, 1858.</item>
                        <item>George S. Schuyler. The Communist Conspiracy Against the Negroes. undated.</item>
                        <item>Maxwell S. Stewart. The Negro in America. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Gunnar Myrdal. An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy. undated.</item>
                        <item>Thomas A. Johnson. The U.S. Negro in Vietnam. 1968.</item>
                        <item>U.S. Navy. The Navy Challenge: Future of the Negro in the United States Army. undated.</item>
                        <item>Harry L. Wright. A Survey of Veterans Services for Negroes in Arkansas. undated.</item>
                        <item>Harry L. Wright. A Survey of Veterans Services for Negroes in Oklahoma. undated.</item>
                        <item>Thomas B. Jones. How the Negro Can Start His Own Business. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Scholarship, Education and Defense Fund For Racial Equality. A New Program to Assist Newly Elected Negro Officials. undated.</item>
                        <item>Lawrence D. Reddick. The World View of the Negro Question. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pauline Podbrey. Famous American Negroes. undated.</item>
                        <item>Judy Davis. The Black Book. undated.</item>
                        <item>Rashi Fein. An Economic and Social Profile of the Negro American. 1966.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Common Sense Anyone? April 1969.</item>
                        <item>Workers Library Publishers. Negroes and the National War Effort: An Address by Frederick Douglass. April 1942.</item>
                        <item>Steve Kingston. Frederick Douglass. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes No. 21-40</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319033" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref123">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Philip S. Foner. Frederick Douglass: Selections from His Writings. 1945.</item>
                        <item>William Pickens. Frederick Douglass and the Spirit of Freedom. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Elbert Hubbard. Little Journeys to the Homes of Great Teachers. 1908.</item>
                        <item>George W. Carver. The Sweet Potato as a Flour Substitute. undated.</item>
                        <item>Tuskegee Institute. Highlights of the George Washington Carver Museum. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Glenn Clark. The Man Who Talks With Flowers. 1939.</item>
                        <item>Mel J. Rothwell. The Hall of Fame Series. George Washington Carver: A Great Scientist. 1944.</item>
                        <item>Facing Reality Publishing Committee. Negro Americans Take the Lead. September 1964.</item>
                        <item>Frank B Crosswaith. The Negro American and Socialism. 1929. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Louis Chapin. One of God's Great Gentlemen: Roland Hayes. March 1969.</item>
                        <item>Voice of America. Distinguished Americans No. 12. WIllie Mays. June 14, 1967.</item>
                        <item>George Schwab. Harriet Tubman. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ann McGovern. Runaway Slave: The Story of Harriet Tubman. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Rev. William Howard Melish. Address at teh Memorial Service of Dr. William Edward Burghardt DuBois. September 29, 1963.</item>
                        <item>Negroes and American Democracy. undated.</item>
                        <item>District Grand Household of Ruth No. 5. Pamphlet for a Banquet Given to Honor Susie F. Jones. April 28, 1949.</item>
                        <item>Esther Cooper Jackson. This Is My Husband. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Albert E. Kahn. Agents of Peace. undated.</item>
                        <item>Constance Webb. What Next for Richard Wright? 1949.</item>
                        <item>New York Committee to Free Angela Davis. A Political Biography of Angela Davis. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref36" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes No. 41-50</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319034" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref124">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>New York Committee to Free Angela Davis. Angela Answers 13 Questions. undated.</item>
                        <item>World Magazine. Free Angela. February 27, 1971.</item>
                        <item>A Letter From Angela to Ericka. May 2, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Young Socialist. Malcolm X Talks to Young People. September 1968.</item>
                        <item>George Breitman. Malcolm X: The Man and His Ideas. 1967. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Two Speeches by Malcolm X. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Merit Publishers. The Assassination of Malcolm X. February 21, 1969.</item>
                        <item>Communist Party, U.S.A. In Honor of Paul Robeson. Excerpts from a speech by William L. Patterson. undated.</item>
                        <item>Friends Ancient and Modern. Levi Coffin. 1915.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Aptheker. John Brown: American Martyr. 1960.</item>
                        <item>D. M. Baxter. Has the Negro's Freedom Paid? undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes No. 51-70</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319035" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref125">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Elizabeth Lawson. Thaddesus Stevens. 1942.</item>
                        <item>Elizabeth Lawson. Thaddeus Stevens. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Charles Longstreet Weltner. John Willie Reed. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Mary E. Varela. Something of Our Own. December 1965.</item>
                        <item>Merit Publishers. Murder in Memphis. May 1968. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Where is the Negro Movement Now? A Conversation with Bayard Rustin. August 1968.</item>
                        <item>Message from the President of the United States in Answer to A Resolution of the House of 27th Ultimo, Relative to the Provisions in the Constitutions of Several States Relative to the Freedmen. May 23 1866.</item>
                        <item>Resolutions of the Legislature of New York. February 8, 1848.</item>
                        <item>Don Benn Owens. The Most Controversial American and Why the Negro Race Lacks Unity. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Resolutions of the General Assembly of South Carolina in Relation to the Controversy Between the States of New York and Virginia, on the Subject of Surrendering Fugitives from Justice. February 7, 1842.</item>
                        <item>Imani. Grassroots Politics in Alabama. undated.</item>
                        <item>W.E.B. DuBois. From McKinley to Wallace. August 1948.</item>
                        <item>T. M. Campbell. Fifty Years of Progress in Agriculture. undated.</item>
                        <item>Eugene Gordon and Cyril Briggs. The Position of the Negro Woman. February 1953.</item>
                        <item>Maxine Williams and Pamela Newman. Black Women's Liberation. September 1971.</item>
                        <item>Claudia Jones. An End to the Neglect of the Problems of the Negro Woman. June 1949.</item>
                        <item>The National Council of Negro Women. Invitation to the First Black Women's Institute 1972 Hunger Convocation. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Jefferson School of Social Science. Questions and Answers on the Woman Question. 1953.</item>
                        <item>The Committee for Unified Newark. Black Woman's Role in the Revolution. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Mwananamke Mwananchi (The Nationalist Woman). 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref38" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes No. 71-</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319036" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref126">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Patricia Robinson. Poor Black Women: Birth Control and Black Children. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Political Development. What Does it Mean to be Black? undated.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Political Development. What is Freedom? Who is the Enemy? undated.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Political Development. Concurrent Nationalism and Stages of Colonial Struggle and Revolutionary Struggle. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Reparations Committee for the Descendants of American Slaves. Why Reparations? Money for Negroes. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Howard E. Seals. You Ain't Thuh Man Yuh Mamma Wuz: The Wisdom of the Dozens. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Wm. E. Bohannan. A Letter to American Negroes. September 1948.</item>
                        <item>Socialist Workers Party. Freedom Now. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Independent Political Council. Some Reasons Why Negroes SHould Vote the Socialist Ticket. undated.</item>
                        <item>The National League on Urban Conditions Among Negroes. Bulletin. March 1913.</item>
                        <item>Mississippi Enterprises. Views of a Southern Negro. undated.</item>
                        <item>NPA Committee of the South. Selected Studies of Negro Employment in the South. May 1954.</item>
                        <item>Houston Council on Human Relations. The Negro and Employment Opportunities in the South. November 1961.</item>
                        <item>Ray Sprigel. I Was A Negro in the South for 30 Days. undated.</item>
                        <item>Remembering Dr. DuBois. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes-History</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319037" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref127">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Journal of Negro History. Negro Casualties in the Civil War. January 1947.</item>
                        <item>Alan Conway. The History of the Negro in the United States. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Inc. Bibliographic Suggestions for the Study of Negro History. undated.</item>
                        <item>Robert B. Eleazer. America's Tenth Man. September 1933.</item>
                        <item>Herbert Aptheker. Negro HIstory: Its Lesson for Our Time.</item>
                        <item>Queens Borough Public Library. Proud Heritage of the Afro-American. September 1968.</item>
                        <item>International Socialist Review. Malcolm X on Afro-American History. 1967.</item>
                        <item>John Hope Franklin. The Future of Negro American History.</item>
                        <item>The Quarterly Journal. The Historical Status of the Negro in Maryland. October 1939.</item>
                        <item>The Quarterly Journal. The Courts and Equality of Rights on Common Carriers. January 1940.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Negroes-History-Kit</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319038" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref128">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Inc. Letter to Patron. undated.</item>
                        <item>Biographical Sketches and Suggested Program Material. undated.</item>
                        <item>News &amp; Letters. American Civilization on Trial. May 1963.</item>
                        <item>New York African Society for Mutual Relief Inc. Memorial Address by Walter N. Beekman. undated.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin J. Davis. On the Struggle for Peace and Freedom. 1956.</item>
                        <item>The New York State Communist Party. Negro History Week. 1950.</item>
                        <item>New York State Communist Party. Negro History Week. 1951.</item>
                        <item>New York State Communist Party. Negro History Week. 1952.</item>
                        <item>New York State Communist Party. Negro History Week. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Schenley. Negro History Calendar. 1950.</item>
                        <item>Howard Selsam. The Negro People in the United States. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Daniel Alexander Payne. Negro History Bulletin. November 1969.</item>
                        <item>Draft Resolution on the Negro Question. undated.</item>
                        <item>Negro History Week Bulletin. A Message From President Truman. 1946.</item>
                        <item>The Association for the Study of Negro Life and History. Pamphlet. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref41" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Prisons</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319039" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">4-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref129">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Saint George's Church. Attica. September 1971.</item>
                        <item>Derrick Morrison and Mary-Alice Waters. Attica: Why Prisoners are Rebelling. January 1972.</item>
                        <item>War Behind Walls. Newspaper. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref42" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Propaganda-Communist</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319040" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref130">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Gus Hall, Claude Lightfoot, William L. Patterson, and Henry M. Winston. Negro Liberation. July 1964.</item>
                        <item>Negro's Struggle Against Capitalist and Imperialist Exploitation and Oppression. undated.</item>
                        <item>Gus Hall. Negro Freedom. July 1964.</item>
                        <item>Gus Hall. Marxism and Negro Liberation. May 1951.</item>
                        <item>Earl Browder. Benjamin J. Davis, Jr., James W. Ford, and William L. Patterson. Communists in the Struggle for Negro Rights. January 1945.</item>
                        <item>James S. Allen and James W. Ford. The Negroes in Soviet America. June 1935.</item>
                        <item>Daily Worker. American Negro Problems. undated.</item>
                        <item>Robert Minor. Tell the People How Ben Davis Was Elected. February 1946.</item>
                        <item>New Outlook Publishers. Viva La Raza! October 1970.</item>
                        <item>Hugh Bradley. Next Steps in the Struggle for Negro Freedom. November 1953.</item>
                        <item>A Communist View. Are Cops the Answer? undated.</item>
                        <item>Workers Library Publishers. The Road to Liberation for the Negro People. September 1937.</item>
                        <item>Paul Robeson. The Negro People and the Soviet Union. January 1950.</item>
                        <item>National Education Department, Communist Party. The Struggle Against White Chauvinism. September 1949.</item>
                        <item>Tim Wohlforth. The New Nationalism and the Negro Struggle. undated.</item>
                        <item>N. Khrushchov. Stalin Friendship Among the Peoples Makes Our Motherland Invincible. 1950.</item>
                        <item>Charles P. Mann. Stalin's Thought Illuminates Problems of Negro Freedom Struggle. January 1953.</item>
                        <item>The Worker. The Southern People's Common Program for Democracy, Prosperity, and Peace. March 1953.</item>
                        <item>New York State Communist Party Committee. Outline on the Negro Question. July 27, 1938.</item>
                        <item>Charles White. Free Angela Herndon. June 1934.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. The Meaning of San Rafael. August 1971.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. Black Americans and the Middle East Conflict. September 1970.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. Negro-White Unity. February 1967.</item>
                        <item>Youth's Fighting Magazine. Old Jim Crow Has Got to Go. March 1941.</item>
                        <item>Henry Winston. New Colonialism U.S. Style. March 1965.</item>
                        <item>James W. Ford. The Right to Revolution for the Negro People. undated.</item>
                        <item>C. A. Hathaway. Who Are the Friends of the Negro People? undated.</item>
                        <item>James W. Ford. The Negro People and the New World Situation. August 1941.</item>
                        <item>James W. Ford. Win Progress for Harlem. 1939.</item>
                        <item>James and Grace Boggs. The Awesome Responsibility of Revolutionary Leadership. undated.</item>
                        <item>Julia Barnes. Why Racism is Used Against Welfare Programs. Mayb 1971. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Dr. Kenneth Goff. Civil Riots: Fruit of Cheap Politicians. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Negro Commission National Committee. Is Japan the Champion of the Colored Races? August 1938.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref43" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publication-African Revolution</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319041" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref131">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>African Revolution. Vol. 1, No. 1. May 1963.</item>
                        <item>African Revolution. Vol. 1, No. 2. June 1963.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref44" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Beau-Cocoa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319042" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref132">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Beau-Cocoa. Employment. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref45" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Art</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319055" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref133">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Art. Special Emancipation Supplement. Vol. 7, No. 1. January 1963.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref46" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Creation</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319044" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref155">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Creation. Vol. 1, No. 1. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref47" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Images</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319045" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref135">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Images. Black Cultural Crisis in Canada. Vol. 1, No. 1. January 1972.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref48" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Magic Juju</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319046" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref136">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Health Workers Alliance. Black Magic Juju. Vol. 1, No. 2. November 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref49" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Black News</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319047" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref137">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black News. Vol. 1, No. 29. February 25, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Black News. Vol. 1, No. 35. October 22, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Black News. Vol. 1, No. 36. December 1971.</item>
                        <item>Black News. Vol. 1, No. 37. January 1972.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref50" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Revolutionary</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319048" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref138">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Revolutionary. Vol. 1, No. 1. May 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref51" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Black Theatre</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319049" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref139">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Black Theatre. Vol. 1, No. 3. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref52" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Community</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319050" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-11</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref140">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Community. Vol. 1, No. 4. October 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref53" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-The Conch</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319051" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-12</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref141">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Conch. Vol. 1, No. 2. September 1969.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref54" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Confrontation</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319052" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-13</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref142">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Confrontation. Vol. 1, No. 1. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Confrontation. Vol. 1, No. 2. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref55" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Congress View</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319053" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-14</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref143">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Congress View. Vol. 3, No. 3. November 1945.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref56" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Contrast</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319054" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-15</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref57" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-The Crisis</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319056" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-16</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref145">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Souther Aid Society of Virginia, Inc. The Crisis. September 1932.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref58" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-The Crusader Newsletter</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319057" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref146">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 9, No. 2. September-October 1967.</item>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 9, No. 3. December 1967.</item>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 9, No. 4. March 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 9, No. 5. May 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 10, No. 1. November 1968. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>The Crusader. Vol. 10, No. 2. 1969. (2 copies)</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref59" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-For the People's Health</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319058" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-18</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref147">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Health Revolutionary Unity Movement. For the People's Health. Vol. 2, No. 6. May 16, 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref60" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-The Free Lance</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319059" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-19</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref148">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Free Lance. Vol. 9, No. 2. 1965.</item>
                        <item>The Free Lance. Vol. 10, No. 1. 1966.</item>
                        <item>The Free Lance. Vol. 10, No. 2. 1966.</item>
                        <item>The Free Lance. Vol. 11, No. 1. 1967.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref61" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Freedomways</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319060" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-20</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref149">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Freedomways. Vol. 2, No. 3. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Freedomways. Vol. 1, No. 3. 1961.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref62" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Garvey's Voice</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319061" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-21</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref150">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Garvey's Voice. 1969.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref63" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Harvard Journal of Negro Affairs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319062" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-22</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref151">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Harvard Journal of Negro Affairs. Vol. 2, No. 1. 1968.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref64" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Insurgent</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319063" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-23</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref152">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Insurgent. March-April 1967.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref65" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Jet</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319064" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-24</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref153">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Jet. February 8, 1962.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref66" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Jewish Currents</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319065" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">5-25</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref154">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Jewish Currents. Vol. 22, No. 5. May 1968.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref67" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Journal of Black Poetry</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319066" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref156">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Journal of Black Poetry. Vol. 1, No. 9. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Black Poetry. Vol. 1, No. 11. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Black Poetry. Vol. 1, No. 12. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Black Poetry. Vol. 1, No. 13. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Black Poetry. Vol. 1, No. 14. 1970-1971.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Black POetry. Vol. 1, No. 15. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref68" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Monthly Review</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319067" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref157">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Monthly Review. Vol. 15, No. 5. September 1963.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref69" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-A Monthly Summary of Events and Trends in Race Relations</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319068" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref158">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>A Monthly Summary of Events and Trends in Race Relations. Vol. 3, No. 1 &amp; 2. August-September 1945.</item>
                        <item>A Monthly Summary of Events and Trends in Race Relations. Vol. 3, No. 3. October 1945.</item>
                        <item>A Monthly Summary of Events and Trends in Race Relations. Vol. 3, No. 4. November 1945.</item>
                        <item>A Monthly Summary of Events and Trends in Race Relations. Vol. 3, No. 5. December 1945.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref70" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Negro Labor</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319069" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref159">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Negro Champion. Vol. 1, No. 3. October 17, 1925.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref71" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-New York (City)-Metropolitan Museum of Art.</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319070" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref160">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Metropolitan Museum of Art. January 1969.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref72" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Opportunity</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319071" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref161">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 5, No. 6. June 1927.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 7, No. 7. July 1929.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 9, No. 5. May 1931.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 9, No. 6. June 1931.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 10, No. 1. January 1932.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 10, No. 2. February 1932.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 10, No. 3. March 1932.</item>
                        <item>Opportunity. Vol. 10, No. 4. April 1932.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref73" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Panther 21 Trial News</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319072" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref162">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 1. September 7-10, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. September 14-17, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 3. September 21-24, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 4. September 28-October 1, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 5. October 5-8, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 6. October 12-15, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 7. October 19-22, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 9. November 2-5, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 10. November 9-12, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 11. November 16-19, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 12. November 23-26, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 13. November 30-December 3, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 14. December 7-10, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 15. December 14-17, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 16. December 21-24, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 17. December 28-31, 1970.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 18. January 4-7, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 19. January 11-14, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 20. January 18-22, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 21. January 25-28, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 23. February 8-11, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 24. February 17-19, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 25. February 22-25, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 26. March 1-4, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 27. March 8-11, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 28-29. March 15-18 &amp; 22-25, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 30. March 29-April 1, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 32. April 12-14, 1971.</item>
                        <item>Committee to Defend the Panthers. Panther 21 Trial News. No. 35. May 3-6 &amp; 10-13, 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref74" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Playbill</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319073" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref163">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Playbill. Buck White. Vol. 6, No. 12. undated.</item>
                        <item>Playbill. Purple. Vol. 7, No. 4. undated.</item>
                        <item>Playbill. Le Ballets Africains. Vol. 7, No. 8. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref75" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Playfare</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319074" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref164">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Playfare. Vol. 2, No. 3. March 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref76" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Political Affairs</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319075" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref165">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Political Affairs. The Battle For Black Liberation. Vol. 47, No. 2. February 1968.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref77" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Race Relations Journal</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319076" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-11</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref166">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Race Relations Journal. Vol. 19, No 2. 1952.</item>
                        <item>Race Relations Journal. Vol. 20, No. 2. 1953.</item>
                        <item>Race Relations Journal. Vol. 21, No. 1. 1954.</item>
                        <item>Race Relations Journal. Vol. 23, No. 1. 1956.</item>
                        <item>Race Relations Journal. Vol. 23, No. 4. 1956.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref78" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Race Relations Reporter</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319077" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-12</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref167">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Race Relations Reporter. Vol. 2, No. 10. June 7, 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref79" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Rights</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319078" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-13</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref168">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Rights. Vol. 13, No. 2. April-June 1966.</item>
                        <item>Rights. Vol. 11, No. 5. October-November, 1964.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref80" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Spear</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319079" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-14</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref169">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Spear. March 1972.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref81" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-Spirit</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319080" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-15</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref170">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Spirit Publications. Spirit. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref82" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Publications-The Word</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319081" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">6-16</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref171">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Word. Vol. 1, No. 3. 1971.</item>
                        <item>The Word. Vol. 1, No. 4. 1971.</item>
                        <item>The Word. 1971.</item>
                        <item>The Word. Vol. 1, No. 5. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref83" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Race Problems, No. 1-20</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319082" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref172">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>NAACP Education Department. Integrated School Books. 1967.</item>
                        <item>PR&amp;R COmmittee on Civil and Human Rights of Educators. A Bibliography of Multi-Ethnic Textbooks and Supplementary Materials. undated.</item>
                        <item>Voltaire Flugschrift. Vol. 24. 1969.</item>
                        <item>A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund. Separatism or Integration: Which Way for America? October 1968.</item>
                        <item>RObert S. Brown. Should the U.S. Be Partitioned. June 1968.</item>
                        <item>Robert A. Brown and Robert Vernon. On Black Separatism. January 1972.</item>
                        <item>Mayor's Committee on Race Relations. Home Front Unity in Chicago. May-June 1945.</item>
                        <item>Los Angeles Committee for Defense of the Bill of Rights. Defense. 1968.</item>
                        <item>People's Progressive Party. This Too is U.S.A. September 1965.</item>
                        <item>Claude M. Lightfoot. The Civil War and Black Liberation Today. February 1969.</item>
                        <item>Little Blue Book No. 1820. How the Understand the Negro Problem. 1943.</item>
                        <item>James Forman. High Tide of Black Resistance. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Monthly Labor Review. The Negro's Journey to the City. May-June 1965.</item>
                        <item>James E. Jackson. At the Funeral of Medgar Evers. July 1963.</item>
                        <item>A. Philip Randolph Education Fund. A. Philip Randolph: Labor's Grand Old Man. May 1969.</item>
                        <item>Angela Davis. Get It Together. March 23, 1971. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Council on African Affairs. For Freedom and Peace. June 19, 1949.</item>
                        <item>Paul Robeson. Forge Negro-Labor Unity for Peace and Jobs. August 1950.</item>
                        <item>Liberation Support Movement Constitution. May 1970.</item>
                        <item>Benjamin J. Davis. The Path of Negro Liberation. April 1947.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. The Christian Century. 1956.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref84" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Race Problems, No. 21-40</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319083" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref173">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>NAACP. The Day They Changed Their Minds. March 1960.</item>
                        <item>Universal Negro Improvement Association. Aims and Objects of Movement for SOlution of Negro Problem Outlined. 1924.</item>
                        <item>Little Blue Book No. 650. KKK: The Kreed of the Klansmen. undated.</item>
                        <item>Tom Hayden &amp; Carl Wittman. An Interracial Movement of the Poor? undated.</item>
                        <item>Jessie P. Guzman and Woodrow W. Hall. Desegragation and the Southern States. 1957.</item>
                        <item>Anarchy: Los Angeles. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Police Terror in Harlem. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bobby K's Freedom Bruiser. Oxford Victim Tells Story. undated.</item>
                        <item>Truman Nelson. People with Strength. undated.</item>
                        <item>Facing Reality Publishing Company. Detroit: The July Days. undated.</item>
                        <item>Socialist Workers Party. The Black Uprisings. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Public Affairs Pamphlet. Race Riots Aren't Necessary. No. 106. 1945.</item>
                        <item>Robert F. Williams. Listen, Borther. September 1968.</item>
                        <item>Christain Crusade Publications. "Burn, Baby, Burn!" Is Your City Next? undated.</item>
                        <item>John Humphrey. Violence and Revolution Are Not Synonymous. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ernie Chambers. Black Fury. undated.</item>
                        <item>House of Un-American Activities COmmittee: Bulwark of Segregation. 1963.</item>
                        <item>NAACP. Segregation: Disgrace for Democracy. 1953.</item>
                        <item>James P. Dees. The Destroyers. undated.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Psychology of Racial Prejudice. August 1969.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref85" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Race Problems, No. 41-60</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319084" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref175">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. The Meaning of Race. 1961.</item>
                        <item>V. Mazov. End Colonial and Racial Crimes. 1971.</item>
                        <item>W.E.B. DuBois Clubs of America. War, Racism, the Movement: As We See It. January 1968.</item>
                        <item>August Claessens. Race Prejudice. 1943.</item>
                        <item>National Council of Jewish Communists. James W. Ford. Anti-Semitism and the Struggle for Democracy. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>The South African Institute of Race Relations. Prejudice in Modern Perspective. 1956.</item>
                        <item>Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders. undated.</item>
                        <item>Byram Campbell. The New Mythology of Racial Equality. undated.</item>
                        <item>International Association for the Advancement of Ethnology and Eugenics. Some Neglected Aspects of the 'Minorities' Problem. 1963.</item>
                        <item>The Nation. September 27, 1952. undated.</item>
                        <item>Imperial Fascist League. Race and Politics. 1938.</item>
                        <item>Bettina Aptheker and Herbert Aptheker. Racism and Reaction in the United States: Two Marxian Studies. 1971. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Herbert Aptheker. America's Racist Laws. 1951.</item>
                        <item>William Van Til. Prejudiced-How Do People Get That Way? undated.</item>
                        <item>Commission on Interracial Cooperation, Inc. The Interracial Commission COmes of Age. September 1940.</item>
                        <item>Negro Publication Society of America. Race and Culture Series No. 1. Should Negroes and Jews Unite? 1943.</item>
                        <item>American Committee Against Racism. Racism and Immorality of the Negro Leaders and Their Supporters. undated.</item>
                        <item>Annual Report of the A. Philip Randolph Institute. 1970.</item>
                        <item>The International Association for the Advancement of Ethnology and Eugenics. Klineberg's Chapter on Race and Psychology.: A Review. July 1960.</item>
                        <item>News and Letters. Freedom Riders Speak for Themselves. November 1961.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref86" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Race Problems, No. 61</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319085" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref176">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Genocide in America. undated.</item>
                        <item>Chicago Tribune. Mayor Welch's Letter to Shriver Links Poverty Funds and 'Revolution'. September 30.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Realism in Race Relations. 1962.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Race Relations East and West. 1953.</item>
                        <item>A National Council for Civil Liberties Publication. Prejudice or Principal: The Government's Policy on Race. undated.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Human Dignity and Race Relations. 1966.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Colour and Christian Community. 1945.</item>
                        <item>Liverpool Youth Organisations Committee. Special But Not Separate. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commissions. undated.</item>
                        <item>Jonathan Power. Colour and Citizenship. 1969. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Race Relations in Britain. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Fabian Research Series. Policies for Racial Equality. November 1969.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. The Race Relations Act 1968. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. The Young Englanders. July 1969.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Health and Welfare of the Immigrant Child. undated.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Public Health Aspects of Immigration. January 1970.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Stationery Office. Report of the Community Relations Commission. 1969-1970.</item>
                        <item>Community Relations Commission. Summary of CRC Report for 1969-1970.</item>
                        <item>National Committee for Commonwealth Immigrants. The housing of Commonwealth Immigrants. August 1968.</item>
                        <item>Labour Research Department. Powell and His Allies. undated.</item>
                        <item>Association for Childhood Education International. Children of Resurrection City. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref87" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>SEDFRE (Scholarship, Education and Defense Fund for Racial Equality)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319086" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref177">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Scholarship, Education and Defense Fund for Racial Equality. Newletter. undated.</item>
                        <item>Scholarship, Education and Defense Fund for Racial Equality. Ten Years of Building Self Reliance. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref88" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>SRC (Southern Regional Council)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319087" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref178">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council. The Southern Regional Council: Its Origin and Purpose. June 1944.</item>
                        <item>Voter Education Project of the Southern Regional Council. Black Elected Officials in the Southern States. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Voter Education Project Southern Regional Council. Southwide Conference of Black Elected Officials. December 11-14, 1968.</item>
                        <item>Voter Education Project. undated.</item>
                        <item>Voter Education Project. Letter. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref89" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>South</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319088" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref179">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>John Gates. The South. September 1948.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Committee of the Social Science Research Council. The South's Place in the Nation. 1941.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council. Wanted: A Healthy South. 1946.</item>
                        <item>South Today. Buying a New World with Old Confederate Bills. 1943.</item>
                        <item>South Today. There Are Things To Do. 1942-1943.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Council. Safety, Security, and the South. undated.</item>
                        <item>Highlander Folk School Occasional Papers. The New Agenda for the White Southerner In His New South. August 1960.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref90" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Theater</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319089" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref180">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Afro Arts, Inc. A Black Quartet. undated.</item>
                        <item>The American Negro Theatre. "Tin Top Valley". 1947.</item>
                        <item>Ghana Playhouse. Souvenir Programme. undated.</item>
                        <item>Belasco Theatre. 1944.</item>
                        <item>The negro Ensemble Company. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref91" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Universities and Colleges</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1319090" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">7-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref181">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>South Carolina State College. Miller F. Whitaker Library. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Fisk university News. February 1916.</item>
                        <item>Butler College. Butler College Bulletin. 1941-1942.</item>
                        <item>Boston University. Martin Luther King, Jr. Afro-American Center Pre-Orientation Booklet.</item>
                        <item>Fisk University. Appointment Calendar. 1951.</item>
                        <item>Boston University Afro-American Center. Progress Report. October 21, 1970.</item>
                        <item>General Legislative Investigation Committee. Report to the Mississippi State Legislature. September 30, 1962.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref187" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series II: Africa</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref189" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Apartheid; Algeria</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref276">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Jacques Soubeyrol. l'Action Internationale Contre l'Apartheid. 1965.</item>
                        <item>International Commission of Jurists. Apartheid in South Africa and South West Africa. June 1967.</item>
                        <item>American Committee on Africa. War in Algeria: Is Confederation the Answer? undated.</item>
                        <item>Labour Research Department. South Africa Apartheid and Britain. 1970.</item>
                        <item>United Nations General Assembly. The Nature and Techniques of South African Racist Propaganda. August 1986.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref190" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Britain in Africa; Burundi</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref277">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>M.J. Christie. The Simonstown Agreements. September 1970.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Notice d'Information. undated.</item>
                        <item>British Information Services. African Challenge. 1945.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache Burundi. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Barbara Rogers. South Africa's Stake in Britain. June 1971.</item>
                        <item>The African Publications Trust. Capital for Africa: The British Contribution. November 1971.</item>
                        <item>British African Land Utilization Conference. Final Report. November 1949.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref191" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cameroon; Chad; Churches; Congo; Dahomey</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref278">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache Cameroun. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Notice d'Information. Dahomey. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Notice d'Information. Cameroun. undated.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encylopedie Africaine et Malgache. Dahomey. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Notice D'information. Tchad. undated.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Petite Encyclopedie. Africaine et Malgache. Tchad. undated.</item>
                        <item>L'agence Economique des Colonies Autonomes du Cameroun et de L'Afrique Equatoriale Francaise. Le Cameroun. undated.</item>
                        <item>J. Angounou Mvele. Je Ne Peux Pas Manger. 1962.</item>
                        <item>l'Union Generale des Etudiants Congolais. Premier Congres de l'UGEC. May 1961.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Notice Dinformation. Congo-Brazzaville. undated.</item>
                        <item>Eric Wright. Behind the Lion Mountains. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Centre d'Information et de Documentation du Congo et du Ruanda-Urundi. l'Economie du Congo Belge et du Ruanda-Urundi. September 1954.</item>
                        <item>Fonds Colonial des Invalidates. La Securite Sociale au Congo Belge. 1954.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Petite Encyclopedie. Africaine et Malgache. Republique Democratique du Congo. undated.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Petite Encyclopedie. Africaine et Malgache. Republique du Congo. undated.</item>
                        <item>Jean Van Lierde. La Revolution Non-Violente au Congo. February 1960.</item>
                        <item>Georges Varron. Le Noeud de la Crise Congolaise. undated.</item>
                        <item>Richard Gott. Mobutus Congo. January 1968.</item>
                        <item>Pierre Houart. Quatre Annees Qui Menerent a l'Independance du Congo. 1960.</item>
                        <item>Service d'Education de l'Armee Nationale Congolaise. Armee Nationale Congolaise. 1961.</item>
                        <item>La Societe Nationale d'Electricite et lamenagement hydro-electique d'INGA. May 1971.</item>
                        <item>Republique de Dahomey. Message a la Nation de M. Le President de la Republique Chef de l'etat. January 1964.</item>
                        <item>Contribution a l'Etude du Determinisme Fontionnel de l'Industrie dans l'Education de l'Indigene Congolais. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref192" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Education; Egypt</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358004" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref279">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>D.W. Ewer. Zoology: Should It Exist? November 1969.</item>
                        <item>K.R. McKilliam. A Handbook for Literacy Teachers. 1970.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Education for Progress. 1971.</item>
                        <item>University of Ibadan Insititute of Education. Human Ecology and Education. 1970.</item>
                        <item>University of Ibadan Insitute of Education. Efik and Ibibio Villages. 1971.</item>
                        <item>Southern Africa Education Fund. Education for Apartheid. undated.</item>
                        <item>R.M. Gregory. The Teaching of Homecraft. 1958.</item>
                        <item>Ahmadu Bello University Press. The Relevance of the University to Our Society. 1972.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Education 1961-1971: A Balance Sheet. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Modupe Oduyoye. Yoruba Numeration System. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Modern English Readers. Emeka-Driver's Guard. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Department of Overseas Trade. Report on the Economic and Financial Situation of Egypt. June 1926.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref193" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Ethiopia; Foreign Countries</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358005" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref280">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>James W. Ford &amp; Harry Gannes. War in Africa: Italian Fascism Prepares to Enslave Ethiopia. 1935.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Information. Patterns of Progress: Education in Ethiopia. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Ethiopian Students Union in North America. Challenge: Journal of the World-Wide Union of Ethiopian Students. February 1970.</item>
                        <item>The British Society for International Understanding. The British Survey. June 1961.</item>
                        <item>Belgian Government Information Center. A Ten Year Plan for the Belgian Trust Territory of Ruanda Urundi. 1952.</item>
                        <item>Journal of the Royal African Society. The Claim for the Colonies: A French View. April 1937.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Information. Financial and Fiscal Policy of Ethiopia. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Information. National Defence of Ethiopia. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Ethiopian Students Union in North America. Repression in Ethiopia. January 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref194" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>France in Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358006" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref281">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occidentale Francais. Le Developpement de l'Agriculture et les Grands Produits Naturels d'Exportation. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. Les Chemins de Fer de l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. 1931.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref195" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>General &amp; History</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358007" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref282">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Tom Mboya. Conflict and Nationhood. Septmeber 1963.</item>
                        <item>Jock Campbell. The New Africa: Pride and Prejudice; Sense and Sensibility. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Freedopm Press. Tragedy in Africa: A Warning and a Challenge. June 1950.</item>
                        <item>The House of Commons. Colonial Development and Welfare Acts. May 1954.</item>
                        <item>Dissent. Vol. 3, No. 3. 1956.</item>
                        <item>East and West. The Rape of Africa. Vol. 5, No. 35. 1961.</item>
                        <item>Librairie Generale de Droit et de Jurisprudence. Les Partis Politiques Africains. 1961.</item>
                        <item>Provisional Secretariat of the Organization of African Unity. Basic Documents of the Organization of African Unity. May 1963.</item>
                        <item>African History. Vol. 1, No. 1. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Histoire de l'Afrique. Africaine et Malgache. undated.</item>
                        <item>Francois Maspero. Guide Politique des etats Africains.</item>
                        <item>Pierre Houart. L'Eglise et l'Emancipation Africaine. 1959.</item>
                        <item>Coleccion Monografica Africana. El Proximo Congreso de Prehistoria Africana y El Futuro de la Apotacion Espanola. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Les Communes, Gardiennes, Vigilantes et Loyales des Acquis de la Revolution. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Insitituo de Estudios Africanos. Africa en la Postguerra. 1961.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref196" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Ghana</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref283">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Kwame Nkrumah. The Way Out. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Pioneer Series. Owura Nico. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Republic of Ghana. The State of Ghana's Economy Today. August 1967.</item>
                        <item>Pioneer Series. The Story of Sampson Opong the Prophet. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Institute of African Studies. Research Review. Vol. 4, No. 3. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Ministry of Information. Christiansborg Castle-Osu. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Colonial Office. The Proposed Constitution of Ghana. February 1957.</item>
                        <item>The Ministry of Information. The Rebirth of Ghana. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Ebenezer Babatrope. The Struggle Continues. undated.</item>
                        <item>Z.I. Sadowski. Population Growth and the Strategy of Economic Development. January 1969.</item>
                        <item>Anowuo Educational Publications. Ghanaian Favourite Dishes. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ghana Association of Teachers of English. The New Generation: Prose and Verse from the Secondary Schools and Training Colleges of Ghana. 1967.</item>
                        <item>The Ministry of Information. Two Years After Liberation.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref197" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Guinea</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358009" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref284">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Francisco Artur Mendes. Vida Material Dos Brames. 1948.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. Le Guinee Francaise. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Francisco Artur Mendes. A Habitacao dos Papeis. 1948.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Freedom in Mozambique, Angola, and Guine. Our People Are Our Mountains. undated.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Guinee. undated.</item>
                        <item>John Biggs-Davison. Portuguese Guinea: Nailing a Lie. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref198" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Individuals; Ivory Coast</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358010" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">8-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref285">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Information and Tourism Division of the Office of the Military Governor. Colonel Mobolaji O. Johnson: Humanist in Uniform. undated.</item>
                        <item>Crownbird Series. Our Pioneers. No. 6. undated.</item>
                        <item>Marianill Mission Press. The Founder of Marian Hill. undated.</item>
                        <item>Friends Peace and International Relations Committee. Non-violence in Action Series. The Significance of John Woolman for Southern Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>FRELIMO. Anniversary of the Death of Josina Machel. undated.</item>
                        <item>Liberation Support Movement. Memorandum of Activities of Medical Serices of the Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola in the Liberated Regions of the Eastern Front. June 1970.</item>
                        <item>Real Life Stories. I Was a Juju Priest. 1971.</item>
                        <item>M. Entwistle. Where the White Men Died. undated.</item>
                        <item>Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Cote d'Ivorie. undated.</item>
                        <item>Hucheshwar G. Mudgal. Marcus Garvey: Is He the True Redeemer of the Negro? 1932.</item>
                        <item>Christian Action. Bram Fischer, Q.C. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pelo Imperio Lisboa. Conselheiro Dr. Antonio Teixeira de Sousa. 1937.</item>
                        <item>Pelo Imperio Lisboa. O Explorador Serpa Pinto. 1936.</item>
                        <item>Jean Jadot. Un Grand Artisan du Katanga. 1950.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occidentale Francaise. La Cote d'Ivorie. 1931.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref199" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Katanga; Kenya</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358011" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref287">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Office National de la Recherche et du Developpement. A Propos de l'Electrification de la Voie Ferree Bas-Congo-Katanga. 1970.</item>
                        <item>British Information Services. Kenya. September 1963.</item>
                        <item>Republic of Kenya. Planning for Progress: Our Second Development Plan. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Humphrey Slade. The Parlaiment of Kenya. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Republic of Kenya. The Policy on Trade Union Organization in Kenya. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Colony and Protectorate of Kenya. Views of the Secretary of State for the Colonies on Kenya's Future. 1959.</item>
                        <item>Contribution a l'etude de l'etat de nutrition des enfants au Katanga. 1959.</item>
                        <item>L'Union Miniere. 1954.</item>
                        <item>The Journal of the Kenya Institute of Administration. Administration in Kenya. December 1965. undated.</item>
                        <item>Margaret P. Anderson. East Africa Today. 1964.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref200" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Lesotho</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358012" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref288">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>British Information Services. Lesotho. July 1966.</item>
                        <item>Commonwealth Relations Office. Basutoland Report on Constitutional Discussions. January 1959.</item>
                        <item>Margaret L. Hodgson and W.G. Ballinger. Indirect Rule in Southern Africa. Basutoland. May 1931.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref201" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Literature</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358013" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref289">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Adult Litercacy Organizing Center. In the Beginning. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Journal of Literacy and Cultural Analysis. The Conch. Vol. 1, No. 2. September 1969.</item>
                        <item>Samuel Nkamgnia. Jeunesse et Patrie Poemes. undated.</item>
                        <item>Pierre Jean Oswald. Hymnes et Sagessse. undated.</item>
                        <item>Kadima-Nzuji. Les Ressacs Poemes. undated.</item>
                        <item>Lettres Congolaises. Murmures Poemes. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref202" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Madagascar; Malawi; Mali; Mauritania; Mauritus</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358014" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref290">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Commonwealth Office. Electoral Registration in Mauritius. 1967.</item>
                        <item>South Africa Institute of Race Relations. Doctor or Witch-Doctor? The Old Medicine and the New. 1943.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Madagascar. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Mali. undated.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Mali. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Madagascar et Somalie. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Petite Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Mauritanie. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Central Office of Information Reference Pamphlet. Malawi. April 1964.</item>
                        <item>Notice Illustree. Madagascar &amp; Dependances. undated.</item>
                        <item>Commonwealth Office. Mauritus General Election 1967. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Malawi Government Information Department. Malawi: Land of Promise. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref203" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Military</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358015" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref291">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Department of Political Science and Public Administration of Makerere University College. Conflicting Images of the Military in Africa. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Mohamed Omer Beshir. The Mercenaries and Africa. 1972.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref204" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Mozambique</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358016" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref292">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale. Colonia de Mocambique Territoire de Manica et Sofala. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale. Portugal: Colonie de Mocambique Le Commerce. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Lourenco Marquea. Camara do Comerio de Lourenco Marques. 1966.</item>
                        <item>International Defence and Aid Fund. Terror in Tete. 1973.</item>
                        <item>Mistica Imperial. Cadernos Coloniais. undated.</item>
                        <item>Atlandtida Editora. Mae Negra. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale. Colonie de Mocambique Services de l'Armee. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Committee for Freedom in Mozambique. Mozambique: A Country at War. undated.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniale. Colonia de Mocambique Territoire de Manica et Sofala. Cadastre. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniale. Colonia de Mocambique Territoire de Manica et Sofala. Administration et Finances. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniai. Colonia de Mocambique Territorie de Manica et Sofala. Ports du Territoire et Moyens de Communication. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniai. Colonia de Mocambique Territorie de Manica et Sofala. Le Sol et Le Climat. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale. Colonie de Mocambique. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniai. Colonia de Mocambique Territorie de Manica et Sofala. Assistance Medicale. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniai. Colonia de Mocambique Territorie de Manica et Sofala. Instruction. 1931.</item>
                        <item>L'Exposition Coloniaie. Colonia de Mocambique Territorie de Manica et Sofala. Agriculture et Elevage. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Baltazar Pereira Co Lago. Cadernos Coloniais. undated.</item>
                        <item>Comissao de Administracao Urbana. A Cidade Da Beira. 1934.</item>
                        <item>The Africa Bureau. South-WEst Africa (Namibia): Proposal for Action. 1970.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref205" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Namibia</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358017" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref293">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Housmans London. Namibia: A Call to be Answered. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Africa Bureau. South-West Africa (Namibia): Proposals for Action. 1970.</item>
                        <item>International Defence and Aid Fund. A Dwelling Place of Our Own. 1973.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref206" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Nigeria</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358018" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">9-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref294">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Federal Ministry of Information. Establishing a Business in Nigeria. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Western Region of Nigeria. Development of the Western Region of Nigeria 1955-1960. 1960.</item>
                        <item>S.A. Rajih. The Complete Story of Nigeria Civil War for Unity. 1971.</item>
                        <item>Federal Republic of Nigeria. University Development in Nigeria. Report of the National Universities Commission. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Information Department of Nigeria. Midwestern Nigeria Handbook. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Nigerian Economic Society. The Nigerian Revolution 1966-1976. 1973.</item>
                        <item>Nigeria Tourist Association. Nigeria Tourist guide. undated.</item>
                        <item>Bureau de Liaison des Agents de Cooperation Technique. Niger. undated.</item>
                        <item>Proclamation of the Republic of Biafra. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Education of Nigeria. A Hausa Village. undated.</item>
                        <item>Federation of Nigeria. Respect for Human Dignity. November 1960.</item>
                        <item>The Concern of the Christian in the Civil War. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ibadan University Press. Ibadan University Library. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Federal Republic of Nigeria. Framework for Settlement. The Federal Case in Kampala. undated.</item>
                        <item>Ibadan University Press. The Issues at Stake: Nigeria 1967. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Embassy of Nigeria. Nigeria. undated.</item>
                        <item>Housmans. Biafra-Britain in the Dock. undated.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Report of the Observer Team to Nigeria. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Staionary Office. Nigeria Constitutional Discussions, May 1960. June 1960.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Nigeria: The Problem of Relief in the Aftermath of the Nigerian Civil War. January 1970.</item>
                        <item>Little Blue Book No. 797. Twenty Years Among African Negroes. undated.</item>
                        <item>African Achievement and Tragedy. Tarikh. 1968.</item>
                        <item>A.H.M. Kirk-Greene. Maiduguri and the Capitals of Bornu. 1958.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref207" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Pan-Africanism</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358019" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref295">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Tony Thomas &amp; Robert Allen. Two Views on Pan-Africanism. January 1972.</item>
                        <item>The Mission to Europe and the Africas. P.A.C. in Perspective. February 1973.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref297" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Portugal in Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1376001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref298">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Cabora Bassa &amp; the Struggle for Southern Africa: Portugal. November 1971.</item>
                        <item>Mesquitela Lima. Alguns Aspectos Sociologicos da Colonizacao. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Internation Defence and Aid Fund. Portugal's Wars in Africa. May 1972.</item>
                        <item>Agencia Geral Do Ultramar. Armando Cortesao. Realides y Deliros Africanos. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Agencia Geral Do Ultramar. Armando Cortesao. African Realities and Delusions. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Rapport destine a l'Exposition Coloniale et Maritime d'Anvers de 1930. Armando Goncalves Pereira. Le Portugal au point de vue colonial. 1930.</item>
                        <item>S.J. Bosgra &amp; Chr. van Krimpen. Portugal and NATO. October 1969.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Rui Patricio. Portugal in Africa. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Ministerio das colonias. Industria de manipulacao de tabacos nas colonias de Angola e Mocambique. 1944.</item>
                        <item>Agencia Geral Do Ultramar. Sobre a Expansao do Livro Portugues Nas Provincias Ultraamarinas. 1953.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref208" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Rhodesia, Rwanda</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358020" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref296">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Africa Fund. Rhodesia or Zimbabwe: No Middle Ground in Africa. September 1969.</item>
                        <item>Africa Bureau. Robert B. Sutcliffe. Sanctions Against Rhodesia. 21 January 1966.</item>
                        <item>Colonial Office. L.P. Mair. Native Administration in Central Nyasaland. 1952.</item>
                        <item>United Nations. A Principal in Torment:I-The United Nations and Southern Rhodesia. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Edgard Santos Mattos. Assim Nasceua. Rhodesia. undated.</item>
                        <item>George Nyandoro. Zapu Zimbabwe. 1973.</item>
                        <item>Interviews in Depth. Zimbabwe Zapu. George Silundika. 1974.</item>
                        <item>Aaron Segal. Massacre in Rwanda. April 1964.</item>
                        <item>International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa. Report on the Education Scheme for Detainees, Restrictees and Convicted Political Prisoners and Their Defendants in Rhodesia. November 1970.</item>
                        <item>Edward Batson. The Poverty Line in Salisbury. 1945.</item>
                        <item>Southern African Research Office. Rhodesia: Proposals for a Sell-Out. 1972.</item>
                        <item>Eshmael Mlambo. No Future Without Us: The Story of the African National Council in Zimbabwe. undated.</item>
                        <item>Lady Craufurd. Seeing is Believing. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Lady Craufurd. Six Letters from Rhodesia. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Federal Information Department. A New Life in the Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Africa Bureau. Ken Brown. Land in Southern Rhodesia. 1959.</item>
                        <item>M.I. Hirsch. Focus on Southern Rhodesia. May 1964.</item>
                        <item>Blantyre Church. Blantyre Church. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref209" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Russia in Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358021" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref299">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Central Asian Research Centre. Russia Looks at Africa. 1960.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref210" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Senegal; Seychelles</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358022" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref300">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Republique Democratique de Congo Ministre de l'Information. Message du President de la Republique au Parti Frere du Senegal. 14 February 1971.</item>
                        <item>Tele Africa. Senghor Senegal. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Commonwealth Office. Seychelles: Proposals for Constitutional Advance. 1967.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref211" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>South Africa; SW Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358023" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref301">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Arthur English Camera. Southern Cape. undated.</item>
                        <item>African National Congress. Forward to Freedom. 1955.</item>
                        <item>State Information Office of South Africa. South Africa's Heritage. undated.</item>
                        <item>Southern Africa: A Time for Change. 1969.</item>
                        <item>Department of Justice of South Africa. South Africa in Fact. 1964.</item>
                        <item>World Horizon Reports. Robert J. Cunningham. A Brief Survey of Southern Africa. No. 14. 1956.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. Nuriel Horrell. Political Status of Non-Europeans in Southern Africa. 1953.</item>
                        <item>The Publicity &amp; Information Bureau of South Africa. African National Congress. undated.</item>
                        <item>The Africa Bureau. Lord Caradon. Southern Africa in International Relations. 8 December 1970.</item>
                        <item>Anti-Apartheid Movement. Labours Record on Southern Africa. 1964.</item>
                        <item>International Defence and Aid Fund. The Sun Will Rise. 1974.</item>
                        <item>Gordon Lawrie. New Light on South West Africa. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Friends Home Service Committee. The Future of South Africa. August 1965.</item>
                        <item>Christian Action. I Am Prepared to Die. undated.</item>
                        <item>South African Institute of Race Relations. D.V. Cowen. Liberty, Equailty, Fraternity-Today. 1961.</item>
                        <item>The International Defence and Aid Fund. South Africa: Trial by Torture. May 1970.</item>
                        <item>Sharpeville and After Suppression and Liberation in Southern Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>South Africa Institute of Race Relations. Swaziland. 1955.</item>
                        <item>The South West Africa People's Organizaton. The Namibian Documentation.</item>
                        <item>The Africa 1960 Committee. Mandate in Trust. 1960.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref212" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Sudan, Spain in Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358024" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref302">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Ediciones de la Direccion General de Marruecos y Colonias y Del Instituto de Estudios Africanos. undated.</item>
                        <item>Osman Hassan Saeed. The Industrial Bank of Sudan. 1962-1968. February 1971.</item>
                        <item>Exposition Coloniale Internationale de Paris Commissariat de l'Afrique Occientale Francaise. Le Soudan Francais. 1941.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref213" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Tanzania; Togo; Upper Volta</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358025" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-8</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref303">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Tanganyika African National Union. Tanzania: Party Guidelines. March 1973.</item>
                        <item>Africa Bureau. The State of Anglo-Tanzanian Relations. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Nutrition in Eastern Africa. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Central Office of Information of the United Kingdom. Zanzibar. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Colojnial Office. Alan T. Peacock &amp; Douglass G.M. Dosser. The National Income of Tanganyika 1952-54. 1958.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Haute Volta. undated.</item>
                        <item>East African Literature Bureau. Occasional Papers on Community Development-1. 1962.</item>
                        <item>Revised Development and Welfare Plan for Tanganyika. 1951.</item>
                        <item>Larousse. Petite Encyclopedie Africaine et Malgache. Togo. 1964.</item>
                        <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Tanganyika: A Story of Progress. 1961.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref214" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Uganda</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358026" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-9</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref304">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>C. J. Wilson. Uganda in the Days of Bishop Tucker. 1955.</item>
                        <item>IMC Research Pamphlets. John V. Taylor. Process of Growth in an African Church. 1958.</item>
                        <item>E.C. Lanning. Uganda'a Past. 1957.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref215" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Zambia</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358027" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">10-10</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref305">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Edith Dahlshcen. Women in Zambia. 1970.</item>
                        <item>National Food and Nutrition Commission. Nutrition in Zambia. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Africa Bureau. Mike Faber. Zambia-The Moulding of a Nation. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Adult Education Association of Zambia. Adult Education and Political and Social Change. undated.</item>
                        <item>The National Monuments Commission of Zambia. Digging Up History. 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref377" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Topics in Africa</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1810001" type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref379">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Liberation Support Movement Interview on Angola. Spartacus Monimambu. undated.</item>
                        <item>The African Repository and Colonial Journal. Vol. 18, No. 13. November 1842.</item>
                        <item>W.E.B. DuBois. Little Blue Book No. 1505. Africa, Its Geography, People and Products. 1930.</item>
                        <item>W.E.B. DuBois. Little Blue Book No. 1552. Africa-Its Place in Modern History. undated.</item>
                        <item>Department of Tourism. Botswana. A Living Heritage. undated.</item>
                        <item>Guy Clutton-Brock. Facing 1960 in Central Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>N. Numade. The African Revolution. 1963.</item>
                        <item>Republica Portuguesa Ministerio Das Colonias. Angola Nos Ultimos Anos. 1936.</item>
                        <item>Jacob Degia. African History. Vol. 1. 1970.</item>
                        <item>Roy Harvey. People's War in Angola. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Alphaeus Hunton. Africa Fights for Freedom. March 1950.</item>
                        <item>The African Communist. Africa in America. Vol. 2, No. 33. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Anti-Apartheid Movement. Human Rights and the Struggle Against Apartheid. Antonio de Figueiredo. Angola. 1968.</item>
                        <item>The Anti-Apartheid Movement. Human Rights and the Struggle Against Apartheid. London Representative of the South West Africa People's Organisation. Human Rights and Apartheid Policy in Namibia.</item>
                        <item>The Anti-Apartheid Movement. Human Rights and the Struggle Against Apartheid. Colin Legum. South Africa as a Threat to World Peace.</item>
                        <item>Liberation Support Movement. Movimento Popular de Libertacao de Angola. 1970.</item>
                        <item>R.I.M. Obioha. A Book for Nigerian Bachelors Guide. undated.</item>
                        <item>Sheena Duncan. The Plight of the Urban African. August 1970.</item>
                        <item>Moral Re-Armament. This Way Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>The African Empire Study Booklet. Dr. G. K. Osei. Fifty Unknown Facts About the African. May 1964.</item>
                        <item>Angola Comite. Petition Concerning the Report by Mr. Pierre Juvigny Regarding the Implementation of the Aboliton of Forced Labour Convention. 1957.</item>
                        <item>R. S. Rattray. Totemism and Blood Groups in West Africa. undated.</item>
                        <item>G. Mirsky and L. Stepanov. Asia and Africa: A New Era. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref188" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series III: West Indies</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref400" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Countries/Islands</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref216" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Antigua</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358028" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-1</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref315">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>James Hackshaw. Social &amp; Economic Planning in the Leeward &amp; Windward Islands. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Antigua. Public Order Act. No. 9. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Reginald St. Johnston. The Old Naval Dockyard, Antigua. undated.</item>
                            <item>Charles L. Henry. Geography of the State of Antigua and Outline of the West Indian Archipelago. undated.</item>
                            <item>Bessi Harper. A Short History of the Heads of Government of the Island of ANtigua. 1962.</item>
                            <item>R. Fitzpatrick. A Report on the Household Budget Survey in the Leeward and Windward Islands. 1961.</item>
                            <item>The Workers' Voice. The Antigua Labour Party Political Platform and Election Manifesto. 1960-1961.</item>
                            <item>The New Horizon Political Platform of the Antigua Labour Party. 1965-1970.</item>
                            <item>The Workers' Voice. Novelle H. Richards. The Struggle and the Conquest. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref217" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Barbados No. 1-12</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358029" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-2</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref316">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Local Governor Commissioner. Local Government in Barbados. undated.</item>
                            <item>Leroy Harewood. Rule of Fear in Barbados. 1968.</item>
                            <item>F.A. Hoyos. Background to Independence. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Black Star. Presentation of Candidate and Manifesto for the People's Progressive Movement of Bridgetown, Barbados . May 1969. (2 copies)</item>
                            <item>S.A. Hammond. The Preservation of Democracy in Barbados. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Bajan Magazine. Richard Allsopp. The Question of Barbadian Culture. October 1972.</item>
                            <item>Cole's Printery. Rules of the Barbados Progressive League Friendly Society. July 1940.</item>
                            <item>Barbados Labour Party. Manifesto of the Barbados Labour Party. 1971.</item>
                            <item>The Barbados Government Printing Office. A Plan for the Implementation and Administration of the Proposed Social Securty Scheme for Barbados. 1964.</item>
                            <item>The Barbados Government Printing Office. Biographical Notes and Notes on Places of Interest. February 1966.</item>
                            <item>McW. Todman. Report on a Customs Union of Barbados, the Leeward and Windward Islands. 1963.</item>
                            <item>The Housing Authority. Fourth Annual Report. 1 April 1959-31 March 1960.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref218" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Barbados No. 13-20</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358030" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-3</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref317">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Ministry of Agriculture. E.C. Pilgrim. The Role andand Structure of Agriculture in Barbados and the Development Programme. 1970.</item>
                            <item>The Sugar Industry of Barbados. Dr. C.Y. Shephard. 1946 Crop: Report on the New Method of Remunerating Cane Cutters. 1946.</item>
                            <item>The Sugar Industry of Barbados. A Method for Calculating the Price of Sugar-Cane. C.Y. Shephard. 1947.</item>
                            <item>The Sugar Industry of Barbados. Dr. C.Y. Shephard. Plantation Wages: Rates Recommended for 1946. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Ministry of Agriculture Barbados. Onions from a Possibility to a Reality in Barbados. January 1970.</item>
                            <item>Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries. L. Walter van Whervin. Ecology, Biology and Behaviour of Lixophaga Diatraeae Tns. May 1966.</item>
                            <item>Democratic Labour Party of Barbados. Democratic Labour Party: Ten Years of Service. 1966.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref219" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Barbados-unnumbered</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358031" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-4</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref318">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Black Star. Leroy Harewood. Black Power Lessness[sic] in Barbados. 1968.</item>
                            <item>The Barbados Government Printing Office. Barbados Independence Celebrations. Official Program of Events. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref220" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Cuba No. 1-14</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358032" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-5</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref319">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Cuban Revolutionary Government. First and Second Declaration of Havana. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cuban Ministry of Foreign Relations. Cuban Protest to the United Nations. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cuban Ministry of Foreign Relations. Fidel Castro Calls for unity. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Joseph North. Socialist Cuba. August 1971.</item>
                            <item>Union Labor. Canadian Students in Cuba. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Fair Play for Cuba Committee. The Real Cuba as Three Canadians Saw It. June 1964.</item>
                            <item>Jack Scott: Vancouver Sun Columnist Takes a Second Look at Cuba. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Arthur Gillette. Cuba's Educational Revolution. June 1972.</item>
                            <item>Harry Ring. How Cuba Uprooted Race Discrimination. June 1961.</item>
                            <item>Joseph Hansen. Trotskyism and the Cuban Revolution-An Answer to Hoy. October 1962.</item>
                            <item>James S. Allen. The Lessons of Cuba. May 1961.</item>
                            <item>The Declaration of Havana. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Pioneer Publishers. The Second Declaration of Havana. March 1962.</item>
                            <item>The Truth About Cuba Committee. Luis V. Manrara. Betrayal Opened the Door to Russian Missiles in Red Cuba. January 1968.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref221" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Cuba No. 15-26</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358033" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-6</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref320">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Young Socialist Forum. Castro Speaks on Unemployment. undated.</item>
                            <item>Foreign Languages Press. Closing Speech to the Congress of Women of the Americas. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Foreign Language Press. Speech at the Mass Rally in Celebration of the Fourth Anniversary of the Cuban Revolution. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Cuba's Socialist Destiny. July 26, 1961.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Some Problems of the Methods and Forms of Work of the Ori. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Declaration of Santiago. July 1964.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. A New Stage in the Advance of Cuban Socialism. undated.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Cuba Confronts the Future: Five Years of the Revolution. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Television Speech Delivered on November 1, 1962.</item>
                            <item>New Beginning Action Core. Women and the Cuban Revolution: Speeches by Fidel Castro. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cuban Student Directorate. Those Who Rebel and Those Who Submit. undated.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Those Who Are Not Revolutionary Fighters Cannot Be Called Communists. 1967.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref222" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Cuba No. 27-35</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358034" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-7</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref321">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Comision Seamana Maciesta. Antonio Maceo por Luis Varona. Decemeber 1969.</item>
                            <item>Directorio Magisterial Cubano. El Mensaje De Cuba en 10 Biografias. Vol. 1, No. 6. undated.</item>
                            <item>Tulio Diaz Rivera. Por Uno Solucion Historica Y A Dimension Cubana. undated.</item>
                            <item>Centro de Estudios Sindicales y Sociales Via Zucchelli. undated.</item>
                            <item>Antonio Capiro. Giron Pedazo de Historia y Cuatro Cuentos Cortos. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cruzada Femenina Cubana. El Comunismo Destruye la Familia en Cuba. undated.</item>
                            <item>F.O.R.D.C. La Seguridad Social en Cuba. undated.</item>
                            <item>Ediciones del Directorio Magisterial Cubano en el Exilio. La Mentira en la UNESCO. undated.</item>
                            <item>Dios, Patria y Libertad. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref223" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Cuba No. 36-44</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358035" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-8</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref322">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>FORDC. El Trabajo en Cuba Socialista. No. 5. undated.</item>
                            <item>Ediciones del Directorio Magisterial Cubano. Debe Mantenerse la Austonomia Universitaria. undated.</item>
                            <item>Ediciones del Directorio Magisterial Cubano. Como Se Apoderaron los Comunistas de la Universidad de la Habana. No. 23. undated.</item>
                            <item>Ediciones del Directorio Magisterial Cubano. Inocentes: En Defensa de los Estudiantes Universtarios Cubanos. undated.</item>
                            <item>Luis Perez Lopez. Asi Hablaba Cuba: Sus Dichos Populares. 1968.</item>
                            <item>AIP. La Agonia de Cuba 1959-1964. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Carlos Rafael Rodrigues. Jose Marti and Cuban Liberation. 1953.</item>
                            <item>The Life of Jose Marti. Nathaniel Weyl. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Marti y Nostros. Jorge Zayas. 1966.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref224" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Dominica</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358036" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-9</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref323">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Dominica. undated.</item>
                            <item>Dominican Royal Instructions for the Windward Islands. 1951.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref225" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Dominican Republic</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358037" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">11-10</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref324">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Wendell Phillips. Toussaint l'Ouverture. May 1966.</item>
                            <item>Staneley Walker. Generalissimo Rafael L. Trujillo. undated.</item>
                            <item>Alexis, Stephen; Leger, Abel-Nicolas; Mercier, Louis. Three Convincing Documents about Dominican Aggressions. 1937.</item>
                            <item>Republica Dominicana. Patents, Trademarks, and Copyright Laws in Dominican Republic. undated.</item>
                            <item>Victor Perlo. Marines in Santo Domingo. June 1965.</item>
                            <item>Santo Domino Hoy. Visitor Guide to Santo Domingo. undated.</item>
                            <item>Foreign Languages Press. Support the Dominican People's Resistance to U.S. Armed Aggression. 1965. (2 copies)</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref226" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Guadeloupe</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358038" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-1</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref325">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Pour la Guadeloupe Independante. Francois Maspero. 1970.</item>
                            <item>La Revue Francaise. La Guadeloupe. 1966.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref227" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Guyana No. 1-10</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358039" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-2</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref326">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Paul Singh. Guyana: Socialism in a Plural Society. October 1972.</item>
                            <item>T. Anson Sancho. Highlights of Guyanese History. undated.</item>
                            <item>Janet Jagan. Army Intervention in the 1973 Elections in Guyana. undated.</item>
                            <item>Norman E. Cameron. 150 Years of Education in Guyana (1808-1957). undated.</item>
                            <item>Feliz Cummings. Guyana Before the United Nations. undated.</item>
                            <item>L.F.A. Burnham. Report to the Nation on the First 6 Months of his Government's Term of Office: January-June 1965. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Norman E. Cameron. Clearing the Political Air. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Norman E. Cameron. An Introduction to our Social Philosophy. January 1965.</item>
                            <item>Education Committee of the People's Progressive Party. Cheddi Jagan. Socialism for Guyana. 1968.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref228" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Guyana No. 11-17</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358040" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-3</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref327">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Guy. E.L. DeWeever. The Children's Story of Guyana. 1932.</item>
                            <item>Cheddi Jagan. The Truth About Bauxite. 1971.</item>
                            <item>Cheddi Jagan. Border Conspiracy Exposed. 1968.</item>
                            <item>D.A. Percival &amp; W.P. D'Andrade. The National Economic Accounts of British Guiana (1948-1951). undated.</item>
                            <item>Edwina Melville. This is the Rupununi. 1956.</item>
                            <item>W.T. Lord. Guianese Travel Talks. 1957.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref229" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Guyana No. 18-23</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358041" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-4</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref328">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Peoples National Congress. The Premier Points to the New Horizon. 1964.</item>
                            <item>People's Progressive Party. 21 Years (1950-1971). undated.</item>
                            <item>Cheddi Jagan. The Coalition Exposed. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cheddi Jagan. A West Indian State: Pro-Imperialist or Anti-Imperialist. 1971.</item>
                            <item>N.E. Cameron. Adventures in the Field of Culture. 1971.</item>
                            <item>Cyril M. Kanhai. My New Guyana. 1969.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref230" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Haiti No. 1-10</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358042" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-5</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref329">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Henock Trouillot. Dessalines ou La Tragedie Post-Coloniale. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie du Seminaire Adventiste. Traits d'Union Enre Deux Tomes et 3eme These de Doctorat. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Jules Heraux. Short Summary of the History of Haiti from 1492-1948. undated.</item>
                            <item>Pavillons Industriels Stands et Magasins. Haiti: Exposition Internationale. undated.</item>
                            <item>Henri Deschamps. Les Noces de Diamant de Me Jerome Adhemar Auguste. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Yves Auguste. La Piene du Bannissement Doit Etre Bannie des Legislations Modernes. 1948.</item>
                            <item>James G. Leyburn. Les Deuz Castes. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Joseph D. Baguidy. Esquisse de Sociologie Haitienne. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Courrier Rouge Haitien M.L. Organe du Parti des Travailleurs Haitiens. Parti des Travailleurs Haitiens. July 1966.</item>
                            <item>Secretairerie d'etat de la Coordination et de l'Information. Paroles de Verite et de Foi. 1957.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref231" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Haiti No. 11-19</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358043" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-6</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref331">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Imprimerie de l'Etat. Dr. Francois Duvalier ou l'Exemple d'Une Vie. 1961.</item>
                            <item>Office National du Tourisme. Haitit et son Chef. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie do l'etat Port-Au-Prince. Emmanuel C. Paul. Culture, Language, Literature. 1954.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie de l'Etat Port-au-Prince. Le Drapeau Dessalinien. June 1964.</item>
                            <item>Les Presses Port-au-Princiennes. Le Role de la Jeune Fille Dans la Famille. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Publie Avec l'Autorisation du Ministere des Finances. Memento-Comptable Relatif a l'Impot Sur le Revenu en Haiti. June 1950.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie de l'Etat Port-au-Prince. Des Restrictions de Droits Dans Notre Regime Successoral. 1942.</item>
                            <item>Antoine Pierre-Paul. Les Contre-Verites d'une these a l'Ecole Normale Superieure et La Levee de Boucliers Dominicano-lecontiste de 1911. November 1963.</item>
                            <item>Gerard Daumec. Ma Reponse a Jacques St-Lot. 1957.</item>
                            <item>Joseph D. Baguidy. Esquisse de Sociologie Hatienne. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref232" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Haiti No. 20-24</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358044" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-7</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref332">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Les Araigness du Soir. Clef du Soliel. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Raphael H. Mehu. Breviare des Educateurs. 1959.</item>
                            <item>Eddy A. Jean &amp; Justin O. Fievre. Carl Brouard Cet Immortel. 1973.</item>
                            <item>Lavinia Williams. Ballets d'Haiti. undated.</item>
                            <item>Paul E. Magliore. Fondation. Au Service des Humbles. 1955.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref233" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Haiti No. 25-29</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358045" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">12-8</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref333">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Sandra L. Burdick. God Is No Stranger. 1970.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie des Antilles. Naifs d'Haiti et Vaudou. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Roland Morisseau. Germination Despair. 1962.</item>
                            <item>Lapierre Drouinaud. Poesis Cosmique. undated.</item>
                            <item>Imprimerie Theodore. Idem Par Davertige. 1962.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref234" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Jamaica No. 1-5</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358046" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-1</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref339">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Department of Extra Mural Studies of the West Indies. Public Affairs in Jamaica. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Ministry of Labour and National Insurance. Guide to Industrial Relations in Jamaica. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Government Printing Office of the Institute of Jamaica. Chronological Outlines of Jamaica History: 1492-1926. 1927.</item>
                            <item>Geological Survey Department of Jamaica. Bauxite Resources of Jamaica and Their Development. 1954.</item>
                            <item>National History Society of Jamaica. Glimpses of Jamaican Natural History. 1949.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref235" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Jamaica No. 6-14</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358047" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-2</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref336">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>J.F. Ward. Pimento. 1961.</item>
                            <item>J.F.Ward. Garden Cherry. 1961.</item>
                            <item>Council of Voluntary Social Services. Bringing Up Your Children. October 1964.</item>
                            <item>Report of Mission to Africa for the Premier of Jamaica. 1961.</item>
                            <item>Jamaica Tourist Board. Interesting People. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Philip Sherlock. The Freedom of the City of Kingston: Speech by Philip Sherlock. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Barbara Stephens. Cities of the World: Kingston. 1952.</item>
                            <item>Jeanne Wilson. A Legacy for Isabel. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Jamaican Information Center. Jamaican Cuisine. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref236" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Jamaica-unnumbered</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358048" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-3</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref337">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Rex Nettleford. National Identity and Attitudes to Race in Jamaica. 1965.</item>
                            <item>L.T. Comber. Colourblind. 1959.</item>
                            <item>Edward Braithwaite. Folk Culture of the Slaves in Jamaica. 1970.</item>
                            <item>Youth Forces for National Liberation. Paul Bogle and the Morant Bay Rebellion. 1967.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref237" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Puerto Rico No. 1-12</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358049" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-4</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref338">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Publicacion del Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. El Centro Ceremonial Indigena de Utuado. undated.</item>
                            <item>International Socialist Pamphlet. Puerto Rican Independence. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Post War World Council. Self-Determination for Puerto-Rico. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Juan Antonio Corretjer. Albizu Campos and the Ponce Massacre. 1965.</item>
                            <item>E. Gutierrez Velez. Asesinato Politico. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Frank Torres. The Governor Goes Professor. 1946.</item>
                            <item>Ruben del Rosario. La Lengua de Puerto Rico. 1985.</item>
                            <item>William Z. Foster. The Crime of El Fanguito. April 1948.</item>
                            <item>U.S. Department of Agriculture. Frank H. Hitchcock. Trade of Puerto Rico. 1898.</item>
                            <item>Puerto Rico Libre. Puerto Rico Se Nacionaliza: No Se "Americaniza". 1970.</item>
                            <item>Puerto Rican Affairs Committee. Handbook on Puerto Rican Work. January 1954.</item>
                            <item>Banco Popular de Puerto Rico. Guia Para las Elecciones. 1972.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref238" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Puerto Rico No. 13-31</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358050" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-5</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref340">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Realismo y Naturalismo en Puerto Rico. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. La Lengua en Puerto Rico. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. La Vida en la Ciudad de San Juan Bautista a Mediados del Siglo XVIII Vista a Traves de Sus Actas Capitulares. 1957.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Los Neoclasicos en Puerto Rico. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. La Generacion del Treinta Cuento y Novela. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Apuntes Sobre La Danza Puertorriquena. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. El Modernismo la Prosa. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. El Romanticismo en la Literatura Puertorriquena. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. El Humorismo, el Epigrama y la Satira en la Literatura Puertorriquena. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. La Literature de Transicion. 1960. (2 copies)</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. La Critica Literaria. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Literatura Infantil Puertorriquena. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Como Vivian Nuestros Abuelos. 1957.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Literatura Folklorica de Puerto Rico. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Historia de las Ideas en Puerto Rico. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Consideraciones Sobre la Lengua en Puerto Rico. 1958.</item>
                            <item>Instituto de Cultura Puertorriquena. Panorama Teatral de Puerto Rico en el Siglo XIX. 1960.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref239" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>St. Lucia</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358051" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-6</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref341">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Public Relations Office of Saint Lucia. Constitution of Saint Lucia: A Summary. March 1967.</item>
                            <item>Sir Garnet Gordon. Two Political Essays. April 1966.</item>
                            <item>Address by the Honourable George Frederick Lawrence Charles at the Budget Meeting of the Legislative Council. March 1961.</item>
                            <item>St. Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. Saint Lucia Miscellany. Vol. 1. 1966.</item>
                            <item>The Saint Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. Saint Lucia Miscellany. Vol. 2. 1969.</item>
                            <item>The Saint Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. Saint Lucia Miscellany. Vol. 3. 1973.</item>
                            <item>The Standard. John H. Pilgrim. Snippets of St. Lucia's History. undated.</item>
                            <item>The Saint Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. A Short History of the Town and District of Vieux Fort (St. Lucia). 1971.</item>
                            <item>The Saint Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. Sketch for a Life of H.H. Breen: (1805-1881). 1968.</item>
                            <item>B.H. Easter. St. Lucia and the French Revolution. 1969.</item>
                            <item>The Saint Lucia Archaeological and Historical Society. A Guide to Morne Fortune: St. Lucia. February 1966.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref240" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>St. Vincent</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358052" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-7</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref342">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Labour Party of St. Vincent. .A Time for Change: Manifesto of the Labour Party General Election 1966. 1966.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref241" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 1-14</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358053" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-8</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref343">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Information Services of the Government of Trinidad and Tobago. Preparation for Nationhood. November 1957.</item>
                            <item>Olga Comma Maynard &amp; Fitz G. Maynard. The New Road. 1969.</item>
                            <item>Independence Celebrations Committee. Independence. August 1962.</item>
                            <item>Action Group of Dedicated Citizens. The ROad to Freedom. October 1970.</item>
                            <item>E.C. Richardson. Trinidad: Revolution or Evolution. undated.</item>
                            <item>Committee for Economic Development of Trinidad and Tobago. Policies for Faster Economic Growth in Trinidad and Tobago. January 1968.</item>
                            <item>E.C. Richardson. Onward Trinidad. undated.</item>
                            <item>E.C. Richardson. P.N.M. and Its Agricultural Policy. undated.</item>
                            <item>Your Land and You: Full Text of Speeches Delivered at the One-Day Seminar on Agriculture at Naparima Bowl. May 1967.</item>
                            <item>Walter Annamunthodo. Sugar Dissected. 1966.</item>
                            <item>The Tripartite Committee of the Trinidad and Tobago Opposition Parties. The Voting Machine Story. January 1968.</item>
                            <item>Trinidad and Tobago. Report of the Commission Appointed by His Excellency the Governor-General to Investigate Allegations of Discriminatory Practices by the Management of the Trinidad Country Club. August 1969.</item>
                            <item>J.M. Dube. Settling the Farmers. September 1965.</item>
                            <item>Soroptimist Club of Port-of-Spain. The Child in Trinidad and Tobago. 1970.</item>
                            <item>The Trinidad and Tobago Tourist Board. Historic Tobago. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref242" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 15-26</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358054" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-9</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref344">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Democratic Socialism for a New Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Democratic Labour Party Manifesto 3: Agriculture. undated.</item>
                            <item>Democratic Socialism for a New Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Democratic Labour Party Manifesto 4: Co-operatives. undated.</item>
                            <item>Democratic Socialism for a New Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Democratic Labour Party Manifesto 6: Part 1: Health. Part 2: Social Welfare. undated.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. The Preservation of our Democracy: An Address Delivered to the Federation of Women's Institute at Queen's Hall on April 22nd 1967. 1967.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. Trinidad and Tobago: Speech by the Minister of External Affairs on the Invasion of Czechoslovakia. August 1968.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. National Emergence: The Final Round. Address by A.N.R. Robinson to the Nation. November 1972.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. Address to the Trinidad Chamber of Commerce at the Annual Dinner of the Chamber on May 19 1967. 1967.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. The Path of Progress Address &amp; the Rescue of Our Children Address. 1967.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. The New Frontier &amp; the New Africa. undated.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. Speech Made by the Honourable Minister of Finance on the Presentation of the Central Bank Bill in the House of Representatives. undated.</item>
                            <item>Max B. Ifill. The Solomon Affair: A Tale of Immortality in Trinidad. undated.</item>
                            <item>Cabot Harry. Buy &amp; Eat More Local. 1963.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref243" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 27-37a</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358055" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-10</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref345">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Anthony E. Rouff. Authentic Facts on the Origin of the Steelband. undated.</item>
                            <item>Trinidad and Tobago. Carnival Calypso Spectacular. 1968 Souvenir Magazine. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Psychological Association of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Hamlyn Dukhan. An Introduction to Psychology. No. 2. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Nationwide Broadcast Delivered by Dr. The Right Honourable Eric Williams. 23 March 1970.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Responsibilities of the Party Member. September 1960.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. The University-Symbol of Freedom. February 1963.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Speech of the Honourable the Prime Minister and Minister of External Affairs of Trinidad and Tobago at the Opening of the Conference Between Trinidad and Tobago and Venezuela, Whitehall, Port-of-Spain, Trinidad. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Office of Premier Public Relations Divisions. Dr. Eric Williams. Reports on the Inter-Governmental Conference. 1961.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Devaluation Speeches. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Economic Aid to Trinidad and Tobago. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Reorganisation of the Public Service. 1965.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref244" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 38-47</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358056" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">13-11</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref346">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Prince Edgar Ferdinand. Citizenship for Trinidad and Tobago. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Little Books on Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Vol. 1, No. 1. Trinibagianese. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Little Books on Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Vol. 2, No. 2. Trinibagianese. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Little Books on Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Vol. Vol, No. 3. Sayings of Trinidad and Tobago. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Little Books on Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Vol. 1, No. 5. A History of Place-Names in Trinidad &amp; Tobago. 1969.</item>
                            <item>J.D. Elder. The Yoruba Ancestor Cult in Gasparillo. January 1969.</item>
                            <item>Franklyn Harvey. Rise and Fall of Party Politics in Trinidad and Tobago. February 1974.</item>
                            <item>Trinityism: The Constitution. Godliness Equality Freedom. undated.</item>
                            <item>John D. Humphrey. Trinityism and Trinidad &amp; Tobago. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref245" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 48-53</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358057" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-1</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref348">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Trinidad Cricket Council. Year Book. 1969.</item>
                            <item>Stephens Books. Independence Day Celebrations. 1969.</item>
                            <item>C.R. Ottley. A Guide to Trinidad &amp; Tobago. undated.</item>
                            <item>M.P. Alladin. Folk Stories and Legends of Trinidad. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Carnival Development Committee. Trinidad &amp; Tobago Carnival 1969. 1969.</item>
                            <item>Carnival Calypso and a Comprehensive Guide to the Seven Jewels in the Sun. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Government of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Trinidad &amp; Tobago. August 1962.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref246" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago No. 54-65</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358058" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-2</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref349">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>George Weekes. Oil in Turmoil and OWTU Memorandum on the Formation of a National Oil Co. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Aubrey E. James. George Cabral. undated.</item>
                            <item>Beryl McBurnie. Dance Trinidad Dance. undated.</item>
                            <item>The Foundation Stone. The New Little Carib. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Horace E. Leighton-Mills. Anthology of Poems and Flora. September 1966.</item>
                            <item>Horace E. Leighton-Mills. Second Anthology of Poems and Short Stories. December 1968.</item>
                            <item>Grenada Progressive Calypsonians Committee. Grenada Calypsos. 1973.</item>
                            <item>Trinidad Publishing Co. J.M. and Other cartoonists from the Trinidad Guardian. 1959.</item>
                            <item>University of the West Indies. Crick-Crack. New World and Lore Series. Vol. 1. June 1966.</item>
                            <item>Richard Bowyer. The Wedding Ring and Other Stories of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. undated.</item>
                            <item>C.R. Ottley. Jokey Stories of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. 1972.</item>
                            <item>H.M. Hoadley. The Green Parakeets. 1972.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref247" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trinidad &amp; Tobago-unnumbered</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358059" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-3</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref350">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Government of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Caribbean Integration. April 1969.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. Fiscal Reform in Trinidad &amp; Tobago. May 1966.</item>
                            <item>A.N.R. Robinson. Economic Development in Trinidad &amp; Tobago. undated.</item>
                            <item>Tony Thomas and John Riddell. Black Power in the Caribbean. May 1971.</item>
                            <item>House of Representatives of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Budget Speech. 28 November 1969.</item>
                            <item>Independence Publication of the Government of Trinidad &amp; TObago. Our Flag and Other National Emblems. undated.</item>
                            <item>The University of Essex. Eric Williams. Britain and the West Indies. 1969.</item>
                            <item>E.C. Richardson. The Scholarship of Eric Williams. undated.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Reflection on the Caribbean Economic Community. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Government of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. Eric Williams. Address Delivered at Queen's College, Georgetown, Guyana. 13 March 1963.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Massa Day Done. undated.</item>
                            <item>Undine Giuseppi. Frank Worrell. 1969.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref401" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Social and Political Issues</unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <c03 id="ref248" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 1-10</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358060" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-4</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref351">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>L.H.C. WEstcott. The Garden of Life: A Collection of Poems. undated.</item>
                            <item>Selwyn Bhajan. Season of Songs. undated.</item>
                            <item>Devendeanath Capildeo. 10 Short Poems. 1969.</item>
                            <item>Devendranath Capildeo. "Maracas Bay" and Other Short Poems. 1972.</item>
                            <item>M.P. Alladin. Man Is a Creator. undated.</item>
                            <item>Augustos, Earl. Moore, Winston. Rennie, Winston. BAKA. undated.</item>
                            <item>C.L.R. James. Wilson Harris: A Philosophical Approach. General Public Lecture Series. Vol. 1. undated.</item>
                            <item>Gilles L. Cobham. Palm Sunday and Other Verse. undated.</item>
                            <item>Odimumba Kwamdela. The Righteous Blackman. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Jack Kelshall. Song From a Prison Courtyard (And Other Poems). undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref249" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 11-20</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358061" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-5</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref352">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Michael R. Als. Poems on Life and Soul. undated.</item>
                            <item>J.R. Ralph Casimir. Africa Arise. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Reginald Myrie Murray. Ramblings. undated.</item>
                            <item>D.W. Rogers. Tagore &amp; Kisagotami. undated.</item>
                            <item>Comite Unitario Pro Libertad de Humberto Pagan. Versos de Humberto Pagan. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Vivain Usherwood. Vivian Usherwood Poems. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Hopeton A.N. Anderson. Out of the Woods. 1970.</item>
                            <item>Abhiman A. Gajadhar. Lovers in the Light. August 1972.</item>
                            <item>Presentation One. undated.</item>
                            <item>Phyllis M. Cousins. Queen of the Mountain. 1967.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref250" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 21-27</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358062" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-6</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref353">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>The "Wendy Price" Selection of "Bedford" Bedtime Stories. Vol. 1. undated.</item>
                            <item>Marion Barteaux. The Guitar of Dolores. undated.</item>
                            <item>Earl Augustus et alii. Gambage. New World Life and Lore Series. Vol. 1. May 1966.</item>
                            <item>Elaine Robertson. Let Us Play. 1971.</item>
                            <item>E. Braithwaite. Four Plays for Primary Schools. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Reggie Griffith. Home on the Hills. June 1967.</item>
                            <item>Errol John. Moon on a Rainbow Shawl. 1958.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref251" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 28-37</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358063" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-7</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref354">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Leonardo Garcia Fox. Poemas del Exilio. undated.</item>
                            <item>Rafael J. Hernandez Carlo. Flores de Mi Camposanto Poemas. 1959.</item>
                            <item>Les Presses Libres. Melange de Vin et de Bois-Cochon. undated.</item>
                            <item>Franck Senat. Confidences des Ondes. 1949.</item>
                            <item>Jacques Large. Cjpses &amp; Gens Vus. undated.</item>
                            <item>Marie-Carmel Lafontant. Legendes de Noel. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Batha Miranda. Rosal de Amor y Recuerdo. undated.</item>
                            <item>Philippe Sterlin. 3 Contes. 1953.</item>
                            <item>Ernest Bennett. Cafe Cafe. undated.</item>
                            <item>Ricardo E. Algeria. Los Renegados. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref252" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 38-50</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358064" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-8</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref356">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Luc B. Innocent. Messages. 1955.</item>
                            <item>Renee Marie-Ange Jolicoeur. Oiseaux de Memoire. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Roger Geaniton. Premiers Cris. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Joseph Renaud. Mil Huit Cent Quatre. 1956.</item>
                            <item>Charles Fernand Pressoir. Set Poem Ki Sot Nan Mon. 1947.</item>
                            <item>Bpmmard Posy. Roussan Camille. December 1962.</item>
                            <item>Suzette C. Antoine. Premier Elan. 1965.</item>
                            <item>Frederic Burr-Reynaud. C'est la Guerre. undated.</item>
                            <item>Frederic Doret. De Mon Coeur a Ton Coeur. undated.</item>
                            <item>Eugene Debrosse. Mes Premierres Pages. April 1968.</item>
                            <item>Herodote Megalos. Petales de Vie. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Ernst Jean Baptiste. Les Heures Hallucinees. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Renee Marie-Ange Jolicoeur. Violon D'Espoir. 1970.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref253" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 51-62</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358065" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-9</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref357">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Louis O. Baptiste. Cantilene. undated.</item>
                            <item>Jules-Andre Marc. Les Chants de Jam et Legendes Sambas. undated.</item>
                            <item>Jean Casimir. Des Vers a Jeter. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Eddy B. Pierre. Myosolis. 1963.</item>
                            <item>Guy D. Georges. L'Immense Profondeur. 1965.</item>
                            <item>CI-GIT de Serge St. Jean. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Rene Liquion. Leon Contrar Damas un Poete de la Negritude. undated.</item>
                            <item>Serge Lacoste. Rose de Sang. undated.</item>
                            <item>Roger Labonte. Lumiere Dans ma Nuil. undated.</item>
                            <item>Marie-Ange Jolicoeur. Guitare de Vers. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Jules Nicolas. Hiver Ensoleille. undated.</item>
                            <item>Nyldde. Aubo. 1969.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref254" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 63-72</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358066" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">14-10</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref358">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Charles Bayard. La Poesie Ensorcelante. 1962.</item>
                            <item>Venenesse Ducasse. Fort de Joux. undated.</item>
                            <item>Retirubtion du Spartacus Noir ou Tragedie de Toussaint Louverture. undated.</item>
                            <item>Presses Nationales d'Haiti. Le Torrent. December 1965.</item>
                            <item>Rony Lescouflair. Notre Amour le Temps et les Espaces. undated.</item>
                            <item>Michaelle Lafontant. Pour Que Renaisse Ma Quisqueya. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Jacques Rollin Monfiston. Un Pour Deux Deuz Pour Un. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Jean Camille Angrand. A Coeur Ouvert. undated.</item>
                            <item>Yves Antoine. Au Gre des Heures. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Yves Antoine. La Veillee. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref255" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Arts No. 73-79</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358067" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-1</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref359">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>CLE-Theatre. Abra Pokou. undated.</item>
                            <item>Pierre Sully. Trois Actes de Marcel Dauphin. 1960.</item>
                            <item>Serge St. Jean. La Terre Aux Fruits d'Or. undated.</item>
                            <item>Occelus Vincent. Brouillerie. undated.</item>
                            <item>Walter Murray Chiesa. Otoqui. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Ruud Mungroo. Hetraam. 1971.</item>
                            <item>Ruud Mungroo. Afanaisa. 1970.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref256" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358068" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-2</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref360">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Idris Hamid. In Search of New Perspectives. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Sehon Goodridge. Politics and the Caribbean Church. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. P.A. Edwards. Education for Development in the Caribbean. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. William G Demas. The Political Economy of the English Speaking Caribbean. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Michael McCormack. Liberation or Development. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. The Role of Women in Caribbean Development. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Dr. Philip Irving Boyd. Health Problems in the Developing Caribbean. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. The Role of Tourism in Caribbean Development. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Caribbean Unity Christian Unity. undated.</item>
                            <item>Caribbean Ecumenical Consultation for Development. Called to Be. November 1971.</item>
                            <item>The Caribbean Conference of Churches. Ashley A. Smith &amp; Michael De Verteuil. Renewal and Ecumenism in the Caribbean. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref257" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Communism</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358069" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-3</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref361">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Directorio Magisterial Cubano. El Imperialismo y el Colonialismo de la U.R.S.S. undated.</item>
                            <item>Movimento Unidad Revolucionaria. Can This Happen to the Americas? Yes. undated.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref258" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Education</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358070" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-4</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref362">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>John H. Figueroa. Staffing and Examinations in British Caribbean Secondary Schools. July 1961.</item>
                            <item>Norman E. Cameron. Gilchrist Scholarships in the Caribbean. undated.</item>
                            <item>Earl Augustus. Cipriani Labour College Related Documents. undated.</item>
                            <item>Sphilip M. Sherlock. Speech of Philip M. Sherlock. October 1964.</item>
                            <item>H.J. Belizaire. Geographical Terms. 1920.</item>
                            <item>University of the West Indies. The University Library at St. Augustine. 1966.</item>
                            <item>Istoua Gnou Fanmi. Jeral E Naomi. undated.</item>
                            <item>J.D. Bentley. Sunny Island Readers. 1961.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref259" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Federations (West Indies)</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358071" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-5</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref363">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Regional Council of Ministers. Draft Federal Scheme. 1964.</item>
                            <item>Anthony Greenwood. Despatch (sic). March 1965.</item>
                            <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Report by the Conference on British Caribbean Federation. February 1956.</item>
                            <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. The Plan for a British Caribbean Federation. December 1955.</item>
                            <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Report by the Conference on West Indian Federation. April 1953.</item>
                            <item>Her Majesty's Stationary Office. Conference on the CLose Association of the British West Indian Colonies. 1948.</item>
                            <item>Education Committee of the People's Progressive Party. Caribbean unity &amp; Carifta. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Sir Arthur Lewis. The Agony of the Eight. undated.</item>
                            <item>Government Printing Office of Barbados. Caribbean Free Trade Association. undated.</item>
                            <item>Kamaluddin Mohammed. The Significance of a Caribbean Economic Community. August 1967.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref260" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Industrialization</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358072" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-6</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref364">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Workers' Educational Association. David M. Callender. The Anti I.S.A. Struggle. undated.</item>
                            <item>Arthur Lewis. The Industrialisation of the British West Indies. undated.</item>
                            <item>Eric Williams. Reflection on the Industrial Stabilisation Bill. April 1965.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref261" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>People's National Movement</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358073" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-7</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref366">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Our Fourth Anniversary...The Last Lap. September 1960.</item>
                            <item>Eric Williams. An Address Delivered by Dr. the Rt. Hon. Eric Williams. September 1965.</item>
                            <item>People's National Movement. Eric Williams. PNM's Perspectives in the World of the Seventies. 1970.</item>
                            <item>Eric Williams. A Review of the Political Scene. September 1960.</item>
                            <item>People's National Movement Address. Eric Williams Address at the Fourteenth Annual Convention. 1972.</item>
                            <item>People's National Movement. The Party in Independence. undated.</item>
                            <item>People's National Movement. Report on Family Planning. March 1965.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref262" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Revolution</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358074" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-8</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref367">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. "The Revolution Must Be a School of Unfettered Thought" Speech. March 1965.</item>
                            <item>Fidel Castro. Speech at the Closing of the First Conference of OLAS. 1967.</item>
                            <item>Angel Aparicio-Laurencio. Revolucion y Desintegracion. 1967.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref263" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Trade Unions</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358075" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-9</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref368">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>The Trades Union Act of 1939. Rules of the Antigua Trades and Labour Union. Septmeber 1961.</item>
                            <item>Trade Union Education Institute. Trade Union and Industrial Relations Terms. undated.</item>
                            <item>New Beginning Movement. Joseph Edwards. Union Versus Menegement. October 1971.</item>
                            <item>Speeches by George Weekes at the Tripartite Conference on Employment and Retrenchment. undated.</item>
                            <item>Oilfields Workers' Trade Union. Commemoration. 1969.</item>
                            <item>National Union of Sugar Workers. A Betrayal of the Sugar Workers. December 1963.</item>
                            <item>Oilfield Workers' Trade Union. Lionel Beckles. Brief Survey of Grievance Procedure. October 1967.</item>
                            <item>Trade Union Education Institute. H.R. Roberts. Introducing Job Evaluation. 1951.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref264" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Miscellaneous No. 1-8</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358076" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-10</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref369">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>New Beginning. Political Economy of the Caribbean. April 1972.</item>
                            <item>Secretary of State for the Colonies. Report of the West Indies Constitutional Conference. 1961.</item>
                            <item>G.W. Roberts. Population Trends in the British Caribbean. undated.</item>
                            <item>Historical Society of Trinidad and Tobago. Eric Williams. The British West Indies at Westminster. 1954.</item>
                            <item>Eric Williams. Some Thoughts on Economic Aid to Developing Countries. February 1963.</item>
                            <item>University of Miami Hispanic American Studies. Caribbean Accounting Methods. November 1958.</item>
                            <item>Pastors' Introductory Course to Agriculture. The Church and Agrarian Reform in the Caribbean. September 1972.</item>
                            <item>Federal Information Service. The West Indies. Federal Elections. March 1958.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref265" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Miscellaneous No. 9-15</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358077" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-11</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref370">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>S. Normal Girwar. The Future of the Commonwealth Sugar in an Enlarged E.E.C. September 1972.</item>
                            <item>Eric Williams. Ghandi. undated.</item>
                            <item>C.L.R. James. Radical America. 1970.</item>
                            <item>Therese Mills. Great West Indians. 1973.</item>
                            <item>AfroAmerican Institute. Caribs, "Cannibals," and Human Relations. 1972.</item>
                            <item>Leine Revolutionare Bibliothek. Che Guevara. undated.</item>
                            <item>Dr. Eric Williams. Tagore Centenary Celebration Address. May 1961.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref266" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Miscellaneous No. 16-25</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358078" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-12</container>
                        </did>
                        <scopecontent id="ref371">
                            <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                            <item>Walter Trobisch. Mouin Rinmin Gnou Jinn Gason. undated.</item>
                            <item>W.M. Hoyer. A Brief Historical Description of the Island of Curacao. 1950.</item>
                            <item>V. Valcin. Essais Sur La Culture. undated.</item>
                            <item>Anglo-American Caribbean Commision. Caribbean Cooperation. undated.</item>
                            <item>William Louis Bass. L'Ordre Nouveau. 1945.</item>
                            <item>Jose Francisco Montalgo. Un Martien Au Vietnam. 1968.</item>
                            <item>Gerard Duc. La Lutte Pour L'Existence Dans le Processus d'Evolution des Collectivites Humaines. undated.</item>
                            <item>W.A. Rochemont. Du Feminisme National. 1950.</item>
                            <item>Workers Educational Association. Racism and Black Power. undated.</item>
                            <item>S.S. Ramphal. The Law in Everyday Life. 1954.</item>
                            <item>Clerie-Laforest. Comment Sonnent les Heures de Toutes Choses. 1968.</item>
                        </list></scopecontent>
                    </c03>
                    <c03 id="ref267" level="file">
                        <did>
                            <unittitle>Miscellaneous No. 26-36</unittitle>
                            <container id="cid1358079" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">15-13</container>
                        </did>
                    </c03>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref268" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series IV: Communism</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref269" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 1-28</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358080" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-1</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref306">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Georgi Dimitroff. To Defend Assassins Is to Help Fascism. 1937.</item>
                        <item>Southern Regional Committee of the Communist Party. The Southern People's Common Program for Democracy, Prosperity and Peace. March 1953.</item>
                        <item>Citizen's Committee for Constitutional Liberties. "A Fateful Moment in Our History". Dissenting Opinion of Associate Justice of the Supreme Court Hugo L. Black in the McCarran Act Decision. undated.</item>
                        <item>Elizabeth Gurley Flynn. The Plot to Gag America. April 1950.</item>
                        <item>Elizabeth Gurley Flynn. The Twelve and You. September 1948.</item>
                        <item>Wm. Z. Foster. In Defense of the Communist Party and the Indicted Leaders. July 1949.</item>
                        <item>Committee on Un-American Activities. Preliminary Report on Neo-Fascist and Hate Groups. December 1954.</item>
                        <item>E. Yaroslavsky. The Meaning of the Soviet Trials. March 1938. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Paul Ruedemann. I Learned About Communism the Hard Way. 1949.</item>
                        <item>Eugene Dennis. Let the People Know. April 1947.</item>
                        <item>Tom Mooney Molders Defense Committee. Tom Mooney Betrayed by Labor Leaders. 1931.</item>
                        <item>Ernst Fischer. Trotsky Unmasked. undated.</item>
                        <item>Adam Lapin. The Un-American Dies Committee. January 1939.</item>
                        <item>Pioneer Publishers. Why Did They "Confess"? A Study of the Radek-Piatakov Trial. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Supreme Court. The Schneiderman Case. August 1943.</item>
                        <item>M. Katz. The Assassination of Kirov. Proletarian Justice vs. White-Guard Terror. February 1935.</item>
                        <item>Morton Sobell. The Scientist in Alcatraz. undated.</item>
                        <item>Soviet Russia Today. At the Moscow Trial. 1937.</item>
                        <item>Modern Books Ltd. The Moscow Trial. undated.</item>
                        <item>Friedrich Adler. The Witchcraft Trial in Moscow. undated.</item>
                        <item>Earl Browder. Traitors in American History. April 1938.</item>
                        <item>Elizabeth Gurley Flynn. Communists and the People. May 1953.</item>
                        <item>Eugene Dennis. In Defense of Your Freedom. Summation in the Trial of the Eleven Communist Leaders. October 1949.</item>
                        <item>The Communist Party. Eugene Dennis. I Challenge the Un-Americans. undated.</item>
                        <item>Guillermo Fernandez Nunez. Communismo Jamas. 1962.</item>
                        <item>William A. Reuben. To Secure Justice in the Rosenberg Case. undated.</item>
                        <item>William Z. Foster. Questions &amp; Answers on the Piatakov-Radek Trial. March 1937.</item>
                        <item>Progressive Citizens of America. Albert E. Kahn. Treason in Congress. undated.</item>
                        <item>National Federation for Constitutional Liberties. Investigate Martin Dies. 1942.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref270" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 31-44</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358081" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-2</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref307">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on Judiciary United States Senate. Nature of Communism in Occupied China. 13 May 1957.</item>
                        <item>Civil Rights Defense Committee. Who Are the 18 Prisoners in the Minneapolis Labor Case. undated.</item>
                        <item>Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary. The Technique of Soviet Propaganda. 1960.</item>
                        <item>National Federation for Constitutional Liberties. In the Criminal Court of Appeals. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States of America Against Harvey M. Matusow. Brief for Appellee. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals. United States vs. Frederick V. Filed, W. Alphaeus Hunton, &amp; Samuel Dashiell Hammett. Brief for the United States. undated.</item>
                        <item>James P. Cannon. Socialism on Trial: The Official Record of James P. Cannon's Testimony in the Famous Minneapolis "Sedition" Trial. March 1944.</item>
                        <item>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. Irving Potash vs. District Director of Immigration and Naturalization at the Port of New York. 8 March 1948.</item>
                        <item>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. Irving Potash vs. Distric Director of Immigration and Naturalization at the Port of New York. Brief for Relator-Appellant. 9 March 1948.</item>
                        <item>The Militant. Why We Are in Prison: Farewkk Speeches of the 18 Socialist Workers Party and 544-CIO Minneapolis Prisoners. undated.</item>
                        <item>International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Frederick Woltman. The McCarthy Balance Sheet. 1954.</item>
                        <item>R. Robinson Chance. Fifth Column. 1940.</item>
                        <item>The South African Communist Party. The Road to South African Freedom. undated.</item>
                        <item>Council for Pan American Democracy. The 5: The Column in Mexico. undated.</item>
                        <item>Irwin Edelman. Freedom's Electrocution. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref271" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 45 vol. 1-4</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358082" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-3</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref308">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>United States of America Against Harry Sacher, Richard Gladstein, George W. Crockett, Jr., Louis F. McCabe, Abraham J. Isserman and Eugene Dennis. Appendix to Appellants' Brief. 17 November 1949.</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America Against Harry Sacher, Richard Gladstein, George W. Crockett, Jr., Louis F. McCabe, Abraham J. Isserman and Eugene Dennis. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America Against Harry Sacher, Richard Gladstein, George W. Crockett, Jr., Louis F. McCabe, Abraham J. Isserman and Eugene Dennis. Appellants' Brief. 14 January 1950.</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America Against Harry Sacher, Richard Gladstein, George W. Crockett, Jr., Louis F. McCabe, Abraham J. Isserman and Eugene Dennis. Appellants' Brief. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref272" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 46-51</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358083" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-4</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref309">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>The Supreme Court of Ohio. Arnold Johnson vs. John E. Sweeney. Appellant's Brief in Opposition to Appellee's Motion to Strike, Assignments of Error and Brief on Appeal. undated. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. Nos. 12587 and 12607. Harry Renton Bridges, et al. vs. United States of America. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America Against Earl Russell Browder. Brief for Defendant-Appellant. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Circuit Court of APpeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America against Earl Russell Browder. Appendix to Brief for Defendant-Appellant. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. United States of America Against Gilbert Green and Henry Winston. Brief for Appellee. November 1956.</item>
                        <item>District Court of the united States for the District of Columbia. United States of America vs. Eugene Dennis, a.k.a Francis Waldron. Brief in Support of Motions to Dismiss Indictment. undated.</item>
                        <item>United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. No. 9658. William Schneiderman vs. United States of America. Brief for Appellant. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref273" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 52-54</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358084" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-5</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref310">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>United States District Court for the Northern District of California. In the Matter of Harry Renton Bridges on Habeas Corpus. Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion to Intervene. undated.</item>
                        <item>District Court of Appeal for the State of California. The People of the State of California vs. Sam Darcy. Appellant's Opening Brief. 1942.</item>
                        <item>The District Court of the United States for the District of Columbia. Transcript of Proceedings. 14 August 1947.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref274" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 55-59</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358085" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-6</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref313">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Junius Irving Scales v. United States of America on Writ of Certiori to the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. 1961.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Nos. 8, 7 and 71 on Writs of Certiori to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. October 1950.</item>
                        <item>Edward I. Aronow. Re: Earl Russel Browder. Memorandum in Behalf of Earl Russel Browder Submitted in Support of Letter Dated March 5th, 1942, Addressed to Hon. Mathias F. Correa, United States Attorney for the Southern District of New York. undated. undated. (3 copies)</item>
                        <item>United States Supreme Court. William Schneiderman Against United States of America. Brief for Petitioner. 1941.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. William Schneiderman Against the United States of America. Petition for Writ of Certiori to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit and Brief in Support Thereof. 1941.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Stephen Mesarosh v. United States of America on Motion to Remand. 1956.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref275" level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Communism No. 60-62</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1358086" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">16-7</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref314">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>United States Supreme Court. William Schneiderman v. The United States of America on Writ of Ceriori to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. Brief for the United States. 1942.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States of America. William Scneiderman v. The United States of America. Reply Brief for Petitioner. 1942.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Motion for Leave to File and Petition for the Exercise by This Court of Its Supervisory Authority Over the District Court for the Southern District of New York to Void Indictments and to Quash Venire of Petit Jurors, for a Rule to Show Cause Why Mandamus and Prohibition Should Not Issue, For Rule Absolute, and for Stay. 1948.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Earl Russel Browder Against the United States of America. Brief for Petitioner. 1940. (2 copies)</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Earl Russell Browder against United States of America. Appendix to Brief for Petitioner. 1940.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Welwel Warszower Against the United States of America. Petitioner's Brief Reply. 1940.</item>
                        <item>Supreme Court of the United States. Welwel Warszower Against the United States of America. Petition for Writ of Certiorari to the Circuit Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit and Brief in Support Thereof. undated.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref380" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series V: Asia</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref381" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>China</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1810002" type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref383">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Headline Series. China: The Uncertain Future. No. 233. December 1947.</item>
                        <item>Foreign Languages Press. The Great Socialist Cultural Revolution in China. No. 3. 1966.</item>
                        <item>Foreign Languages Press. The Great Socialist Cultural Revolution in China. No. 4. 1966.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref382" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Vietnam</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1810003" type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref384">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Foreign Languages Press. Support the People of Vietnam, Defeat U.S. Aggressors. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Vietnamese Studies. In Face of AMerican Aggression. No. 16. 1966-1967.</item>
                        <item>Neo Lao Haksat Publications. Rains in the Jungle. 1967.</item>
                        <item>Giai Phong Publishing House. South Viet Nam. March 1968.</item>
                        <item>Liberation Editions. Speech by Nguyen Huu Tho. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Ministry of Education in the Democratic Republic of Vietnam. 20 Years' Development of Education in the Democratic Republic of Vietnam. 1965.</item>
                        <item>Vietnamese Studies. Mountain Regions and National Minorities in the D.R. of Vietnam. 1968.</item>
                        <item>Foreign Languages Publishing House. Vietnamese and Teaching in Vietnamese in D.R.V.N. Universities. 1968.</item>
 
<item>Vietnam Courier. No. 255. 1970.</item>
 
<item>South Viet Nam In Struggle. No. 124. 1971.</item>
 
<item>Seven Point Statement of the Provisional Revolutionary Government of the Republic of South Viet Nam, Issued by Mme. Nguyen Thi Binh. undated. </item>
 
                   </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>


            <c01 id="ref183" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series VI: Other Topics</unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 id="ref389" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Dating/Marriage</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1810006" type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref390">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>How to Write Famous Love Letters, Love Stories, and Make Friend with Girls. January 1973.</item>
                        <item>Make Up Your Mind Series. Discussions on Marriage Problems. No. 3. undated.</item>
                        <item>Oluseyi Press Limited. Getting Married? 1962.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref388" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Other</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1810005" type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref391">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Institut Royal Colonial Belge. Memoires. 1934.</item>
                        <item>Guarantees No Longer Being Enjoyed by Indigenous Peopls. undated.</item>
                        <item>R.M. Burke. Pounds and Pennies. July 1965.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref373" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Other (Oversize)</unittitle>
                        <container id="cid1528001" type="Box" label="Box">18</container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent id="ref374">
                        <head>Bibliography</head><list>
                        <item>Special; Colloque sur la Negritude. Le Soliel. No. 305. May 8, 1971.</item>
                    </list></scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
