<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00164">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00164::John Collins
Enright)//EN" "viblbv00164"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John Collins Enright Letters <date> 1861-1863 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Enright, John Collins Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms96-021
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>John M. Jackson
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by John M. Jackson.<date>2005 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John Collins Enright Letters<date> 1861-1863 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms96-021
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>John M. Jackson
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">John Collins Enright Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1861-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">Ms96-021
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Transcribed war-time letters of John Collins Enright, first sergeant in the 18th Virginia Infantry, written from camps in northern and eastern Virginia.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the John Collins Enright Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>John Collins Enright Letters, Ms96-021 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The John Collins Enright Letters were donated to the Special Collections in 1996.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the John Collins Enright Letters commenced and was completed in April 2005.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>John Collins Enright, a soldier in the 18th Virginia Infantry, was born on January 22, 1837, in Kilmeedy, County Limerick, Ireland. Emigrating to New York at age 11, he settled in Danville, Virginia in 1859. At
the outbreak of the Civil War, Enright joined the Danville Blues, which was mustered into Confederate service as Company A, 18th Virginia Infantry. He was promoted from corporal to second sergeant on October 15,
1861, and to first sergeant on March 1, 1862. Records indicate that Enright was discharged from the service on July 23, 1862, but he was assigned for the remainder of the war to the Quartermaster's Department in
Richmond. (In the final letter of this collection, Enright indicates that he is no longer in the army but is employed cutting clothes in Richmond for the Confederate Army.)
</p>
<p>Enright married Mary ("Mollie") Adams of Petersburg on May 7, 1863. He was taken prisoner during the evacuation of Richmond in 1865 but was soon paroled. Following the Civil War, he operated a tailoring
business in Danville, counting among his customers several prominent Civil War-era families. He was a member of the Cabell-Graves Camp of the United Confederate Veterans and the Masonic Knights Templar. He died in
Danville on October 13, 1900, and was buried in Danville's Green Hill Cemetery.
</p>
<p>Among Enright's descendants have been two graduates of Virginia Tech: William Enright Stepp Sr. (class of 1924) and William Enright Stepp Jr. (class of 1969).
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains the letters of John Collins Enright, a soldier in the 18th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War. The letters are in the form of transcripts (71 pages), made by Enright's wife in 1899.
Enright writes from various locations in Virginia, including Danville, Manassas, Centreville, Germantown, Fairfax, Warwick, Yorktown, Richmond, and Charles City. His letters discuss his company's formation, early
troop movements and skirmishes in northern Virginia, the Battle of First Manassas and its aftermath, camp activities, his duties as orderly sergeant, the Siege of Yorktown, the Battles of Williamsburg and Seven
Pines and the Seven Days' Battles.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The letter transcripts are arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
