<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY Robertson SYSTEM "http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/robertsonj.htm" NDATA html>
]>
<ead id="viblbv00039">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00039::John P. Sheffey Papers)//EN&amp;#34;&amp;#34;viblbv00039.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC
             "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
             University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00039::John P. Sheffey
             Papers)//EN" "viblbv00039.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the John P. Sheffey Papers 
            <date>1853-1989</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Sheffey, John. Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2001-060</num></subtitle>
            <author>John M. Jackson</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia
            Polytechnic Institute and State University</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Special Collections</addressline>
               <addressline>University Libraries</addressline>
               <addressline>P.O. Box 90001</addressline>
               <addressline>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
               University</addressline>
               <addressline>Blacksburg, Virginia
               24062-9001</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (540) 231-6308</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (540) 231-3694</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: specref@vt.edu</addressline>
               <addressline>URL: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By Virginia
            Polytechnic Institute and State University</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">ca. 56 Kilobytes</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         Clayton McGahee. Date of source: 
         <date>2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-16">Feb 16, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00039::John P. Sheffey
            Papers)//EN" "viblbv00039.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the John P. Sheffey Papers 
         <date>1853-1989</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Special Collections 
         <num type="Collection Number">Ms2001-060</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia
         Polytechnic Institute and State University</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>University Libraries</item>
            <item>P.O. Box 90001</item>
            <item>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University</item>
            <item>Blacksburg, Virginia 24062-9001</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (540) 231-6308</item>
            <item>Fax: (540) 231-3694</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:specref@vt.edu">
            specref@vt.edu</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/">
            http://spec.lib.vt.edu/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections staff</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections,
      Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, Virginia
         Polytechnic Institute and State University</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">John P. Sheffey Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1853-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">Ms2001-060</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2 containers; .6
         linear feet</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract label="Abstract">Letters of a Confederate cavalry
         officer to his wife in Wytheville, Virginia, together with
         other Civil War and family correspondence, military documents, writings, printed material and ephemera.</abstract>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from the John P. Sheffey
            Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: John P. Sheffey Papers, Ms2001-060 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University. </p>
         </prefercite>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the John P. Sheffey Papers commenced in December 2001 and was completed in March 2002. Additional materials, received from the same source in 2004, were added to the collection in April 2009. 
</p>
</processinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>John Preston "Pres" Sheffey, Southwest Virginia attorney,
         judge and Confederate cavalry officer, was born in Marion,
         Virginia on December 12, 1837. The son of James W. and Eleanor
         F. Preston Sheffey, John Sheffey graduated from Emory and
         Henry College in 1857, then studied law at the
         University of Virginia. Admitted to the bar in 1859, Sheffey
         entered into law practice as a junior partner with his
         father.</p>
         <p>In February 1861, the elder Sheffey was elected delegate to
         Virginia's secession convention; later, he served as captain
         of the Smyth County home guards, responsible largely for
         guarding the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad. John Sheffey, meanwhile, enlisted in the Smyth Dragoons on
         May 27, 1861. Initially incorporated into the 50th Virginia
         Infantry as a cavalry company, the dragoons in September were
         assigned to the 8th Virginia Cavalry as Company A, with
         Sheffey serving as first lieutenant. Company A served
         throughout much of the war in southwestern Virginia and the
         counties that later became West Virginia. The company was
         encamped near Lewisburg, (West) Virginia during the autumn of
         1861 and in Mercer County the following spring.</p>
         <p>Sheffey was elected captain of Company A on May 14, 1862.
         During that summer and autumn, his unit participated in
         Jenkins' cavalry raid, proceeding through northwestern
         Virginia to the Ohio River, then southward to the Kanawha
         Valley. They had returned to the New River Valley by November
         and established quarters in Montgomery County for the winter
         of 1862-63. Sheffey was granted leave in the summer of 1863, while the
         8th Virginia was in the Shenandoah Valley. Traveling southward
         to Wytheville, Sheffey married Josephine Spiller on June 19.
         (The couple would have seven children: Eleanor F., Susan M.,
         Margaret P., Josephine S., James W., Miriam and John P.).</p>
         <p>During the winter of 1863-64, Sheffey took a brief medical
         leave and then served as judge advocate in a Lee County
         court-martial session, while the 8th Virginia remained in
         southwestern Virginia. On August 7, 1864, Company A participated in a battle at Moorefield, West Virginia. Sheffey was one of a number of 
         Confederates captured by Union forces.
         Soon transferred to Camp Chase, Sheffey remained a prisoner
         until exchanged in February 1865. He apparently rejoined his
         regiment at Appomattox, just as the war was drawing to a
         close.</p>
         <p>Returning to Marion, Sheffey continued as his father's law
         partner until the latter's death in June 1876. Sheffey's law
         practice remained his primary occupation until his election to
         the Virginia House of Delegates in 1893 and his subsequent
         appointment as judge of Virginia's sixteenth judicial circuit
         in 1895. Josephine S. Sheffey died November 19, 1904, and John P.
         Sheffey died the following year on August 20. He is buried in
         Round Hill Cemetery, Marion, Virginia.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>This collection contains the papers of John Preston Sheffey, an
         attorney, judge and Confederate cavalry officer from Smyth
         County, Virginia. Included are such items as correspondence, journals, military documents, printed materials and ephemera. </p>
         <p>Comprising the majority of the collection, the
         correspondence consists mostly of letters written by
         Sheffey to his wife, Josephine Spiller Sheffey, during the
         Civil War. Sheffey's early letters are devoted largely to
         personal matters, particularly his courtship with Josephine. His
         war-time letters also chronicle the establishment of Company
         A of the 8th Virginia Cavalry and its role in the war. General
         observations on military matters and social conditions are
         included as well, as Sheffey writes from various camps in western Virginia and later from the military prison at Camp Chase, Ohio. Scattered throughout the correspondence are
         a few letters from other friends and relatives--particularly
         Sheffey's sisters Margaret and Ellen. Like Sheffey's
         correspondence, these letters (approximately 15 in number)
         also relate largely to personal matters and the war's progress. Together with the original correspondence are photocopies of selected letters. </p>
	<p>The collection also contains the texts of three speeches, likely delivered by James W. Sheffey, on the 1848 presidential election and intemperance. Two bound volumes of John Sheffey's own writings are included as well. The first, available in the collection only as a photocopy, is a journal spanning three months in 1855. Recorded in its entries are weather conditions, book readings, sermons attended, and other daily activities. Sheffey also writes of local and state political affairs and mentions such incidents as the flogging of a local slave for marrying without consent, the murder of W. H. Spiller in Wytheville, and a fire. Included also are three recipes and various newspaper clippings, largely relating to Reconstruction politics. The second volume is a copy book spanning the years 1855 to 1860 and containing various compositions penned by Sheffey on such diverse topics as "Spain, Her Chivalry and Shame," "America and Greece: the Living and the Dead," "Creation," and "Virtue: the Best National Safeguard." (Perhaps most significant among the essays is Sheffey's "Can the Union be Dissolved," in which the writer takes a very strong pro-Union position.) Included also are texts of speeches delivered at Emory &amp; Henry College and the University of Virginia, together with a few poems. </p>
	<p>Representing Sheffey's service in the 8th Virginia Cavalry is a small set of documents, including two muster rolls, a court-martial specification of charges against Private H. F. Gullion, a leave of absence granted to Sheffey, a letter of transfer for Private James P. Mantz, and a letter from Sheffey to General Echols, requesting a pass for his wife to Greenbrier.</p>
         
         <p>Included among the printed materials are various newspaper articles about the Civil War in Southwest Virginia and a 1921 article about former slave Betty Blount. Also included here is an 1868 invitation for a Calliopean Society program at Emory &amp; College.</p>
         <p>Completing the collection is a set of general materials, including a Civil War poem by Sheffey, certification of Sheffey's election as judge in 1894, and several calling cards.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged by document type, then chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Robertson, James I. Jr., ed., <title render="italic">Soldier of southwestern Virginia: the Civil War letters of Captain John Preston Sheffey</title> (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 2004). E581.6 8th S54 2004 Civil War Spec
</p>
<p>The <extref entityref="Robertson"> James I. Robertson Jr. Papers (Ms94-021)</extref> contain materials compiled by Robertson in preparation for <title render="italic">Soldier of southwestern Virginia</title>. Included are transcripts of the letters, Sheffey genealogy notes and sources, and essays on Sheffey and various battles in which he participated. Many of these materials (transcripts and essays) were produced by Prof. Robert Seager II.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
      <dsc type="in-depth">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">
               </unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1853-1858</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">Jan-Jun
                  1861</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">Jul-Dec
                  1861</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1862</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">Jan-Jun
                  1863</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">Jul-Dec
                  1863</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1864</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865-1902,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
	</c01>
	<c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Photocopies of correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">
               </unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1861</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-9</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1862</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-10</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1863</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-11</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle> 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1864-65</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-12</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         
	<c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Speeches
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1848, n.d.</unitdate>
	       </unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-13</container>
	    </did>
         </c01>
<c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Journal
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1855</unitdate>
	       </unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-14</container>
	    </did>
         </c01>
<c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Compositions Book
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1855-1860</unitdate>
	       </unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-15</container>
	    </did>
         </c01>
	<c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Military Documents
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1862-63</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-16</container>
		<physdesc>[See also Oversize Materials]
		</physdesc>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Printed Materials 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1912-1989,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
               <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
	            1-17</container>
            </did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Invitation to annual exercises of Calliopean Society of Emory &amp; Henry College
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1868
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"A Chapter of Local War History In and Around the
                  Town of Marion" (by Mrs. B. E. Copenhaver) - <title render="italic">Richmond Times Dispatch</title>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Jul 7 1912
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Old Aunt Betty, 105, Primps for Picture" [re: former slave Betty Blount of Southwest Virginia] - <title render="italic">Richmond Times-Dispatch</title>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Oct 9 1921
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"The Federal Raid Against Wytheville" (by
                  Miriam Sheffey) - <title render="italic"> Marion Democrat</title>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Feb 4 1930
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"The Civil War Made These Women Heroines and
                  Victims" <title render="italic"> - Smyth County News</title>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Feb 28 1985
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Flyer for re-enactment of the Battle of
                  Carnifex Ferry
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Leaders of the War Between the States" -
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>[typescript, 47 pages]
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>[biographical sketches of Civil War leaders]
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
       </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>General Materials 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">1862-1966,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1-18</container>
            </did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"The Downfall of Peace: a Christmas Reverie at Camp Chase, Ohio" by John P. Sheffey 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1864
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>[typescript, 5 pages]
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Tax receipt: Josephine Spiller - Wytheville
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1862
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Bill of lading from Southern Express Company to Mrs. Sheffey for valise
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1864
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Certificate of election for John P. Sheffey as judge of 16th circuit
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1864
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter from S. B. Campbell to Virginia Historical Society
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1966
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>[phototocopies]
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>[re: 1867 letter from Gen. W. H. Powell to Mrs. Spiller; accompanied by typescript of Powell's letter]
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>John Preston Sheffey II obituary
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Extract from eulogy delivered by Goodridge A. Wilson Jr. at the funeral of John Preston Sheffey II
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>[typescript]
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Calling cards
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>


<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>James H. Buford
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>

<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Mr. and Mrs. William W. Hanson
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Mr. Huff
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Julia A. Lynch
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>A. G. Pendleton
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Jul 4 1857
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Miss Radfords"
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Mr. and Mrs. Robert Sayers
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>John P. Sheffey
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Jun 14 1857
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>

<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Mrs. Susan Spiller
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelopes
	<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>[10 items]
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Oversize Materials
<unitdate type="inclusive">1862
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster rolls for Company A, 8th Virginia Cavalry
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Jun 30 1862
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Oct 31 1862
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
