<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv01823">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
        scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
        repositoryencoding="iso15511">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01823::American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials, c.1966)//EN" "viblbv01823.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
                    >c.1966</date></titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2015-060</num></subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
                <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2015 By Virginia Tech. All rights
                    reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                        xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
                    </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
                calendar="gregorian">2015-12-17T13:34-0500</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c.1966</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms2015-060</num></subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015 </date>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
            <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                   <label>Processed by: Anthony Wright de Hernandez, Librarian,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>

    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
                Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials,</unittitle>
             <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2015-060</unitid>
            <repository>
                <corpname>Special Collections</corpname>
            </repository>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.1 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 folder</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <unitdate>c.1966</unitdate>
            <abstract id="ref10" label="Abstract">This collection includes materials from a membership recruiting packet for the American Nazi Party from c.1966.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator">
                <corpname source="naf">American Nazi Party.</corpname>; <persname source="local">Koehl, Matt, Jr, (Matthias), 1935-2014</persname>; <persname source="local">Patler, John, 1938-</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref2">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref3">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref5">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials, Ms2015-060, Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref4">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials were purchased by Special Collections in April 2015.</p>
        </acqinfo>  
            <processinfo id="ref7">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the American Nazi Party Recruiting Materials was completed in December 2015.</p>
        </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref8">
            <head>Biographical/Historical note</head>
            <p>The American Nazi Party was founded as the World Union of Free Enterprise National Socialists by George Lincoln Rockwell in 1959. The name was changed to the American Nazi Party in 1960, then to the National Socialist White People's Party in 1967, and finally to New Order in 1983. The party was founded on the political principles of National Socialism (Nazism). The party's political platform included deporting black people, sterilizing Jewish people and liquidating their assets, honoring Adolf Hitler's memory, and promoting racial purity for white people. The party was led by its founder, George Lincoln Rockwell, from 1959 until his assassination in 1967. One of his deputies, Matt Koehl, succeeded him and led the party from 1967 until his death in 2014. Another original member of the party, Rocky Suhayda founded his own organization using the American Nazi Party name. Suhayda's organization has been active since at least the 2008 presidential election and claims a connection to the American Nazi Pary from 1959 but is officially a separate entity.</p>
            <p>George Lincoln Rockwell was born in Bloomington, Illinois on March 9, 1918 and was assassinated in Arlington, Virginia on August 26, 1967. Rockwell's parents were vaudeville comedians and actors. They divorced early in his life and he spent his childhood in both Maine and New Jersey as a result. Rockwell attended Hebron Academy in Maine and Brown University in Providence, Rhode Island before enlisting in the United States Navy in 1940. Following World War II, he worked in the advertising industry in Maine before returning to military service in 1950 for the Korean War. After his time in the Korean War, Rockwell began to read the writings of Adolf Hitler. In 1959, Rockwell founded the American Nazi Party based on the writings and philosophy of Adolf Hitler. He served as Commander of the party from 1959 until he was assassinated by John Patler in 1967.</p>
            <p>Matt Koehl was born January 22, 1935 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin and died in October 2014 in Wisconsin. Koehl studied Journalism at the University of Wisconsin-Madison and served in the United States Marine Corps before joining the American Nazi Party in 1960. Between 1960 and 1967, he served as the National Secretary and second-in-command of the party. Following the assassination of George Lincoln Rockwell in 1967, Koehl became the Commander of the American Nazi Party. He served as Commander until his death in 2014.</p>
            <p>John Patler was born John Patsalos on January 6, 1938 in New York, New York. He served in the United States Marines from 1958 to 1960. In 1960, he received an honorable discharge after being arrested at a Nazi rally, changed his name from Patsalos to Patler, and joined the American Nazi Party. Patler served as a Captain in the American Nazi Party and worked primarily as an editor and cartoonist for the party's magazine, the 
                <title render="italic">Stormtrooper</title>, and other publications. In April 1967, Patler was expelled from the party for "Bolshevick leanings." In August 1967, Patler assassinated American Nazi Party Commander George Lincoln Rockwell. He was convicted of first-degree murder in December 1967 and sentenced to 20 years in prison. In 1975, after serving eight years, he was paroled. He later served an additional six years following a violation of his parole.</p>
        </bioghist>

        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection includes materials from a membership recruiting packet for the American Nazi Party from c.1966. The materials are a letter signed by Matt Koehl, the National Secretary for the American Nazi Party, a biographical article about George Lincoln Rockwell, founder of the American Nazi Party, a copy of the 
                <title render="italic">Program of the World Union of National Socialists</title> describing the party platform, an order form for the party magazine, 
                <title render="italic">The Rockwell Report</title>, an order form for political flyers called "'Back to Africa' tickets", and a copy of a short comic book called 
                <title render="italic">Here Comes Whiteman</title>.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Corporate Names:</head>
            <corpname source="naf">American Nazi Party.</corpname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Persons:</head>
            <persname source="naf">Rockwell, George Lincoln, 1918-1967</persname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Genre and Form Terms</head>
            <genreform source="rbgenr">Ephemera</genreform>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">Fascism</subject>
            <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Political parties--Socialist parties</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref9" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Recruiting materials, <unitdate>c.1966</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid2183001" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
