<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00618">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00618::Richard Colburn Diary, 1861-1863)//EN"
            "viblbv00618.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Richard Colburn Diary, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Colburn, Richard Diary <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2010-010</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011-01-31T14:03-0500</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Richard Colburn Diary, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2010-010</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Carmen Boggs-Parker, Student Assistant; Marc Brodsky,
                        Public Services and Reference Archivist,</label>
          <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Richard Colburn Diary, <unitdate normal="1861/1863" type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms2010-010</unitid>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent>0.1 cu. ft.</extent>
        <extent>1 folder</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">The collection consists of the Civil War diary of
                Richard Colburn, an enlisted soldier of the 12th Infantry of the Army of the
                Potomac. The diary details camp life, daily activities, battles, and Colburn's
                captivity as a POW beginning in July 1862.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Colburn, Richard</persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref3" encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref4" encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Richard Colburn Diary must be obtained
                    from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref5" encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Richard Colburn Diary, Ms2010-010, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref6" encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Richard Colburn Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2009.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo id="ref7" encodinganalog="583$a">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Richard Colburn Diary
                    commenced and was completed in March 2010. Additional description was completed
                    in January 2011.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="ref8" encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Born in Ohio on 8 October 1832, son of Francis Noble Colburn (born, New York) and
                wife, the former Caroline Bloss (born, Vermont), Richard Colburn enlisted in the
                12th Infantry of the United States Regular Army on 18 December 1861. His home at the
                time of his enlistment, as indicated in the diary, was Ellington, Iowa, in Hancock
                County. Colburn served as a cook with Company B of the 12th Infantry Regiment, which
                was attached for much of the war to the Army of the Potomac. He was wounded--shot
                through the calf--and captured at the Battle of Gaines' Mill on 27 June 1862. After
                recuperating for about a month in Confederate hospitals, he was transferred to Union
                custody and eventually was taken to Philadelphia to continue his convalescence. He
                was released from the hospital on 15 January 1863 and returned home.</p>
      <p>His diary mentions several relatives as either recipients or writers of letters.
                Among them are his wife, Elmira, to whom he was married on 7 May 1861; brothers,
                Oliver, Parley, Francis, and Lewis; sisters Maryetta and Rhoda; and brother-in-law
                J.C.[?] Heckart. Other siblings included Paul, Lorenzo, and Harvey. (History of
                Kossuth, Hancock, and Winnebago Counties, Iowa reports that Paul, a member of an
                Illinois regiment, was killed near Richmond and Lorenzo died in hospital, a member
                of the Wisconsin 12th. A Paul Colburn of the Illinois 93rd was killed at Champion
                Hills, MS in May 1863. A Lorenzo Colburn of the Iowa 23rd died of disease in June
                1863 at Young's Point, LA. A Harvey Colburn, also of the Illinois 93rd was
                discharged in January 1863. A Lewis Colburn of Hancock Co. Iowa and a member of the
                2nd Iowa Cavalry, died of disease in June 1865 in Eastport, MS.) Colburn's first
                wife, Diana (Diena) died in Ellington in April 1858, shortly after the death of
                their infant daughter, Calista.</p>
      <p>According to the 1870 census, Richard and Elmira lived in Ellington, Iowa with sons
                Amos, Francis, John, and daughter Caroline. Also in Ellington in 1870 are his
                parents, F.N. Colburn and wife Caroline, along with his brother Parley and his
                family. The 1880 census shows Richard Colburn in Ellington with wife Anna (his
                second wife Elmira died in 1872), age 26, from Holland, with sons Francis and John,
                young daughter Diena, and two nieces and nephews, both from Holland. Later census
                records show Anna's place of birth to be Denmark. Richard Colburn died on 2 December
                1907 in Kingman, Arizona.</p>
      <p>See also: <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">History of Kossuth, Hancock, and Winnebago Counties,
                    Iowa; together with sketches of their cities, villages, and townships,
                    educational, civil, military, and political history; portraits of prominent
                    persons, and biographies of representative citizens</title>, Springfield, IL:
                Union Publishing Co., 1884.</p>
      <p>The Army of the Potomac was organized at Fort Hamilton, New York under the direction
                of President Lincoln on May 4, 1861, and confirmed by Act of Congress on July 29,
                1861. The Army of the Potomac fought in several battles including: Bull Run,
                Antietam, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, and Gettysburg. During the term of
                service, the regiment lost 126 soldiers by death from wounds and 193 men by death
                from diseases.</p>
      <p>Sources and additional resources at <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="http://www.itd.nps.gov/cwss/index.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.itd.nps.gov/cwss/index.html">http://www.itd.nps.gov/cwss/index.html</extref></p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="ref9" encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection consists of the Civil War diary of Richard Colburn, an enlisted
                soldier of the 12th Infantry of the United States Regular Army attached to the Army
                of the Potomac. The diary contains entries from December 18, 1861 to February 17,
                1863 and details camp life, daily activities, battles, and experience as a prisoner
                of the Confederate army. It traces Colburn's first days in the army in Iowa and his
                travel from 14 February 1862 when he left Iowa to his arrival at Fort Hamilton in
                New York City two days later and his continuing journey to Washington DC. Upon
                arrival in Washington, Colburn notes that he "put in to help cook." Many of his
                subsequent entries include brief notations of cooking for the men. Expecting to
                march to Manassas Junction from Washington, he moved first to Camp California, just
                outside Alexandria, VA, and from there to Fort Monroe in late March 1862.</p>
      <p>The 12th Infantry, marching from Fort Monroe, became involved in the Peninsula
                Campaign, which lasted into July 1862. Coburn refers to "the hard battle between
                Yorktown and Richmond" (Battle of Williamsburg) on May 5th and makes reference to
                Big Bethel and Camp Winfield Scott where he was camped. On Friday 27 June 1862,
                Coburn was engaged in the Battle of Gaines' Mill and writes, "marched off to the
                left where we had a heavy battle where Maj. Clitz [Henry Boynton Cliz] myself and
                several others were wounded and taken prisoner by the 5th regiment Va, with some
                that was not wounded, many killed." The remainder of the diary describes his time
                in hospital, both Confederate and Union, his eventual release on 15 January 1863,
                and his trip home. Colburn's last entry is dated 17 February 1863 when he was in
                Southington, Ohio visiting his sister on his way, presumably, to Iowa.</p>
      <p>A transcript of the diary is available as part of the collection.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="ref10" encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by material type.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Local Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="ref11" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Diary, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid99002" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
