<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00264">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00264:: Merritt Hager Smith Diary, 1863)//EN" "viblbv00264.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Merritt Hager Smith Diary, <date>1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Smith, Merritt Hager
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-037
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>7/17/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Merritt Hager Smith Diary, <date>1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-037
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Merritt Hager Smith Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-037
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War diary of Private Merritt Hager Smith of Company G, 97th New York Infantry, serving with the regimental quartermaster.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Creator
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Merritt Hager Smith Diary must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Merritt Hager Smith Diary, Ms2008-037 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Merritt Hager Smith Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Merritt Hager Smith Diary commenced and was completed in July 2008. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>A history of the 97th New York includes in its roster a Private Merritt A. Smith, who enlisted in Boonville, New York on December 16, 1861 at age 19. According to his diary, Smith was born June 28, 1842. Census records indicate that he was the son of Julia Smith of Turin (Lewis County), New York. Smith notes himself a member of the regimental brass band, and Civil War rosters include a Merritt H. Smith who served as a second class musician in the band of the 1st Brigade, 2nd Division, 3rd/1st Army Corps. No further information about Smith could be found.
</p>
<p>The 97th New York Infantry (also known as the Conkling Rifles) was organized in 1861 with men recruited from Herkimer, Lewis and Oneida counties. It was mustered into U. S. service on February 18, 1862, under command of Colonel Charles Wheelock. The regiment saw its first action at Cedar Mountain on August 9. Among the battles in which it fought were Second Bull Run, Antietam, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, The Wilderness, Petersburg, and Appomattox Courthouse. The 97th New York was mustered out of service on July 18, 1865 near Washington, D.C.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains the Civil War diary of Private Merritt Hager Smith of Company G, 97th New York Infantry, a member of the regimental band. The diary entries span the entire year of 1863. The first entry finds Smith receiving orders to proceed to Belle Plain Landing, Virginia to assist Lt. Louis Rowan, the regiment's quartermaster. Smith describes his work, the relative comfort in which he lives, recreation, the weather, homesickness, prayer meetings, sutlers, and makes many references to frequent and excessive drinking by various officers. Smith mentions attending Lincoln's grand review of the 1st Army Corps on April 9. Later that month, the regiment began marching northwestward, frequently changing camp, and Smith writes of the difficulty in marching and the conditions of the various camps. On July 1, the regiment arrived in the Gettysburg, Pennsylvania area. Smith describes the area, provides a brief synopsis of the news he has heard from the battle and mentions speaking with a group of Confederate prisoners. As the army again moves to camps southeastward, Smith notes the many towns and villages through which they pass. He writes of news received via newspaper and word-of-mouth but makes few references to specific battles; nor does he make any significant mention of the regimental band's activities. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive">1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
