<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00274">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00274:: William Vinson Letter, 1854)//EN" "viblbv00274.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William Vinson Letter, <date>1854</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Vinson, William Letter
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-048
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>07/30/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William Vinson Letter, <date>1854</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-048
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William Vinson Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1854
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-048
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Letter from Virginia House of Delegates member William Vinson to his family at home in Wayne County, (West) Virginia, discussing his attempts in the general assembly to secure roads and mail routes, his children's education, health and weather conditions in Richmond, and winning local lotteries.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the William Vinson Letter must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: William Vinson Letter, Ms2008-048 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The William Vinson Letter was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. Sold in a lot named the "Scott County Collection," the letter was accompanied by three receipts for Emory M. Cox and a land sale contract between Samuel Wallace and John Allan. In the course of processing, the items were divided into three separate manuscript collections.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>A typed transcript accompanies the letter.
</p>
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the William Vinson Letter commenced and was completed in July, 2008.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William Vinson, son of James Vinson and Rhoda Sperry, was born about 1819 in Lawrence County, Kentucky. He married Jane Chambers, of Wyoming County, (West) Virginia in September 1835. The couple lived in Wayne County for some time and had several children. Vinson served in the Virginia House of Delegates for one session (1853-1854). One source indicates that he served as a captain in the 14th Kentucky Infantry, though no further record of his service could be found. Vinson died in 1883 in Lawrence County, Kentucky. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains a letter written by Virginia House of Delegates member William Vinson to his wife and children in Wayne County, (West) Virginia. After noting his homesickness, Vinson proceeds to write of the possibility of the general assembly session being extended, then makes note of health conditions in the Richmond area ("the has bin Right smart feever in this plase and small pox...") and describes his personal health. Addressing his son, Richard, Vinson extols at length the value of a good education. He then expresses delight at recent news about the birth of his new son ("Jane after i heard that you had that Whig Boy i enlisted my frends to come to my Room that Nite and that it was my treat..."). Vinson makes some mention of his own endeavors in the general assembly on behalf of his constituents, including his attempts to get a mail route and road up the Tug Fork River and a road up Twelve Pole Creek. Vinson concludes by noting that he has won more than $100 and an expensive pen and pencil set through local lotteries. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter
<unitdate type="inclusive">1854
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
