<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00850">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00850::David M. Davis Ledger, 1875-1896)//EN"
            "viblbv00850.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the David M. Davis Ledger, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1896</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Davis, David M. Ledger <num type="collectionnumber">Ms1940-003</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011-03-24T10:48-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>David M. Davis Ledger, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1896</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms1940-003</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">David M. Davis Ledger, <unitdate normal="1875/1896" type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1896</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms1940-003</unitid>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Characteristics" id="ref5">
        <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
        <extent>1 box</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract id="ref14" label="Abstract">Ledger of David M. Davis, farmer, proprietor of
                clothing/shoe store, treasury clerk, and resident of Washington, D.C. and Fauquier
                County, Virginia. Contains daily transactions of clothing/shoe store, including
                customer name, goods purchased, and prices paid; accounts with farm workers; and
                daily diary entries for summer months of 1890-1892.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref6" encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref7" encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the David M. Davis Ledger must be obtained
                    from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref8" encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: David M. Davis Ledger, Ms1940-003, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref9" encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The David M. Davis Ledger was acquired by Newman Library prior to 1941.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo id="ref10" encodinganalog="583$a">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the David M. Davis Ledger
                    commenced and was completed in March, 2011.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="ref3" encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>David M. Davis was born in New York in 1843. He married Sarah E. Porter (born in
                1842), the daughter of Henry N. and Helen Polson Porter. The 1870 census describes
                David Davis as a treasury clerk, residing in Washington, D.C. Also in the household
                are Sarah Davis and two children: Charles (five) and Helen (two). Washington
                newspapers of 1874-1875 contain notices under the name of D. M. Davis, advertising
                ties and boots for sale at his store, located at the corner of F and Twelfth
                streets. The Davis family is again listed as residents of Washington, D.C. in the
                1880 census, with the addition of two younger children, Henry (eight) and David
                (three). (The record notes that all of the children had been born in Washington,
                with the exception of Helen, born in New York.) An 1897 newspaper account mentions
                that D. M. Davis, a Republican, had lost his job in the Bureau of Engraving to a
                political shakeup in 1893. Materials within this collection show that the Davises
                were living in Fauquier County, Virginia between 1895 and 1896, though it appears
                likely that the family maintained residences in both the capital and in Fauquier for
                a number of years. Sarah E. Davis is listed in the 1900 census as a 57-year-old
                widow living in Washington, D.C., with her three surviving children: Henry, 29;
                David, 23; and Helen, 32. The census again records Sarah Davis living with her
                family in Washington, D.C. in 1910. No further record could be found.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains a ledger maintained (at least in part) by David M. Davis of
                Fauquier County, Virginia. The ledger contains a number of different types of
                entries. The first section consists of a daybook, apparently for a clothing, shoe
                and accessories business opened by Davis at the corner of Washington D. C.'s F and
                12th streets in January, 1875. Over the course of several weeks, the entries detail
                sales of footwear, lace and other clothing goods. Beginning on March 3, 1875, the
                entries describe only general transactions, with no lists of goods purchased. These
                entries continue through November, 1875, perhaps indicating a settlement of the
                business's accounts. The account entries are followed by entries, apparently written
                in a different hand, detailing work performed by various farm laborers, together
                with wages paid in both cash and goods. Among the other items in the ledger's pages
                are a sharecropping agreement with William Brown, receipts, livestock records, and
                copies of letters.</p>
      <p>Also in the ledger is the daily journal of an unidentified individual, presumably a
                woman, perhaps Sarah E. Davis. The entries span July-October 1890, May-October 1891,
                and May-October 1892, indicating that these were the months that the family was
                present on the Fauquier County farm. In brief entries, the journal describes daily
                work on the house and farm, activities of family members, visitors, and weather.</p>
      <p>The collection also contains several loose documents that had been kept within the
                ledger. Among these are a sharecropping contract with J. W. Cubbage and an
                employment/poultry business contract with G. W. Bailey. Also included is a contract
                in which Davis agrees not to press trespassing charges against John Mann with the
                proviso that Mann will relinquish one of his horses to Davis should he be "detected
                in tresspassing [sic] and committing any unlawful act upon the property of said
                Davis..."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="ref11" encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by item type.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="ref2" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ledger, <unitdate normal="1875/1896" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1896</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid612001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="ref12" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Documents, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1895-1896, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="cid612002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
