<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00237">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00237:: John H. Hancock Diary, 1862-1863)//EN" "viblbv00237.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Hancock Diary, <date>1862-1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Hancock, John H. Diary
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-008
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>03/24/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Hancock Diary, <date>1862-1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-008
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John H. Hancock Diary
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1862-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-008
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Civil War diary of John H. Hancock, of Co. H, 29th Massachusetts Infantry. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the John H. Hancock Diary must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: John H. Hancock Diary, Ms2008-008 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University., Ms2008-008, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The John H. Hancock Diary was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the John H. Hancock Diary commenced and was completed in March 2008. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>John H. Hancock, a sergeant in Company H, 29th Massachusetts Infantry during the Civil War, was born ca. 1841 in Massachusetts. While employed as a clerk, Hancock enlisted as a private at Charlestown, Massachusetts, in a unit that would be designated as Company H, 29th Massachusetts Infantry and join the remainder of the regiment already deployed on the Virginia Pensinsula. Hancock was promoted to corporal on August 3, 1862, and to sergeant on March 15, 1863. Wounded, he was discharged from the service on August 25, 1864. Returning to Massachusetts, Hancock married later that year. Together with his wife, Annie, Hancock resided in Chelsea, Massachusetts, and was employed as a custom house inspector. The couple had several children (including Lucy B., Elizabeth, Annie, Herbert and Edgar W.). John H. Hancock died on September 9, 1913.
</p>
<p>The 29th Massachusetts Infantry was organized at Newport News, Virginia, in December 1861, combining the existing 1st Battalion Massachusetts Infantry with three new companies (including Company H) organized in the Suffolk County, Massachusetts area. The regiment remained on the Virginia Peninsula until the end of August, participating in battles at Fair Oaks and Malvern Hill. With the failure of the Peninsula Campaign, the 29th withdrew to Washington, D.C., where it assisted in covering the retreat from the second battle of Bull Run, then joined in the advance into Maryland. The regiment saw heavy losses at the Battle of Antietam. During the fall and winter of 1862, the 29th remained in the northern Virginia area. In the spring, it was transferred westward and participated in the siege of Vicksburg and the capture of Jackson, Mississippi. The regiment spent the fall and winter in eastern Tennessee, participating in the battle of Campbell's Station, then was transferred to eastern Virginia, where it took part in the Wilderness Campaign and the siege of Petersburg. After the fall of Petersburg and Richmond, the regiment returned to northern Virginia. It was mustered out of service on July 29, 1865.
</p> 
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains the diary of John H. Hancock, who served in Company H, 29th Massachusetts Infantry during the Civil War. The diary entries cover January-June 1862, with a single entry made from Paris, Kentucky on April 1, 1863. Hancock's diary entries relate largely routine information such as weather conditions, personal health, camp routines, and troop movements. Longer entries relate to orders, marching, battles, and war news. Frequent mentions are made of gun boats. Contrabands and prisoners of war are also mentioned, as are activities of other regiments within the brigade.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
	<c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diary
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1862-1863
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
