<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00794">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00794::Peter C. Dodge Papers, 1938-1948)//EN"
            "viblbv00794.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Peter C. Dodge Papers, <date>1938-1948</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Dodge, Peter C., Papers <num type="collectionnumber"
                        >Ms2011-012</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date>2011-02-28T11:11-0500</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Peter C. Dodge Papers, <date>1938-1948</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2011-012</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2011 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Sarah R. Olney,</label>
                    <item> Student Assistant, Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Peter C. Dodge Papers, <unitdate
                    normal="1938/1948" type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" label="Date"
                    >1938-1948</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms2011-012</unitid>
            <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Description">
                <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 box</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">The collection contains VT student memorabilia,
                ca.1938-1948.</abstract>
            <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
                <persname source="local">Dodge, Peter C.</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict id="ref3" encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="ref4" encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Permission to publish material from Peter C. Dodge Papers must be obtained from
                    Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite id="ref6" encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Peter C. Dodge Papers, Ms2011-012, Special Collections, Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo id="ref5" encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>The collection was acquired by Special Collections prior to 2007.</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo id="ref7" encodinganalog="583$a">
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Peter C. Dodge Papers was
                    completed in February 2011.</p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref11" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
            <p>Peter C. Dodge was from Catonsville, Maryland. A student at V.P.I from 1936-1940. He
                was a Member of the 1941 Class, but never graduated with his class. It appears that
                he enlisted in the Navy during the war. He graduated in 1948 with a Civil
                Engineering degree. While at school, he joined the Corps, took part in Intermural
                Bowling, and attended a number of concerts, dances and plays. </p>
            <p>In 1887, the Cadet Dancing Club was formed, with its "germans" (a type of formal
                dancing) becoming social features for the students. the German Club started to hold
                dances. In 1891 the club renamed itself, forming the VAMC German Club. It obtained a
                charter in October 1893. Membership was restricted to male students who had the
                "anxiety to dance" and who could "acquit himself creditably on the ballroom floor."
                Membership was by application, but was limited in number and was not easily
                attained. A dance usually began with a figure, led by one of the club members. The
                Viennese waltz, german, cotillion, polka, schottische, and two-step were the dances
                of the day; any new dance had to be demonstrated for, and approved by, faculty wives
                before it would be allowed. At the 1940 Mid-Winter Dance, Tommy Tucker and his
                orchestra were to play for the dance-goers, on February 2 and 3. The concert was
                held on February 2 from 6:45 to 7:15 at the ballroom of the Student Activities
                Building. In 1947 two dances were held by the German Club. The first February 7th
                and 8th, followed by November 14th and 15th. At these dances, Johnny Long and His
                Orchestra and Russ Morgan and His Orchestra played for the guest. </p>
            <p>In March 1913, the first dance was presented by the Cotillion Club. The next year,
                the club "allowed some of the new dances, the one step, grapevine, and the
                hesitation waltz being the most prominent." The Cotillion Club was in competition to
                the German Club Dances.</p>
            <p>The Ring Dance is a VT Class tradition which symbolizes the transition from Junior to
                Senior. The tradition has been celebrated for over 100 years. Upon entering the
                dance, each couple receives a pair of ribbons in the Class colors. The lady wears
                her date's ring on her wrist with the darker colored ribbon, and the gentleman wears
                his date's ring on his wrist with the lighter colored ribbon. When the time comes
                for the Ring Exchange, the Corps of Cadets walk into the ballroom and stand in the
                shape of the Class numerals. As each couple exchanges rings, "Moonlight and VPI,"
                written specifically for the Ring Dance by composer Fred Waring and lyricist Charles
                Gaynor, is played. As the clock strikes midnight, the evening ends with an elaborate
                fireworks display on the Drillfield, and the playing of "Silvertaps." The Class of
                1935 held the first Ring Dance on April 27, 1934, where the ring figure, sabre arch,
                and presentation of the ring by the Junior's date were introduced. Since then, the
                fame of the Ring Dance has spread across the nation, introducing many memorable
                highlights. Always, the Dance is a night to remember for those receiving their
                rings: "Night after night we "dragged" the rats and learned to flip our sabres
                correctly. . . Friday finally rolled around and brought our dates... as well as V.
                M. I.'s ambassadors of good will. The reception at the S. A. B. formally opened our
                debut and after three years of waiting... the figure - the ring - and the kiss. And
                we were made men." </p>
            <p>Halted temporarily during the years 1944-1946 due to World War II, the Ring Dance has
                been a manifestation of fine dining, superior entertainment, and distinctive guests.
                The entire weekend, which occurs in the spring of the junior year, is primarily for
                the Juniors and their dates, although the entire university community is invited.
                Since the beginning, each Virginia Tech class has designed a ring distinctive and
                unique to their class. Today, Virginia Tech is one of only a few colleges and
                universities that redesigns their ring collection each year.</p>
            <p>The Christian Club was succeeded by the Young Men’s Christian Association during the
                1882-1883 session. In 1965 the YMCA merged with the Young Women’s Christian
                Association but retained the YMCA name. Sue Ann “Susie” Shertzer became the first
                female student to be elected as its president in 1967; she was the only woman in the
                country to head a chapter of the organization. The YMCA still exists and operates
                from the Lucy Lee Lancaster house on Washington Avenue. Lancaster, one of the first
                five women to enroll at Virginia Tech in 1921 and a long-time librarian at the
                university, donated the house to the Y.</p>
            <p>The Maroon Mask was an undergraduate student theater club, successor to the Tech
                Players, and a chapter of the National Theater Honor Society, Alpha Psi Omega. By
                the 1940s, student membership had reached 175 people. It was through Maroon Mask
                that the University Theater was formed. </p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content Note</head>
            <p>The collection contains VT student memorabilia, ca.1938-1948. The collection includes
                student identification cards, letters from the school to students, concert and
                performance pamphlets, ticket stubs, a dance card, Honor Code, an over due book
                note, Social Club forms, a list, and membership cards.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref12" encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged by subject matter.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Local Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="local">University Archives</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref17" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Concert Association Materials.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541005" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref18" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Concert and Theatre Programs.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541006" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-2</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref14" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>German and Cotillion Club Materials.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Membership Cards and Ticket Stubs.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref16" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Programs and Newsletters.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541004" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-5</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref15" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Religious Emphasis Program.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-6</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref19" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Silver Lake Social Club.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541007" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-7</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref20" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Unidentified Ephemera.</unittitle>
                    <container id="cid541008" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-8</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
