<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00206">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00206:: Thomas Watson Letters, 1862-1866)//EN" "viblbv00206.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Thomas Watson Letters, <date>1862-1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Watson, Thomas Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-005
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>01/21/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Thomas Watson Letters, <date>1862-1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Accession Number">Ms2008-005
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Speical Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Thomas Watson Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1862-1866
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-005
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Photocopies of typed transcripts of letters of Thomas Watson, a private in Company D, 93rd Illinois Infantry during the Civil War.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Thomas Watson Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Thomas Watson Letters, Ms2008-005 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Thomas Watson Letters were donated to Special Collections in 2008.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the Thomas Watson Letters commenced and was completed in February 2008.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Born in Lancaster County, Pennsylvania on August 15, 1844, Thomas Watson later moved with his family to Stevenson County, Illinois, where they engaged in farming and stockholding. Watson enlisted in Company D of the 93rd Illinois Infantry at Adeline, Illinois, on August 7, 1862. He trained with the regiment at Fort Douglas, Illinois, and participated in Grant's Vicksburg Campaign and Sherman's Atlanta Campaign. Watson mustered out with the regiment on June 23, 1865 at Louisville, Kentucky. In the final letter within this collection, written in 1866, Watson expresses an intent to settle in Macon City, Missouri. By 1869, however, he was in Freeport, Illinois, where he married Lydia Amelia Sheller. An 1898 regimental history indicates that Watson was living in Kansas in the late 19th century. Some time later, the family moved to Olympia, Washington, where Watsson lived until his death on May 23, 1927. He is bured in the Masonic Memorial Park Cemetery of Tumwater, Washington.</p>
<p>The 93rd Illinois Infantry was organized at Chicago and mustered into service on October 13, 1862. The regiment participated in Grant's Vicksburg Campaign and Sherman's Atlanta Campaign. The 93rd was mustered out of service in Kentucky on June 23, 1865.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains photocopies of typed transcripts of the letters of Thomas Watson, a private in Company D, 93rd Illinois Infantry during the Civil War. The letters commence with Watson's training at Camp Douglas, Illinois, then follow his regiment's movements throughout the war. Writing to his parents and brother from camps in Mississippi, Tennessee, Alabama, and Georgia, Watson provides descriptions of prisoners at Camp Douglas, his regiment's movements and battles, his environs, Southerners, and camp life. The letters are accompanied by a brief chronology of Watson's military activities and movements.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive">1862-1866, n.d.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
