<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00574">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV:::: Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings, 1971-1994)//EN" ".xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings, <date>1971-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Ninova, Tsvetana, Architectural Drawings
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2000-006
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Lora Settle, <date>11/09/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings, <date>1971-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2000-006
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Federica Goffi, Architectural Intern; Gerrianne Schaad, Curator of Manuscripts,
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1971-1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2000-006
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">4 oversize folders; 3.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="hun">Hungarian
</language>
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings consist of a resume and 34 architectural drawings (original ink drawings on lucid paper).
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Tsvetana Ninova
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings, Ms2000-006 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings were donated to Special Collections in 1998.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings commenced and was completed in March 2000.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Tsvetana (Tsetsa) Ninova was born on 16 September 1923 in the village of Popitsa, Vratsa County, Bulgaria. She graduated from high school in 1942 in the town of Biala Slatina. She began her architectural studies at the University of Zagrel, Yugoslavia (today the capital of Croatia) in 1943 but, due to the war, returned to Bulgaria (1944) and continued her education at the recently founded (1943) department of Architecture of Sofia Polytechnic. She graduated in 1949 and began working at &quot;Engergoproject&quot; and then at &quot;Glavroject&quot; (1958-1966).
</p>
<p>From 1966 to 1971 Ninova worked in Paris, France at the Institute for Urbanism (1966-1970) and Ecole des Beaux-Arts (1970-1971). She also worked in several architectural offices designing apartment buildings in Paris and the suburbs. Her thesis project, for urban development of Como and the Lake of Como near Milan, Italy, won her recognition in the 1970 international competition. </p>
<p>Moving back to Sofia, Tsvetana worked in the Regional Design Organization and, beginning in 1978, headed a design studio at &quot;Sofproject&quot;, the design organization of Sofia Municipality. After her retirement in 1986, she opened a private office and continued to practice. For two years, from 1991 to 1992, Ninova worked again in Paris as a specialist in housing. In addition to her practice, she has been an adjunct professor at Sofia Polytechnic sharing her expertise in housing design and construction. </p>
<p>For her numerous contributions to the profession Tsvetana Ninova has been recognized several times. In 1981 she received first prize at the Biennial of the International Union of Architects for her housing estate &quot;Mladost 4&quot; in Sofia. The following year she was decorated with the order &quot;Sts Cyril and Methodius&quot;. In 1983 she received the gold badge of the Union of Bulgarian Architects and in 1986 the order &quot;Red Banner of Labor&quot;. For her large housing estate &quot;Beli Brezi&quot; (white birches), for which she won a national competition (1977), Ninova was awarded the Silver Hexagon at the international competition &quot;Habitation Space&quot; in Milan, Italy in 1980 and the Grand Prize of Sofia in 1983. At her exhibition commemorating fifty years of professional practice (October 1998) Tsvetana Ninova was recognized by the Union of Bulgarian Architects with its highest award, the Gold Badge with Precious Stone. </p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Tsvetana Ninova Architectural Drawings consist of a resume and 34 architectural drawings (original ink drawings on lucid paper). This collection documents the design of the Railroad Station in Ikhtiman (5 original drawings), located in Bulgaria and the design of Rest Shop Facilities, located in Kolotino, Bulgaria (11 original drawings). 
</p>
<p>The collection also contains one original drawing documenting the design of a multi-family apartment house with commercial facilities located at the corner of Bulgaria, Topli dol and Poduevo Streets, Bulgaria.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged chronologically. 
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<unittitle>Curriculum Vitae
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize" type="oversize">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<unittitle>Railroad Station in Ikhtiman, Bulgaria.
(5) original drawings regarding the preliminary design (ink on lucid paper),
<unitdate type="inclusive">1971.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize" type="oversize">2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<unittitle>Rest shop facilities, Kolotino, Bulgaria.
(11) Original design and working drawings (ink on lucid paper), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1973-1975.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize" type="oversize">3
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<unittitle>Multi family apartment house with commercial facilities on the ground floor (18 original ink drawings on lucid paper), 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1994.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Oversize" type="oversize">4
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
