<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv00520">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00520:: Frances A. Murdoch Journal, 1861-1863)//EN" "viblbv00520.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Frances A. Murdoch Journal, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Murdoch, Frances A.
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-132
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10/15/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-23">2014-01-23</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Frances A. Murdoch Journal, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-132
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Frances A. Murdoch Journal
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-132
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="DIGITAL CONTENT">
        <emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://omeka.lib.vt.edu/items/show/2673">online</extref></emph>.</physdesc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Journal of a young woman living on a Mississippi plantation during the Civil War, relaying descriptions of a battle between the Natchez militia and a Union gunboat, the death of Colonel Stuart Wilkins Fisk at the Battle of Murfreesboro, the plundering of Bruinsburg by Union soldiers, and other war news.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Frances A. Murdoch Journal must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Frances A. Murdoch Journal, Ms2009-132 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Frances A. Murdoch Journal was donated to Special Collections in 2005. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail id="ref11">
        <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
        <p>This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://omeka.lib.vt.edu/items/show/2673" xlink:actuate="onRequest">online</extref>.</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing and description of the Frances A. Murdoch Journal commenced and was completed in October 2009. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Frances A. "Fannie" Murdoch was born in Mississippi around 1847. Her father, John Murdoch (1813-1861) had been born in Louisiana, attended Yale University (class of 1834), and in 1840 married Frances Louisa Bristol (1819-1875), daughter of a New Haven, Connecticut family. The Murdochs later resided at Cane Mount, their cotton plantation near Rodney (Jefferson County), Mississippi. Fannie was one of eight children and was schooled by private tutors at home with her siblings  before briefly attending Professor Baird's school from December 1862 until April 1863. No further information about Fannie Murdoch could be found.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of a journal maintained by Frances A. "Fannie" Murdoch, a young woman living on a Mississippi plantation during the Civil War. Containing approximately 90 pages, the journal commences with an entry dated May 29, 1861. The journal is largely introspective in nature, as Murdoch dwells on personal feelings, focusing heavily on her religious beliefs. She often questions her worthiness and chastises herself for sins, frequently mentioning her quick temper. At the same time, Murdoch takes pride in the evening Bible studies she conducts with the plantation's slaves. Murdoch also describes the weather and often refers to siblings Willie, Jonnie and Sallie, as well as various relatives, servants and neighbors. 
</p>
      <p>As the Civil War commences, Murdoch very briefly mentions reports from Harpers Ferry and Philippi, Virginia. After the Battle of Manassas, her entries focus more on war rumors and news. She mentions a personal telegram received by acquaintances from President Davis, relaying news of the Confederate victory at Manassas, and Davis' proclamation for a day of prayer and fasting. </p>
      <p>On April 18, 1862, Murdoch expresses thanks for what she considers a Confederate victory at Shiloh, while at the same time disagreeing with those who believe the war's end may soon be drawing near. "...I think we have just begun this long dreary war," she writes. "Still we must fight on, our lives, our homes, our lands, our slaves, depend on the end of this matter." As the war progresses, she becomes ever less hopeful of victory and mentions a prophecy that the war will last four years and result in the reunification of the states. She relays secondhand but somewhat lengthy descriptions of a battle between the Natchez militia and a Union gunboat, the death of Colonel Stuart Wilkins Fisk at the Battle of Murfreesboro, and the plundering of Bruinsburg by Union soldiers. Elsewhere, she reports the surrenders of New Orleans and Vicksburg. </p>
      <p>On a few occasions, Murdoch expresses her fear of a slave insurrection but feels confident that slaves Ben or Henry would save her and brother Jonnie, "as they say they like us so much." Elsewhere, Murdoch deplores the torture used on Natchez slaves to elicit information about rumored plans for an uprising. On May 3, 1863, she notes that many of the family's slaves have departed, averring that they had forgotten how well they were treated by the family and comparing them to a fly being lured by a spider--the lure in this case being the promise of eleven dollars a month. Also on this date, Murdoch notes that the carriage horses are all gone, and she feels in danger of being "outraged and insulted at any time." After intermittent entries made during the next several months, the journal ends on October 12, 1863. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <blockquote>
        <p><emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://omeka.lib.vt.edu/items/show/2673" xlink:actuate="onRequest">online</extref></emph>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
