<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00360">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00360:: USS Pittsburg Paymaster's Ledger, 1862)//EN" "viblbv00360.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the USS Pittsburg Paymaster's Ledger, <date>1862</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">USS Pittsburg Paymaster's Ledger
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-026
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>02/13/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the USS Pittsburg Paymaster's Ledger, <date>1862</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-026
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">USS<title render="italic"> Pittsburg</title> Paymaster's Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1862
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-026
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.3 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">U.S. Navy paymaster's ledger, believed to be from the USS <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title>, a Union Navy gunboat during the Civil War. Also includes a single sheet officers' pay roll, dated 1866, believed to be from the USS <title render="italic">Shawmut</title>.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the USS <title render="italic"> Pittsburg</title> Paymaster's Ledger must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: USS <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title> Paymaster's Ledger, Ms2009-026 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The USS<title render="italic"> Pittsburg</title> Paymaster's Ledger was purchased by Special Collections in 2008. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing and description of the USS<title render="italic"> Pittsburg</title> Paymaster's Ledger commenced and was completed in February 2009. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>The USS <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title> (sometimes spelled the "<title render="italic">Pittsburgh</title>"), an ironclad gunboat, was built at St. Louis Missouri and commissioned for service in January 1862, with Lieutenant Egbert Thompson commanding. Joining the U. S. Army's Western Gunboat Flotilla, the <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title> sustained damage during the bombardment of Fort Donelson, Tennessee. Following repairs, the gunboat participated in the sieges of Mississippi River Island 10 and Fort Pillow later that spring. The <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title> was transferred to U. S. Navy service on October 1, 1862 and joined in operations on the Yazoo River and Steele's Bayou, Mississippi. In April 1863, the gunboat successfully passed Confederate emplacements at Vicksburg and led the attack at Grand Gulf. In 1864, the <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title> joined the Red River Expedition. The gunboat was decommissioned after the war and sold in November 1865. 
</p>
<p>The USS <title render="italic">Shawmut</title>  was a steamship commissioned for service in the U.S. Navy in 1864. With Lt. Commander George U. Morris commanding, the <title render="italic">Shawmut</title> served primarily as a gunboat within the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron. In 1865, it was refitted for foreign service and soon afterward sailed to Brazil Station, where it served a year before being decommissioned in December 1866. Recommissioned in August 1867, the gunboat served in the North Atlantic Squadron until July 1868, and again from March 1871 until January 1877. The USS <title render="italic">Shawmut</title> was decommissioned and sold to E. Stannard &amp; Co. in September 1877.</p>
<p>George Upham Morris was born in Massachusetts in 1830 and commissioned a U. S. Navy midshipman in 1846. By March 1862, Morris was a lieutenant in temporary command of the USS <title render="italic">Cumberland</title> when that vessel was sunk by the CSS <title render="italic">Virginia</title>. Promoted to lieutenant-commander in July 1862, Morris was placed in command of the gunboat <title render="italic">Port Royal</title>, serving in the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron and later the Western Gulf Blockading Squadron. He took command of the USS <title render="italic"> Shawmut</title> in 1864, serving in that position until 1866, when given command of the <title render="italic">Brooklyn</title>. Morris retired from the navy in 1874 and died the following year.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains a paymaster's ledger from an unidentified Union Navy ship during the Civil War. Research on the crewmembers named within the ledger suggests that the item originated from the USS <title render="italic">Pittsburg</title>. The ledger contains the names of 169 sailors and records the pay issued to each in the form of clothing, personal goods from small stores, and money. Listed among the crew are two "contrabands," African Americans who had escaped slavery and joined Union military forces. 
</p>
<p>The collection also contains a single payroll sheet listing officers of an unidentified ship. Again based on research on individual names--including those of George U. Morris, commander; and B. J. Cromwell, lieutenant-commander--the item seems likely to have been from the USS <title render="italic">Shawmut</title>. The sheet contains names of officers, their rank, and pay.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Paymaster's Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive">1862
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
<physdesc>[accompanied by payroll sheet, 1866]
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
