<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv00344">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00344::
      Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers, 1863-1864)//EN" "viblbv00344.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers, <date era="ce"
            calendar="gregorian">1863-1864</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Hutchins, Everett and Warren Papers <num type="collectionnumber"
            >Ms2009-014 </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic
          Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">01/20/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1863-1864</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-014
        </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
      University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
        Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers <unitdate
          type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1863-1864 </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-014 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="DIGITAL CONTENT">
        <emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/74">online</extref></emph>.
      </physdesc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft. </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Five items relating to Everett and Warren Hutchins, who served
        during the Civil War in the 33rd Massachusetts Infantry and 7th Massachusetts Light
        Artillery Battery respectively. Includes diary, two letters and two cartes-de-visite.
      </abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers must be
          obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information:
          Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers, Ms2009-014 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic
          Institute and State University. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 2008.
        </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail id="ref16">
        <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
        <p>This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/74" xlink:actuate="onRequest">online</extref>.</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information </head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Everett and Warren Hutchins Papers
          commenced and was completed in January 2009. </p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information </head>
      <p>Edward Everett Hutchins, the son of Stephen and Catharine Hutchins, was born November 17,
        1842. The 1860 census lists an Everett Hutchins as a servant--probably an apprentice--in the
        Lowell, Massachusetts home of Isaac Scripture, baker. Hutchins enlisted in Company F, 33rd
        Massachusetts Infantry and mustered into service with the company on August 5, 1862. Everett
        Hutchins was killed at the Battle of Resaca, Georgia on May 15, 1864. </p>
      <p>Warren E. Hutchins, brother of Everett Hutchins, served with the 7th Battery, Massachusetts
        Light Artillery. He died in a hospital at De Valls Bluff, Arkansas on November 29, 1864.</p>
      <p>The 33rd Massachusetts Infantry was organized at Springfield, Massachusetts during the
        summer of 1862 and mustered into Federal service in August. The regiment arrived in
        Washington, D.C. on August 17. Establishing camp across the Potomac, the regiment remained
        in defense of northern Virginia throughout the autumn and went into winter quarters near
        Falmouth. In 1863, the regiment participated in the battles of Chancellorsville and
        Gettysburg, then was encamped near Bristoe Station, Virginia before being ordered southward.
        In September, the 33rd arrived in Bridgeport, Tennessee. It saw heavy fighting at Wauhatchie
        on October 29 and participated in the battles of Lookout Mountain and Missionary Ridge
        before going into winter quarters. In May 1864, the regiment joined the Atlanta campaign and
        saw heavy fighting at Resaca (May 16), Dallas (May 25) and Kenesaw Mountain (June 22). The
        regiment participated in the siege of Atlanta, the city's occupation, and Sherman's march to
        the sea, then in the march northward into the Carolinas. At war's end, the 33rd participated
        in the Grand Review at Washington, D.C. and was mustered out of service on June 10,
        1865.</p>
      <p>The 7th Battery, Massachusetts Light Artillery, was organized as Richardson's Light Guard,
        an independent infantry company, at Lowell, Massachusetts. The company was mustered into
        service on May 21, 1861 and immediately departed for Fort Monroe, Virginia, where it engaged
        in garrison duty through the fall and winter. Detached on light artillery duty on December
        25, the company became designated the 7th Massachusetts Battery on March 17. The unit served
        in eastern Virginia, seeing action near Franklin and Deserted House and participating in the
        siege of Suffolk. In May 1863, it joined the Carrsville Expedition, then remained at
        Portsmouth until June, participating in Dix's Peninsula Campaign. In July, the 7th was
        ordered to Washington, D.C., and from there to New York, where it saw duty during the draft
        riots. In September, the battery returned to Washington, D.C., where it remained for several
        months. In January 1864, the 7th sailed to New Orleans, and it would eventually serve in the
        Red River Campaign, generally remaining in Arkansas from May 1864 until January 1865. The
        battery returned to Louisiana, then moved to Dauphin Island, Alabama in February,
        participating in the campaign against Mobile. The 7th remained in Alabama through June, then
        was moved to Houston, Texas, where it served until October. The 7th Massachusetts Light
        Artillery returned to Boston and was mustered out on November 10, 1865. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection contains five items relating to Everett and Warren Hutchins, two brothers
        who served in Massachusetts military units during the Civil War. The collection includes
        cartes-de-visite of Everett (Company F, 33rd Massachusetts Infantry) and Warren (7th
        Independent Battery, Massachusetts Light Artillery), with Warren appearing in full uniform. </p>
      <p>Also included are two letters from Everett, addressed to his sister. In a letter written
        January 3, 1864 at Lookout Valley, Tennessee, Everett discusses winter quarters, the
        regiment's recent march to Knoxville and back, and various family members. In the second
        letter, written on April 3, [1864], Everett discusses at length brother Warren's term of
        military service, expressing the opinion that Warren will have to serve out his three-year
        enlistment regardless of when his battery's term of enlistment ends. </p>
      <p>Warren Hutchins' diary for 1863 is also included in the collection. Commencing on January
        1, apparently from the area of Nansemond County, Virginia, Warren writes of weather
        conditions, battery target practice and goods received from home. In brief, daily entries,
        he makes frequent mention of drill, inspection, police and picket duty. He writes of the
        battery firing salutes in honor of generals Corcoran, "Heys" [Hays?], and Halleck.
        Occasionally, he mentions war news and rumors, including the Battle of Murfreesboro, the
        destruction of the <emph render="italic">Monitor</emph>, the capture of the <emph render="italic">Indianola</emph>, draft riots, and Hooker's Chancellorsville defeat. At the
        end of January, Warren describes an unidentified battle [probably at Deserted House,
        Virginia] and another battle in mid-April, probably at Blackwater. A lengthy entry for May
        1, 1863 describes another unidentified battle, followed by a description of the Carrsville
        Expedition in mid-May. The next entry, for May 26, seems to describe the return of the 6th
        Massachusetts Militia (9 months' service) to Boston. The trip is described, as is the
        welcoming ceremony, and the governor's address to the regiment is paraphrased at length.
        Diary entries commence again with June 5, 1863 and recount the 7th's daily movement on the
        Virginia Peninsula until it was ordered back to Washington D.C. on July 20. Warren writes of
        the battery's arrival in New York on August 19 in response to the draft riots and describes
        the battery's placement in the city. With the exception of an entry for September 25, the
        remainder of the diary is blank. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by document type. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <blockquote>
        <p><emph render="bold">This collection has been digitized and is available 
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/74" xlink:actuate="onRequest">online</extref></emph>.</p>
      </blockquote>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Papers <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1864, n.d.
            </unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
