<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viblbv00339">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00339:: Henry Helms Letters, 1861-1863)//EN" "viblbv00339.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Helms Letters, <date>1861-1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Helms, Henry Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-008
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date>01/12/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Helms Letters, <date>1861-1863</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-008
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henry Helms Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1861-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-008
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Photocopies of typed transcripts of Civil War letters of Private Henry Helms of Company I, 95th Pennsylvania Infantry, mortally wounded at the Battle of Gaines' Mill. 
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Henry Helms Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Henry Helms Letters, Ms2009-008 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Henry Helms Letters were donated to Special Collections. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Henry Helms Letters commenced and was completed in January 2009. 
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>Henry Helms, son of Ann, was born in 1838. A resident of Philadelphia, Helms worked as a bookbinder for approximately two years prior to the Civil War. Helms enlisted in Company I, 95th Pennsylvania Infantry on August 10, 1861. He received a head wound at the Battle of Gaines' Mill on June 27, 1862 and was presumed to have died soon thereafter.
</p>
<p>The 95th Pennsylvania Infantry was organized at Philadelphia beginning in August 1861. The regiment was mustered into Federal service in October 1861 and ordered to the defense of Washington, D.C. later that month. The 95th remained in northern Virginia until April 1862, when it joined McClellan's Virginia Peninsular Campaign. The regiment participated in the Seven Days Battles, before being moved back to northern Virginia. During the next three years, the regiment would participate in all of the major battles of the eastern theatre (including Antietam, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, The Wilderness, Spotsylvania Courthouse, and Cold Harbor. It also participated in Sheridan's Shenandoah Campaign, the siege of Petersburg, and the Appomattox Campaign. The 95th Pennsylvania Infantry mustered out of service on July 17, 1865. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains photocopies of typed transcripts of the Civil War letters of Private Henry Helms of Company I, 95th Pennsylvania Infantry. Writing from various camps, Helms addresses most of his letters to brother James Helms, at home in Philadelphia. Other letters are addressed to his mother, Ann. Helms' early letters focus mostly on personal matters, including his need for various items of clothing and food. He complains of the camp sutlers, compliments his officers, writes of weather and health conditions (including vaccination for smallpox), mentions mutual acquaintances, describes the execution of a deserter, and notes the ruinous conditions of some northern Virginia mansions.  On November 26, 1861, he mentions seeing President Lincoln and describes Lincoln's horsemanship. From November 1861 to March 1862, Helms writes from Camp Franklin, near Alexandria, Virginia. Beginning in April, Helms' letters are written from the <title render="italic">State of Maine</title> and from various camps on the Virginia Peninsula. He describes skirmishes, the aftermath of battle, and Confederate prisoners-of-war; and notes camp activities and rumors. His letter of May 8 describes a combat engagement at West Point. 
</p>
<p>The correspondence also contains two letters from John Harper, commanding officer of Company I, describing Helms' battlefield wound and certifying his death. Also included are letters from C. P. Goodwin and David F. Foley, also of Company I, providing their knowledge of Helms' fate.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
