<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00321">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00321:: Hamilton S. Sclater Letters, 1862-1864)//EN" "viblbv00321.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Hamilton S. Sclater Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1864</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Sclater, Hamilton S., Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-087
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Marc Brodsky, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/24/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Hamilton S. Sclater Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1864</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2008-087
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Marc Brodsky,
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Hamilton S. Sclater Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1864
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2008-087
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Three Civil War letters, all written by Hamilton S. Sclater, Company D, 25th Virginia Battalion, to his mother. Letter of 13 August 1862, written from a camp near Gordonsville (Orange County Virginia), describes the aftermath of the Battle of Cedar Mountain. Other letters, dated 6 April 1864 and 4 July 1864 respectively, were written from Camp Chaffin's Farm, an area of fortifications south of Richmond.
</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Hamilton S. Sclater
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Hamilton S. Sclater Letters must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information:  Hamilton S. Sclater Letters, Ms2008-087 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Hamilton S. Sclater Letters were purchased by Special Collections in 2004.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Hamilton S. Sclater Letters commenced and was completed in November 2008.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Hamilton S. Sclater was born in Fluvanna County Virginia in 1844, the son of Robert, a farmer, and Janetta (possibly Jennetta) Sclater. Census indexes for 1850 and 1860 record the family name as Selater. The 1850 census shows a family of eight brothers and sisters: William H., age 18; James R., age 16; Mary A.[?], age 14; Richard J., age 12; Morton T.[?], age 8; Hamilton S., age 6; George T., age 4; and Louisa E., age one month. The ages of the parents, Robert and Janetta are shown as 42 and 39, respectively. By 1860, the only children listed are Morton, Hamilton, George, and Louisa. The 1870 census shows Morton and Hamilton living with their parents in the Cunningham Township of Fluvanna County The occupation of each is noted as "works on James," while Robert continues to be listed as a farmer, and Janetta's occupation is "keeping house." Cunningham Township lies in the southwestern corner of Fluvanna County and is bordered by the James River on the south.
</p>
      <p>Hamilton S. (H.S.) Sclater was a private in D Company of the 25th Virginia Battalion in April and July 1864 when he wrote two of the letters in this collection. Part of the Local Defense Troops, the 25th was known as the Richmond City Battalion, or simply the City Battallion, as Sclater refers to it. Company D, commanded by Captain John F. C. Potts, was known as the Richmond Minute Men. Muster rolls for the 25th Battalion show that Sclater was enlisted on either 21 January or 18 February 1863, in Richmond, by either Captain S. T. Bailey or Captain Potts. According to Wallace's A Guide to Virginia Military Organizations, 1861-1865, the 25th was originally organized on 15 August 1862 for a period of six months, for service in and around Richmond. It was then re-mustered in January and February 1863.
</p>
      <p>Sclater's first letter, dated 13 August 1862, requests that mail be directed to him via "Ewell's Division Earley's Brigade." In Stonewall Jackson at Cedar Mountain, Robert K. Krick identifies the infantry units comprising Jubal Early's brigade as the Virginia 13th, 25th, 31st, 52nd, 58th, and the 12th Georgia. Existing muster rolls for the 25th Virginia Infantry do not include records for H. S. Sclater. 
</p>
      <p>The battle at Cedar Mountain began in earnest on Saturday 9 August 1862. Sclater reports that he arrived at the battlefield the following morning. His letter to his mother was written the following Wednesday from camp near Gordonsville, approximately 15 miles south of the battle site.
</p>
      <p>The letter from Chaffin's Farm on 4 July 1864 mentions George, Hamilton's younger brother, of whom Sclater says, "it would be best for him to join this Company before he is 18."
</p>
      <p>Sources:</p>
      <p>Wallace, Jr., Lee A. A Guide to Virginia Military Organizations, 1861-1865, rev. 2nd ed. Lynchburg, VA: H.E. Howard, Inc., 1986.
</p>
      <p>Krick, Robert K. Stonewall Jackson at Cedar Mountain. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1990.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains three letters written by Hamilton S. Sclater, a private in Company D, 25th Battalion Virginia Infantry during the Civil War. These letters describe several aspects of the life of a Confederate soldier in Virginia. The earlier letter, written following the battle at Cedar Mountain, describes the "considerable loss" on both sides and mentions the capture of a Union brigadier general. (The general in question is Henry Prince.) In this letter, Sclater also describes, in some detail, one of the several presumed, but false Union charges that led to a Confederate panic. (In Stonewall Jackson at Cedar Mountain, Krick suggests that the Cedar Mountain campaign involved "more unwarranted panics than any two other campaigns of the war combined.") 
</p>
      <p>The letters from Chaffin's Farm in April and July 1864 report a quieter scene, despite mention of the shelling of Petersburg in the latter, but also a situation where rations are meager and Sclater's hunger is evident. General Grant's order to General Lee to surrender Petersburg or face its destruction is mentioned, as is Sclater's hope that "Lee will not give it up without a fight. . . ." (Chaffin's Farm, an area of fortifications south of Richmond, would, in late September 1864, be the site of a major engagement.)
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged chronologically. 
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Letters">
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1864
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
