<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00202">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00202::
      Martha L. Johnson Family Papers, 1821-1882)//EN" "viblbv00202.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Martha L. Johnson Family Papers, <date era="ce"
            calendar="gregorian">1821-1882</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Johnson, Martha L. Family Papers <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2001-065
          </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By Virginia Polytechnic
          Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10/26/2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Martha L. Johnson Family Papers, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1821-1882</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Accession Number">Ms2001-065
        </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
      University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
        Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Martha L. Johnson Family Papers <unitdate
          type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1821-1882 </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2001-065 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 container; 0.5 cu. ft. </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator"><famname>Martha L. Johnson family</famname></origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Martha L. Johnson Family Papers must be obtained
          from the Special Collections, Virginia Tech. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Martha L. Johnson Family Papers, Ms2001-065 - Special Collections, University Libraries,
          Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The Martha L. Johnson Family Papers were donated to the Special Collections in 2001. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information </head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Martha L. Johnson Family Papers
          commenced in June 2004 and was completed in October 2006. </p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information </head>
      <p>Martha L. "Patsy" Robinson Johnson was born in Frederick County, Virginia on February 19,
        1803. Evidence suggests that she was the daughter of William and Martha Robinson of Orange
        County, Virginia. Martha married Robert C. Johnson (ca.1798-1863), the son of Valentine and
        Ann Johnson of Orange County, probably in the late 1820s. The Johnsons moved several times
        during the following two decades. In 1833, they lived at Amherst Court House and at
        Lynchburg, where Robert was a merchant. The next year, they were living in Patrick County,
        Virginia, where Robert was keeper of a public house and served as master commissioner of the
        Patrick County superior court. The family was still in Patrick County as late as 1839,
        though Robert was operating the Red Sulphur Springs tavern that year. In 1840/41, Robert was
        keeping tavern in Danville, Virginia, while Martha and his daughters lived in Stanardsville
        (Greene County). </p>
      <p>The Johnsons seem to have settled by 1843 in Carroll County, Virginia, where Robert kept a
        tavern. Evidence in the collection suggests that he also operated a store and served as
        Hillsville postmaster and commissioner of the revenue. The couple had three daughters: Ann,
        Martha and Alverda.</p>
      <p>The Carroll County census for 1860 lists Robert Johnson as "insane." He was hospitalized in
        the Eastern Lunatic Asylum (Williamsburg, Virginia) later that year and died there around
        October 23, 1860. By 1880, Martha Johnson was living with her son-in-law, John Early, and
        his children in Carroll County. She died April 15, 1886.</p>
      <p>Ann Johnson (1828-1879), oldest daughter of Robert and Martha Robinson Johnson, was born in
        Orange County, Virginia. She married John Early (born c.1821), and the couple had several
        children, including Peter S., Robert J., James L., and William H., and Martha
        (c.1851-1864).</p>
      <p>Alverda "Buddie" Johnson (1830-1917) married twice, first to James H. Hounshell in 1849.
        The couple had one daughter, Martha (1852-1865). After Hounshell's death, Alverda married
        Robert Toncrey (born ca.1815), a local dentist, in 1863. The couple's children included Mary
        E., Laura E. and Alverda J.</p>
      <p>Martha Loury Johnson (1832-1916) married William Craig Thornton (1825-1913) in 1848.
        William worked at times as a tailor, a dry goods merchant, and operator of Hillsville's
        Thornton Hotel. He also served as justice of the peace. The couple raised a large family,
        including Alverda R., Emma R. ("Sissie"), Ann Eliza, Margaret B., Martha Elizabeth, Ida May,
        Agnes W., Jesse Maud, Dora N., Robert Cave Johnson, and William Hiram.</p>
      <p>William Lithgow Robinson, Martha Johnson's nephew, was born around 1837. He enlisted in the
        Danville Blues on April 23, 1861; prior to enlistment, he had worked as a clerk. In October
        1861, Robinson was hospitalized at Orange Court House, Virginia with periostitis; he
        returned to duty on November 18. He was again admitted to the hospital on March 11 for
        contusion of the leg and was discharged April 5, 1862. Robinson's own letters indicate that
        he was infected with typhoid in 1861, probably resulting from the contaminated water at
        Manassas, where, he wrote, "All the streams and springs were contaminated with putrefying
        bodies of men and horses." He also mentions being wounded in the leg during hand-to-hand
        combat in October 1861. By 1863, Robinson was working as deputy clerk of Hastings Court
        House and as chief of police in Danville, Virginia. He died March 1, 1914 and is buried in
        Danville's Green Hill Cemetery.</p>
      <p> Creating a sketch of this family proved difficult. Martha Robinson Johnson seems to have
        been known as "mother" by both her children and her grandchildren; likewise, Ann Johnson
        Early was referred to as "Sister Ann" by all family members. The prevalent use of nicknames
        within the correspondence compounds the difficulty in identifying individuals, as does the
        large number of extended family of both Johnsons and Robinsons. (Among Martha's siblings
        mentioned in this collection are Thomas A., William R., Norborne and Richard Robinson; named
        within the collection as siblings of Robert are Belfield C., Benjamin V., George W., and
        William B. Johnson, Mildred C. Collins, Lucy Leggett, and Sallie Ann Dickerson.) The sketch
        above is based on interpretation of the documents and surviving public (especially census)
        records, and therefore likely contains errors. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection contains the papers of the family of Martha L. Robinson Johnson,
        nineteenth-century matriarch of a Carroll County, Virginia family. The collection consists
        largely of correspondence to Johnson from various family members and friends, providing a
        chronicle of the life of a Southwest Virginia family during the mid-nineteenth century,
        mostly from a feminine perspective. The letters focus on childbirth, death, illness, folk
        medicine, fashion, sewing, knitting, quilting, gardening, food, spirituality and the Civil
        War. The letters were mailed from various locales--mostly in Virginia--including Hillsville,
        Copper Mines, Orange Court House, Lynchburg, Texas House, Chatham Hill, Coal Hill, Warm
        Springs, Red Sulphur Springs, Spring Valley, Grayson County, Cove and Hickory Grove. Though
        the majority of the correspondence is addressed to Martha Johnson, the collection also
        contains correspondence to and from her husband, Robert C. Johnson, a Carroll County tavern
        keeper, postmaster and commissioner of revenue. </p>
      <p>Significant among the letters from extended family are those of William Lithgow Robinson,
        nephew of Martha Johnson and a soldier in Company A, 18th Virginia Infantry ("Danville
        Blues"). Robinson's letters, which focus on accounts of camp life and battles, include
        references to Harpers Ferry, Vienna, Fairfax Court House, Germantown, Manassas, Richmond,
        Centreville, Leesburg, Gordonsville, General Johnson, food, sickness (typhoid fever) and
        clothing. Robinson describes battle scenes in which he saw dead Yankees "piled up 15-20 to a
        grave." He reports the Danville Blues fought at Bull Run and lost 41 men. Robinson also
        mentions alcohol use among his fellow soldiers. On December 3, 1861, Robinson wrote a moving
        letter to Martha Johnson describing how he witnessed the execution of two men for attempting
        to kill an officer.</p>
      <p>The collection also includes the Johnsons' legal and financial papers. Significant among
        the legal papers is the 1848 will of Valentine Johnson, of Orange County. The financial
        records include mostly personal receipts, account statements, and promissory notes but also
        include several items which appear to be subscription fee bills to local residents from the
        Hillsville post office. Also among the financial records are several of the Johnsons'
        account books, including two that were apparently kept by Robert Johnson acting in the
        capacity of commissioner of revenue. The books list, among other things, resident names and
        numbers of white tithes, slaves between 12 and 16, slaves over the age of 16, watches,
        clocks, 2- and 4-wheel carriages, etc. </p>
      <p>Among other miscellaneous materials in the collection are a subscription/promotional
        booklet for Fitch W. Taylor's <title render="italic">Voyage Round the World and Visits to
          Various Foreign Countries of the United States Squadron</title>, a handwritten cure for
        dysentery, a petition-letter of recommendation for Robert C. Johnson, an obituary for Martha
        Ann Hounshell, and a canvas pocket document organizer used by Robert Johnson.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by document type. Correspondence--arranged alphabetically by
        surname, then chronologically--is followed by legal, financial, and miscellaneous materials.
      </p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="local">Folk, historical, and patent medicine</subject>
        <subject source="local">Local/Regional History and Appalachian South</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Traditional medicine</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Women -- History</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
   <dsc type="combined">
     <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref10_u8q" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>A-C correspondence,
          <unitdate>1866-1881, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_704bfc2cf429a21983d4cf7ddee955d5">[17 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_2c05821e282ff7d630b1baeffa3c8bec" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_88107c8acc477fdfd07ab2ccd617094f"
            parent="aspace_2c05821e282ff7d630b1baeffa3c8bec" type="folder">1</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref12_hzz" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Brown, Jane</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref13_d1a" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Byrd, E. R.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref14_ohl" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Campbell, Kate R.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref15_2ac" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Chaffin, Sarah A.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref16_niu" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Crawford, E. R.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref17_51s" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>D-I correspondence,
          <unitdate>1849-1881, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_14872d8519c63983ef543bbaf170dc6b">[13 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_1277157371753c13563484ce9985ed67" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_936cd5c5bca774b01370dc1e5333b599"
            parent="aspace_1277157371753c13563484ce9985ed67" type="folder">2</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref19_yuw" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dickenson, Sallie Ann</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref20_evs" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Early, Ann E.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref21_k7v" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Early, John</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref22_iiy" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Galt, John M. (Eastern Lunatic Asylum)</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref23_zpn" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Garland, A. B.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref24_ewt" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hale, A. S.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref25_1zh" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hounshell, Martha Ann</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref26_mjy" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Johnson, Ann correspondence,
          <unitdate>1831</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_3ef6b2a6080f019be5442c8ae73c4b50">[1 item]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_09069cc7b2b225bf45b4cb42aa845123" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_1f57abf03467b755b85302ca2ba1a902"
            parent="aspace_09069cc7b2b225bf45b4cb42aa845123" type="folder">3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref28_pa8" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Johnson, Martha correspondence,
          <unitdate>1840-1866</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_661dd89261ac7a6d8e7f3a9ace42604f">[3 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_84d24133e8b5f1c701b52fcef765e0ef" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_27a92fc08bbfe66551aa17652c6b4c3f"
            parent="aspace_84d24133e8b5f1c701b52fcef765e0ef" type="folder">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref30_wb6" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Johnson, N. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1824</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_0109f7136d44ff4e713e0cea390048b2">[1 item]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_4c28067c9c9ac6e4e31025eac46b69d3" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_41877c78ebe00e8a38d3b543f079b48d"
            parent="aspace_4c28067c9c9ac6e4e31025eac46b69d3" type="folder">5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref32_hv6" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Johnson, Robert C. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1827-1848</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_1cfbb5f1eb6d518d16092e6412058dea">[14 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_bac2a1f23d8eacb4fb8b702238aed305" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_32503b91d43f789f932f287eaef89a0a"
            parent="aspace_bac2a1f23d8eacb4fb8b702238aed305" type="folder">6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref34_seh" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>K-Q correspondence,
          <unitdate>1835, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_d2a4a616b326a190cb6a2223d5d7e6a4">[2 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_0a0d2dd5f1836f920da9e904dd855d52" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_e9e5d4746312ecb3184b4181a3cff181"
            parent="aspace_0a0d2dd5f1836f920da9e904dd855d52" type="folder">7</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref36_0kj" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lee, C. C.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref37_jrb" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Livingson, A. B.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref38_8ns" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Richards, C. R. (Mrs.) correspondence,
          <unitdate>1849</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_4d4f3520a3110baec47287396531cf9d">[1 item]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_107d7ddc303e8ec941c17a3d9611c685" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_8d91df5a9a204bf553def26037f31404"
            parent="aspace_107d7ddc303e8ec941c17a3d9611c685" type="folder">8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref40_dq7" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, Ann correspondence,
          <unitdate>1831-1841</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_a1939eeebf6fdf828978aa9705facfb0">[6 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_1d9e78e5d7d6a2a61272c143d64c8af5" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_76b289d66f3d3659de1070e8912405c5"
            parent="aspace_1d9e78e5d7d6a2a61272c143d64c8af5" type="folder">9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref42_80t" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, Annie correspondence,
          <unitdate>1871-1882</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_67d471516540c7ed3b19ac813e21514d">[4 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_de24dac31c50fb5210d81f879e64ae9d" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_5a7b11baf49e16727b5298120e62c712"
            parent="aspace_de24dac31c50fb5210d81f879e64ae9d" type="folder">10</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref44_9gi" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, Eva A. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1880</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_3c2f58eb1c45b366bb9ec52a9abce90a">[1 item]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_6a21e1236219d8b48ba2ebfa3be28bdd" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2cf459010cfaa7cea2000247249c501a"
            parent="aspace_6a21e1236219d8b48ba2ebfa3be28bdd" type="folder">11</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref46_fk4" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, Mary B. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1852-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_e0bdb3e1040fecf03f896fa91dec3112">[9 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_570f427db7736f7a9d3eb75c357ed591" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_c25d3b7c64a3dcfac5083efe53fbb5de"
            parent="aspace_570f427db7736f7a9d3eb75c357ed591" type="folder">12</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref48_fzk" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, Thomas A. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1846-1861</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_7a8602b3b9cfc5cfbab9dc58525de8ec">[3 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_94c3542b3942a1d8db1a9eaa8ec0cd63" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2d2a04c2b3c254bcf9182f0bce554f6b"
            parent="aspace_94c3542b3942a1d8db1a9eaa8ec0cd63" type="folder">13</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref50_snk" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, William Lithgow correspondence,
          <unitdate>1841-1843</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_20593ee92804db0eb23ef58af8a018e1">[21 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_079cb587c9b0a869de32f4bf733e71b2" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_e93ad6cf87332801fd91b83a0c40edef"
            parent="aspace_079cb587c9b0a869de32f4bf733e71b2" type="folder">14</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref52_2z7" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson, William R. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1841-1843</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_cd0ae46e3e5ecc94ddb95e12de1a8642">[4 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_73a5f39420e57ebb94a1bb6a3f802f4c" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_c41025190f579eafea9097acd344301b"
            parent="aspace_73a5f39420e57ebb94a1bb6a3f802f4c" type="folder">15</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref54_dsa" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>S correspondence, 1838-1852,
          <unitdate>1838-1852</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_58e00457e6f40c86028f204793782e26">[2 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_ed0c949067cecfb9819f21fc3537d1d2" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_0f69f836c6d82219d0f0d6b067d4c831"
            parent="aspace_ed0c949067cecfb9819f21fc3537d1d2" type="folder">16</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref56_ou4" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Staples, A.</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref57_q6l" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Stuart, Arch</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref58_8iw" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Talbot, Mary correspondence,
          <unitdate>1879</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_5f9bdea24d33882a0dbe4ad946bd9af8">[1 item]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_985fa45077acb1c727c6f057d16f4c57" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_9ec58b6560edf3e835b3aab6ce273fd0"
            parent="aspace_985fa45077acb1c727c6f057d16f4c57" type="folder">17</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref60_mur" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, Emma R. "Sissie" correspondence,
          <unitdate>1868-1879, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_3905728a22c6843281a14738d842f6ca">[28 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_76929f8989ef20552274b04b6ca8fe56" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_7603834ec4640e8a67d0d081dbfa9276"
            parent="aspace_76929f8989ef20552274b04b6ca8fe56" type="folder">18</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref62_gw1" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, Ida correspondence,
          <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_3f08190547b9529445a065e559d98dde">[3 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_e61ff625caa7e343c514d8835807b521" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_2a8130dcfa4c749ee2dccadb04509ba8"
            parent="aspace_e61ff625caa7e343c514d8835807b521" type="folder">19</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref64_lom" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, Lily correspondence,
          <unitdate>1868-1871</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_04d114ff6fe49443fe9863314b4e2ea0">[7 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_dd2ea3d8532992a24128d38ea247cc71" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_cc5bb7f97fe81da92f09b00f97d809d3"
            parent="aspace_dd2ea3d8532992a24128d38ea247cc71" type="folder">20</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref66_wbl" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, Martha L. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1862, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_684fd13fe7b1560e8aba10592658af1f">[3 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_124d80258ecc623e64a56d43ae977560" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_d594685daeeecc6b14251d6ae160d968"
            parent="aspace_124d80258ecc623e64a56d43ae977560" type="folder">21</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref68_z3s" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, Robert "Bobby" correspondence,
          <unitdate>1877, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_2592b34aeefd1554a83cbc575432a7f3">[4 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_36a470b4fb661637ca7176a22a83959a" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_502f571eb687609d1a07be12defd8f7f"
            parent="aspace_36a470b4fb661637ca7176a22a83959a" type="folder">22</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref70_svh" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thornton, William C. correspondence,
          <unitdate>1876-1879, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_52e7864d5d8fa318b9bc5079cb013f35">[7 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_1544d1c1ef78e61e2f3ed24c2c02362e" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_1756fea74a403a0a891876fc367d1b1a"
            parent="aspace_1544d1c1ef78e61e2f3ed24c2c02362e" type="folder">23</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref72_aje" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Toncrey, Alverda correspondence,
          <unitdate>1862-1876, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_9604fe4b5a782eeaf5d733cce194c74a">[16 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_d3d4cf7ac248b3ee7dbb9b492e5ee53d" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_84254d33708b0ebcc3f57f93b57aa246"
            parent="aspace_d3d4cf7ac248b3ee7dbb9b492e5ee53d" type="folder">24</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref74_yoy" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>U-Z correspondence,
          <unitdate>1880</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_091c6441fede2b98fb7a88fa89024848">[2 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_4a30af8b849517419a19e7bcee66807e" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_235a1bfa94cb5261939da5cac2835c63"
            parent="aspace_4a30af8b849517419a19e7bcee66807e" type="folder">25</container>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_ref76_qd7" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Young, Sarah</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref77_vcq" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Unidentified or first-name-only correspondence,
          <unitdate>1853-1854, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_7d7e2fe6e16f179acfa0b939e8e4fe11">[4 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_e62d672c658bc3f8ab5a05cae27b67e2" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_c210e5a06fd41ce73f5a567c8e58f7ef"
            parent="aspace_e62d672c658bc3f8ab5a05cae27b67e2" type="folder">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref79_p5o" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Legal documents,
          <unitdate>1823-1871</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_ac4eafb81e4b9fd9e89774a3614e743f">[11 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_fe28f390b425bad71c925a4af5f832a6" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_a58b308e198f02bf84b39695f47b77f6"
            parent="aspace_fe28f390b425bad71c925a4af5f832a6" type="folder">27</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref81_lj4" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records,
          <unitdate>1821-1846</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_71a24590b3becdef3284ba371654015c">[68 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_f22061f34c9d4658caf1938d3300a31a" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_bdad05de269bcfa82b60c0e0486e9b02"
            parent="aspace_f22061f34c9d4658caf1938d3300a31a" type="folder">28</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref83_8bp" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial records,
          <unitdate>1847-1866, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_bd8934bf54b6606309a81c95b445aabf">[63 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_bd3fb82c75688cf390430879f1acd5d7" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_faeb9fccfcce36d37bccaedb076d098c"
            parent="aspace_bd3fb82c75688cf390430879f1acd5d7" type="folder">29</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref85_m0u" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Account books,
          <unitdate>1846-1856</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_2929205c7f52dfb76f542e4e140fade3">[4 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_c6f53749156385f2f02d925f84a2c6d4" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_856eede74bdc653f5c7b943a1ce06e7f"
            parent="aspace_c6f53749156385f2f02d925f84a2c6d4" type="folder">30</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref87_cpr" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Commissioner of revenue account books,
          <unitdate>1850</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_3d1960236067ba720b0c89fffc9683af">[2 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_460725344411a55f8a43ae3e76c90b09" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_77c261792e12b4052181a9a0427cffbc"
            parent="aspace_460725344411a55f8a43ae3e76c90b09" type="folder">31</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref89_ynm" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous,
          <unitdate>1838, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc id="aspace_711cb8ebc7ddd83f29324c8d98decf8e">[10 items]</physdesc>
          <container id="aspace_d5e18b240bba93d6e8aed0145fef385f" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_5dbd2904f21645e4d44172367931c70b"
            parent="aspace_d5e18b240bba93d6e8aed0145fef385f" type="folder">32</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_ref91_pj7" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Canvas document organizer,
          <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_f214cda957474aa05f5673121ec1096f" label="Box-Folder" type="box"
            >1</container>
          <container id="aspace_385c297963ec3954aa1557fd59933f3d"
            parent="aspace_f214cda957474aa05f5673121ec1096f" type="folder">33</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
