<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viblbv00393">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00393:: Edwin R. Coghill Collection, ca. 1864-1970)//EN" "viblbv00393.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Edwin R. Coghill Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1864-1970</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Coghill, Edwin R. Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-058
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by John M. Jackson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">04/09/2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-23">2014-01-23</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Edwin R. Coghill Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1864-1970</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-058
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>John M. Jackson, Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Edwin R. Coghill Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1864-1970
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-058
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 containers; 0.2 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Civil War memoir of Sergeant Edwin R. Coghill of Company E ("Caroline Greys"), 30th Virginia Infantry, together with a post-war company roster, and a 1970 booklet commemorating a memorial service for General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson at Bethel Baptist Church and containing a transcript of Coghill's memoir. 
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Edwin R. Coghill Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Edwin R. Coghill Collection, Ms2009-058 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Edwin R. Coghill Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2006. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
        <p>Images of the original diary may be found <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/civwar/pdfs/CoghillCivilWarDiary.pdf">
here</extref> (in pdf format). The 1970 Bethel Baptist Church booklet included in the collection contains a full transcript of Coghill's memoir. Also in the collection is a photocopy of the original memoir in its entirety. 
</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement and description of the Edwin R. Coghill Collection commenced and was completed in April 2009. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
      <p>Edwin Ruthven "Ned" Coghill, a sergeant in Company E, 30th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War, was born in Caroline County, Virginia on November 1842.  The son of William A. and Sarah L. Coghill, he attended school at Flippo's Store, Virginia and worked as a farmer. Coghill enlisted in the Caroline Greys on May 9, 1861; he was promoted to corporal on April 26, 1862, and to sergeant about three months later. Surrendering with his regiment, Coghill was paroled at Appomattox on April 9, 1865. Following the war, Coghill lived with his wife Elizabeth ("Bettie") and children in  Caroline County, where he worked as a teacher and farmer. He also served as clerk of the Caroline County Circuit Court from 1894 to 1925, and as clerk of Bethel Baptist Church from 1866 to 1924. Edwin R. Coghill died on November 16, 1925.
</p>
      <p>The 30th Virginia was organized in the area of Fredericksburg, Virginia and mustered into Confederate service in July 1861. After reorganization in April 1862, the 30th proceeded to participate in a number of major battles (including the Seven Days Battles, Antietam, Fredericksburg, Cold Harbor, the siege of Petersburg, and Five Forks), and was present at the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia on April 9, 1865. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains three items relating to Sergeant Edwin R. "Ned" Coghill of Company E ("Caroline Greys"), 30th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War. The collection includes Coghill's war memoir and a roster of Company E soldiers, as well as a 1970 booklet commemorating a memorial service for General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson, held at Bethel Baptist Church (Caroline County, Virginia).
</p>
      <p>Identified on its first page as a diary, Coghill's account of events seems instead to be recollected from memory. (Because the account ceases with mid-May 1864, however, it seems likely that Coghill may have been summarizing his experiences to that point.)  Beginning with the march to Manassas Junction, Coghill details the movements of his regiment. He describes battles between artillery emplacements and gunboats on the Potomac River near Evansport and briefly notes the battles at Harpers Ferry and Antietam, recording the deaths of a number of comrades. Coghill mentions attending the funeral service for General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson at Bethel Baptist Church. (Held sometime between May 15 and June 3, 1863, the service was instead more likely one of the first of many memorial services held for Jackson throughout the South.) The memoir also contains a list of the company's members present at the surrender of forces at Appomattox and lists of Company E soldiers who were killed in battle or died of wounds and disease. The memoir concludes with a handwritten copy of Robert E. Lee's farewell address to the Army of Northern Virginia. The accompanying roster of the Caroline Greys, compiled after the war, lists names, ranks, and notes on deaths, wounds, imprisonments, promotions, and transfers. </p>
      <p>Also contained in the collection is a 1970 booklet commemorating the 1863 funeral of General Thomas J. Jackson at Bethel Baptist Church. The booklet contains information on Jackson's death, photos of Edwin R. Coghill and some of his descendants, and a complete transcript of Coghill's memoir. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by document type.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="local">Civil War</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Diaries</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Memoir
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1864
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bethel Church memorial service booklet
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Caroline Greys post-war roster
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Oversize" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
