<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00656">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00656::Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University
            Libraries, 2007-2010)//EN" "viblbv00656.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University
                    Libraries, <date>2007-2010</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University
                    Libraries <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2008-020</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By Virginia
                    Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                    <date>2010-11-19T13:53-0500</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries,
                    <date>2007-2010</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                    Ms2008-020</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2010 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by:</label>
                    <item> Special Collections Staff</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>

    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of
                the University Libraries, <unitdate normal="2007/2010" type="inclusive" label="Date"
                    encodinganalog="245$f">2007-2010</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms.2008.020</unitid>
            <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Description">
                <extent>500.0 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>517 boxes, 17 map case drawers, and standing racks</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" id="ref17" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language> Additional materials are in other
                languages, including Korean.</langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref16" label="Abstract">The Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the
                University Libraries consists mainly of condolence items received by the university
                in the wake of April 16, 2007 in which 32 faculty and students were killed. The
                subseries organization is by type of item. The bulk of materials were received in
                the first few months following April 16, 2007. There also is a very small series
                with items specifically sent to or relating to those killed, which is organized
                alphabetically by name.</abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict id="ref18" encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="ref19" encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Special Collections does not own copyright to all materials in the Virginia Tech
                    April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries. If the department has the
                    copyright, permission to publish materials must be obtained from Special
                    Collections, Virginia Tech. Permission to publish materials not owned by the
                    department must come from the copyright holder. Please contact Special
                    Collections ( <extref href="mailto:specref@vt.edu">specref@vt.edu</extref>) with
                    copyright questions and concerns.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite id="ref23" encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries,
                    Ms2008-020, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo id="ref20" encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>The Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries contains a
                    selection of artifacts sent to the university between April 16, 2007 and June
                    2010. The material arrived in many thousands of separate accruals. The bulk of
                    the collection was received in the first few months after April 16, 2007.</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <altformavail id="ref22" encodinganalog="530$a">
                <head>Alternate Form Available</head>
                <p>Digital images of selected items in this collection are available through the
                    online Virginia Tech April 16, 2007, Condolence Archives of the University
                    Libraries <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new" title="here"
                        href="http://contentdm.lib.vt.edu/cdm4/index_416.php?CISOROOT=/416"
                        >here</extref>. Some items in the Condolence Archives do not have a physical
                    representation.</p>
            </altformavail>
            <processinfo id="ref21" encodinganalog="583$a">
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Virginia Tech April 16, 2007
                    Archives of the University Libraries commenced in July 2007 and was completed in
                    summer 2010. Processing began at Virginia Tech's Corporate Research Center
                    (CRC). In September of 2008, the collection moved to Newman Library, Special
                    Collections.</p>
                <p>Initial processing involved entering metadata about materials in lots. A lot
                    might contain one item, for example, a quilt, or 32,000 items, such as a gift of
                    origami cranes. After being photographed, selected items were arranged,
                    described and housed in archival containers. Thus, there is a digital collection
                    and a physical collection; both contain selected items, some of which are
                    represented in only one of these collections. Close to 7,000 lots of items were
                    accessioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph render="bold">Note:</emph> The names of the victims are given in their
                    complete form in the finding aid even though they may be represented on the
                    actual items in a much more informal way. Recognizing names was sometimes
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>Since there were two Daniels--Daniel Perez Cueva and Daniel Patrick O'Neil--and
                    two Matthews--Matthew Gregory Gwaltney and Matthew Joseph La Porte--it sometimes
                    was not clear which person was intended; therefore abbreviated names were
                    included as they were written. An effort was made to record any instances in
                    which a specific name appeared on an item. An effort was also made to record
                    social commentary as it appeared on items.</p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref24" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Historical Information</head>
            <p>On the morning of April 16, 2007, Seung-Hui Cho shot and killed two students in West
                Ambler Johnston Residence Hall. About two hours later, Cho proceeded to Norris Hall,
                a building on the other side of the campus. When in Norris Hall he shot and killed
                five professors and 25 students, and injured over two dozen others, before turning
                the gun on himself.</p>
            <p>The night of April 16, 2007, Hokies United, a student-organized response group, set
                up a memorial shrine with a semicircle of stones on the Drillfield in front of
                Burruss Hall, the university's administration building. The next day students placed
                large plywood boards, painted white, on the Drillfield for people to sign and leave
                expressions of grief, support, etc. Other spontaneous shrines appeared on campus and
                in the community.</p>
            <p>The events of April 16, 2007, received intense media coverage, and people around the
                world responded. Virginia Tech received over 90,000 condolence items from all 50
                states and 80 countries. These items included banners, posters, books of
                condolences, sound materials, various media materials, poetry, correspondence,
                resolutions, textiles, memorabilia, ephemera, and handcrafted items. Thousands of
                these items were displayed for the university community through University Unions
                and Student Activities' Squires Student Union.</p>
            <p>Items continued to be received for months and years afterwards, and families of those
                killed were offered the option of receiving many materials directly related to their
                loved ones from the Office of Recovery and Support, or having them placed in storage
                for later retrieval.</p>
            <p>We continue to remember the 32 victims:</p>
            <p>Ross A. Alameddine</p>
            <p>Christopher James Bishop</p>
            <p>Brian R. Bluhm</p>
            <p>Ryan Christopher Clark</p>
            <p>Austin Michelle Cloyd</p>
            <p>Jocelyne Couture-Nowak</p>
            <p>Daniel Alejandro Perez Cueva</p>
            <p>Kevin P. Granata</p>
            <p>Matthew Gregory Gwaltney</p>
            <p>Caitlin Millar Hammaren</p>
            <p>Jeremy Michael Herbstritt</p>
            <p>Rachael Elizabeth Hill</p>
            <p>Emily Jane Hilscher</p>
            <p>Jarrett Lee Lane</p>
            <p>Matthew Joseph La Porte</p>
            <p>Henry J. Lee Liviu</p>
            <p>Librescu G.V. Loganathan</p>
            <p>Partahi Mamora Halomoan Lumbantoruan</p>
            <p>Lauren Ashley McCain Daniel</p>
            <p>Patrick O'Neil</p>
            <p>Juan Ramon Ortiz-Ortiz</p>
            <p>Minal Hiralal Panchal</p>
            <p>Erin Nicole Peterson</p>
            <p>Michael Steven Pohle, Jr.</p>
            <p>Julia Kathleen Pryde</p>
            <p>Mary Karen Read</p>
            <p>Reema Joseph Samaha</p>
            <p>Waleed Mohamed Shaalan</p>
            <p>Leslie Geraldine Sherman</p>
            <p>Maxine Shelly Turner</p>
            <p>Nicole Regina White</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref25" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>The Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries consists mainly
                of condolence items received by the university following the events of April 16,
                2007. The bulk of materials were received in the first few months following April
                16, 2007.</p>
            <p>The collection is arranged using standard archival procedures. Due to the unique
                nature of this collection (i.e., the way it was received, the variety of formats,
                and the content), archivists developed specialized arrangement and description
                procedures. Since the collection and its contents are unique, the arrangement and
                description of individual series and subseries may differ.</p>
            <p>The collection contains two series, Series I: Condolence Series and Series II:
                Individual Collections. Series I: Condolence Material includes twelve subseries,
                described in the "Arrangement" note below. Series II: Individual Collections has no
                subseries.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref26" encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged in the following series:</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Series I. Condolence Materials, 2007-2010</emph>. This series
                was arranged in 12 subseries. The items were arranged according to the person or
                organization who donated the materials. Within these groupings, the items were
                further categorized alphabetically.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 1. Banners, pp. 1-62.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains banners received by Virginia Tech following the events of
                April 16, 2007. Banners were defined as items that could be rolled or folded. Some
                banners were made of cloth or vinyl. Many of the banners were signed and/or included
                messages. In some cases, the finding aid includes notes about the content of these
                messages. An effort was made to note any instances in which the names of any of the
                32 victims appeared on the banners.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 2. Posters, pp. 63-92.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains posters received by Virginia Tech following the events that
                occurred on campus on April 16, 2007. Many of the posters were signed and/or
                included messages. In some cases, the finding aid includes notes about the content
                of these messages. An effort was made to note any instances in which the names of
                any of the 32 victims appeared on the posters.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 3. Books of Condolences, pp. 93-113.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains books of condolences received by Virginia Tech following the
                events of April 16, 2007. Although gathered under the broad term of books of
                condolences, the items in this series appear in a wide array of formats and sizes.
                While a number of the materials take the form of traditional books of condolences,
                most are of a more informal, impromptu nature. Many of the items in this subseries
                contain messages from people who gathered at memorial ceremonies throughout the
                United States and the world.</p>
            <p>Other books had simply been put in public places to receive the names and messages of
                passersby before being sent to Virginia Tech. In addition to names and messages,
                many of the items in this series include photographs, original artwork, and
                poetry.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 4. Sound Materials: Audio CD, Sound Cassettes, Sheet
                    Music, and Song Lyrics, pp. 114-125.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains various sound materials such as audio CDs, audio cassettes,
                sheet music, and song lyrics received by Virginia Tech following the events of April
                16, 2007. There is also some overlap between this subseries and Subseries 5.</p>
            <p>This subseries was arranged alphabetically by donor name. The donor may or may not be
                the creator of the item.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 5. Videos, DVDs, CDs, and Slideshows, pp.
                    126-133.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains materials that have visual content, including videos, DVDs,
                CDs, and slideshows that were received by Virginia Tech following the events of
                April 16, 2007. There is also some overlap between this subseries and Subseries
                4.</p>
            <p>This subseries was arranged alphabetically by donor name. The donor may or may not be
                the creator of the item.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 6. Correspondence, pp. 134-292.</emph></p>
            <p>Following the events of April 16, 2007, Virginia Tech received cards and letters of
                condolence from organizations and individuals across the United States and
                internationally. A majority of the correspondence appears in standard greeting card
                format, in letters, and in oversize cards. Some contain messages from several
                individuals. Many of these cards were handmade, and some senders enclosed newspaper
                clippings or religious literature. Many cards and letters feature artwork,
                especially items sent from children. Other significant materials include official
                letters from international embassies and governments.</p>
            <p>In general, all of the cards and letters were organized according to the sender;
                domestic and international correspondence remains separated. The items were arranged
                according to the nature of the creator from which they were received. Within these
                groupings, the items were further categorized alphabetically. Specifically, the
                Department of Foreign Languages and Literatures of Virginia Tech received many
                condolence artifacts, including correspondence and floral arrangements; these items
                were arranged separately. While a substantial portion of condolences were sent
                directly to Virginia Tech or one of its departments, some correspondence was sent to
                the Blacksburg and Virginia Tech police departments. Many of these cards came from
                fellow police departments, EMTs, fire departments, and other public service
                agencies; these items were arranged separately.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 7. Photographs and Digital Images, pp.
                293-328.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries contains photographs and digital images sent to Virginia Tech
                following the events of April 16, 2007. Groups and individuals are pictured, for
                example, wearing Virginia Tech colors, holding a memorial service, or raising money
                for the Hokie Spirit Fund. Other subseries may include photographs.</p>
            <p>This subseries was arranged alphabetically by donor name. The donor may or may not be
                the creator of the item.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 8. Textiles, Memorabilia, Artwork, and Handcrafted
                    Items, pp. 329-381.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries includes a wide variety of items sent to Virginia Tech following the
                events of April 16, 2007. The subseries includes items such as quilts, drawings,
                paintings, a car hood, sports memorabilia, U.S. flags flown at various places in
                honor of the victims, t-shirts, and a life preserver.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 9. Poetry, pp. 382-412.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries consists of poems composed or sent by individuals from across the
                United States. Some organizations sending poetry include schools, churches,
                colleges, and universities. Anonymous poems are also included.</p>
            <p>This subseries was arranged into two groups: poetry sent by organizations or groups
                and poetry sent by individuals. Each group was alphabetized by the name of the
                organization or individual.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 10. Resolutions, Proclamations, Declarations, Bills,
                    and Other Legislation, pp. 413-422.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries consists of official resolutions and proclamations passed by the
                governing bodies for colleges and universities, organizations, and state and local
                governments. Additional correspondence accompanies some of the resolutions.</p>
            <p>Resolutions were arranged in alphabetical order by organization name, with oversized
                items in separate boxes.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 11. Books, pp. 423-425.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries consists of books and booklets received by Virginia Tech following the
                events of April 16, 2007. Subjects of the books include handling grief and grieving
                or are offered as possible sources of consolation.</p>
            <p>Books were arranged alphabetically by donor name. The donor may or may not be the
                creator of the item.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Subseries 12. Sample Collection of Materials Received by
                    Individual Families of Victims, pp. 426-431.</emph></p>
            <p>This subseries includes materials sent to the family of an individual victim. The
                material in the subseries, although anonymous, represents the cross section of gifts
                and items given to the families and the University community. The subseries contains
                music and DVD recordings of songs written for or performed on behalf of the victims,
                as well as recordings of memorial events on campus. There are cards, poetry, and
                books of condolences from schools, universities, religious organizations, and
                individuals. Memorabilia includes a flag flown at the United States Capitol, a
                knitted prayer shawl, original artwork from an alumna, and a candle burned at a New
                York University vigil. The subseries also contains publications and programs from
                memorial events on the Virginia Tech campus.</p>
            <p>The subseries was arranged alphabetically by donor name. The donor may or may not be
                the creator of the material.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Series II. Individual Series, pp. 432-433.</emph></p>
            <p>This very small series contains items either sent to or specifically relating to the
                individuals who were killed on April 16, 2007.</p>
            <p>The series was arranged alphabetically. A separate box for Seung-Hui Cho is placed at
                the end.</p>
            <p>Please note: The Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries
                    <emph render="bold">DOES NOT</emph> contain any official documents. Official
                documents available to the public may be viewed at dedicated computers in Newman
                Library, Virginia Tech, and at the Library of Virginia in Richmond.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <descgrp type="add">
            <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
            <relatedmaterial id="ref27" encodinganalog="544$a">
                <head>Related Materials</head>
                <p>Virginia Tech April 16, 2007, Condolence Archives of the University Libraries is
                    available online <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new" title="here"
                        href="http://contentdm.lib.vt.edu/cdm4/index_416.php?CISOROOT=/416"
                        >here</extref>.</p>
                <p>The Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries DOES NOT
                    contain any official documents. Official documents available to the public may
                    be viewed at dedicated computers in Newman Library, Virginia Tech, and at the
                    Library of Virginia in Richmond.</p>
                <p>Other Virginia Tech resources, as well as several state and federal government
                    resources, are available through the Digital Library and Archives' "Additional
                    April 16, 2007 Resources" webpage <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                        title="here"
                        href="http://contentdm.lib.vt.edu/416mem/resources.php?CISOROOT=/p15234coll2"
                        >here</extref>.</p>
            </relatedmaterial>
        </descgrp>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
                    State University</subject>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Local Subjects:</head>
                <subject source="local">Local/Regional History</subject>
                <subject source="local">University Archives</subject>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref28" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series I: Condolence Materials, <unitdate normal="2007/2010"
                            type="inclusive">2007-2010.</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent id="ref29">
                    <head>Scope and Content</head>
                    <p>The contents list of each series or subseries is available as an individual
                        pdf file. Click on the link below for the subseries to view, search, and/or
                        save the pdf.</p>
                    <p>The entire contents list of both series, including all subseries, is
                        available as a single, 436-page pdf <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                            title="here"
                            href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/4_16_Archives.pdf"
                            >here</extref>.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 id="ref30" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 1: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Banners"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/banners.pdf"
                                >Banners</extref>, pp. 1-62.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref31" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 2: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Posters"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/posters.pdf"
                                >Posters</extref>, pp. 63-92.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref32" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 3: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Books of Condolences"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/condolencebooks.pdf"
                                >Books of Condolences</extref>, pp. 93-113.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref33" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 4: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Sound Materials: Audio CDs, Sound Cassettes, Sheet Music, and Song Lyrics"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/audio.pdf">Sound
                                Materials: Audio CDs, Sound Cassettes, Sheet Music, and Song
                                Lyrics</extref>, pp. 114-125.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref34" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 5: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Videos, DVDs, CDs, Slideshows"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/video.pdf">Videos,
                                DVDs, CDs, Slideshows</extref>, pp. 126-133.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref35" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 6: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Correspondence"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/correspondence.pdf"
                                >Correspondence</extref>, pp. 134-293.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref36" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 7: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Photographs and Digital Images"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/photographs.pdf"
                                >Photographs and Digital Images</extref>, pp. 294-329.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref37" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 8: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Textiles, Memorabilia, Artworks, and Handcrafted Items"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/textiles.pdf"
                                >Textiles, Memorabilia, Artworks, and Handcrafted Items</extref>,
                            pp. 330-384.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref38" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 9: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Poetry"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/poetry.pdf"
                                >Poetry</extref>, pp. 385-415.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref39" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 10: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Resolutions, Proclamations, Declarations, Bills, and Other Legislation"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/resolutions.pdf"
                                >Resolutions, Proclamations, Declarations, Bills, and Other
                                Legislation</extref>, pp. 416-425.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref40" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 11: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Books"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/books.pdf"
                                >Books</extref>, pp. 426-428.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 id="ref41" level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries 12: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                                title="Sample Collection of Materials Received by Individual Families of Victims"
                                href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/samplecollection.pdf"
                                >Sample Collection of Materials Received by Individual Families of
                                Victims</extref>, pp. 428-434.</unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref42" level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series II: <extref actuate="onrequest" show="new"
                            title="Individual Collections"
                            href="http://spec.lib.vt.edu/mss/4_16_Archives/individuals.pdf"
                            >Individual Collections</extref>, pp. 435-436. <unitdate
                            normal="2007/2010" type="inclusive">2007-2010.</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
