<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl"?>
<ead id="viblbv00497">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00497::William Avery Stratton Correspondence, 1864-1940 (Bulk
            1864-1880))//EN" "viblbv00497.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the William Avery Stratton Correspondence, <date>1864-1940
                        (Bulk 1864-1880)</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Stratton, William Avery, Correspondence <num
                        type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-114</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By
                    Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>Machine-readable finding aid written in oXygen by Kira A. Dietz,
                    <date>09/25/2009</date></creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the William Avery Stratton Correspondence, <date>1864-1940 (Bulk
                    1864-1880)</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number"
                    >Ms2009-114</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2009 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: Kira A. Dietz, </label>
                    <item>Processing and Acquisitions Archivist, Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William Avery Stratton Correspondence,
                    <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1864-1940 (Bulk
                    1864-1880)</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-114 </unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 boxes; 0.8 cu.
                ft.</physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains correspondence to William Avery
                Stratton from friends and family. Letters date from as early as the Civil War (1864)
                to the year after Stratton's death (1940). For the most part, letters are about
                social and family news, though some of the early letters contain Civil War and
                post-bellum news from the South. Letters from friends in Oregon, Colorado, and
                Nevada also provide details on Indian affairs, railroad growth, and cattle in the
                West. The collection also contains a large number of wedding and graduation
                invitations for events in Oxford, New York, where Stratton spent much of his
                life.</abstract>
            <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Dealer </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions</head>
                <p>Collection is open to research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions</head>
                <p>Permission to publish from the William Avery Stratton Correspondence must be
                    obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation</head>
                <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following
                    information: William Avery Stratton Correspondence, Ms2009-114, Special
                    Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg,
                    Va.</p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information</head>
                <p>The William Avery Stratton Correspondence was purchased by Special Collections
                    before 2000.</p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo>
                <head>Processing Information</head>
                <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the William Avery Stratton
                    Correspondence commenced in August 2009 and was completed in September 2009.</p>
            </processinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Information</head>
            <p>George Stratton (1823-1910) married Mariette Robinson (abt. 1824-1865) in January
                1845. They had six children, all born in Oxford, New York: William Avery
                (1845-1939), Edward L. (b. December 1847), Harvey J. (b. January 1850), Luke A.
                (1853-1862), Tracy Frink (b. June 1858), and Alice Robinson (b. February 1864). Some
                time between 1866 and 1870, George married his first wife's cousin, Maria A.
                Robinson. George and his four sons who survived to adulthood were all involved in
                dairy farming and lumber work at one time or another. Stratton seems to have worked
                in both business, probably in an office capacity, after mid-1881.</p>
            <p>Although some details of Stratton's life are unknown, a great deal can be found in
                the letters. He spent much of his life in parts of Chenango County, New York. He
                never married. He went to the Oxford Academy, which continues to serve (in an
                expanded form), as the central school district for Oxford. Around 1866, he attended
                business college in Poughkeepsie, New York. </p>
            <p>In 1870 and early 1871, Stratton seems to have been looking for work. After a brief
                trip to visit family and friends in Mississippi and Georgia in the spring of 1871,
                he settled in Washington, DC, having taken a clerk position with the Office of
                Internal Revenue, Treasury Department. In 1877, he left the Treasury Department and
                traveled in California and Oregon. Letters from his trip, as well as after, suggest
                he may be been looking to find work there. He was back in Oxford the next year,
                however. By the spring of 1879, Stratton was working for Lord and Taylor in New York
                City. In 1881, he moved to Othello, Mississippi. Some time after May 1881, he
                returned again to Chenango County. It is unclear if he remained with the family
                business(es) or found other work. He died in 1939. His sister, Alice, was his only
                sibling still alive at that time. </p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>A significant portion of the family correspondence shares news from places around the
                country. There is also an emphasis on family business (the selling of butter from
                the farm, land, and stock dividends, for example) and local politics. Stratton's
                extended family lived throughout central and eastern New York, as well as in other
                parts of the country, and appear often throughout the correspondence both as writers
                and topics. In addition to <famname normal="Stratton family">Stratton</famname>s,
                other connected families include the <famname normal="Chase family"
                >Chase</famname>s, the <famname normal="Robinson family">Robinson</famname>s, the
                    <famname normal="Ten Brock family">Ten Brock</famname>s (<famname
                    normal="Ten Brock family">Ten Broeck</famname>s) and the <famname
                    normal="Juliand family">Juliand</famname>s. A list of major correspondents by
                decade is provided at the start of the &quot;Content List&quot; below.</p>
            <p>
                <emph render="bold">Note:</emph> There is very little correspondence for the period
                of June 1882 through November 1890, and none for the period of 1920 to 1934. </p>
            <p>In addition to letters, the collection also contains a series of wedding and
                graduation invitations. During the second half of his life, while living
                predominantly in Oxford, New York, Stratton appears to have been a popular invitee.
                Many of the graduation invitations are for his old school, the Oxford Academy. Other
                materials include miscellaneous photographs and business papers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>The collection is arranged in three series&ndash;Series I: Correspondence,
                1864-1940, Series II: Invitations, 1874-1935, and Series III: Ephemera. </p>
            <p>Series I: Correspondence, 1864-1940, contains more than 75 years of personal and
                business letters written to, and in a few cases, by, Stratton. A majority of the
                letters are from immediate and extended family. The remainder are from friends and
                business associates. In addition to his own jobs over the years, Stratton appears to
                have facilitated business transactions for his family's dairy.</p>
            <p>Hattie Chase (Stratton's cousin), wrote Stratton a number of letters from Georgia
                concerning treatment and perceptions of African-Americans in the south after the
                Civil War. Her letters continue into the early 1870s. After 1871, Stratton's
                brother, Edward, also writes about African-Americans, when he moved to Bolton,
                Mississippi, for a job with Robinson &amp; Withers, later Robinson &amp;
                Williams, then C. L. Robinson &amp; Co. Charles L. Robinson was probably a
                relation through William and Edward's mother and step-mother.</p>
            <p>Starting in 1878, Stratton received letters from a cousin, Eli Ten Brock, and a
                number of other friends living out west. These letters contain discussion of
                troubles with Indians, the growth of the railroad, and cattle driving in Oregon,
                Colorado, Nevada, and Texas. These were not the only colorful characters with whom
                he corresponded. After an unknown attack of some kind while living in Mississippi, a
                friend advised him that &quot;if I had been in your place I would have shot a
                hole in him big enough to see what he had for last meal.&quot; His friend then
                recommends he buy a pistol and &quot;shoot the H--l out of the first man that
                attempts to molest [him].&quot; Later letters from his sister and
                brother-in-law, Alice and Ira MacFarland, relate stories of gold mining and ranching
                in Nevada.</p>
            <p>This series is arranged chronologically.</p>
            <p>Series II: Invitations, 1874-1935, includes invitations to events in and around
                Oxford, New York, and other locations. It contains two subseries: Subseries I:
                Weddings and Anniversaries, 1874-1935, and Subseries II: Graduations and Reunions,
                1890-1900. Subseries I includes weddings and anniversary party invitations and
                announcements. Many of these have place cards attached. Subseries II contains
                invitations to graduation and reunion events at the Oxford Academy, some of which
                have attached calling cards.</p>
            <p>This series is arranged chronologically within each subseries. </p>
            <p>Series III: Ephemera, contains a small group of unidentifed photographs and a
                selection of business papers. This series is arranged by material type.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Persons:</head>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Brown, Alice">Brown,
                    Alice.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Chase, Hattie">Chase,
                    Hattie.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Currier, Lottie Lewis"
                    >Currier, Lottie Lewis.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Juliand, Sarah Stratton"
                    >Juliand, Sarah Stratton.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs"
                    normal="MacFarland, Alice Robinson Stratton">MacFarland, Alice Stratton
                    (b.1864).</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="MacFarland, Ira">MacFarland,
                    Ira.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Robinson, Charles L."
                    >Robinson, Charles L.</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Stratton, Edward L."
                    >Stratton, Edward L. (b.1847).</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Stratton, George">Stratton,
                    George (1823-1910).</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Stratton, Harvey J."
                    >Stratton, Harvey J. (b.1850).</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Stratton, Tracy Frink"
                    >Stratton, Tracy Frink (b.1858).</persname>
                <persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs" normal="Stratton, William Avery"
                    >Stratton, William Avery (b.1845).</persname>
            </controlaccess>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Family Names:</head>
                <famname encodinganalog="600$a" source="dacs">Stratton family.</famname>
            </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series I: Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                            >1864-1940.<lb/></unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <head>Scope Note</head>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1864-1869: Alice Brown, Hattie Chase, M.H. Hall,
                        Wallace Mott, Anna (Annie), Julia, and Ida Nichols, George Stratton, Sarah
                        Stratton (later Juliand), and Minnie Tremain. </p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1870-1879: Hattie Chase, Lottie Lewis (later Currier),
                        Edward L. Stratton, Harvey J. Stratton, George Stratton, and Maria A.
                        Stratton. </p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1880-1889: Edward L. Stratton, and Tracy F. Stratton. </p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1890-1899: George Juliand, II, Ira MacFarland, and
                        Jennie Randall.</p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1900-1909: None.</p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1910-1919: Edward L. Stratton.</p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1920-1934: No correspondence from this period.</p>
                    <p>Major Correspondents, 1935-1940: Alice Stratton MacFarland.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1864</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1865.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, January-February, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                                >1866.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, March-December, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                                >1866.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1867.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, January-July, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                                >1868.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, August-December, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                                >1868.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1869.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="file">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1870.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1871.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1872.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1873.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1874.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1875.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1876.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1877.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1878.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1879.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1880.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1881-1889.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:20</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1890-1893.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1894-1899.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1900-1909.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1910-1919.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1935-1940.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02>
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series II: Invitations, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                            >1874-1935.</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries I: Weddings and Anniversaries, <unitdate
                                type="inclusive">1874-1935.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7-9</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Subseries II: Graduations and Reunions, <unitdate
                                type="inclusive">1890-1900.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10</container>
                    </did>
                </c02>
            </c01>
            <c01 level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Series III: Ephemera and Photographs, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                            >undated.</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11-12</container>
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
