<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00162">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00162::Directory of Administrators and New Faculty, 1988
            Collection)//EN" "viblbv00162" </eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Directory of Administrators and New Faculty, 1988
                    Collection <date>1988 </date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Directory of Administrators and New Faculty, 1988 Collection,
                        <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2005-004 </num>
                </subtitle>
                <author>Special Collections </author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University </publisher> &address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2005
                    By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved. </date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
                <p id="filesize">[ca. 50 Kilobytes] </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word processing program, created by
                Kimberli Weeks, <date> 2005</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
                Directory of Administrators and New Faculty, 1988 Collection, <date> 1988</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<num
                    type="Collection Number">Ms2005-004 </num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University </publisher>
            <date type="publication">2005 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: </label>
                    <item>Special Collections Staff </item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
            State University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic
                Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title">University Directory of Administrators and New Faculty, 1988
                Collection, <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1988 </unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <unitid label="Collection number">Ms2005-004 </unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 container; 0.4 cu. ft. </physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract label="Abstract">Collection consists of one-page vitas and photographs of
                administrators and new faculty in 1988 at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University. </abstract>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information </head>
            <accessrestrict>
                <head>Access Restrictions </head>
                <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict>
                <head>Use Restrictions </head>
                <p>Permission to publish material from the Directory of Administrators and New
                    Faculty 1998 Collection must be obtained from Special Collections,
                    Virginia Tech. </p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite>
                <head>Preferred Citation </head>
                <p>Directory of Administrators and New Faculty 1998 Collection, Ms2005-004 Digital
                    Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University,
                    Blacksburg, Va. </p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo>
                <head>Acquisition Information </head>
                <p>The Directory of Administrators and New Faculty 1998 Collection was donated to
                    Special Collections in 2004. </p>
            </acqinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist>
            <head>Biographical/Historical Information </head>
            <p>The collection was originally housed in and apparently used by the Office of the
                President. James D. McComas was president of Virginia Tech from 1988-1993. </p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <head>Scope and Content </head>
            <p>The collection was originally housed in and apparently used by the Office of the
                President. James D. McComas was president of Virginia Tech from 1988-1993. </p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <head>Arrangement </head>
            <p>The collection is arranged by college or administrative office. Within the folder for
                an administrative office or college, names are listed alphabetically. </p>
        </arrangement>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List </head>
            <c01 level="series">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Directory of
                        Administrators and New Faculty, 1988 Collection <unitdate type="inclusive"
                            >1988 </unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Agriculture and Life Sciences: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-1 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p> Robert Adams, William A. Allen, Ruth Alscher, Michael R. Bell, Duane F.
                            Berry, Judith Bond, Edward A. Borchers, Robert Q. Cannell, Gerald H.
                            Cross, Brady J. Deaton, Richard R. Frahm, Thomas A. Fretz, Kevin
                            Grueber, David Ames Herbert, Glen L. Heuberger, Robert L. Horsburgh,
                            John Hosner, Gefa Ifju, James E. Johnson, Eluned Jones-Russell, David S.
                            Kronfeld, Gregory S. Lewis, George S. Libey, Jesse Logan, John Allen
                            Marcy, P. Howard Massey, Jr., Ann Mary McGuirk, Laurence D. Moore, James
                            R. Nichols, Thomas L. Payne, John Perumpral, Merle D. Pierson, Judy
                            Stallmann, Herbert H. Stovener, Nicholas D. Stone, Bradley J. Sullivan,
                            Charles Swann, Andy Swiger, James L. Tramel, Jr., Richard B. Vasey,
                            William E. Vinson, John M. White, Tracy Wilkins, Carol Wilkinson, Daniel
                            R. Williams, John H. Wolford, Roger R. Youngman </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Architecture and Urban Studies: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-2 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>James Bohland, John Browder, William Brown, Vincent Cilimberg, W. David
                            Conn, Ronald Daniel, Robert Dunay, Dayton Egger, Olivio Ferrari, Timothy
                            Fluck, Dixon Hanna, Jaan Holt, Dennis Kilper, Frederick Krimgold,
                            Patrick Miller, Hulan Rutland, Robert Schubert, Charles Steger </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Arts and Sciences: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-3 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Herman Doswald, Joseph Aistrup, Donald Allison, Sergio Antoy, Lewis
                            Barnett, Robert Bates, Alan Bayer, Andrew Becker, F. Donald Bloss, Lyle
                            Broemeling, Jeffrey Brown, Richard Burian, Hilbert Campbell, Neal
                            Castagnoli, George Crofts, Robert Denton, Jr., Paul Distler, Donald
                            Drapeau, J. Christopher Eustis, Christopher Faraone, Mordechai Finegold,
                            Steve Fuller, Thomas Gilmer, Jr., Susan Green, Jon Hale, Albert
                            Hamilton, Sally Harris, Peter Haskell, Klaus Hinkelmann, Paul Hubbard,
                            John Husser, David Johnson, James Karr, Burton Kaufman, Charles Kennedy,
                            Hans-Dieter Klingemann, Robert Landen, Wayne Montgomery Lee, Robert
                            Morrill, Derek Myers, Michael Ogliaruso, Robert Paterson, C. Wayne
                            Patty, Peter Pruim, Lynette Rummel, David Russell, Ruth Salvaggio,
                            Charles Saplak, Duane Schattle, Robert Schiek, Thomas Sevison, Joseph
                            Sgro, George Simmons, Gary Smallwood, Jean Speer, Charles Taylor,
                            William Tehan, III, Bailey Van Hook, James Wolfe </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>R. B. Pamplin College of Business: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-4 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Richard Alvarez, Dirk Baldwin, T. W. Bonham, Catherine Eckel, Richard
                            Harshberger, Elwood Holton III, Ronald Johnson, N. Leroy Kauffman,
                            Arthur Keown, Wayne Leininger, Robert Leitch, Robert Litschert, James
                            Littlefield, Daniel Orr, Gerald Shapio, Richard Sorensen, Norrine
                            Spencer, Bernard Taylor III, Nancy Templeman </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Education: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-5 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>S. Kern Alexander, Ronald Bos, Darrel Clowes, on Creamer, Nevin Frantz,
                            Libby Hoffman, Thomas Hunt, Elizabeth Koball, Mary Ann Lewis, Susan
                            Magliaro, Leroy Miles, Steve Parson, Dianne W. Robertshaw, Robert Smith,
                            Jay H. Williams </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Engineering: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-6 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Robert Beaton, Edith Berkowitz, Benjamin Blanchard, Joseph Blum, G. W.
                            Clough, Robert Comparin, William Conger, Steven Crider, John Daigle,
                            Richey Davis, Jesus De La Graza, Andrea Dietrich, Panayiotis Diplas,
                            Robert Dryden, W. Samuel Easterling, David Elrod, Daniel Frederick,
                            Daniel Gallagher, Timothy Greene, Robert Hendricks, Daniel Hodge, Owen
                            Hughes, Mario Karfakis, Michael Karmis, Pamela Kurstedt, Robert Leonard,
                            Daniel Ludwig, Virginia McWhorter, Thomas Murray, Charles Nunnally, Lynn
                            Nystrom, John Osborne, Leo Padis, John Perumpral, Joseph Schetz, Joseph
                            Sherrard, Charles Spencer, F. W. Stephenson, James Sword, Clarence
                            Teske, Paul Torgersen, Thomas Walker </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>College of Human Resources: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-7 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Nancy Barclay, Mark Benson, Deloris Ellis, Gina Eubanks, Yvette
                            Harps-Logan, Mary Helen Marshall, Joseph Maxwell, Roberta Minish,
                            Carolyn Moore, Michael Olsen, Kathleen Parrott, Rita Purdy, S. J.
                            Ritchey, Eleanor D. Schlenker, Vera Wall </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-8 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Donald Barber, Jim Bowen, Thomas Brown, Donald Cordes, Peter Eyre, Helen
                            C. Foley, Frederick Fregin, William Huber, Bradley Klein, Blair Meldrum,
                            Hara Misra, Sashi Mohanty, R. Lee Pyle, Theresa Rowles, Mark Smith,
                            Gregory Troy, Don Waldron </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Business
                            Officer: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-9 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>David Braine, David Ford, David Goodyear, Katherine Johnston, Robert
                            Madigan, Minnis Ridenour, Raymond Smoot, Ann Spencer </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Executive Vice President and Provost: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-10 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>David Bousquet, Eugene Carson, Bruce Chaloux, Wanda Dean, Dennis Hinckle,
                            Gary Hooper, Patricia Hyer, Martha Johnson, Bernard Jones, Bernard La
                            Berge, Ronald Nurse, John M. Perry, Arnold Schuetz, Richard Stillwagon,
                            Ernest Stout, Roger Teekell, Joyce Williams-Green </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Vice President for Business Affairs: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-11 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Jane Armbruster-Hu, Shauna Barnaby, Deanna Colaianne, Charles Forbes,
                            Larry Hincker, Franklin Perry, Archie Phlegar, Gary Ragnow, Jane
                            Robertson, Richard Stoltz, William Walker, Jr., Dorothy </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Vice President for Business Affairs: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-12 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Raymond Smoot </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Vice President for Development and University
                            Relations: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-13 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Jane Armbruster-Hu, Shauna Barnaby, Deanna Colaianne, Charles Forbes,
                            Larry Hincker, Franklin Perry, Archie Phlegar, Gary Ragnow, Jane
                            Robertson, Richard Stoltz, William Walker, Jr., Dorothy White </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Vice President for Information Systems: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-14 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Erv Blythe, Theta Bowden, Steve Chapman, Randy Crockett, Esley Dillon,
                            Bela Foltin, Jr., Robert Frary, A. Wayne Donald, Paul Gherman, Shirley
                            Glazener, J. Thomas Head, Robert C. Heterick, Jr., Stanley Huffman, Jr.,
                            Phyllis Johnson, Judy Lilly, John Moore, Frances Painter, William
                            Sanders, Michael Williams </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Office of the Vice President for Student Affairs: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-15 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>Ernest Andrews, Phillip Barkley, Donna Cassell, Thomas Cook, Landrum
                            Cross, Charlotte Davis, Elizabeth Bohon Dedman, Steven Janosik, H. Duane
                            Lagan, Howard M. Lane, James H. Malone, James Lee McBride, Jr., David
                            Ostroth, Edward Spencer, Brian Warren, Pamela Winfrey </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
                <c02 level="subseries">
                    <did>
                        <unittitle>Cooperative Extension and Continuing Education: </unittitle>
                        <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1-16 </container>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>William Allen, John Barrett, Barbara Board, Bonnie Braun, Judy Burtner,
                            F. Charlene Coker, Elton W. Compton, Deloris Ellis, William Flowers,
                            Patricia Foutz, Dorothy Freeman, Edith Friend, Mitchell R. Geasler,
                            Annie Gilmer, John Huddleston, James Johnson, C. Clark Jones, Roy Jones,
                            Wayne Keffer, Peter Kipp, Linda Leffel, Clarence Lester, A. J. Lilly,
                            Lorena Lyons, Kennith Martin, James McAlister, Charles Perkins, Herbert
                            Pettaway, Arnold Travis Poole, Jr., Ann Sanderson, Robert Swain, Pat
                            Trotter, Clinton Turner </p>
                        <p>&nbsp; </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
