<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viblbv00000">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and
      State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViBlbV::viblbv01723:: A Guide to the Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection, 2001-2005)//EN" "viblbv01723.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >2001-2005</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Shchetinina, Anna Alexandrovna Architectural Collection, <num type="collectionnumber">Ms2007-031</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2015 By Virginia Tech. All rights
          reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">2015-10-22T14:50-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language> and
                <language langcode="rus">Russian</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2005</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
        Ms2007-031</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Tech</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Courtney Dowse, Student Worker and Samantha Winn, Collections Archivist, </label>
          <item> Special Collections</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>

  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Tech </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Tech,
        Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection, <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
        >2001-2005</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">Ms2007-031</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">0.2 cu.ft., 1 box</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language"> 
        <language langcode="rus">Russian</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">
	  Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina (19578-present) graduated from the Moscow Architectural Institute in 1982. Anna Shchetinina founded her architecture studio, TERRA, in 1991. Anna Schetinina serves as the head of the studio. TERRAfocuses on interior design as well as larger projects. Select projects of note include Anna's work on the interior design for the cinema "Drummer" and restaurants in Ostankino tower. Anna Shchetinina is a member of the Union of Architects of Russia and the Russian Artists' Union. This collection consists of project files, floor plans, interior design plans, and other materials related to seven projects Shchetinina's studio worked on between 2001-2005.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Shchetinina, Anna Alexandrovna</persname>
            </origination>
    </did>

    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref2">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="ref3">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Permission to publish material from the Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="ref5">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection, Ms 2007-031, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="ref4">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in October 2007 as part of the International Archive of Women in Architecture.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo id="ref7">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina was completed in October 2015.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
      <p>Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina is a Soviet and Russian architect, interior designer, and modern artist. Anna Shchetinina is also a member of the Union of Architects of Russia and the Russian Union of Artists. Her firm TERRA is still active and undertakes projects of design and reconstruction of residential, public, and industrial buildings. In addition, TERRA offers landscape organization, creation of interior items, and art layouts. TERRAhas been published in various architectural journals including "Arch-Moscow", "Headquarters", "The Best Interiors", "Tabouret", "Architectural Herald", and others.</p> 
	  
	  <p>Shchetinina was born on April 27, 1958 in Moscow, USSR. Her father was a Soviet physicist. He was the head of the Experimental Laboratory and the Central Aerological Observatory at the USSR Academy of Sciences in Moscow. Her mother was the Deputy Chief Economist for "Dzerzhinets." In 1982, Anna graduated from the Moscow Architectural Institute. She opened TERRAin 1991, an architectural firm in Moscow concentrating on private interiors and larger projects. As the head of TERRA, Shchetinina worked on the cinema called "Drummer" and restaurants in Ostankino Tower, which is owned by the unitary enterprise Russian TV and Radio Broadcasting Network in Moscow.</p>
	  
	  <p>Her first marriage, from 1977-1990, was to Vasily Vladimirovich Bychkov, a Soviet architect, Russian businessman, and public and political figure. Bychkov is also a member of the Civic Chamber of the Russian Federation. Anna Shchetinina married an English architect from 1994-1995 and moved to the United Kingdom where she worked on several private galleries. Shchetinina was encouraged by friends to return to Russia. She became the head of landscape workshops for the Nikola-Lenivets park, a place for artists to live and work. At Nikola-Lenivets, Anna met Vasily Mikhailovichy Shchetinina, a Russian artist and architect. Shchetinina and Shchetinin married in 1996.</p>
	  </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains project records by Anna Alexandrovna Shchetinina, the head of the TERRA architectural firm in Moscow, Russia. This collection contains seven project records dated from 2001-2006.</p>
	  <p>The project records show a four-story residential home with an angled glass wall, 2001; the interior and exterior construction and design plans for a large residence with a pool, 2002; the project records for a dacha, 2004; the interior and exterior reconstruction and design plans for Irito Great Wall Motors car dealership showroom, offices, garage, and restaurant, 2005; and the site survey for a large electric insulator factory, 2006.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection consists of a single series which is arranged in chronological order.</p>
    </arrangement>

    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="aat">Architecture</subject>
		<subject source="local">History of Women in Architecture</subject>
		<subject source="local">International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)</subject>
		<subject source="lcsh">Women architects--Russia</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>

    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
	  <c01 id="ref15" level="item">
		<did>
		  <unittitle>Residential house in the village of Ivanovskoye, in the Istrinsky district, Moscow oblast [Zhiloy dom v pos. Ivanovskoye, Istrinkovo, r-na, Moscovskoy Oblasti], <unitdate>2001</unitdate></unittitle>
		  <container id="cid2144001" type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
		</did>
		<scopecontent id="ref40">
			<p>This project record includes floor plans for a residential home, including a small house for a caretaker and a summer barbecue area.</p>
		</scopecontent>
	  </c01>
	  <c01 level="item">
		<did>
		  <unittitle>Working draft: reconstruction of a country home. Exterior. Village of Penates, Moscow oblast 
		  [Rabochi proyekt reconstruktsi zagorodnovo zhilovo doma. facadi. Poc. Penati, Mosckovskoy oblasti], <unitdate>2002</unitdate>
		  </unittitle>
		  <container id="cid2144002" type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
		</did>
		<scopecontent id="ref41">
			<p>Floor plan and computer rendering of a country home.</p>
		</scopecontent>
	  </c01>
	  <c01 id="ref20" level="item">
		<did>
			<unittitle>Working draft: reconstruction of a country home. Exterior. Village of Penates, Moscow oblast
			[Rabochi proyekt: reconstruktsi zagorodnovo zhilovo doma facadi. pos. Penati, Moscovskoy oblasti],
			<unitdate>2002</unitdate></unittitle>
			<container id="cid2144004" type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
		</did>
		<scopecontent id="ref42">
			<p>Floor plan and computer rendering of the interior design plan.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c01>
		<c01 id="ref18" level="item">
			<did>
				<unittitle>Designs of a Banya: the Oven-House, [Proyekt doma-pechi]
				<unitdate>2004</unitdate></unittitle>
				<container id="cid2144003" type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
			</did>
			<scopecontent id="ref43">
				<p>Floor plans and photographs of a model for a banya.</p>
			</scopecontent>
		</c01>
		<c01 id="ref21" level="item">
			<did>
				<unittitle>Design project showroom located at address: Mitnaya St., house number 66 [Dizayn proyekt avtosalon, racpolozhenovo po adresu, ulitza mitnaya, dom 66], </unittitle>
				<unitdate>2005</unitdate>
				<container id="cid2144005" type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
			</did>
			<scopecontent id="ref44">
				<p>Site plans for the Irito car dealership. Photographs of the exterior as well as floor plans and computer renderings of the interior plan.</p>
			</scopecontent>
		</c01>
		<c01 id="ref22" level="item">
			<did>
				<unittitle>Remodeling of the garage building with the car dealership in the city of Moscow, Mitnaya st., house number 66. Architectural solutions 
				[Pereplanirovka chasti zdaniya garazha s avtosalona v g. Mosckva, ul. Mitnaya, 66. Arkitekturnaya resheniya], </unittitle>
				<unitdate>2005</unitdate>
				<container id="cid2144006" type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
			</did>
			<scopecontent id="ref45">
				<p>Detailed floor plan and computer renderings for the interior design plan.</p>
			</scopecontent>
		</c01>
		<c01 id="ref23" level="item">
			<did>
				<unittitle>Detailed plan of the territory of "Gzhel factory 'electric insulators'" [Proyekt detalnoy planirovki teratori OAO "Gzhelski zavod 'Elektroizolyator'"],</unittitle>
				<unitdate>2005</unitdate>
				<container id="cid2144007" type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
			</did>
			<scopecontent id="ref46">
				<p>Site survey with computer renderings for the Gzhel factory.</p>
			</scopecontent>
		</c01>
	  
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
