<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viblbv00993">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute
            and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00993::Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers, 1958-1970)//EN" "viblbv00993.xml"</eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers, <date>1958-1970</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Hawkins, Herman Bruce Papers
                    <num type="collectionnumber">Ms1974-014</num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                    University</publisher>&address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2012 By Virginia
                        Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.</date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2012-05-22T08:52-0400</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers, 
                <date>1958-1970</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">
                Ms1974-014</num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
                University</publisher>
            <date type="publication">2012 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: John M. Jackson,</label>
                    <item> Special Collections</item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>

    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State
            University </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia
                Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va. </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers, <unitdate normal="1958/1970" type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">1958-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <unitid encodinganalog="099$a" label="Collection Number">Ms1974-014</unitid>
            <physdesc encodinganalog="300$a" label="Physical Characteristics">
                <extent>0.2 cu. ft.</extent>
                <extent>1 box</extent>
            </physdesc>
	    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546$a" label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract id="ref2" label="Abstract">Papers of Herman Bruce Hawkins, graduate of Virginia Tech (BS, electrical engineering, 1910), consisting largely of correspondence exchanged with classmate Charles Taylor Adams on topics such as communism, race relations, and nuclear disarmament. Also includes a file regarding Adams' attempt to organize a protest march in response to the appearance of General William Westmoreland on the Virginia Tech campus in 1969, and material relating to the Virginia Tech Distinguished Alumni Citation awarded to Hawkins in 1961.</abstract>
            <origination label="creator">
                <persname source="local">Hawkins, Herman Bruce</persname>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information</head>
        <accessrestrict id="ref5" encodinganalog="506$a">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict id="ref6" encodinganalog="540$a">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Permission to publish material from Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <prefercite id="ref7" encodinganalog="524$a">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers, Ms1974-014, Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <acqinfo id="ref8" encodinganalog="541$a">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>The Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1974.</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <processinfo id="ref9" encodinganalog="583$a">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Herman Bruce Hawkins Papers commenced and was completed in May 2012.</p>
        </processinfo>
            </descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref10" encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p>Herman Bruce "Bill" Hawkins, son of William B. and Alice G. Slayton Hawkins, was born in Waverly, Virginia, in 1889. He graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute with a BS in electrical engineering in 1910. Hawkins worked for General Electric in Schenectady, New York from 1910 until 1913, when he was hired as an electrical engineer for Canadian Explosives, Ltd., in Montreal. Hawkins founded the Hawkins-Hamilton Company in Richmond, Virginia in 1914, and served as the company's president until retiring in 1959. He was an active alumnus of Virginia Tech, serving as the alumni association's first vice president and president and was also a member of the association's board of directors and the Alumni Fund Council. Hawkins married Mary Edith Lynn in 1919; the couple had two children. Herman B. Hawkins died on March 1, 1981 and was buried in Richmond's Hollywood Cemetery.</p>
            <p>Charles Taylor Adams (more widely known as Taylor Adams) was born in Richmond, Virginia on November 18, 1888. The son of Robert Lee Adams, he entered Virginia Polytechnic Institute as a sophomore in the school's horticultural program in 1908. As editor of the school newspaper, 
                <title render="italic">The Virginia Tech</title>, Adams became involved in at least one controversy relating to editorials issued under the title "Asbestographs." In response to criticism, Adams on Februrary 2, 1910, issued a "spotless edition" of the paper; the issue contained only only advertising, all text columns remaining blank. Adams left school in 1910 and was hired as a reporter by 
                <title render="italic">The Lynchburg News</title>. Later, he moved to New York, where he spent nearly 50 years working in advertising. Following the death of his first wife, Adams married Muriel Haynes--also an advertising executive--in 1956. Charles Taylor Adams died on in New York on December 10, 1981.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1" encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content Note</head>
            <p>This collection contains the papers of Herman Bruce Hawkins, a graduate of Virginia Tech (BS, electrical engineering, 1910), president of the Virginia Tech Alumni Association, and 1961 recipient of the university's Distinguished Alumni Citation. The collection includes correspondence and printed materials.</p>
            <p>Much of the collection focuses on Charles Taylor Adams (more widely known as Taylor Adams), a classmate of Hawkins. The collection includes two files of correspondence exchanged between Hawkins and Adams, largely concerning the topics of communism, civil rights, and nuclear disarmament. Adams, an avowed communist, rails against the ills of western society, especially those of the southern United States, and extolls the virtues of communism in Russia and China, foreseeing a utopian ideal in the distant future. Adams frequently advocates civil rights for African Americans and, in doing so, encloses a number of printed materials from the NAACP and CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) concerning Freedom Riders; Robert F. Williams; events in Monroe, North Carolina; and (briefly) desegregation of schools in Prince Edward County, Virginia. Elsewhere, Adams writes of nuclear disarmament, enclosing printed materials to support his views. Hawkins, meanwhile, defends capitalism and the existing social structure, concluding that a utopian society would be "frightfully dull... a world of ants." Also within these folders are a few letters exchanged between Hawkins and Virginius Dabney (editor of the 
                <title render="italic">Richmond Times-Dispatch</title>), with whom Hawkins was surreptitiously sharing some of Adams' correspondence.</p>
            <p>In addition to the correspondence file is a subject file on Adams, mostly relating to his attempt to remotely organize a protest march at Virginia Tech in response to a 1969 campus appearance by U. S. Army Chief of Staff General William Westmoreland. Included are copies of advertisements placed by Adams in 
                <title render="italic">The Virginia Tech </title>school newspaper, letters to the editor from Adams and others, and correspondence (regarding Adams) exchanged between Hawkins and others, including Virginia Tech President T. Marshall Hahn.</p>
            <p>The collection also contains a folder of material relating to Hawkins as recipient of the Virginia Tech Distinguished Alumni Citation. Included are correspondence, memoranda, biographical material, and printed materials.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement id="ref14" encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>Arranged by subject matter.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess>
            <head>Index Terms</head>
            <controlaccess>
                <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="local">University Archives</subject>
            <subject source="local">University History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Virginia Polytechnic Institute</subject>
                </controlaccess>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List</head>
            <c01 id="ref11" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Taylor Adams correspondence, <unitdate>1958-1963, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid1139001" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-1-2</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref12" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Taylor Adams subject file, <unitdate>1966-1970, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid1139002" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-3</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
            <c01 id="ref13" level="file">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Distinguished Alumni Citation, <unitdate normal="1961/1961">1961</unitdate></unittitle>
                    <container id="cid1139003" type="Box-folder" label="Box-folder">1-4</container>
                   
                </did>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
