<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vt.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vt_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY ms73 SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00059.xml.frame" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY hbpic SYSTEM "http://spec.lib.vt.edu/archives/125th/confeds/harvey_black.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY imagebase SYSTEM "http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/index.php" NDATA html>
]><ead id="viblbv00435">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViBlbV">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University::University Libraries::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViBlbV::viblbv00435:: Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black, 1865-1867, 1879)//EN" "viblbv00435.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black, <date>1865-1867, 1879</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black
<num type="collectionnumber">Ms2009-084
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Kira A. Dietz, <date>6/3/2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black, <date>1865-1867, 1879</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">Ms2009-084
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Lora Settle
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1865-1867, 1879
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Ms2009-084
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.1 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains a bill detailing medical service provided to the family of Rev. William A. Wade by Dr. Harvey Black. The bill includes the cost of services, as well as a note from Black forgiving payment.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Permission to publish material from the Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Researchers wishing to cite this collection should include the following information: Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black, Ms2009-084 - Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black was purchased by Special Collections in May 2009. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The processing, arrangement, and description of the Medical Bill Signed by Dr. Harvey Black commenced and was completed in June 2009.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Dr. Harvey Black (1827-1888) was the great grandson of Samuel Black and grandson of John Black who were among the original settlers of Blacksburg, Virginia. He was born to Alexander and Elizabeth McDowell Black in 1827. He served as a private in the Mexican War. Following his discharge in 1848, he attended medical school at the University of Virginia, then set up a private practice in Blacksburg in 1850. In 1852, he married Mary Irby Kent (b. 1836), who he called &quot;Mollie.&quot; They had four children: Kent (b.1853), Elizabeth (b.1855), Alexander (b.1957), and Charles (b.1859). </p><p>
During the Civil War, Black was a surgeon with the 4<emph render="super">th</emph> Regiment, Virginia Infantry, and ran the field hospital of the 2<emph render="super">nd</emph> Corps, Army of Northern Virginia. Black assisted in the operation on General Thomas J. &quot;Stonewall&quot; Jackson after Jackson had been wounded at the Battle of Chancellorsville. </p><p>
After the Civil War, Harvey Black resumed his medical practice in Blacksburg. He was elected president of the Medical Society of Virginia in 1872. He played an instrumental role in the founding of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College in Blacksburg in 1872. He was the first rector of the Board of Visitors.</p><p>
From 1876 to 1882, Harvey Black was Superintendent of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum in Williamsburg. In 1884, he was appointed to the board of a proposed state mental hospital for southwestern Virginia. In 1885, he was elected to represent Montgomery County in the House of Delegates and served two sessions. In the House, he influenced the decision to locate the new hospital in Marion. In 1887, Black became the first superintendent of the new Southwestern State Lunatic Asylum in Marion. He appointed John S. Apperson (who later married Black's daughter Elizabeth in 1889) assistant physician there. Harvey Black died in Richmond in October 1888 and was buried in Westview Cemetery in Blacksburg.</p><p>
William A. Wade was born in Virginia about 1827. He was a Methodist Episcopal minister. Some time around 1850, he married Charlotte (Charlette) Louisa (b. abt. 1830). They had three children: Elizabeth (b. abt.1851), Willie (b. abt.1862), and Allice (b. abt. 1864). In 1860, the family lived in Blacksburg, possibly with Charlotte's extended family. In 1880, they were in Opequon, Frederick County, Virginia.</p></bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This medical bill is an itemized list of the services provided by Dr. Harvey Black to the family of Rev. William A. Wade between 1865 and 1867. Many of Black's visits were for Wade's wife and children, but the list also notes service to &quot;negro woman Rachel.&quot; Black provided such services as cupping while also administering prescribed medicines, such as olive oil, rhubarb, chalk, and brandy. </p>
<p>While the price of each service and/or prescribed medicine is listed and totaled, Black wrote the following at the end, dated 1879: &quot;The Rev W.A. Wade being engaged in the active work of the ministry the above balance is hereby canceled. The bond of $36.39 named in his statement cannot be found. While it is probably among my papers at Blacksburg, its payment is hereby acknowledged.&quot;</p></scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged by material type. 
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p><bibref>Black, Harvey, Mary Kent Black, and Glenn L. McMullen. <title render="italic">The Civil War Letters of Dr. Harvey Black: A Surgeon with Stonewall Jackson</title>. Army of Northern Virginia series, 3rd v. Baltimore, Md: Butternut and Blue, 1995. Spec Civil War E 605 .B53 1995</bibref></p>
<p>Papers of the Black, Kent, and Apperson  Families, 1779-1984 (Bulk 1821-1948). Ms73-004. <extref entityref="ms73">Finding aid
</extref> available on Virginia Heritage.</p>
<p>A digital image of <extref entityref="hbpic">Dr. Harvey Black</extref> is available from the University Archives History of Virginia Tech pages. </p>
<p>Harry Downing Temple, Jr., Papers and Photographs, 1927-1998. Ms88-039. Contains additional images related to Dr. Harvey Black also available on <extref entityref="imagebase">Imagebase</extref>.</p></relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Medical bill,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1865-1867, 1879.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>			
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
