<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil000016">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Supreme Court of Virginia Archives::Virginia State Law Library Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil000016::A Guide to the Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, 1881-2011 (1950-2011)//EN" "vil000016.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A guide to the Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Constitution records, <date>1922-1936 (bulk 1926-1927).</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Constitution records, 1922-1936 (bulk 1926-1927).  
<num type="collectionnumber">00030217
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2012 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>30 July 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Constitution records, <date>1922-1936 (bulk 1926-1927)</date></titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00030217
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library staff</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Constitution,     
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1922-1936 (bulk 1926-1927)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00030217
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.35 cu. ft. (1 box)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia. Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Constitution.  
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no access restrictions.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Commission to Suggest Changes to the Constitution records, 1922-1936 (bulk 1926-1927), Accession #00030217, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records were tranferred to the State Law Library from the Office of the Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, in 2007.  Robert Prentis, President of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, was a member of the commission.     
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>By authority of an act approved March 25, 1926, Governor Harry Byrd appointed a commission of seven members (Robert R. Prentis, President, Supreme Court of Appeals), R. Gray Williams, of Winchester; William Minor Lile, Robert M. Hughes, of Norfolk; Joseph H. Chitwood, of Roanoke, former Governor Henry C. Stuart, and William Meade Fletcher, of Sperryville, to a commission to suggest amendments to the Virginia Constitution. The commission was "charged with the duty of studying the constitution of Virginia nad proposing in detail such revisions of the same as in the opinion of the commission will be for the best interests of the commonwealth." The suggested amendments, approved by the General Assembly, reduced the number of statewide elected officials from eight to three (what became known as the short ballot), and "revised the state tax system by implementing a system of tax segregation that gave localities the power to tax real estate and personal property while leaving the income tax available to the state."</p>
<p>The Bureau of Municipal Research was a citizens committee headed by William T. Reed, friend and mentor of Harry F. Byrd. The General Assembly authorized the bureau to survey Virginia government and recommend reductions.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Commission to Suggest Amendments to the Virginia Constitution records documenting the work of the commission from 1926-1927. Contains meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, press release, suggested amendments, drafts, notes, a transcript of public hearing about proposed amendments, a pamphlet summarizing a survey, initiated by the Office of the Governor, of county and city government in other states; newspaper clippings, and two speeches. Contains correspondence between Chief Justice Robert Prentis, Chair of the Commission, and Governor Harry F. Byrd, and with Congressmen R. Walton Moore (8th District), commission member Robert M. Hughes, as well as letters from lawyers, state officials and delegates, commenting on proposed amendments. Also contains correspondence pertaining to press relations and public hearings.     
</p>
<p>Of particular interest is correspondence between University of Virginia president Edwin A. Alderman and Judge Prentis in which Alderman describes his concerns about Section 184 of the Constitution, which prohibited public borrowing for improvements; a memo from Governor Byrd to the members of the commission enclosing recommendations of the New York Bureau of Municipal Research for changes to the constitution, 1927 Jan. 18; and a letter recommending contemporary scientific research on race to the commission. </p>  
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Heinemann, Ronald L. "Harry F. Byrd (1887–1966)." Encyclopedia Virginia. Ed. Brendan Wolfe. Viewed July 30, 2012. Virginia Foundation for the Humanities. 7 Apr. 2011 http://www.EncyclopediaVirginia.org/Byrd_Harry_Flood_Sr_1887-1966. 
</bibref>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Personal Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Alderman, Edwin Anderson, 1861-1931.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hughes, Robert M. (Robert Morton), b. 1855.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Moore, R. Walton (Robert Walton), 1859-1941.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Prentis, Robert Riddick, 1855-1931.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">New York Bureau of Municipal Research.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Commission to Suggest Changes to the Constitution.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Constitution (1902).</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Finance, Public -- Virginia.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre/form</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Clippings (information artifacts) -- Virginia -- Richmond. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Correspondence -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Minutes -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Pamphlets -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Press releases -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Speeches -- Virginia.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
