<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00027">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Supreme Court of Virginia Archives::Virginia State Law Library Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00027::A Guide to the Oral History of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2013 Mar. 27)//EN" "vil00027.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Oral History of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia,  <date>2013 Mar. 27</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Oral History of the Court of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia F
<num type="collectionnumber">00031900
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169;2013 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>19 April 2013</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Oral History of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, <date>2013 Mar. 27</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Numbers">00031900
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2013
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine G. OBrion
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Oral History of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia,    
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2013 Mar. 27  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">00031900</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1 .mov (digital video, 1 hour, 39 minutes, 52 seconds); 1 transcript (45 p.)</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia. Supreme Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.   
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.  
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Oral History of the Organization of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2013 Mar. 27, Accession number 00031900, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The interview is a project of the Virginia State Law Library for the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Court of Appeals of Virginia was established January 1, 1985. It provides appellate review of final decisions of the circuit courts in domestic relations matters, appeals from decisions of an administrative agency, traffic infractions and
criminal cases, except where a sentence of death has been imposed. It also hears appeals of final decisions
of the Virginia Workers' Compensation Commission. Except in those cases where the decision of
the Court of Appeals is final, any party aggrieved by a decision of the Court of Appeals may petition the Supreme Court for an appeal.
The Court of Appeals consists of eleven judges. The court sits in panels of at least three judges, and the membership of the panels is rotated. The court sits at such locations as the chief judge designates, so as to provide convenient access to the various geographic areas of the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>The Court of Appeals began operations in January 1985 with ten judges: Chief Judge E. Ballard Baker, who died suddenly in March 1985; Bernard G. Barrow, James W. Benton, Charles H. Duff, William H. Hodges, Barbara M. Keenan, Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr. (Chief Judge, 1985-1992), Norman K. Moon (Chief Judge, 1992-1997), and Marvin F. Cole.</p> 
<p>Judge Benton served on the court until he retired in 2007; Judge Coleman from 1985-2001, when he took senior status; Judge Keenan from 1985 to 1991, when she became a justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia; Justice Koontz from 1985 to 1995, when he joined Keenan on the Supreme Court of Virginia; and Norman K. Moon from 1985 to 1997, when he became a U.S. District Judge for the Western District of Virginia.</p>
<p>Cassandra Newby-Alexander is Professor of history at Norfolk State University.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Oral history interview with five of the ten judges who sat on the Court of Appeals of Virginia when it was founded in 1985: James W. Benton, Jr., Sam W. Coleman, III, Barbara M. Keenan, Lawrence W. Koontz, and Norman K. Moon. Moderated by Cassandra Newby-Alexander, Professor of History at Norfolk State University. Recorded at the Community Idea Staions in Richmond. Transcript available.</p>
<p>The participants discuss the historical context in which the court was created, support and opposition for the court when it was created, the process of establishing procedures for the new court, and the experience of being on the new court, and the successes of the court. Toward the end of the discussion, Newby-Alexander asks each participant what led him or her to pursue a legal career.</p>
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>
