<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00001">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00001::A Guide to the Clerk's correspondence and other records, 1906-2005 (bulk 1924-1977))//EN" "vil00001.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clerk's correspondence and other records, <date>1906-2005 (bulk 1924-1977)</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Clerk's correspondence and other records
<num type="collectionnumber">00028513
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>13 December 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clerk's correspondence and other records, <date>1906-2005 (bulk 1924-1977)</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00028513
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine G. OBrion
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law LibrarySupreme Court of Virginia Archives
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Clerk's correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1906-2005 (bulk 1924-1977)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00028513
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2.50 cu. ft. (8 boxes).
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Clerk's correspondence, Accession # 00028513, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records were transferred from the Clerk's office to the State Law Library in 2006.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia is the officer of the court responsible for overseeing filings with the Court and maintaining its records.  Maury B. Watts was appointed Clerk in 1933 and served until his death in 1952; Howard G. Turner served from 1952 to 1977, and David Beach served from 1977 to 2003.  
</p>
<p>The Special Court of Appeals was established by the General Assembly to relieve congestion of the high court docket by ajudicating cases assigned to it by the state Supreme Court.  It met from 1924 to 1928.  Thomas R. Morris, The Virginia Supreme Court: An Institutional and Political Analysis, University Press of Virginia, 1977.</p>
<p>The Judicial Council was established by the General Assembly in 1928.  It was relatively inactive between 1936 and 1847, when Chief Justice Hudgins revitalized it. Morris, p. 109.</p>
<p>Leo Fox made a business soliciting commissions for portraits from leading figures of society under the pseudonym Charles J. Fox.  The portraits were painted by Irving Resnikoff (1897-1988), A Russian immigrant.  He executed the paintings from photographs.  
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection is comprised of correspondence of the Office of the Clerk, 1918-2005 (bulk 1928-1977), correspondence pertaining to establishment of a Special Court of Appeals, 1924-1928; Judicial Council correspondence, 1930-1935; subject files documenting swearing-in ceremonies and investitures, portrait presentations and memorials, and court anniversaries, 1945-2005; speeches, 1954-1975; and miscellaneous items, 1909-2001.
</p>
<p>Clerk's correspondence is comprised mostly of internal correspondence between the Clerk of the Supreme Court and the justices, but also includes some copies justices' correspondence with other people.   There are several files of correspondence with Chief Justice Holt, 1928-1947; Chief Justice Hudgins, 1930-1958; Justice Gregory, 1933-1951, and Justice Spratley, 1936-1977.  Correspondence pertains mostly to day-to-day administrative issues, editing and copy-editing of opinions, and management of court documents.  Some letters from justices to the Clerk include rationales for decisions or opinions, references to court policies, concerns about declining health of other justices, and personal matters.
</p>
<p>The series includes one file of correspondence of Justice Holt, 1937-1938, pertaining to portraits of St. George Tucker and Justice Chinn, a memorial plaque for Judge Carrington, and a portrait of St. George Tucker.  Also included is a folder containing personal correspondence of Chief Justice Holt, 1944-1947, which is comprised mostly of short letters to his three two daughters, and personal friends.
</p>
<p>Correspondence between Clerk Maury B. Watts and Chief Justice Hudgins includes correspondence regarding the Judicial Council of Virginia, 1947-1958. Of particular interest are letters from Chief Justice Hudgins protesting a bill pending in the House of Delegates in 1954 that would have required approval of the General Assembly of rules adopted by the Supreme Court, through the Judicial Council, affecting the practice of law in Virginia.   A file of personal correspondence of Chief Justice Hudgins, 1941-1950, includes a letter from Senator A. Willis Robertson, 1947, responding to Hudgins' inquiry about legislation to help tobacco farmers and protect archaeological findings in the section of the Roanoke River Basin to be flooded by construction of the Buggs Island Dam.
</p>
<p>Correspondence between M.B. Watts, Clerk, and Justice Spratley, 1936-1952, pertains mostly to Watts' editorial suggestions, research questions, and research advice, and some correspondence about Justice Spratley's law clerks in the early 1940s.  Correspondence between Howard G. Turner, Clerk, and Justice Spratley, 1953-1977, pertains mostly to management of court documents, hiring of law clerks, and court ceremonies.</p>
<p>Correspondence regarding the organization of a Special Court of Appeals, 1924-1928, is comprised of letters from Justice Frederick Walker Sims, Court President, 1925-1925, and Justice Robert Prentis, Chief Justice, 1925-1931, with other justices, judges, and legislators, documenting efforts to establish a special Court of Appeals in Virginia and recommendations for members of the court. Correspondents include state Senators Robert J. Noel, Alfred C. Smith, and W. Worth Smith, Jr., Delegates George A. Bowles, Charles Henry Smith, and Thomas W. Ozlin, Speaker; Louis S. Epes, State Corporation Commission, attorney Eppa Hunton, Jr., and Richmond judge Beverley T. Crump.
</p>
<p>Clerk's general correspondence, 1924-1985, contains correspondence with other court clerks from around the state, including W.W. Smales, Deputy Clerk, Supreme Court of Appeals, Staunton; regarding planning of presentations of portraits and memorials to justices, 1929-1985; admission of foreign attorneys, 1933-1942; cessation of court sessions in Staunton and Wytheville, 1938; regarding management of portraits, 1941-1968; requests for  biographical information on former clerks George Taylor and John Brown, 1941 and 1959; modifications to court rules, 1960 and 1981; alterations to the state library and supreme court building,1967; and a solicitation for business from Leo Fox, 1969.
</p>
<p>Judicial Council correspondence contains correspondence of Chief Justice Prentis, President of the Judicial Council; and M.B. Watts, Clerk of the Supreme Court and Secretary of the Judicial Council, 1930-1935. Correspondence documents organization and administration of the Judicial Council and the Council's work in seeking recommendations from lawyers and judges for changes to statues regulating the practice of law in Virginia.  Correspondents include individuals invited to join the Council, representatives of Judicial Councils from other states, and Virginia attorneys and judges proposing changes in laws.  The correspondence includes an exchange between Herbert G. Cochran, Norfolk Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court Judge, to Norfolk, and Chief Justice Prentis, 1931, regarding a request for the Council's help with the Virginia State Bar Association's Committee on Organization of the Bar; and a letter from Chief Justice Campbell to Governor Peery, 1935, requesting re-appropriation for the Council in the Governor's budget for 1936.
</p>
<p>Speeches, 1954-1975, consist of an addresses by Justices Carrico, Eggleston, and I'anson dediciating portraits or memorials or about the functions of the court.  Included is an address, 1975, by Justice Carrico to the Richmond Association of Attorneys' wives, 1975.
</p>
<p>The collection also contains subject files on swearing-in ceremonies and investitures for justices, chief justices, Supreme Court Clerk's, and the Executive Secretary, Office of the Executive Secretary, 1965-2005; portrait presentations, memorials, resolutions of appreciation, and memorial, 1945-2004; and court anniversaries, 1979-2004.  These files contain invitations, programs, oaths of office, transcripts of ceremonies, speeches and remarks, and sometimes seating charts and ceremony planning notes.</p>
<p>Subject files on portrait presentations, memorials, resolutions of appreciations, and memorials, 1945-2004, contain invitations, programs, transcripts of ceremonies, including remarks; printed memorials, resolutions of appreciation (legislative and judicial), planning notes, some seating charts, and newspaper clippings.   
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Persons:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Bowles, George A.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Brown, John, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Campbell, Preston White, 1874-1946.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Carrico, Harry Lee, 1916-.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Carrington, Paul, 1733-1818.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Chinn, Joseph William, 1866-1936.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Cochran, George Moffett, 1912-2011.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Crump, Beverly, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Eggleston, John William, 1886-1976.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Epes, Louis S., DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Fox, Leo, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Gregory, Herbert Bailey, 1884-1951.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Holt, Henry Winston, 1864-1947.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hudgins, Edward Wren, 1882-1958.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hunton, Eppa, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">I'Anson, Lawrence Warren, 1907-1990.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Noel, Robert J., DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Ozlin, Thomas W., DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Peery, FIRST NAME, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Prentis, Robert Riddick, 1855-1931.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Robertson, A. Willis, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Sims, Frederick Wilmer, 1862-1925.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Smales, W.W.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Spratley, Claude Vernon, 1936-1967.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Smith, Alfred C., DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Smith, Charles Henry, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Smith, W. Worth, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Taylor, George, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Tucker, St. George, DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Turner, Howard G., DATES.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Watts, Maury B., DATES.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Judicial Council of Virginia.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Richmond Association of Attorneys' Wives.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Special Court of Appeals.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia State Bar Association. Committee on Organization of the Bar.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Executive Secretary.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Court rules -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Courts -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Judges -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Judicial opinions -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Judicial process -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Virginia -- Supreme Court -- History -- 20th century.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Ceremonies</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Clippings (information artifacts)</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Correspondence</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Dedications (ceremonies)</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Invitations</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Oaths</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Obituaries</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Portraits</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Souvenior programs</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Speeches--Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Transcripts</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
