<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vil00006">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00006::A Guide to the Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc. legal correspondence, 1842-1851)//EN" "vil00006.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc. legal correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1851</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc. legal correspondence, 1842-1851  
<num type="collectionnumber">00029240
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vsll-scv_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 February 2012</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc. legal correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1851</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00029240
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012
</date>
      <list type="simple">
        <head>Contact information:</head>
        <item>Virginia State Law Library</item>
        <item>Supreme Court of Virginia</item>
        <item>100 North Ninth Street</item>
        <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219</item>
        <item>URL: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.courts.state.va.us/courtadmin/library/home.html">http://www.courts.state.va.us/courtadmin/library/home.html</extref></item>
        <item id="email">Email: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="mailto:LawLibrary@courts.state.va.us">LawLibrary@courts.state.va.us</extref></item>
        <item>Phone: (804) 786-2075</item>
      </list>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Catherine G. OBrion
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library. </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., legal correspondence,    
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1851
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00029240
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">9 items   
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Terry, Abner Wentworth Clopton (1815-1851)
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Colombian College v. Abner W. Clopton's Administrators etc. legal correspondence, 1842-1851, Accession #00029240, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The letters were acquired by the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives in 2012.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Abner W. Clopton (1784-1833) was a Baptist minister in Charlotte County.  In 1827, Clopton was appointed Georgia fund-raising agent for Colombian College (later George Washington University), founded by Baptist missionary Luther Rice and chartered in 1821.  Due to his success in raising funds for the financially strapped college, Clopton was appointed to its Board of Trustees in 1829 and general agent in 1832.  After Clopton's death, Colombian College sued in chancery court in Charlotte County, Virginia, to recover Clopton's conditional bequest to the college.  The court ruled against the college in 1843, and Court of Appeals upheld the lower court's decision in 1850.  
</p>
      <p>Abner Wentworth Clopton Terry (1815-1851) was the son of Daniel Terry, one of Clopton's executors, and the grandson of Abner W. Clopton.  The other executors named in the will were Archibald A. Davis and John W. Roach. Abner W.C. Terry died suddenly in June 1851.  Terry, who was a publisher of the Lynchburg Virginian newspaper, was killed on the street in Lynchburg by James D. Saunders, who was upset about an editorial published in the newspaper.</p>
      <p>Conway Robinson was a lawyer, legal scholar, and court reporter for the Court of Appeals of Virginia 1842-1843. Between 1846 and 1849, he and acting Governor John M. Patton worked on revisions to the Code of Virginia. The revisions, adopted by the General Assembly in 1849, remained in use for nearly forty years.</p>
      <p>Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849) was a Richmond lawyer and politician.  He prepared the 1819 revised code of Virginia and was a court reporter for the Court of Appeals from 1829 to 1841.</p>
      <p>James Wood Bouldin (1792-1854) was a lawyer who practiced at Charlotte County Courthouse beginning in 1813.  He represented Colombian College in the chancery suit against Clopton's administrators.  Bouldin was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1872 to 1875.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection consists of the correspondence of Abner W.C. Terry (eight letters, 1842-1851) about a court case involving the estate of Abner W. Clopton, Terry's grandfather; and a document from a related chancery cause filed in Pittsylvania county circa 1851.  The Charlotte County case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., was decided in Terry's favor in 1843 and appealed to the Court of Appeals in 1850.  The court upheld the decision of the lower court, ruling that Clopton's bond to the college was not binding because the conditions of the bond were not met before Clopton died.  The correspondence includes two letters from noted Richmond attorney Conway Robinson explaining the legal strategy he planned to use in arguing the case before the Court of Appeals, and advice to Terry about resolving remaining legal issues among the heirs in the case.</p>
      <p>The first letter, dated 1842 Mar. 28, is from Archibald A. Davis, one of the executors named in Clopton's will, discussing the status of the estate and the claim against it by Colombian College. The second letter, dated 1843 Apr. 24, is from Wood Bouldin, attorney for Colombian College in the Charlotte County chancery cause, giving notice to Terry about depositions taken in Washington, D.C. from members of the Columbian College Board of Trustees. The third letter, dated 1843 Dec. 10, is from Richmond attorney Benjamin Watkins Leigh offering his services and those of Conway Robinson to Terry should the case come before the Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p>
      <p>The fourth letter is a photostat copy of a letter dated 1844 Jun. 29 from Terry to Robinson seeking his opinion about the ultimate disposition of the bequest to the college.  Terry noted in the letter he had heard that Charlotte County Judge Lee's opinion in the case was "a very ingenious one."</p>
      <p>The fifth letter, dated 1844 Jul. 18, is from Robinson to Terry advising him that the college had obtained an appeal, relating his ideas for possible arguments for the case and citing legal precedents he had used successfully before the court in similar cases.  In a subsequent letter, dated 1851 Apr. 15, Robinson wrote Terry advising him about how to resolve remaining claims to the Clopton legacy among the nieces and nephews named in the will, Newton Institute, a Baptist seminary in Massachusetts; and next of kin.  He suggests having someone representing one of the interests file suit against the other two parties.</p>
      <p>The last two items in the collection are a letter from  John M. Waldron to Terry, 1851 Mar. 19, advising Terry that he is seeking his mother's portion of the Clopton legacy; and a manuscript copy of a bill of complaint from a suit filed in Pittyslvania County chancery court by Waldron, 1851, circa (Administrator of Nancy Waldron v. Administrator of Daniel Terry, etc.). The court document includes genealogical information about Clopton's nieces and nephews, their spouses and their children.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography
</head>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Jewel L. Spangler, "Clopton, Abner Wentworth," in Sara B. Bearss, ed., Dictionary of Virginia Biography Vol. 3 (2006), 305; obituary notice for Abner W.C. Terry in the Lynchburg Virginian, 1851 June 12, available on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.</bibref>
      </bibliography>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Charlotte County Chancery Cause, Colombian College v. Administrator of Abner W. Clopton, etc., Charlotte County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1765-1912 (bulk 1784-1912), 1843-004. Local Government Records Collection, Charlotte County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.  The court case has been digitized and is available through the Library of Virginia's digital collections portal, Virginia Memory.  The case documents include a bill of complaint, answers from Terry and Archibald Davis, depositions from Colombian College Trustees James Wood, Andrew Rothwell, and James L. Edwards; copies of the act incorporating Colombian College charter, and a copy of Clopton's bond to the college.</p>
        <p>Virginia Court of Appeals opinion, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., Virginia Reports, Vol. VII (1850), 168-177.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Bouldin, James Wood (1792-1854).</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Clopton, Abner Wentworth (1784-1833).</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Clopton family.</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Davis, Archibald A.</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Leigh, Benjamin Watkins (1781-1849).</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Robinson, Conway (1805-1884).</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Terry, Abner Wentworth (1815-1851).</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Terry family.</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Waldron, John M.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Colombian College (Washington, D.C.)</corpname>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Court of Appeals.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Baptists -- clergy -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Courts -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (law) -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Lawyers -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Charlotte County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Legal correspondence -- Virginia.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
