<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00015">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Supreme Court of Virginia Archives::Virginia State Law Library Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00015::A Guide to the Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, 1881-2011 (1950-2011)//EN" "vil00015.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A guide to the Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, <date>1881-2011 (bulk 1950-2011).</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, 1881-2011 (bulk 1950-2011). 
<num type="collectionnumber">00003029
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2012 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>28 June 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, <date>1881-2011 (bulk 1950-2011)</date></titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00003029
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library staff</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, 1818-2011 (bulk 1950-2011)    
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1818-2011 (bulk 1950-2011)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00003029
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.60 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia. Supreme Court.  
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Access to recent photographs of members of the court (1990-2011) is restricted.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Supreme Court of Virginia photographs, 1881-2011 (bulk 1950-2011), Accession #00003029, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The official portraits, and the photograph of Justice Burks, 1918, circa, were acquired from the Office of the Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia. Most of the other photographs were acquired in a transfer from the Office of the Executive Secretary in 2005. The photograph of Moncure Conway, 1881, was donated to the State Law Library by C.M. Chichester in 1923.    
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the new General Assembly in 1779. By Constitutional amendment in 1928, the number of justices was increased from five to seven and the title of the presiding officer of the Court  was changed from President to Chief Justice. At the same time, the amendment significantly increased the power given the Supreme Court by permitting the Court to prescribe forms and to regulate the practice of Virginia's courts. The Constitution of 1971 changed the name of the Court  to its present title of Supreme Court of Virginia. </p>
<p>The Court of Appeals of Virginia was established January 1, 1985. It provides appellate review of final decisions of the circuit courts in domestic relations matters, appeals from decisions of an administrative agency, traffic infractions and criminal cases, except where a sentence of death has been imposed.</p>
<p>The Office of the Executive Secretary was established in 1952. It provides administrative support for all of the courts  and magistrate offices within the Commonwealth. This includes the training and education of all judicial branch employees, as well as legal research assistance for judges.</p>  
<p>The Office of the Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, receives, processes, and maintains permanent records of all appeals and other official documents filed with the Court. The Clerk also maintains records of qualified attorneys and other administrative records.</p> 
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection is comprised mostly of official annual group portraits of the justices in the courtroom and the judicial conference room, 1900-2011 (bulk 1956-2011). It includes one formal portrait of the Court of Appeals in the courtroom, 1989, circa. Also included are individual portraits of justices, photographs of paintings of justices, candid photographs of justices and others at ceremonial occasions of the court. The earliest photograph is a photograph of Moncure Conway, a court reporter in the antebellum period, 1881. When known, the photographer is listed in the catalog record for the individual photograph.</p>
<p>Box 1 contains photographs (approximately 71 items) cataloged individually under the PHOT 1.1 call number prefix. Most are formal group portraits (11 x 14, black and white) of the Supreme Court of Virginia justices in the courtroom or in the judicial conference room. For the years 1998-2011, most of the official portraits are in color. This box contains official portraits for the following years: 1952, 1957, 1958, 1969, 1972, 1974, 1977, 1983, 1987-1991, 1996, 1998, 2000, 2003, 2007, 2008, and 2011.    
</p>
<p>In addition to the group portraits, Box 1 also contains a group photograph of the fifteenth annual convention of the Association of Trial Justices of Virginia at the Hotel Jefferson in Richmond, 1949; and a candid photograph of Justices Buchanan, Eggleston, and Snead and Governor Mills Godwin at the Commonwealth Club, 1969.</p>  
<p>Box 2 contains photographs (approximately 125 items) cataloged individually under the PHOT 2.1 call number prefix. Most are formal group portraits (8 x 10, black and white) of the Supreme court of Virginia justices in the courtroom or in the judicial conference room. Includes some duplicates and photographic negatives. This box contains official portraits for the years 1900 (copy), 1931, 1935, 1936, 1947, 1958, 1959, 1960,1965,1968,1969,1972,1973,1974,1979-1982, 1987, 1998, 2000, and 2003, and an official portrait of the Court of Appeals (color), 1989, circa.</p> 
<p>In addition to the group portraits, Box 2 contains a photograph of attorney Conway Robinson, 1881; a candid photograph of Justice Alexander Harman, 1987; individual portrait photographs of Justice Burks, 1918; Howard G. Turner, Clerk, 1950, circa; Chief Justice Hudgins, 1950, circa; Justice Whittle, 1965, circa; and Justice Poff, 1970, circa; photographs of court ceremonies, including the 200th anniversary of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1979, a dinner for the court hosted by Governor Charles S. Robb, 1983, circa (24 color prints); Justice Spratley presenting a scroll to Chief Justice Eggleston commemorating his thirtieth year as a member of the court, 1965, and portrait presentation ceremonies for Chief Justice Eggleston, 1976, and Justice Cochran, 1989. In addition, here is a photograph of a meeting of the Judicial Council of Virginia, 1931; the dedication of the Supreme Court building in 1941; the swearing-in ceremonies for two members of Governor Linwood Holton's cabinet (Earl Shiflet and Maurice Rowe), 1972; and employees of the office of the Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia in the courtroom, 2000 (10 color prints and negatives). 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. History.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Court of Appeals. History.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Executive Secretary.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Judges -- Virginia -- Portraits.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre/form</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Commemorations (events) -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Photographs -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
