<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00024">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00024::A Guide to Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., May-August 2011)//EN" "vil00024.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., <date>May-August 2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, Sr., May-August 2011
<num type="collectionnumber">00031707
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2013 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created <date>18 March 2013</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., <date>2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00031707
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2013
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library staff.
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">May-August, 2011
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00031707
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">11 MP4s (37 minutes, 53 seconds); 1 transcript (18 p.)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Supreme Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Remembrances of Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., Accession #00031707, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred to the Virginia State Law Library, August 2011.
</p>
</acqinfo></descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the  Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989.  He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007 and served until his death in February 2011.  He was born in Norfolk and earned an undergraduate degree from the University of Virginia and a JD from Harvard University. Hassell was the first African American to serve as chief justice on the court.</p>
</bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains video recordings of judges' personal remembrances of Chief Justice Hassell, recorded at the Virginia Judicial Conference of Virginia in Roanoke, Virginia, in May 2011 and the Virginia Judicial Conference for District Court Judges in Virginia Beach, Virginia, in August 2011.  Two additional interviews were recorded at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond in June 2011. Transcript available.</p>
<p>F. Bruce Bach, retired circuit court judge, Fairfax County (5 minutes, 19 seconds), recorded in Roanoke. Bach worked with Hassell in 2005, when he served as interim executive secretary, or court administrator. 
</p>
<p>Rufus Banks, Jr., chief judge, juvenile and domestic relations court, Chesapeake (1 minute, 10 seconds), recorded in Virginia Beach. 
</p>
<p>Stephen D. Benjamin, Richmond defense lawyer (9 minutes, 34 seconds), recorded in Richmond.  Benjamin talks about working with Hassell on an initiative to improve training and support for court-appointed defense attorneys. 
</p>
<p>D. Eugene Cheek, judge, general district court, Richmond (1 minute, 51 seconds), recorded in Virginia Beach.
</p>
<p>Roxie O. Holder, judge, general district court, Portsmouth (53 seconds), recorded in Virginia Beach. 
</p>
<p>Birdie H. Jamison, judge, general district court, Richmond (1 minute, 7 seconds), recorded in Virginia Beach. 
</p>
<p>H. Thomas Padrick, Jr., judge, circuit court, Virginia Beach (8 minutes, 7 seconds), recorded in Roanoke. Padrick and Hassell served together on the Committee on District Courts.</p>
<p>Cleo E. Powell, judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia (5 minutes), recorded in Richmond. Powell met Hassell when they were both students at the University of Virginia in the 1970s.</p>
<p>Angela Roberts, judge, juvenile and domestic relations court, Richmond (4 minutes, 11 seconds), recorded in Virginia Beach.  
</p>
<p>Thomas S. Shadrick, retired judge, circuit court, Virginia Beach (4 minutes), recorded in Roanoke. Shadrick talks about Hassell's work mentoring children in the Virginia Beach school system.    
</p>
<p>Phillip Trompeter, judge, juvenile and domestic relations court, Roanoke. Trompeter served with Hassell on the Committee on District Courts, recorded in Virginia Beach.</p> 
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>

