<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00014">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Supreme Court of Virginia Archives::Virginia State Law Library Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00014::A Guide to the Office of the Executive Secretary Records, 1952-1995.)//EN" "vil00014.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Office of the Executive Secretary Records, <date>1952-1995.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Office of the Executive Secretary records, 1952-1995. 
<num type="collectionnumber">00028358
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2012 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>22 June 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Office of the Executive Secretary Records, <date>1952-1995</date></titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00028358
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library staff</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Office of the Executive Secretary Records,   
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1952-1995
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00028358
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.90 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Executive Secretary. 
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Office of the Executive Secretary Records, 1952-1995, Accession #00028358, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The collection was transferred to the State Law Library from the Office of the Executive Secretary in 2005. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Office of the Executive Secretary was established in 1952. It provides administrative support for all of the courts and magistrate offices within the Commonwealth. This includes the training and education of all judicial branch employees, as well as legal research assistance for judges.</p>
<p>Hubert Bennett the first person appointed to the position of Executive Secretary.  He served from 1952 to 1976.</p> 
<p>Robert N. Baldwin  was Executive Secretary from 1976 to 2005.</p>
<p>The Judicial Council of Virginia was established by the General Assembly in 1928. It is charged with the responsibility for making a continuous study of the organization, rules and methods of procedure and practice of the judicial system of the Commonwealth. The Chief Justice of the Supreme Court is presiding officer for the Council whose membership includes one Court of Appeals judge, six circuit court judges, one general district court judge, one juvenile and domestic relations district court judge, two attorneys qualified to practice in the Supreme Court and the Chairmen of the Committees for Courts of Justice in the Virginia Senate and House of Delegates. Council members are appointed by the Chief Justice and serve for four years or at the pleasure of the Chief Justice.</p> 
<p>By order of the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia dates November 29, 1966, new rules for depositions and discovery were adopted effective February 1, 1967.  Existing  Rule 3:23 was repealed and replaced by new Rules 4:1 through 4:12.  The new rules were substantially the same as the corresponding Federal Rules of Civil Procedure adopted in 1938. 
</p>
<p>The Court System Study Commission was created by the regular session of the 1968 General Assembly to make a full and complete study of the entire judicial system of the Commonwealth of Virginia. Justice Warren I'Anson was appointed chairman.  In 1971, the commission reported to the General Assembly recommendations for changes in the organization of the court system and recommended creation of an immediate court of appeals.</p>
<p>At a meeting on March 28, 1994, the Judicial Council of Virginia appointed an Ad Hoc Committee for Development of a Proposal for a Study of Gender Bias in the Virginia Court System.  In December 1994 the committee reported there were sufficient areas of inquiry to merit study as to justification formation of task force to study gender bias in the court system of Virginia.  Committee members were Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge Robert W. Stewart, Judge John F. Daffron, Jr., Judge Suzanne K. Fulton, William G. Broaddus, and Lisa C. Germano. A task force was appointed and submitted a final report to the Judicial Council of Virginia in October 2000.</p>  
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains three series of records created by the Office of the Executive Secretary, 1952-1995: the Hubert Bennett files on changes in rules for discovery and pretrial procedures, 1952-1967 (box 1, folders 1-3); court reorganization implementation strategy records, 1972-1981 (box 2); and records of the Ad Hoc Committee for the Development of a Proposal for a Study of Gender Bias in the Virginia Court System, 1993-1995 (box 1, folders 4-21).</p>
<p>The Hubert Bennett files (3 folders) are research  files, reports, and memos pertaining to changes in rules for discovery and pretrial procedures, 1952-1967. They include a report of the Judicial Council Special Committee to Study Discovery and other Pretrial Procedures, chaired by Richmond attorney Aubrey Bowles, 1965; a letter from Judge Walter A. Page outlining his reasons for dissenting from the report of the committee, 1965; a copy of a report to the Judicial Council in Virginia," 1962, about confusion over Rule 3:23, and other reports, letters, and memos pertaining to the issues, 1952-1955.  Correspondents include Chief Justice Hudgins, Richmond lawyer Israel Steingold, Richmond Chancery Court Judge Brockenbrough Lamb, and State Corporation Commission Judge Ralph T. Catterrall, responding to an article on Rule 3:18 (d) by Florian J. Bartosic in the William and Mary Review of Virginia Law.   
</p>
<p>Court reorganization strategy records document strategies for implementation of recommendations made by the Court Study Commission in 1972, including creation of an intermediate appellate court. The collection contains a memo and timeline outlining a strategy for implementation of the commission's recommendations, memos from Robert Baldwin, Executive Secretary, to the Ad Hoc Committee on Court Reorganization, 1980; presentations (outlines) containing rationales for changes in the administration of the circuit court system, in the court cost and fee structure, the use of chief judges and substitute judges, the magistrate system,  and procedures for granting a trial de novo; draft documents and legislation, and research files.  Also included is a copy of a speech given by Court Study Commission Chair, Justice Lawrence I'Anson, to an October 19, 1972, meeting of the Judicial Conference of Virginia in Fredericksburg.  In the speech, I'Anson summarizes the commission's suggestions and recommendations for relieving the Supreme Court of Virginia's case load.</p>  
<p>The records of the Ad Hoc Committee for the Development of a Proposal for a Study of Gender Bias in the Virginia Court System, 1994-1995, contain correspondence, memos, research files containing findings from studies on gender bias in the courts in other states, draft reports, and conference files pertaining to the National Conference on Eliminating Racial and Ethnic Bias and Gender Bias in the Courts in Albuquerque, New Mexico, March 2-5, 1995.</p> 
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Judicial Commission. Ad Hoc Committee on Court Reorganization.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Judicial Commission. Ad Hoc Committee on the Development of a Proposal for a Study of Gender Bias in the Virginia Court System.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Executive Secretary.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Court of Appeals. History.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Court Study Commission.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Personal Names:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Baldwin, Robert N.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">I'Anson, Lawrence W. (Lawrence Warren), 1907-1990.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Court administration -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Courts -- Virginia -- history -- twentieth century.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Discovery (law) -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Courts -- Virginia -- history -- twentieth century.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Sex discrimination in justice administration --  Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Sexism -- Virginia.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre/form</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Articles.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Black and white transparencies.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Memorandums.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Presentations.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Speeches.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
