<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vil00002">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00002::A Guide to the List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1869-1978//EN" "vil00002.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869-1978</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1860-1978 
<num type="collectionnumber">00030578
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Catherine G. OBrion 
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vsll-scv_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2012 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 September 2012</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869-1978</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00030578</num></subtitle>
      <author>Catherine G. OBrion 
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012
</date>
      <list type="simple">
        <head>Contact information:</head>
        <item>Virginia State Law Library</item>
        <item>Supreme Court of Virginia</item>
        <item>100 North Ninth Street</item>
        <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219</item>
        <item>URL: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.courts.state.va.us/courtadmin/library/home.html">http://www.courts.state.va.us/courtadmin/library/home.html</extref></item>
        <item id="email">Email: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="mailto:LawLibrary@courts.state.va.us">LawLibrary@courts.state.va.us</extref></item>
        <item>Phone: (804) 786-2075</item>
      </list>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Library staff. 
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869-1898
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00030578 
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 v. (438 p.)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Supreme Court. 
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>List of Attorneys Practicing in the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1869-1978, Accession #00028932, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These records were transferred from the office of the Clerk to the State Law Library in 2006.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the new General Assembly in 1779. Its jurisdiction was primarily appellate, and its members were elected by the legislature. The Constitution of 1971 changed the name of the court to its present title of Supreme Court of Virginia.
</p>
      <p>Any lawyer licensed to practice law in any court in Virginia was permitted to practice in any other court in Virginia, provided he take an "oath of fidelity to the Commonwealth of Virginia and to honestly demean himself in the practice of the law, and to the best of his ability execute his office of attorney at law." This provision also applied to residents of any state adjoining Virginia or the District of Columbia. (Code of Virginia, Including Legislation to the Year 1860, Chapter CLXIV, 699).  
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The List of Attorneys Practicing in the Court of Appeals, 1869-1978, is a register  of signatures of attorneys qualifying to practice in the Supreme Court of Virginia. Most entries include the date the year the oath was taken and the lawyer's residence (town, courthouse, county, or city). Beginning in 1907, each entry includes the date the attorney qualified.</p>
      <p>Individuals who took the oath from 1869 to 1896 are listed. Beginning in 1897, a written bar exam was given by the Supreme Court of Appeals and the names of those who passed were published by Virginia Law Register (Lynchburg: J.P. Bell Company).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1869:</p>
      <p>Thomas S. Bocock
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1870:</p>
      <p>W.R. Berkeley, George L. Christian, Charles S. Cox, John Dunlop, James G. Field, James W. Green, John G. Griswold, James W. Humes, H.H. Robertson, William Terry.</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1871-1872:</p>
      <p>M. Dulany Ball (resident of Maryland), R.L.T. Beale, George S. Bernard, George W. Booker (Martinsville), Charles A. Bower, E. Holmes Boyd, James O. Brooke, Joseph Bryan (Richmond), L.A. Buckingham (Childress Store), Joseph s. Budd, E.C. Cabell, E.C. (Richmond), George Cabell (Danville), John R. Chambliss, John M. Chapman, C. D. Christian (Lynchburg), John A. Coke (Richmond), Robert S. Craighill (Lynchburg), Richard H. Christian, R.A. Coghill (New Glasgow, Amherst County), F.M. Conner, Samuel Davies (Petersburg), James Davis, John B. Donovan (Mathews Courthouse), Gilbert Elliott, William Ellis, Thomas P. Fitzpatrick, J. Wesley Friend, John T. Garlick, George H. Gilmer (Pittsylvania Courthouse), John Gilmer, J.D. Godwin, E.P. Goggin (Lynchburg), John Goode, Jr. (Norfolk), William Gregory, Matthew Harrison, Luther D. Haymond, William Wirt Henry (Charles County Courthouse), Drury A. Hinton (Petersburg), Robert Howard (Richmond), Robert T. Hubard, Jr. t T., Jr. (Thurston, Buckingham County), George Hundley (Buckingham Courthouse), John Hunter, Jr. (Richmond), Eppa Hunton, Thomas G. Jackson, John Johns, Jr., Bradley T. Johnson, Otho G. Kean, Walter D. Leake (Goochland Courthouse), William J. Leake (Richmond), Francis Levitt,Jr., Richard Lillauny (?), R.H. Logan (Salem), Alfred Martin (Richmond), G. Martin (Norfolk), George A. Martin, George A., James M. Matthews (Richmond), Joseph Mayo, Jr., E.C. Moncure, E.B. Montague,(Shacklefords, King and Queen County), J.B. Mordecai (Richmond), R. T. Musick, L.C. Neale, J.G. Nelson (Fredericksburg), William W. Old, John Orr (?)(Loudoun), Richard G. Pegram, John E. Penn (Patrick Courthouse), James Pleasants (Richmond), H.R. Pollard, John W. Riely (Halifax Courthouse), Harrison Robertson, L.A. Sale (Liberty, Bedford County), John R. Scots, Jr. (Baltimore, Maryland), Robert Scott, Jr., M.B. Seawell (Gloucester County), John Lane Stern, Charles Stewart, Charles Stringellow, William a. Swartz (?), W.B. Tabb, William B. Taliaferro (Gloucester Courthouse), John E. Taylor (Richmond), H. Terry (Lynchburg), Lee Thomas, W.W. Walker, A.M. Wallace, C. Wistar Wallace, Thomas N. Welch, (Flippos, Caroline County), W. Winn, Frank V. Winston, and John S. Wise.</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals in Virginia, 1873-1875:
</p>
      <p>Stephen Adams (Lynchburg), John J. Allen (Waskeys Mills, Botetourt County), Robert H. Armistead (Williamsburg), William R. Aylett (Ayletts, King William County), R.b. Berkeley (Richmond), E.E. Bouldin (Danville), John M. Bouldin (Charlotte Courthouse), E.C. Burks (Liberty, Bedford County), F.W. Christian (Richmond), James Clarke (Manchester), J. Preston Cocke (Richmond), Charles F. Collins (Petersburg), Richard B. Davis (Petersburg), S.S. Dinwiddie (Tazewell Courthouse), B.J. Epes (Dinwiddie Courthouse), H.r. Farrar (Amelia County), J.P. Fitzgerald(Farmville), Lewis C. Fleming (Onancock, Accomack County), George B. Harrison (Richmond), Lewis Lee Henderson (Lunenburg), F.D. Irving (Farmville), John M. Johnson (Alexandria), B.W. Lacy (Tunstall Station), John A. Logan, (Halifax Courthouse), L.M. (or T.M.) Logan (Richmond), W.B. Martin (Norfolk), Julius J. Mason, John Neely (Accomack County), William H. Payne (Warrenton), E.P. Pitts (City of Norfolk), Edward D. Pitts (Norfolk), J. Benjamin South (or Sutton?) (Stafford Courthouse), Charles E. Stuart (Alexandria), R.T. Thorp (Boydton), Zeph. Turner (Woodville, Rappahanock County), George Walker (Richmond), Richard Walker (City of Norfolk), and H.T. Wickham (Richmond).</p>
      <p>List of attornreys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals in Virginia, 1876, circa:</p>
      <p>A.B. Chandler (Bowling Green), William T. Chandler (Bowling Green), N.T. Green (Halifax Couthouse), Alexander Hamilton (Petersburg), Powell Harrison (Leesburg), Wade Haskins (Richmond), Philip B. Hiden (Orange Courthouse), F.M. McMullan (Stanardsville), and Thomas Page (Richmond).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1877, circa:</p>
      <p>(first name illegible) Cleary (District of Columbia), Alexander Coke (Richmond), C.D. Fishburne (Charlottesville), Theodore S. Garnett, Jr.(Norfolk), Asa Gray (Fluvanna), Addison Holladay (Richmond), George McIntosh (Norfolk), S.C. Redd (Hanover County), Leigh Robinson (District of Columbia), Isaac Shields (Richmond), W.E. Sims (Chatham), James Walker (Madison Courthouse), S.G. Whittle (Henry Courthouse), E.B. Williams (Richmond), and T.R.B. Wright (Tappahannock).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1878-1888 (in chronological order, as they appear in the register):
</p>
      <p>Thomas W. Pierce, William Ellyson (Richmond), J.H.C. Jones (St. Stephens, King and Queen County), Richard N. Lee (Millwood), B.F. Bland (Saluda, Middlesex County), John B. Moon (Scottsville), Edgar Allen (Farmville), William R. Barksdale (Halifax Courthouse), John H. Dinnall (Richmond), C. Mason, F.D. Irving (Farmville), James Lyons, Jr.(Richmond), David L. Pulliam (Manchester), B.A. Hancock (Chesterfield County), Henry W. Hobson (Richmond), Beverly T. Crump (Richmond), F.H.M. McGuire (Richmond), John Martin (Danville), Henry Heaton (Leesburg), Howard R. Bayne (Richmond), Elisha E. Meredith (Brentsville, Prince William County), A.D. Payne (Warrenton), M.P. Burks (Liberty, Bedford County), Charles Stage (Richmond), Harvey Willson (Onancock, Accomack County), Tucker R. Warren (Richmond), Micajah Woods (Charlottesville), L.B. Cox (Cincinnati, Ohio), James Caskie (Richmond), William M. Walker (Montross, Westmoreland County), James L. Tredway (Chatham), J.W. Hudgin (Bowling Green), John W. Porter (Portsmouth), Johh Goode (Norfolk), W. Almond (Petersburg), Robert M. Newton (District of Columbia), Samuel G. Brent (Alexandria), Tazewell Ellett (Richmond), Graham Claytor (Liberty, Bedford County), William C. Roane (Richmond), William Gordon Robertson (Richmond), William W. Field (Richmond), Robert M. Hughes (Norfolk), Henry C. Coke (Richmond), Solomon L. Bloomberg (Richmond), H.E. Davis (District of Columbia), B.P. Noland (Middleburg), T.E. Conn (Weatherford, Texas), Richard Fuller Shryock (Charlottesville), Frank S. Blair (Wytheville), L.T. Hanckel (Charlottesville), Linden Kent (Alexandria), Thomas L. Brown (Charleston, West Virginia), B.D. Peachy (Williamsburg), Henry Harrison (Leesburg), J.M. Foster (Leesburg), Louis H. Powell (Leesburg), Edmund Burke (Alexandria), I.F. Hubbard (Yorktown), D.M. Bernard (Lawrencville, Brunswick County), G. Santini (Richmond), William P. De Saussure (Richmond), D.S. Hournshell (Richmond), John W. Ashby (Luray), Jackson Guy (Richmond), Richard M. Venable (Baltimore), Frank Clark (Baltimore), William H. Mann (Nottoway Courthouse), George J. Hooper, Jr. (Richmond), Thomas Smith homas (Warrenton), S. Patteson (Richmond), H. Taylor, Jr. (Richmond), William Hegenheuer (Richmond), Edward D. Minor (Henrico County), Willis B. Smith (Portsmouth), Odin G. Clay, Jr. (Richmond), T.F. Bayard (Wilmington, Delaware), J. Alston Cabell (Richmond), W.G. Elliott  (Norfolk), Arthur S. Segar (Hampton), W.T. Shields (Lexington), James O. Shepherd (Palmyra, Fluvanna County), W. Sydnor (Hanover County), H.R. Miller (Danville), Henry E. Bastian (Danville), P.B. Borst (Luray), J. Fitzpatrick (Chesterfield Courthouse), L.M. Fowler (Louisa Courthouse), B. Rand Wellford (Richmond), William McKierney (Westmoreland Courthouse), Wyndham R. Meredith (Richmond), James M. Ambler (Hanover County), R.H. Cardwell (Hanover Courthouse), W. Peek (Hampton), H.W. Smith, Jr., George Bryan (Richmond), L.D. Starke (Norfolk), 
Archibald Taylor (Baltimore), E.E. Nicol (Brentsville, Prince William County), Daniel Lewis (Manassas), Berryman Green (Danville), Langhorne Scruggs (Pittsylvania Courthouse), Cassius Carter (Fairfax Courthouse), John B. Brockenbrough (Liberty, Bedford County), R. Walton Moore (Fairfax), David H. Pannill (Chatham), W.P. Houston (Lexington), J.L. Hubbard (Nelson County), William Westham (Lexington), Guy H. Thompson (District of Columbia), William F. Atkins (Boydton), Angus M.D. Green (Culpeper), Landon C. Berkeley, Jr. (Danville), Charles W. Turner (Richmond), Robert E. Scott (Richmond), W.E. Bibb (Louisa Courthouse), J.S. Powell (Spotsylvania County), William O. Fry (Charlottesville), R. Douglas Wortham (Richmond), Thomas M. Miller (Manchester), H.G. Moffett, Jr. (Rappahannock County), W.E. Townes (Boydton), Frank E. Anderson (Richmond), Courtland H. Smith (Alexandria), T.N. Jones (Smithville, Charlotte County), John P. Pickett (Richmond), E.P. Phelps, W.W. Henry, Jr.(City of Roanoke), Robert McCandlish (Middlesex County), James E. Heath (Richmond), I. Brown Thompson (Arrington Depot, Nelson County), H.S. Menfee (Washington, Rappahannock County), Charles J. Everett (Utica, New York), Thomas Williams (Mecklenburg, West Virginia), Frank Gilmer (Charlottesville), Edmund Waddell (Richmond), W.L. Jeffries (Culpeper), J.L. Jeffries (Culpeper), W.W. Hubard (Buckingham Courthouse), J.J. Powell (Columbia, Fluvanna Courthouse), James F. Crocker (Portsmouth), C.W. Murdaugh (Portsmouth), W.W.H. Harris (Lynchburg), T.H. Hill (Madison Courthouse), James F. Epes (Nottoway County), Eppa Hunton, Jr. (Warrenton), James E. Heath (Norfolk), George A. Jones (Hanover County), John W. Haffner (Portsmouth), L.R. Watts (Portsmouth), W.B. Barton (Alexandria), William Stewart (Portsmouth), William B. Tinsley (Lynchburg), Leonidas D. Yarrell (Hicksford), Samuel Williams (Blount Courthouse, West Virginia?) 1883, Robert D. Yancey (Lynchburg), W.S. Holland (Isle of Wight County), L.M. Kean (Lynchburg), R. Deveraux Doyle (Norfolk), J.M. Gregory (Drewrys Bluff, Chesterfield), Allan C. Hill (Charles City County), James Lamb (Richmond), Issac H. Christiera (?), Page Morris Page (Lynchburg), J. Singleton Diggs (Lynchburg), William H. Sands (Richmond), Charles H. Carter (Ashland), G. Carlton Jackson (Richmond), J.O. Reddy (Richmond), William H. Dudley (Lynchburg), J.B. Johnston (Richmond), M.L. Spotswood (Richmond), Ben Gunter (Accomack Courthouse), R.T. Wilson (Petersburg), Arthur P. Thom (Norfolk), R.A. Ayers (Estilleville), James G. Holladay (Portsmouth), William D. Casell (Portsmouth), James Pollard (Baltimore), R.B. Seurs (District of Columbia), R.W. Peatross , R.W. (Danville), Charles H. Lee (District of Columbia), Richard B. Tunstall (Norfolk), T.R. Borland (Norfolk), I.I. Deures (Manassas), P. Virney (?) (Fauquier County), Rosewell Page (Danville), Frederick N. Fleming (Goochland Courthouse), Thomas G. Jones (Urbanna, Middlesex County), Edward Spalding (Norfolk), B.W. James (Goochland Courthouse), R.H. Rawles (Suffolk), R.H. Steger (Richmond), R.C. Marshall (Portsmouth), R.M. Dickinson (Farmville), A.A. Tunstall (Lynchburg), R. W. Watkins (Halifax Courthouse), A.B. Geldner (Norfolk), a.K. Leake (Goochland Courthouse), William Flanagan (Powhatan Courthouse), James P. Harrison (Danville), Geroge Perkins (Charlottesville), Samuel B. Woods (Charlottesville), (first name illegible) Rixey (Culpeper), Charles H. Sackett (Appomattox Courthouse), William Cosby, William, Jr. (Richmond), A.W. Armstrong (Alexandria), C.H. Causey (Suffolk), L.W. Marye (Richmond), William M. Peyton (Martinsville), A.M. Aiken (Danville), George T. Rison (Chatham), W.P. Dillard (Orange Courthouse), Edward Nicols (Leesburg), Graham Gordon (Baltimore), William A. Little, Jr. (Fredericksburg), James E. Edmunds (Lynchburg), C.C. Faulkner (Bergston), F.M. Whitehurst (Norfolk), William E. Ennis (Bowling Green), J. Samuel Parrish (Columbia, Fluvanna County), Thomas S. Martin (Scottsvillle), John Critcher, Jr. (Alexandria), Floyd Hughes (Norfolk), George A. Mushback (Alexandria), G.D. Wooton (District of Columbia), G. Harman (?) (District of Columbia), James Hay (Madison Courthouse), William F. Wickham (Richmond), W.T. Robins (Gloucester Courthouse), Carter K. Louthan (?) (Clarke County), Allen Watts (Roanoke), Edmund Pendleton (Richmond), Thomas P. Bagby (West Point), G.E. Caskie (Lovingston, Nelson County), Frank A. Massie (Charlottesville), R.O. Thomas (Stanardsville), Morgan H. Beach (Alexandria), James E. Clements (Alexandria), Edward R.D. Wayne (District of Columbia), Thomas Tabb (Hampton), A.b. Evans (Churchview), Robert B. Campbell (Warrenton), W.G.W. Farthing (Lightfoot, James City County), Beverley B. Munford (Chatham)), W.B. McIlwaine (?)(Petersburg), J.r. (surname illegible) (Richmond), R.S. Lacy (Talleysville, New Kent County), George W. Mayo (Richmond), John H. Greene (Alexandria), James Kerr (Norfolk), James W. Martin (Orange Courthouse), Robert Christy (District of Columbia), Thomas C. Croxton (Tappahannock), John G. Williams (Orange Courthouse), W.W. Burgess (Orange Courthouse), John B. Goode (Department of Justice, District of Columbia), William C. Preston (Richmond), John W. Bell (Culpeper), Charles P. Janney (Leesburg), Milton White, Jr. (Abingdon), John r. Moss (Buckingham Courthouse), William H. Innis (Petersburg), John Jackson (Richmond), A.W. Patterson (Richmond), J.M. Ricks (District of Columbia), B. Minor (District of Columbia), Matthew F. Maury (Richmond), Richard H. Gibbs (Leesburg), Charles Pollard (Leesburg), William Turpin (Richmond), Bernard Manns (Petersburg), George T. Garrison (Accomack Courthouse), Thomas H. Bayly Browne (Accomack Courthouse), Hugh C. Davis (Norfolk), Gordon, R.L. (Louisa Courthouse), F. Wilmer Sims (Louisa Courthouse), Abner H. Dickinson (Fredericksburg), Lloyd T. Smith (Heathsville), John G. Blackstone (Accomack Courthouse), Giles B. Jackson (Richmond), G. Hatton (Portsmouth), John Booker (Hampton), Samuel F. Coleman (Oak Forest), John O. Reynolds, John O. (Ashby), George Shackleford (Orange Courthouse), J. Fleshman, (Nebraska, Va.) (Appomattox), J.B. McCabe (Leesburg), Thomas Hughes (Baltimore), A. Merriman (District of Columbia), C. Whittle Sams (Norfolk), W.A. Jones (Warsaw), Charles H. Taylor (Kansas City, Kansas), W.W. Berry (Liberty, Bedford County), W.W. Moffett (District of Columbia), A.T. Holtzmann, (Washington, Rappahanock County), H.F. Woodhouse (Berkley, Norfolk County), George F. Parramore (Accomack Courthouse), James Reeves Lassiter (Petersburg), Claude A. Swanson (Chatham), W.T. Harris (Danville), W.W. Hardaway (Martinsville), R.B. Brown (Petersburg), A.D. Smith, Jr. (District of Columbia), R. Washington, R. (Oak Grove, Westmoreland County), Overton Howard (Richmond), A. Waller (District of Columbia), and L. Bristow (Saluda, Middlesex County)
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in December 1888:</p>
      <p>Walter Addison (Richmond), James R. Caton (Alexandria), Thomas Temple Powell (Richmond), Edmund S. Ruffin (Norfolk), and John H. Wright,  (Suffolk).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys taking the oath to pracitice in the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1889:</p>
      <p>L.B. Allen (Norfolk), R.G. Bickford (Newport News), Thomas E. Blakey (Tappahannock), Watson Boyle (District of Columbia), E.B. Brown  (Hampton), E.P. Buford (Lawrenceville), John C. Bullitt (Philadelphia), Charles Caldwell (Warrenton), William Calvin Chase (District of Columbia), Joseph S. Clark (Philadelphia), N.B. Clark (Newport News), J.J. Cocke (Petersburg), Charles E. Foster (District of Columbia), James H. Hayes (Richmond), John W. Helbig (Richmond), Robert W. Hunter (Winchester), Richard W. Johnston (Arlington), Joseph Leedom (?)  (Philadelphia), William H. Lyons (Richmond), Leonard Turner Mauxy (University of Virginia), H. Gordon McCinch (Philadelphia), John H. McGraw (Richmond), James M. McMullen (Petersburg), William P. McRae (Petersburg), A.J. Montague (Danville), Hosea B. Moulton (District of Columbia), J. Norton (Alexandria), Eston Randolph (Danville), John Rutherford (Richmond), E. Beverly Slater (Richmond), John N. Staples  (Greensboro, North Carolina), Charles D. Swett (District of Columbia), and L. Wendenburg (Richmond).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1890:
</p>
      <p>J. Wesley Avery (Alexandria), A.H. Burroughs (Lynchburg), John W. Carter (Martinsville), W.D. Dabney (Charlottesville), J.M. Dayton (Petersburg), Isaac Diggs (West Point), A.C. Drunisfore (?) (Philadelphia), W.E. Garrett (Leesburg), Roger Gregory (Lester Manor, Virginia), C. Kowaslav (?) (Berryville), J.E. Mann (King George County), N.C. Manson, Jr. (Lynchburg), George Mason (Petersburg), Samuel McCue (Charlottesville), J.M. McDougal (Lynchburg), William A. Moncure (Richmond), Robert L. Montague (Richmond), G. Hartley Norton (District of Columbia), Conway R. Sands (Richmond), R.W. Scott (Richmond), Edwin B. Shawnasee (?) (Richmond), R.E. Thornton (District of Columbia), R. Turnbull (Lawrenceville), and Hugh S. White (Martinsburg, West Virginia).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1891:
</p>
      <p>John H. Alexander (Leesburg), W.H. Beveridge (Richmond), Patrick J. Brennan (District of Columbia), William E. Burnes (Lebanon, Virginia), Charles C. Clokey (District of Columbia), T.T. Cockrell (Reedville), William B. Coles (Richmond), G.M. Dillard (Norfolk), John C. Foster (Newark, New Jersey), Robert Grasty (District of Columbia), Randolph Harrison (Lynchburg), Addison Haythe (Buena Vista), L.L. Kelley (Richmond), Wilbur J. Kilby (Suffolk), Julian Lewis (District of Columbia), Robert W. Mallert (?) (Norfolk), Bellum Miller (District of Columbia), H.L. Newbill (Essex County), Howard P. Okie (District of Columbia), W.N. Portlocke (Norfolk), Charles H. Rauman, (Alexandria), A.B. Rawlings (Spotsylvania Courthouse), R.G. Southall (Amelia Courthouse), Walter F. Taylor (District of Columbia), and Hank C. Townsend (Alexandria).
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1892:
</p>
      <p>Frank S. Appleman (District of Columbia), Richard B. Ayer (District of Columbia), Strode Barton (Culpeper), M.K. Chamblin (?) (District of Columbia), T.K. deGraffenried (Atlanta, GA), J.H. Deploe (Richmond), T.H. Edwards (West Point), R.R. Fauntleroy (Richmond), W.A. Fentress (Portsmouth), G.W. Fitzgerald (District of Columbia), A.D. Flood (Appomattox Courthouse), W.C. Franklin (Pamplin City, Virginia), J.B. Gunn (Richmond), B. Lacy Hoge (Roanoke), Mateo H. Jeffer (District of Columbia), J.P. Jeffries (Warrenton), H. Lewis (West Point), William M. McCallister (Warm Springs), J.B. McGirr (District of Columbia), J.F. McNabb (District of Columbia), Julian Meade  (Danville), R.H. Merchant (Lynchburg), Ralph C. Minor (Richmond), C.L. Munson (West Point), J.P. OBrien (District of Columbia), D.C. Richardson (Richmond), J. Edgar Smith (District of Columbia), C.M. White (Warrenton), Westel Willoughby (District of Columbia), and R.W. Winborne (Buena Vista).
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1893:</p>
      <p>B.S. Barret (Richmond), W.R. Booker (Richmond), Wallace Brown (Richmond), P.H.C. Cabell (Richmond), W.D. Cardwell (Richmond), Louis Cuvillier (Alexandria), Will W. Douglas (District of Columbia), T.C. Gordon (Richmond), Newton B. Gorham (Richmond), W.H. Graveley  (Martinsville), Charles D. Hine (Vienna, Fairfax County), W.M. Justis, Jr. (Richmond), R.T. Irvine (Big Stone Gap), Walter Manly (District of Columbia), Leonard Marbury (Alexandria), Eugene C. Massie (Richmond), Chapman W. Maupin (Bedford), George H. Maxwell (District of Columbia), A.R. Monteiro (Goochland County), C.L. Munson (West Point), John H. Nelson (Leesburg), Willoughy Newton,Jr. (Richmond), J.D. Smith (Roanoke), P.A.L. Smith (Richmond), Z.P. Smith (Culpeper), and George Copping Warner (University Station, Charlottesville).
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1894:</p>
      <p>George Ainslee (Richmond), William P. Barksdale (Houston, Virginia), Bentley Bleamsbed (?) (Amherst), Gardner L. Boothe (Alexandria), P. Bouldin, Sr. (Stuart), J.W. D. Brady (Petersburg), C.C. Carlin (Alexandria), A.E. Chalmers (Richmond), Alfred Cohen (Richmond), Malcolm Argyle Coles (Northumberland County), Alden March Collins (Fairfax Courthouse), James J. Corridan (District of Columbia), Edwin P. Cox (Richmond), Abram C. Eby (Richmond), W.A. Farmer (Richmond), John M. George (District of Columbia), Daniel Grinnan (Richmond), Howard Hathaway (White Stone), J. Jordan Leake (Richmond), John L. Lee (Amherst), Lee Lindsey (Norfolk County), Robert Marye (Richmond), George A. Melvin (Portsmouth), Cornelius Mimms (Chesterfield County), John Garland Pollard (Richmond), J. Breckenridge Robertson (Charlottesville), Beverley T. Sewer (Charlottesville), E.B. Taylor (Alexandria), C.W. Throckmorton (Danville), Charles M. Waite  (Culpeper), William Leigh Williams (Norfolk), and Eugene Withers (Danville).</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1895:</p>
      <p>Archer Anderson, Jr.(Richmond), P. St. George Barraud (Richmond), William W. Barrow (Richmond), E. Boggs (Atlanta, Georgia), William Brinnan (?)(Fincastle), Irving E. Campbell (Richmond), James E. Cannon (Richmond), Edgar Carrington (Richmond), George D. Carter (Henrico County), C.H. Causey, Jr. (Suffolk), W.L. Clark (Winchester), Walter A. Dunn (Richmond), Charles W. Dunstan (Richmond), William N. Fisher (District of Columbia), H.W. Flournoy (Richmond), W.H. Garnett (Manchester), S. Hamilton Graves (Roanoke), James W. Green (Culpeper), N.T. Greene (Danville), Raleigh Gunn (Richmond), R. Randolph Hicks (Roanoke), Volney E. Howard (Lynchburg), E. Hilton Jackson (District of Columbia), Claggett B. Jones (Bruington, King and Queen County), F. Kirkpatrick (Lynchburg), Benjamin Watkins Leigh (Houston, Virginia), W.H.T. Lyall (Norfolk), Laurence T. McCormick (Berryville), John B. Minor (Richmond), Kirkwood Mitchell (Richmond), Hill Montague (Richmond), George W. Morris (Charlottesville), John J. Murphey (District of Columbia), John Adair Pleasants (Richmond), Allen Potts (Richmond), John P. Pryor (Alexandria), Samuel Regester (Richmond), Edward W. Robertson (Roanoke), Walter H. Ryland (Richmond), William Skelton (Richmond), Walter H. Taylor (Norfolk), John G. Tilton (Norfolk), Littleton W. Waller (Norfolk), Edmund Williams (Richmond) and George E. Wise (Richmond).
</p>
      <p>List of attorneys signing the oath to practice in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1896:</p>
      <p>J.C. Asbury (Norfolk), Edward R. Baldwin (Norfolk), J. Warren Booker (Richmond), Hunsdon (?) Cary (Richmond), J. Edward Cole  (Norfolk), Allen Collins (Richmond), Frederick Cox (District of Columbia), Frederick L. Davidson (Richmond), Marion L. Dawson (Richmond), William Fendall, Lewis H. Finney, Jr. (District of Columbia), R.C. Florance (Richmond), Minstres (?) Folkes (Richmond), James W. Gordon  (Richmond), Charles B. Glenn (Richmond), Harrcy C. Glenn (Richmond), John E. Heath, Jr. (Norfolk), James H. Hitchen, Jr. (Accomack Court House), A.A. Hochling, Jr. (District of Columbia), Thomas F. Keith (Fairfax Courthouse), William B. King (District of Columbia), James Mann (Nottoway Courthouse), M.M. Martin (Richmond), Thomas McDougall (Cincinnati, Ohio), C.F. McMullan (Madison Courthouse), Warren H. Mercer (Richmond), Bernard L. Metruck (?) (Baltimore), P. Morris (Norfolk), W.G. Pilkinton (Powhatan County), Robert Ramsey (Cincinnati, Ohio), W.A. Ross (Norfolk), William W. Smith (Cumberland Courthouse), E.J. Spade (Eastville), Minton W. Talbot (Norfolk), C.H. Vines (Roanoke), George R. Wales (District of Columbia), Charles M. Wallace, Jr. (Richmond), A.E. Warren (Portsmouth), Asa D. Watkins (Farmville), Jeremiah M. Wilson (District of Columbia), G.D. Wingo (?) (Green Bay, Virginia), and W.W. Woodward (Saluda).
</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
