<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00025.xml">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00025.xml::A Guide to the Video Recordings of Court Ceremonies, 2003-2011)//EN" "vil00025.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to Video Recordings of Court Ceremonies, <date>2003-2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Video Recordings of Court Ceremonies, 2003-2011 
<num type="collectionnumber">00030367, 00030295
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2013 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, <date>11 March 2013</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to Video Recordings of Court Ceremonies, <date>2003-2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">00030367, 00030295
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2013
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library staff.
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Video recordings of court ceremonies
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2003-2011
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">00030367, 00030295.
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">16 video recordings; transcripts of some recordings are available.   
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Supreme Court.</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Video Recordings of Court Ceremonies, 2003-2011, Accession 00030367, 00030295, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records were transferred from the Office of the Executive Secretary to the Virginia State Law Library, 2005-2011 (accession 00030367); and the Education Department in May 2012 (accession 00030295). 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Original recordings on VHS, DVD, and miniDV cassettes. Recordings were converted to MP4 format in 2012 for preservation and access. The recording of Justice Agee's investiture was transferred from VHS to digital mov and mp4 formats in 2013.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the new General Assembly in 1779. Its jurisdiction was primarily appellate, and its members were elected by the legislature. The Constitution of 1971 changed the name of the court to its present title of Supreme Court of Virginia.
</p>
<p>Justices are elected by a majority vote of both houses of the General Assembly for a term of twelve years. Vacancies on the court occurring between sessions of the General Assembly may be filled by the Governor for a term expiring thirty days after the commencement of the next session of the General Assembly. By statute, the Chief Justice is chosen by a majority vote of the seven justices.</p>
<p>By statute, the court may designate a retired justice to serve as Senior Justice for a renewable one year term. Senior justices sit with the court during regular sessions hearing writs and sitting on merit cases, especially when an active member of the court is recused from hearing a particular case.</p>
<p>Steven Agee (born 1952) served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 2003 to 2008, when he was appointed to the  U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Previously, he was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia (2001 to 2003) and in the General Assembly from 1982-1994.  
</p>
<p>Robert N. Baldwin was Executive Secretary for the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1976 to 2005.</p>
<p>David Beach was Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1984 to 2003.</p> 
<p>Harry L. Carrico (1916-2013) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1961 to 2003 and was chief justice from 1981 to 2003. He took senior status in 2003.</p>
<p>A. Christian Compton (1929-2006) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1975 to 2000.</p>
<p>S. Bernard Goodwyn (born 1961) has served on the Supreme Court of Virginia since 2007. 
</p>
<p>Leroy Rountree Hassell, Jr., (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011.  He was elected to a four-year term as chief justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007. He was the first African American to serve as chief justice.  
</p>
<p>Barbara M. Keenan (born 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1991 to 2010, when she was confirmed as a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. She was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1991. She was the first woman to serve as an appellate court judge in Virginia.</p>
<p>Cynthia Fannon Kinser (born 1951) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997. She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2010. She is the first woman to serve as chief justice.</p> 
<p>Larkins L. Koontz, Jr. (born 1940) served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 1995 to 2011, when he took senior status.  He was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1995.</p>
<p>Elizabeth B. Lacy (born 1945) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1988 to 2007, when she took senior status.  She was the first woman to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>
<p>Kathy Mays was Director of Judicial Planning, Office of the Executive Secretary, from 1982 to 2005. 
</p>
<p>Elizabeth A. McClanahan (born 1959) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 2011. Before that, she was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia (2003-2011).
</p>  
<p>Charles S. Russell (born 1926) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1991. He returned to the court as a senior justice in 2004.</p>
<p>Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997.</p>
<p>John Charles Thomas (born 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1983 to 1989. He was the youngest person appointed to the court (32) and the first African American to serve on the court.</p> 
</bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains 16 video recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia ceremonies, 2003-2011. The ceremonies took place in the courtoom in Richmond, unless otherwise noted.</p>
<p>Investitures and swearing-in ceremonies, 2003-2011:</p>
<p>Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, recorded at Roanoke College in Salem, Va., 2003 Mar. 5 (1 hour, 5 minutes, and 35 seconds). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by State Senator Charles Hawkins, Delegate Robert McDonnell, Attorney General Jerry Kilgore, Delegate Lacy Putney, and Justice Agee.</p>
<p>Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as chief justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 Feb. 11 (45 seconds), with Justice Barbara M. Keenan administering the oath of office and Chief Justice Hassell's wife, Linda Hassell, holding the Bible.</p>
<p>Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2007 Oct. 10 (12 minutes, 28 seconds), with Chief Justice Hassell administering the oath of office to Goodwyn, who is accompanied by his wife, Sharon Smith Goodwyn, and his two children.  Brief remarks by Chief Justice Hassell, and greetings from Senior Justices Elizabeth Lacy and Charles Russell, Executive Secretary Karl Hade, and Patricia Harrington, Clerk.</p>
<p>Investiture of Chief Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser (47 minutes). Justice Donald W. Lemons, presiding; remarks by Governor Robert R. McDonnell, Senior Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, and Chief Justice Kinser. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 281 Virginia Reports, xi-xxiv.</p>
<p>Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 Sep. 1 (46 minutes, 28 seconds). Chief Justice Cynthia Kinser, presiding; invocation, Reverend Betty C. Reiff; remarks, Retired Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna L. Fitzpatrick; Senator  William C. Wampler, Jr., Delegate Terry G. Kilgore, Governor Robert F. McDonnell, former Attorney General Jerry W. Kilgore, Hon. Joseph P. Johnson, Jr.; benediction, Reverend Walter P. Weikel.</p>
<p>Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 Oct. 21. Chief Justice Kinser, presiding; invocation, Reverend Shirley Powell Layton; remarks by Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, Walter S. Felton, Jr.; Reverend Grady Wilson Powell, Sr., Irving M. Blank, Past President, Virginia State Bar; Senator John C. Watkins, Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Richmond Mayor Dwight C. Jones, Senator A. Donald McEachin, and Justice Powell.</p>
<p>Portrait presentation ceremonies, 2006 and 2011:</p>     
<p>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell, 2006 Feb. 28 (26 minutes, 8 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, presiding. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix-xii.</p>
<p>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring John Charles Thomas, Elizabeth B. Lacy, Barbara M. Keenan, Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., and G. Steven Agee, 2011 Nov. 2. Chief Justice Kinser, presiding; remarks by Kinser and each of the honorees. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 282 Virginia Reports, 1iii-1xvii.</p>
<p>Court ceremonies, 2004 and 2006:</p>
<p>Ceremony commemorating the 225 anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2004 De. 9 (41 minutes, 48 seconds). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Mark Warner, Lieutenant Governor Timothy Kaine, Attorney General Jerry Kilgore, Senator Kenneth Stolle, Chair, Courts of Justice Committee; Speaker of the House J. Morgan Griffith, President of the Virginia State Bar David B. Bobzien, and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>
<p>Ceremony commemorating the 230 anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution, 2006 Nov. 2 (46 minutes, 35 seconds). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Lieutenant Governor William Bolling, Attorney General Robert McDonnell, Speaker of the House of Delegates William Howell, President of the Senate John H. Chichester, Senator Benjamin Lambert, Karen A. Gould, president of the Virginia State Bar, Governor Tim Kaine, and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>
<p>Interview with Chief Justice Hassell by Barbara Berlin for the program Perspective, produced by the Community Idea Stations, Richmond, Virginia, and originally airing 2006 Nov. 24 (27 minutes, 14 seconds; produced by Craig Keeton, Community Idea Stations, Richmond.)  Berlin interviews Hassell about the 230 anniversary of the enactment of the Virginia Constitution and includes video clips of the commemorative ceremony, 2006 Nov. 2.</p>   
 
<p>Retirement ceremonies, 2003-2005, 2011:</p>       
<p>Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 2003 Jan. 1 (43 minutes, 18 seconds). Poor quality video recording. Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, presiding; remarks by Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary; and Justice Donald W. Lemons; presentation of slideshow with photographs of family and court staff.</p>
<p>Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 Jun. 1 (47 minutes, 19 seconds). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Senior Justice Harry L. Carrico, U.S. District Court Judge John A. Gibney, Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, Trish Harrington, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia; Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary; and David Beach.</p>
<p>Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2005 Mar. 24 (1 hour, 11 minutes, 51 seconds). Chief  Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Bill Howell, Speaker of the House of Delegates; Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna Fitzpatrick;  James Ullman, former chair, House Courts Committee; Retired Judge J.R. Zepkin, Judge Phillip Trompeter, and Larry Palmer, Clerk, Lynchburg Circuit Court.</p>
<p>Retirement ceremony honoring Kathy Mays, Director, Judicial Planning, Office of the Executive Secretary, Richmond, 2005 Mar. 31 (1 hour, 45 minutes, 16 seconds). Executive Secretary Robert N. Baldwin, presiding; remarks by Chief Justice Hassell, Susan Clarke Schaar, Clerk, Senate of Virginia; Mary McQueen, president, National Center for State Courts; Philip V. Anderson, President, Virginia State Bar; Court of Appeals Judge James W. Benton, Judge William Alexander, Lelia Hopper, Kathy Mays, and others.</p>   
<p>Ceremony honoring Senior Justice Harry L. Carrico for 50 Years of Service, 2011 Jan. 11 (9 minutes, 57 seconds). Remarks by Senior Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr. and Senior Justice Carrico (audio of Senior Justice Koontz is barely audible).</p>  
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>
