<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00006">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Virginia State Law Library::Supreme Court of Virginia Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00006::A Guide to the Abner W. C. Terry correspondence about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., 1842-1851)//EN" "vil00006.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Abner W. C. Terry correspondence about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., <date>1842-1851</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Terry correspondence about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrator, etc., 1842-1851  
<num type="collectionnumber">0001111
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>22 February 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Abner W.C. Terry correspondence about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc.,<date>1842-1851</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Number">0001111
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine G. OBrion
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library. </repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Abner W. C. Terry correspondence about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc.,   
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1842-1851
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0001111
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">9 items   
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Terry, Abner Wentworth Clopton (1815-1851)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Abner W. C. Terry correspondence regarding Colombian College v. Abner W. Clopton's Administrators etc., 1842-1851, Accession #0001111, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The letters were acquired by the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives in February 2012.</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Abner W. Clopton (1784-1833) was a Baptist minister in Charlotte County.  In 1827, Clopton was appointed Georgia state fund-raising agent for Colombian College (later George Washington University), founded by Baptist missionary Luther Rice and chartered in 1821.  Due to his success in raising funds for the financially strapped college, Clopton was appointed to its Board of Trustees in 1829 and general agent in 1832.  After Clopton's death, Colombian College sued in chancery court in Charlotte County, Virginia, to recover a conditional bequest to the college included in Clopton's will.  The court ruled against the college in 1843, and Court of Appeals upheld the decision in 1850.  
</p>
 <p>Abner Wentworth Clopton Terry (1815-1851) was the son of Daniel Terry, one of Clopton's executors, and the grandson of Abner W. Clopton.  The other executors named in the will were Archibald A. Davis and John W. Roach. Terry died suddenly in June 1851.  He was killed by James D. Saunders, who also died in the confrontation.  Saunders was angry about an editorial printed in the Lynchburg Virginian newspaper (Terry was a publisher of the newspaper).</p>
<p>Conway Robinson was a legal scholar and Virginia Court of Appeals court reporter in 1842 and 1843. Between 1846 and 1849, he and acting Governor John M. Patton worked on revisions to the Code of Virginia. The revisions, adopted by the General Assembly in 1849, remained in use for nearly forty years.</p>  
<p>Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849) was a Richmond lawyer and politician.  He prepared the 1819 revised code of Virginia and was a court reporter for the Court of Appeals from 1829 to 1841.</p>
<p>James Wood Bouldin (1792-1854) was a lawyer who practiced at Charlotte County Courthouse beginning in 1813.  He represented Colombian College in the chancery suit against Clopton's administrators.</p>   
</bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection consists of six letters to Abner C.W. Terry, a copy of a letter from Terry to Conway Robinson, about the court case, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., upheld by the Virginia Court of Appeals in December 1850. ; and a manuscript copy of bill of complaint, undated, from a Pittsylvania County chancery cause (Administrator of Nancy Waldr
on v. Administrator of Daniel Terry, etc.), seeking distribution of the Clopton legacy to his nieces and nephews.  The court document includes genealogical information about the nieces and nephews, their spouses, and their children.</p>
<p>The first letter, dated 1842 Mar. 28, is from Archibald A. Davis, one of the executors named in Clopton's will, discussing the status o the estate and the claim against it by Colobmian College. The second letter, dated 1843 Apr 24, is from Wood Bouldin, attorney for Colombian College in the Charlotte County chancery cause, giving notice to Terry about depositions taken in Washington, D.C. "to prove compliance with the conditions of the bond and will." The third letter, dated 1843 Dec. 10, is from Richmond attorney Benjamin Watkins Leigh offering his services and those of Conway Robinson to Terry should the Colombian College case come before the Court of Appeals.</p>
<p>There are two letters from attorney Conway Robinson about the legal issues in the case Conway Robinson, and one letter from Terry to Robinson.  On 1844 June 29, Terry wrote Robinson seeking his opinion about the ultimate disposition of the bequest to the college, noting he had heard that Judge Lee's opinion in the Charlotte County in his favor was "a very ingenious one."  On 1844 Jul. 18, Robinson wrote to Terry advising him that the college has obtained an appeal of the Charlotte County case and confirming that he and Leigh would serve as counsel for the appellees. Robinson wrote about possible arguments for the case and cited legal precedents he had used successfully before the court in other cases.  On 1851 Apr. 15, after the Court of Appeals upheld the lower court decision in favor of Clopton's administrators, Robinson wrote Terry acknowledging receipt of his fee and advising him about the best way to resolve the distirubtion of the Clopton legacy among the three remaining interests:  the nieces and nephews named in the will, Newton Institute, a Baptist instituion in Massachusetts; or the next of kin.  He suggests the best way to resolve the issue woudl be to have one interest file suit against the other two interests. The last two items in the collection are a letter from  John M. Waldron to Terry, 1851 Mar. 19, advising that he is seeking his mother's portion of the Clopton legacy denied by the Court of Appeals to Colobmian College, and a manuscript copy of a bill of complaint filled in Pittyslvania County chancery court by Waldron, 1851, circa.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Jewel L. Spangler, "Clopton, Abner Wentworth," in Sara B. Bearss, ed., Dictionary of Virginia Biography Vol. 3 (2006), 305.</bibref>
</bibliography>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Charlotte County Chancery Cause, Colombian College v. Administrator of Abner W. Clopton, etc., Charlotte County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1765-1912 (bulk 1784-1912), 1843-004. Local Government Records Collection, Charlotte County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.  The court case has been digitized and is available through the Library of Virginia's digital collections portal, Virginia Memory.  The case documents include a bill of complaint, answers from Terry and Archibald Davis, depositions from Colombian College Trustee James Wood, Trustee and College Treasurer Andrew Rothwell, James L. Edwards, President of the Board of Trustees, and copies of the act incorporating Colombian College charter, and a copy of Clopton's bond to the college.</p>
<p>Virginia Court of Appeals opinion, Colombian College v. Clopton's Administrators, etc., Virginia Reports, Vol.VII (1850), 169-177.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Persons:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Bouldin, James Wood (1792-1854).</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Clopton, Abner Wentworth (1784-1833).</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Davis, Archibald A.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Leigh, Benjamin Watkins (1781-1849).</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Robinson, Conway.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Waldron, John M.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Colombian College (Washington, D.C.)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia. Court of Appeals.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Baptists -- clergy -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (law) -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Virginia -- Lawyers.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Charlotte County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Legal correspondence -- Virginia.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
