<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/scv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/scv_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vil00008">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViL">PUBLIC "-//Supreme Court of Virginia Archives::Virginia State Law Library Archives//TEXT (US::ViL::vil00008::A Guide to the Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews, 2009)//EN" "vil00008.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews, <date>2009</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews 
<num type="collectionnumber">00020373
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169;2012 By The Virginia State Law Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>13 March 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews, <date>2009</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
<num type="Accession Numbers">00020373, 00022067
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine G. OBrion
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews,   
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2009 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">00020373, 00022067</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">2 mini video cassettes (DV camera) 4 hours, 12 min., sound, color; and 2 transcripts (106 p.)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Oral history interviews of two judges who served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia. Oral history interviews were conducted by Cassandra Newby-Alexander, Professor of History, Norfolk State University, for the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission. Interviews were conducted with the following: retired Court of Appeals Judge James W. Benton, Jr., at the Supreme Court of Virginia; and retired Court of Appeals Judge Johanna L. Fitzpatrick, at her home in Alexandria. Transcripts available.</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.   
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Because the library is not open to the general public, researchers should contact the library to arrange access to the collection.  
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Court of Appeals of Virginia oral history interviews, 2009, Accession numbers 00020372 and 00022067, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The interviews were created for the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives by the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission in 2009.   
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Court of Appeals of Virginia was established January 1, 1985. It provides appellate review of final decisions of the circuit courts in
domestic relations matters, appeals from decisions of an administrative agency, traffic infractions and
criminal cases, except where a sentence of death has been imposed. It also hears appeals of final decisions
of the Virginia Workers' Compensation Commission. Except in those cases where the decision of
the Court of Appeals is final, any party aggrieved by a decision of the Court of Appeals may petition the Supreme Court for an appeal.
The Court of Appeals consists of eleven judges. The court sits in panels of at least three judges, and the membership of the panels is rotated. The court sits at such locations as the chief judge designates, so as to provide convenient access to the various geographic areas of the Commonwealth.</p>
<p>James W. Benton, Jr. (b. 1944) was appointed to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1985 and retired in 2007. A native of Norfolk, Benton attended public schools there and participated in civil rights demonstrations while he was in high school.  He earned an undergraduate degree from Temple University in Boston and a law degree from the University of Virginia.  He worked as an intern for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund in Richmond, at the law firm of Hill, Tucker Marsh, and continued practicing law there for 15 years, trying school desegregation cases as well as housing discrimination and business cases.</p>
<p>Judge Johanna L. Fitzpatrick (b. 1946) served on the Virginia Court of Appeals from 1992 to 2006. A native of Birmingham, Alabama, she attended Tufts University in Botson and earned a law degree from Catholic University in Washington, D.C.  She began working for Fairfax Legal Aid Society in 1974.  In 1980, she was elected Juvenile and Domestic Relations judge in Fairfax County, making her the second woman elected judge in Virginia.  In 1982, Fitzpatrick was elected circuit court judge in Fairfax County.  
</p>
<p>The Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission was established in 2006 to preserve and promote the history of the court.  Oral history interviews of retired Supreme Court justices, Court of Appeals judges, other individuals associated with the court, and civil rights attorneys were begun in 2007.  The project is ongoing.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>In the interview of Judge James W. Benton, Jr., conducted March 12, 2009 (2 hours, 12 minutes; transcript available), Benton discusses growing up in the Huntersville neighborhood of Norfolk Va., attending segregated schools, participating in sit-in protests to desegregate public facilities, and being among the first African Americans to attend a formerly white high school in Norfolk.  He talks about attending Temple University in Philadelphia, graduate school in Northwestern University in Chicago, and law school at the University of Virginia in the late 1960s and experience of being one of the first African Americans to attend the law school. He relates his experiences working as an attorney for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund at the Richmond law firm Hill, Tucker, Marsh in Richmond; his work on the Norfolk school desegregation court cases, and his work on business cases and housing discrimination cases in the 1970s and 1980s. Benton also talks about the circumstances leading to his appointment on the Court of Appeals of Virginia when it was established in 1985, the work of establishing the court, his approach to his role as a judge, his thoughts about writing dissenting opinions, and his views on constitutional rights and criminal cases.  
</p>
<p>In the interview of Judge Johanna Levenson Fitzpatrick, conducted July 13, 2009 (2 hours; transcript available), Judge Fitzpatrick talks about growing up in Birmingham, Alabama, being Jewish, and her father's department store in downtown Birmingham; her education at Tufts University in Boston and Catholic University Law School in Washington, D.C., working as a legal-aid lawyer and on revisions to the code on neglect and abuse of children; and her work as a Juvenile and Domestic Relations judge and a circuit court judge in Fairfax County. She talks about breaking down gender barriers as a judge in Virginia, and her appointment to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1992; choosing and mentoring law clerks, the process of writing opinions, differences between working as a trial judge and an appellate judge, her decision to retire in 2006, and her subsequent career as a mediator.    
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Benton, James W., 1944-.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Fitzpatrick, Johanna Levenson, 1946-.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hill, Oliver White, 1907-2007.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Hoffman, Walter Edward, 1907-1996.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Marsh, Henry L., 1933-.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Newby-Alexander, Cassandra, 1956-.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Tucker, Samuel Wilbert, 1913-1990.</persname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia -- Court of Appeals -- History.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Virginia -- Supreme Court -- Historical Commission.</corpname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African American civil rights workers -- Interviews.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African American lawyers -- Interviews.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Civil rights -- United States -- History -- 20th century.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Domestic relations court -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Juvenile court -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Minorities -- Civil rights -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Segregation in education -- Virginia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women lawyers -- Interviews.</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Birmingham (Al.) -- History -- 20th century.</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Norfolk (Va.) -- History -- 20th century.</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Richmond (Va.) -- History -- 20th century.</geogname>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Oral histories (document genre) -- Virginia.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
