<?xml version="1.0" encoding="WINDOWS-1252"?>

<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viro00023">


<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">

<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Viro">PUBLIC "-//Roanoke Public Libraries//TEXT (US::viro::viro00023::A Guide to the Papers of Ora Belle Mayberry McColman//EN" "viro00023.xml" </eadid>


<filedesc>


<titlestmt>


<titleproper>
A Guide to the Papers of Ora Belle Mayberry McColman  
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> </date>

</titleproper>


<subtitle id="sort">
Ora Belle Mayberry McColman, A Guide to the Papers of
<num type="collectionnumber">2009.2.13 </num>

</subtitle>

</titlestmt>


<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Roanoke Public Libraries </publisher>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/rpl_address.xi.xml"/>

<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="publication">Â© 2014 By the Roanoke Public Libraries. All rights reserved. </date>


<p id="usestatement">

<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Conditions of Use </extref>

</p>

</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>


<creation>
Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Dyron Knick. 
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 December 2014</date>

</creation>


<langusage>
Description is in 
<language langcode="eng">English </language>

</langusage>

</profiledesc>


<revisiondesc>


<change>

<date normal="20140904">20141219</date>

<item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>

</change>

</revisiondesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>


<titlepage>


<titleproper>
A Guide to the Papers of Ora Belle Mayberry McColman
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> </date>

</titleproper>


<subtitle>
A Collection in 
<lb/>
Roanoke Public Libraries 
<num type="Accession Number">2009.2.13 </num>

</subtitle>


<p id="logostmt">

<extptr xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/RPLlogo.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"/>

</p>

<publisher>Roanoke Public Libraries </publisher>

<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="publication">2014 </date>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/rpl_contact.xi.xml"/>


<list type="deflist">


<defitem>

<label>Processed by: </label>

<item>Special Collections Staff </item>

</defitem>

</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>


<archdesc level="collection">

<runner placement="footer">Roanoke Public Libraries </runner>


<did>

<head>Descriptive Summary </head>

<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Roanoke Public Libraries </repository>

<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">A Guide to the Papers of Ora Belle Mayberry McColman </unittitle>

<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2009.2.13 </unitid>

<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 letter size document storage box </physdesc>


<langmaterial label="Language">

<language langcode="eng">English </language>

</langmaterial>

</did>


<descgrp type="admininfo">

<head>Administrative Information </head>


<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">

<head>Access Restrictions </head>

<p>There are no restrictions. </p>

</accessrestrict>


<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">

<head>Use Restrictions </head>

<p>There are no restrictions. </p>

</userestrict>


<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">

<head>Preferred Citation </head>

<p>Papers of Ora Belle Mayberry McColman, Accession #2009.2.13, Roanoke Public Libraries, Roanoke, VA </p>

</prefercite>


<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">

<head>Acquisition Information </head>

<p>Donated by Sunny Hubble</p>

</acqinfo>

</descgrp>


<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">

<head>Biographical Note </head>

<p>Ora Belle Mayberry McColman was born December 4, 1917 to Harvey E. and Emma Florence Mayberry on a farm in Snowville area of Montgomery County, VA. Growing up during the Depression era, McColman was one of 16 students to graduate from Auburn High School in Riner, VA. After graduation from high school, Ora Belle attended Virginia Tech for two years. Her father became ill and she had to drop out of school. When she returned to school, she graduated from National Business College in Roanoke, VA.	McColman married Belton F. McColman, Jr. July 3, 1942 and lived in Covington, VA for 10 years where she worked as a secretary to the office manager of the West Virginia Pulp and Paper Company. 
In 1952, she moved with her husband to Roanoke, VA where he began working for The Roanoke Times as a linotype setter. She was employed by McKesson and Robbins Drugs, Westinghouse Electric Supply, L. S. Waldrop Realty and J. H. Pence Company. Ora Belle completed all but one seat of the test for a Certified Professional Secretary. McColman developed Carpal Tunnel Syndrome that slowed her typing speed below the requirements forcing her to quit. In 1974, Ora Belle decided to open a secretarial service in Roanoke on Williamson road. She offered all types of secretarial and accounting services, but her business mostly evolved into printing. She ran this business alone, printing school yearbooks, Historical Society Journals and other things. She printed two books for Helen Prillaman: "A Place Apart," "Places near the Mountain," and one book for Saunders Guerrant "Franklin County Corn." She also printed a book for Mary Kegley entitled "The Big Fort." She printed a number of cookbooks, booklets, and brochures. Ora Belle was genealogist without a computer that published three family history books: "Emera Altizer of Montgomery County, VA and some of his descendants, 1736-1997;" "A few of the descendants of Charles Mayberry/Mabry of Grayson (Carroll) County, VA 176?-1840;" and "Descendants of Elder John Lawrence of southwest Virginia and New England." She has a fourth unpublished book. (See this collection.)
McColman was a member of Oakland Baptist Church and served as Librarian for several years. She was a member of DAR (Daughters of American Revolution) and of UDC (United Daughters of the Confederacy). Both of her grandfathers fought in the Civil War. She was a founding member of the Williamson Road Action Forum. She served as editor of The Forum for about four to 5 years. McColman was an organizing member of Williamson Road Area Business Association and was a lifetime member. She served as secretary for the first 15 years. McColman passed away on August 19, 2008 and is buried in the Blue Ridge Memorial Gardens in Roanoke, VA.
 </p>

</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">

<head>Scope and Content </head>

<p>The Ora Belle Mayberry McColman Memoir Manuscripts are comprised of twelve yellow ruled notepads of the thirteen piece collection. The first notepad in the collection was missing at time of donation. This is her fourth family history book unpublished.  
</p>

</scopecontent>


<arrangement encodinganalog="351">

<head>Arrangement </head>

<p>12 notebooks arranged in numerical order as labeled by McColman. </p>

</arrangement>


<dsc type="combined">

<head>Contents List </head>


<c01 level="series">

<did>

<unittitle></unittitle>

<container type="box" label="Box">1 </container>

</did>

<c02 level="subseries">

<did>

<unittitle>
12 of 13 notebooks Notebook 1 missing at the time of donation.  
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="inclusive"> </unitdate>

</unittitle>

<container type="folder" label="Folder">1 </container>

</did>

</c02>

</c01>

</dsc>

</archdesc>

</ead>

