<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi00094">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00094::A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Insurrection Records, 1800-1833)//EN" "vi00094.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Insurrection Records, <date>1800-1833</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Insurrection Records, 1800-1833
<num type="collectionnumber">APA 758
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Renee M. Savits
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169;   By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Renee M. Savits, <date>21 June 2016</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Insurrection Records, <date>1800-1833</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">APA 758
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication"> 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Renee M. Savits
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Insurrection Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1800-1833
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">APA 758
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.85 cu. ft. (2 boxes)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Renee M. Savits
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>These materials are available on microfilm [Misc. reels 1323] and should be served instead of the originals. It should be noted that the filming was done previously and does not follow the current arrangement of the papers.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928). Insurrection Records, 1800-1833. Accession APA 758, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>SLAVE INSURRECTIONS: Although Virginia society was 
       generally orderly, the fear of slave rebellion lay just below
         the surface. There were two such rebellions in the antebellum
         period: Gabriel's Insurrection, in 1800, and the Southampton
         Insurrection, or Nat Turner's Rebellion, in 1831. Gabriel and
         his followers were caught before they could act, but Nat
         Turner and his supporters killed several whites before they
         were captured. In each instance retribution was swift. Local
         militia units were called out, many slaves were imprisoned,
         and the ringleaders were executed.</p>
      <p>AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS: Although the colonial
         government had appointed auditors general from time to time,
         the office was not established on a permanent basis until
         after independence was declared. At its first session, which
         convened on 7 October 1776, the General Assembly passed an act
         creating a board of three auditors to examine and settle
         claims concerning receipts and expenditures for military
         purposes. The confusing financial situation of the state,
         however, resulted in a series of acts being passed over the
         next fifteen years elaborating and refining the duties of the
         auditors. Finally, at its session begun in November 1791, the
         General Assembly passed an act that combined the duties of the
         board of auditors and the solicitor general, whose office had
         been created in 1785 to settle the accounts of the state with
         the United States, and assigned them to a single auditor of
         public accounts effective 1 January 1792. The auditor soon
         became the most powerful fiscal officer in the state. All
         receipts and disbursements were made only upon his warrant to
         the treasurer, and his books were the standard against which
         those of the treasurer were checked.</p>
      <p>The first changes were made as the accounts of the
         revolutionary era were settled. As the state moved into a
         period of steady financial and governmental growth in the
         nineteenth century, the number of accounts and funds
         maintained by the auditor became excessive. Thus, on 24
         February 1823 the General Assembly passed an act creating the
         office of the second auditor to ease the auditor's burden.
         Although the second auditor handled several large special
         funds, the auditor continued to be responsible for most of the
         accounts concerning the daily operation of state
         government.</p>
      <p>During the Civil War both the state government and the
         pro-Union Restored Government of Virginia, which was based
         first in Wheeling and then in Alexandria, had auditors of
         public accounts. After the war, near the end of
         Reconstruction, the military authorities appointed Major
         Thaddeus H. Stanton, of the United States Army, as auditor of
         public accounts. Stanton was paid by the state during his
         service from 3 April 1869 to 12 February 1870, although he
         remained an army officer. The position was returned to
         civilian control on 12 February 1870 with the election of
         William F. Taylor as auditor by the General Assembly.</p>
      <p>Following the Civil War the complexities of an increasingly
         sophisticated financial world threatened to overwhelm the
         state fiscal offices, which had changed their practices but
         little since the end of the eighteenth century. Inadequate
         bookkeeping procedures and embezzlements of state funds
         resulted in a public demand for corrective action. It was not
         until a state government reorganization act was passed by the
         General Assembly on 18 April 1927, however, that the demand
         was satisfied. Effective 1 March 1928 the office of auditor of
         public accounts and second auditor were abolished and replaced
         by the office of comptroller--head of the Department of
         Accounts--to monitor the receipt and disbursement of state
         funds, and a new office of auditor of public accounts, under
         the General Assembly, to audit state and local government
         agencies.</p>
      <p>The records of the first auditor of public accounts have
         not survived intact; periodically they have been subjected to
         disarrangement or destruction. When the auditor's office was
         created in 1776, Virginia's seat of government was in
         Williamsburg. In 1780, when the capital was moved to Richmond,
         the auditors and their records also moved. At this time, and
         during Benedict Arnold's raid on Richmond in 1781, some
         auditor's records were misplaced or destroyed. During the War
         of 1812, when it was believed that British troops were
         marching on Richmond, the state's records were loaded onto
         wagons and hauled to the James River for transportation
         upstream. Before the boats sailed, however, the alarm proved
         false and the records were unloaded and returned to the State
         Capitol.</p>
      <p>The next threat to the auditor's records came on the night
         of 2-3 April 1865, when the evacuation fire broke out as the
         Confederate garrison abandoned the city. Fortunately, the
         auditor's records escaped the flames because they were stored
         in the basement and attic of the State Capitol, which did not
         burn. Following the capture of Richmond by Union troops,
         however, a detachment of the Twentieth New York Infantry
         Regiment served as a guard in the Capitol building and browsed
         through the records of the state's fiscal offices (sometimes
         recording candid opinions concerning the late Confederacy in
         the margins of ledgers and journals). After the state library
         building was completed on the east side of Capitol Square in
         the late 1890's the auditor's office moved into it and the
         older records were stored in the basement. There they remained
         until 1913, when they were transferred to the custody of the
         state library.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Insurrection Records, 1800-1833, are housed in two boxes and arranged into two series. Series have been designated for Series I: Gabriel's Insurrection, 1800-1801, and Series II: Southampton Insurrection, 1831-1833. These records concern payment from the Auditor of Public Accounts to Virginia citizens and militia regiments who assisted with the insurrections.</p>


<p>The records, 1800-1833, contain accounts, manumissions, muster rolls, pay rolls, provision returns, and receipts. The bulk of the collection are the muster and pay rolls for regiments of the Virginia Militia assisting with the insurrections. The muster and pay rolls contain the names of members of the militia as well as their rank, pay, and dates of service. The accounts and receipts include payments for guard duty, purchases of food supplies, liquor, powder, and munitions for the militia, clothing repairs, and doctors visits. </p>

<p>The Insurrection records mainly concern the militia and citizens assisting the state with the insurrections. For information on the slaves and free blacks see the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Condemned Slaves and Free Blacks Executed or Transported Records, 1781-1865 (LVA Accession APA 756). For information on the governments response see the Office of the Governor, Executive Papers of Governor James Monroe, 1799-1802 (LVA Accession 40936) and Executive Papers of Governor John Floyd, 1830-1834 (LVA Accession 42665).

</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged in the following series:</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Gabriel's Insurrection, 1800-1801</item>
<item>Series II: Southampton Insurrection, 1831-1833</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I: Gabriel's Insurrection</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1800-1801</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: .40 cu. ft. (1/2 legal size box and 1/2 oversize box).</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Gabriel's Insurrection records series, 1800-1801, are housed in two boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. The series contains accounts and receipts, manumission receipts, muster and pay rolls, and provision returns.
</p>
<p>Gabriel's Insurrection was a large slave insurrection planned for the fall of 1800 by Gabriel (1776-1800), a blacksmith owned by Thomas Henry Prosser of Henrico County, Virginia, and other conspirators. A heavy rainstorm postponed the plot which aimed to take Richmond, hold the governor hostage, and bargain for the freedom of all slaves. After the storm, two slaves informed their owners and the white community marshaled the forces of the governor, the militia, and the courts to root out and punish the conspirators. Gabriel was captured on a schooner in Norfolk and returned to Henrico for trial. The end result of the trials were that twenty six slaves were executed, including Gabriel and his brothers Solomon and Martin. Others were convicted but pardoned; several were sold out of state.</p>
<p>Militiamen were sent to secure the state arsenal at Point of Fork in Fluvanna County, militia companies were called up in Suffolk and Nansemond, and guards were placed on duty to watch captured conspirators and escort witnesses in Richmond and at Bowling Green, in Caroline County. Included are accounts and receipts detailing the costs for rations and spirits furnished to the militia, guard duty at the Penitentiary, transportation of captured slaves, and other sundry expenses. Also included are muster rolls, pay rolls, and provision returns containing the names of those serving guard, rank, days of service, provisions supplied, and amount paid. </p>
<p>Of note are the manumission receipts, 17 March 1801, for Pharoah and Tom, slaves belonging to Philip Sheppard and Elizabeth Sheppard. Pharoah and Tom had revealed Gabriel's plot to Mosby Sheppard and were rewarded with their freedom afterwards by the General Assembly who authorized their purchase and manumission. The receipts were for payments made to the Sheppard family and were signed by Governor James Monroe.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Oversize materials were separated and placed in oversize boxes though everything is listed in alphabetical order in the finding aid. Researchers should pay special attention to note the box numbers.
</p>
</arrangement>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Accounts and receipts, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Accounts and receipts, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Manumission receipts, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, Caroline Court House guards [oversize],
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800-1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, Fluvanna and Goochland Counties militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, Richmond Penitentiary guards [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800-1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
 <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, 4th Regiment and 4th Division, Richmond Troop of Cavalry [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, 23rd Regiment Chesterfield County Militia, 1st Battalion [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, 23rd Regiment Chesterfield County Militia, 2nd Battalion [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
  <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payrolls, 23rd Regiment Chesterfield County Militia, Town of Manchester (Richmond, Va.) guards; and Field and Staff officers payrolls [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
   
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Provision returns, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800-1801</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II: Southampton Insurrection</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1831-1833</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Boxes" type="box">1-2
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: .45 cu. ft. (1/2 legal size box and 1/2 oversize box).</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Southampton Insurrection records series, 1831-1833, are housed in two boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. The series contains accounts and receipts and muster and pay rolls.
</p>
<p>Nat Turner (1800-1831) was an enslaved African American who led a rebellion of more than fifty enslaved and free African Americans in Southampton County, Virginia, on 21 August 1831, that resulted in the deaths of 55 to 65 white people. The rebellion was suppressed within 48 hours, but Turner was not apprehended until 30 October 1831. A white militia with twice the manpower of the rebels and reinforced by three companies of artillery eventually defeated the insurrection. More than 200 African Americans were killed in retaliation by mobs and the militia in the course of putting down the rebellion. Turner was tried and convicted 5 November 1831 and executed by hanging in the town of Jerusalem, Southampton County, Virginia, on 11 November 1831.</p>
<p>Included are accounts and receipts detailing items furnished to Southampton County citizens during the insurrection; food, candles, fodder, tin pans, and other sundry items supplied to the militia; doctor care of militia members; newspaper advertisements; and travel costs. Also included are muster and pay rolls for artillery and militia regiments, including the 15th, 29th, 59th, 62nd, 65th, and 71st Virginia Militia. Included are the names of those serving guard, rank, days of service, provisions supplied, and amount paid. </p>
<p></p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Oversize materials were separated and placed in oversize boxes though everything is listed in alphabetical order in the finding aid. Researchers should pay special attention to note the box numbers.
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Accounts and receipts, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, Artillery Regiment of Captain David Hargrave, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, Captain Alexander P. Peete's company [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 15th Regiment Virginia Militia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1833</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 29th Regiment Virginia Militia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 29th Regiment Virginia Militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">10
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 59th Regiment Virginia Militia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 59th Regiment Virginia Militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">11
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 62nd Regiment Virginia Militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">12
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 65th Regiment Virginia Militia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">10
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 65th Regiment Virginia Militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">13
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 71st Regiment Virginia Militia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">11
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Muster and payrolls, 71st Regiment Virginia Militia [oversize], 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1831-1832</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">14
	</container>
	</did> 	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>