<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00961">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00961::A Guide to the Governor Mark R. Warner, Transition Office, Records, , 2001)//EN" "vi00961.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Mark R. Warner, Transition Office, Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Warner, Governor Mark R., Transition Office, Records, 2001
<num type="collectionnumber">42628
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Roger E. Christman
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Roger E. Christman, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 July 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Mark R. Warner, Transition Office, Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">42628
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Roger E. Christman
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Roger E. Christman
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Governor R. Warner, Transition Office, Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">42628
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">0.53 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Governor Mark R. Warner, Transition Office, Records, 2001, Accession 42628, State Records Collection, Library of Virginia
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, transferred on 7 April 2006.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
      <p>Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named his transition leadership team on 7 November 2001.  Former Congressmen L.F. Payne served as Transition Chair; former Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU) Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs Grace E. Harris served as Vice-Chair; former Virginia Transportation Secretary John Milliken served as Transition Director; former Director of the Joint Commission on Health Care Jane Kusiak served as Deputy Transition Director; and former Warner campaign spokesperson Mo Elleithee served as Transition Spokesperson.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Governor Mark R. Warner, Transition Office, Records are housed in 2 boxes.  The collection consists of three transition binders:  Government Processes, November 2001; Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, November 2001; and Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and The Cabinet, 17 December 2001.  The contents of each binder have been removed and placed into folders.
The Government Processes binder, prepared by the Department of Planning and Budget in November 2001, provides briefings of key processes that involve the Governor's Office including:  Budget Highlights, Budget Process, Capital Outlay, Executive Orders, Legislative Process, Regulatory Review, Expenditure Forecasting, Virginia's 'Best Practices' Unit and Strategic Planning and Performance Measurement.  The briefing explains each of these items and the Governor's Office role.
</p>
      <p>The Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, prepared by John W. Forbes, Governor James S. Gilmore's Finance Secretary, describes the Commonwealth's finances as well as provides an overview of the Finance Secretariat.  The briefing includes an Executive Summary, Overview, Expenditure Trends and Budget Issues, Revenues:  Historical and Forecast, October Revenues, Year-End Financial Statements (FY 1998-FY 2001), Economic Impact of Terrorist Attacks (September 11, 2001), Debt and Debt Capacity, Cash Investments, Revenue Stabilization Fund, and an overview of Finance Agencies (Department of Accounts, Department of Planning and Budget, Department of the State Internal Auditor, Department of Taxation and Department of Treasury).</p>
      <p>The Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Cabinet, compiled by Jane N. Kusiak and dated 17 December 2001, contains Issue Work Group Findings for the Administration, Commerce and Trade, Education, Technology, Health and Human Resources, Natural Resources, Public Safety and Transportation Secretariats.  The purpose of the Issue Work Groups was to assemble a group of citizen leaders in each secretarial area of responsibility, provide detailed information on the area of responsibility for each cabinet secretary, identify relevant campaign issues and other pending issues within the secretariat, make recommendation for near-term action and develop issue briefs on topics needing more detailed policy analysis.  Each Issue Work Group Report includes a Historical and Operational Analysis of the Secretariat, Duties and Responsibilities of Boards and Agencies within the Secretariat, Current Process, Internal Operating Procedures and Key Constituents, Summary of Current Issues and Key Initiatives, Recommended Goals and Priorities of the Governor for the Secretary and The First 100 Days.  The Reports are arranged as follows:  Administration, Commerce and Trade, Education, Health and Human Resources, Public Safety, Technology, Natural Resources, Transportation and Issue Briefs.  This briefing binder provides an overview of the issues facing the Warner Administration as it took office in January 2002  as well as listing its' goals for the first 100 days.</p>
      <p>Members of the Administration Work Group were:  Jim Roberts (Staff), Alan Albert, May Fox, Anthony Graziano, Phyllis Katz, and Carolyn Jefferson-Moss.  Members of Commerce and Trade Work Group were:  Grant Neely (Staff), Pat Gottschalk, Adele Johnson, Hugh Keogh, Danny LeBlanc, Martha Moore and Bob Templin.  Members of the Education Work Group were:  Suzette Denslow and Sarah Hopkins Finley (Staff), Peggy Baggett, William C. Bosher, Jr., Deborah DiCroce, Donald Finley, Robley Jones, Robert Lambeth, Stewart Roberson, Linwood Rose and Alan Wurtzel.  Members of the Health and Human Resources Work Group were:  Howard Cullum, Mike Evans, Randy Gordon, M.D., Debbie Oswalt, Jim Rothrock, Chris Spanos, Joe Teffey, Marilyn West, and Jane Woods.  Members of the Public Safety Work Group were:  Jim Roberts (Staff), Carl Baker, Chuck Duvall, John Jones, Lane Kneedler, Mike Mohler, Jerry Oliver, Rich Savage and T. Twitty.  Technology Work Group members were:  Eugene Huang (Staff), Jack Kennedy, Doug Koelemay, Stan Mauphin, Anne Reed and Bob Stolle.  Natural Resources Work Group members were:  Jeffrey Bourne (Staff), Tayloe Murphy, John Daniel, Jimmy Wheat, Steve Walker, Bob Burnley, Joe Maroon, Sherry Crumley and Alexander Crumley.  Transportation Issue Work Group members were:  Mike Edwards (Staff), Jim Atwell, Robert Merhige, Pierce Homer, Rob Shinn, Ray Pethtel, Linda McMinimy, Jack Hodge, Oscar Mabry and Marianne Radcliff.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Government Processes, Dept. of Planning and Budget, November 2001
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, November 2001 (part one)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, November 2001 (part two)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, November 2001 (part three)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Secretary of Finance, A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team, November 2001 (part four)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and The Cabinet, 17 December 2001 (part one)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and The Cabinet, 17 December 2001 (part two)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and The Cabinet, 17 December 2001 (part three)
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
