<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00838">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00838::A Guide to the Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Business Records, 1934-1957)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00838.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00838::A Guide to the Benvir
             Coal Company, Incorporated, Business Records,
             1934-1957)//EN" "vi00838.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Benvir Coal Company,
            Incorporated, Business Records, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1957</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated,
            Business Records, 1934-1957 
            <num type="collectionnumber">1124168-1124171,
            1124307-1124314, 1128236-1128256</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2003 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 04 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         record. Created by Greg Crawford 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 July 2003</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 14, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00838::A Guide to the Benvir Coal Company,
            Incorporated, Business Records, 1934-1957)//EN"
            "vi00838.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-08">2014-01-08</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated,
         Business Records, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1957</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Barcode Numbers">1124168-1124171, 1124307-1124314,
         1128236-1128256</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">A Guide to the Benvir Coal Company,
         Incorporated, Business Records, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1934-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers">1124168-1124171,
         1124307-1124314, 1128236-1128256</unitid>
      <physloc label="Physical Location">The Library of Virginia,
         Local Government Records Collection, Lee County</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">33 volumes (7223
         p.). Two volumes missing cover and spine.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector">Lee County</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Payroll Account Ledger, 1955-1957, includes private information. Do not serve. There are no restrictions for serving rest of collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated Business Records,
            1934-1957. Local Government Records Collection, Lee County
            Court Records, The Library of Virginia, Richmond,
            Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These materials came to the Library of Virginia in
            shipments of court papers from Lee County.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated and the Benedict Coal
         Corporation operated coal mines in Lee County, Virginia,
         during the mid-twentieth century with offices located in the
         town of St. Charles, Virginia. The Benvir Coal Company
         purchased controlling interest of the Benedict Coal
         Corporation during the mid-1950's.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Various business records, 1934-1957, of the Benvir Coal
         Company, Incorporated and the Benedict Coal Corporation. The
         majority of records relate to activities of the Benedict Coal
         Corporation which was purchased by Benvir Coal Company during
         the mid-1950's.</p>
      <p>Two trial balance books of Benedict Coal Corporation,
         1944-1955, used to check that the debits and credits in a
         double-entry bookkeeping ledger are equal at the end of each
         month. It lists the titles of accounts, date, and the amount
         of money debited or credited in that particular month.
         Accounts listed in volume include general ledger, petty
         ledger, cash, mining, payroll, sales ledger, and scrip change
         fund. Information found in trial balance book was taken from
         cash journals and transferred to appropriate ledger.</p>
      <p>Three general ledgers of Benedict Coal Corporation,
         1946-1957, and one general ledger of the Benvir Coal Company,
         1955-1957, that record the corporations' controlling and
         operating accounts which include interest account, coal sales,
         depreciation, insurance claims, social security tax, store
         salaries, ventilation, drainage, unemployment insurance, and
         mine operating costs. Each individual account lists date of
         transactions, amount debited, amount credited, and page number
         or account number where transaction can be found in
         corresponding cash journal or voucher record book. Information
         related to individual accounts found in general ledger was
         taken from trial balance books, voucher record books, cash
         journals, and expense journals. General ledger (1946-1949)
         includes an index listing accounts in alphabetical order and
         page number where they can be found. General ledgers
         (1950-1957) also include an index listing accounts in
         alphabetical order and account number, rather than page
         number, where they can be found. General ledger (1950- 1953)
         is missing its cover and spine.</p>
      <p>Ten cash journals of Benedict Coal Corporation, August
         1948-September 1957, and four cash journals of the Benvir Coal
         Company, August 1955-September 1957 that record the
         corporation's transactions on a daily basis similar to a
         daybook. Information found in each volume includes date of
         transaction, form of transaction, and amount owed and paid.
         The cash amount of transaction is listed under the name of
         ledger where it eventually was transferred. Ledgers listed
         include general ledger, petty ledger, cash ledger, payroll
         ledger, sales ledger, scrip ledger, store sales ledger, etc.
         Page numbers and account numbers found in many transactions
         correspond to page numbers and account numbers found in
         corresponding general ledgers. At the end of each month, the
         bookkeeper subtracted the cash received from cash paid to
         calculate the total balance for each ledger. The amount was
         then placed in the trial balance book and eventually
         transferred to the corresponding ledger. Loose papers
         (correspondence, receipts, etc.,) found in several ledgers
         were removed and placed in folder.</p>
      <p>Two mining supplies voucher ledgers of Benedict Coal
         Corporation, 1948-1953, that record on a monthly basis how
         much the corporation owed suppliers for the purchase on credit
         of mining supplies or services. They list the names of
         companies from whom the corporation made purchases, area or
         department of corporation for whom the purchase was made
         (ventilation, electrical, machine repair, delivery,
         engineering, etc.), and amount paid.</p>
      <p>Depreciation accounts ledger of Benedict Coal Corporation,
         1934-1944, that records on an annual basis the amount by which
         the corporation's property and equipment decreased in value.
         It lists the name of property and equipment (mine cars,
         trucks, ropes, telephone lines, office furniture, service
         stations, etc.), it's original value, and amount it
         depreciated over time. Loose documents found in volume related
         to the company's depreciation schedule were removed and placed
         in folder. The cover of volume reads "Trial Balance."</p>
      <p>Two voucher record books of the Benedict Coal Corporation,
         1948-1955, and one voucher record book of the Benvir Coal
         Company, 1955-1957, that record on a monthly basis how much
         the corporations owed suppliers for the purchase on credit of
         supplies or services. They are similar to an accounts payable
         ledger. Information found in the volumes includes the names of
         companies from whom the corporations purchased supplies and
         services on credit, the amount of payment, and the name of the
         account from which the payment was expended. Transactions were
         transferred from voucher record book to general ledger.
         Account numbers found at the end of each month's transactions
         correspond to account numbers in corresponding general
         ledgers. Loose documents found in Benvir Coal Company voucher
         record book were removed and placed in folder.</p>
      <p>Two cash flow ledgers of Benedict Coal Corporation,
         1949-1955, and one cash flow ledger of Benvir Coal Company,
         1955-1956, used to calculate on a monthly basis the amount of
         cash remaining to pay wages of the corporation's employees
         following the payment of debts. It records the expenses
         incurred by employees including medical, rental fees, scrip
         advances, lights, store accounts, burial, union dues, and
         overdrafts and payroll expenses such as Social Security tax
         and unemployment insurance. It also records expenses related
         to mining operations including drainage, ventilation, truck
         delivery, timbers, and machine repairs. Each of the previous
         were totalled and subtracted from the gross payroll to
         determine the cash remaining to pay employees.</p>
      <p>Petty ledger of Benvir Coal Company, 1955-1957, that
         records accounts of little importance. They are the accounts
         of individuals perhaps employees. Information found in each
         account includes date of transaction, page number of
         corresponding cash journal or voucher record book where
         information was transferred, amount owed, and amount paid.
         Accounts arranged in alphabetical order by surname of
         individual.</p>
      <p>Coal shipment record book of Benvir Coal Company,
         1955-1957. It records monthly the type (block, round, stoker,
         carbon, nut and slack), tonnage, and price of coal shipped to
         Holmes-Darst Coal Corporation by Benvir Coal Company from its
         various mines. Various loose documents were found in volume.
         They include receipts, coal shipment accounts containing
         information from volume, payroll, vacation payroll for year
         1956- 1957, service station account, and balance sheets of
         company listing assets, liablilities, and net worth. The
         various payroll accounts list the names of employees, amount
         of wages, taxes withheld, vacation pay, other expenses taken
         from wages, and net amount of wages. Documents were removed
         from volume and placed in folder.</p>
      <p>Payroll Account ledger of Benvir Coal Company, August 1955
         - May 1957, that records monthly the individual payroll
         accounts of employees. Information found in each account
         includes name of employee, month paid, amount of taxable
         earning, withholding tax, vacation pay (yes or no), and an
         unidentified account perhaps Social Security tax withheld. The
         front page of ledger records the totals of each category.
         Ledger is missing cover and spine.</p>
      <p>Checkbook ledger of Benvir Coal Company, 1957, that
         contains check stubs and blank checks. Information found on
         check stubs includes check number, date check issued, name of
         company or individual to whom check was written, and amount of
         check.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Volumes arranged chronologically within each series.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Trial Balance Book,
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1944-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Trial Balance Book,
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1950-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation General Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1946-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation General Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1950-1953</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation General Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1950-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, General
               Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1948-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1951-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1952-1953</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1953-1954</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1954-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Cash Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Cash
               Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Cash
               Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Cash
               Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1956-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Cash
               Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Mining Supplies
               Vouchers Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1948-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Mining Supplies
               Vouchers Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1950-1953</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Depreciation
               Accounts Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1934-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Voucher Record
               Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1948-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Voucher Record
               Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1952-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Voucher
               Record Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Monthly Cash Flow
               Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1949-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benedict Coal Corporation Monthly Cash Flow
               Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1952-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Monthly
               Cash Flow Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Petty
               Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Coal
               Shipment Record Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Payroll
               Account Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1955-1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benvir Coal Company, Incorporated, Checkbook
               Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
