<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00545">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00545::A Guide to the Highland County (Va.) Business Records, 1891-1914//EN" "vi00545.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Highland County (Va.) Business Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891-1914</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Highland County (Va.) Business Records, 1891-1914
</subtitle>
        <author>J. Porter
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2012 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by J. Porter, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012 April 30</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Highland County (Va.) Business Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891-1914</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>J. Porter
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Highland County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891-1914
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">State Records Center - Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">4 volumes
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Highland County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Highland County (Va.) Business Records, 1891-1914. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Highland County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers Highland County, Va under undated accessions.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.</p>
<p>These records were processed by Greg Crawford in 2003.
</p>
<p>Encoded by J. Porter: 2012; updated by J.Taylor: June 2024.</p>
</processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Highland County was so named because of its high altitude, which ranges from 1,611 to 4,491 feet, giving it one of the highest mean-elevations east of the Mississippi River. The county seal identifies it as "Virginia's Switzerland." It was formed from Pendleton (now in West Virginia) and Bath Counties in 1847. The county seat is Monterey</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Highland County (Va.) Business Records, 1891-1914, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Highland County (Va.). Represented records include company ledgers. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into three series: 

<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Beverage and Brown Business Records, 1905-1913</item>
<item>Series II: Don Sullenberger and Company Business Records, 1891-1893</item>
<item>Series III: Sullie B. Rexrode Business Records, 1909-1914.</item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Highland County records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA129">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Beverage and Brown Business Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1913
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Beverage and Brown was a blacksmith shop owned by Edward C. Beverage and Paul Brown. It conducted business in Highland County, Virginia during the early twentieth century. Beverage sold his share of the business to Brown in 1907.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Beverage and Brown Business Records consists of a ledger that records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found includes date of transaction, services rendered or items sold, form of payment, and amount owed or paid. Services rendered include shoeing horses, setting axles, balancing tires, and repairing tools, sleds, buggies, and sleighs. Items sold include bolts, tire irons, chains, and metal rings. Payments made by cash, credit, and barter of items such as wheat, sheep skin, and honey. Volume includes an index at the front that lists customers names in alphabetical order and the page number of their account. Numerous miscellaneous papers found in volume were placed into a folder at the front of volume.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1107123">Beverage and Brown Ledger,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1913
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">Don Sullenberger and Company Business Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">1891-1893
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Don Sullenberger and Company was a general store that conducted business in Highland County, Virginia during the late nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Don Sullenberger and Company Business Records consists of two ledgers which record the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items sold, quantity of items sold, cost per item, form of payment, amount owed, and amount paid. Goods sold include flour, lye, dry goods, apparel, food, nails, kerosene, violin strings and candy. Payments made by cash, credit, labor, and barter of items such as wool, chestnuts, butter, and bacon. Volume also records the store's controlling accounts such as expense account, cash account, and accounts due.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1107120">Don Sullenberger Ledger A
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1891-1893
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1107105">Don Sullenberger Ledger B
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1893
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III: ">Sullie B. Rexrode Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1909-1914
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<container label="Box" type="box">
</container>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Sullie B. Rexrode's general store conducted business in Highland County, Virginia during the early twentieth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Sullie B. Rexrode's Business Records consists of a ledger, which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items sold, quantity of items sold, cost per item, form of payment, amount owed, and amount paid. Goods sold include onions, combs, dry goods, apparel, coffee, spices, syrup, oil, and fruit. Payments made by cash, credit, labor, and barter of items such as lambs, butter, and eggs. Additional miscellaneous information unrelated to the general store was found at the end of volume. Numerous pages were torn from volume.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1107113">Sullie B. Rexrode Ledger, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1909-1914
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>
	</c01>
</dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
