<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vi00006">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00006::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont, 1865-1868)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00006.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00006::A Guide to the Executive
             Papers of Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont,
             1865-1868)//EN" "vi00006.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers Governor
            Francis Harrison Pierpont, 
            <date>1865-1868</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Pierpont, Governor Francis Harrison,
            1865-1868 
            <num type="collectionnumber">37024</num></subtitle>
            <author>Craig Moore</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>The Library of Virginia</addressline>
               <addressline>800 East Broad Street</addressline>
               <addressline>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archdesk@lva.lib.va.us
               (Archives)</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2001 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">51 kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000. Machine-readable finding aid created by Paige Neal, 
         <date>14 September 2001</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00006::A Guide to the Executive Papers of
            Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont, 1865-1868)//EN"
            "vi00006.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor
         Francis Harrison Pierpont, 
         <date>1865-1868</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">37024</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2001</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Craig Moore</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Executive Papers of Governor Francis Harrison
         Pierpont, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1865-1868</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Accession number">37024</unitid>
         <physloc label="Location">State Records Collection, Record
         Group 3.</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">4.2 cubic feet; 9
         boxes; boxes 1-9</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont, Executive papers,
            1865-1868. Accession 37024. State records collection, The
            Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <custodhist>
            <head>Provenance</head>
            <p>Transferred prior to 1905. No other acquisition
            information available.</p>
         </custodhist>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Francis Harrison Pierpont was born on January 25, 1814,
         just east of Morgantown, W. Va. After working on his father's
         farm and tannery business in Fairmont, W. Va., Pierpont
         studied law at Allegheny College in Meadville, Pa., in 1835.
         He was admitted into the bar in 1842 and served as counsel for
         the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad until 1856. Pierpont was also
         involved in various business ventures including mining and
         shipping coal by rail. In December 1854, Pierpont married
         Julia Robinson, the daughter of a Presbyterian minister.
         Pierpont was an active member of the Whig political party and
         an anti-slavery proponent. Although he did not hold political
         office, Pierpont acted as a spokesman for northwest Virginia
         delivering speeches and writing commentaries in the newspapers
         attacking the Democrats and slavery. When the Virginia
         Convention voted on April 17, 1861, to pass the Ordinance of
         Secession, mass meetings were held in opposition to secession
         in northwest Virginia. Pierpont took an active part in these
         meetings and in the Wheeling Convention on May 13, 1861, in
         which he represented Marion County. The Convention voted to
         defy the Secession Convention. The Second 1861, and Pierpont
         was unanimously elected governor of the Restored Government of
         Virginia on June 20, 1861 with the recognition of President
         Lincoln.</p>
         <p>Pierpont was again elected governor for a four-year term on
         May 28, 1863. Following Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation,
         Pierpont called for a new Constitutional Convention. The
         Convention assembled in Alexandria, the new seat of
         government, on February 3, 1864, and adjourned on April 11,
         1864, having adopted an amendment for the abolition of
         slavery. The Convention also added a provision disfranchising
         those men who previously held office in the Confederate
         government and who refused to take an oath affirming that they
         did not aid the rebellion and swearing loyalty to the U.S.
         Constitution. Following the Civil War and the death of
         President Lincoln, President Johnson recognized Pierpont as
         provisional governor and removed the state capital to Richmond
         by an executive order on May 9, 1865. Pierpont succeeded in
         removing the disfranchisement from the Alexandria Convention
         after the war. However, in the summer of 1866, Congress passed
         the 14th Amendment guaranteeing the rights of freedmen and
         preventing former Confederate officials from holding office.
         Virginia, failing to ratify the amendment, was placed under
         military rule as a result of the passage of the first
         Reconstruction Act on March 2, 1867. Virginia became Military
         District No. 1 under the command of Major Gen. John M.
         Schofield whose role was to direct Virginia's Reconstruction.
         Pierpont remained governor, but his powers were greatly
         weakened. Schofield eventually replaced Pierpont with Horatio
         H. Wells as provisional governor on April 4, 1868. Pierpont
         died at the home of his daughter in Pittsburgh, Pa., on March
         24, 1899.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>Governor Pierpont's Executive papers are organized chronologically and primarily consist of incoming correspondence between May 10, 1865 and April 3, 1868. Correspondence, resolutions, circular letters, proclamations, special orders, petitions, certificates of qualification, certificates of election, commissions, applications, ordinances, telegrams, election returns, proceedings, pardons, affidavits, lists, appointments, clippings, reports, resignations, and other items can be found in this series.</p>
<p>
The majority of the correspondence relates to requests for appointments in Virginia state government for such positions as notaries public, public guard, commissioners, postmaster, inspectors, etc. Recommendations or petitions often accompany these letters of appointment. Other correspondence relates to citizens seeking recompense for services rendered during the war. Pierpont corresponded often with Secretary of State, William H. Seward, regarding a variety of issues including pardons, passports, and freedmen. Seward wrote to Pierpont transmitting warrants of pardon for citizens of Virginia. Some of the correspondence in these papers relates to the Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, &amp; Abandoned Lands. The Bureau adjudicated disputes between negroes and negroes and whites. The Bureau often forwarded court cases to Pierpont for his opinion. This correspondence is often filled with endorsements from various officers in the Bureau stating their opinion as well. Pierpont also corresponded with and received special orders from Major Gen. Alfred H. Terry and others from the U.S. Army, Department of Virginia. Lastly, Pierpont corresponded with Captain E.S. Gray of the Public Guard re. appointments and other issues.</p>
<p>
Other types of documents found in Pierpont's papers include circulars, special orders, and correspondence from Major Gen. Oliver O. Howard, Chief Commissioner, and Colonel Orlando Brown, Assistant Commissioner, of the Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, &amp; Abandoned Lands; proclamations from other state governors calling for days of Thanksgiving; petitions of protest against elections of certain individuals due to their role during the war; applications for pardons along with affidavits and court cases; and appointments of county officers issued from the Headquarters of the 1st Military District.</p>
<p>
Noteworthy documents include a resolution from a portion of the citizens of Warren County to support the U.S. Constitution (May 15, 1865); a letter to the Secretary of War re. the Orange &amp; Alexandria Railroad and Gen. Grant's recommendation for its repair (May 11, 1865); a letter and resolutions from the secretary of the Lincoln Memorial Association re. a monument to be erected in Springfield, IL. (May 19, 1865); a letter from an ex-slave in New Orleans asking the governor for assistance in locating his wife and five children (May 21, 1865); proclamation reestablishing the seat of government at Richmond (May 23, 1865); documents including Special Order No. 22 by Major Gen. Halleck turning the Richmond &amp; Danville Railroad over to the Board of Public Works (June 2, 1865); a list of names of prominent men of Richmond who remained faithful to the Union (June 6, 1865); a letter from Secretary of State William H. Seward re. the safety of public property in Richmond (June 20, 1865); a letter from former governor William Smith re. the contents of the Governor's Mansion following the evacuation (June 11, 1865); and a report of the Board of Directors of the Western Lunatic Asylum (June 21, 1865).</p>
<p>
Other noteworthy documents include an act prescribing means by which persons who have been disfranchised by the third article of the Constitution may be restored to the rights of voters (June 22, 1865); a letter from Pierpont to the Superintendent of the Virginia Central Railroad asking him to allow Confederate prisoners free transport to their homes (June 23, 1865); a printed letter from Thomas R. Bowden, Attorney General of Virginia, stating that ex-Confederate soldiers and officers are not eligible to hold state offices (July 14, 1865); a letter from John N. Camp, U.S. Consul in Jamaica, re. colonization of freedmen (Aug. 7, 1865); a report by Thomas H. DeWitt, Clerk of the Board of Public Works, re. the condition of the Orange &amp; Alexandria Railroad (Aug. 16, 1865); telegram from President Andrew Johnson re. interference by the military in the municipal elections in Richmond (N.D., 1865); testimony in examination of the conduct of the Superintendent of the Board of Visitors of the Institution for the Deaf, Dumb, and Blind (Sept. 14, 1865); special orders from Major Gen. Terry surrendering the charge of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum (Oct. 23, 1865); ordinance by the Convention of Alabama abolishing slavery and declaring the ordinance of secession null &amp; void (Oct. 4, 1865); a letter to President Johnson transmitting the resolution of the General Assembly re. the pardon of Jefferson Davis and others (Dec. 22, 1865); Arthur Barbarin's plan for an electro-magnetic torpedo (oversized, May 28, 1865); proposals and bids for repairs to the Capitol &amp; Governor's Mansion (Feb. 9 &amp; 23, 1866); a printed remonstrance to the U.S. Congress against the bill to annex the city &amp; county of Alexandria to the District of Columbia (May 17, 1866); a letter from Governor Arthur I. Boreman of W.Va. re. the return of a bronze statue of George Washington taken from the Virginia Military Institute during the war (May 28, 1866); a circular from William H. Seward re. the 14th Amendment to the Constitution (June 16, 1866); a letter from William H. Richardson, Adjutant General of Va., re. the destruction of the State Armory (Oct. 1866); a list of stockholders of the Richmond &amp; Danville Railroad Company (July 26, 1866); a letter from Randolph Rogers re. the equestrian statue of Washington to be completed by him due to the death of William Crawford (Nov. 10, 1866); report of the Treasurer of Virginia for the fiscal years 1 Oct. 1865 to 30 Sept. 1866 &amp; Oct. 1866 to Sept. 1867; a letter from William H. Seward re. schemes to emigrate freedmen to other countries particularly Peru for cheap labor (Oct. 6 &amp; 17, 1866); resolutions from the states of Michigan, Massachusetts, Arkansas, and North Carolina re. the 14th Amendment (Feb. &amp; March 1866); a letter from former governor John Letcher accepting appointment of visitor to the Virginia Military Institute (May 25, 1867); and proposals for the erection of a railing around the statue of Washington in Capitol Square (May 1867).
</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Papers are arranged chronologically by date of
         endorsement.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <dsc type="combined">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Executive Papers</unittitle>
               <container label="Boxes" type="box">1-9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
               <p>Governor Pierpont's Executive papers are arranged
               chronologically by the date of endorsement which
               indicates when the document was received and what action
               was taken by the governor and primarily consist of
               incoming correspondence between May 10, 1865 and April
               3, 1868. Correspondence, resolutions, circular letters,
               proclamations, special orders, petitions, certificates
               of qualification, certificates of election, commissions,
               applications, ordinances, telegrams, election returns,
               proceedings, pardons, affidavits, lists, appointments,
               clippings, reports, resignations, and other items can be
               found in this series.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <arrangement>
               <p>Executive Papers arranged chronologically.</p>
            </arrangement>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 May
                  10-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 June
                  1-10</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 June
                  11-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 June
                  15-22</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 June
                  23-30</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 July
                  1-7</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 July
                  8-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 July
                  16-24</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 July
                  25-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 August
                  1-10</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 August
                  11-25</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 August
                  26-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 September
                  1-12</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 September
                  13-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 September
                  16-30</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 October
                  2-24</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 October
                  25-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 November
                  1-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 November
                  16-30</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 December
                  1-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1865 December
                  16-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:9</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 January
                  1-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 January
                  16-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 February
                  1-10</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 Feburary
                  11-27</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  March</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  April</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  May</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  June</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  July</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 August
                  1-15</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866 August
                  16-31</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  September</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  October</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  November</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1866
                  December</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  January</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  February</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  March</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  April</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  May</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  June</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  July</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  August</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  September</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:9</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  October</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:10</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  November</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1867
                  December</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1868
                  January</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1868
                  February</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1868
                  March</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1868 April
                  2-3</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  7:7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  8:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  8:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  8:3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  8:4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  Undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  8:5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence - Oversize 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1865</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  9:1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence - Oversize 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1866-1867</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  9:2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
