<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi00315">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00315::A Guide to the Walter Jones Papers, 1846-1850)//EN" "vi00315.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Walter Jones Papers, <date>1846-1850</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Jones, Walter, Papers, 1846-1850
<num type="collectionnumber">37463
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Alex Lorch
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>11 July 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Walter Jones Papers, <date>1846-1850</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">37463
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Alex Lorch
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Alex Lorch
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Walter Jones Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1846-1850
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">37463
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">7 leaves and 19 pages
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Walter Jones
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Walter Jones Papers, 1846-1850.  Accession 37463.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Purchased, 16 March 2000, from Donna Lee Wlson, Alexandria, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Walter Jones (1776-1861) of Virginia was the son of Dr. Walter Jones and Ailsie Flood. After studying law under Bushrod Washington, Walter Jones was admitted to the bar in 1796. In 1802 President Thomas Jefferson appointed him the United States attorney for the District of Columbia, an office which he held until 1821. He also was a major general in the District of Columbia militia, and during the War of 1812 he took part in the Battle of Bladensburg. Jones gained a national reputation for the prominent part he took in the celebrated Girard will case, the Myra Clark Gaines case, McCullough vs. Maryland, the Randolph will case, Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company vs. Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company, and John Randall vs. Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Company. He was married in 1808 to Anne Lucinda and with her had three sons and eleven daughters. Upon his death in Washington, D.C., he was buried in the Congressional Cemetery.
</p>
<p>William Hayward Foote (1781-1846) inherited "Hayfield" from his aunt and adopted mother Elizabeth Foote. Hayfield plantation was a 360 acre portion of the Mount Vernon estate acquired by Elizabeth Foote's husband, Lund Washington, from George Washington after the Revolutionary War. William Foote prospered as Hayfield's proprietor and in his will bequeathed the estate and all his property to his wife of 15 years, Mary Marshall Scott Foote. After his death the executors of the will led by Francis L. Smith contested William Foote's heirs' entitlement. In his will he had bequeathed everything to his wife "for as long as she remains my widow or for life... if, however, she should cease to be my widow or marry again, she must account for all these things and take her dower at law... It is not my purpose to give any Cur a Sop."</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1846-1850, of Walter Jones (1776-1861) of Virginia consisting of correspondence, legal answers, and receipts concerning the will of William Hayward Foote (1781-1846) of "Hayfield," Fairfax County, Virginia, and the subsequent lawsuit over Foote's estate between his heirs and his executors.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>26 April [1846?]
</unitdate>from Walter Jones to William H. Foote asking for a detailed account of his real estate and personal property to be included in Jones' draft of Foote's will.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>[1846], 
</unitdate>from Francis L. Smith (1808-1877), Alexandria, Virginia, to Walter Jones containing four questions concerning Foote's will.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>December 1846, 
</unitdate>from Jones to Smith answering the four questions asked by Smith concerning the powers of Foote's heirs and executors to sell his personal property and real estate.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Legal answer, 
<unitdate>10 March 1847, 
</unitdate>written by Jones outlining his opinions on questions concerning the interpretation of Foote's will, specifically the personal property and real estate entitlements of Foote's widow, the emancipation of his slaves, and the sale of his crops.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Receipt, 
<unitdate>11 May 1848, 
</unitdate>from Walter Jones to Francis L. Smith for payment of fifty dollars for draft of answer to the bill of Foote's heirs versus Foote's executors.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Draft, 
<unitdate>27 May 1850, 
</unitdate>on the Farmers Banks of Virginia for payment to Dr. James Hunter for his services resurveying Hayfield Plantation for the suit of Foote's heirs versus Foote's executors.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Draft, 
<unitdate>5 December 1850, 
</unitdate>on the Farmers Bank of Virginia for the balance standing for the sale of Hayfield.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
