<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vi00328">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00328::A Guide to the Records of Ante-Bellum Southern Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War. Series F, Part 4, North Carolina and Virginia Plantations, 2001.)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00328.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00328::A Guide to the Records of
             Ante-Bellum Southern Plantations from the Revolution
             through the Civil War. Series F, Part 4, North Carolina
             and Virginia Plantations, 2001.)//EN"
             "vi00328.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of Ante-Bellum Southern
            Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War.
            Series F, Part 4, North Carolina and Virginia Plantations, 
            <date>2001</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Records of Ante-Bellum Southern
            Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War.
            Series F, Part 4, North Carolina and Virginia Plantations,
            2001 
            <num type="collectionnumber">38395</num></subtitle>
            <author>Alex Lorch</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>The Library of Virginia</addressline>
               <addressline>800 East Broad Street</addressline>
               <addressline>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archdesk@lva.lib.va.us
               (Archives)</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">2 KB</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Marc
         record. Created by Renee M. Savits 
         <date>11 May 2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00328::A Guide to the Records of Ante-Bellum
            Southern Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil
            War. Series F, Part 4, North Carolina and Virginia
            Plantations, 2001.)//EN" "vi00328.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of Ante-Bellum Southern
         Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War. Series
         F, Part 4, North Carolina and Virginia Plantations, 
         <date>2001</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">38395</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Alex Lorch</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Records of Ante-bellum Southern
         Plantations from the Revolution through the Civil War. Series
         F: Selections from the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special
         Collections Library, Duke University, Part 4: North Carolina and Virginia plantations</unittitle>
         <unitid label="Accession number">38395</unitid>
         <physloc label="Physical Location">Miscellaneous reel
         2584-2608</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">25 reels of
         microfilm</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Special permission for reproduction or extensive
            quotation must be obtained through written application to
            the Duke University, Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special
            Collections Library, Durham, North Carolina.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Records of Ante-bellum Southern Plantations from the
            Revolution through the Civil War. Series F: Selections from
            the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library,
            Duke University, Part 4: North Carolina and Virginia plantations. Accession 38395, Personal papers collection,
            The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Purchased, 20 June 2000.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>The Records are arranged into 25 series. Series 1: The
         Bryant Bennett Papers, 1767-1902, document the life and work
         of Bryant Bennett, a Martin County, North Carolina merchant
         and planter. Includes mercantile accounts, plantation account
         books (1848-1883), slave records, deeds, promissory notes,
         property tax receipts, and letters sent to Bennett in the
         later years of his life concerning business and personal
         matters.</p>
         <p>Series 2: The Samuel Simpson Biddle Papers, 1764-1895,
         consist of business and personal correspondence of four
         generations of the Simpson and Biddle families of Craven
         County, North Carolina, principally those of John Simpson, his
         son Samuel, and his great-grandson Samuel Simpson Biddle. The
         early correspondence primarily concerns the Simpson and Biddle
         families mercantile and agricultural business interests and
         land dealings, but there is also correspondence related to the
         education of Biddle family members at various universities in
         North Carolina. Also some Civil War letters contain
         descriptions of campaigns, troop movements, camp life,
         epidemics, naval battles, Union prisoners, deserters, and
         various generals and politicians. This series also holds
         letters from ministers concerning the Baptist Church in east
         central North Carolina as well as some Baptist Church records.
         There also are notes, deeds, leases, wills, slave records, and
         invoices and receipts concerned with the business interests of
         the Simpson and Biddle families.</p>
         <p>Series 3: The Devereux Family Papers, 1776-1936, chiefly
         include the personal letters of Thomas Pollock Devereux, Sarah
         Elizabeth Devereux, John Devereux, and Margaret Mordecai
         Devereux, all of Wake County, North Carolina, and Robert L.
         Maitland of New York. Topics include: family matters, Civil
         War camp life, and the military careers of Devereux family
         members. Within this series there are also financial and legal
         papers concerning land disputes, surveys, and estate
         settlements. Also contained in these papers are a business
         ledger (1821-1839) of Thomas Pollock Devereux and a plantation
         account book (1842-1863) of John Devereux relating to the
         management of the Barrow, Montrose, and Runiroi plantations.
         These account books also contain extensive slave lists
         including names and birth, death, and purchase dates.</p>
         <p>Series 4: The William T. Bain Papers, 1850-1865,
         principally contain the family letters of William T. Bain, his
         wife and children sent to his daughter Mollie Bain Bitting,
         all of Wake County, North Carolina.The letters concern the
         plantation business, slaves and slave punishments, and
         national and regional politics.</p>
         <p>Series 5: The Major Bell Papers, 1853-1864, comprise the
         personal and business letters of Major Bell of Pasquotank
         County, North Carolina including letters from his daughter
         Christian Bell at Chowan Female College in North Carolina.</p>
         <p>Series 6: The E. A. Crudup Papers, 1857-1872, consist of
         two extremely detailed plantation diaries of Edward Alston
         Crudup of Franklin County, North Carolina. Information
         contained in the diaries includes accounts of slave expenses,
         slave names and other slave records, and accounts concerning
         crop conditions.</p>
         <p>Series 7: The John Buxton Williams Papers, 1804-1870,
         contain the personal correspondence of John Buxton Williams, a
         Warren County, North Carolina planter, and Henry G. Williams,
         a North Carolina General Assembly member, chiefly concerning
         agricultural affairs, the hiring and treatment of slaves.</p>
         <p>Series 8: The Lucy Cole Burwell Papers, 1751-1905, comprise
         the personal correspondence and letters of Lucy Cole Burwell
         and the Burwell family of Mecklenburg County, Virginia, and
         Warren County, North Carolina. These papers document the
         social life of an agrarian family over four generations. The
         series also includes a ledger (1807-1807) for Lewis A. Burwell
         of Mecklenburg County, and an account book (1866-1868) for the
         Mecklenburg County mercantile firm White and Burwell.</p>
         <p>Series 9: The William Massie Papers, 1766-1882, include the
         papers of William Massie, his brother Thomas and their father
         Thomas, all plantation owners in Nelson County, Virginia. The
         collection contains letters exchanged between family members
         concerning family matters and business letters between the
         family and mercantile firms in Lynchburg and Richmond,
         Virginia; and Maryland. There are also a less amount of
         letters concerning William Massie's political career and the
         Civil War. This series also has indentures, deeds,
         genealogies, the estate records of William and Thomas Massie,
         an architect's drawings of the plantation buildings and
         landscape (1847-1862), plantation account ledgers (1817-1857),
         surveys, and a weather notebook (1858-1860).</p>
         <p>Series 10: The Hugh Minor and Peter Carr Minor Papers,
         1812-1870, principally consist of the plantation records of
         Peter Carr Minor, agricultural reformer and owner of Ridgeway
         Plantation in Albemarle County,Virginia, and his son Hugh
         Minor. Includes plantation account books and agricultural
         notebooks concerning plantation operations and production, and
         the weather. Also contains the agricultural notebooks of Hugh
         Minor, including a rather full description of Ridgeway
         Plantation. The estate accounts (1816-1835) of Peter Carr
         Minor are also within this series.</p>
         <p>Series 11: The Isaac Butler Papers, 1816-1907, contain the
         personal correspondence and business records of Isaac Butler
         and the Butler family of Caroline County, Virginia; and
         Florida, Illinois, New York and Ohio. Includes letters
         exchanged between Butler family members concerning family
         matters, business activities in relation to their tobacco
         plantation, and general social and economic conditions. The
         letters post-dating Isaac Butler's death principally consist
         of a long correspondence between Isaac's son Thomas Butler and
         his uncle Leland W. Butler. Also in this series are the estate
         records of Isaac Butler and an undated plantation account
         book.</p>
         <p>Series 12: The Sterling Neblett Papers, 1821-1871, are the
         business and personal letters of Sterling Neblett, physician
         and planter of Lunenburg County, Virginia, and Mississippi.
         Topics include: the purchase and sale of land in Virginia,
         legal difficulties selling slaves in Mississippi and
         Louisiana, and his plantation and business affairs.</p>
         <p>Series 13: The Green W. Penn Papers, 1764-1894, consist of
         the personal and business correspondence of the Green W. Penn
         and the Penn family of Henry and Patrick Counties, Virginia.
         Principal topics include: the tobacco culture, westward
         migration, life in the South, Virginia politics, religious
         life, Civil War battle campaigns, camp life and sickness, the
         economic conditions during Reconstruction, presidential
         elections, and manumission.</p>
         <p>Series 14: William H. E. Merritt Papers, 1834-1889, contain
         the family and business correspondence of William H. E.
         Merritt, Brunswick County, Virginia legislator and plantation
         owner. The correspondence principally concerns the purchase
         and sale of slaves, slave manumissions, camp life in the
         Confederate States of America Army, Civil War battle
         campaigns, and conditions of African-Americans after
         manumission. Also includes plantation accounts, invoices, and
         receipts.</p>
         <p>Series 15: The Henry Clark Papers, 1806-1845, comprise the
         business and personal letters, invoices, receipts, legal
         papers, and checks of Henry Clark, a Campbell County, Virginia
         tobacco planter.</p>
         <p>Series 16: George Dromgoole and Richard B. Robinson Papers,
         1767-1974, are composed of the papers of George Coke
         Dromgoole, Edward Dromgoole, and other members of the
         Dromgoole family of Brunswick County, Virginia, including
         Richard B. Robinson, George Dromgoole's nephew. The papers of
         George Coke Dromgoole include a large number of letters
         concerning plantation operations and production, Virginia
         politics, and Dromgoole family matters. The papers of Richard
         B. Robinson include correspondence, business records, and a
         daybook (1848-1868). The papers of Edward Dromgoole largely
         comprise plantation business records including receipts, sales
         accounts, and business letters concerning farm management.
         This series also contains daybooks, plantation account books
         including an account book of slaves (1843-1865) with slave
         birth dates, estate records of Thomas Dromgoole, and Dromgoole
         family genealogical notes.</p>
         <p>Series 17: The William C. Adams Papers, 1817-1897, consist
         of the business records and diary (1829-1897) of William C.
         Adams, a prosperous Albemarle County, Virginia planter. Items
         include a plantation account book (1817-1824) and a plantation
         ledger (1838-1865) both containing information concerning farm
         operations and production. Diary topics include: plantation
         operations, crop production, slaves, legal matters, travel,
         Adams family matters, camp life in the Confederate States of
         America Army, and activities in the slave patrol.</p>
         <p>Series 18: The John Woodall Papers, 1837-1905, are the
         family letters exchanged between John Woodall, a Prince Edward
         County, Virginia, plantation overseer, and his brother William
         Woodall, a poor farmer in Halifax County, Virginia. The
         letters concern social and agricultural conditions of poorer
         tobacco farmers and the general migration westward of small
         farmers following the Civil War. There are also some letters
         from Thomas T. Treadway, owner of the plantation John Woodall
         managed, regarding plantation operations and treatment of
         slaves.</p>
         <p>Series 19: The Philip Ludwell Lee Papers, 1743-1783,
         consist of a plantation account ledger containing lists of
         items purchased for the plantation. The accounts were kept by
         Philip Ludwell Lee, tobacco planter of Stratford plantation,
         Westmoreland County, Virginia; although, some accounts pertain
         to the estate of his father, Thomas Lee.</p>
         <p>Series 20: The Nathaniel Price Papers, 1789-1861,
         principally are the correspondence, financial papers, and
         account books chiefly related to the management of the
         plantation owned by Nathaniel Price of Prince Edward County,
         Virginia. Also contained in the account books are the estate
         papers of James Price, Sr. and William Price for whom
         Nathaniel Price was the executor.</p>
         <p>Series 21: The James M. Wilcox Papers, 1831-1871, chiefly
         contain the letters of the Wilcox and Lamb families of Charles
         City County, Virginia, united by the marriage of James M.
         Wilcox, a planter and member of the House of Delegates, and
         Mary Ann S. Lamb. These letters afford an excellent record of
         operations at Wilcox's plantations, Peace Hill and Buckland,
         and Wilcox family relations during the late antebellum, Civil
         War, and Reconstruction periods. Other topics include: social
         life in Charles City County, horse racing, Nat Turner's
         Rebellion, slave activities, the condition of Monticello,
         epidemics, effects of the Civil War on planting, and Civil War
         campaigns and camp life.</p>
         <p>Series 22: The B. J. Dalby Account Books, 1855-1858,
         contain the plantation records of Wilsonia, the plantation
         estate of William E. Taylor of Northampton County, Virginia,
         as kept by Benjamin J. Dalby, the manager and overseer. These
         account books include inventories of slaves and livestock,
         records of crop production, and records of slave holidays and
         work days.</p>
         <p>Series 23: The Frederick A. Harris Papers, 1817-1844,
         consist of the family and business correspondence of Frederick
         A. Harris, a Campbell County, Virginia farmer. Principal
         correspondents include his brothers William Harris and
         Hannibal Harris. Topics include: farm management, effects of
         the Panic of 1819 on Virginia farmers, crop production,
         slaves, and westward migration.</p>
         <p>Series 24: The Lewis Family Papers, 1802-1852, comprise
         letters from Alexander Wood, overseer of Audley Farm in Clarke
         County, Virginia, to the owner Lawrence Lewis (1767-1839). The
         letters give details of plantation production and crop and
         slave sales. Other letters in this series are from Wood to
         Lorenzo Lewis, Lawrence Lewis' son. Also contains a Lewis
         family genealogy.</p>
         <p>Series 25: The Samuel Bryarly Papers, 1787-1884,
         principally are the letters of Samuel Bryarly (d. 1850), a
         Clarke County, Virginia planter, relating to agricultural
         conditions in Virginia, and in Mississippi, Ohio and
         Tennessee, where several Bryarly family members had relocated.
         There also are plantation account books, a scrapbook of
         Richard and Rowland Bryarly, the estate records of Samuel
         Bryarly, and the letters of Richard Bryarly.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Organization</head>
         <p>Organized into twenty-five series: 1) Bryant Bennett Papers
         (misc. reels 2584-2585); 2) Samuel Simpson Biddle Papers
         (misc. reels 2585-2589); 3) Devereux Family Papers (misc.
         reels 2589-2590); 4) William T. Bain papers (misc. reel 2590);
         5) Major Bell Papers (misc. reel 2590); 6) E. A. Crudup Papers
         (misc. reel 2590); 7) John Buxton Williams Papers (misc. reel
         2591); 8) Lucy Cole Burwell Papers (misc. reels 2591-2593); 9)
         William Massie Papers (misc. reels 2593-2595); 10) Hugh Minor
         and Peter Carr Minor Papers (misc. reels 2595-2596); 11) Isaac
         Butler Papers (misc. reels 2596-2597); 12) Sterling Neblett
         Papers (misc.reels 2597-2598); 13) Green W. Penn Papers (misc.
         reel 2598); 14) William H. E. Merritt Papers (misc. reel
         2599); 15) Henry Clark Papers (misc. reel 2599); 16) George
         Dromgoole and Richard B. Robinson Papers (misc. reels
         2599-2603); 17) William C. Adams Papers (misc. reels
         2603-2604); 18) John Woodall Papers (misc. reel 2604); 19)
         Philip Ludwell Lee Papers (misc. reel 2604); 20) Nathaniel
         Price Papers (misc. reels 2604-2605); 21) James M. Wilcox
         Papers (misc. reels 2605-2606); 22) B. J. Dalby Papers (misc.
         reels 2606-2607); 23) Frederick A. Harris Papers (misc. reel
         2607); 24) Lewis Family Papers (misc. reel 2607); 25) Samuel
         Bryarly Papers (misc. reels 2607- 2608).</p>
      </arrangement>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
