<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi00093">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00093::A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Free Black Records, 1833-1863)//EN" "vi00093.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Free Black Records, <date>1833-1863</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Free Black Records, 1833-1863
<num type="collectionnumber">APA 757
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Renee M. Savits
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2016  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Renee M. Savits, <date>12 May 2016</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Free Black Records,<date>1833-1863</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">APA 757
</num>
</subtitle>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2016 
</date>

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Renee M. Savits
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>


<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Free Black Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1833-1863
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">APA 757
</unitid>
<physloc label="">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>cu. ft. (4 boxes)</extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>These materials are available on microfilm [Misc. reels 1320-1323] and should be served instead of the originals. It should be noted that the filming was done previously and does not follow the current arrangement of the papers.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928). Free Black Records, 1833-1863. Accession APA 757, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>PUBLIC SERVICE CLAIMS FOR SLAVES AND FREE BLACKS: During
         the antebellum period the General Assembly passed increasingly
         restrictive laws in response to white fears of slave crime and
         insurrection. Procedures were established to compensate
         slaveholders for the loss of their property when slaves ran
         away or were imprisoned or executed. Some condemned slaves
         were transported beyond the state's boundaries to Africa. The
         American Colonization Society chartered ships to transport
         free negroes and condemned slaves to Liberia.</p>
      <p>Free blacks were discouraged from remaining in Virginia
         because their presence was a contradiction of the concept of
         black slavery. Restrictive laws and special taxes, as well as
         official support for emigration to Liberia, prompted many free
         blacks to leave. A few were reenslaved "voluntarily" because
         of debt or criminality. Occasionally a free black was
         authorized to remain in the state by a special act of the
         General Assembly for some "essential service".</p>
      <p>AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS: Although the colonial
         government had appointed auditors general from time to time,
         the office was not established on a permanent basis until
         after independence was declared. At its first session, which
         convened on 7 October 1776, the General Assembly passed an act
         creating a board of three auditors to examine and settle
         claims concerning receipts and expenditures for military
         purposes. The confusing financial situation of the state,
         however, resulted in a series of acts being passed over the
         next fifteen years elaborating and refining the duties of the
         auditors. Finally, at its session begun in November 1791, the
         General Assembly passed an act that combined the duties of the
         board of auditors and the solicitor general, whose office had
         been created in 1785 to settle the accounts of the state with
         the United States, and assigned them to a single auditor of
         public accounts effective 1 January 1792. The auditor soon
         became the most powerful fiscal officer in the state. All
         receipts and disbursements were made only upon his warrant to
         the treasurer, and his books were the standard against which
         those of the treasurer were checked.</p>
      <p>The first changes were made as the accounts of the
         revolutionary era were settled. As the state moved into a
         period of steady financial and governmental growth in the
         nineteenth century, the number of accounts and funds
         maintained by the auditor became excessive. Thus, on 24
         February 1823 the General Assembly passed an act creating the
         office of the second auditor to ease the auditor's burden.
         Although the second auditor handled several large special
         funds, the auditor continued to be responsible for most of the
         accounts concerning the daily operation of state
         government.</p>
      <p>During the Civil War both the state government and the
         pro-Union Restored Government of Virginia, which was based
         first in Wheeling and then in Alexandria, had auditors of
         public accounts. After the war, near the end of
         Reconstruction, the military authorities appointed Major
         Thaddeus H. Stanton, of the United States Army, as auditor of
         public accounts. Stanton was paid by the state during his
         service from 3 April 1869 to 12 February 1870, although he
         remained an army officer. The position was returned to
         civilian control on 12 February 1870 with the election of
         William F. Taylor as auditor by the General Assembly.</p>
      <p>Following the Civil War the complexities of an increasingly
         sophisticated financial world threatened to overwhelm the
         state fiscal offices, which had changed their practices but
         little since the end of the eighteenth century. Inadequate
         bookkeeping procedures and embezzlements of state funds
         resulted in a public demand for corrective action. It was not
         until a state government reorganization act was passed by the
         General Assembly on 18 April 1927, however, that the demand
         was satisfied. Effective 1 March 1928 the office of auditor of
         public accounts and second auditor were abolished and replaced
         by the office of comptroller--head of the Department of
         Accounts--to monitor the receipt and disbursement of state
         funds, and a new office of auditor of public accounts, under
         the General Assembly, to audit state and local government
         agencies.</p>
      <p>The records of the first auditor of public accounts have
         not survived intact; periodically they have been subjected to
         disarrangement or destruction. When the auditor's office was
         created in 1776, Virginia's seat of government was in
         Williamsburg. In 1780, when the capital was moved to Richmond,
         the auditors and their records also moved. At this time, and
         during Benedict Arnold's raid on Richmond in 1781, some
         auditor's records were misplaced or destroyed. During the War
         of 1812, when it was believed that British troops were
         marching on Richmond, the state's records were loaded onto
         wagons and hauled to the James River for transportation
         upstream. Before the boats sailed, however, the alarm proved
         false and the records were unloaded and returned to the State
         Capitol.</p>
      <p>The next threat to the auditor's records came on the night
         of 2-3 April 1865, when the evacuation fire broke out as the
         Confederate garrison abandoned the city. Fortunately, the
         auditor's records escaped the flames because they were stored
         in the basement and attic of the State Capitol, which did not
         burn. Following the capture of Richmond by Union troops,
         however, a detachment of the Twentieth New York Infantry
         Regiment served as a guard in the Capitol building and browsed
         through the records of the state's fiscal offices (sometimes
         recording candid opinions concerning the late Confederacy in
         the margins of ledgers and journals). After the state library
         building was completed on the east side of Capitol Square in
         the late 1890's the auditor's office moved into it and the
         older records were stored in the basement. There they remained
         until 1913, when they were transferred to the custody of the
         state library.</p>
    </bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Records
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title with oversize materials arranged to the rear.</p>


</arrangement>

<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
    <c01 level="file">
  	<did>
  	<unittitle>Acts of Assembly, 
  	<unitdate type="inclusive">1833</unitdate>.</unittitle>
  	<container label="Box" type="box">1
  	</container>
  	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
  	</container>
  		</did>
  		</c01>
  		
  		
  		
  		</dsc>
  		</archdesc>
  		</ead>
  	
