<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi00883">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00883::Virginia Military Institute, Records, 1837-1850)//EN" "vi00883.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Military Institute Records, <date>1837-1850 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia Military Institute Records, 1837-1850
<num type="collectionnumber">36739
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">1 KB
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft Word, created by Craig S. Moore, <date>2005 October 4 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Military Institute Records, <date>1837-1850 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">36739
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Craig S. Moore
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Virginia Military Institute Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1837-1850
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">36739
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.36 cubic feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia Military Institute, Records, 1837-1850. Accession 36739. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Acquired prior to 1905.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>On March 29, 1839 the General Assembly passed the final version of the act establishing a military school at the Lexington Arsenal, where the students would protect the arms while pursuing educational courses.
The School was named the Virginia Military Institute and is the nation's oldest state supported military college. The governor appointed nine members to the Board of Visitors to oversee the new school and they
elected Claudius Crozet as president of the board and named Francis H. Smith as the first superintendent. On November 11, 1839 the first corps of cadets reported to VMI and officially replaced the arsenal guard.
Cadets to this day perform guard duty and serve the state as a military corps.
</p>
<p>VMI is a state-supported, totally undergraduate college organized under the laws of the commonwealth of Virginia and is governed by a Board of Visitors appointed by the governor. The challenging military
portion of the VMI program is a distinctive aspect of the VMI college experience, and reflects the Institute's debt to the United States Military Academy and the Ecole Polytechique in France. All students at VMI
are members of the Corps of Cadets and all participate in officer training programs associated with Army, Naval or Air Force ROTC. In accordance with the Code of Virginia, the cadets constitute a military corps.
Historically, about twenty percent of VMI's graduates have chosen military careers. Members of the faculty and staff are commissioned in the Virginia Militia by the governor, who serves as ex-officio commander-in-
chief. While the military program is an important aspect of the educational experience, the VMI program is specifically designed to produce leaders for peace or war.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Virginia Military Institute records are housed in one archival box and are arranged in chronological order between 1837 and 1850. The records include correspondence, reports, merit rolls, returns, accounts,
lists, proceedings, statements, and other sundry items. Reports by the Board of Visitors and Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute represent the most significant documents within these records. The
President of the Board of Visitors submits annual reports from the superintendent to the governor, and later, adjutant general. The first report of the Board of Visitors relates to the inspection of the public
arms at the Lexington Arsenal according to the law constituting the Board of Visitors of the military school proposed to be established at the Arsenal (1837 Aug. 8). On 2 November 1839, the Board of Visitors writes
to Governor David Campbell certifying that the school is ready to go into operation and that a sufficient number of students or cadets have been admitted to guard the public arms and other property at the
Lexington Arsenal. The Visitors also ask that the public guard at the Arsenal be disbanded and that the public property be transferred to the Virginia Military Institute. On 21 January 1840, Claudius Crozet,
President of the Board of Visitors, transmits the first report of Maj. Francis H. Smith, Principal Professor and later Superintendent, to Governor David Campbell which includes quarterly merit &amp; conduct rolls.
Reports to subsequent governors enclose items such as lists of new cadets, merit rolls, accounts, lists of graduates, returns of arms &amp; ordnance, and statements on the condition of the various departments. In
addition to reports, Jacob M. Ruff, Treasurer, corresponds with William H. Richardson, Adjutant General, enclosing a statement of the accounts of the Virginia Military Institute from its commencement to 11 July
1842 (1842 Sept. 1). There are also proceedings by the Board of Visitors regarding charges preferred against Capt. Thomas H. Williamson by Col. Francis H. Smith for gross insubordination, etc. (1845 Sept. 24).
Lastly, the report of the Board of Visitors from 4 July 1850, encloses Smith's report to Philip St. George Cocke, President Pro Tem. This report includes a merit roll of cadets; statements exhibiting the condition
of the finances, Quarter Master's Department, Subsistence Department, &amp; Tailor's Department; the account of R. E. Colston, Treasurer; an account of the current expenses &amp; Sinking Fund of the Subsistence
Department; and a statement of monthly &amp; daily consumption of provisions at the Cadets Commons &amp; Hospital.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged in chronological order.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<separatedmaterial>
<head>Separated Material
</head>
<p>Oversized materials separated to Miscellaneous Oversized Box.
</p>
</separatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>
<emph render="bold">Virginia Military Institute Records
</emph>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>1837-1840
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="Folder" type="Folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1841-1845
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="Folder" type="Folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1848
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="Folder" type="Folder">3
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1850
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="Folder" type="Folder">4
</container>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>
<emph render="bold">Oversized
</emph>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<unittitle>1840-1850
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="Folder" type="Folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
