<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi00285">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00285::A Guide to the Clark-Buchanan Family Letters, 1862-1864 and undated)//EN" "vi00285.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clark-Buchanan Family Letters, <date>1862-1864 and undated</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">Clark-Buchanan Family, Letters, 1862-1864 and undated
<num type="collectionnumber">42855
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Jessica Tyree
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;

<date type="publication">&copy; 2007 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Jessica Tyree, <date>20 September 2007</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clark-Buchanan Family Letters, <date>1862-1864 and undated</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">42855
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Jessica Tyree
</author>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2007
</date> &contact;

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Jessica Tyree
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Clark-Buchanan Family Letters, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1862-1864 and undated
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">42855 (Miscellaneous reel 5229)
</unitid>

<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1 reel of microfilm
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>

<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Clark-Buchanan family
</origination>
</did>

<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Clark-Buchanan Family Letters, 1861-1864 and undated. Accession 42854. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia. Originals in the collection of the Emory &amp; Henry College Archives, Emory, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loaned for microfilming by Emory &amp; Henry College, Emory, Virginia, on 18 September 2006.
</p>
</acqinfo>


</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>James Clark was born on 20 May 1830 in Glade Spring, Washington County, Virginia, one of twelve sons of John Breckendridge Clark and Mary Beattie Clark. He married Martha Amanda Buchanan (b. ca. 1835) on 8 September 1858 in Rich Valley, Smyth County, Virginia. James Clark served with the 63rd Virginia Infantry Regiment, Company F, rising to the rank of captain. He was wounded in action at Murfreesboro, Tennessee, on 7 December 1864, and eventually was granted a medical furlough. Clark was still at home in Rich Valley when the war ended. His family with Martha grew to include seven children. James Clark died on 10 December 1911. Martha Clark's brother, Samuel T. Buchanan, served with the 48th Virginia Infantry Regiment, Company D, also attaining the rank of captain. He was captured at the Battle of Spotsylvania Court House on 12 May 1864 and transferred to the Union prison at Point Lookout, Maryland, where he died of an illness on 16 July 1864. Other Buchanan siblings, children of Wilson (b. ca. 1797) and Eliza Buchanan (b. ca. 1807) of Smyth County, include Nan (b. ca. 1831) and James C., or Jim (b. ca. 1842).</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Letters, 1862-1864 and undated, of the Clark and Buchanan families of Washington and Smyth Counties, Virginia. More than half of the letters in this collection were written by James Clark (1830-1911), chiefly to wife Martha Buchanan Clark (b. ca. 1835), while he served with the 63rd Virginia Infantry Regiment, Company F. Writing from various locations including Giles, Southampton, and Washington Counties, Virginia; Kanawha County, (West) Virginia; and Georgia, Clark's letters discuss his disdain for one's lack of freedom while in the army; camp life, including meals, sleeping accommodations, and religious observances; witnessing the severe punishment of deserters; rumors of upcoming battles and nearby Union troop movements; problems with ragged clothing and lice; his impressions of Confederate Generals Joseph Johnston (1807-1891) and William Wing Loring (1818-1886); a 20 January 1863 engagement at Kelly's Store near Suffolk, Virginia; and the Battle of Kolb's Farm near Marietta, Georgia, 22 June 1864.</p>

<p>Most of the Buchanan letters were written by Samuel T. Buchanan (ca. 1836-1864), 48th Virginia Infantry Regiment, Company D, to family members including sisters Martha Buchanan Clark and Nan Buchanan (b. ca. 1831). Writing from Culpeper, Orange, and Spotsylvania Counties, Virginia, and Maryland, Buchanan describes camp life and living conditions; his participation in the Battle of Gettysburg; grueling marches; a revival meeting in camp; witnessing the execution of ten deserters from a North Carolina regiment in September 1863; and April 1864 rumors of Union General Ulysses S. Grant's approach and his intention to take Richmond that spring. A letter to Martha from brother Jim Buchanan (b. ca. 1842) tells of Samuel's 12 May 1864 capture at Spotsylvania Court House; a 29 August 1864 letter from family friend and 50th Virginia Infantry Regiment officer Clayton Hubble (d. 1864) informs father Wilson Buchanan of Samuel's death. Another letter, from Colonel Robert H. Dungan (1834-1903), also of the 48th Virginia, Company D, describes Samuel as a man of good nature and strong character.</p>
</scopecontent>


<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>

<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Originals are owned by Emory &amp; Henry College, Emory, Virginia.</p>
</originalsloc>

</descgrp>

<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Clark-Buchanan family letters</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1862-1864 and undated</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>



<container label="Miscellaneous reel" type="reel-frame">5229
</container>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 reel of microfilm.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>

</c01>

</dsc>

</archdesc>
</ead>






