<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi00993">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00993::A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009))//EN" "vi00993.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, <date>2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">Kaine, Governor Timothy M., Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
<num type="collectionnumber">44708
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Roger E. Christman
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Roger E. Christman, <date>3 January 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, <date>2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44708
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Roger E. Christman
</author>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2014 
</date>

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Roger E. Christman
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44708
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">90824 emails (on-going).
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>



<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, many records pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>

<p>Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+42.1-78">42.1-78</extref>
, <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-3800">2.2-3800</extref>
 and <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-3705.1">2.2-3705.1-8</extref>
. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: pardon files granted and denied, restoration of rights granted and denied, privacy protected information, appointment of special counsel, and attorney-client privileged material. 
</p>

</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.  The Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, collection is accessible on line.  Researchers are strongly urged to view the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">Kaine email web site</extref>
 for search tips, related content and project information.  Despite the Library's best efforts, we knew it was possible for restricted information to be overlooked during the processing of this collection. Thus we created a virtual "reading room agreement" by creating a secure gateway to the online collection. In order to view the Kaine emails, users must log in using a generic account that the Library created for this collection. By logging in, users are acknowledging their researcher responsibilities regarding protected materials.  
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Governor (2006-2010 : Kaine), Electronic Files, Email, of the Administration of Governor Timothy M. Kaine, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), Accession 44708, State Records Collection, Library of Virginia 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>David Allen, Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, accession 44708 transferred on 25 January 2010. 
</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>

<p>The electronic files, including email, from the Governor Tim Kaine administration were transferred to the Library of Virginia on a hard drive. The files on the hard drive were loaded on the Library's secure dark archive and replicated on an off-site server. The electronic files were also loaded on to the processing server accessible to the processing archivists. All processing was done from the copied files on the processing server. Prior to processing, the Governors' Records Archivist compiled an inventory of each email pst file. The processing archivist noted the file name, name and title of box owner, date range, file size in KB and total number of email files. This information was categorized by office or cabinet secretariat. 
</p>

<p>Starting with the Executive Office, the processing archivist reviewed each email message to determine: if the email was a public record with a permanent disposition and/or if it should be restricted for legal, medical or personal privacy issues. The processing archivist consulted the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/retention_schedules/">office specific</extref>


 and <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/index.htm">general records retention and disposition schedules</extref>
 for guidance. The processing archivist used the category function available in Microsoft Outlook to color code non-records and restricted records. Non-records/non-permanent records include: personal or private correspondence, meeting requests/scheduling meetings (including RSVPs and going to lunch), administrative files (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule 101, series 100302</extref>
), declined invitations, travel arrangements, parking assignments (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 100345</extref>
), vacation or work schedules (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 100385</extref>
), leave records (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-102.pdf">General Schedule No. 102, series 012136</extref>
), computer problems, press releases and news clips (record copy is filed with Press Office), logistics for the Governor's Fellowship program, travel logistics for the governor, Executive Protections Unit contact information, conflict of interest files (Specific Schedule No. 166-001, 015120), grievance records and reports (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-103.pdf">General Schedule No. 103, series 100490</extref>
), unsolicited applications and resumes (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-103.pdf">General Schedule No. 103, series 100503</extref>
), legal summons (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule 101, series 100334</extref>
), voice mail messages (General Schedule No. 101, series 100388), invoices (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-102.pdf">General Schedule No. 102, series 012082</extref>
), disaster and emergency planning files (General Schedule 108, series 012274 building maintenance/space utilization (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-106.PDF">General Schedule No. 106, series 012232</extref>
), and Freedom of Information Act Requests (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 012029</extref>
). The processing archivist made an exception for two FOIA requests that were deemed of historic value since the requests led to policy changes. Delegate Scott Lingamfelter's FOIA requests for how much state government spent on printing led to a near ban on state publications. After Governor Tim Kaine became chairman of the Democratic National Committee in January 2009, media outlets submitted FOIA requests for his daily schedule. The Kaine administration did not provide the schedule but did release the cities to which he traveled. 
</p>

<p>Processed copies of the email PST files were then passed on to the Library's information technology department for the technical phase of the project.  
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-126">Section 2.2-126 of the Code of Virginia</extref>
 states that governor's records of a strictly personal or private nature are not public records and do not have to be transferred to the Library of Virginia. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/retention_schedules/121-001%20Office%20of%20the%20Governor.pdf">The Office of the Governor Records Retention and Disposition Schedule (Specific Schedule No. 121-100)</extref>
 further states that personal or private papers of the governor are non-records per the Virginia Public Records Act. Types of records may include but are not limited to correspondence with family or friends, personal business records and records of/from political organizations, not related to the role of the Governor or the Governor's staff. Only a small number of email messages met this definition and were removed from the collection. 
</p>

</processinfo>

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Timothy M. Kaine was born on 26 February 1958 in St. Paul, Minnesota. He grew up in Kansas City and graduated from the University of Missouri-Columbia in 1979. While attending Harvard Law School, Kaine took a leave of absence to work with Jesuit missionaries as principal of the Institution Tecnico Loyola, a Catholic vocational school in El Progreso, Honduras. Kaine graduated from Harvard Law School in 1983 and was admitted to the Virginia Bar. Practicing law in Richmond, Virginia, as director of the McCandlish Kaine law firm, Kaine specialized in housing discrimination cases. He received recognition from the Richmond Bar Association, the National Fair Housing Association, and Lawyers for Public Justice for his work with civil rights. In addition, Kaine taught legal ethics for six years at the University of Richmond Law School.
</p>

<p>Kaine began his political career with an election to the Richmond City Council in 1994, serving as mayor from 1998 to 2001. During his four terms in the Richmond City Council, Kaine helped build new schools, encourage economic development, and implement the Project Exile Program to reduce violent crime. In 2001, Kaine ran for the Democratic Party nomination for Lieutenant Governor and won with 64,008 votes (39.66%). His opponents were Delegate Alan Diamonstein, with 50,753 votes (31.45%) and Del. Jerrauld C. Jones with 46,640 votes (28.90%). On 6 November 2001 Kaine was elected Lieutenant Governor with 925,974 votes (50.35%), defeating Republican Delegate Jay Katzen (883,886 votes, 48.86%) and Libertarian Gary Reams (28,783 votes, 1.57%). As Lieutenant Governor under Governor Mark R. Warner, Kaine supported state budget reform, education improvements, and the public broadcasting of the General Assembly. He served on the Governor's K-12 Accountability Workgroup, the Governor's Higher Education Summit, the Workforce Training Sub-Committee, the Secure Virginia Panel, the Citizens and Committees Sub-Committee, and chairman of the Disability Commission. In addition, Kaine worked on the Affordable Housing Preservation Action Committee, the Virginia Military Advisory Council, and the Olmstead Task Force.
</p>

<p>Kaine sought the governorship in 2005. On 8 November 2005, Kaine was elected Governor with 1,025,942 votes (51.72%) defeating Republican Attorney General Jerry Kilgore (912,327 votes, 45.99%) and Independent State Senator Russ Potts (43,953 votes, 2.22%). Tim Kaine became the 70th Governor of Virginia on 14 January 2006. 
</p>

<p>The Kaine administration was dominated by three issues: budget deficits, transportation funding and the 16 April 2007 shootings at Virginia Tech. Governor Kaine took office shortly before the beginning of the "Great Recession", the worst economic downturn since the Great Depression of the 1930s. From 2007 to the end of his administration in January 2010, Kaine cut nearly $5 billion in state spending in order to balance the budget without raising taxes. Despite these cuts, Virginia retained its AAA bond rating and in 2008 was ranked as the best managed state in America by Governing Magazine. Virginia was also named as the most business-friendly state in America for 2006, 2007, 2008 and 2009 by Forbes.com.
</p>

<p>Despite several attempts, the Kaine administration was unable to find a reliable source of transportation funding. Kaine's 2006 proposal of increased taxes and fees was rejected by the Republican-controlled House of Delegates. In 2007 Kaine reached agreement with the Republican General Assembly on a compromise transportation package. It was the biggest transportation funding increase since 1986. The plan did not include a statewide tax increase but authorized borrowing up to $3 billion over ten years. It also granted taxing powers to regional authorities in Northern Virginia and Tidewater to support $500 million in bond-financed transportation projects. Success was short lived. One section of the legislation on abuser driver fees drew extensive criticism when it was discovered that the fees only applied to Virginians and not out-of-state residents. The General Assembly later repealed this provision. In early 2008 the Virginia Supreme Court ruled that unelected regional authorities could not raise taxes. In May 2008 Kaine proposed a new transportation plan that called for an increase in vehicle registration fees and the sales tax. A 2008 special session on transportation funding ended without an agreement.
</p>

<p>On 16 April 2007, Seung Hui Cho killed 32 people and injured at least 17 others before turning the gun on himself. The massacre at Virginia Tech is the deadliest shooting incident by a single gunman in United States history. At the time of the shooting, Governor Kaine had just arrived in Tokyo, Japan, for a trade mission. Kaine immediately returned to Virginia to deliver the convocation at Virginia Tech the next day. On 19 April 2007, Kaine commissioned the Virginia Tech Review Panel "to conduct an independent, thorough, and objective incident review of the tragedy at Virginia Tech and to make recommendations regarding improvements that can be made in the Commonwealth's laws, policies, procedures, systems and institutions, as well as those of other governmental entities and private providers." Kaine formalized the Tech Panel's charge in Executive Order 53 (2007) issued on 18 June 2007. Colonel Gerald Massengill, a retired Virginia State Police Superintendent, chaired the Panel. The Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel was released on 30 August 2007. It revealed deficiencies in the mental health care system, campus security and gun laws. The Panel made more than 70 recommendations directed to colleges, universities, mental health providers, law enforcement officials, emergency service providers and law makers. The General Assembly passed legislation to reform the mental health commitment laws and campus security policies. One major recommendation by the Panel was defeated: requiring background checks for all firearms purchased at gun shows.
</p>

<p>In April 2008, the state reached an $11 million financial settlement with 24 families of students and faculty who were killed or injured during the Virginia Tech shooting. The state agreed to provide monetary pay outs, medical care and information on the shooting in exchange for the families to waive their rights to sue. Two families who filed claims against the state did not accept the settlement and filed a civil suit in 2009. The discovery of Cho's Cook Counseling Center records in July 2009 and other concerns by family members about the Panel's timeline for 16 April 2007, lead to calls for the Panel to reconvene. Kaine did not reconvene the Panel but agreed to have the report revised to reflect the new details that surfaced since 2007. The amended report was released in the last month of the Kaine administration. On 12 March 2012, a jury in the civil suit found Virginia Tech negligent in failing to warn students of a possible gunman on campus. 
</p>

<p>Other significant accomplishments of the Kaine administration include: a ban on smoking in bars and restaurants, funding to clean up the Chesapeake Bay, the preservation of over 400,000 acres of open spaces, passage of a $1.6 billion bond package for higher education construction projects, expanding pre-K education, required teacher evaluations, and Renew Virginia Initiatives (energy).
</p>

<p>During his term, Governor Kaine served as chairman of the Southern Governors' Association (2008-2009) and Chairman of the Democratic National Committee (2009-2011). On 6 November 2012, Kaine was elected United States Senator with 2,010,067 votes (52.86%) defeating Republican George Allen (1,785,542 votes, 46.96%).
</p>

<p>Kaine is married to Anne Bright Holton, youngest daughter of former Governor Linwood Holton. Anne and Tim have three children, Nat, Woody, and Annella.
</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>These records include agreements, briefing books, reports, correspondence, memorandums, agendas, electronic mail, handouts, invitations, meeting notes, press releases (drafts), spreadsheets (budget), talking points, and speeches. This collection documents the email of the Kaine Administration (2006-2010). The Library of Virginia is releasing the Kaine email in batches.  Future releases will include email from the Policy Office and Communication Office.  This collection contains email from staff members who also worked in Governor Mark R. Warner's administration (2002-2006) including William H. Leighty and Margaret Hughson. To access the Kaine email collection and to learn more about other Kaine administration records, click <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">here</extref>
.
</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Tim Kaine Email, 2007-2010</item>
<item>Subseries B. Lawrence Roberts Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries C. Mark Rubin Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries D. Shane Emmett Email, 2008-2010</item>
<item>Subseries E. William H. Leighty Email, 2002-2007</item>
<item>Subseries F. Wayne Turnage Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries G. Stephen Harms Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries H. Marc Follmer Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries I. Sherrie Harrington Email, 2007-2010</item>
<item>Subseries J. Kate Paris Email, 2006-2010</item>
<item>Subseries K. Margaret Hughson Email, 2005-2007</item>
<item>Subseries L. Sarah Plumb Email, 2007-2008</item>
<item>Subseries M. Beau Cribbs Email, 2007-2010</item>
<item>Subseries N. Bryce Schunke Email, 2009</item>
<item>Subseries O. Sarah Robertson Email, 2009</item>
</list>

</arrangement>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>

<p>
<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00978.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records, 2005-2009.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00982.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records, 2006-2009.</extref></p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00983.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, Records, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00984.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00986.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Press Office, Records, 2004-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.archive-it.org/collections/263">Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00987.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Records, 2006-2009.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00988.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Latino Liaison Records, 2004-2009. </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03050.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2005-2010. </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04330.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04328.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Technology, 2000-2009 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>


<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 90824 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Executive Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Executive Office of the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 90824 emails in 15 subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Tim Kaine Email; B. Lawrence Roberts Email; C. Mark Rubin Email; D. Shane Emmett Email; E. William H. Leighty Email; F. Wayne Turnage Email; G. Stephen Harms Email; H. Marc Follmer Email; I. Sherrie Harrington Email; J. Kate Paris Email; K. Margaret Hughson Email; L. Sarah Plumb Email; M. Beau Cribbs Email; N. Bryce Schunke Email; and O. Sarah Robertson Email.  There are 13594 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.  On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 10808 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.  
</p>


<p>The Executive Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. Members of the Executive Office include the Governor, Chief of Staff, Counselor to the Governor and their deputies and assistants. The Governor is the Chief Executive of the Commonwealth and chief advocate for annual legislative and budget priorities. Sherrie Harrington served as Confidential Assistant to Governor Tim Kaine.
</p>



<p>The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government, responsible for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office. The Chief is assisted in these responsibilities by a Deputy Chief of Staff and an Executive Assistant. The following individuals held these positions during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010): William H. Leighty, Chief of Staff (January 2006-May 2007); Wayne Turnage, Deputy Chief of Staff, (January 2006-May 2007) and Chief of Staff (May 2007-2010); Margaret Hughson, Executive Assistant (2006-2007); Steve Harms, Deputy Chief of Staff (June 2007-2010); and Kate Paris, Confidential Assistant to the Chief of Staff and Counselor (2007-2010).
</p>



<p>The Counselor in the Kaine administration provided legal advice to the Governor and acted as a liaison with the judiciary and the Office of the Attorney General. The Counselor also provided broader advice to the Governor on political and personal matters as assigned. The Counselor was the chief liaison with the Democratic Party, the Moving Virginia Forward PAC, and outside political constituency groups. The Counselor was assisted in these responsibilities by a Senior Advisor, a hybrid position, who provided legal assistance to the Counselor and legislative assistance to the Policy Director. The Senior Advisor was available to mediate important policy disputes for the Governor, or with the Governor's consent, for legislators and other external constituents. The following individuals held these positions during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010): Lawrence Roberts, Counselor to the Governor (January 2006-May 2009) and Mark E. Rubin, Senior Advisor to the Governor and Deputy Counselor (January 2006-May 2009) and Counselor to the Governor (May 2009-January 2010).
</p>



<p>The Leadership Team in the Office of the Governor consisted of the Chief of Staff, Deputy Chief of Staff, Counselor, Senior Advisor, Policy Director, Legislative Director, Communications Director, Scheduling Director and Press Secretary.  This group conducted daily morning meetings in preparation for that day's events in the Governor's Office. The Governor held regular meetings with this group and in certain instances convened small subsets of the Leadership Team to address specific or more targeted issues.  
</p>


</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries A. Tim Kaine Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 3875 emails in three pst files:  <emph render="bold">TKAINE.PST</emph>, <emph render="bold">KaineLibkaine.pst</emph>, and <emph render="bold">TKAINE59404639.pst</emph>.  Governor Kaine's email did not have a file structure.  Governor Kaine archived his own email.  In an email from Kaine, dated 30 December 2009, to Mark Rubin, Counselor to the Governor, and Sherrie Harrington, Confidential Assistant to the Governor, Kaine stated he had "now gone through all emails from May 07 until current.  David Allen [VITA/NG] was not able to find earlier emails."  However, email messages Kaine sent from January 2006 to April 2007 may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine administration (Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Wayne Turnage, Bill Leighty, etc.).
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibkaine.pst</emph> contains 10 emails between Governor Kaine and Marc Follmer, Senior Advisor to the Governor.  The <emph render="bold">TKAINE59404639.pst</emph> contains 109 emails sent by the public to the GovKaine email account and were forwarded to Sasha Scott, Special Assistant in Constituent Services.  All of these emails comment on the University of Virginia's newspaper, The Cavalier Daily, publication of a cartoon attacking Christianity in 2008.
</p>
 


<p>The <emph render="bold">TKAINE.PST</emph> contains 3756 emails sent and received by Governor Kaine between April 2007 and January 2010.  There are 146 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted material may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.  On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 201 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident.  Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including creation and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, notes from meeting with family members and correspondence between Governor Kaine and family members; budget issues; transportation (drafts of June 2008 General Assembly special session speech, Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute, 2007 abusive driver fees); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2008, 2009 and 2010); Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative (includes Biscuit Run property in Albemarle County); blanket restoration of rights; clemency (Norfolk Four and Percy Walton-restricted); relocation of Northrup Grumman's corporate headquarters to northern Virginia; drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2007, December 2007, August 2008, December 2008, August 2009 and December 2009); fiscal 2010-2012 budget development; 2009 closure of International Paper's mill in Franklin, Virginia; Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG); Chesapeake Bay clean-up; Virginia tribal recognition; Choose Life license plate; smoking ban in restaurants; economic development projects; proposal by the United States Navy to move a nuclear-powered aircraft carrier from Norfolk Naval Station to Naval Station Mayport, Florida; preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; draft of Kaine's 15 December 2008 speech to the Electoral College; preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election (Weekly Election Working Group); energy policy; education; drafts of Kaine's eulogy for civil rights icon Oliver Hill; Virginia State Air Pollution Control Board (Dominion Power's Wise County project); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); payday lending; Kaine's official portrait; domestic partner benefits; structure and responsibilities of Office of the Governor;  and retirement of Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in 2007. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Kimberly Bowers, Gina Boyle, Amy Bridge, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Aneesh Chopra, Robert Crouch, Suzette Denslow, Mark Emblidge, Shane Emmett, Cathy Ghidotti, Patrick Gottschalk, Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Gail Jaspen, Michael Kelly, Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Tom Morris, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Brian Sheppard, Delacey Skinner, Nick Surace, Marilyn Tavenner, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, Jody Wagner, and Stephen Walz.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Lawrence Roberts</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 34627 emails in three pst files:  <emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst</emph>, <emph render="bold">LRoberts2.pst</emph>, and <emph render="bold">LRoberts3.pst</emph>.  Lawrence Roberts served as Counselor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 until 9 March 2009 when resigned to take a position as Senior Advisor to the Chairman of the Democratic National Committee (Governor Tim Kaine).  During the Kaine Administration, the Counselor to the Governor provided legal advice to the Governor, including liaison with the judiciary and the Office of the Attorney General.  The Counselor also handled Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, conflict of interest statements, contracts/leases for the Governor, settlement agreements for the Governor, clemency requests, death warrants, and provided broader advice to the Governor on political and personal matters as assigned.  The Counselor was the chief liaison with the Democratic Party, the Moving Virginia Forward PAC, and outside political constituency groups.  As part of his outreach efforts, the Counselor developed strategies to interact and facilitate implementation of the Governor's agenda.  Roberts also worked with the Scheduling Director to oversee the Governor's time.  After his resignation, Roberts continued to serve as an unpaid advisor to the Governor on four issues:  the Commonwealth's response to the Virginia Tech tragedy; concluding clemency matters which he had worked on; reviewing his files and documents for archiving; and reaching an agreement with the Library of Virginia as to archiving policies as they apply to the Counselor to the Governor and his staff.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph 		render="bold">January 2006-January 2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst</emph> file contains 28916 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 6246 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.  On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 8915 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. </p>



<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including creation and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, notes from meeting with family members, settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families and correspondence between Roberts and family members; revenue budget issues; transportation (drafts of June 2008 General Assembly special session speech, 2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute, Tyson Tunnel Plan and Full Funding Grant Agreement (FFGA), 2007 abusive driver fees, Elliston intermodal facility in Montgomery County, 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation, and Coalfields Expressway); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2006, August 2007, December 2007 and August 2008); clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); open carry (firearms in state parks); archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; talking points for February 2009 Virginia Congressional Delegation meeting (drafts); smoking ban in restaurants; proposal by the United States Navy to move a nuclear-powered aircraft carrier from Norfolk Naval Station to Naval Station Mayport, Florida; state government printing expenses (Freedom of Information Act request from Delegate Scott Lingamfelter); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; student voting; teleworking; Civil Rights Memorial; drafts of press releases/comments on media stories; Dominion Power's Wise County project; cabinet meetings (agendas); legislation/legislative sessions; Virginia Latino Advisory Board; election issues in Chesterfield County, 2008 Presidential primary; talking points (drafts, etc.) on a variety of subjects; resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish from Virginia Commission on Immigration; education (Pre-K, Start Strong); death of Oliver Hill and viewing at Governor's Mansion; Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood; judicial vacancies; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); health care work group; Governor incapacity and succession; Virginia tribal recognition; electricity re-regulation; Fort Monroe; Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria;  State Board of Elections issues; agreements with Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE)/287(g) [Executive Work Group related to possible state immigration authority with ICE under 287 (g) (8 USC Section 1357 (g))]; Comprehensive Services Act (CSA); Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA)/Arlington; energy policy; drafts of some executive orders; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); 2006 budget impasse; menhaden fisheries management measures; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth and successful confirmation of Kate Hanley for same post; DNA testing/old DFS files; domestic partner benefits; Employee Free Choice Act; estate tax repeal; TANF (Temporary Assistance for Needy Families); and Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email from Tim Kaine, 15 October 2007, Budget Issues I Care About ; email from Mark Rubin on Supreme Court rollout of Judge Goodwyn, 3 October 2007; email from Kaine on improving vetting process after resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish, 27 September 2007;  Kaine's comments on speech to money committees (18 August 2007); email thread started by Kaine on the operations/structure of the Governor's Office (3 April 2007); email from Kaine on electricity reregulation (17 March 2007); emails from Kaine on transportation (22 July 2008, 1 July 2008, 9 May 2008, 8 May 2008, 28 April 2008, 19 March 2008, 2 April 2007, 30 March 2007, 20 March 2007, 28 February 2007, 5 February 2007); email threads on abusive driver fees (19 July 2007, 18 July 2007, 17 July 2007, 16 July 2007); email from Larry Roberts, 7 May 2007, on strategic scheduling for 2007; email from Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 4 May 2007, on budget timeline/schedule; email thread between Roberts and Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email from Ric Signer to Leighty (Roberts cc'd), 17 April 2007, on the trade mission to Japan; email thread on electric reregulation (see Kaine's lengthy email dated 17 March 2007); 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: James Alcorn, Amber Amato, Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, Sindy Benavides, Mark Bowles, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Kim Busch, Larry Byrne, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Barnie Day, Suzette Denslow, Nick Donohue, Jason Eige, Kim Farrar, Patrick Finnerty, Marc Follmer, Manju Ganeriwala, Cathy Ghidotti, Kathy Glazer, Patrick Gottschalk, Eric Gregory (assistant AG), Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurcie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent (assistant AG), Jeff Kraus, Danny LeBlanc, Keetch leGrand, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Maureen Matsen (assistant AG), Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt (assistant AG), Steve Owens (assistant AG), Kate Paris, David Paylor, Sarah Plumb, Barbara Reese, Nancy Rodrigues, Nikki Rovener, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Sheppard, Ric Siger, Williams Sims, Delacey Skinner, D.B. Smit, Jeff Southard, Phil Sunderland, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Matthew Tucker, Wayne Turnage, Jim Ukrop, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, Tom Whipple and Richard Zorn.
</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts2.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
              
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts2.pst</emph> file contains 288 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  Subjects include:  American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); Federal issues impacting Virginia; and Virginia tribal recognition.
	</p>



<p>Correspondents include:  Gena Boyle, Eileen Filler-Corn, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Barbara Reese, and Brian Sheppard.
</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts3.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
              
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts3.pst</emph> file contains 5423 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 4033 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 94 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.

</p>



<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including leak of report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel to the New York Times; email thread between Chief of Staff Bill Leighty and Secretary of Natural Resources Preston Bryant, 16 May 2007, in which Leighty discusses how he informed Governor Kaine about the Virginia Tech shooting; retirement of Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in 2007; archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); DNA testing/old DFS files; drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly ( August 2007, December 2007); transportation (Tysons Corner tunnel, 2007 legislation, abusive driver fees); Clemency ; Maurice Henderson, Deputy Press Secretary, reports from 2006-2007 press gaggles/news conferences; drafts of Kaine's 2006 commencement address at the University of Virginia; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth; and clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted).
	</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email from Kaine, 23 April 2007, describing the policy development agenda for the rest of 2007; email thread between Roberts and Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email thread between Turnage and Roberts, 27 April 2007, discussing issues with Leighty; email exchange between Roberts and Sherrie Harrington, 9 November 2006, re: execution of John Yancey Schmitt; email exchange between Roberts and Turnage, 7 June and 9 June 2006 on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email from Marilyn Tavenner, 5 June 2006, on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email exchange between Roberts and Brian Sheppard, 27 April 2006, re:  execution of Dexter Lee Vinson; and email thread between Kaine, Roberts and Delacey Skinner, 17 April and 16 April 2006, on Kaine's concerns about the marriage amendment. 

</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Katherine Burnett, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Marla Decker, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Cathy Ghidotti, Patrick Gottschalk, Kevin Hall, Robert Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurice Henderson, II, E. Desmond Hogan, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Danny LeBlanc, William Leighty, John Marshall, Walter McFarlane, William Mims, Jeffery Mitchell, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt, Sarah Plumb, Brian Pumphrey, Mark Rubin, Brian Sheppard, Delacey Skinner, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>


</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Mark Rubin Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 10263 emails in two pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">MRUBIN.pst</emph>. Mark Rubin served as Deputy Counselor and Senior Advisor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 to 9 March 2009.  Following the resignation of Lawrence Roberts, Rubin served as Counselor to the Governor from 10 March 2009 to 16 January 2010.  The Senior Advisor was a hybrid position.  He provided legal assistance to the Counselor and legislative assistance to the Policy Director.  The Senior Advisor as helped mediate important policy disputes for the Governor.  Rubin frequently met with legislators and others and shared what he learned with senior administration officials.  His email provides information on legislation development and the legislative process.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst</emph> file contains 10261 emails sent and received by Mark Rubin between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 1515 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 461 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including issues regarding the settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families, forwarded emails sent to families by Jay Poole, Director of Virginia Tech's Office of Recovery and Support, and correspondence between Rubin and family members; budget issues including fall 2009 state agency reduction plans; legislation; transportation (2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, 2007 abusive driver fees, and 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (December 2007, August 2008, December 2009); blanket restoration of rights; closure of Natural Bridge Juvenile Correctional Center; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; Virginia tribal recognition; smoking ban in restaurants; payday lending; Dominion Power's Wise County project; eminent domain; uranium mining; mental health legislation; workgroup for the Virginia Birth-Related Neurological Injury Compensation Program; Education (Pre-K); Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; energy policy (including Renewable Portfolio Standards); electricity re-regulation; indigent defense; machinery and tools legislation; Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); setting dates for special elections; clemency (Jens Soering, John T. Harrison, Daniel Cox, Richard M. Hawkins, Chris Sharikas, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Whitney Shelton, Norfolk Four, and Earl Washington-all restricted); and Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 16 April 2008, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate David Alba on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 18 April 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate Joe May on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 8 May 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with several legislators on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 17 March 2007, to Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Larry Roberts, Patrick Gottschalk, Preston Bryant, and Bill Leighty, listing his concerns with the electric reregulation bill; email from Tim Kaine, 30 May 2006, to Larry Roberts, Jody Wagner, and Mark Rubin, sharing additional thoughts on the budget; email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 28 April 2008, setting the process for selection of circuit court judges, Supreme Court and an SCC judge; email from Mark Rubin, 11 February 2006, to Larry Roberts, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, Preston Bryant, Mike Henry, Bill Murray, and Daniel LeBlanc, detailing the latest vote count in the General Assembly to confirm LeBlanc as Secretary of the Commonwealth; email from Preston Bryant, 12 February 2006, to Mark Rubin, describing his conversations with several members of the House of Delegates on the LeBlanc nomination; email from Tim Kaine, 8 August 2006, to Bill Murray, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, and Mark Rubin, with Kaine's notes from phone conversations with several members of the General Assembly (notes as attachment) on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 15 August 2006, 17 August 2006, and 21 August 2006, to Mark Rubin, Bill Murray and Brian Shepard, describing Kaine's contacts with several members of the General Assembly on transportation; email from Mark Rubin, 23 April 2006, to Brian Shepard and Bill Murray, on post mortem on the 2006 General Assembly session; email from Tim Kaine, 27 November 2009, to Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, and Ric Brown, where Kaine shares his views on eliminating the car tax in his final budget; and email from Tim Kaine, 6 February 2008, to Jody Wagner, Ric Brown, Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, Brian Shepard, Mark Rubin, Suzette Denslow, Larry Roberts, Delacey Skinner, and Gordon Hickey, in which Kaine shares his thoughts on the budget.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Philip Abraham, Amber Amato, David Bailey, Chris Bast, Steve Benjamin, Robert Blue, Gena Boyle, William Broaddus, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Don Carr, Bob Chase, Marc Cheatham, Eileen Filler-Corn, Robert Crouch, Marla Decker, George Deebo, Suzette Denslow, Chip Dicks, Dave Dickson, Betsy Edwards, Jerry Edwards, Mike Edwards, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Claudia Farr, Frank Ferguson, Marc Follmer, May Fox, Robert Hall, Stephanie Hamlett, Stephen Harms, Kay Heidbreder, Bernard Henderson, Pierce Homer, Barbara Hulburt, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Anne Leigh Kerr, Jim Kibler, Irene Leech, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Maureen Matsen, Michael Maul, Walter McFarlane, Bill McKelway, Eric Murdock, Bill Murray, Stephen Parker, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nancy Rodrigues, Michele Satterlund, Aimee Perron Seibert, Brian Shepard, Ric Signer, Jeff Southard, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, Bret Vassey, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, and Kent Willis.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MRUBIN.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">MRUBIN.pst</emph> file contains two email messages received by Mark Rubin dated 15 January 2010.  One message is from Kent Willis of the Virginia American Civil Liberties Union on Kaine's decision not to issue a blanket restoration of rights executive order.  The second message is from Gordon Hickey regarding Jens Soering.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>


</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Shane Emmett Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1090 emails in one pst file:  <emph render="bold">KaineLibsemmett.pst</emph>.  Shane Emmett worked as a Governor's Legal Fellow and as a Deputy Counselor to Mark Rubin from December 2008 to January 2010.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsemmett.pst</emph> contains 1090 email messages sent and received by Shane Emmett.  There are 1019 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: pardon files granted and denied, restoration of rights granted and denied.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  clemency (Edward Bell, Norfolk Four, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Jens Soering, and John Muhammad-all restricted); and domestic partner benefits.  Correspondents include:  Katherine Burnett Baldwin, Andrew Block, Klaus Botzet, Marla Decker, Helen Fahey, E. Desmond Hogan, Gail Jaspen, Tim Kaine, Tom Kelly, Walter McFarlane, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, and Donald Salzman.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. William H. Leighty Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2002-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>This subseries contains 15896 emails in one pst file:  <emph render="bold">Leighty.pst</emph>.  William H. Leighty served as Chief of Staff to Governor Mark R. Warner (January 2002-January 2006).  He was reappointed Chief of Staff by Governor Tim Kaine.  On 23 May 2007 Leighty announced his retirement effective 1 September 2007.  He stepped down as Chief of Staff effective 25 May 2007. Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage assumed his duties.  Leighty remained in the administration as Chief Emeritus working on several projects including efforts to improve minority procurement for state agencies, workforce development and the implementation of the outsourcing of state governments' IT functions.  The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government for all aspects of service to citizens.  The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office.  Governors Mark Warner and Tim Kaine delegated additional responsibilities to Leighty in Executive Order 3 (2002) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff and Executive Order 4 (2006) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">Leighty.pst</emph> file contains 15896 email messages sent and received by William H. Leighty between January 2002 and September 2007.  There are 133 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: investigative records, attorney-client privileged documents and medical information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 218 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  At-Will Employee lists; 8th and 9th Street Office Buildings (movement of offices and demolition of 8th Street Office Building); Appalachian Regional Commission (ARC); bird flu (AI-2002); Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC); Beltway Sniper; Black Bear Landfill; Board of Veterans Services; budgets; possible budget shutdown 2006; Capitol renovation; consolidation of Department of Environmental Quality  boards; Department of Corrections media policy; Department of Game and Inland Fisheries investigation; Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute; economic development; education funding error (2006); education for a lifetime; Enterprise Applications Program; eVA; Virginia tribal recognition; Norfolk Ford plant closure; Fort Monroe, Governor's Commission on Efficiency and Effectiveness (Wilder Commission); Governor's December 2006/August 2006 speech to money committees (2006 drafts); Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives; Hurricane Isabel (including City of Poquoson aid); Hurricane Ivan; Hurricane Katrina (including reports from Leighty who helped in Louisiana); Jamestown 2007; King William Reservoir/Newport News; land conservation, including Governor Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth; mail consolidation; Medicaid reform; menhaden fisheries management measures; mine safety; Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; moving offices to State Library Building (now the Patrick Henry Building); NASCAR Hall of Fame; No Child Left Behind (NCLB); Occoneechee State Park; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Pillowtex; Pre-K; Queen Elizabeth's visit to Virginia (2007); Race to GED; Seven Hills Health Care Center, Start Strong program; state climatologist; State Library building renovation (now the Patrick Henry Building; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); Tax Reform (2004); transportation (HB 3202, regional authorities, Elliston Intermodal, VDOT, Real ID, I-81, VDOT commissioner, Dulles Rail, Coalfields Expressway, Woodrow Wilson Bridge, Springfield interchange, and rest stops); Tropical Depression Gaston; Tropical Storm Ernesto (includes Battery Park area in Richmond); urban issues; Virginia Election and Registration Information System (VERIS); veterans issues; Virginia Horse Center; Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (billing issues, service issues, etc.); 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; Virginia Information Technology Investment Board (ITIB); Virginia Works; Washington Building renovation; Wise County water shortage (2005); and workforce development.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  Governor Kaine to Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard and Jody Wagner, 15 October 2006, re Kaine's thought's on 2nd year budget;  Sherrie Harrington to Bill Leighty, 6 June 2006 with attachment - presentation to rating agencies in New York;  Thanks from the Green Family, 28 September 2006; email thread between Leighty and Linda Hall re: death of detective Vicky Armel, 17 August 2006; Governor Kaine in Iraq, 14 March 2006; email thread between Leighty and Jim Waldron, that includes Leighty's thoughts on the Federal government's response to Hurricane Katrina, 24 September 2005; email exchange between Leighty and Ellen Qualls on preserving governor's web site, 3 May 2005; Leighty to Secretary of Technology Eugene Huang, re:  his European trip, 18 November 2004; and email exchange between Leighty and Turnage highlighting tension between them, 28 August 2007.

</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sheryl Bailey, Gerald Baliles, Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, John Bennett, Peter Blake, Robert Bloxom; Robert Blue, Barbara Bolin, Sandra Bowen, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Vincent Burgess, Robert Burnley, Marc Cheatham, Ryan Childress, Aneesh Chopra, Cheryl Clark, Whitt Clement, Michael Cline, Merritt Cogswell, Clyde Cristman , Robert Crouch, Pamela Currey, Don Darr, Ralph Davis, Jo Lynne Demary, Ben Dendy, Suzette Denslow, Bill Dickinson, David Ekern, Matt Erskine, Jan Faircloth, Eileen Filler-Corn, Kim Farrar, Eric Finkbeiner, George Foresman, Manju Ganeriwala, Patrick Gottschalk, Steven Gould, Barry Green, Kevin Hall, David Hallock, Lynette Hammond, Kate Hanley, Stephen Harms, Marilyn Harris, Anna Healy, Judith Heiman, Bernard Henderson, June Hines, Pierce Homer, Amanda Howe, Eugene Huang, Margaret Hughson, Bruce Jamerson (Queen's visit), Jean Jensen, Maurice Jones, Tim Kaine, Andy Kopplin, Jeff Krause, Daniel LeBlanc, Alfonso Lopez, Jon Mangis; John Marshall, Dominic Martin (Queen's visit), Gerald Massengill, Earl McClenney, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Tayloe Murphy, Bill Murray, Judy Napier, George Newstrom, David Paylor, David Poisson, Charles Pyle, Ellen Qualls, Karen Rae, Paul Reagan, Scott Reed, Barbara Reese, Jim Roberts, Larry Roberts, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Tareq Salahi (WH crasher), Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Jr., Michael Schewel, Saba Shami, Bill Shelton, Brian Shepard, Philip Shucet, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, D.B. Smit, Julie Stanley, Lem Stewart, Marilyn Tavenner, Ken Thorson, Dan Timberlake, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Fred Vincent, David Von Moll, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, Belle Wheelan, Michaele White, Sara R. Wilson, Jane Woods, and Richard Zorn
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries F. Wayne Turnage Email</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1046 number of email messages in one pst file:  <emph render="bold">KaineLibWTurnage.pst</emph>. Wayne Turnage served as Deputy Chief of Staff (January 2006-May 2007) and as Chief of Staff to Governor Tim Kaine (May 2007-January 2010). On 23 May 2007 Chief of Staff William H. Leighty announced his retirement effective 1 September 2007. Leighty stepped down as Chief of Staff effective 25 May 2007 and Turnage assumed his duties. The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office. Governor Tim Kaine delegated additional responsibilities to Turnage in Executive Order 4 (2006) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff. Turnage's pst file contained less than 1000 messages.  However, a large number of Turnage's messages can be found in the email files of Deputy Chief of Staff Stephen Harms, Governor Tim Kaine, Counselor to the Governor Larry Roberts, Senior Advisor to the Governor Mark Rubin, and Chief of Staff William H. Leighty.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibTurnage.pst</emph> file contains 1046 email messages sent and received by Wayne Turnage between January 2006 and January 2010. There is one privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional one message pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  8th and 9th Street Office Buildings (movement of offices and demolition of 8th Street Office Building); audit reports; budget (budget cuts, budget development, Cabinet cuts, etc.); cabinet meeting agendas; Capitol Square parking; Council on Virginia's Future; Governor's Office (structure and performance management); Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); transportation; urban issues/policy; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email to Bill Leighty, Delacey Skinner, Brian Shepard, and Larry Roberts, 12 November 2006, transmitting memorandum on Governor's Office operations; email to Jody Wagner, 27 August 2006, transmitting Chronology of Events Which Governor Learned of Education Funding Error; email to Larry Roberts and Brian Shepard, 17 July 2006, on education funding error; and email to Leighty, 20 July 2006, forwarding an email from Roberts containing detailed Governor's Office procedures for the execution Brandon Hedrick (restricted).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Ric Brown, [global messages to Cabinet], Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Don Darr, Stephen Harms, Margaret Hughson, Tim Kaine, Jane Kusiak, Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Earl McClenney, Kate Paris, Brian Shepard, and Sara Wilson.
</p>


</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries G. Stephen W. Harms Email</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 13565 email messages in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharms.pst</emph>.  Stephen Harms served as Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources (January 2006-June 2007) and Deputy Chief of Staff (June 2007-January 2010).  Harms' email file contains a large number of messages about intergovernmental operations (IGO), finance and budget issues, and health care initiatives.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharms.pst</emph> file contains 13565 email messages sent and received by Stephen Harms between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 239 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 131 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  preparations for 12 February 2008 Democratic presidential primary and the 4 November 2008 presidential election;  American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-criteria for projects and creation of web site); archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; briefings/budgeting for severance of at-will employees; budget cuts (revenue reports and budget cuts for Governor's Office and Cabinet); FY 2010-2012 budget development (also includes elimination of car tax and budget meeting with Governor-elect McDonnell); cabinet meetings (agendas); cabinet day(s); campus security conference (2007); Computer Matching and Privacy Protection Act (CMPPA) agreement with the Social Security Administration and Virginia; annual Virginia Congressional Delegation meeting; correspondence issues (late responses, need of editing, VIP process, etc.); drought conditions; Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute; education (early childhood and pre-K); state government printing expenses (Freedom of Information Act request from Delegate Scott Lingamfelter); responses to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests for Governor Kaine's complete daily schedule (2009); gubernatorial transition; drafts of Governor Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (December 2006, December 2007, August 2008, December 2008, August 2009 and December 2009); preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; smoking ban in restaurants and state office buildings; teleworking; workforce development; Family Foundation Marriage Commission; National Service Initiative; Department of General Services, Division of Real Estate Services; Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS); transportation (Dulles Rail and abusive driver fees); unemployment insurance/Virginia Employment Commission (VEC); Virginia State Police report on terrorism groups (2009); 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (billing issues, service issues, etc.); United We Serve; and issues with responses to VIP correspondence.
</p>



<p>A significant number of messages related to health and human resources issues.  Subjects include:  budget;  Health IT Council; federal health care reform proposals; White House health care reform talking points (forwarded by Alphonso Lopez); Office of Health It; nursing program at Longwood University; Virginia SHARE network; Governor's Health Reform Commission; McKinsey proposal to Virginia; state agency issues [Commonwealth Services Act for At-Risk Youth and Families (CSA), Department of Medical Assistance (DMAS), Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services (DMHMRSAS)- name changed to Department of Behavioral Health and Development (DBHDS), Department of Rehabilitative Services (DRS), Department of Social Services (DSS), and Virginia Department of Health (VDH)]; State Executive Council (SEC); foster care; Medicaid; State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP); Family Access to Medical Insurance Security (FAMIS); Medicare Part D; Western State Hospital; Southeastern Virginia Training Center (SEVTC); Executive Directive 7 (07) Central Criminal Records Exchange; autism; prisoner re-entry; Poverty Task Force; Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF) cuts; fuel assistance for low-income Virginians; Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; Secretary of Health and Human Resources agency weekly reports; Olmstead (Community Integration for People with Disabilities); H1N1 strain of influenza; Sugar Grove water issue; Town of Goshen water leak; Patrick County hospital; HPV vaccine; and Seven Hills Nursing Home in City of Richmond.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email exchange between Wayne Turnage and Tim Kaine, 31 December 2008, re:  Office Restructuring Proposal;  Governor's Office procedures for the execution of Robert Stacey Yarbrough, 25 June 2008 (restricted); State Board of Election issues, 12 June 2008; email exchange between Mark Rubin et al, 28 April 2008, re:  process for selecting judges; outline for gubernatorial transition, 18 April 2008; post 9/11 policy that one legislator sent to a secure location during State of the Commonwealth address, 7 January 2008; Governor Kaine's VIP mail process, 13 July 2007; Harms' thoughts on June meeting with Virginia Tech families, 25 June 2007; Email from Governor Kaine sharing his views on revenue options for 2012-2014 budget, 27 November 2009; email from Governor Kaine describing a meeting about legislation with Delegate Lacey Putney, 13 February 2008; email from Governor Kaine to senior staff sharing his thoughts on the budget, 6 February 2008, 3 February 2008, 30 January 2008, and 15 October 2007 ("Budget Issues I care about"); drafts of Health Care Reform op-ed by Tim Kaine and Mark O'Connell, 20 September 2009, 19 July 2009, 15 July 2009, 13 July 2009, 3 July 2009, and 30 June 2009; email between Tim Kaine and Wayne Turnage, State Health Insurance Policy Change (other qualified adult) and Wayne Turnage and Sara Wilson, 11 April 2009 and 12 April 2009; email from Kaine, 23 April 2007, re Reactions in the Aftermath of the Virginia Tech Shooting, 23 April 2007; email from Secretary of Health and Human Resources Marilyn Tavenner, 17 November 2009, re: list of on-going projects/issues for McDonnell Administration; "ransom note" from alleged PMP hacker forwarded by Alicia Cavanaugh, 30 April 2009; email from Robert Stroube to Marilyn Tavenner, et al with attachment listing autopsy information from Virginia Tech shooting, 18 April 2007; email exchange between Pierce Homer and Wayne Turnage on the dismal transportation budget numbers, 2 August 2009; draft of Kaine op-ed on transportation published in Washington Post,7-10 June 2009; Rest Area closure decision brief, 23 April 2009; email from Kaine sharing his thoughts on transportation, 22 July 2008; Mark Rubin's transportation to-do-list, 2 July 2008; email from Kaine to Pierce Homer, et al on transportation, 1 July 2008; drafts of Kaine's speech on transportation to joint session of General Assembly, 21-23 June 2008; email from Kaine on transportation message for roll-out and town hall meetings, 9 May 2008; email from Kaine relaying conversations he's had with state legislators on transportation issues, 8 May 2008; email from Kaine with his comments on the 21 April 2008 transportation compromise, 28 April 2008; email from Kaine relaying conversation he had with Joe May on transportation, 18 April 2008; and email from Kaine on his thoughts on transportation, 8 March 2008.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sarah Abubaker, Amber Amato, Karen Angelici (Casey Foundation), Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Kristin Burhop, Craig Burns, Patrick Callahan, Alicia Cavanaugh, Marc Cheatham, Julie Christopher, Aneesh Chopra, Julie Christopher, Anthony Conyers, Scott Crawford, Clyde Cristman, Bob Crouch, Don Darr, Suzette Denslow, Heidi Dix, Emily Ehrlichmann, William Ellwood, Michael Evans, Michael Farley (Elk Hill Farm), Eileen Filler-Corn, Patrick Finnerty, Joe Flores, Chris Freund (VP, Policy and Communications, Family Foundation of Virginia [marriage commission]), Andrea Gaines, Manju Ganeriwala, Thomas Gates, Kathy Glazer, Patrick Gottschalk, Barry Green, Kevin Hall, Phil Hamilton, Lynette Hammond, Joyce Hann, Sherrie Harrington, Bo Harris, Marilyn Harris, Bernard Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Gary Janak, Gail Jaspen, Dennis Johnson, Latosha Johnson, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Karen Lawson, [John Layman - revenue reports forward], Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Dean Lynch, John Marshall, Jim Martinez, Kenneth McCabe, John McDonald, Kim McGaughey, Martha Mead, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Marsha Mucha, Bill Murray, Linda Nablo, Kate Paris, Ray Ratke, Barbara Reese, James Reinhard, Karen Remley, Larry Roberts, Gail Robinson, James Rothrock, Mark Rubin, Sandra Ryals, Brian Shepard, Margaret Schultze, Michael Shook, Richard Silwoski, Delacey Skinner, Chris Spanos, Julie Stanley, Robert Stroube, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Ed Turner, Michael Tutor, Seta Vandegrift, David Von Moll, Jody Wagner, Ruth Ann Walker, Sara Wilson, Patricia Wright, Beatrice Yarney, Joy Yeh, and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries H. Marc Follmer Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 5735 in two pst files:  <emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.PST</emph> and <emph render="bold">KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph>.  Marc Follmer was Deputy Director, Department of General Services (January 2006-2007), Deputy Assistant to the Governor, Office of Commonwealth Preparedness (2007-2009) and Senior Advisor to the Governor (2009-January 2010).  He also was a member of Virginia Tech Working Group.  
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.pst</emph> file contains 5524 emails sent and received by Marc Follmer between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 115 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 479 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. </p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including workgroup established in Governor's Office to implement the settlement agreement between the Commonwealth and families; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; 2009 hurricane preparedness sales tax holiday; H1N1 strain of influenza; Virginia Business Credentials Program-Priority Access Stakeholder System (PASS); Secure Commonwealth Panel; revisions to Executive Order 6 (2006) Delegation of Governor's Authority to Declare a State of Emergency and to Call the Virginia National Guard to Active Service for Emergencies or Disasters when the Governor is Out of the Commonwealth of Virginia and Cannot be Reached; Air Force Cyber Command (AFCYBER); HB 1687 (2009) Motor vehicle dealers; disclosure if financing, cancellation of purchaser's contract to buy vehicle; HB 1983 (2009) Governor-declared emergency; provides civil immunity for private and charitable organizations; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); Real ID; Secure Commonwealth Panel; Fort Monroe including Fort Monroe Federal Area Development Authority (FMFADA); hurricane preparedness; gubernatorial disability; Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); Business and Industry Sub Panel; campus security conference (2007); mortgage foreclosure task force; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Office of Commonwealth Preparedness budget cuts; Office of Commonwealth Preparedness legislation; Ready Virginia; Virginia Military Advisory Council (VMAC); and Virginia National Defense Industrial Authority (VNDIA).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Amber Amato, Curtis Brown, Preston Bryant, Mar Cheatham, Bob Crouch, Nicholas Donohue, Chris Essid, Douglas Fierberg, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Alleyn Harned, Marilyn Harris, Wendy Hoffman, Catherine Hutchins, Elizabeth Kersey, Bill Leighty, Robert Mauskapf, Constance McGeorge, Steven Mondul, Susan Mongold, Steve Owens, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Joe Samaha, Megan Samford, Phil Schaenman, Brian Shepard, Rick Siger, Richard Silwoski, Kerry Stuver, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Virginia Retail Merchants Association, Sara Wilson, Robert Young, and Richard Zorn.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph> file contains 211 emails sent and received by Marc Follmer between October 2006 and December 2009. Subjects include:  Virginia Secure Commonwealth Panel.  Correspondents include:  Don Butts and Leigh B. Middleton, Jr.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries I. Sherrie Harrington Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2178 emails in two pst files:  <emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph>.  Sherrie Harrington was Confidential Assistant to Governor Tim Kaine from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst</emph> file contains 2164 emails sent and received by Sherrie Harrington between December 2007 and January 2010. There are 58 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 9 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; procedures for and issues with responses to VIP correspondence; Virginia tribal recognition; gifts for governor; and arrangements for President Barack Obama to call in to Governor Kaine's final Ask the Governor program on WTOP radio in December 2009.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  Brian Chiglinsky, a Constituent Services staff member, was on "loan" as Governor Kaine's aide, filling in for Harrington (who was teleworking on Monday and Wednesday, beginning in November 2008),  and made frequent email reports to Harrington about what happened in the office and with the Governor.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Connie Briggs, Preston Bryant, Kimberly Busch, Marc Cheatham, Brian Chiglinsky, Beau Cribbs, Carol Denson, Catherine Evans, Cathy Ghidotti, Martha Hazelgrove, Gordon Hickey, Darryl Holt, Anne Holton, Tim Kaine, Lorraine Lintecum, Alphonso Lopez, Jennie Moline, Ryan Newcomb, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, and Stephen Walz.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph> file contains 14 emails sent and received by Sherrie Harrington between June 2007 and July 2008. There are 9 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 4 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; and Percy Walton.  All correspondence are from Larry Roberts.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries J. Kate Paris Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 876 emails in two pst files:  <emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">KPARIS.pst</emph>.  Kate Paris was Special Assistant to the Counselor to the Governor (2006-2007) and Executive Assistant to the Chief of Staff and Counselor to the Governor (2007-2010).
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst</emph> file contains 264 emails sent and received by Kate Paris between September 2006  and January 2010. There are 37 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 79 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (meetings and updates for families); state agency head meeting; budget; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); and Norfolk Four (restricted).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Preston Bryant, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, and Sara Wilson.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KPARIS.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KPARIS.pst</emph> file contains 612 emails sent and received by Kate Paris between June 2006 and January 2010. There are 29 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, an additional 79 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (meetings and updates for families); agency contract spending; budget; cabinet meeting agendas; constituent correspondence; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); drought conditions; election security working group; and gubernatorial transition.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sherrie Harrington, Barbara Reese; Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries K. Margaret Hughson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 389 emails in one pst files:  <emph render="bold">Mhughson.pst</emph>.  On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, 105 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.  Margaret Hughson served as Governor Mark Warner's Director of Constituent Services (2005-2006) and Executive Assistant to Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in Governor Tim Kaine's administration (2006-2007).  Hughson also coordinated the Warner and Kaine's administration records management and archiving activities.  During her time of service, she was the Library of Virginia's primary contact for these issues.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  state agency head meeting; archiving of Governor's records for Warner and Kaine administrations; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (letters of support).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Ariel Billmeier, Roger Christman, Conley Edwards, William H. Leighty, Paige Neal, Wayne Turnage and Mark Walsh.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries L. Sarah Plumb Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1022 emails in one pst files: <emph render="bold">KaineLibSPlumb.pst</emph>. Sarah Plumb served as Director of External Relations from 2007 to October 2008. On the advice of the Office of the Attorney General, 32 messages pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: Virginia Tech Review Panel report; Education (Pre-K); revenue advisory group; transportation (2008 town hall meetings); and State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Jean Bankos, Andrew K. Block, Gena Boyle, Lauren Cunningham, Suzette Denslow, Andrea Gaines, Kathy Glazer, Julia Hammond, Pierce Homer, Michael Kelly, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Jeff Southard, and Jeff Tiller. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries M. Beau Cribbs Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 248 in two pst files:  <emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph>. Cribbs was a Special Assistant in Constituent Services (2007-2008) and Executive Aide to the Governor (2008-2010).  
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst</emph> file contains 21 emails sent and received by Beau Cribbs in 2007.  All of the correspondents were related to constituent services work and were between Cribbs and Amber Amato, Director of Constituent Services.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph> file contains 227 emails sent and received by Beau Cribbs between 2007-2010.  Subjects are primarily constituent correspondents work and declined invitations handled by Cribbs in his role as Executive Aide to the Governor.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries N. Bryce Schunke Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 12 emails in one pst files:  <emph render="bold">BSCHUNKE.pst</emph>.  Bryce Schunke served as a Governor's Legal Fellow in 2009.  All 12 emails contain privacy protected and confidential information that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions.
</p>





</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries O. Sarah Robertson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2 emails in one pst files:  <emph render="bold">SROBERTSON.pst</emph>.  Sarah Robertson served as a Governor's Legal Fellow in 2009.  Both emails contain privacy protected and confidential information that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


</c01>

</dsc>

</archdesc>
</ead>



