<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % notats SYSTEM 
"http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/ead/eadnotat.ent"> %notats;
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vi00335">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00335::A Guide to the Records of Ante-bellum Southern Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil War. Series J, Selections from the Southern Historical Collection, Manuscript Department, Library of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9, Virginia, 1991.)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00335.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00335::A Guide to the Records of
             Ante-bellum Southern Plantations From the Revolution
             Through the Civil War. Series J, Selections from the
             Southern Historical Collection, Manuscript Department,
             Library of the University of North Carolina at Chapel
             Hill, Part 9, Virginia, 1991.)//EN" "vi00335.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of Ante-bellum Southern
            Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil War.
            Series J, Selections from the Southern Historical
            Collection, Manuscript Department, Library ofthe University
            of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9, Virginia, 
            <date>1991</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Records of Ante-bellum Southern
            Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil War.
            Series J, Selections from the Southern Historical
            Collection, Manuscript Department, Library of the
            University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9,
            Virginia, 1991 
            <num type="collectionnumber">35353</num></subtitle>
            <author>Jim Greve</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>The Library of Virginia</addressline>
               <addressline>800 East Broad Street</addressline>
               <addressline>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archdesk@lva.lib.va.us
               (Archives)</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">2 KB</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Marc
         record. Created by Renee M. Savits 
         <date>11 May 2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00335::A Guide to the Records of Ante-bellum
            Southern Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil
            War. Series J, Selections from the Southern Historical
            Collection, Manuscript Department, Library of the
            University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9,
            Virginia, 1991.)//EN" "vi00335.xml" converted from EAD 1.0
            to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of Ante-bellum Southern
         Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil War. Series
         J, Selections from the Southern Historical Collection,
         Manuscript Department, Library of the University of North
         Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9, Virginia, 
         <date>1991</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">35353</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Jim Greve</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Records of Ante-bellum Southern
         Plantations From the Revolution Through the Civil War. Series
         J, Selections from the Southern Historical Collection,
         Manuscript Department, Library of the University of North
         Carolina at Chapel Hill, Part 9, Virginia, 
         <unitdate label="Date">1991</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Accession number">35353</unitid>
         <physloc label="Physical Location">Miscellaneous reels
         1615-1647</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">33 reels of
         microfilm</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Special permission for reproduction or extensive
            quotation must be obtained through written application to
            the Southern Historical Collection, Manuscripts Department,
            Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel
            Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Records of Ante-bellum Southern Plantations From the
            Revolution Through the Civil War. Series J : Selections
            from the Southern Historical Collection, Manuscript
            Department, Library of the University of North Carolina at
            Chapel Hill. Accession 35353, Personal papers collection,
            The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Purchased 29 May 1997.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>The Charles W. Dabney Papers, 1716-1865, documents the life
         and work of Charles William Dabney, as well as four
         generations of Dabney ancestors residing in King William and
         Louisa Counties, Virginia, and California, including William
         Dabney, Charles Dabney, Charles William Dabney, Robert Lewis
         Dabney, Lavina (Morrison) Dabney, James Morrison, and Mary
         Chilton (Brent) Dabney. There are letters, business papers,
         account books, and related papers. Topics include church
         matters, Hampden-Sydney College and the Union Theological
         Seminary near Farmville, Virginia, Civil War service,
         manuscripts and rough drafts of publications, memoirs, and
         addresses, work with the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the
         advancement of scientific, technical, agricultural, and
         general education, the University of Tennessee, the University
         of Cincinnati, genealogical information, travel, and family
         affairs. (Misc. Reels 1615-1619).</p>
         <p>The Fredericks Hall Plantation Books, 1727-1863, comprise
         account books (1727-1775) from Hanover and York Counties,
         Virginia, and from Fredericks Hall Plantation (1849-1862) in
         Louisa County, Virginia. There is also a letter book
         (1757-1775) of Major John Snelson. Principal subjects of the
         account books include tobacco shipments, imported merchandise,
         mining and mineral export, the daily work of merchants, and
         import inventories. The Fredericks Hall Plantation ledgers
         document lumber production, manufacture and sale of shoes,
         tobacco production and trade, and merchants' accounts. (Misc.
         Reels 1620-1624).</p>
         <p>The Burwell Family Papers, 1750-1943, consists of
         correspondence, financial, legal, business, and personal
         papers of the Burwell family of Mecklenburg County, Virginia,
         and Granville, Vance, and Warren Counties, North Carolina, and
         of the Williams family of Warren County, North Carolina.
         Topics include family news, tobacco and cotton farming, slave
         sales and purchases, and family estates. Financial and legal
         papers include receipts, insurance papers, school
         superintendent's papers, and letters from agricultural agents.
         Also included are advertising circulars, report cards,
         genealogical material, and thirty-eight volumes of church,
         school, and farm records, and account books. (Misc. Reels
         1624-1629).</p>
         <p>The Thomas Edward Cox Books, 1829-1854, document the
         farming activities of Cox at his farm, Laurel Spring, in
         Henrico County, Virginia in 1853 and 1854, as well as his
         medical practice in the 1840's and early 1850's. The seven
         volumes in the collection consist of two farm account books of
         Edward Cox, and two physician's ledgers and three farm
         account/daybooks of Thomas Cox. (Misc. Reels 1629-1630).</p>
         <p>The Crenshaw and Miller Family Papers, 1751-1916, consist
         almost entirely of estate and legal papers, primarily
         concerning the estates of Major Nathaniel Crenshaw of
         Pittsylvania County, Virginia, and Charles Crenshaw, Jr. of
         Hanover County, Virginia. Included are deeds, wills, bonds,
         writs of summons, legal correspondence, contracts, land plats,
         court orders, and articles of agreement. (Misc. Reel
         1630).</p>
         <p>The Thomas Baylie Cropper Papers, 1832-1879, consist
         primarily of family and business letters, 1832-1848, received
         by Cropper. The bulk of the family letters document the
         personal, financial, economic, religious, and political
         affairs of Cropper and his relatives in Accomack County,
         Virginia. (Misc. Reels 1630-1631).</p>
         <p>The Howerton Family Papers, 1817-1858, are composed of
         financial and legal papers of the Howerton family of Halifax
         County, Virginia, primarily Philip Howerton and Rufus H. Owen.
         Included are correspondence with commission merchants,
         receipts, tax lists, and materials relating to the
         imprisonment of insolvent debtors. (Misc. Reels
         1631-1632).</p>
         <p>The Cornelius Dabney Diary, 1863-1869, consists of the
         original, as well as a typescript of Cornelius Dabney of
         Albemarle and King William Counties, Virginia. Topics covered
         include family news, work on the farm, social activities,
         attendance at prayer meetings and Sunday school, the Civil
         War, and student life while attending the University of
         Virginia. (Misc. Reel 1632).</p>
         <p>The T. L. Jones Journal, 1862-1869, was kept by him at his
         farm, Pear Point, in Albemarle County, Virginia. The journal
         records mostly farm work done, crops, and the weather. Other
         topics include church attendance, travels, visits, schooling,
         estate sales attended, and local births, marriages, and
         deaths. (Misc. Reel 1632).</p>
         <p>The James McDowell Papers, 1770-1915, includes
         correspondence, speeches, essays, public addresses and notes,
         bills, legal papers, and other materials of McDowell, chiefly
         during his term as a state legislator from Rockbridge County,
         Virginia, as well as governor, and congressman. Topics covered
         include slavery, especially in the territories, internal
         improvements, temperance, nullification, Democratic Party
         politics in Virginia, colonization societies, collegiate and
         literary societies, land speculation, currency and credit
         issues, and education, both public school and higher education
         in Virginia. (Misc. Reels 1633-1641).</p>
         <p>The Meriwether Family Papers, 1791-ca. 1880's, consists of
         correspondence and financial and legal papers of the
         Meriwether family of Albemarle County, Virginia, and Kentucky
         and Tennessee. The correspondence is chiefly letters to
         Charles N. Meriwether from family and friends. Topics include
         tobacco sales, estate settlements, family news, slave and
         tobacco sales, and land disputes and prices. There is a great
         deal of correspondence from his brother, William D.
         Meriwether. (Misc. Reel 1641).</p>
         <p>The E. H. Riggan Account Book, 1846-1870, contains cash
         account entries, mainly dated 1854-1864, kept by an
         individual, presumably E. H. Riggan, who apparently lived in
         or near Mecklenburg County, Virginia. The book includes
         records of payments received and of payments made. (Misc. Reel
         1641).</p>
         <p>The Edmund Ruffin Jr. Plantation Diary, 1851-1873,
         documents affairs on Ruffin's plantation, Beechwood, in Prince
         George County, Virginia, between 1851 and 1862, and of his
         Hanover County, Virginia, plantation, Marlbourne, between 1866
         and 1873. The journal provides detailed information on the
         weather, crop conditions, crop rotations, fertilizers used,
         plantation finances, and general farm tasks completed by
         slaves and hired hands at Beechwood and Marlbourne. (Misc.
         Reel 1642).</p>
         <p>The Ruffin and Meade Family Papers, 1796-1906, consists of
         mainly correspondence of the Ruffin and Meade families of
         Hanover and Prince George Counties, and Petersburg, Virginia,
         as well as Alabama and New Jersey. The correspondence is
         mainly that of the women of the Meade family, and provides
         extensive information on the social, school and family life,
         including courtship, friendship, religious devotion,
         plantation affairs, family relationships, secession, and the
         outbreak of the Civil War. Postwar letters concern mostly
         family and financial matters. (Misc. Reels 1642-1644).</p>
         <p>The Francis Gildart Ruffin Papers, 1802-1860, consist of
         the postwar business papers of Francis G. Ruffin of
         Chesterfield County, Virginia, as well as legal, financial and
         personal papers of his relatives, Albert and Eliza Ruffin, and
         Spencer Roane. (Misc. Reels 1644-1646).</p>
         <p>The John Walker Papers, 1824-1844, consist of the
         plantation journal of John Walker. The journal is useful for
         the study of religious life, plantation finances, and slavery
         in and around King and Queen County, Virginia. The journal
         documents his finances, and is also rich as a source for slave
         genealogy, activities, slave/owner relations, often recording
         vital statistics, family relationships, and the purchase and
         sale of slaves. (Misc. Reels 1646-1647).</p>
         <p>The Floyd L. Whitehead Papers, 1830-1886, consist chiefly
         of financial, business, and legal papers of Floyd L. Whitehead
         of Nelson County, Virginia, including some personal papers,
         and several items relating to Whitehead's brother, John.
         Business and financial material includes letters from tobacco
         dealers, indentures, receipts, tax records, and slave bills of
         sale. Legal material relates to the settlement of estates,
         land and property disputes, and the collection of bad debts.
         (Misc. Reel 1647).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Organization</head>
         <p>Charles W. Dabney Papers (Misc. Reels 1615-1619);
         Fredericks Hall Plantation Books (Misc. Reels 1620-1624);
         Burwell Family Papers (Misc. Reels 1624-1629); Thomas Edward
         Cox Books (Misc. Reels 1629-1630); Crenshaw and Miller Family
         Papers (Misc. Reel 1630); Thomas Baylie Cropper Papers (Misc.
         Reels 1630-1631); Howerton Family Papers (Misc. Reels
         1631-1632); Cornelius Dabney Diary (Misc. Reel 1632); T. L.
         Jones Journal (Misc. Reel 1632); James McDowell Papers (Misc.
         Reels 1633-1641); Meriwether Family Papers (Misc. Reel 1641);
         E. H. Riggan Account Book (Misc. Reel 1641); Edmund Ruffin Jr.
         Plantation Diary (Misc. Reel 1642); Ruffin and Meade Family
         Papers (Misc. Reels 1642-1644); Francis Gildart Ruffin Papers
         (Misc. Reels 1644-1646); John Walker Papers (Misc. Reels
         1646-1647); and Floyd L. Whitehead Papers (Misc. Reel
         1647).</p>
      </arrangement>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
