<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vi00454">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00454::A Guide to the Telfair family Papers, 1803-1893 )//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00454.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00454::A Guide to the Telfair
             family Papers, 1803-1893 )//EN" "vi00454.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Telfair family Papers, 
            <date>1803-1893</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Telfair family Papers, 1803-1893 
            <num type="collectionnumber">32226</num></subtitle>
            <author>Trenton Hizer</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            &address;
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">2 KB</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Marc
         record. Created by Renee M. Savits 
         <date>15 June 2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00454::A Guide to the Telfair family Papers,
            1803-1893 )//EN" "vi00454.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Telfair family Papers, 
         <date>1803-1893</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">32226</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Trenton Hizer</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Telfair family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1803-1893</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Accession number">32226</unitid>
         <physloc label="Physical Location">Personal papers collection,
         Acc. 32226</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.04 cu. ft.,
         photocopies</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Telfair family. Papers, 1803-1893. Accession 32226,
            Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia,
            Richmond, Virginia.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Lent for copying by M.O. Roache, Jr., 25 June 1984.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Thomas Telfair was born 2 March 1787 and Margaret Long was
         born 31 January 1789. They married 18 March 1809. The Telfairs
         became a prominent and wealthy family in Georgia, owning
         property in Savannah, and Chatham and Wilkes Counties,
         Georgia.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>Papers, 1803-1893, of the Telfair family of Chatham and
         Wilkes Counties, Georgia, consisting of correspondence, deeds,
         genealogical notes and charts, and wills. Some correspondence
         concerns a land claim in Maury County, Tennessee. There is a
         list, 1838, of slaves which gives their ages.</p>
         <p>Items consist of: a) will, 21 September 1803, of William
         Gibbons of Chatham County, Georgia, disposing of his property
         including slaves, copy made 19 April 1861; b) will, 20 January
         1807, of George W. Long of Halifax County, North Carolina,
         disposing of his property in North Carolina, Georgia, and the
         "western country, and of his slaves; c) marriage license, 29
         November 1827, for John Burch and Patience D. Cobb of Wilkes
         County, Georgia; d) letter, 4 April 1832, from Alexander
         Telfair (d. 1832) of Savannah, Georgia, to Margaret Telfair of
         Wilkes County sending copies of a marriage agreement, and
         discussing settlement of his father's and brother's estates,
         and cotton crops on various Telfair properties; e) deed, dated
         16 March 1836 and recorded 8 November 1836, for a tract of
         land in Wilkes County from Margaret Telfair of Chatham County
         to Lock Weems of Wilkes County; f) letter, 25 January[?] 1837,
         from Robert Habersham to John M. Berrien concerning Mrs.
         Cobb's marriage settlement and the estate of Thomas Telfair;
         g) list, 1838, of slaves giving ages and values taken by G.
         Jones; h) letter, 15 September 1838, from Robert Habersham of
         Savannah to Margaret Telfair of Jefferson County, Georgia,
         regarding legal and personal matters; i) letter, 3 February
         1840, from Robert Habersham to Margaret Telfair concerning
         legal matters involving a division of property and slaves; j)
         letter, 8 March 1848, from Genevieve Pierce of Annisquam,
         Massachusetts, to her sister Mrs. Harriet M. Andrews of
         Boston, Massachusetts, containing personal news; and k)
         letter, 28 October 1851, from Duke Williams of Maury County,
         Tennessee, to Margaret Telfair of Savannah concerning land in
         Maury County owned at one time by her grandfather and part of
         his estate.</p>
         <p>Also includes: l) letter, 1858, from Harriet Pierce of
         Annisquam, Massachusetts, to her daughter Harriet M. Andrews
         of Boston, Massachusetts, containing personal news; m)
         receipt, 22 January 1866, from the United States to A. P.
         Wetter for payment of direct taxes on property in Savannah; n)
         letter, 25 May 1871, from Frank Baltzell of Marianna, Florida,
         to A. P. Wetter of Savannah informing Wetter that as an heir
         of Margaret Telfair he has claim to land in Maury County,
         Tennessee, on which the town of Columbia sits; o) certified
         list, 1 March 1889, of marriage licenses issued in Wilkes
         County from 1813 to 1830 for the Long family; p) agreement, 11
         October 1893, between John W. Taylor of Omaha, Nebraska, and
         Edward Telfair Wetter of Chatham County, Georgia, in which
         Taylor agrees to sell to Wetter his interests and claims in
         the "Las Arcas Cays" in the Gulf of Mexico and all rights to
         guano deposits on the islands; q) memorandum on the the family
         of Thomas and Margaret Telfair including their birth and
         marriage dates and the birth dates of their children; r) notes
         on the division of property formerly owned by James Ballion
         and William Gibbons; s) genealogical notes on the Benning
         family of Georgia; t) genealogical chart of the Long, Milton,
         Telfair, and Weems families of Georgia; and u) genealogical
         notes and chart on the Long and Cobb families of Georgia.</p>
      </scopecontent>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
