<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05886">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00846::A Guide to Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, 1844-1849)//EN" "vi00846.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, <date>1867</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book
<num type="barcodenumber">0007848112
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2003  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record by Greg Crawford, <date>17 November 2003</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, <date>1844-1849</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Number">0007848112
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1844-1849
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007848112
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 volume (70 pages)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Lunenburg County (Va.)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, 1844-1849. Local government records collection, Lunenburg County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Lunenburg County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: November 2003; updated by M. Long: May 2023.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:</title> Captain John C. Epes was an agent who acted as the southern link of the trading partnership Sneed &amp; Epes, a Lunenburg-based firm that was engaged in the business of buying, transporting, and reselling enslaved people.
</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Lunenburg County was named for King George II, duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg, a German possession of England's Hanoverian kings. It was formed from Brunswick County by an act that took effect on 1 May 1746. Part of Lunenburg County was added in 1777.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Materials in the Library of Virginia’s collections contain historical terms, phrases, and images that are offensive to modern readers. These include demeaning and dehumanizing references to race, ethnicity, and nationality; enslaved or free status; physical and mental ability; religion; sex; and sexual orientation and gender identity.</title></p>

<p><title render="italic">The Library of Virginia will at times choose to retain original language in collection descriptions to preserve historical accuracy or to document context. Historical terms and phrases are indicated by the use of quotation marks to differentiate between language taken from a historical source and the language generated by Library of Virginia staff. Examples: Organizational names, titles, place names, and personally chosen identifiers.</title></p>

<p>Captain John C. Epes Memorandum Book, 1844-1849 contains miscellaneous information related to Epes's transporting and selling of enslaved people. A portion of the book was used as a travel journal that gives a brief account of Epes's journey from his home in Gainesville, Alabama to Lunenburg Court House, Virginia. The book includes entries related to the purchase and sell of enslaved people on behalf of Sneed &amp; Epes, as well as accounts of related expenses incurred by Epes over the course of the journey, such as additional clothing for several of the enslaved. Entries record names of enslaved people and their initial and final purchase price. It also lists names of enslaved people owned by Daniel S. McCormick.
</p>
<p>Also includes a letter dated August 27, 1847, written by Richard J. Epes of Jackson, Mississippi to his brother Captain John C. Epes at Lunenburg Court House, Virginia. In the letter, Richard Epes makes reference to his brother transporting and selling enslaved people. 
</p> 
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Lunenburg County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
<p>
Records related to free and enslaved people of Lunenburg County and other localities are available on <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/discovery/search?vid=01LVA_INST:VU">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia.</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
