<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi00993">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00993::A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009))//EN" "vi00993.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, <date>2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">Kaine, Governor Timothy M., Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
<num type="collectionnumber">44708
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Roger E. Christman and Ben Bromley
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2014-2018  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Roger E. Christman, <date>3 January 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, <date>2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44708
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Roger E. Christman and Ben Bromley
</author>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2014-2018 
</date>

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Roger E. Christman and Ben Bromley
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44708
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">204279 emails (total as of 16 October 2018; on-going); 183558 emails open to researchers (as of 16 October 2018).
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>



<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>

<p>Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+42.1-78">42.1-78</extref>
, <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-3800">2.2-3800</extref>
 and <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-3705.1">2.2-3705.1-8</extref>
. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: pardon files granted and denied, restoration of rights granted and denied, privacy protected information, appointment of special counsel, mediation and settlement discussions, and attorney-client privileged material. 
</p>

</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.  The Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, collection is accessible on line.  Researchers are strongly urged to view the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">Kaine email web site</extref>
 for search tips, related content and project information.  Despite the Library's best efforts, we knew it was possible for restricted information to be overlooked during the processing of this collection. Thus we created a virtual "reading room agreement" by creating a secure gateway to the online collection. In order to view the Kaine emails, users must log in using a generic account that the Library created for this collection. By logging in, users are acknowledging their researcher responsibilities regarding protected materials.  
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Governor (2006-2010 : Kaine), Electronic Files, Email, of the Administration of Governor Timothy M. Kaine, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), Accession 44708, State Records Collection, Library of Virginia 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>David Allen, Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, accession 44708 transferred on 25 January 2010. 
</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>

<p>The electronic files, including email, from the Governor Tim Kaine administration were transferred to the Library of Virginia on a hard drive. The files on the hard drive were loaded on the Library's secure dark archive and replicated on an off-site server. The electronic files were also loaded on to the processing server accessible to the processing archivists. All processing was done from the copied files on the processing server. Prior to processing, the Governors' Records Archivist compiled an inventory of each email pst file. The processing archivist noted the file name, name and title of box owner, date range, file size in KB and total number of email files. This information was categorized by office or cabinet secretariat. 
</p>

<p>Starting with the Executive Office, the processing archivist reviewed each email message to determine: if the email was a public record with a permanent disposition and/or if it should be restricted for legal, medical or personal privacy issues. The processing archivist consulted the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/retention_schedules/">office specific</extref>


 and <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/index.htm">general records retention and disposition schedules</extref>
 for guidance. The processing archivist used the category function available in Microsoft Outlook to color code non-records and restricted records. Non-records/non-permanent records include: personal or private correspondence, meeting requests/scheduling meetings (including RSVPs and going to lunch), administrative files (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule 101, series 100302</extref>
), declined invitations, travel arrangements, parking assignments (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 100345</extref>
), vacation or work schedules (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 100385</extref>
), leave records (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-102.pdf">General Schedule No. 102, series 012136</extref>
), computer problems, press releases and news clips (record copy is filed with Press Office), logistics for the Governor's Fellowship program, travel logistics for the governor, Executive Protections Unit contact information, conflict of interest files (Specific Schedule No. 166-001, 015120), grievance records and reports (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-103.pdf">General Schedule No. 103, series 100490</extref>
), unsolicited applications and resumes (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-103.pdf">General Schedule No. 103, series 100503</extref>
), legal summons (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule 101, series 100334</extref>
), voice mail messages (General Schedule No. 101, series 100388), invoices (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-102.pdf">General Schedule No. 102, series 012082</extref>
), disaster and emergency planning files (General Schedule 108, series 012274 building maintenance/space utilization (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-106.PDF">General Schedule No. 106, series 012232</extref>
), and Freedom of Information Act Requests (<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/agencies/records/sched_state/GS-101.pdf">General Schedule No. 101, series 012029</extref>
). The processing archivist made an exception for two FOIA requests that were deemed of historic value since the requests led to policy changes. Delegate Scott Lingamfelter's FOIA requests for how much state government spent on printing led to a near ban on state publications. After Governor Tim Kaine became chairman of the Democratic National Committee in January 2009, media outlets submitted FOIA requests for his daily schedule. The Kaine administration did not provide the schedule but did release the cities to which he traveled. 
</p>

<p>Processed copies of the email PST files were then passed on to the Library's information technology department for the technical phase of the project.  
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?000+cod+2.2-126">Section 2.2-126 of the Code of Virginia</extref>
 states that governor's records of a strictly personal or private nature are not public records and do not have to be transferred to the Library of Virginia. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/retention_schedules/121-001%20Office%20of%20the%20Governor.pdf">The Office of the Governor Records Retention and Disposition Schedule (Specific Schedule No. 121-100)</extref>
 further states that personal or private papers of the governor are non-records per the Virginia Public Records Act. Types of records may include but are not limited to correspondence with family or friends, personal business records and records of/from political organizations, not related to the role of the Governor or the Governor's staff. Only a small number of email messages met this definition and were removed from the collection. 
</p>

<p>The Library released this collection on-line as follows:  Series I. Executive Office on 13 January 2014; Series II. Policy Office on 28 March 2014; Series III. Communications Office on 30 April 2014; Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwelath on 7 July 2014; Series V. Secretary of Technology on 7 July 2014; Records pertaining to the 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech from Series I, II, III and IV, were released on 5 November 2015; Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety on 5 May 2016; records related to Jens Soering on 2 September 2016; Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce on 20 October 2016; and Series VIII. Secretary of Education on 16 October 2018.
</p>

</processinfo>

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Timothy M. Kaine was born on 26 February 1958 in St. Paul, Minnesota. He grew up in Kansas City and graduated from the University of Missouri-Columbia in 1979. While attending Harvard Law School, Kaine took a leave of absence to work with Jesuit missionaries as principal of the Institution Tecnico Loyola, a Catholic vocational school in El Progreso, Honduras. Kaine graduated from Harvard Law School in 1983 and was admitted to the Virginia Bar. Practicing law in Richmond, Virginia, as director of the McCandlish Kaine law firm, Kaine specialized in housing discrimination cases. He received recognition from the Richmond Bar Association, the National Fair Housing Association, and Lawyers for Public Justice for his work with civil rights. In addition, Kaine taught legal ethics for six years at the University of Richmond Law School.
</p>

<p>Kaine began his political career with an election to the Richmond City Council in 1994, serving as mayor from 1998 to 2001. During his four terms in the Richmond City Council, Kaine helped build new schools, encourage economic development, and implement the Project Exile Program to reduce violent crime. In 2001, Kaine ran for the Democratic Party nomination for Lieutenant Governor and won with 64,008 votes (39.66%). His opponents were Delegate Alan Diamonstein, with 50,753 votes (31.45%) and Del. Jerrauld C. Jones with 46,640 votes (28.90%). On 6 November 2001 Kaine was elected Lieutenant Governor with 925,974 votes (50.35%), defeating Republican Delegate Jay Katzen (883,886 votes, 48.86%) and Libertarian Gary Reams (28,783 votes, 1.57%). As Lieutenant Governor under Governor Mark R. Warner, Kaine supported state budget reform, education improvements, and the public broadcasting of the General Assembly. He served on the Governor's K-12 Accountability Workgroup, the Governor's Higher Education Summit, the Workforce Training Sub-Committee, the Secure Virginia Panel, the Citizens and Committees Sub-Committee, and chairman of the Disability Commission. In addition, Kaine worked on the Affordable Housing Preservation Action Committee, the Virginia Military Advisory Council, and the Olmstead Task Force.
</p>

<p>Kaine sought the governorship in 2005. On 8 November 2005, Kaine was elected Governor with 1,025,942 votes (51.72%) defeating Republican Attorney General Jerry Kilgore (912,327 votes, 45.99%) and Independent State Senator Russ Potts (43,953 votes, 2.22%). Tim Kaine became the 70th Governor of Virginia on 14 January 2006. 
</p>

<p>The Kaine administration was dominated by three issues: budget deficits, transportation funding and the 16 April 2007 shootings at Virginia Tech. Governor Kaine took office shortly before the beginning of the "Great Recession", the worst economic downturn since the Great Depression of the 1930s. From 2007 to the end of his administration in January 2010, Kaine cut nearly $5 billion in state spending in order to balance the budget without raising taxes. Despite these cuts, Virginia retained its AAA bond rating and in 2008 was ranked as the best managed state in America by Governing Magazine. Virginia was also named as the most business-friendly state in America for 2006, 2007, 2008 and 2009 by Forbes.com.
</p>

<p>Despite several attempts, the Kaine administration was unable to find a reliable source of transportation funding. Kaine's 2006 proposal of increased taxes and fees was rejected by the Republican-controlled House of Delegates. In 2007 Kaine reached agreement with the Republican General Assembly on a compromise transportation package. It was the biggest transportation funding increase since 1986. The plan did not include a statewide tax increase but authorized borrowing up to $3 billion over ten years. It also granted taxing powers to regional authorities in Northern Virginia and Tidewater to support $500 million in bond-financed transportation projects. Success was short lived. One section of the legislation on abuser driver fees drew extensive criticism when it was discovered that the fees only applied to Virginians and not out-of-state residents. The General Assembly later repealed this provision. In early 2008 the Virginia Supreme Court ruled that unelected regional authorities could not raise taxes. In May 2008 Kaine proposed a new transportation plan that called for an increase in vehicle registration fees and the sales tax. A 2008 special session on transportation funding ended without an agreement.
</p>

<p>On 16 April 2007, Seung Hui Cho killed 32 people and injured at least 17 others before turning the gun on himself. The massacre at Virginia Tech is the deadliest shooting incident by a single gunman in United States history. At the time of the shooting, Governor Kaine had just arrived in Tokyo, Japan, for a trade mission. Kaine immediately returned to Virginia to deliver the convocation at Virginia Tech the next day. On 19 April 2007, Kaine commissioned the Virginia Tech Review Panel "to conduct an independent, thorough, and objective incident review of the tragedy at Virginia Tech and to make recommendations regarding improvements that can be made in the Commonwealth's laws, policies, procedures, systems and institutions, as well as those of other governmental entities and private providers." Kaine formalized the Tech Panel's charge in Executive Order 53 (2007) issued on 18 June 2007. Colonel Gerald Massengill, a retired Virginia State Police Superintendent, chaired the Panel. The Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel was released on 30 August 2007. It revealed deficiencies in the mental health care system, campus security and gun laws. The Panel made more than 70 recommendations directed to colleges, universities, mental health providers, law enforcement officials, emergency service providers and law makers. The General Assembly passed legislation to reform the mental health commitment laws and campus security policies. One major recommendation by the Panel was defeated: requiring background checks for all firearms purchased at gun shows.
</p>

<p>In April 2008, the state reached an $11 million financial settlement with 24 families of students and faculty who were killed or injured during the Virginia Tech shooting. The state agreed to provide monetary pay outs, medical care and information on the shooting in exchange for the families to waive their rights to sue. Two families who filed claims against the state did not accept the settlement and filed a civil suit in 2009. The discovery of Cho's Cook Counseling Center records in July 2009 and other concerns by family members about the Panel's timeline for 16 April 2007, lead to calls for the Panel to reconvene. Kaine did not reconvene the Panel but agreed to have the report revised to reflect the new details that surfaced since 2007. The amended report was released in the last month of the Kaine administration. On 12 March 2012, a jury in the civil suit found Virginia Tech negligent in failing to warn students of a possible gunman on campus. 
</p>

<p>Other significant accomplishments of the Kaine administration include: a ban on smoking in bars and restaurants, funding to clean up the Chesapeake Bay, the preservation of over 400,000 acres of open spaces, passage of a $1.6 billion bond package for higher education construction projects, expanding pre-K education, required teacher evaluations, and Renew Virginia Initiatives (energy).
</p>

<p>During his term, Governor Kaine served as chairman of the Southern Governors' Association (2008-2009) and Chairman of the Democratic National Committee (2009-2011). On 6 November 2012, Kaine was elected United States Senator with 2,010,067 votes (52.86%) defeating Republican George Allen (1,785,542 votes, 46.96%).
</p>

<p>Kaine is married to Anne Bright Holton, youngest daughter of former Governor Linwood Holton. Anne and Tim have three children, Nat, Woody, and Annella.
</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>These records include agreements, briefing books, reports, correspondence, memorandums, agendas, electronic mail, handouts, invitations, meeting notes, press releases (drafts), spreadsheets (budget), talking points, and speeches. This collection documents the email of the Kaine Administration (2006-2010). The Library of Virginia is releasing the Kaine email in batches.  This collection contains email from staff members who also worked in Governor Mark R. Warner's administration (2002-2006) including William H. Leighty, John Marshall, and Margaret Hughson. To access the Kaine email collection and to learn more about other Kaine administration records, click <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">here</extref>
.
</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Tim Kaine Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Lawrence Roberts Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Mark Rubin Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Shane Emmett Email, 2008-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries E. William H. Leighty Email, 2002-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Wayne Turnage Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Stephen Harms Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries H. Marc Follmer Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries I. Sherrie Harrington Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries J. Kate Paris Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries K. Margaret Hughson Email, 2005-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries L. Sarah Plumb Email, 2007-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries M. Beau Cribbs Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries N. Bryce Schunke Email, 2009;</item>
<item>Subseries O. Sarah Robertson Email, 2009.</item>
</list>

<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, 2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Steven P. Gould Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Suzette Denslow Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Felix Sarfo-Kantanka Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Gena Boyle Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Jennie Moline Email, 2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2008);</item>
<item>Subseries F. Maribel Ramos Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Megan Root Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries H. Barbara Reese Email, 2009-2010.</item>
</list>

<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Lynda Tran Email, 2009-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Jeff Kraus Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Gordon Hickey Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Maurice A. Henderson II Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Jeff Tiller Email, 2006-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Robin Winchell Email, 2005-2006;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Michael Kelly Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries H. Lauren Cunningham Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries I. Doug Scott Email, 2008-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries J. Laura DeLibero Email, 2009;</item>
<item>Subseries K. Amanda Howe Email, 2009-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries L. Michaele White Email, 2006-2010.</item>
</list>


<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Kate Hanley Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Bernard Henderson Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries C. JoAnn Pulliam Email, 2006;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Lynn Clayton Email, 2005-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Jonathan Young Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Alicia Roberts Email, 2007;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Paul Brockwell Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries H. Matt Gross Email, 2009;</item>
<item>Subseries I. Betsy Anderson Email, 2008-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries J. Chris Marshburn Email, 2007-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries K. Greg Hennig Email, 2008-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries L. Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries M. Sindy Benavides Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries N. Kimberly Bowers Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries O. Nick Surace Email, 2008-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries P. Dawn Farrar Email, 2006-2007.</item>
</list>


<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Aneesh Chopra Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Tristen Pegram Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Len Pomata Email, 2009-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries D. John McDonald Email, 2009-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Tim Bass Email, 2005-2006;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Karen Jackson Email, 2008;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Brian Chiglinsky Email, 2008-2010.</item>
</list>


<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Files, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. John Marshall Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Clyde Cristman, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Marilyn Harris Email, 2008-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Dawn Smith Email, 2002-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Erin Bryant Email, 2005-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Susan Gholston Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Jacklyn Varela Email, 2006-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries H. Iva Frizzle Email, 2002-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries I. Martha Hazelgrove Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries J. Gabrielle Williams Email, 2008-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries K. Beth Camphouse Email, 2009-2010.</item>
</list>

<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A.  Daniel LeBlanc Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries B.  Gail Robinson Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries C.  Brian Davis Email, 2007 and 2009;</item>
<item>Subseries D.  Marietta Salyer Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries E.  Beatrice Yarney Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries F.  Sarah Abubaker Email, 2007-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries G.  Patrick Callahan Email, 2009-2010.</item>
</list>

<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009):</emph></item>
<item>Subseries A. Thomas Morris Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries B. Judy Heiman Email, 2006-2008;</item>
<item>Subseries C. Dietra Trent Email, 2006-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries D. Douglas Garcia Email, 2007-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries E. Jean Bankos Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries F. Kathy Glazer Email, 2006-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries G. Kendall Tyree Email, 2005-2009;</item>
<item>Subseries H. June Hines Email, 2006-2007;</item>
<item>Subseries I. Lorraine Lintecum Email, 2008-2010;</item>
<item>Subseries J. Nicholas Galvin Email, 2009.</item>
</list>





</arrangement>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>

<p>
<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/kaine/">Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.archive-it.org/collections/263">Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dhCkCL">Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00998.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration YouTube Channel Videos, 2008-2010.</extref>
</p>


<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00978.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records, 2005-2009.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00982.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records, 2006-2009.</extref></p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00983.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, Records, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00984.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00986.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Press Office, Records, 2004-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00987.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Records, 2006-2009.</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00988.xml">A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Latino Liaison Records, 2004-2009. </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04852.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1995-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03089.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2002-2010 (bulk 2005-2009. </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03050.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2005-2010. </extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04330.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>

<p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04328.xml">A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Technology, 2000-2009 (bulk 2006-2009).</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>


<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 90436 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Executive Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Executive Office of the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 90436 emails in 15 subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Tim Kaine Email; B. Lawrence Roberts Email; C. Mark Rubin Email; D. Shane Emmett Email; E. William H. Leighty Email; F. Wayne Turnage Email; G. Stephen Harms Email; H. Marc Follmer Email; I. Sherrie Harrington Email; J. Kate Paris Email; K. Margaret Hughson Email; L. Sarah Plumb Email; M. Beau Cribbs Email; N. Bryce Schunke Email; and O. Sarah Robertson Email.  There are 16077 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.  </p>


<p>The Executive Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. Members of the Executive Office include the Governor, Chief of Staff, Counselor to the Governor and their deputies and assistants. The Governor is the Chief Executive of the Commonwealth and chief advocate for annual legislative and budget priorities. Sherrie Harrington served as Confidential Assistant to Governor Tim Kaine.
</p>


<p>The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government, responsible for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office. The Chief is assisted in these responsibilities by a Deputy Chief of Staff and an Executive Assistant. The following individuals held these positions during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010): William H. Leighty, Chief of Staff (January 2006-May 2007); Wayne Turnage, Deputy Chief of Staff, (January 2006-May 2007) and Chief of Staff (May 2007-2010); Margaret Hughson, Executive Assistant (2006-2007); Steve Harms, Deputy Chief of Staff (June 2007-2010); and Kate Paris, Confidential Assistant to the Chief of Staff and Counselor (2007-2010).
</p>


<p>The Counselor in the Kaine administration provided legal advice to the Governor and acted as a liaison with the judiciary and the Office of the Attorney General. The Counselor also provided broader advice to the Governor on political and personal matters as assigned. The Counselor was the chief liaison with the Democratic Party, the Moving Virginia Forward PAC, and outside political constituency groups. The Counselor was assisted in these responsibilities by a Senior Advisor, a hybrid position, who provided legal assistance to the Counselor and legislative assistance to the Policy Director. The Senior Advisor was available to mediate important policy disputes for the Governor, or with the Governor's consent, for legislators and other external constituents. The following individuals held these positions during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010): Lawrence Roberts, Counselor to the Governor (January 2006-May 2009) and Mark E. Rubin, Senior Advisor to the Governor and Deputy Counselor (January 2006-May 2009) and Counselor to the Governor (May 2009-January 2010).
</p>


<p>The Leadership Team in the Office of the Governor consisted of the Chief of Staff, Deputy Chief of Staff, Counselor, Senior Advisor, Policy Director, Legislative Director, Communications Director, Scheduling Director and Press Secretary.  This group conducted daily morning meetings in preparation for that day's events in the Governor's Office. The Governor held regular meetings with this group and in certain instances convened small subsets of the Leadership Team to address specific or more targeted issues.  
</p>


</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries A. Tim Kaine Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 3875 emails in three pst files: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cUFWyx"><emph render="bold">TKAINE.PST, KaineLibkaine.pst, and TKAINE59404639.pst</emph></extref>. Governor Kaine's email did not have a file structure.  Governor Kaine archived his own email.  In an email from Kaine, dated 30 December 2009, to Mark Rubin, Counselor to the Governor, and Sherrie Harrington, Confidential Assistant to the Governor, Kaine stated he had "now gone through all emails from May 07 until current.  David Allen [VITA/NG] was not able to find earlier emails."  However, email messages Kaine sent from January 2006 to April 2007 may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine administration (Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Wayne Turnage, Bill Leighty, etc.).
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibkaine.pst</emph> contains 10 emails between Governor Kaine and Marc Follmer, Senior Advisor to the Governor.  The <emph render="bold">TKAINE59404639.pst</emph> contains 109 emails sent by the public to the GovKaine email account and were forwarded to Sasha Scott, Special Assistant in Constituent Services.  All of these emails comment on the University of Virginia's newspaper, The Cavalier Daily, publication of a cartoon attacking Christianity in 2008.
</p>
 


<p>The <emph render="bold">TKAINE.PST</emph> contains 3756 emails sent by Governor Kaine between April 2007 and January 2010.  There are 158 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted material may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including creation and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, notes from meeting with family members and correspondence between Governor Kaine and family members; budget issues; transportation (drafts of June 2008 General Assembly special session speech, Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute, 2007 abusive driver fees); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2008, 2009 and 2010); Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative (includes Biscuit Run property in Albemarle County); blanket restoration of rights; clemency (Norfolk Four and Percy Walton-restricted); relocation of Northrup Grumman's corporate headquarters to northern Virginia; drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2007, December 2007, August 2008, December 2008, August 2009 and December 2009); fiscal 2010-2012 budget development; 2009 closure of International Paper's mill in Franklin, Virginia; Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG); Chesapeake Bay clean-up; Virginia tribal recognition; Choose Life license plate; smoking ban in restaurants; economic development projects; proposal by the United States Navy to move a nuclear-powered aircraft carrier from Norfolk Naval Station to Naval Station Mayport, Florida; preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; draft of Kaine's 15 December 2008 speech to the Electoral College; preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election (Weekly Election Working Group); energy policy; education; drafts of Kaine's eulogy for civil rights icon Oliver Hill; Virginia State Air Pollution Control Board (Dominion Power's Wise County project); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); payday lending; Kaine's official portrait; domestic partner benefits; structure and responsibilities of Office of the Governor;  and retirement of Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in 2007. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Kimberly Bowers, Gina Boyle, Amy Bridge, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Aneesh Chopra, Robert Crouch, Suzette Denslow, Mark Emblidge, Shane Emmett, Cathy Ghidotti, Patrick Gottschalk, Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Gail Jaspen, Michael Kelly, Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Tom Morris, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Brian Sheppard, Delacey Skinner, Nick Surace, Marilyn Tavenner, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, Jody Wagner, and Stephen Walz.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Lawrence Roberts</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 34247 emails in three pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNK9jg"> <emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst, LRoberts2.pst, and LRoberts3.pst</emph></extref>. Lawrence Roberts served as Counselor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 until 9 March 2009 when resigned to take a position as Senior Advisor to the Chairman of the Democratic National Committee (Governor Tim Kaine).  During the Kaine Administration, the Counselor to the Governor provided legal advice to the Governor, including liaison with the judiciary and the Office of the Attorney General.  The Counselor also handled Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, conflict of interest statements, contracts/leases for the Governor, settlement agreements for the Governor, clemency requests, death warrants, and provided broader advice to the Governor on political and personal matters as assigned.  The Counselor was the chief liaison with the Democratic Party, the Moving Virginia Forward PAC, and outside political constituency groups.  As part of his outreach efforts, the Counselor developed strategies to interact and facilitate implementation of the Governor's agenda.  Roberts also worked with the Scheduling Director to oversee the Governor's time.  After his resignation, Roberts continued to serve as an unpaid advisor to the Governor on four issues:  the Commonwealth's response to the Virginia Tech tragedy; concluding clemency matters which he had worked on; reviewing his files and documents for archiving; and reaching an agreement with the Library of Virginia as to archiving policies as they apply to the Counselor to the Governor and his staff.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">January 2006-January 2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts1.pst</emph> file contains 28542 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 8655 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.</p>



<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including creation and report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, notes from meeting with family members, settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families and correspondence between Roberts and family members; revenue budget issues; transportation (drafts of June 2008 General Assembly special session speech, 2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute, Tyson Tunnel Plan and Full Funding Grant Agreement (FFGA), 2007 abusive driver fees, Elliston intermodal facility in Montgomery County, 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation, and Coalfields Expressway); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2006, August 2007, December 2007 and August 2008); clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); open carry (firearms in state parks); archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; talking points for February 2009 Virginia Congressional Delegation meeting (drafts); smoking ban in restaurants; proposal by the United States Navy to move a nuclear-powered aircraft carrier from Norfolk Naval Station to Naval Station Mayport, Florida; state government printing expenses (Freedom of Information Act request from Delegate Scott Lingamfelter); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; student voting; teleworking; Civil Rights Memorial; drafts of press releases/comments on media stories; Dominion Power's Wise County project; cabinet meetings (agendas); legislation/legislative sessions; Virginia Latino Advisory Board; election issues in Chesterfield County, 2008 Presidential primary; talking points (drafts, etc.) on a variety of subjects; resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish from Virginia Commission on Immigration; education (Pre-K, Start Strong); death of Oliver Hill and viewing at Governor's Mansion; Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood; judicial vacancies; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); health care work group; Governor incapacity and succession; Virginia tribal recognition; electricity re-regulation; Fort Monroe; Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria;  State Board of Elections issues; agreements with Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE)/287(g) [Executive Work Group related to possible state immigration authority with ICE under 287 (g) (8 USC Section 1357 (g))]; Comprehensive Services Act (CSA); Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA)/Arlington; energy policy; drafts of some executive orders; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); 2006 budget impasse; menhaden fisheries management measures; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth and successful confirmation of Kate Hanley for same post; DNA testing/old DFS files; domestic partner benefits; Employee Free Choice Act; estate tax repeal; TANF (Temporary Assistance for Needy Families); and Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email from Tim Kaine, 15 October 2007, Budget Issues I Care About ; email from Mark Rubin on Supreme Court rollout of Judge Goodwyn, 3 October 2007; email from Kaine on improving vetting process after resignation of Dr. Esam Omeish, 27 September 2007;  Kaine's comments on speech to money committees (18 August 2007); email thread started by Kaine on the operations/structure of the Governor's Office (3 April 2007); email from Kaine on electricity reregulation (17 March 2007); emails from Kaine on transportation (22 July 2008, 1 July 2008, 9 May 2008, 8 May 2008, 28 April 2008, 19 March 2008, 2 April 2007, 30 March 2007, 20 March 2007, 28 February 2007, 5 February 2007); email threads on abusive driver fees (19 July 2007, 18 July 2007, 17 July 2007, 16 July 2007); email from Larry Roberts, 7 May 2007, on strategic scheduling for 2007; email from Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 4 May 2007, on budget timeline/schedule; email thread between Roberts and Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email from Ric Signer to Leighty (Roberts cc'd), 17 April 2007, on the trade mission to Japan; email thread on electric reregulation (see Kaine's lengthy email dated 17 March 2007); 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: James Alcorn, Amber Amato, Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, Sindy Benavides, Mark Bowles, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Kim Busch, Larry Byrne, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Barnie Day, Suzette Denslow, Nick Donohue, Jason Eige, Kim Farrar, Patrick Finnerty, Marc Follmer, Manju Ganeriwala, Cathy Ghidotti, Kathy Glazer, Patrick Gottschalk, Eric Gregory (assistant AG), Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurcie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent (assistant AG), Jeff Kraus, Danny LeBlanc, Keetch leGrand, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Maureen Matsen (assistant AG), Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt (assistant AG), Steve Owens (assistant AG), Kate Paris, David Paylor, Sarah Plumb, Barbara Reese, Nancy Rodrigues, Nikki Rovener, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Sheppard, Ric Siger, Williams Sims, Delacey Skinner, D.B. Smit, Jeff Southard, Phil Sunderland, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Matthew Tucker, Wayne Turnage, Jim Ukrop, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, Tom Whipple and Richard Zorn.
</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts2.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
              
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts2.pst</emph> file contains 288 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  Subjects include:  American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); Federal issues impacting Virginia; and Virginia tribal recognition.
	</p>



<p>Correspondents include:  Gena Boyle, Eileen Filler-Corn, William Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Barbara Reese, and Brian Sheppard.
</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LRoberts3.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
              
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">LRoberts3.pst</emph> file contains 5417 emails sent and received by Lawrence Roberts between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 4033 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.</p>



<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including leak of report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel to the New York Times; email thread between Chief of Staff Bill Leighty and Secretary of Natural Resources Preston Bryant, 16 May 2007, in which Leighty discusses how he informed Governor Kaine about the Virginia Tech shooting; retirement of Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in 2007; archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; personnel changes in Office of the Governor (esp. spring/summer 2007); DNA testing/old DFS files; drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007, 2008 and 2009); preparations for the 4 November 2008 presidential election; drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly ( August 2007, December 2007); transportation (Tysons Corner tunnel, 2007 legislation, abusive driver fees); Clemency ; Maurice Henderson, Deputy Press Secretary, reports from 2006-2007 press gaggles/news conferences; drafts of Kaine's 2006 commencement address at the University of Virginia; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth; and clemency (Edward Bell, Mario Bustillo, Christopher Scott Emmett, Kevin Green, Brandon Wayne Hedrick, Kent Jackson, Michael William Lenz, Norfolk Four, John Yancey Schmitt, Jens Soering, Dexter Lee Vinson, Percy Walton, Earl Washington and Robert Stacy Yarbrough-all restricted).
	</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email from Kaine, 23 April 2007, describing the policy development agenda for the rest of 2007; email thread between Roberts and Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, 26 April 2007, about hiring Suzette Denslow as Deputy Policy Director and Leighty's unhappiness; email thread between Turnage and Roberts, 27 April 2007, discussing issues with Leighty; email exchange between Roberts and Sherrie Harrington, 9 November 2006, re: execution of John Yancey Schmitt; email exchange between Roberts and Turnage, 7 June and 9 June 2006 on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email from Marilyn Tavenner, 5 June 2006, on scheduled execution of Percy Walton; email exchange between Roberts and Brian Sheppard, 27 April 2006, re:  execution of Dexter Lee Vinson; and email thread between Kaine, Roberts and Delacey Skinner, 17 April and 16 April 2006, on Kaine's concerns about the marriage amendment. 

</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Katherine Burnett, Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Marla Decker, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Cathy Ghidotti, Patrick Gottschalk, Kevin Hall, Robert Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Bernard Henderson, Maurice Henderson, II, E. Desmond Hogan, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Danny LeBlanc, William Leighty, John Marshall, Walter McFarlane, William Mims, Jeffery Mitchell, Bill Murray, Thomas Nesbitt, Sarah Plumb, Brian Pumphrey, Mark Rubin, Brian Sheppard, Delacey Skinner, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>


</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Mark Rubin Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 10247 emails in two pst file: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNzbv3"><emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst and MRUBIN.pst</emph></extref>. Mark Rubin served as Deputy Counselor and Senior Advisor to the Governor from 14 January 2006 to 9 March 2009.  Following the resignation of Lawrence Roberts, Rubin served as Counselor to the Governor from 10 March 2009 to 16 January 2010.  The Senior Advisor was a hybrid position.  He provided legal assistance to the Counselor and legislative assistance to the Policy Director.  The Senior Advisor as helped mediate important policy disputes for the Governor.  Rubin frequently met with legislators and others and shared what he learned with senior administration officials.  His email provides information on legislation development and the legislative process.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibmrubin.pst</emph> file contains 10245 emails sent and received by Mark Rubin between January 2006 and January 2010.  There are 1563 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, mediation and settlement discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including issues regarding the settlement agreements between Commonwealth and families, forwarded emails sent to families by Jay Poole, Director of Virginia Tech's Office of Recovery and Support, and correspondence between Rubin and family members; budget issues including fall 2009 state agency reduction plans; legislation; transportation (2008 Kaine Transportation Plan, 2007 abusive driver fees, and 2006 General Assembly special session on transportation); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007 and 2009); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (December 2007, August 2008, December 2009); blanket restoration of rights; closure of Natural Bridge Juvenile Correctional Center; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; Virginia tribal recognition; smoking ban in restaurants; payday lending; Dominion Power's Wise County project; eminent domain; uranium mining; mental health legislation; workgroup for the Virginia Birth-Related Neurological Injury Compensation Program; Education (Pre-K); Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; energy policy (including Renewable Portfolio Standards); electricity re-regulation; indigent defense; machinery and tools legislation; Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); setting dates for special elections; clemency (Jens Soering, John T. Harrison, Daniel Cox, Richard M. Hawkins, Chris Sharikas, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Whitney Shelton, Norfolk Four, and Earl Washington-all restricted); and Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 16 April 2008, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate David Alba on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 18 April 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with Delegate Joe May on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 8 May 2008, to Mark Rubin, Larry Roberts, Suzette Denslow, Brian Shepard, Pierce Homer and Delacey Skinner, relaying a conversation Kaine had with several legislators on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 17 March 2007, to Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Larry Roberts, Patrick Gottschalk, Preston Bryant, and Bill Leighty, listing his concerns with the electric reregulation bill; email from Tim Kaine, 30 May 2006, to Larry Roberts, Jody Wagner, and Mark Rubin, sharing additional thoughts on the budget; email thread between Tim Kaine and Mark Rubin, 28 April 2008, setting the process for selection of circuit court judges, Supreme Court and an SCC judge; email from Mark Rubin, 11 February 2006, to Larry Roberts, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, Preston Bryant, Mike Henry, Bill Murray, and Daniel LeBlanc, detailing the latest vote count in the General Assembly to confirm LeBlanc as Secretary of the Commonwealth; email from Preston Bryant, 12 February 2006, to Mark Rubin, describing his conversations with several members of the House of Delegates on the LeBlanc nomination; email from Tim Kaine, 8 August 2006, to Bill Murray, Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard, and Mark Rubin, with Kaine's notes from phone conversations with several members of the General Assembly (notes as attachment) on transportation; email from Tim Kaine, 15 August 2006, 17 August 2006, and 21 August 2006, to Mark Rubin, Bill Murray and Brian Shepard, describing Kaine's contacts with several members of the General Assembly on transportation; email from Mark Rubin, 23 April 2006, to Brian Shepard and Bill Murray, on post mortem on the 2006 General Assembly session; email from Tim Kaine, 27 November 2009, to Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, and Ric Brown, where Kaine shares his views on eliminating the car tax in his final budget; and email from Tim Kaine, 6 February 2008, to Jody Wagner, Ric Brown, Wayne Turnage, Stephen Harms, Brian Shepard, Mark Rubin, Suzette Denslow, Larry Roberts, Delacey Skinner, and Gordon Hickey, in which Kaine shares his thoughts on the budget.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Philip Abraham, Amber Amato, David Bailey, Chris Bast, Steve Benjamin, Robert Blue, Gena Boyle, William Broaddus, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Don Carr, Bob Chase, Marc Cheatham, Eileen Filler-Corn, Robert Crouch, Marla Decker, George Deebo, Suzette Denslow, Chip Dicks, Dave Dickson, Betsy Edwards, Jerry Edwards, Mike Edwards, Shane Emmett, Helen Fahey, Claudia Farr, Frank Ferguson, Marc Follmer, May Fox, Robert Hall, Stephanie Hamlett, Stephen Harms, Kay Heidbreder, Bernard Henderson, Pierce Homer, Barbara Hulburt, Gail Jaspen, Jean Jensen, Tim Kaine, Martin Kent, Anne Leigh Kerr, Jim Kibler, Irene Leech, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Maureen Matsen, Michael Maul, Walter McFarlane, Bill McKelway, Eric Murdock, Bill Murray, Stephen Parker, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nancy Rodrigues, Michele Satterlund, Aimee Perron Seibert, Brian Shepard, Ric Signer, Jeff Southard, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, Bret Vassey, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, and Kent Willis.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MRUBIN.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">MRUBIN.pst</emph> file contains two email messages received by Mark Rubin dated 15 January 2010.  One message is from Kent Willis of the Virginia American Civil Liberties Union on Kaine's decision not to issue a blanket restoration of rights executive order.  The second message is from Gordon Hickey regarding Jens Soering.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>


</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Shane Emmett Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1090 emails in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cWx8TV"><emph render="bold">KaineLibsemmett.pst</emph></extref>.  Shane Emmett worked as a Governor's Legal Fellow and as a Deputy Counselor to Mark Rubin from December 2008 to January 2010.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsemmett.pst</emph> contains 1090 email messages sent and received by Shane Emmett.  There are 980 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: pardon files granted and denied, restoration of rights granted and denied.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  clemency (Edward Bell, Norfolk Four, Joseph Giarrantano, Larry Bill Elliott, Jens Soering, and John Muhammad-all restricted); and domestic partner benefits.  Correspondents include:  Katherine Burnett Baldwin, Andrew Block, Klaus Botzet, Marla Decker, Helen Fahey, E. Desmond Hogan, Gail Jaspen, Tim Kaine, Tom Kelly, Walter McFarlane, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, and Donald Salzman.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. William H. Leighty Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2002-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>This subseries contains 15752 emails in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e5ESYL"><emph render="bold">Leighty.pst</emph></extref>.  William H. Leighty served as Chief of Staff to Governor Mark R. Warner (January 2002-January 2006).  He was reappointed Chief of Staff by Governor Tim Kaine.  On 23 May 2007 Leighty announced his retirement effective 1 September 2007.  He stepped down as Chief of Staff effective 25 May 2007. Deputy Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage assumed his duties.  Leighty remained in the administration as Chief Emeritus working on several projects including efforts to improve minority procurement for state agencies, workforce development and the implementation of the outsourcing of state governments' IT functions.  The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government for all aspects of service to citizens.  The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office.  Governors Mark Warner and Tim Kaine delegated additional responsibilities to Leighty in Executive Order 3 (2002) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff and Executive Order 4 (2006) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">Leighty.pst</emph> file contains 15892 email messages sent and received by William H. Leighty between January 2002 and September 2007.  There are 141 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: investigative records, attorney-client privileged documents and medical information.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  At-Will Employee lists; 8th and 9th Street Office Buildings (movement of offices and demolition of 8th Street Office Building); Appalachian Regional Commission (ARC); bird flu (AI-2002); Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC); Beltway Sniper; Black Bear Landfill; Board of Veterans Services; budgets; possible budget shutdown 2006; Capitol renovation; consolidation of Department of Environmental Quality  boards; Department of Corrections media policy; Department of Game and Inland Fisheries investigation; Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute; economic development; education funding error (2006); education for a lifetime; Enterprise Applications Program; eVA; Virginia tribal recognition; Norfolk Ford plant closure; Fort Monroe, Governor's Commission on Efficiency and Effectiveness (Wilder Commission); Governor's December 2006/August 2006 speech to money committees (2006 drafts); Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives; Hurricane Isabel (including City of Poquoson aid); Hurricane Ivan; Hurricane Katrina (including reports from Leighty who helped in Louisiana); Jamestown 2007; King William Reservoir/Newport News; land conservation, including Governor Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative; rejection by General Assembly of Danny LeBlanc, Kaine's selection for Secretary of the Commonwealth; mail consolidation; Medicaid reform; menhaden fisheries management measures; mine safety; Mirant Potomac River Generating Plant (Mirant Plant) in Alexandria; moving offices to State Library Building (now the Patrick Henry Building); NASCAR Hall of Fame; No Child Left Behind (NCLB); Occoneechee State Park; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Pillowtex; Pre-K; Queen Elizabeth's visit to Virginia (2007); Race to GED; Seven Hills Health Care Center, Start Strong program; state climatologist; State Library building renovation (now the Patrick Henry Building; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); Tax Reform (2004); transportation (HB 3202, regional authorities, Elliston Intermodal, VDOT, Real ID, I-81, VDOT commissioner, Dulles Rail, Coalfields Expressway, Woodrow Wilson Bridge, Springfield interchange, and rest stops); Tropical Depression Gaston; Tropical Storm Ernesto (includes Battery Park area in Richmond); urban issues; Virginia Election and Registration Information System (VERIS); veterans issues; Virginia Horse Center; Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (billing issues, service issues, etc.); 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; Virginia Information Technology Investment Board (ITIB); Virginia Works; Washington Building renovation; Wise County water shortage (2005); and workforce development.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  Governor Kaine to Bill Leighty, Brian Shepard and Jody Wagner, 15 October 2006, re Kaine's thought's on 2nd year budget;  Sherrie Harrington to Bill Leighty, 6 June 2006 with attachment - presentation to rating agencies in New York;  Thanks from the Green Family, 28 September 2006; email thread between Leighty and Linda Hall re: death of detective Vicky Armel, 17 August 2006; Governor Kaine in Iraq, 14 March 2006; email thread between Leighty and Jim Waldron, that includes Leighty's thoughts on the Federal government's response to Hurricane Katrina, 24 September 2005; email exchange between Leighty and Ellen Qualls on preserving governor's web site, 3 May 2005; Leighty to Secretary of Technology Eugene Huang, re:  his European trip, 18 November 2004; and email exchange between Leighty and Turnage highlighting tension between them, 28 August 2007.

</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sheryl Bailey, Gerald Baliles, Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, John Bennett, Peter Blake, Robert Bloxom; Robert Blue, Barbara Bolin, Sandra Bowen, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Vincent Burgess, Robert Burnley, Marc Cheatham, Ryan Childress, Aneesh Chopra, Cheryl Clark, Whitt Clement, Michael Cline, Merritt Cogswell, Clyde Cristman , Robert Crouch, Pamela Currey, Don Darr, Ralph Davis, Jo Lynne Demary, Ben Dendy, Suzette Denslow, Bill Dickinson, David Ekern, Matt Erskine, Jan Faircloth, Eileen Filler-Corn, Kim Farrar, Eric Finkbeiner, George Foresman, Manju Ganeriwala, Patrick Gottschalk, Steven Gould, Barry Green, Kevin Hall, David Hallock, Lynette Hammond, Kate Hanley, Stephen Harms, Marilyn Harris, Anna Healy, Judith Heiman, Bernard Henderson, June Hines, Pierce Homer, Amanda Howe, Eugene Huang, Margaret Hughson, Bruce Jamerson (Queen's visit), Jean Jensen, Maurice Jones, Tim Kaine, Andy Kopplin, Jeff Krause, Daniel LeBlanc, Alfonso Lopez, Jon Mangis; John Marshall, Dominic Martin (Queen's visit), Gerald Massengill, Earl McClenney, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Tayloe Murphy, Bill Murray, Judy Napier, George Newstrom, David Paylor, David Poisson, Charles Pyle, Ellen Qualls, Karen Rae, Paul Reagan, Scott Reed, Barbara Reese, Jim Roberts, Larry Roberts, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Tareq Salahi (WH crasher), Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Jr., Michael Schewel, Saba Shami, Bill Shelton, Brian Shepard, Philip Shucet, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, D.B. Smit, Julie Stanley, Lem Stewart, Marilyn Tavenner, Ken Thorson, Dan Timberlake, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Fred Vincent, David Von Moll, Jody Wagner, Stephen Walz, Belle Wheelan, Michaele White, Sara R. Wilson, Jane Woods, and Richard Zorn
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries F. Wayne Turnage Email</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1046 number of email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dBaKlh"> <emph render="bold">KaineLibWTurnage.pst</emph></extref>. Wayne Turnage served as Deputy Chief of Staff (January 2006-May 2007) and as Chief of Staff to Governor Tim Kaine (May 2007-January 2010). On 23 May 2007 Chief of Staff William H. Leighty announced his retirement effective 1 September 2007. Leighty stepped down as Chief of Staff effective 25 May 2007 and Turnage assumed his duties. The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office. Governor Tim Kaine delegated additional responsibilities to Turnage in Executive Order 4 (2006) Authority and Responsibility of Chief of Staff. Turnage's pst file contained less than 1000 messages.  However, a large number of Turnage's messages can be found in the email files of Deputy Chief of Staff Stephen Harms, Governor Tim Kaine, Counselor to the Governor Larry Roberts, Senior Advisor to the Governor Mark Rubin, and Chief of Staff William H. Leighty.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibTurnage.pst</emph> file contains 1046 email messages sent and received by Wayne Turnage between January 2006 and January 2010. There is one privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.   
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  8th and 9th Street Office Buildings (movement of offices and demolition of 8th Street Office Building); audit reports; budget (budget cuts, budget development, Cabinet cuts, etc.); cabinet meeting agendas; Capitol Square parking; Council on Virginia's Future; Governor's Office (structure and performance management); Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM); transportation; urban issues/policy; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email to Bill Leighty, Delacey Skinner, Brian Shepard, and Larry Roberts, 12 November 2006, transmitting memorandum on Governor's Office operations; email to Jody Wagner, 27 August 2006, transmitting Chronology of Events Which Governor Learned of Education Funding Error; email to Larry Roberts and Brian Shepard, 17 July 2006, on education funding error; and email to Leighty, 20 July 2006, forwarding an email from Roberts containing detailed Governor's Office procedures for the execution Brandon Hedrick (restricted).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Ric Brown, [global messages to Cabinet], Aneesh Chopra, Clyde Cristman, Don Darr, Stephen Harms, Margaret Hughson, Tim Kaine, Jane Kusiak, Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Earl McClenney, Kate Paris, Brian Shepard, and Sara Wilson.
</p>


</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries G. Stephen W. Harms Email</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 13563 email messages in one pst file: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dvlCFw"><emph render="bold">KaineLibsharms.pst</emph></extref>. Stephen Harms served as Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources (January 2006-June 2007) and Deputy Chief of Staff (June 2007-January 2010).  Harms' email file contains a large number of messages about intergovernmental operations (IGO), finance and budget issues, and health care initiatives.
</p>



<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharms.pst</emph> file contains 13563 email messages sent and received by Stephen Harms between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 247 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  preparations for 12 February 2008 Democratic presidential primary and the 4 November 2008 presidential election;  American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-criteria for projects and creation of web site); archiving/records retention schedule for the Office of the Governor; briefings/budgeting for severance of at-will employees; budget cuts (revenue reports and budget cuts for Governor's Office and Cabinet); FY 2010-2012 budget development (also includes elimination of car tax and budget meeting with Governor-elect McDonnell); cabinet meetings (agendas); cabinet day(s); campus security conference (2007); Computer Matching and Privacy Protection Act (CMPPA) agreement with the Social Security Administration and Virginia; annual Virginia Congressional Delegation meeting; correspondence issues (late responses, need of editing, VIP process, etc.); drought conditions; Dulles Metro/Tysons Corner tunnel dispute; education (early childhood and pre-K); state government printing expenses (Freedom of Information Act request from Delegate Scott Lingamfelter); responses to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests for Governor Kaine's complete daily schedule (2009); gubernatorial transition; drafts of Governor Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (December 2006, December 2007, August 2008, December 2008, August 2009 and December 2009); preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; smoking ban in restaurants and state office buildings; teleworking; workforce development; Family Foundation Marriage Commission; National Service Initiative; Department of General Services, Division of Real Estate Services; Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS); transportation (Dulles Rail and abusive driver fees); unemployment insurance/Virginia Employment Commission (VEC); Virginia State Police report on terrorism groups (2009); 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (billing issues, service issues, etc.); United We Serve; and issues with responses to VIP correspondence.
</p>



<p>A significant number of messages related to health and human resources issues.  Subjects include:  budget;  Health IT Council; federal health care reform proposals; White House health care reform talking points (forwarded by Alphonso Lopez); Office of Health It; nursing program at Longwood University; Virginia SHARE network; Governor's Health Reform Commission; McKinsey proposal to Virginia; state agency issues [Commonwealth Services Act for At-Risk Youth and Families (CSA), Department of Medical Assistance (DMAS), Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services (DMHMRSAS)- name changed to Department of Behavioral Health and Development (DBHDS), Department of Rehabilitative Services (DRS), Department of Social Services (DSS), and Virginia Department of Health (VDH)]; State Executive Council (SEC); foster care; Medicaid; State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP); Family Access to Medical Insurance Security (FAMIS); Medicare Part D; Western State Hospital; Southeastern Virginia Training Center (SEVTC); Executive Directive 7 (07) Central Criminal Records Exchange; autism; prisoner re-entry; Poverty Task Force; Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF) cuts; fuel assistance for low-income Virginians; Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; Secretary of Health and Human Resources agency weekly reports; Olmstead (Community Integration for People with Disabilities); H1N1 strain of influenza; Sugar Grove water issue; Town of Goshen water leak; Patrick County hospital; HPV vaccine; and Seven Hills Nursing Home in City of Richmond.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  email exchange between Wayne Turnage and Tim Kaine, 31 December 2008, re:  Office Restructuring Proposal;  Governor's Office procedures for the execution of Robert Stacey Yarbrough, 25 June 2008 (restricted); State Board of Election issues, 12 June 2008; email exchange between Mark Rubin et al, 28 April 2008, re:  process for selecting judges; outline for gubernatorial transition, 18 April 2008; post 9/11 policy that one legislator sent to a secure location during State of the Commonwealth address, 7 January 2008; Governor Kaine's VIP mail process, 13 July 2007; Harms' thoughts on June meeting with Virginia Tech families, 25 June 2007; Email from Governor Kaine sharing his views on revenue options for 2012-2014 budget, 27 November 2009; email from Governor Kaine describing a meeting about legislation with Delegate Lacey Putney, 13 February 2008; email from Governor Kaine to senior staff sharing his thoughts on the budget, 6 February 2008, 3 February 2008, 30 January 2008, and 15 October 2007 ("Budget Issues I care about"); drafts of Health Care Reform op-ed by Tim Kaine and Mark O'Connell, 20 September 2009, 19 July 2009, 15 July 2009, 13 July 2009, 3 July 2009, and 30 June 2009; email between Tim Kaine and Wayne Turnage, State Health Insurance Policy Change (other qualified adult) and Wayne Turnage and Sara Wilson, 11 April 2009 and 12 April 2009; email from Kaine, 23 April 2007, re Reactions in the Aftermath of the Virginia Tech Shooting, 23 April 2007; email from Secretary of Health and Human Resources Marilyn Tavenner, 17 November 2009, re: list of on-going projects/issues for McDonnell Administration; "ransom note" from alleged PMP hacker forwarded by Alicia Cavanaugh, 30 April 2009; email from Robert Stroube to Marilyn Tavenner, et al with attachment listing autopsy information from Virginia Tech shooting, 18 April 2007; email exchange between Pierce Homer and Wayne Turnage on the dismal transportation budget numbers, 2 August 2009; draft of Kaine op-ed on transportation published in Washington Post,7-10 June 2009; Rest Area closure decision brief, 23 April 2009; email from Kaine sharing his thoughts on transportation, 22 July 2008; Mark Rubin's transportation to-do-list, 2 July 2008; email from Kaine to Pierce Homer, et al on transportation, 1 July 2008; drafts of Kaine's speech on transportation to joint session of General Assembly, 21-23 June 2008; email from Kaine on transportation message for roll-out and town hall meetings, 9 May 2008; email from Kaine relaying conversations he's had with state legislators on transportation issues, 8 May 2008; email from Kaine with his comments on the 21 April 2008 transportation compromise, 28 April 2008; email from Kaine relaying conversation he had with Joe May on transportation, 18 April 2008; and email from Kaine on his thoughts on transportation, 8 March 2008.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sarah Abubaker, Amber Amato, Karen Angelici (Casey Foundation), Viola Baskerville, Tim Bass, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Kristin Burhop, Craig Burns, Patrick Callahan, Alicia Cavanaugh, Marc Cheatham, Julie Christopher, Aneesh Chopra, Julie Christopher, Anthony Conyers, Scott Crawford, Clyde Cristman, Bob Crouch, Don Darr, Suzette Denslow, Heidi Dix, Emily Ehrlichmann, William Ellwood, Michael Evans, Michael Farley (Elk Hill Farm), Eileen Filler-Corn, Patrick Finnerty, Joe Flores, Chris Freund (VP, Policy and Communications, Family Foundation of Virginia [marriage commission]), Andrea Gaines, Manju Ganeriwala, Thomas Gates, Kathy Glazer, Patrick Gottschalk, Barry Green, Kevin Hall, Phil Hamilton, Lynette Hammond, Joyce Hann, Sherrie Harrington, Bo Harris, Marilyn Harris, Bernard Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Gary Janak, Gail Jaspen, Dennis Johnson, Latosha Johnson, Cindi Jones, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Karen Lawson, [John Layman - revenue reports forward], Daniel LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Dean Lynch, John Marshall, Jim Martinez, Kenneth McCabe, John McDonald, Kim McGaughey, Martha Mead, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Marsha Mucha, Bill Murray, Linda Nablo, Kate Paris, Ray Ratke, Barbara Reese, James Reinhard, Karen Remley, Larry Roberts, Gail Robinson, James Rothrock, Mark Rubin, Sandra Ryals, Brian Shepard, Margaret Schultze, Michael Shook, Richard Silwoski, Delacey Skinner, Chris Spanos, Julie Stanley, Robert Stroube, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Ed Turner, Michael Tutor, Seta Vandegrift, David Von Moll, Jody Wagner, Ruth Ann Walker, Sara Wilson, Patricia Wright, Beatrice Yarney, Joy Yeh, and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries H. Marc Follmer Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 5735 in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dHDYRD"><emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.PST and KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph></extref>. Marc Follmer was Deputy Director, Department of General Services (January 2006-2007), Deputy Assistant to the Governor, Office of Commonwealth Preparedness (2007-2009) and Senior Advisor to the Governor (2009-January 2010).  He also was a member of Virginia Tech Working Group.  
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">MFOLLMER.pst</emph> file contains 5524 emails sent and received by Marc Follmer between January 2006 and January 2010. There are 125 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech including workgroup established in Governor's Office to implement the settlement agreement between the Commonwealth and families; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; 2009 hurricane preparedness sales tax holiday; H1N1 strain of influenza; Virginia Business Credentials Program-Priority Access Stakeholder System (PASS); Secure Commonwealth Panel; revisions to Executive Order 6 (2006) Delegation of Governor's Authority to Declare a State of Emergency and to Call the Virginia National Guard to Active Service for Emergencies or Disasters when the Governor is Out of the Commonwealth of Virginia and Cannot be Reached; Air Force Cyber Command (AFCYBER); HB 1687 (2009) Motor vehicle dealers; disclosure if financing, cancellation of purchaser's contract to buy vehicle; HB 1983 (2009) Governor-declared emergency; provides civil immunity for private and charitable organizations; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); Real ID; Secure Commonwealth Panel; Fort Monroe including Fort Monroe Federal Area Development Authority (FMFADA); hurricane preparedness; gubernatorial disability; Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); Business and Industry Sub Panel; campus security conference (2007); mortgage foreclosure task force; Naval Air Station Oceana in Virginia Beach; Office of Commonwealth Preparedness budget cuts; Office of Commonwealth Preparedness legislation; Ready Virginia; Virginia Military Advisory Council (VMAC); and Virginia National Defense Industrial Authority (VNDIA).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Amber Amato, Curtis Brown, Preston Bryant, Mar Cheatham, Bob Crouch, Nicholas Donohue, Chris Essid, Douglas Fierberg, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Alleyn Harned, Marilyn Harris, Wendy Hoffman, Catherine Hutchins, Elizabeth Kersey, Bill Leighty, Robert Mauskapf, Constance McGeorge, Steven Mondul, Susan Mongold, Steve Owens, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Joe Samaha, Megan Samford, Phil Schaenman, Brian Shepard, Rick Siger, Richard Silwoski, Kerry Stuver, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Virginia Retail Merchants Association, Sara Wilson, Robert Young, and Richard Zorn.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibmfoller.pst</emph> file contains 211 emails sent and received by Marc Follmer between October 2006 and December 2009. Subjects include:  Virginia Secure Commonwealth Panel.  Correspondents include:  Don Butts and Leigh B. Middleton, Jr.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries I. Sherrie Harrington Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2176 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e5H6ay"><emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst and KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph></extref>. Sherrie Harrington was Confidential Assistant to Governor Tim Kaine from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">SHARRINGTON.pst</emph> file contains 2163 emails sent and received by Sherrie Harrington between December 2007 and January 2010. There are 54 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions, and records containing personal/personnel information.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; procedures for and issues with responses to VIP correspondence; Virginia tribal recognition; gifts for governor; and arrangements for President Barack Obama to call in to Governor Kaine's final Ask the Governor program on WTOP radio in December 2009.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email</emph>
:  Brian Chiglinsky, a Constituent Services staff member, was on "loan" as Governor Kaine's aide, filling in for Harrington (who was teleworking on Monday and Wednesday, beginning in November 2008),  and made frequent email reports to Harrington about what happened in the office and with the Governor.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Connie Briggs, Preston Bryant, Kimberly Busch, Marc Cheatham, Brian Chiglinsky, Beau Cribbs, Carol Denson, Catherine Evans, Cathy Ghidotti, Martha Hazelgrove, Gordon Hickey, Darryl Holt, Anne Holton, Tim Kaine, Lorraine Lintecum, Alphonso Lopez, Jennie Moline, Ryan Newcomb, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, and Stephen Walz.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsharrington.pst</emph> file contains 13 emails sent and received by Sherrie Harrington between June 2007 and July 2008. There are 9 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; and Percy Walton.  All correspondence are from Larry Roberts.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries J. Kate Paris Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 874 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cWBcDn"><emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst and KPARIS.pst</emph></extref>. Kate Paris was Special Assistant to the Counselor to the Governor (2006-2007) and Executive Assistant to the Chief of Staff and Counselor to the Governor (2007-2010).
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KateLibParis.pst</emph> file contains 262 emails sent and received by Kate Paris between September 2006  and January 2010. There are 55 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (meetings and updates for families); state agency head meeting; budget; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); and Norfolk Four (restricted).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Preston Bryant, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, and Sara Wilson.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KPARIS.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KPARIS.pst</emph> file contains 612 emails sent and received by Kate Paris between June 2006 and January 2010. There are 39 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions and records containing personal/personnel information.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (meetings and updates for families); agency contract spending; budget; cabinet meeting agendas; constituent correspondence; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus); drought conditions; election security working group; and gubernatorial transition.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sherrie Harrington, Barbara Reese; Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries K. Margaret Hughson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 389 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dxJ1mn"><emph render="bold">Mhughson.pst</emph></extref>. Margaret Hughson served as Governor Mark Warner's Director of Constituent Services (2005-2006) and Executive Assistant to Chief of Staff William H. Leighty in Governor Tim Kaine's administration (2006-2007).  Hughson also coordinated the Warner and Kaine's administration records management and archiving activities.  During her time of service, she was the Library of Virginia's primary contact for these issues.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  state agency head meeting; archiving of Governor's records for Warner and Kaine administrations; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (letters of support).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Ariel Billmeier, Roger Christman, Conley Edwards, William H. Leighty, Paige Neal, Wayne Turnage and Mark Walsh.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries L. Sarah Plumb Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1022 emails in one pst files: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNCP8j"><emph render="bold">KaineLibSPlumb.pst</emph></extref>. Sarah Plumb served as Director of External Relations from 2007 to October 2008.  One privacy protected and confidential email in this pst file is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: Virginia Tech Review Panel report; Education (Pre-K); revenue advisory group; transportation (2008 town hall meetings); and State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Jean Bankos, Andrew K. Block, Gena Boyle, Lauren Cunningham, Suzette Denslow, Andrea Gaines, Kathy Glazer, Julia Hammond, Pierce Homer, Michael Kelly, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Jeff Southard, and Jeff Tiller. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries M. Beau Cribbs Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 248 in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dhBIgp"><emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst and KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph></extref>. Cribbs was a Special Assistant in Constituent Services (2007-2008) and Executive Aide to the Governor (2008-2010).  
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">BCRIBBS.pst</emph> file contains 21 emails sent and received by Beau Cribbs in 2007.  All of the correspondents were related to constituent services work and were between Cribbs and Amber Amato, Director of Constituent Services.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibBCribbs.pst</emph> file contains 227 emails sent and received by Beau Cribbs between 2007-2010.  Subjects are primarily constituent correspondents work and declined invitations handled by Cribbs in his role as Executive Aide to the Governor.
	</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries N. Bryce Schunke Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 12 emails in one pst files:  <emph render="bold">BSCHUNKE.pst</emph>.  Bryce Schunke served as a Governor's Legal Fellow in 2009.  All 12 emails contain privacy protected and confidential information that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions.
</p>





</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Office Electronic Files, Subseries O. Sarah Robertson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2 emails in one pst files:  <emph render="bold">SROBERTSON.pst</emph>.  Sarah Robertson served as a Governor's Legal Fellow in 2009.  Both emails contain privacy protected and confidential information that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency and restoration of rights decisions/discussions. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


</c01>



<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 23308 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Policy Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Policy Office of the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 23308 emails in 8 subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Steven P. Gould Email; B. Suzette Denslow Email; C. Felix Sarfo-Kantanka Email; D. Gena Boyle Email; E. Jennie Moline Email; F. Maribel Ramos Email; G. Megan Root Email; and H. Barbara Reese Email.  There are 300 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, and records containing personal/personnel information. The pst file for Brian Shepard, Policy Director, was empty.  However, email messages sent by Shepard may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine Administration (Executive Office, Policy Office, etc.).
</p>



<p>The Policy Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. The Policy Director is responsible for planning and implementing the Governor's policy initiatives, including proposed legislation, as well as overseeing the Administration's response to legislation and initiatives proposed by legislators and other interested parties.  The Policy Director is responsible for managing the Governor's Office review of regulations and for the development and issuance of executive orders and executive directives.  Brian Sheppard held this position during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010).
</p>



<p>The Policy Director was assisted in his responsibilities by a Legislative Director/Deputy Policy Director (William L. Murray, January 2006-May 2007; Suzette Denslow, May 2007-January 2009; and Barbara Reese, January 2009-January 2010), Senior Advisor (Mark E. Rubin) and Policy Staff (Steven Gould, 2006-2007; Felix Safro-Katanka, Jr., 2006-2007; Gena Boyle, January 2006-December 2009; Maribel Ramos, 2006-2007; Joyce Walton; Jennie Moline, 2006-2009; Hayes Framme, 2006-2008; Marc Cheatham; and Megan Root). The Policy Director and Legislative Director were also a member of the Governor's Leadership Team.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries A. Steven P. Gould Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 594 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNURpY"><emph render="bold">Archive.pst</emph></extref>. Steven Gould served as Senior Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy from January 2006 to July 2007 when he left the Kaine administration to attend law school. Gould previously worked as Policy Assistant for Governor Mark Warner. During the Kaine administration, Gould focused on agriculture and forestry, commerce and trade, technology, and workforce development issues. He also coordinated the Governor's Fellows program.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  2006 and 2007 bill signing requests from legislators and interested parties; agriculture and forestry; consumer data privacy working group (Executive Directive 5-Protecting Consumer Privacy); Governor's Fellows Program; housing; legislation; Northern Virginia Technology Council executive trip to southside Virginia with Governor Kaine, June 2007; roadless rule for two national forests (George Washington and Jefferson); and workforce issues.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Andres Alvarez, Gena Boyle, Steve Bridges, Bill Dickinson, Patrick Gottschalk, Daniel LeBlanc, William H. Leighty, Bill Murray, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Shepard, Rick Siger, and Ed Turner.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Suzette Denslow Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 452 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNWTqn"><emph render="bold">SDENSLOW.PST</emph></extref>. Suzette Denslow served as Governor Kaine's Deputy Director of Policy and Legislative Director from May 2007 to January 2009 when she left the Kaine administration to become Chief of Staff to Richmond Mayor Dwight C. Jones. One privacy protected and confidential email is this file is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Denslow previously worked as Deputy and Director of Policy for Governor Mark Warner. During the Kaine administration, Denslow focused on legislation, education issues and foster care.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  education (including funding for Pre-K, teacher salaries, budget); legislation, smoking ban; fuel issues (Virginia Petroleum Convenience and Grocery Association); foster care; drafts of an executive order for Hurricane Hanna (September 2008); and legislation.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Jean Bankos, Craig Burns, Michael Cline, Alex Daniel, Kent Dickey, Al Eisenberg,  David Englin, Emmett Hanger, Bob Herndon, Anne Holton, Lynette Isbell, Tim Kaine, William H. Leighty, Joseph Maroon, Mike O'Connor, David Poisson, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Mira Siner, Dr. Thomas W.D. Smith, David Toscano, Dietra Trent, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Felix Sarfo-Kantanka Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 5601 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e5MJpd"><emph render="bold">FSarfo-Kantanka.pst</emph></extref>. There are 167 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: personal information.  Felix Sarfo-Kantanka served as Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy in the Kaine administration from January 2006 to November 2007.  Sarfo-Kantanka worked as liaison between Public Secretary Office, Office of Commonwealth Preparedness and the General Assembly.  He also assisted Deputy Counselor Mark Rubin with vetting Virginia Supreme Court candidates.  He left the administration to join McGuireWoods Consulting as Assistant Vice President for State Government Relations.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  legislation (including bill review); Executive Orders related to Commonwealth Preparedness/Public Safety; Fort Monroe; constituent correspondence; decision briefs; policy office staff assignments; policy background memorandums primarily for Public Safety/Commonwealth Preparedness events attended by Governor Kaine; indigent defense (SB1168/HB2361 - 2007 session); Commission on Sexual Violence; 5th anniversary of 9/11 memorial event; Military Survivors and Dependents Education Program (MSDEP); military and veterans issues; Hurricane Evacuation and Sheltering Task Force; 2006 transportation town hall meetings; Air Force Cyber Command (AFCYBER); Base Realignment and Closure Commission (BRAC); Governor's Campus Security Conference (13 August 2007); emergency communication systems (interoperability); Gabriel Prosser "pardon" (letter to Linda Thomas, President, Virginia State Conference NAACP; Department of Corrections hair grooming policy; Virginia Crime Commission's Illegal Immigration Taskforce/immigration issues; fire programs funding/state fire marshall legislation; and Drive to Work program. 
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Sindy Benavides, Bennett Blodgett, Al Bowers, Gena Boyle, Gregory L. Brittingham, Curtis Brown, Erin Bryant, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Steven Combs, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Marla Decker, Suzette Denslow, Betsy Wells Edwards, Chris Essid, Marc Follmer, Hayes Framme, Iva Frizzle, Steven Gould, Kevin Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Marilyn Harris, Martha Hazelgrove, Maurice A. Henderson, II, Wendy Hoffman, Tim Kaine, Robert Kemmler, Anne Leigh Kerr, Jeff Kraus, William H. Leighty, Thomas A. Lisk, Alfonso Lopez, John Marshall, Constance McGeorge, Jennie Moline, Steven M. Mondul, William Murray, Steve Owens, Sarah Plumb, Maribel Ramos, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Aimee Perron Seibert, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Dawn Smith, Jeff Tiller, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Jacklyn Varela, and Aaron Ver. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Gena Boyle Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2586 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dO5GIP">GBOYLE.pst</extref>. There are 2 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client privileged information. Gena Boyle served as Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy in the Kaine administration from January 2006 to December 2009.  Boyle provided policy advice in the areas of Health and Human Resources, Natural Resources and Agriculture and Forestry.  
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  agriculture issues, autism; bill signings; Chesapeake Bay issues; cigarette tax; Commission on Sexual Violence; energy issues (including ethanol waiver and off-shore drilling); database breach notification (consumer data privacy); executive orders/executive directives; federal health care reform proposals; firearms in state parks; For Keeps initiative (foster care); Governor's Commission on Climate Change; Governor's Health Reform Commission; health and human resources issues; health care; legislation; natural resources issues; payday lending; Physical Evidence Recovery Kit (PERK); Puppy Mills; regulations (HHR and NR); Renew Virginia Initiatives (energy). ; Scapie eradication; smoking ban in restaurants; SGA Climate Change Initiative; State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP); and Virginia Commission on Immigration/immigration issues.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Preston Bryant, Secretary of Natural Resources and former member of the Virginia House of Delegates, to Gena Boyle, 25 July 2007, providing his analysis/profile of members of the General Assembly and their views on natural resource issues.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Sindy Benavides, Bennett Blodgett, Robert Bloxom, Erin Bryant, Preston Bryant, Kristin Burhop, Alicia Cavanaugh, Jeff Corbin, Suzette Denslow, Carol Denson, Bill Dickinson, Heidi Dix, David Dowling, Patrick Finnerty, Carl E. Garrison, Kristine Hall, Todd Haymore, Anne Holton, Lynette Isbell, Gail Jaspen, Anne Leigh Kerr, Aryan Khalid, Heidi Lawyer, Alfonso Lopez, Kim McGaughey, Joseph Maroon, Bill Norris, Bonnie Price, Ray Ratke, Nikki Rovener, Mark Rubin, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Margaret Schultze, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Kim Snead, Marilyn Tavenner, Wayne Turnage, and Stephen Walz.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. Jennie Moline Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2008)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent:  5694 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 5694 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e5Vlw4"><emph render="bold">JMOLINE.pst and JMOLINE2.pst</emph></extref>. Jennie Moline served as a Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy from January 2006 to 10 December 2008. Moline was the liaison between the Governor's Office, Secretary of Education's office, Secretary of Administration's office, and Workforce office.  In education, she focused on pre-k, Special Education regulations and Standards of Accreditation, Career and Technical Education initiatives, Southern Regional Education Board (SHREB), National Governors Association (NGA) and higher education restructuring.  In administration, Moline focused on elections and SWAM (The Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business) initiatives.  In workforce, she attended workforce subcabinet meetings, Virginia Workforce Council issues, the transition to the vCSS and the one-stops.  Moline left the administration in December 2008 to work Terry McAuliffe's unsuccessful 2009 gubernatorial campaign.  She returned to the administration as a part-time employee working with scheduling/communications from 8 September 2009 to January 2010.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">JMOLINE.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The JMOLINE.pst file contains 5524 emails sent and received by Jennie Moline between January 2006 and December 2008.  There are 37 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 2.2-3800. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel information. 
	</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: background and talking points for governor (primarily education events); constituent correspondence; education (Early Childhood, Pre-K, Department of Education legislative proposals, funding, regulations, Start Strong, Smart Beginnings, special education, Standards of Accreditation); Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives; elections (legislation); Healthy Virginians; Interfaith Service of Remembrance and Hope (20 April 2007, Richmond); legislation (including bill review); National Governors Association (NGA) Education , Early Childhood, Workforce Committee (ECW); Pell grants; Queen Elizabeth's visit to Virginia (2007); Southern Regional Education Board (SREB); State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV); Virginia Community College System (VCCS); and workforce development.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  emails from Kathy Glazer, Executive Director, Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives, to various administration officials, dated 22 September 2006 and 2 October 2006, containing Glazer's notes from education meetings across the commonwealth.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  James Alcorn, Jean Bankos, Peter Blake, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Kim Busch, Billy Cannaday, Angela Cioffi, Suzette Denslow, Kent Dickey, Marc Emblidge, Laura Fornash, Doug Garcia, Cathy Ghidotti, Kathy Glazer, Judith E. Heiman, Joe Hilbert, Amanda Howe, Gary Janak, Robley Jones, Tim Kaine, Sheree Kaplan, Anna Kimsey, Rob Krupicka, Danny LeBlanc, Stephanie Maltz, Juanita McHale, Tom Morris, William Murray, Kristen Nelson, Shaylah Nunn, Kelly Powell, Charles Pyle, Maribel Ramos, Gail Robinson, Nancy Rodrigues, Megan Root, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Richard Sliwoski, Delacey Skinner, Sandra Treadway, Wayne Turnage, Ed Turner, Linda Wallinger, Emily Ward, Anne Wescott, Patricia Wright, and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">JMOLINE2.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The JMOLINE2.pst file contains 169 emails sent and received by Jennie Moline between September 2009 and January 2010.  There is one privacy protected and confidential email in this pst file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 2.2-3800. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel information. 
	</p>




<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: event logistics (including talking points).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Alleyn Harned, Amanda Howe, Michael Kelly, Megan Root, Brian Shepard, Lynda Tran, and Patricia Wright.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries F. Maribel Ramos Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 394 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dhK5bP"><emph render="bold">Inbox.pst</emph></extref>. Maribel Ramos served as Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy in the Kaine administration from January 2006 to March 2007.  Ramos provided policy advice in the areas of administration and natural resources.  Ramos left the administration in March 2007 to work for Virginia Senator Jim Webb.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  legislation (bill review with focus on Administration and Natural Resources).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Viola Baskerville, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Tim Kaine, Bill Leighty, Bill Murray, Missy Neff, Nikki Rovner, Brian Shepard, Richard Sliwoski, Karen Smith, and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries G. Megan Root Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 2293 emails in one pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2d6iDju"><emph render="bold">KaineLibMRoot.pst</emph></extref>. There are 58 attorney-client privileged emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 2.2-3705.1-8.  Megan Root served as Executive Assistant to the Senior Advisor for Workforce from  August 2006 to January 2008.  Root served as Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy from January 2008 to January 2010.  Root provided policy advice in the areas of education, workforce development, and regulations.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  archiving; energy; legislation (bill review, talking points, Budget Action Reports, tracking, Attorney General's Office review of legislation); education (Governor's College and Career Readiness Summit; Race to the Top, Virginia Privacy Act, Southern Regional Education Board (SREB), special education regulations); and workforce development (Governor's Workforce Development Strategic Plan, Workforce Investment Board, Virginia Workforce Council, establishment of Comprehensive One Stop Centers).
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sarah Abubaker, Jean Bankos, Chris Bast, Peter Blake, Angela Bowser, Gena Boyle, Brian Davis, Paula Dehetre, Kent Dickey, Douglas Garcia, Katya Herndon, Gordon Hickey, Margaret Hughson, Gary Janak, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Kathy Glazer, Daniel LeBlanc, Deborrah Mahone, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Kirsten Nelson, Bill Norris, Shaylah Nunn, Charles Pyle, Barbara Reese, Gail Robinson, Mark Rubin, Jacqueline Scott, Brian Shepard, Dan Timberlake, Stephen Walz, Anne Wescott, and Patricia Wright.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Policy Office Electronic Files, Subseries H. Barbara Reese Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent:  5694 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 5694 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dxYzpF"><emph render="bold">BREESE.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">GOVPOLibV2.pst</emph></extref>.  Barbara Reese served as Deputy Policy Director from January 2009 to January 2010.  Reese lead the implementation of Virginia's $5 billion share of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act including program and project design, implementation, reporting, and auditing.  She also directed Virginia's $2 billion High Speed Rail Program and federal application process.  Reese served as Legislative Director following the departure of Suzette Denslow in January 2009.  She also served as Deputy Secretary of Transportation from July 2007 to January 2009
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">BREESE.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The BREESE.pst file contains 1485 emails sent and received by Barbara Reese between January 2009 and January 2010.  There are 5 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications. 
	</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus - projects, guidelines, web site development, implementation); fiscal 2010-2012 budget development; draft/outline of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2009, December 2009); Enterprise Zones; High Speed Rail; Recovery Zone Economic Development Bonds; REAL ID; Dulles Toll Road; Virginia Port Authority; Energy Performance PPEA; unemployment insurance/Virginia Employment Commission (VEC); and legislation.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Reese to Brian Shepard transmitting draft of 2009 Reconvened Session Vetoes and Amendments Talking Points, dated 6 April 2009.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Gena Boyle, Craig Burns, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Bill Shelton, Richard Sliwoski, D.B. Smit, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Stephen Walz, Eva Whitley, and Patricia Wright. 
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">GOVPOLLibV2.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The GOVPOLLibV2.pst file contains 4209 emails sent and received by Barbara Reese between January 2009 and January 2010.  There are 29 privacy protected and confidential email in this pst file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 2.2-3800. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing attorney-client communications and personal/personnel information. 
	</p>




<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus - projects, guidelines, web site development, implementation); legislation (bill review, amendments, notes from conversations with members of the General Assembly about legislation, talking points, bill signing requests, administration position on select bills, and 2010 legislative proposals); Recovery Zone Economic Development Bonds; Qualified School Construction Bonds (QSCB); 2008-2010 budget cuts/amendments; Virginia's response to the Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U.S. 205 (2009), United States Supreme Court decision that ruled that it was a violation of the Sixth Amendment right of confrontation for a prosecutor to submit lab testing results without the testimony of the person who performed the test; 2010-2012 budget development; energy; unemployment insurance;  95/395 HOT lanes; Dulles Toll Road; TIGER Discretionary Grant program; Virginia Port Authority/APM Terminals; REAL ID; and rest area closures.
</p>




<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email exchange between Tim Kaine and Wayne Turnage on the administration's proposed process to manage stimulus money, 5 February 2009 (forwarded to Barbara Reese by Turnage); and email to senior administration officials from Wayne Turnage outlining work groups and procedures for economic stimulus package, 5, 2-3 February 2009.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Jeffrey Allen, Amber Amato, Kristen Amundson, Arthur Anderson, II, Janet Aylor, Charles Badger, Chris Bast, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Young Ho Chang, Marc Cheatham, Ed Crooks, Don Darr, Kent Dickey, Nick Donohue, Manju Ganeriwala, Melinda Glazer, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Sherrie Harrington, Marilyn Harris, Mark Haskins, Gordon Hickey, Pierce Homer, Karen Jackson, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Malcolm Kerley, Wes Kleene, John Lawson, Aflonzo Lopez, Michael Maul, Jo Anne Maxwell, Declan McManus, Kevin Page, Kate Paris, David Paylor, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Bill Shelton, Brian Shepard, D.B. Smit, Dan Timberlake, Lynda Tran, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Stephen Walz, Evie Whitley, and Patricia Wright.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 22062 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Communications Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Communication Office of the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 22064 emails in twelve (12) subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Lynda Tran Email; B. Jeff Kraus Email; C. Gordon Hickey Email; D. Maurice A. Henderson II Email; E. Jeff Tiller Email; F. Robin Winchell Email; G. Michael Kelly Email; H. Lauren Cunningham Email; I. Doug Scott Email; J. Laura DeLibero Email; K. Amanda Howe Email; and L. Michaele White Email.  There are 127 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records, and records containing personal/personnel information. The pst files for Delacey Skinner, Communications Director from January 2006 to December 2008, and Kevin Hall, Press Secretary from January 2006 to November 2007, were empty.  However, email messages sent by Skinner and Hall may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine Administration (Executive Office, Policy Office, Communications Office, etc.).
</p>

<p>The Communications Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. The Communications Office promotes the Governor's initiatives and priorities outside of government, as well as monitoring coverage of the Governor from outside, independent news sources.  During Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2002-2010), the Communications Director strategically explained the Administration's priorities to the public in a variety of media.  Any statement written or otherwise attributed to the Governor had to be cleared with Communications.  The Communications Director was assisted in her responsibilities by a Press Secretary, additional press staff, a web master, and a photographer.  In addition, the Communications Director oversaw the work of the Constituent Services Director whose staff members promptly responded to inquiries of the pubic received via mail, phone and email.  The Communications Director was also a member of the Governor's Leadership Team.  Delacey Skinner (January 2006-December 2008) and Lynda Tran (January 2009-January 2010) held this position during the Kaine administration (2006-2010).
</p>

<p>The Communications Director was assisted in her responsibilities by a Press Secretary (Kevin Hall, January 2006-October 2007, and Gordon Hickey, October 2007-January 2010). Jeff Kraus served as Senior Advisor to the Governor and Speech writer from January 2006 to January 2007.
</p>

</scopecontent>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries A. Lynda Tran Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 6844 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNKBiy"><emph render="bold">KaineLibLTran.pst</emph></extref>. Lynda Tran served as Communications Director from January 2009 to January 2010.  There are 86 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records and records containing personal/personnel information. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Chesapeake Bay; gubernatorial transition (Kaine to McDonnell); drafts/edits of press releases; review of Kaine quotes; responses to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests for Governor Kaine's complete daily schedule (2009); responses to press inquiries; arrangements for President Barack Obama to call in to Governor Kaine's final Ask the Governor program on WTOP radio on 22 December 2009; drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2009 and 2010); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2009, December 2009); clemency (Jens Soering, Larry Bill Elliott, John Allen Muhammad, Norfolk Four, Edward Bell-all restricted); preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-including development of Virginia stimulus website); Kaine administration accomplishments document; drafts of op-ed articles by Kaine (payday lending, end-of-term, Chesapeake Bay);  event briefings/talking points; unemployment insurance; resignation of Tareq Salahi (White House party crasher) from Virginia Tourism Corporation board (2009); tax amnesty program (2009); smoking ban in restaurants; Dept. of Health Professions Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; H1N1 strain of influenza;  Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative (includes Biscuit Run property in Albemarle County); Asian oysters in the Chesapeake Bay; controversy over Department of State Police 2009 Virginia Terrorism Threat Assessment:  Universities Possible Terror Portals;  Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) (management issues); broadband program; rest area closures; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
: email correspondence between Tran and Anita Kumar of the Washington Post, dated 9 December 2009, on resignation of Tareq Salahi from Virginia Tourism Authority (contains Salahi resignation letter); and email to Governor Kaine from Lynda Tran, dated 29 January 2009, containing her proposed communications plan.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Viola Baskerville, Chris Bast, Bennett Blodgett, Gena Boyle, Ric Brown, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Aneesh Chopra, Jeff Corbin, Beau Cribbs, Bob Crouch, Lauren Cunningham, Don Darr, Nick Donohue, Shane Emmett, Eric Finkbeiner, Marc Follmer, Greg Garner, Cathy Ghidotti, Phil Giaramita, Patrick Gottschalk, Mark Halperin, Lynette Hammond, Stephen Harms, Alleyn Harned, Sherrie Harrington, Marilyn Harris, Todd Haymore, Roz Helderman, Bernard Henderson, Fred Hiatt, Gordon Hickey, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Amanda Howe, Karen Jackson, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Martin Kent, Aryana Khalid, Anita Kumar, Bob Lewis, Travis Loop, Alphoso Lopez, J. Tucker Martin, John Marshall, Marianne McGhee, Megan McGuire, Christie Miller, James Nolan, Kate Paris, Len Pomata, Dena Potter, Barbara Reese, Karen Remley, Larry Roberts, Megan Root, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, and Julian Walker.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries B. Jeff Kraus Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 2705 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dVycgy"><emph render="bold">Jkraus.pst</emph></extref>. Jeff Kraus served as Senior Advisor to the Governor and Speech writer from January 2006 to January 2007.  Kraus served as Deputy Communications Director during Tim Kaine's 2005 gubernatorial campaign and Lt. Governor Kaine's Communications Director (2003-2005).  He left the administration in January 2007 for a position with the Virginia Community College System.  Kraus wrote speeches, op-ed pieces, talking points, and letters to government officials for Governor Kaine.  Kraus also wrote several speeches for First Lady Ann Holton.  He served as Kaine's liaison for special projects including Jamestown 2007 commemoration.  
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: Freedman's Bank historical marker in Richmond; drafts of speeches, remarks, talking points, etc. for Governor Kaine (includes background information); drafts of speeches and remarks for First Lady Anne Holton (including background information); draft of piece by Kaine describing his 12-17 March 2006 trip to visit Virginia troops in Iraq, Kuwait and Afghanistan; Jamestown 2007 planning (including issues related to Tareq Salahi); 2006 transportation plan (speeches, talking points and Town Hall meetings); drafts of Kaine's State of the Commonwealth Address (2007); drafts of Kaine's speeches to the Joint Money Committees of the General Assembly (August 2006 and December 2006); and drafts of Kaine's biography for web site.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, James Carr, Marc Cheatham, Aneesh Chopra, Kevin Crossett, B. Hayes Framme, Manju Ganeriwala, Cathy Ghidotti, Steven Gould, Kevin Hall, Sherrie Harrington, Carrie Henderson, Maurcie Henderson, II, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Bill Leighty, Emily Lockhart, John Marshall, Jane Minerly, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Missy Neff, Maribel Ramos, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Tareq Salahi, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Brian Shepard, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>


</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries C. Gordon Hickey Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 6250 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dNMhbH"><emph render="bold">KaineLibGHickey.pst</emph></extref>. Hickey served as Press Secretary to Governor Kaine from October 2007 to January 2010.  Hickey had previously worked as a reporter for the <title render="italic">Richmond Times Dispatch</title>.  As Press Secretary, Hickey answered all media inquiries concerning the Kaine's administration on issues.  He provided background information to reporters, approved quotes from the Governor, and wrote, edited, and approved press releases.  Hickey, as member of the Governor's Leadership Team, advised the Governor on media issues. There are 30 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records and records containing personal/personnel information. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: transportation (abusive driver fees, rest stops, legislation); background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points (includes press releases never issued); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (federal stimulus-criteria for projects and creation of web site); legislation; budget issues/press inquiries; media queries on clemency, restoration of rights, and blanket restoration of rights; Dominion Power's Wise County project; Dulles Toll Road; H1N1 strain of influenza; media requests for comments for news stories; requests by administration for corrections in news stories;  preparations for the 20 January 2009 presidential inauguration, costs for Virginia and localities and reimbursement by the federal government for those expenses; Kaine's 400,000 acre land conservation initiative; and approval of Kaine quotes for press releases.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email thread on the Wise County power plant/mountaintop mining, dated 21 February 2008, started by Governor Kaine on 18 February 2008; email from Gordon Hickey, dated 22 April 2009, to Wayne Turnage, containing a spread sheet attachment listing all "projects lost" by the Virginia Economic Development Partnership from January 2005 to 15 April 2009.  The spread sheet lists:  name of project/company, lost date, approved amount, state won, primary reason lost, and real reason lost; email from Gordon Hickey, dated 13 May 2009, to Wayne Turnage, containing a spread sheet attachment listing Virginia Announcements of Employment Creation and Capital Investment from 1 January 1998 to 22 April 2009; Governor's Office procedures for the execution of Edward Nathan Bell, 19 February 2009 (restricted); and email from Gordon Hickey, dated 23 April 2009, to Jeff Tiller forwarding an email exchange between Tim Kaine and Tim Dunn, re: Amendment 596.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Viola Baskerville, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Craig Burns, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Jeff Corbin, Lauren Cunningham, Nick Donohue, Gary Emerling, Manju Ganeriwala, Greg Garner, Kathy Glazer, Frank Green, Todd Haymore, Roz Helderman, Bernard Henderson, Pierce Homer, Drew Houff, Tim Kaine, Michael Kelly, Anita Kumar, Bob Lewis, Alfonso Lopez, J. Tucker Martin, Seth McLaughlin, Olympia Meola, Christie Miller, Jim Nolan, Dena Potter, Charles Pyle, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Nikki Rovner, Mark Rubin, Jeff Schapiro, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, J. Garren Shipley, Delacey Skinner, Bob Spieldenner, Tamra Talmadge-Anderson, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Lynda Tran, Larry Traylor, Wayne Turnage, Jody Wagner, Julian Walker, Stephen Walz, Suzanne West, Tyler Whitley, and Michael Paul Williams.
</p>

</scopecontent>


</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries D. Maurice A. Henderson, II Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 572 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dxZu9I"><emph render="bold">Inbox.pst</emph></extref>. Henderson served as Deputy Press Secretary to Governor Kaine from March 2006 to June 2007. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: First Lady press releases; photographs of First Lady at public events; First Lady event briefings; talking points and background information for Governor's events; and photographs of Governor Kaine (as attachments) taken by Michaele White, Governor's Photographer.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Bill Leighty, dated 23 August 2006, to Jeff Kraus, listing the Kaine Administration's accomplishments (in email to Henderson sent 16 November 2006).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Kevin Hall, Asha Holloman, Bill Leighty, Delacey Skinner, Michaele White, and Robin Winchell.
</p>

</scopecontent>


</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries E. Jeff Tiller Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 425 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dvzPCa"><emph render="bold">2007Libjtiller.pst</emph></extref>. Jeff Tiller served as Press Aide (January-December 2006), Assistant Press Secretary from (January 2007 to July 2007), and Deputy Press Secretary (August 2007 to July 2008). </p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points; approval of Kaine quotes for press releases; logistics for Cabinet Community Days; and 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech (creation of panel and release of Virginia Tech Review Panel report).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Kevin Hall, Gordon Hickey, Tim Kaine, Jim Kudla, and Delacey Skinner.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries F. Robin Winchell Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1313 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dHTDAj"><emph render="bold">inbox.pst</emph></extref>. Robin Winchell served as Senior Press Aide in the Kaine Administration from January 2006 to May 2006.  She previously worked as a Communications Assistant to the 2005 Kaine for Governor campaign.  Winchell left the administration in May 2006 to take a position as Communications Director for Congressman Charlie Melancon (LA-03).  Winchell wrote and distributed press releases, talking points, and op-eds.  She also directed communications for First Lady Anne Holton.  
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: communications for First Lady Anne Holton including writing press releases, news releases, event briefing forms, and coordinating public appearances and interviews; news clips compiled for Tim Kaine's gubernatorial campaign (2005); photographs (as attachments from Michaele White) of Governor Kaine events; Winchell's weekly reports from January to May 2006; and drafts of press releases and talking points.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Sindy Benavides, Katie Boyer, Kimberly Busch, Kevin Hall, Maurice A. Henderson, II, Asha Holloman, Anne Holton, Tim Kaine, Jeff Kraus, Bill Leighty, Rick Siger, Delacey Skinner, Martha Steger, Jeff Tiller, and Michaele White.
</p>

</scopecontent>


</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries G. Michael Kelly Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent:  3074 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 3074 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dy0prh"><emph render="bold">MKELLY.PST</emph> and <emph render="bold">KaineLibMKelly.pst</emph></extref>. Michael Kelly served as a Press Aide (September 2007 to May 2009) and Assistant Press Secretary (May 2009-January 2010) in the Kaine administration from September 2007 to January 2010.  Kelly compiled daily news clippings, assisted with press events, drafted press releases, coordinated with agencies and organizations on media-related requests, lead advance work for key events statewide including Cabinet Community Days, and acted as on-the-record spokesperson for Governor Kaine as appropriate.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MKELLY.PST</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The MKELLY.PST file contains 1188 emails sent and received by Michael Kelly between September 2007 and January 2010.  There are 9 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency discussions and records containing personal/personnel information. 
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points (includes press releases never issued); American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009; legislation; budget issues/press inquiries; media queries on clemency; compiling news clippings, Cabinet Day events; briefing material for Governor's events; drafting Kaine quotes for press releases; notes from news conferences held by Governor Kaine, General Assembly Republicans, etc.; and notes from press "gaggles" held by Governor Kaine.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Chris Bast, Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, Marc Cheatham, Lauren Cunningham, Nick Donohue, Cathy Ghidotti, Alleyn Harned, Carrie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Amanda Howe, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Kate Paris, Barbara Reese, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Lynda Tran, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibMKelly.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KaineLibMKelly.pst file contains 1886 emails sent and received by Michael Kelly between September 2007 and January 2010.  There are 2 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: public safety. 
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: background information for and drafts of press releases and talking points; event briefing forms prepared for Scheduling Office (includes event, date/time, attire, location, contact information, staff assigned to Governor, Governor's role in event, talking points, and additional information; many appear to be drafts); Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach; cabinet day(s); notes from news conferences held by Governor Kaine, General Assembly Republicans, etc.; scripts for Governor Kaine's Public Service Announcements (PSA); and media/external inquiries and requests.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email thread between Marilyn Tavenner, Secretary of Health and Human Resources, and Sandra Ryals, Director, Department of Health Professionals, dated 7 August 2009, responding to New York Times inquiry about Prescription Monitoring Program (PMP) data breach.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, Hollie Cammarasana, Lauren Cunningham, Phillip Giaramita, Alleyn Harned, Carla Harris, Carrie Henderson, Gordon Hickey, Tim Kaine, Christie Miller, Charles Pyle, Mike Salster, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Jeff Tiller, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Stephen Walz, and Suzanne West.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries H. Lauren Cunningham Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent: 110 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 110 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cXH7sb"><emph render="bold">KaineLiblcunningham.pst and LCUNNINGHAM.PST</emph></extref>. Lauren Cunningham served as a Special Assistant in Constituent Services (January 2006 to August 2007),  Press Aide (September 2007 to July 2008) and Assistant Press Secretary (July 2008 to January 2010) in the Kaine administration.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLiblcunningham.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KaineLiblcunningham.pst file contains 42 emails sent and received by Lauren Cunningham between May 2006 and January 2010.  
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: cabinet day(s) including suggestions from cabinet and agency heads as to where to visit; compiling news clippings; constituent correspondence; drafts of press releases; and media/external inquiries and requests.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Robert Bloxom, Preston Bryant, Michael Kelly, and Lynda Tran.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LCUNNINGHAM.PST</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The LCUNNINGHAM.PST  file contains 68 emails sent and received by Lauren Cunningham between October 2007 and January 2010.  
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: drafts of press releases; talking points; op-ed by Secretary of Public Safety John Marshall on immigration enforcement in Virginia, October 2007; op-ed by Governor Tim Kaine on budget cuts, 15 October 2008; and op-ed Governor Tim Kaine on alternative to payday lending, December 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Suzanne West.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries I. Doug Scott Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 240 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dPgNkK"><emph render="bold">KaineLibdscott.pst</emph></extref>. Doug Scott served as Press Intern (September 2008 to May 2009), Press Fellow (June 2009 to August 2009) and Press Aide (August 2009 to January 2010) in the Kaine administration.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: drafts of press releases; scripts for Governor Kaine's Public Service Announcements (PSA); and media/external inquiries and requests.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Lauren Cunningham, Gordon Hickey, Michael Kelly, and Lynda Tran.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries J. Laura DeLibero Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 43 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dww6Se"><emph render="bold">LDILIBERO.PST</emph></extref>. Laura DeLibero served as Press Intern from January to April 2009 in the Kaine Administration.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: event briefing forms; notes from news conferences held by members of the General Assembly; and Kaine administration accomplishments document.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Kim Busch, Lauren Cunningham, Michael Kelly and Lynda Tran.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries K. Amanda Howe Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 441 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cVJ78R"><emph render="bold">AHOWE2.PST</emph></extref>. Amanda Howe was hired by the Kaine administration in August 2009 as a communications advisor to highlight the accomplishments of the Kaine administration.  She developed and coordinated a strategic calendar of themes and events to highlight during the final four months of Kaine's administration.  Howe previously worked in the Kaine administration as executive director of Virginia's Royal Welcome, which coordinated Queen Elizabeth II's visit in May 2007.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
: event briefing forms (economic development announcements, smoking ban in restaurants, land conservation, workforce development, etc.); Howe's weekly reports; development of communication plan to highlight Kaine administration's accomplishments including:  themes (best state for business, best managed state, best state for kids, and improving quality of life) and drafts and updates to communication plan; and talking points. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Gena Boyle, Preston Bryant, Kim Busch, Jeff Corbin, Laura Cunningham, Cathy Ghidotti, Alleyn Harned, Gordon Hickey, Michael Kelly, Jennie Moline, Barbara Reese, Nikki Rovner, Doug Scott, Brian Shepard, Marilyn Tavenner, Lynda Tran, Wayne Turnage, and Michaele White.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Communications Office Electronic Files, Subseries L. Michaele White Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent: 45 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 45 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dwuHes"><emph render="bold">KaineLibMWhite.pst and MWHITE.PST</emph></extref>. Michaele White served as the Governor's Photographer for Governor Tim Kaine from January 2006 to January 2010.  White was retained by the McDonnell Administration (2010-2014).  
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibMWhite.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KaineLibMWhite.pst file contains 40 emails sent and received by Michaele White between September 2006 to December 2009.  Her emails primarily contain jpeg attachments of photographs of Governor Kaine taken by someone other than White.
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   James Greene, Kevin Hall, Amanda Howe, and Christie Miller.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">MWHITE.PST</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The MWHITE.PST  file contains 5 emails sent and received by Michaele White in January 2010.  
</p>


</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

</c01>



<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 8520 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 8520 emails in sixteen (16) subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Kate Hanley Email; B. Bernard Henderson Email; C. JoAnn Pulliam Email; D. Lynn Clayton Email; E. Jonathan Young Email; F. Alicia Roberts Email; G. Paul Brockwell Email; H. Matt Gross Email; I. Betsy Anderson Email; J. Chris Marshburn Email; K. Greg Hennig  Email; L. Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton Email; M. Sindy Benavides Email; N. Kimberly Bowers Email; O. Nick Surace Email; and P. Dawn Farrar.  There are 3819 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: clemency records, and records containing personal/personnel information. 
</p>

<p>The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and "publishing" (on-line only) the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
</p>

<p>On 29 December 2005, Governor-elect Tim Kaine appointed Daniel LeBlanc, President of the Virginia AFL-CIO, as Secretary of the Commonwealth.  LeBlanc's nomination was rejected by the Republican-controlled House of Delegates on 7 March 2006.  LeBlanc became the first cabinet member to fail to receive General Assembly approval.  Kaine later named LeBlanc Senior Advisor for Workforce Development.  Bernard Henderson, Senior Deputy Secretary of the Commonwealth, served as acting Secretary from 7 March 2006 to 20 March 2006.  Governor Kaine appointed former Fairfax County board chairman Katherine K. Henley as Secretary on 20 March 2006.  Hanley served on the Fairfax County School Board from 1984 to 1986 and the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors from 1986 to 2004.
</p>

</scopecontent>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries A. Kate Hanley Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 53 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dPhKtg"><emph render="bold">KHANLEY.PST</emph></extref>. Kate Hanley served as Secretary of the Commonwealth from 20 March 2006 to January 2010.  There are 10 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  eNotary; restoration of rights inquiries; constituent correspondence; and board resignations.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email exchange between Hanley and Bill Leighty, dated 3 March 2008, discussing Tareq Salahi, a member of the Virginia Tourism Authority.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Paul Brockwell, Bernard Henderson, Bill Leighty, and Len Pomata.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries B. Bernard Henderson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 313 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e72b4s"><emph render="bold">BHENDERSON.PST</emph></extref>. Bernard Henderson served as Senior Deputy Secretary of the Commonwealth from January 2002 to January 2010.  There are 120 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights and clemency.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  clemency; restoration of rights inquiries; eNotary; and VITA and Lockhead-Martin issues with consolidated IT in Virginia state government.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Betsy Anderson, John "Chip" Dicks, Lynn DuBard, Donnovan Dunkley, Peggy Feldmann, Kate Hanley, Greg Hennig, Judy Napier, Pam Patrick, Eric Perkins, Ajay Rohatgi, John Tackley, and Pia Trigiani.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries C. JoAnn Pulliam Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 189 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2cVKCnv"><emph render="bold">jpulliam.pst</emph></extref>. JoAnn Pulliam served as Executive Assistant to the Secretary of the Commonwealth from January 2006 to January 2007.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  board vacancy updates; revisions of the Notary statute; weekly reports; and confirmation of Kate Hanley as Secretary of the Commonwealth in March 2006.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries D. Lynn Clayton Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent: 620 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 620 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dyWTwu"><emph render="bold">KaineLibLClayton.pst and LCLAYTON.PST</emph></extref>. Lynn Clayton served as Restoration of Rights Specialist from 2005 to 3 January 2007 and Executive Assistant to the Secretary of the Commonwealth from 4 January 2007 to January 2010. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibLClayton.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KaineLibLClayton.pst contains 378 emails sent/received by Lynn Clayton between June 2005 and January 2008.  There are 365 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights and clemency.
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  restoration of rights (queries, status of application, procedures, clemency report requests from law enforcement, etc.).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Bernard Henderson and Patty Tucker.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">LCLAYTON.PST</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The LCLAYTON.PST contains 242 emails sent/received by Lynn Clayton between February 2006 and January 2010.  There are 189 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights and clemency.  </p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  restoration of rights (queries, status of application, procedures, clemency report requests from law enforcement, etc.).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Bernard Henderson, Patty Tucker, and Micah Womack.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>
</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries E. Jonathan Young Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 261 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dQbnLn"><emph render="bold">JYOUNG.PST </emph></extref>. Jonathan Young served as the Conflicts of Interest Specialist and Special Assistant for Gubernatorial Appointments in the Kaine Administration from January 2006 to 16 November 2007 when left to take job at Virginia State University.  Young also worked in Secretary of the Commonwealths Office during the administrations of Governor James Gilmore and Mark Warner (2000-2006).  
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  board vacancy updates and Virginia Tech Review Panel.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Kevin Hall, Bernard Henderson, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries F. Alicia Roberts Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 11 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e72n3w"><emph render="bold">AROBERTS.PST</emph></extref>. Alicia Roberts served as Special Assistant to the Secretary of the Commonwealth (January-November 2007) and Conflict of Interest Director (November 2007-January 2008). The emails in this subseries date between January and November 2007.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries G. Paul Brockwell Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1476 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dyYgeL"><emph render="bold">pbrockwell.pst</emph></extref>. Paul Brockwell served as Conflict of Interest Director from January 2008 to 14 May 2009. Brockwell left the administration to attended graduate school. Brockwell previously worked as a Governor's Fellow (summer 2007), Special Projects Assistant in the office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry from August 2007 to January 2008. This subseries contains email sent and received by Brockwell between June 2007 and March 2009.  There are 2 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client privilege.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  vacancy updates (resignations from boards, commissions, etc.); agriculture and forestry legislation (2008 session:  data breach notification and credit report freeze); 2007 Continuity of Operations and Continuation of Government plans for the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry (and agencies) (RESTRICTED); consumer privacy project, Executive Directive 5 (2007) includes members, meeting agendas and notes and final report; Farm to School Task Force - At the Request of the General Assembly in Senate Joint Resolution 347 (2007), the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry and the Secretary of Education jointly convened a task force to study Farm-to-School concepts and develop a plan for implementation in the Commonwealth of Virginia.  Records include: final report, draft report, comments on draft report, agendas, and meeting notes.; and archiving records for Library of Virginia.

</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Gena Boyle, dated 20 February 2008, to Andres Alvarez, Brian Shepard and Mark Rubin (Paul Brockwell copied), summarizing a meeting with Anne Leigh Kerr and Chris Whyte about the data breach notification bill; email from Paul Brockwell, dated 28 November 2007, containing (as an attachment) The Executive Directive Report, Improving Consumer Privacy in the Commonwealth, November 2007 (final); and email from Paul Brockwell, dated 19 October 2007, to Andes Alvarez and Erin Williams, containing  (as attachments) draft summary, draft recommendations, etc.. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Andres Alvarez, Robert Bloxom, Gena Boyle, Aneesh Chopra, Patrick Cushing, Stephen DeLuca, Bill Dickinson, Lynne Fellin, Gene Fishel, Steven Gould, Tegan Hagy, Kate Hanley, Todd Haymore, Bernard Henderson, Barbara Hulburt, David Irvin, Ronald Jenkins, Anne Leigh Kerr, Judy Napier, Kathryn Paxton, Mark Rubin, Aaron Ver, Peggy Ward, and Chris Whyte.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries H. Matt Gross Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>


<p>The subseries contains 3 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dyYZMU"><emph render="bold">MGROSS.PST </emph></extref>. Matt Gross served as Conflict of Interest Director from May 2009 to January 2010.  The emails in this series date between May and December 2009.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries I. Betsy Anderson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 46 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dPmmzF"><emph render="bold">BANDERSON.PST </emph></extref>. Betsy Anderson served as Director of Authentications/Notary Public Division in the Office of the Secretary of Commonwealth from October 2006 to January 2010. The date range of the email in this subseries is May 2008 and November 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  eNotary.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Donna Bohlin, Chip Dicks, Bernard Henderson, and Ajay Rohatgi.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries J. Chris Marshburn Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 44 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dOzxlj"><emph render="bold">KaineLibCMarshburn.pst </emph></extref>. Chris Marshburn served as a Governor's Fellow and Extradition and Clemency Specialist in the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth from 2007 to 2008.  There are 38 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to clemency.  The date range of the email in this subseries is July 2007 to April 2008.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  clemency requests (restricted).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Martha Hazelgrove and Patricia Tucker.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries K. Greg Hennig Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 3039 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e8FDwa"><emph render="bold">GHENNIG.PST</emph></extref>. Greg Hennig served as an Extradition and Clemency Specialist in the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth from April 2008 to January 2010.  There are 3012 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to clemency and restoration of rights.  The date range of the email in this subseries is April 2008 to January 2010.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Clemency and restoration of rights (all restricted).
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Janice Dow, Shane Emmett, Laura Hall, Martha Hazelgrove, Bernard Henderson, Belinda Holt, Sam Overstreet, Candice Reid, Donna Tate, Patty Tucker, Joan Wade, and Micah Womack.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries L. Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent: 52 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 52 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dLW2Zj"><emph render="bold">KADELFLIPPO.PST and KaineLibkdefilippo.pst</emph></extref>. Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton served as Assistant Secretary of the Commonwealth (Director of Gubernatorial Appointments) from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KADELFLIPPO.PST</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KADELFLIPPO.PST file contains 12 emails sent and received by Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton between July 2006 and January 2010.
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  gubernatorial transition (Kaine to McDonnell).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Janet Polarek.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibkdefilippo.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The KaineLibkdefilippo.pst contains 40 emails sent/received by Kathryn DeFilippo Paxton between January and October 2007.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  vacancy updates.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Jonathan Young.
</p>


</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries M. Sindy Benavides Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
        <physdesc><extent>Extent: 1956 emails</extent>
        </physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This subseries contains 1956 emails in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dLX7QK"><emph render="bold">Sindy In box.pst and Sindy Sent box.pst</emph></extref>. Sindy M. Benavides served as Deputy Director of Constituent Services (January 2006-September 2006), Director of Gubernatorial Appointments (September 2006-April 2009), and Latino Liaison (January 2006-April 2009).  Benavides left the administration in April 2009 to work at the Democratic National Committee as Director of Community Outreach. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Sindy In box.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
    
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The Sindy In box.pst contains 1055 emails sent/received by Sindy M. Benavides between January 2006 and April 2009.  There are 43 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights and clemency.  
	</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Governor's 2008 Latino Summit; Virginia Latino Advisory Board; immigration legislation; illegal immigration; Governor's Commission on Immigration; Governor Tim Kaine's 6 February 2008 meeting with El Salvador President Elias Antonio Saca; New Americans Initiative (NAI); Asian Advisory Board; Mario Bustillo; constituent services weekly report (2006); and constituent services.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Gena Boyle, Erin Bryant, Marc Cheatham, Angela Chiang, Heidi Dix, Doug Garica, Leni Gonzalez, Matt Gross, Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Bernie Henderson, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Jeff Kraus, Aaron Larrimore, Bill Leighty, Peter Loach, Alfonso Lopez, Vicki Mirandah, Hung Nguyen, Kate Paris, Sarah Plumb, Larry Roberts, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Nick Surace, Marilyn Tavenner, Gresilda A. Tilley-Lubbs, Jeff Tiller, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>


	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Sindy Sent box.pst</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
                
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The Sindy Sent box.pst contains 901 emails sent/received by Sindy M. Benevides between January 2006 and April 2009.  There are 40 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to restoration of rights and clemency.  An additional message pertaining to the aftermath of the Virginia Tech shooting will not be opened until final resolution of all litigation relating to the incident. Some of these records may be kept confidential for longer in order to comply with the terms of the settlement agreements the Commonwealth accepted.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Virginia Latino Advisory Board; Governor Tim Kaine's 6 February 2008 meeting with El Salvador President Elias Antonio Saca; Governor's Commission on Immigration; Mario Bustillo; immigration legislation; Hispanic College Fund; and New Americans Initiative (NAI).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Gena Boyle, Marc Cheatham, Douglas Garcia, Leni Gonzalez, Matt Gross, Kevin Hall, Kate Hanley, Bernie Henderson, Tim Kaine, Aryana Khalid, Jeff Kraus, Bill Leighty, Alfonso Lopez, Kate Paris, Maribel Ramos, Larry Roberts, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Nick Surace, Marilyn Tavenner, Walter Tejada, Jeff Tiller, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries N. Kimberly Bowers Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 47 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dYyUbJ"><emph render="bold">KBOWERS.PST </emph></extref>. Kimberly Bowers served as Director of Gubernatorial Appointments from March 2007 to April 2009.  The date range of the email in this subseries is March 2007 to April 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  appointments procedures and board assignments.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Kate Hanley, Bernie Henderson, Nick Surace, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries O. Nick Surace Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 28 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dXJ9uA"><emph render="bold">NSURACE.PST</emph></extref>. Nick Surace served as a Governor's Fellow (Summer 2007) and Director of Gubernatorial Appointments from August 2007 to January 2010. He assisted the Governor and Secretary of the Commonwealth in searching for well-qualified citizens to server on 120 boards and commissions in the areas of education, natural resources, finance and administration. Surace was also responsible for tracking General Assembly legislation that may affect the operations of the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth. The date range of the email in this subseries is January 2008 to March 2009.</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  General Assembly legislation related to the operations of the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Bernie Henderson, Gary Janak, Jennie Moline, Megan Root, and Brian Shepard.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries P. Dawn Farrar Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 382 email messages in one pst file: <emph render="bold">DFARRAR.PST</emph>. Farrar served as Deputy Secretary of the Commonwealth from January 2006 to June 2007.</p>

<p>DFARRAR.PST contains 382 emails sent and received by Dawn Farrar between January 2006 and March 2007.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  board profiles; legislation; and weekly reports.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Kathryn Defilippo, Kate Hanely, Bernard Henderson, Bill Leighty, Joanna Martin, Bill Murray, Svandis Pollard, Brian Shepard, Wayne Turnage, and Jonathan Young.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>




</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 15701 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Secretary of Technology Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 15701 emails in seven (7) subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Aneesh Chopra Email; B. Tristen Pegram Email; C. Len Pomata Email; D. John McDonald Email; E. Tim Bass Email, 2005-2006; F. Karen Jackson Email; and G. Brian Chiglinsky Email.  There are 320 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel information. 
</p>

<p>The Secretary of Technology and its agencies are responsible for the efficient and effective use of information technology to simplify government operations, advance technology applications to improve public services, and drive the innovation economy through the Commonwealth's leadership. The Secretary of Technology oversees two agencies: Virginia's Center for Innovative Technology (CIT) and the Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA).
</p>

<p>On 15 December 2005, Governor-elect Tim Kaine appointed Aneesh Chopra as Secretary of the Commonwealth.  Prior to joining Governor Kaine's cabinet, Chopra served as Managing Director with the Advisory Board Company, a publicly-traded health care think tank serving nearly 2,500 hospitals and health systems. He led the firm's Financial Leadership Council and the Working Council for Health Plan Executives, as well as assisted the launch of the firm's first business intelligence software solution, Compass.  Chopra left the administration in April 2009 when he was named the United States' first Chief Technology Officer by President Barack Obama.  In June 2009, Governor Kaine appoint Len Pomata Secretary of Technology; he served until the end of the administration.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries A. Aneesh Chopra Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 195 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dxw0cb"><emph render="bold">KaineLibachopra.pst</emph></extref>. Aneesh Chopra served as Secretary of Technology from 2006 to April 2009.  There are 10 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.  Additional Chopra email is contained in his assistant's, Tristen Pegram, email.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  telework, Office of Health IT, technology in education, and broadband stimulus.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email exchange between Chopra, Governor Kaine, and John Knapp of Verizon, dated 15 March 2009, regarding broadband stimulus.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Peter Blake, Amir Huddan, Tim Kaine, Bill Leighty, L. Scott Lingamfelter, Joe May, and Judy Napier.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries B. Tristen Pegram</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 7072 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dLXxqe"><emph render="bold">Kainelibtpegram.pst</emph></extref>. Tristen Pegram, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Technology, served from 2006 until 13 November 2009. After leaving the Secretary of Technology's office, she served in the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy and then on the campaign team for Aneesh Chopra's 2013 unsuccessful bid for Lieutenant Governor of Virginia.  A large portion of this .pst file seems to be the correspondence of Aneesh Chopra, Secretary of Technology from 2006 to 2009.  There are 80 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  the legislative and policy priorities of the Secretariat of Technology; grants given by the Center for Innovative Technology, the Productivity Investment Fund, and the Commonwealth Technology Research Fund; the Commonwealth of Virginia Innovative Technology Symposium; health information technology and electronic medical records; improvements to broadband access for rural populations; and the implementation of the public-private partnership between the Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Preston Bryant, Aneesh Chopra, Thomas Gates, Karen Jackson, Peter Jobse, and Marilyn Tavenner.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries C. Len Pomata Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 570 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e6Q8W6"><emph render="bold">LPOMATA.PST</emph></extref>. Len Pomata served as the Secretary of Technology from 5 June 2009 until the end of the administration in January 2010. He also served as interim Chief Information Officer after the firing of Lem Stewart from 12 June 2009 until 20 August 2009.  There are 29 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  VITA/Northrop Grumman partnership; VITA management and budget issues; the Virginia Information Technology Investment Board (ITIB); the Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), the planning for the 2009 COVITS conference, and health information technology.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email, dated 9 August 2009, about the structure of the Commonwealth's deal with CGI-AMS and two emails, dated 11 August 2009, with Hiram Johnson about the relationship between Pomata and the ITIB.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Brian Chiglinsky, John McDonald, Tristen Pegram, Marilyn Tavenner, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries D. John McDonald Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 2783 email messages in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dXL3LT"><emph render="bold">JMCDONALD.PST and KaineLibjmcdonald.pst</emph></extref>. John McDonald served as Deputy Secretary of Technology from March 2009 to July 2010.  There are 24 privacy protected and confidential emails in these pst files that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p>The JMCDONALD.PST contains 2302 emails sent by John McDonald between 2009 and 2010.  The KaineLibjmcdonald.pst contains 481 emails received by John McDonald between 2009 and 2010.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  management of and issues with the Commonwealth of Virginia's contract with Northrop Grumman for their information technology infrastructure, including the re-negotiation and re-baselining of the contract. There is also information about the planning of the 2009 COVITS conference as well as the transition from the Tim Kaine administration to the Robert McDonnell administration.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Wayne Turnage, dated 8 April 2009, about the issues with the Northrup Grumman contract; email from Aneesh Chopra, dated 21 April 2009, discussing the issues between VITA and Northrup Grumman; email dated 11 June 2009 about Lem Stewart being removed as Virginia's Chief Information Officer (CIO); email from Jackie Simien-Jones, dated 29 July 2009, containing a letter from Fred Duball to Northrop Grumman withholding payment due to alleged violations of the contract; email to Len Pomata, dated 4 August 2009, about issues between VITA and Northrop Grumman; and email to George Coulter, dated 8 September 2009, regarding a proposal for a new contract with Northrop Grumman.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Fred Duball, Cynthia Cordova-Edwards, Len Pomata, David Swynford, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries E. Tim Bass Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 3576 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dLV92T"><emph render="bold">TBassKaine.pst</emph></extref>. J. Timothy Bass served as Enterprise Applications Program Director from 11 April 2005 to 2006, as Deputy Secretary of Technology and Enterprise Applications Program Director from January to 1 July 2006, and as Enterprise Applications Program Director from 1 July 2006 to 2007. His work primarily concerned enterprise applications and their use by the Commonwealth of Virginia. Prior to his appointment, Bass worked for the Virginia Retirement System..  There are 176 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  negotiations for the Enterprise Applications PPEA contract, for which there were two bids: CGI-AMS, who eventually was awarded the contract, and IBM/BearingPoint. The negotiations also included a number of outside consultants, including McClain Group II, Gordon and Glickson, Gartner Consulting, and Latham and Watkins. Also included are the due diligence for the project, the receipt of bids, the negotiations, and the reaction of the General Assembly.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email dated 7 September 2005 regarding the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) investigation of BearingPoint; email to Bill Leighty, dated 14 September 2005, regarding the vote to continue negotiations with CGI-AMS only; email from Lem Stewart, dated 25 October 2005, announcing the selection of Northrop Grumman as the IT infrastructure partner; email from Michael Hepburn, dated 16 December 2005, containing the final agreement between the Commonwealth of Virginia and CGI-AMS; and email from David Von Moll, dated 20 February 2006, regarding cuts to EA budget. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Paul Doty, Michael Hepburn, Daniel Keene, Bill Leighty, Carrie Nee, John Westrick.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries F. Karen Jackson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1 email message in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dxeVgU"><emph render="bold">KJACKSON.pst</emph></extref>. Karen Jackson served as the director of Office of Telework and Broadband Assistance.  Jackson was appointed Deputy Secretary of Technology by Governor Kaine on 7 May 2009.  The email is from 2008 between Jackson and State Senator Frank Ruff and the subject is the auction of the 700 mhz wireless band by the Federal Communications Commission.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries G. Brian Chiglinsky Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1504 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dT32DU"><emph render="bold">KaineLibbchiglinsky.pst </emph></extref>. Brian Chiglinsky served as a Governor's Fellow assigned to the Secretariat of Technology from 2 June 2008 until August 2008, the Special Assistant for Constituent Services from August 2008 to 10 June 2009, and then the Special Assistant to the Secretary of Technology from 11 June 2009 until the end of the administration. While working in Constituent Services, Chiglinsky continued to work on projects for the Secretary of Technology and also worked in the Executive Office of the Governor.  There is 1 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  the creation, funding, organization, and operation of VA STAR, a program which takes used computers from a variety of donors and gives them to school districts throughout the Commonwealth. There is also correspondence relating to comments on the Governor's weekly reports and health care technology.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Andrew LeVasseur, dated 24 November 2009, which includes the award of over $300,000 from the Productivity Investment Fund to fund the VA STAR program.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Amber Amato, Aneesh Chopra, Chuck Drake, Sherrie Harrington, John McDonald, Tristen Pegram, and Len Pomata.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 6774 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 6774 emails in eleven (11) subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. John Marshall Email; B. Clyde Cristman Email; C. Marilyn Harris Email; D. Dawn Smith Email; E. Erin Bryant Email; F. Susan Gholson Email; G. Jacklyn Varela Email; H. Iva Frizzle Email; I. Martha Hazelgrove Email; J. Gabrielle Williams Email; and K. Beth Camphouse Email.  There are 29 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800, 42.1-78 and 53.1-40.10. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel and social services information. 
</p>

<p>During the administration of Governor Timothy Kaine, the Secretary Public Safety provided guidance to the following state agencies:  Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC), Commonwealth's Attorneys' Services Council (CAS); Department of Correctional Education (DCE), Department of Correction (DOC), Department of Criminal Justice Services (DCJS), Department of Emergency Management, Department of Fire Programs, Department of Forensic Science (DFS), Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP), Department of Juvenile Justice (DJJ), Department of Military Affairs (DMA), Virginia Parole Board, Virginia State Police (VSP), Department of Veterans Services (VDVA), and the Virginia War Memorial.
</p>

<p>These agencies enforced criminal, highway safety, and alcoholic beverage and tobacco laws; protected public safety through confinement, treatment and monitoring of felons and through the supervision, treatment and monitoring of people on parole or probation; provided technical assistance, research and training for law enforcement agencies, community fire departments and prosecutors; planed and coordinated the state's emergency preparedness, response, recovery and mitigation efforts; trained firefighters, investigated crimes and tested crime scene evidence; trained Army and Air National Guard members; and provided services to Virginia's veterans.
</p>

<p>John Marshall served as Secretary of Public Safety from January 2002 to January 2010.  Marshall was initially appointed by Governor Mark Warner in January 2002 and reappointed by Governor Tim Kaine on 15 January 2006.
</p>

<p>Marshall began his career in public service and law enforcement in 1980 as a Virginia State Trooper. During his 14 years with the Department of State Police, he also served as a Special Agent in the Narcotics Division, Sergeant-Instructor at the Training Academy and as a Sergeant assigned to Field Operations. 
</p>

<p>In 1994, President William J. Clinton appointed Marshall to serve as the United States Marshal for the Eastern District of Virginia. Later in 1999, President Clinton nominated Marshall to serve as the Director of the United States Marshals Service, our nation's oldest federal law enforcement agency. Upon confirmation by the U.S. Senate, Marshall took office as Director in November of 1999. He is the first African-American to serve as the Director.
</p>

<p>Secretary Marshall graduated from Georgetown University in1988 with a BA in Government, and he also holds a Post-Baccalaureate Certificate in the Administration of Justice from Virginia Commonwealth University.
</p>


</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries A. John Marshall Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 652 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dT7Glg"><emph render="bold">KaineLibjmarshall.pst</emph></extref>. John Marshall served as Secretary of Public Safety from 2002 to 2010.  There are four privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 32.1-127.1:03, 42.1-78, and 63.2-103. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Virginia National Guard; Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC) take home vehicles; storm updates and damage assessments; declarations of state of emergencies; budget reductions; Department of Corrections' media interview policy; technology issues related to the Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG) contract; Virginia Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS); Virginia Tourism poster (gang sign); Virginia Citizen Soldier Support Council; 2009 presidential inaugural planning; Public Safety Memorial Commission;  Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM) procurement program; 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; and the 2007 Governor's Campus Security Conference.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Vince Burgess, Michael Cline, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Pamela O'Berry Evans, W. Steven Flaherty, Marc Follmer, Stephen Harms, Marilyn Harris, Martha Hazelgrove, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Robert Kemmler, Bill Leighty, John McDonald, Walter McFarlane, Robert Newman, Len Pomata, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries B. Clyde Cristman</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 804 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ddtSDP"><emph render="bold">CCristman_SOPS.pst</emph></extref>. Clyde Cristman served as Deputy Secretary of Public Safety from January 2006 to October 2007. Cristman left the Secretary of Public Safety's office for a position with the Virginia State Senate Finance Committee. There are four privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800 and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information and medical information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Commonwealth Interoperability Coordinator's Office (CICO); State Interoperability Advisory Group; Criminal Justice Task Force of the Chief Justice's Commission on Mental Health Law Reform; 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; DNA testing by the Virginia Department of Forensic Science (ordered by Governor Mark Warner in 2004); Virginia correctional system; prisoner re-entry; strategic plan for Secretary of Public Safety; and memorandum of understandings between Public Safety state agencies and Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA).
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Robert Crouch, Chris Essid, Paul Ferrara, Iva Frizzell, Marilyn Harris, Jennifer Hastings, Martha Hazelgrove, Pete Marone, John Marshall, Melissa McMenemy, Kevin Patrick, Thomas Stuzzieri, Larry Traylor, Wayne Turnage, Carol Ulrich, and Charles Werner.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries C. Marilyn Harris Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 270 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dlDRu6"><emph render="bold">MHARRIS.PST</emph></extref>. Marilyn Harris served as Deputy Secretary of Public Safety and Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP) Director from January 2006 to January 2010. One email in this subseries is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3801 and 42.1-78. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  budget reductions; public safety employee assistance; closure of Natural Bridge Juvenile Correctional Center (NBJCC); public safety legislation; electronic interrogations; and the Virginia Public Safety Memorial.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Helen Fahey, Pete Marone, Walter McFarlane, and B.J. Northington.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries D. Dawn Smith Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2002-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 603 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dXKDFx"><emph render="bold">DSmith.pst</emph></extref>. Dawn B. Smith served as Assistant Secretary of Public Safety from 2002 to 2006 in Governor Mark Warner's administration.  She was reappointed by Governor Tim Kaine and served until August 2008.  Smith also served as staff to the Virginia Citizen-Soldier Support Council, formed by Governor Mark Warner in 2003. Two emails are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 2.2-3801 and 42.1-78.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWaM) and minority procurement; National Advisory Board, Norfolk State University Intelligence Community, Center for Academic Excellence (NSU ICCAE); reports to the Virginia General Assembly; Congressional briefings on public safety federal appropriation requests; and prisoner reentry.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Clyde Cristman, Barbara Lee, John Marshall, and Cindy Sanger.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries E. Erin Bryant Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 2688 email messages in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ehguV3"><emph render="bold">KaineLibEBryant.pst and EBRYANT.PST</emph></extref>. Erin Bryant served as Senior Special Assistant (2005-2008) and Assistant Secretary of Public Safety (2008-2010).  In 2007, Bryant worked in the Office of Special Projects assisting with Queen Elizabeth II's visit to Virginia in May 2007.  There are nine privacy protected and confidential emails in these pst files that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 52-48.  Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client priviledge and Virginia Fusion Intelligence Center reports.
</p>

<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibEBryant.pst</emph> contains 2682 emails sent/received by Erin Bryant between August 2005 and January 2010.  The <emph render="bold">EBRYANT.PST</emph> contains six emails sent/received by Erin Bryant on 15 January 2010.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  constituent correspondence; continuity of operations programs (COOP) summary sheets for public safety agencies; public safety legislation for the 2006-2010 general assembly sessions (bill assignments, enrolled bill review, legislative action summaries, status of legislation, amendments, talking points, budget); ARRA (stimulus funding for public safety agencies); public relations/activities (press releases, media alerts, talking points, bill signings, Cabinet Community Days, Pre-K events, Public Safety Memorial, Queen's visit, and the 2006 September 11 Memorial Event); Alternatives for Non-Violent Offenders Task Force; Commission on Sexual Violence (agenda, meeting notes, recommendations, final report, PERK legislation [Physical Evidence Recovery Kit]); Governor's Fellows Program; Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup; Prevention Comes First initiative to reduce gang violence and related crime; and the Virginia Public Safety Memorial Commission.
</p>

<p>Records related to Queen Elizabeth II's 2007 visit to Virginia include:  photographs, minute-by-minute overview of the Queen's visit to Capitol Square, event planning time-line, Royal protocol instructions, and biographies of participants.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  email from Jacklyn Varela, dated 14 May 2007, to Bryant, transmitting typed notes from the 10 May 2007 meeting of the Virginia Tech Review Panel.  Metadata on the attachment indicated the notes were taken by Hollis Stambaugh, Virginia Tech Review Panel staff deputy director. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Melissa Ball, Marilyn Batan, Diane Bechamps, Amy Bridge, Greg Brittingham, Beth Camphouse, Steven Combs, Laura Cross, Marla Decker, Fran Ecker, Eileen Guertier, Marilyn Harris, Amanda Howe, Margaret Hughson, Gary Janak, Richard Jerome, Robert Kemmler, John Marshall, Jane Minerly, Jennie Moline, Jason Newman, Jeffery Painter, Judy Philpott, Brook Pittinger, Robbie Prevette, Patricia Rollston, Felix Sarfo-Kantanka, Alison Shames, Brian Shepard, Dawn Smith, Tamra Talmadge-Anderson, Gayle Turner, George Urquhart, and Russell Woodlief.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries F. Susan Gholston Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 524 email messages in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dduJUR"><emph render="bold">SGHOLSON.PST and KaineLibsgholston.pst</emph></extref>. Susan Gholston served as the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP) Community Data Director from 2006 to 2010.
</p>

<p>The <emph render="bold">SGHOLSON.PST</emph> contains 504 emails sent by Susan Gholston between 2006 and 2010.  The <emph render="bold">KaineLibsgholston.pst</emph> contains 20 constituent correspondence sent/received by Gholson between April 2006 and October 2009.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Community Profile Database (CPD) Development (includes technical problems with database); and the EPI Grant (State Epidemiological Outcome Workgroup), a collaborative project between GOSAP and DMHMRSAS; Gholston was project director.  Records include proposal, budget, work plans, Summary Status Reports, drafts of report and final report.
</p>



<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Marilyn Harris, Hope Merrick, Gene Miles, and Rosemary Shoemaker. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries G. Jacklyn Varela Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 594 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dXJFsv"><emph render="bold">KaineLibJVarela.pst</emph></extref>. Jacklyn Varela served as Special Assistant to the Secretary of Public Safety/GOSAP from 2006 to April 2008.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  weekly reports  from the Virginia Department of Fire Programs; legislation (2008 session); gangs (Committee on Developing Partnerships with Other States); Public Safety Memorial Commission; and the Commission on Sexual Violence.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Erin Bryant, Steven Combs, Lois Fegan, Eileen Guertler, Marilyn Harris, J. Kay Hunnel, Jeffrey Painter, Brook Pittinger, Patricia Rollston, George Urquhart, and Russell Woodlief.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safet Electronic Files, Subseries H. Iva Frizzle Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2002-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 63 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ehhjNp"><emph render="bold">2006Libifrizzell.pst</emph></extref>. Iva Frizzell served as Executive Assistant to the Secretary of Public Safety from January 2002 to June 2007. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  list of Public Safety agency accomplishments for 2004 as requested by Governor Mark Warner; CapWIN (Capital Wireless Integrated Network); meeting notes, agendas, and reports; post Katrina/Rita evaluation measuring state agency preparedness (February 2006);  photographs of damage in New Orleans from Hurricane Katrina; and Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) MOU issues with Public Safety agencies (2006).
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Deborah Hayes, Tom Henderson, and Tom Jacobs.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries I. Martha Hazelgrove Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 339 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2etruxH"><emph render="bold">KaineLibMHazelgrove.pst</emph></extref>.Martha Hazelgrove served as a Special Assistant (2006-2007) and Executive Assistant (2007-2010) in the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety.  There are nine privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 53.1-40. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel and social services information.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  2009 Presidential inauguration; constituent correspondence; transition documents prepared by Public Safety agencies for Governor-Elect Bob McDonnell; and Secretary of Public Safety weekly reports.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Marilyn Harris, John Marshall, and Secretary of Public Safety website comments.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries J. Gabrielle Williams Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 10 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dKGKVO"><emph render="bold">KaineLibGWilliams.pst</emph></extref>. Gabrielle Williams served as a Special Assistant in the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety from July 2007 to January 2010.  
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  constituent correspondence and decisions briefs.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries K. Beth Camphouse Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 227 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2d8r8fH"><emph render="bold">KaineLibbcamphouse.pst</emph></extref>. Beth Camphouse served a Governor's Fellow (June-August 2009) and Special Assistant in the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety from August 2009 to January 2010.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   legislative files; Alternatives for Non-Violent Offenders Task Force; Virginia Prisoner Reentry Policy Academy; Criminal Justice/Mental Health Transformation Consortium; Virginia Public Safety Memorial; and Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP).
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Erin Bryant (Rice), Barry Green, and Marilyn Harris.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 10490 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration.  This series contains 10490 emails in seven (7) subseries.  Subseries have been designated for A. Daniel LeBlanc Email; B. Gail Robinson Email; C. Brian Davis Email; D. Marietta Salyer Email; E. Beatrice Yarney Email; F. Sarah Abubaker Email; and G. Patrick Callahan Email.  There are 49 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications. 
</p>

<p>The Workforce Investment Act (WIA), signed by President Bill Clinton in 1998, reformed federal job training programs and created a new comprehensive workforce investment system. The WIA did five things: created a state workforce investment system, created a local one stop delivery system, authorized three local workforce programs for adults, youth and dislocated workers, amended three related federal statutes (Adult Education and Literacy), (Wagner-Peyser) and (Rehabilitation Act) and authorized five national workforce programs - Job Corps, Migrant and Seasonal Farm Workers, Veterans, Native Americans and Youth Opportunity Grants.
</p>

<p>A 2002 Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission review of Virginia's implementation of WIA recommended the creation of a workforce development coordinator, reporting directly to the Governor, whose sole responsibility would be statewide coordination of workforce development services. When the General Assembly did not pass this recommendation in 2003, Governor Mark Warner, took executive action and on 17 June 2003 appointed Dr. Barbara Bolin as Special Assistant to the Governor on Workforce Development.
</p>

<p>In 2004 the General Assembly codified the position (renamed Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development) and clarified the advisor's specific duties. The advisor is responsible for serving as the liaison for workforce training with state and local government, the Virginia Workforce Council (VWC), local work investment boards, as well as the general business community. The advisor is also responsible for reviewing fund allocation, helping the VWC implement policies for the Virginia Workforce System, monitoring federal workforce-related legislation, and reporting annually on the condition of statewide workforce training programs. Dr. Bolin resigned her position in May 2005, and Dolores Esser of the Virginia Employment Commission was appointed to fill the vacancy in November 2005.
</p>

<p>In 2006 General Assembly passed legislation creating the Chief Workforce Development Officer. The Governor is the Chief Workforce Development Officer and he may delegate that responsibility to a senior person on his immediate staff. The Chief Workforce Development Officer is responsible for the coordination of workforce development across Secretariats and ensuring that the Commonwealth's workforce development efforts are implemented in a coordinated and efficient manner. This position replaced the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development created in 2004.
</p>

<p>On 21 March 2006, Governor Tim Kaine named Daniel C. LeBlanc, former President of the Virginia AFL-CIO and Kaine's failed nominee for Secretary of the Commonwealth, as Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce. Executive Order 25 issued by Governor Kaine on 23 June 2006 delegated his authority as Chief Workforce Development Officer to the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce and further clarified the Advisor's duties and responsibilities. This order was issued to ensure that initial transition steps occurred to implement the 2006 legislation. Kaine's Executive Order 61, issued on 4 January 2008, rescinded Executive Order 25 and was issued to ensure that the next phase of transition occurred including: the creation of a Workforce Sub Cabinet to ensure Cabinet collaboration regarding workforce development as required by state and federal statute; listing of the duties of the Cabinet Secretaries and designating the Virginia Community College System (VCCS) as the designated state agency for the WIA, including that of grant recipient and fiscal administrative agency. 
</p>

<p>Executive Order 61 also tasked the Senior Advisor for Workforce with overseeing the implementation of the development of comprehensive integrated seamless local One Stop workforce service delivery systems. To further advance the implementation of this effort, the State Partner Memorandum of Understanding for Comprehensive One Stop Centers was signed in March of 2008. This document was the first in Virginia to clearly delineate specific requirements of state agencies and programs across multiple Secretariats towards the creation and support a workforce development system that operates effectively in a one stop environment with a primary focus on citizens and employers in an efficient manner.
</p>

<p>With the assistance of Camille Miller, a consultant, five workforce centers were opened by the end of the Kaine administration in January 2010.  An additional seven were scheduled to open by June 2010.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries A. Daniel LeBlanc Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 2353 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ebqG1W"><emph render="bold">DLABLANC.PST</emph></extref>. As Senior Advisor for Workforce from 2006 to 2010, LeBlanc served as a member of Governor Tim Kaine's Cabinet in his role as Chief Workforce Development Officer.  LeBlanc's responsibilities included advising the Governor on all workforce development matters. LeBlanc also chaired the Workforce Sub Cabinet. In this role, he coordinated with the Virginia Community College System and mandated State government representatives in order to realize the Governor's vision for workforce development. LeBlanc oversaw the development and implementation of the Commonwealth's first ever Strategic Plan for Workforce Development. He also worked across Secretariats to achieve consensus on a State Partner Memorandum of Understanding for Comprehensive One Stop Centers, a landmark directive for workforce service delivery in the Commonwealth. There are four privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client communications.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Closing of Ford Motor Company plant in Norfolk; Workforce Investment Act (WIA) including the transition WIA responsibilities from the Virginia Employment Commission (VEC) to the Virginia Community College System (VCCS); Comprehensive One-Stops (Charlottesville, Danville, Roanoke, South Boston) including location, site selection, real estate and information technology issues; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act (ARRA) funding for workforce development; state budget/funding; Career Readiness Certificate (CRC); closing of International Paper in Franklin; workforce related legislation; closing of Quimonda plant in Henrico County; Virginia Veterans Workforce Development Taskforce; layoffs at Volvo truck plant in Dublin; Workforce Sub Cabinet; and the development of the Memorandum of Instruction and Understanding (MOU) for Comprehensive One Stop Workforce Centers (including drafts, comments and implementation).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  exchange between LaBlanc and Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, dated 6 February 2009, on the closing of Quimonda plant in Henrico County and the budget problems facing the Commonwealth.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Sarah Abubaker, Peter Blake, Willie Blanton, Aneesh Chopra, Brian Davis, Paula Dehetre, Katherine DeRosear, Delores Esser, Peter Gottschalk, Steven Gould, Lynette Hammond, Tim Kaine, Robert Leber, Bill Leighty, Camille Wright Miller, Bobby Myers, Aida Pacheco, Barbara Reese, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Marietta Salyer, Brian Shepard, George Taratsas, Wayne Turnage, and Dick Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries B. Gail Robinson Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 3703 email messages in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2eKm6Yb"><emph render="bold">KaineLibGRobinson.pst and GROBINSON.PST</emph></extref>. Gail Robinson served as Deputy Workforce Advisor from May 2006 to January 2010. Her responsibilities included: development and implementation of the Governor's Workforce Development Strategic Plan for the statewide delivery of workforce development and training programs and activities; cross-Cabinet collaboration in state workforce policy development and program implementation; and workforce systems design and workforce system performance and outcome measures. There are 16 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client privilege.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibGRobinson.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibGRobinson.pst</emph> file contains 1406 emails sent and received by Gail Robinson between 2006 and 2010. There are three privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  the development of the Memorandum of Instruction and Understanding (MOU) for Comprehensive One Stop Workforce Centers (including drafts, comments and implementation); status reports on the One Stop Centers; preparations for opening Comprehensive One Stops; cost allocations for One Stop Centers; Workforce Sub Cabinet; Workforce Development Program Performance Indicators for the Commonwealth of Virginia, report prepared for the Governor's Office by Kevin Hollenback of W.E. Upjohn Institute (Fall 2007) - records include development of report, progress reports by Hollenback, and comments from effected parties; work of and report from the Interagency Workgroup on Workforce Performance Data Issues (Fall 2009); transference of Workforce Investment Act (WIA) responsibilities from the Office of the Senior Advisor and the Virginia Employment Commission (VEC) to the Virginia Community College System (VCCS) - records include MOU and transition issues; technology issues between the Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) and One-Stop Centers; drafts and final version of an IT Guide for One Stop Workforce Centers written by VITA; and the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Notable email includes</emph>
:  a series of weekly One-Stop reports from Camille Wright Miller to Daniel LeBlanc in 2009. These reports provided a summary of activities at One-Stops across the Commonwealth.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Sarah Abubaker, Peter Blake, Brian Davis, Paula Dehetre, Katherine DeRosear, Patrick Gottschalk, Lynette Hammond, Kevin Hollenbeck, Hal Hughey, Danny LeBlanc, Bill Leighty, Camille Wright Miller, Marietta Saylor, George Taratsas, Wayne Turnage, and Richard Zorn.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">GROBINSON.PST</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">GROBINSON.PST</emph> file contains 2297 emails sent and received by Gail Robinson between 2006 and 2010. There are 13 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to:  attorney-client communications.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  development of the Memorandum of Instruction and Understanding (MOU)for Comprehensive One Stop Workforce Centers (including drafts, comments and implementation); Comprehensive One-Stops (Charlottesville, Danville, Roanoke, South Boston) including location, site selection, real estate and information technology issues; drafts of Executive Order on posting jobs created by ARRA federal projects; drafts of IT Guide for One Stop Centers; draft legislation for the 2009 General Assembly session moving workforce development to the Education secretariat; workforce legislation; Workforce Subcabinet; and the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
: Peter Blake, Willie Blanton, Patrick Callahan, Brian Davis, Paula Dehetre, Lynette Hammond, Hal Hughley, Gail Jaspen, Daniel LeBlanc, Camille Wright Miller, Linda Nablo, Marietta Saylor, George Taratsas, and Beatrice Yarney.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>


</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries C. Brian Davis Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007 and 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1492 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2dsDyKv"><emph render="bold">KaineLibBDavis.pst</emph></extref>. Brian Davis worked in the Workforce Office from 2006 to 2007 and 2008 to 2009 as Director of Workforce Systems. There are 22 privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client communications.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   One Stop Workforce Centers (Charlottesville, Danville, Roanoke); Governor's WIA Discretionary Funds; Workforce Program Performance; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA); drafts of Executive Order on posting jobs created by ARRA federal projects; drafts of, One-Stop Implementation Guide, IT Guide for One Stop Centers and One Stop HR Guidance; WIA Waiver Plans submitted to the United States Department of Labor; Poverty Reduction Task Force; and Workforce weekly report.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Kim Adkins, Beth Brinly, Delores Esser, Jeffrey Gabriel, Lynette Hammond, Rosalyn Key-Tiller, Danny LeBlanc, Camille Wright Miller, Gail Robinson, Shelby Robinson, Megan Root, Marietta Sayler, George Taratsas, and Beatrice Yarney.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries D. Marietta Salyer Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 1987 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2e4n4eo"><emph render="bold">KaineLibMSalyer.pst</emph></extref>. Marietta Salyer served as Statewide One Stop System Director from 2007 to July 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   One Stop Workforce Centers including planning process, status reports, cost sharing, and development of centers (Arlington, Charlottesville, Danville, Fredericksburg, Hampton Roads, Harrisonburg, Martinsville, Petersburg, Prince William, Roanoke, South Boston, Winchester, and Wytheville); technology issues between the Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) and One-Stop Centers; drafts and final version of an IT Guide for One Stop Workforce Centers written by VITA; VITA status reports for each Comprehensive One Stop center; notes from One Stop Information Technologies Planning Committee meetings; One Stop Implementation Guide; and the creation and work of the Senior Advisor's Strike Force to resolve critical issues with the Charlottesville One Stop.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Kim Adkins, Joe Ashley, Peter Blake, Willie Blanton, Deborah Crowder, Brian Davis, William Diamond, Heather Foor, Robert Gluck, Carmen Hoge, Hal Hughey, David Hunn, Daniel LeBlanc, Ronnie Martin, Camille Wright Miller, Kim Moore, Etta Morehouse, Bobby Myers, Nablo, Linda, Aida Pacheco, Dee Pisciella, Gail Robinson, Shelby Robinson, Donna Scarlett, Lori Stumpf, Levin C. Sullivan, George Taratsas, Dolores Vest, Tom Vozenilek, Tracy Walker, and Beatrice Yarney.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries E. Beatrice Yarney Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2009 </emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 290 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ewjKa7"><emph render="bold">yarney.pst</emph></extref>.  Beatrice Yarney served as Special Assistant to the Senior Advisor for Workforce from January to July 2009.  She worked as an intern in the Workforce office from 2007 to 2008. There are seven privacy protected and confidential emails in this pst file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client communications.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  One Stop Workforce Centers; Economic Crisis Strike Force; 2009 legislative session bill review; and weekly reports. 
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Brian Davis, Gary Janak, Daniel LeBlanc, Camille Wright Miller, Aida Pacheco, Gail Robinson, and Megan Root. 
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries F. Sarah Abubaker Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> September 2007 to January 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 612 email messages in two pst files:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2emYl8J"><emph render="bold">SABUBAKER.PST and KaineLibSAbubaker.pst</emph></extref>. Sarah Abubaker served as Executive Assistant to the Senior Advisor for Workforce Development from January 2008 to January 2009. She worked as a Special Assistant in Constituent Services from 2007 to 2008.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">SABUBAKER.PST</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2007-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">SABUBAKER.PST</emph> file contains 264 emails sent and received by Sarah Abubaker between September 2007 and January 2009.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  the development of the Memorandum of Instruction and Understanding (MOU) for Comprehensive One Stop Workforce Centers (including drafts, comments and implementation); One Stop Workforce Centers; Decision Briefs; 2008 legislative session bill review; and Workforce Sub Cabinet.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Peter Blake, Brian Davis, Daniel LeBlanc, Gail Robinson, Marietta Salyer, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibSAbubaker.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2008-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibSAbubaker.pst</emph> file contains 348 emails sent and received by Sarah Abubaker between January 2008 and January 2009.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Workforce Sub Cabinet; 2008 legislative session bill review; One Stop Workforce Centers; and Weekly Report items from GOWD staff members.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Willie Blanton, Brian Davis, Paula Scott Dehetre, Gary Janak, Daniel LeBlanc, Gail Robinson, and Marietta Salyer.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Office of the Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Electronic Files, Subseries G. Patrick Callahan Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009-2010 </emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 53 email messages in one pst file:  <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2ep8u0R"><emph render="bold">KaineLibpcallahan.pst</emph></extref>.  Patrick Callahan served as Special Assistant to the Senior Advisor for Workforce from August 2009 to January 2010. He also was a Governor's Fellow from June to August 2009 assigned to the Workforce office.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   disability issues; and One Stop Workforce Centers.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Brian Davis, Daniel LeBlanc, Gail Robinson, and Ed Turner.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 26988 emails.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>

<p>The Secretary of Education Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine administration. This series contains 26988 emails in ten (10) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Thomas Morris Email; B. Judith Heiman Email; C. Dietra Trent Email; D. Douglas Garcia Email; E. Jean Bankos Email; F. Kathy Glazer Email; G. Kendall Tyree Email; H. June Hines Email; I. Lorraine Lintecum Email; and J. Nicholas Galvin Email. 
</p>

<p>The Secretary of Education assists the Governor in the development and implementation of the state's education policy. During the Kaine administration, the Secretary of Education provided guidance to 16 public universities, the Virginia Community College System, higher education and research centers, state educational agencies, and state supported museums and libraries. The Virginia education agencies and institutions include: Department of Education, Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Virginia Career Education Foundation, Virginia Early Childhood Foundation, Christopher Newport University, College of William and Mary, George Mason University, James Madison University, Longwood University, Norfolk State University, Old Dominion University, Radford University, University of Mary Washington, University of Virginia, University of Virginia's College at Wise, Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia State University, Virginia Tech, State Council of Higher Education, Virginia Community College System, Library of Virginia, Frontier Culture Museum, Gunston Hall, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Science Museum of Virginia, and Virginia Commission for the Arts.
</p>

<p>Dr. Thomas Morris served as Secretary of Education from January 2006 to January 2010. Prior to his appointment by Governor-elect Kaine, Dr. Morris served as the president of Emory and Henry College for over 13 years. A distinguished Constitutional scholar and political scientist, he was a distinguished faculty member at the University of Richmond for 21 years.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries A. Thomas Morris Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>The subseries contains 560 email messages in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibtmorris.pst</emph>. Thomas Morris served as Secretary of Education from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>

<p>The KaineLibtmorris.pst contains 560 email messages send and received by Thomas Morris between January 2006 and January 2010.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  state budget including agency budget reductions; education initiatives and policy including Pre-K; state agency issues and correspondence [Department of Education, State Council of Higher Education for Virginia, Virginia Community College System]; early childhood education and creation of the Office of Early Childhood Development.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   James Batterson, Peter Blake, Billy Cannaday, Aneesh Chopra, Douglas Garcia, Glenn DuBois, Judy Heiman, Tim Kaine, Daniel LaVista, Bill Leighty, Tod Massa, Brian Shepard, Dietra Trent, and Wayne Turnage.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries B. Judy Heiman Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 3047 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">JHEIMAN.PST</emph>. Judy Heiman served as Deputy Secretary of Education from January 2006 to December 2007. Heiman left the Kaine administration when she accepted a position in the California Legislative Analyst's Office. Prior to joining the Kaine administration, Heiman worked as budget and policy analyst for the Virginia Department of Planning and Budget.
</p>

<p>The JHEIMAN.PST contains 3047 email messages sent and received by Judy Heiman between February 2006 and October 2008. The emails from 2008 are broadcast messages captured in Heiman's email box after she left the administration.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   Achieve - Virginia's American Diploma Project Network (ADP); career and technical education; College Readiness Project; Commonwealth Scholars; 
state agency correspondence and issues from Department of Education; state budget issues including agency budget reductions; legislative files; early childhood education and creation of the Office of Early Childhood Development; Governor's Workforce Development Strategic Plan; and State Workforce Sub Cabinet.

</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Mark Allan, Jean Bankos, Jim Batterson, Peter Blake, Deborah Bliss, Andrew Block, David Breneman, Bethann Canada, Billy Cannaday, Dean Clifford, Don Darr, Kent Dickey, Glenn DuBois, Eileen Filler-Corn, Sterling Daniel, Tabitha Foreman, Douglas Garcia, Kathy Glazer, Michael Harreld, Deborah Jonas, Bill Leighty, Tod Massa, Juanita McHale, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Karen Petersen, Charles Pyle, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Elizabeth Russell, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Christine Tell, Dan Timberlake, Dietra Trent, Karen Trump, Kendall Tyree, Wayne Turnage, Kendall Tyree, Linda Wallinger, Anne Wescott, and Patricia Wright.
</p>

</scopecontent>



</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries C. Dietra Trent Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 6267 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibdtrent.pst</emph>. Dietra Trent served as Deputy Secretary of Education, Higher Education, from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>

<p>The KaineLibdtrent.pst contains 6267 emails sent and received by Dietra Trent from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   state budget including agency budget requests and reductions; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA) federal stimulus grants and projects for higher education; legislation; 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; creation of the Virginia Tech Victims (VTV) Family Outreach Foundation; VITA/NG issues and costs with the Library of Virginia; and correspondence from higher education institutions.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   James Alessio, Ruth Anderson, Lee Andes, Brenda Atkins, Viola Baskerville, John Bennett, Thomas Bernadas, Peter Blake, Ric Brown, Susan Carney, Paul Casalaspi, Aneesh Chopra, Donald Combs, Clementine Cone, Rich Conti, Carolyn Cook, Robert Crouch, Pam Currey, Don Darr, Cintra Davis, Kent Dickey, Barry Dorsey, Deborah Dowd, Alan Edwards, Christine Fields, Marc Follmer, Laura Fornash, Dominic Gabello, Manju Ganeriwala, Douglas Garcia, Robert Green, Judy Heiman, Tom Hennessey, Chris Hinkle, Dan Hix, Gail Jaspen, Tim Kaine, Gary Knick, Daniel LaVista, Bill Leighty, Brian Longwood, Alfonso Lopez, Tony Maggio, Tod Massa, Michael Maul, Tom McKeon, Jennie Moline, Liz Montalvo, Tom Morris, Bill Murray, Kirsten Nelson, Patty Nelson, Shaylah Nunn, Jack Parry, Cindi Perry, Karen Petersen, Michael Pohle, Barbara Reese, Gail Robinson, Mark Rubin, Joe Samaha, Michael Sandridge, Scott Sandridge, Colette Sheehy, Brian Shepard, Anne Smith, Diane Stamp, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Sandra Treadway, Maribeth Trun, Wayne Turnage, David Von Moll, Jody Wagner, Elizabeth Wallace, Emily Ward, Anne Wescott, Walter Witschey, Patricia Wright, Nolan Yelich, and Richard Zorn.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>



	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries D. Douglas Garcia Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2007-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 350 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibdgarcia.pst</emph>. Douglas Garcia served as Assistant Secretary of Education from January 2006 to January 2010.
</p>

<p>The KaineLibdgarcia.pst contains 350 emails sent and received by Douglas Garcia between April 2007 and January 2010.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   legislation including bill review.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Judy Heiman, Gary Janak, Tom Morris, Kirsten Nelson, Megan Root, and Brian Shepard.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries E. Jean Bankos Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009 </emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 1635 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibJBankos.pst</emph>. Jean Bankos served as Senior Advisor to the Governor for Educational Project from June 2006 to June 2009.
</p>

<p>The KaineLibJBankos.pst contains 1635 emails sent and received by Jean Bankos between June 2006 and June 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   Virginia's State Scholars Initiative; American Diploma Project (ADP) (Achieve, Inc.); Governor's Career and Technical Academies; Commonwealth Scholars; Standards of Accreditation; Governor's Award for Educational Excellence; state budget; Career Readiness Certificates; career and technical education; Commission on Civics Educations; weekly reports; legislation; Virginia's participation in National Governors Association (NGA) education initiatives; P-16 initiatives; and Virginia Career Education Foundation (VCEF).
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   James Batterson, Peter Blake, Aneesh Chopra, Elizabeth Creamer, Jessica Eades, Douglas Garcia, Melissa Goldberg, Judy Heiman, Wendy Kang, Daniel LeBlanc, Lorraine Lintecum, Betsy McClearn, Juanita McHale, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Charles Pyle, Barbara Reese, Emily Richardson, Gail Robinson, Megan Root, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Dietra Trent, Kendall Tyree, Linda Wallinger, Anne Wescott, Lois Williams, and Patricia Wright.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries F. Kathy Glazer Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 2075 emails in two pst files: <emph render="bold">cglazer.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">KaineLibKGlazer.pst</emph>. Kathy Glazer served as Executive Director, Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives, from 2006 to June 2008. In July 2008, Glazer became the director of the new Office of Early Childhood Development within the Virginia Dept. of Social Services.
</p>

</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold"></emph>cglazer.pst, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p><emph render="bold">The cglazer.pst</emph> contains 2071 emails sent and received by Kathy Glazer between August 2006 and April 2009.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  Virginia Preschool Initiative (VPI); Pre-K; weekly reports; budget; creation of Office of Early Childhood Development (OECD); School Readiness Task Force; and Start Strong.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Mark Allan, Catherine Bodkin, Denise Branscome, Billy Cannaday, Julia Coffman, Suzette Denslow, Kent Dickey, Heidi Dix, Kathy Gillikin, Judy Heiman, Anne Hyslop, Debora Jonas, Rob Krupicka, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Kate Paris, Cassandra Peters, Sarah Plumb, Cosby Rogers, Margaret Schultze, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, Dan Timberlake, Wayne Turnage, Linda Wallinger, Emily Ward, and Patricia Wright.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KaineLibKGlazer.pst</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2006-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KaineLibKGlazer.pst</emph> contains four emails sent and received by Kathy Glazer between August 2006 and May 2008. Subjects include: Virginia Preschool Initiative (VPI).</p>
</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>


	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries G. Kendall Tyree Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2005-2009 </emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 10741 emails in two pst files: <emph render="bold">KaineLibKTyree.pst</emph> and <emph render="bold">KTYREE.PST</emph>. Kendall Tyree served as Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education from June 2005 to October 2008.
</p>
</scopecontent>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold"></emph>KaineLibKTyree.pst, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2008</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">cglazer.pst</emph> contains 2071 emails sent and received by Kathy Glazer between August 2006 and April 2009.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  weekly reports/SWAM reports from education agencies including public colleges and universities; and legislative files.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Heather Adams, Ashley Amey, Teresa Anders, Melissa Anderson, Lynne Archer-Brownlee, Teresa Bailey, Jean Bankos, Candy Banks, Mike Barton, John Bennett, Foster Billingsley, Peter Blake, Jackie Blasco, Ellie Boyd, Gena Boyle, Fran Bradford, Erin Bryant, Anthony Cannion, Sylvia Cannon, Valarie Carter, Mark Cartwright, Linda Chapman, Elizabeth Charity, Debra Nicole Collins, Denise Crittenden, Noreen Crowley, Ellen Davenport, Dane Davis, Ronald Davis, Carline Deal, Nan Dunford, Judy Dunn, Glenise Evans, Richard Farrow, Susan Fauver, Sarah Finley, Keith Gagnon, Douglas Garcia, Terri Givler, Kathy Glazer, Velvet Grant-Johnson, Charles Grosik, Cassandra Hamilton, Donna Harper, Anne Harris, Linda Harris, Jan Hathcock, Judy Heiman, Mary Hicks-Coston, Joe Hilbert, Lori Hiner, June Hines, Connie Houff, Stephen Hudson, Gary Janak, Nancy Jimison, Thomas Kaloupek, Nick Kaveski, Dianah Kelly, Deborah Kranz, Lorraine Lacy, Nick Langridge, Cheri Lankford, Jeff Lawhorne, Bet Ludden, Jeff Lunsford, Juanita McHale, Jessica Milburn, Cathryn Mobley, Jennie Moline, Robin Moore, Tom Morris, Donna Morrow, Kirsten Nelson, Jack Parry, Pam Perkins, Janice Phillips, Steven Pierson, Wanda Poff, Devonia Rexrode, Emily Richardson, Doris Roach, Megan Root, Nan Rowe, Lee Ann Rung, Nancy Sanders, Linda Scott, Suzy Scott, Darlene Selz, Colette Sheehy, Jeanne Shuler, Becca Slayton, Anne Smith, Debra Smith, Roger Spencer, Margaret Sumiel, Gary Tilley, Paul Timmreck, Eugene Trani, Dietra Trent, Michelle Vucci, Elizabeth Wallace, Linda Wallinger, Joyce Walton, Anne Wescott, Ruth Whitt, Lisle Wilke, Cindy Woodfork, and Kathy Worster.
</p>
</scopecontent>

</c03>

	<c03 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">KTYREE.PST</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2005-2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        </did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The <emph render="bold">KTYREE.PST</emph> contains 1837 emails send and received by Kendall Tyree between June 2005 and April 2009. This file includes email sent to Tyree after she left the Secretary of Education's Office in October 2008.</p>

<p>
<emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:  weekly reports/SWAM reports from education agencies including public colleges and universities; weekly report from Secretary of Education to Governor; legislative files; and state budget.
</p>


<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:  Jean Bankos, Peter Blake, Gena Boyle, Anthony Cannion, Noreen Crowley, Ellen Davenport, Douglas Garcia, Cassandra Hamilton, Jan Hathcock, Judy Heiman, Shay Hope, Bet Ludden, Jennie Moline, Tom Morris, Kirsten Nelson, Svandis Pollard, Doris Roach, Megan Root, Juanita Tabor, Dietra Trent, Michelle Vucci, Elizabeth Wallace, and Anne Wescott.
</p>

</scopecontent>
</c03>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries H. June Hines Email</emph>, <unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2006-2007</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 140 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">JHines_SOE.pst</emph>. June Hines served as Executive Assistant to the Secretary of Education from January 2006 to October 2007.
</p>

<p>JHines_SOE.pst contains 140 emails sent and received by June Hines between January 2006 and October 2007.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   meeting materials; talking points, and reports.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Judy Heiman, Tom Morris, Dietra Trent, and Kendall Tyree.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries I. Lorraine Lintecum Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2008-2010</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains 2170 emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">KaineLibLLintecum.pst</emph>. Lorraine Lintecum served as Executive Assistant to the Secretary of Education from January 2008 to January 2010.
</p>

<p>KaineLibLLintecum.pst contains 2170 emails sent and received by Lorraine Lintecum between January 2008 and December 2009.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Subjects include</emph>
:   weekly reports/SWAM reports from education agencies including public colleges and universities; weekly report from Secretary of Education to Governor; Workforce Sub Cabinet; and state budget including cost savings strategies.
</p>

<p><emph render="underline">Correspondents include</emph>
:   Bob Almond, Jean Bankos, Candy Banks, Billy Cannaday, Anthony Cannion, Judy Dunn, Douglas Garcia, Kathy Glazer, Daniel LaVista, Juanita McHale, Tom Morris, Svandis Pollard, Lee Ann Rung, Dietra Trent, Wayne Turnage, Kendall Tyree, and Beatrice Yarney.
</p>

</scopecontent>

</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII. Secretary of Education Electronic Files, Subseries J. Nicholas Galvin Email</emph>,<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 2009</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
        
	</did>
	<scopecontent>

<p>This subseries contains three emails in one pst file: <emph render="bold">NGALVIN.pst</emph>. Nicholas Gavin served as an intern in the Secretary of Education's office from January 2009 to April 2009.
</p>

<p>NGALVIN.pst contains three emails sent in January 2009 by Nicholas Galvin to Doug Garcia about legistion.
</p>


</scopecontent>

</c02>


</c01>


</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>


