<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00820">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00820::A Guide to the William Crutchfield Business Records, 1848-1870)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00820&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00820::A Guide to the William
             Crutchfield Business Records, 1848-1870)//EN"
             "vi00820"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the William Crutchfield Business
            Records, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1870</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Crutchfield, William, Business Records,
            1848-1870 
            <num type="collectionnumber">1107270, 1107271, 1107276,
            1107280, 1107282, 1107284, 1107287, 1107288, 1107291,
            1107304, 1128725, 1128735-1128738</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford</author>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2003 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 50 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         record. Created by Greg Crawford 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 January 2003</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 14, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00820::A Guide to the William Crutchfield
            Business Records, 1848-1870)//EN" "vi00820" converted from
            EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-08">2014-01-08</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the William Crutchfield Business
         Records, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1870</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Barcode Numbers">1107270, 1107271, 1107276,
         1107280, 1107282, 1107284, 1107287, 1107288, 1107291, 1107304,
         1128725, 1128735-1128738</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">William Crutchfield Business Records,
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1848-1870</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers">1107270, 1107271, 1107276,
         1107280, 1107282, 1107284, 1107287, 1107288, 1107291, 1107304,
         1128725, 1128735-1128738</unitid>
      <physloc label="Physical Location">The Library of Virginia.
         Local Government Records Collection, Goochland
         County</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">15 volumes (Three
         daybooks are in poor condition due to missing covers and
         damaged spines. Two ledgers are in poor condition due to
         damaged spines. One account book is in poor condition due to
         torn spine)</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector">Goochland County</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>William Crutchfield Business Records, 1848-1870. Local
            government records collection, Goochland County Court
            Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These materials came to the Library of Virginia in
            shipments of court papers from Goochland County.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information</head>
      <p>William Crutchfield was a merchant who, on his own or in
         partnership with others, owned general stores in the towns of
         Rocketts, Cedar Point, and Merry Oaks in Goochland County,
         Virginia, during the mid- nineteenth century. He also perhaps
         owned a blacksmith shop in Cedar Point that was worked by
         blacksmith Olonzo C. Cantrell.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Six daybooks, four ledgers, three account books, one
         journal, and one statement book used to record the financial
         activities of several businesses owned by William Crutchfield
         of Goochland County, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Three daybooks, one dated December 1851-January 1853, the
         second dated September 1853-August 1855, and the third dated
         March 1857-February 1859, that record the daily transactions
         of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. Information found in
         entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items
         purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item,
         form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Entries
         correspond with entries with similar dates found in Account
         Book, 1849-1856, Journal 1851-1857, and Ledger, 1853-1858.</p>
      <p>Account book, 1849-1856, used as a ledger and a daybook at
         Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. The ledger portion of the
         volume records the accounts of individual customers. One set
         of accounts lists transactions in chronological order.
         Information found in each entry includes date of transaction,
         items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each
         item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid.
         Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs
         and butter. Entries for 1852 correspond with entries for 1852
         in Daybook, December 1851-January 1853. The second set of
         accounts in volume lists transactions in chronological order.
         Information found in each entry includes date of transaction,
         style of transaction, and amount owed and paid. Entries do not
         list the names of items purchased; rather, they use the
         general term "amount of bill." The daybook portion of the
         volume records the daily transactions of Crutchfield's store
         in Rocketts from August to October 1855. Information found in
         entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items
         purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item,
         form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Volume also
         records the payments of bonds by individuals and the store's
         controlling accounts, such as cash account and bills payable
         account. Volume includes an index that lists customers in
         alphabetical order and the page numbers where their accounts
         can be found.</p>
      <p>Journal, 1851-1857, and Ledger, 1853-1858, record the
         accounts of individual customers of Crutchfield's store in
         Rocketts. Transactions are listed in chronological order.
         Information found in each entry includes date of transaction,
         items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each
         item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid.
         Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs
         and leather. Entries in the journal and ledger correspond with
         entries found in Daybook, December 1851-January 1853, Daybook,
         September 1853-August 1855, daybook portion of Account Book,
         1849-1856, and Daybook, March 1857-February 1859. Ledger,
         1853-1858, also records the payments of bonds by individual
         and payments of bills by customers.</p>
      <p>Statement book, 1855-1858, records varying accounts of
         Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. One set of accounts include
         bond accounts of customers. It lists the name of individual,
         amount of bond, and whether individual paid or not. A separate
         listing for Negro accounts is included with an additional
         category for how well or how poorly the individual was in
         repaying his or her bond. A second set of accounts records the
         accounts of individual customers. Transactions are listed in
         chronological order. Information found in each entry includes
         date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items
         purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total
         amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter
         of items such as eggs and hogs. Entries for 1853-1855
         correspond with entries found in Daybook, September
         1853-August 1855.</p>
      <p>Account book, 1848-1864, used by Crutchfield as a ledger
         and a daybook. The ledger portion of the volume records the
         accounts of individual customers from 1848 to 1856 of
         Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. Transactions are listed in
         chronological order. Information found in each entry includes
         date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items
         purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total
         amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter
         of items such as eggs, butter, and beeswax. Volume includes
         inventories of the store's goods for December 1849 and October
         1854. Information found in each entry includes name of item,
         price of each item, and the total amount, both quantity and
         value, of each item. There is also an inventory of the store's
         goods at Cedar Point for April 1863. It simply lists the item
         and the total number of item. The daybook portion of the
         volume records the transactions of a warehouse or store owned
         by Crutchfield in Cedar Point from November 1863 to January
         1865. Transactions relate to the storage of goods by
         Crutchfield on behalf of individuals. Information found in
         entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items
         stored, quantity of items stored, cost for storing item, form
         of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Items stored
         include salt, flour, meat, tobacco, and furniture. Volume has
         two separate listings of Negro accounts. Each entry includes
         individual's name and amount owed to the store. Volume
         includes an index that lists customers in alphabetical order
         and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.</p>
      <p>Account book, 1857-1868, used as a ledger and a daybook.
         The ledger portion of the volume records the accounts of
         individual customers of Crutchfield's store in Merry Oaks in
         1857 and 1858. Transactions are listed in chronological order.
         Information found in each entry includes date of transaction,
         items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each
         item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid.
         Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as
         eggs, coonskin, and beef. Volume also records the payments of
         bonds owed the store by individuals. The daybook portion of
         the volume records the daily transactions of a store or
         warehouse owned by Crutchfield in Cedar Point from April 1865
         to August 1868. Transactions relate to the storage of goods by
         Crutchfield on behalf of individuals. Information found in
         entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items
         stored, quantity of items stored, cost of storing item, form
         of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Items stored
         include flour, guano, corn, salt, whiskey, safes, various size
         boxes, sugar, and meat. Volume includes an index that lists
         customers in alphabetical order and the page numbers where
         their accounts can be found.</p>
      <p>Three daybooks, one dated July 1866-June 1867, the second
         dated June 1867-June 1869, and the third dated July
         1869-January 1870, that record the daily transactions of
         Crutchfield's store in Cedar Point. Information found in
         entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items
         purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item,
         form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made
         by cash, credit, labor, and barter of items such as corn,
         eggs, and meal. The last few pages contain information related
         to the sale of items following Crutchfield's death. Entries in
         Daybook, July 1866-June 1867, and Daybook, June 1867-June
         1869, correspond with entries with similar dates found in
         Ledger, 1865-1869, and Ledger, 1869-1870.</p>
      <p>Two ledgers, one dated 1865-1869, and the second dated
         1869-1870, that recordss the accounts of individual customers
         of Crutchfield's store in Cedar Point. Transactions are listed
         in chronological order. Information found in each entry
         includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of
         items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total
         amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter
         of items such as oats, onion cloves, butter, and bacon.
         Entries in ledgers correspond with entries found in Daybook,
         July 1866-June 1867, Daybook, June 1867-June 1869, and
         Daybook, July 1869-January 1870. Ledger, 1865-1869, includes
         an index that lists customers in alphabetical order and the
         page numbers where their accounts can be found.</p>
      <p>Ledger, 1861-1868, used as a freight record book and
         blacksmith account book. Freight record portion of volume
         records expenses and cash received from transportion of
         merchandise by river for January-July 1861. Information found
         in expense accounts include date of transaction, type of
         expense, and amount paid. Expenses include labor costs, tolls,
         and quantity of merchandise transported. The cash received
         accounts record payments received from customers to cover
         transportation costs of merchandise incurred by store.
         Information found in entries include date of payment, name of
         customer, name of merchandise, and amount of payment received.
         The blacksmith portion of volume records the accounts of
         individual customers of a blacksmith shop from 1862 to 1868,
         perhaps located in Cedar Point. Transactions are listed in
         chronological order. Information found in each entry includes
         date of transaction, items purchased or services rendered,
         quantity of items purchased, cost of item or service, form of
         payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash
         and credit. Services rendered include shoeing horses and
         mules, sharpening farm tools, repairing saddles and wagons,
         and drilling holes in saws. Items sold include horseshoes,
         keys for yokes, chain links, bolts, and screws. An index is
         found at the end of blacksmith portion of volume that lists
         the blacksmith shop's customers in alphabetical order, the
         page numbers where their accounts can be found, and the total
         amount each customer owed.</p>
      <p>Items sold at Crutchfield's stores include dry goods,
         whiskey, food, herrings, candles, umbrellas, matches, candy,
         nails, clothing, knives, violin strings, cologne, scissors,
         dictionaries, soap, paper, coffee, spoons, shoes, and
         spices.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional loose records related to William Crutchfield's business activities can be found at the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 December-1853 January,
               268 p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 September-1855 August,
               644 p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 March-1859 February, 358
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866 July-1867 June, 433
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 June-1869 June, 689
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Daybook, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869 July-1870 January, 282
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853-1858, 622
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1868, 251
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865-1869, 180
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Ledger, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869-1870, 159
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Crutchfield and Nicholas Account Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1864, 445
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Account Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1856,
               672p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Account Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857-1868, 269
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Journal, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1857, 470
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Crutchfield Statement Book, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1858, 126
               p.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
