<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00790">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00790::A Guide to the Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-1912)//EN" "vi00790.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1758-1912</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-1912
<num type="collectionnumber">Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-001-1912-012
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2018 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 March 2018</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1758-1912</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-001-1912-012
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2018
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field processing and LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1758-1912
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-001-1912-012 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Charles City County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Charles City County  (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-1912. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Charles City County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Charles City County was named for King Charles I and was one of the original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. The county seat is Charles City. Part of James City County was added to Charles City in 1721.
</p>
    <p>Records have been destroyed at various times. The most damage occurred during the Civil War when the records were strewn through the woods in a rainstorm. A few pre-Civil War volumes such as deed books, will books, minute books, and order books exist.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Charles City County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1758-1912, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, division of enslaved people, freedom suits, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Charles City County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>
      <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.
</p>
 <p>For more information and a listing of lost records localities see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/guides/rn30_lostrecords.pdf">Lost Records research note</extref>.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
     </descgrp>
    
 <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1845-003: Ned, an enslaved person, etc. v. Admr. of George Moore, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom suit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1875-010: Edmund Waddill, trustee v. Rep of Richard M. Graves, etc. and 1883-003 Richard M. Graves, etc. v. John Wight and wife, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Both causes include the will of Mary Brown in which emancipates enslaved persons except old man John who wished to remain enlaved.  In one of her codicils, she rescinds the emancipation by stating that she emancipates only the enslaved people whop desire to be free. She gives Louisa and Mary and their children one month to decide. She wishes to send them to Liberia. The will enclosed in the 1875-010 cause omits an enslaved man named George.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1880-009: Johnson Jones v. Harriet Jones: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The parties were married prior to the Civil War. Johnson Jones was sold into enslavement in the South. After the Civil War, he returned to Charles City County to claim Harriet as his wife. She deserted the plaintiff and married Solomon Tyler and went with him to the City of Richmond, then Alabama and now Georgia-where they were living as man and wife.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1881-004: Thomas Barham, creditor v. Exx of Benjamin H. (Harrison) Harrison, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff resided in New Kent County. The defendants resided in City of Richmond and Cumberland counties. The widow of Benjamin H. Harrison noted in her answer that she had to flee her house during the Civil War. All the personal property left by her deceased husband was destroyed by the federal troops and all the enslaved people were freed shortly after his death in 1862. Her husband, a Confederate captain, fought in the Civil War. He died at the Battle of Malvern Hill.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1882-010: Board of Supervisors of County of Charles City v. Board of Overseers of the Poor of Charles City County, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause notes "the selling of the Glebe Lands" of the Parish of Westover and the formation of the Charles City Charity School. County's Overseers of the Poor will erect a poorhouse, workhouse and schoolhouse.   
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1883-004: Exr. of Hill Carter v. Lizzie H C Wickham, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause deals with Hill Carter's beloved estate, Shirley Plantation-includes mill pond and land in Henrico County. Sets up trust fund for his granddaughter, the main defendant in cause, who resides near the City of Richmond. Divides up the land and money between his sons and daughter but leaves the rest of his money and all stock in a trust fund for his granddaughter and administered by his son, plaintiff Robert R. Carter. At the age of 21, she was entitled to the remaining 1037.09.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1883-007: Henry Haxall, etc. v. Thomas Gant, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Clara Haxall in her will leaves enslaved people Rosalie and Betsy to her son, David Walker Haxall. The enslaved people were to be freed if David has passed away.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1885-006: Joseph A. Christian v. Malinda (Melinda) M. Christian:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff claimed defendant deserted him and his family and moved to Philadelphia ("She was from the North") and committed adultery. Defendant claimed that the plaintiff gave her a "secret and vile" disease and that she was forced to travel to different places for care and eventually moved North to Philadelphia for her health. Cause contains a record of a divorce suit from Philadelphia. Marriage license was destroyed during the Civil War. Defendant supported herself in Philadelphia by teaching music and canvassing.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
