<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi00511">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00511::A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, 1841-1865)//EN" "vi00511.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, <date>1841-1865</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Rives Family Papers, 1841-1865
<num type="collectionnumber">24065
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>7 June 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, <date>1841-1865</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">24065
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Rives Family Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1841-1865
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">24065
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">.1 cubic feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Rives Family
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Rives Family Papers, 1841-1865.  Accession 24065.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Purchased, 10 November 1953, from Elizabeth R. Snead, Scottsville, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Robert Rives (1798-1869) was born in Nelson County, Virginia, and attended the College of William and Mary, graduating in 1817. He represented Nelson County, Virginia, in the House of Delegates from 1823 to 1829. After his service in the House of Delegates, he moved to Albemarle County. Rives was one of the wealthiest men in Virginia before the Civil War began, but lost most of his fortune during the Civil War. He married Elizabeth Pannill (1811-1895), daughter of Samuel Pannhill of Campbell County, Virginia, in 1841, and they had one child, Cornelia E. Rives (1845-1910), who married Charles Carter Harrison (1842-1882) in 1866. Harrison served as a lieutenant in Company I, 46th Virginia Infantry, and after the Civil War was a prosperous farmer in Albemarle County.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1841-1865, of the Rives family of Albemarle County, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1848-1863, from Alfred T. Harris and Harris and Gibson of Richmond, Virginia, to Robert Rives concerning Rives' agricultural and stock interests, the sale of slaves, Rives' accounts, and a Union assault on Drewry's Bluff in 1862; letters, 1855-1862, from Samuel Nowlin of Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives discussing property Nowlin manages for Rives in Lynchburg; and letters, 1861-1864, from Charles C. Harrison of the 46th Virginia Infantry to Cornelia E. Rives concerning camp life, the Peninsular campaign, the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks), and his love for Cornelia. Papers also include letters, 1841-1864, to and from members of the Rives family concerning personal news, agricultural information, the stationing of cavalry Charlottesville, Virginia, and the wounding of Charles Harrison and letters, 1864, from Harrison to his sister Rosalie Harrison concerning camp life; and miscellaneous accounts and papers, 1865 and no date, of Cornelia E. Rives.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters and Accounts, Alfred T. Harris and Harris and Gibson to Robert Rives, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1848-1863.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account and letter, 
	<unitdate>23 May 1848, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, Virginia, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, Virginia, concerning the sale of Rives' tobacco and his bonds in the James River and Kanawha Company.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>15 July 1848, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' wheat and tobacco, whiskey for Rives, and dividends from the James River and Kanawha Company bonds.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account and letter, 
	<unitdate>5 August 1848, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' tobacco and wheat, noting the poor market for the latter.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>23 January 1849, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and noting that he has sent the blacksmith tools Rives ordered.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>21 July 1849, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and the market for wheat.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>11 August 1849, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating he has purchased state stock for Rives and commenting on the price of wheat.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>20 October 1849, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning a purchase of state stock for Rives and the sale of Rives' wheat.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>23 July 1850, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, sending items Rives purchased, as well as the stock Rives purchased in the James River and Kanawha Company, and commenting on the wheat market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>3 August 1850, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock bought for Rives, bacon shipped to Rives, and the sale of Rives' wheat crop.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>8 August 1851, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that he has bought state stock for Rives, and commenting on the wheat market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>1 December 1851, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concering a purchase of state stock for Rives and the sale of one of Rives' slaves.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account and letter, 
	<unitdate>4 August 1852, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' wheat, the purchase of state stock, and the shipping of two french bedsteads to Rives.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>17 January 1853, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' interest and dividends, state stock, and a shipment of sugar to Rives.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>1 July 1853, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and the wheat market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>30 June 1853, 
	</unitdate>of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>31 December 1853, 
	</unitdate>of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>3 July 1854, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' tobacco and a city certificate of debt.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>21 July 1854, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating they have received his certificate of deposit on the Bank of Virginia, and noting that there is cholera in Richmond.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>31 May 1855, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, regarding the purchase of state stock.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>31 December 1856, 
	</unitdate>of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson, along with letter, 2 January 1857, concerning his account.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>28 October 1857, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of state stock, money from the sale of Rives' wheat, and the current slave market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>6 November 1857, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' purchase of state stock and the wheat market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>21 May 1858, 
	</unitdate>of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson for sale of tobacco.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>4 February 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, regarding the purchase of state stock for Rives.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>8 July 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that Rives' interest and dividends will be collected and state stock purchased.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>12 July 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning his dividends on bank stock and interest from state stock, as well as purchase of state stock.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>3 August 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' check on the Bank of Scottsville for the purchase of state stock.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account and letter, 
	<unitdate>21 September 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of 57 bags of guano.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>6 February 1860, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' bonds in the James River and Kanawha Company, his dividends and interest, and the tobacco market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>9 March 1860, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the inspection and sale of Rives' tobacco in Richmond.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>25 July 1860, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, regarding the purchase of state stock for Rives, and the James River and Kanawha Company's unwillingness to pay interest on its bonds.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>30 July 1860, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of state stock and asking if Rives wants to convert his Jaems River and Kanawha bonds into state stock.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>7 December 1860, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the conversion of Rives' James River and Kanawha bonds into state stock, banks discounting, the dull stock market, and the downward turn of the tobacco and wheat markets.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>9 January 1861, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that he has collected Rives' dividends from the Bank of Virginia and the Farmers' Bank as well as his interest from state stock, and commenting on the possibility of civil war.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>16 May 1862, 
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, asking Rives to hold on to an envelope for him, commenting on Richmond during wartime, an attack by Union gunboats on Drewery's Bluff, the departure of civilians and wounded soldiers from Richmond, and news of Harris' son who took part in a fight at Giles Court House.  He also comments on the stock market.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>15 July 1863
	</unitdate>from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Richmond, stating that he has collected Rives' dividends and interest and placed them in the Bank of Virginia, sending a certificate.  Harris also sends news that the enemy had been repulsed at Jackson, Mississippi.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters, Samuel Nowlin to Robert Rives, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1855-1862.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>7 November 1855, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that C. Jordan, Rives' tenant on property in Lynchburg is moving out and promises to pay money owed.  Nowlin adds that he will fix up the property and rent it again.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>31 December 1855, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating he has distrained Jordan for the rent and adding what repairs he will make to the house.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>8 February 1856, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he has received the rent he distrained from Jordan and commenting on the needed repairs.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>31 March 1856
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, informing Rives of the death of his [Nowlin's] son.  Nowlin comments on a new door for the house and asking Rives to come look at the house.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>24 February 1857, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, concerning his efforts to find a renter for Rives' property and mentioning that someone was interested in purchasing it.  Nowlin adds that the house needs some repairs.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>9 May 1857, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he had received some back rent owed, but that it won't cover repairs, that a new tenant has moved in, and that a stone wall surrounding the lot has collapsed.  He comments about repairs to the wall.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>July 1857, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, concerning repairs to the stone wall on Rives' property.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>16 February 1858, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he has not found a new renter for the property.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>28 March 1862, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, sending a certificate of deposit, stating that the renter would like a reduced rent for the following year, and commenting on the condition of the house and yard.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters, Charles C. Harrison to Cornelia Rives, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1865.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, concerning life in camp, the lack of religion, and his love for Cornelia.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, commenting on the marching he has done, stating that he was elected first lieutenant of his company, and adding his thoughts of Cornelia sustain him.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>31 May 1862, 
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, describing the beginning of the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks), camp conditions, and professing his love for Cornelia.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>19 November 1862, 
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Richmond, concerning his love for Cornelia.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>5 October 1864, 
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, concerning his love for Cornelia.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters of the Rives Family, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1841-1865.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>7 April 1841, 
	</unitdate>from Robert Rives, Albemarle County, to Elizabeth Pannill, Campbell County, Virginia, sending personal news and professing his love for her.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>19 June 1852, 
	</unitdate>from Samuel Pannill, Campbell County, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, sending personal and local news, and commenting on the tobacco and wheat crops.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>12 December 1859, 
	</unitdate>from Elizabeth Pannill Rives, Albemarle County, to Cornelia E. Rives sending local, family, and personal news, and adding that she misses her.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>24 April 1861, 
	</unitdate>from Elizabeth Rives, Albemarle County, to Cornelia E. Rives sending local and family news, commenting on the preparations for war, and commenting on the people in Maryland.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>19[?] October 1863, 
	</unitdate>from C. Edward Rives, at the University of Virginia, to his cousin, possibly Cornelia E. Rives, sending social and personal news.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>13 February 1864, 
	</unitdate>from C. Edward Rives, University of Virginia, to his sister Eleanor Rosalie Rives sending personal and social news, and adding that the cavalry has been stationed in Charlottesville, Virginia.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>24 May 1864, 
	</unitdate>from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to his sister Rosalie Harrison providing general comments on the war and camp life, and stating he misses Cornelia Rives.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>1 June 1864, 
	</unitdate>Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to his sister Rosalie Harrison containing news on camp life and the regiment.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>no date, 
	</unitdate>from an unknown writer to Cornelia E. Rives stating that Charles C. Harrison had been slightly wounded and that Harrison was thinking of her.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Accounts and Miscellaneous Items of Cornelia E. Rives, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1865 and no date.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>1 December[?] 1865, 
	</unitdate>of Cornelia E. Rives with William N. Bell and Company, Richmond, for clothing items.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>13 December 1865, 
	</unitdate>of Cornelia E. Rives with William N. Bell and Company, Richmond, for clothing items.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>no date, 
	</unitdate>of Miss Rives with A. A. Housewright for clothing items and headwear.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>no date, 
	</unitdate>of Cornelia Rives with R. Ferrandin[?] for hair and makeup products.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Account, 
	<unitdate>no date, 
	</unitdate>of Miss Rives with E. V. A. Place[?] for clothing items.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Invitation, 
	<unitdate>24 June no year, 
	</unitdate>to attend the celebration of the Brookland and Piedmont Literary Societies at Brookland School.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>	
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
