<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi00991">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::00991::A Guide to the Records of the William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 1984-1990)//EN" "00991.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation,<date>1984-1990</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Leighty, William H.
<num type="collectionnumber">50129
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Roger Christman 
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2011  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Roger Christman, <date>12 September  2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Records of William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation,<date>1984-1990</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">50129
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Roger Christman 
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Roger Christman 
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Records of William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1984-1990
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">50129
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">3 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>


</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia Secretary of Transportation, William H. Leighty.  Records, 1984-1990.  Accession 50129.  State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>William H. Leighty, 2004 Millington Dr., Henrico, VA 23238, date of gift 3 June 2011; accessioned 12 September 2011.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>This collection has been processed using minimal processing standards:  the original arrangement has been maintained, the container list is brief and simple, and the records have not been refoldered and fasteners have not been removed.  
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>In 1986 Governor Gerald L. Baliles (1986-1990) named William H. Leighty Deputy Secretary of Transportation.  Leighty served as served as policy adviser to the Governor on transportation-related issues and oversaw operation of seven state agencies--Departments of Transportation, Aviation, Motor Vehicles, Emergency Services, Military Affairs, Fire Programs and Virginia Port Authority.  Leighty also served as Chief of Staff to Governors Mark R. Warner and Tim Kaine.
</p>

<p>The Commission on Virginia's Transportation in the Twenty-First Century was created by Senate Joint Resolution 10 of 1986 to study future needs and financing of transportation for the Commonwealth. The Commission was composed of six (6) house of Delegate member's appointed by the Speaker, four (4) Senate members appointed by the Committee on Privileges and Elections, fourteen (14) members at large appointed by the Governor and former Gorvernors of the Commonwealth.
</p>

<p>The Commission was authorized to carry out its work in two phases. The first phase required that the Commission determine the most critical transportation needs and determine what legal changes would be necessary to establish separate funds for highway maintenance and construction. The second phase required the Commission to study in detail alternatives for planning and financing the entire transportation system including rail, air and water transportation. The second phase was also charged with addressing the role of local government in financing various transportation projects and the discovery of alternative methods of raising funds such as tolls, dedicated revenues and transportation districts.
</p>

<p>Senate Joint Resolution Number 148 of 1987 further outlined phase two of the Commissions responsibilities. The Commission had four areas of specific concerns: (1) builder contributions to off-site road improvements; (2) development impact fees; (3) granting to local governments increased statutory authority to consider the capacity of local roads and other public facilities when rendering land use decisions such as rezoning; and (4) proposals to grant to local units of government expanded power to construct and control local roads.
</p>

<p>The Commission was charged with completing its first phase of work and submitting a report with recommendations to Governor and General Assembly no later than August 1, 1986. The first phase of the report served as the basis for action on transportation needs taken by the Special Session of the General Assembly on September of 1986. The second phase and report with recommendations had a scheduled completion date of December 1, 1987.
</p>

</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains Deputy Secretary William H. Leighty's briefing binders, memorandums, minutes and reports concerning transportation legislation and Governor Gerald Baliles' (1986-1990) Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century.  In September 1986 Governor Baliles convened a special session of the General Assembly that passed a 12-year, $12 billion transportation package to modernize the state's roads, seaports, airports, and mass transit, partially funded by a half cent increase in the sales tax. Additional records document the implementation of this legislation including a list of transporation week events in September 1987.  Also included are miscellaneous state government reform reports.
</p>

</scopecontent>


<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>I. Records, 1984-1990</item>
</list></arrangement>


<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">I. Records</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1984-1990</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container type="box" label="Boxes">1-3
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 3 cubic feet (3 boxes).</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Original order maintained</p>
</scopecontent>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Briefing Binder on Senate Bill 79 (1986),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">1
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Briefing Binder on Transportation Special Session of the General Assembly,       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">September 1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">1
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Bill Book (Transportation Special Session Legislation),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">1
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (reports, memorandums, memorandums,       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1985-1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">2
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (strategic implementation binder),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">2
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Transportation Commission Briefing Manual for Members of the General Assembly (Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1 August 1986</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">2
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Transportation Commission Briefing Manual for Members of the General Assembly (Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">December 1987</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">2
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (Phase II),       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1987</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">1
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>


 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Briefing Book, Transportation Week,       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">September 1987</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">1
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>


 		<c02 level="file">
 		<did>
	 	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Reports and Documents,       
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1984-1990</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
 		<container label="Box" type="box">3
 		</container>
 		</did>
 		</c02>

</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>