<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00539">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::vi::vi00539::A Guide to the Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian,  CETA Files, 1978-1983//EN" "vi00539.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, CETA Files, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1983</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Library, Virginia State, Office of the State Librarian,  CETA Files, 1978-1983
<num type="collectionnumber">44535
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Joanne Porter
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Marc Word, created by J Porter, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 July 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian,  CETA Files, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1983</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44535
</num></subtitle>
      <author>J. Porter
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>J. Porter
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia State Library, Office of the State Librarian, CETA Files, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1983
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44535
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.35 cu. ft., 
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia State Library
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no use restrictions. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Virginia State Library, CETA Files, Accession 44535.  State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>No acquisition information is available.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>For many years, the Library of Virginia had no definitive home.  Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end.  By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond.</p>
      <p>Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson.  The Bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use.  Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.</p>
      <p>The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE.  From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council.  In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration.  Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856.  The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.</p>
      <p>The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic.  Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856.  Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development.  General W. H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles."  At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters.</p>
      <p>Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers.  The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education.  The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.</p>
      <p>While many public records somehow survived the Commonswealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence.  When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them."  The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.</p>
      <p>The new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections.  Ground was broken for the current facility on December 7, 1938.  At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.</p>
      <p> The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia state Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose today.  In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to the Library of Virginia.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains memorandums, correspondence, and reports describing the library's administering of the employment program known as CETA or the Federal Comprehensive Employment and Training Act.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>Series I. CETA Files, 1978-1983</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. CETA Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1978-1983</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Boxes" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: .35 cu. ft. </extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> This series gives a brief look at the Virginia State Lib ray's participation in the federal jobs training program known as CETA or the Comprehensive Employment and Training Act.  These records offer correspondence and memorandum highlighting information regarding the program and correspondence between staff from the Library, the U.S. Department of Labor and the Virginia Employment Commission.</p>
          <p> There is information concerning the implementation of affirmative action requirements, accessibility issues for handicapped individuals participating in the CETA program and there are a few copies of the Virginia Employment Commission Newsletter entitled Update, CETA Balance of the State. There are audit and financial compliance reports detailing payroll, time and attendance of participates and budgetary statements giving budgetary amounts and expenditures.  The correspondence consists of communications between library staff and CETA regional officials regarding program and training implementation offered by the staff of the library.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>This series is arranged alphabetically.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Affirmative Action/CETA BOS Packet, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Audit Financial Reports, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>CETA Proposal, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1981-1983.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Circuit Court Retention Schedules, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1983.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newsletters and Brochures, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Regulations, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
