<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00076">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00076::A Guide to the Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayers lists of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1850-1852)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00076.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00076::A Guide to the Delinquent
             Free Negro Taxpayers lists of the Auditor of Public
             Accounts, 1850-1852)//EN" "vi00076.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayers
            Lists of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1852</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayers Lists
            of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1850-1852, A Guide to
            the 
            <num type="collectionnumber">APA 413</num></subtitle>
        <author>Description Services Staff</author>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">2 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         record. Created by Paige Neal 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 February 2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 14, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00076::A Guide to the Delinquent Free Negro
            Taxpayers lists of the Auditor of Public Accounts,
            1850-1852)//EN" "vi00076.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-08">2014-01-08</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayers
         Lists of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1852</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">APA 413</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Library of Virginia Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayers Lists
         of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1850-1852</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">APA 413</unitid>
      <physloc label="Physical Location">State Records Collection,
         Auditor of Public Accounts (Record Group 48)</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2 inches</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts, Delinquent Free
            Negro Taxpayers Lists, 1850-1852. Accession APA 413, State
            Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond,
            Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Transferred from the Office of the Auditor of Public
            Accounts in 1913.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Although the colonial government had appointed auditors
         general from time to time, the office was not established on a
         permanent basis until after independence was declared. At its
         first session, which convened on 7 October 1776, the General
         Assembly passed an act creating a board of three auditors to
         examine and settle claims concerning receipts and expenditures
         for military purposes. The confusing financial situation of
         the state, however, resulted in a series of acts being passed
         over the next fifteen years elaborating and refining the
         duties of the auditors. Finally, at its session begun in
         November 1791, the General Assembly passed an act that
         combined the duties of the board of auditors and the solicitor
         general, whose office had been created in 1785 to settle the
         accounts of the state with the United States, and assigned
         them to a single auditor of public accounts effective 1
         January 1792. The auditor soon became the most powerful fiscal
         officer in the state. All receipts and disbursements were made
         only upon his warrant to the treasurer, and his books were the
         standard against which those of the treasurer were
         checked.</p>
      <bioghist>
        <p>The first changes were made as the accounts of the
            revolutionary era were settled. As the state moved into a
            period of steady financial and governmental growth in the
            nineteenth century, the number of accounts and funds
            maintained by the auditor became excessive. Thus, on 24
            February 1823 the General Assembly passed an act creating
            the office of the second auditor to ease the auditor's
            burden. Although the second auditor handled several large
            special funds, the auditor continued to be responsible for
            most of the accounts concerning the daily operation of
            state government.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist>
        <p>During the Civil War both the state government and the
            pro-Union Restored Government of Virginia, which was based
            first in Wheeling and then in Alexandria, had auditors of
            public accounts. After the war, near the end of
            Reconstruction, the military authorities appointed Major
            Thaddeus H. Stanton, of the United States Army, as auditor
            of public accounts. Stanton was paid by the state during
            his service from 3 April 1869 to 12 February 1870, although
            he remained an army officer. The position was returned to
            civilian control on 12 February 1870 with the election of
            William F. Taylor as auditor by the General Assembly.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist>
        <p>Following the Civil War the complexities of an
            increasingly sophisticated financial world threatened to
            overwhelm the state fiscal offices, which had changed their
            practices but little since the end of the eighteenth
            century. Inadequate bookkeeping procedures and
            embezzlements of state funds resulted in a public demand
            for corrective action. It was not until a state government
            reorganization act was passed by the General Assembly on 18
            April 1927, however, that the demand was satisfied.
            Effective 1 March 1928 the office of auditor of public
            accounts and second auditor were abolished and replaced by
            the office of comptroller--head of the Department of
            Accounts--to monitor the receipt and disbursement of state
            funds, and a new office of auditor of public accounts,
            under the General Assembly, to audit state and local
            government agencies.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist>
        <p>The records of the first auditor of public accounts have
            not survived intact; periodically they have been subjected
            to disarrangement or destruction. When the auditor's office
            was created in 1776, Virginia's seat of government was in
            Williamsburg. In 1780, when the capital was moved to
            Richmond, the auditors and their records also moved. At
            this time, and during Benedict Arnold's raid on Richmond in
            1781, some auditor's records were misplaced or destroyed.
            During the War of 1812, when it was believed that British
            troops were marching on Richmond, the state's records were
            loaded onto wagons and hauled to the James River for
            transportation upstream. Before the boats sailed, however,
            the alarm proved false and the records were unloaded and
            returned to the State Capitol.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist>
        <p>The next threat to the auditor's records came on the
            night of 2-3 April 1865, when the evacuation fire broke out
            as the Confederate garrison abandoned the city.
            Fortunately, the auditor's records escaped the flames
            because they were stored in the basement and attic of the
            State Capitol, which did not burn. Following the capture of
            Richmond by Union troops, however, a detachment of the
            Twentieth New York Infantry Regiment served as a guard in
            the Capitol building and browsed through the records of the
            state's fiscal offices (sometimes recording candid opinions
            concerning the late Confederacy in the margins of ledgers
            and journals). After the state library building was
            completed on the east side of Capitol Square in the late
            1890's the auditor's office moved into it and the older
            records were stored in the basement. There they remained
            until 1913, when they were transferred to the custody of
            the state library.</p>
      </bioghist>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This series contains lists of free blacks returned by sheriffs as delinquent in the payment of their capitation tax. Lists include the name of the delinquent taxpayer, amount of tax owed, and may also include remarks (moved, dead, over age, etc.).  In some instances local courts had ordered the delinquents hired out in lieu of paying the tax, and lists of those who were not hired are also included.  For several localities, only the wrapper with amounty of total delinquent tax is included and these are noted in the contents list.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Lists are arranged chronologically by tax year, and
         alphabetically by locality thereunder.</p>
    </arrangement>

<dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>



      

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Delinquent Free Negro Taxpayer Lists</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1850-1852</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>


</did>


  <c02 level="series">
	<did>
	<unittitle>1850</unittitle>

	</did>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Accomack County (wrapper only), 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
            </did>
          </c03>







</c02>
</c01>





</dsc>

  </archdesc>
</ead>
