<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00493">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00493::A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1845-1865)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00493.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00493::A Guide to the Tredegar
             Iron Works Records, 1845-1865)//EN" "vi00493.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845-1865</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1845-1865 
            <num type="collectionnumber">25744</num></subtitle>
        <author>Renee M. Savits</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2003 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">5 KB</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Marc
         record. Created by Renee M. Savits 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 February 2004</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 14, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00493::A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works
            Records, 1845-1865)//EN" "vi00493.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-08">2014-01-08</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845-1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">25744</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Renee M. Savits</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Tredegar Iron Works Records, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1845-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">25744</unitid>
      <physloc label="Physical Location">Business Records
         Collection, Acc. 25744</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.25 cu. ft.,
         negative photostats</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Tredegar Iron Works. Records, 1845-1865. Accession
            25744, Business records collection, The Library of
            Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Lent for copying by D.G. Hasse, Richmond, Virginia,
            through the Virginia Civil War Commission, Richmond,
            Virginia, 1962 and 1963.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Tredegar Iron Works was chartered in 1837 in Richmond,
         Virginia, to produce high-quality iron products. In 1848
         Joseph R. Anderson purchased the company and developed it into
         one of the most important and largest iron making factories in
         Virginia and the Confederacy. The company produced horseshoes,
         munitions, and railroad products, along with owning several
         furnaces and timber lots. During the Civil War, Tredegar
         produced artillery pieces, cannons, shot, and weapons for the
         Confederacy, including the iron plates for the CSS Virginia
         (Merrimac). After the war the company continued to grow and
         supplied iron bridges, rails, and spikes to rebuild the
         southern railroads.</p>
      <p>As iron gave way to steel in the 1870s and 1880s, Tredegar
         found it did not have the capital necessary to make the
         production conversion. Tredegar continued to make iron
         products, producing munition for the Spanish American War,
         World War I, and World War II. Spikes, horseshoes, rail
         fastenings, and car wheels were constant sellers and led to
         expanded facilities. In 1957 the company sold its Richmond
         plant to the Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company, and moved
         some of its rolling mill equipment to Chesterfield County,
         Virginia. In 1986 operation of the rolling mill in
         Chesterfield County was discontinued and the machinery was
         sold to the Cleveland Track Material in Cleveland, Ohio. In
         2003 the Tredegar National Civil War Center Foundation was
         created to operate a museum on the original site of the
         foundry in Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Joseph Reid Anderson (1813-1892), was the youngest of nine
         children of William and Anna Thomas Anderson of Botetourt
         County, Virginia. He graduated West Point in 1836 and worked
         as an engineer in Virginia. He married Sally Archer in 1837,
         daughter of Dr. Robert and Frances Williamson Archer. By 1841,
         he had acquired an interest in the Tredegar Iron Works in
         Richmond which supplied iron products to railroads and the
         U.S. government, and he became owner of the company in 1848.
         When the South seceded, Anderson offered his services to the
         Confederate Government as an infantry officer and was
         commissioned a brigadier-general in September 1861, serving
         meritoriously in North Carolina and Virginia. After being
         wounded at the battle of Frazier's Farm in 1862, Anderson
         resigned in mid-July to return to Tredegar Iron Works where
         his talent was needed more than on the battlefield. The
         company operated throughout the war, but after the surrender
         of Richmond, the U.S. government confiscated Tredegar Iron
         Works. Upon Anderson's request to President Johnson for a
         pardon in the fall of 1865, the Works were returned to him.
         Anderson continued to head Tredegar Iron Works and remained
         active in state, city, and local affairs until his death in
         1892.</p>
      <p>Archer Anderson (1838-1919), eldest of twelve children of
         Joseph Reid and Sally Anderson, was born in Ft. Monroe,
         Virginia. He served as chief of staff to General Joseph E.
         Johnston during the Civil War and married Mary Anne Mason,
         daughter of John Young Mason, in 1859. He was president of
         Tredegar Iron Works from 1892 to 1918. Archer Anderson, Jr.
         (1866-1942), third of seven children of Archer and Mary Anne
         Anderson, was born in Richmond, Virginia. He served as
         president of Tredeger Iron Works from 1918, until his death in
         1942.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Records, 1845-1865, of the Tredegar Iron Works, including
         correspondence, receipts, promissory notes, suit papers,
         insurance policies, and price lists, mainly relating to the
         companies work during the Civil War. These records include
         information on munitions Tredegar sold pre-Civil War to the
         United States government and to the Confederate government
         during the Civil War, operation of Tredegar furnaces, general
         operations of the factory, and slave labor.</p>
      <p>Includes orders for munitions from Ft. Monroe Arsenal,
         1845; copy of an insurance policy from the Virginia Fire and
         Marine Insurance Co., 11 September 1850; inspection notices of
         munitions, 26 November 1856; an order from the United States
         government for munitions, 1857 November; letter to John F.
         Tanner, from his son W.E. Tanner, 16 March 1861, regarding a
         trip to Cuba to sell rails; a passport for John F. Tanner from
         Cuba, 1862; and a copy of a suit, Confederate States of
         America vs. Joseph R. Anderson and Company, 12 November 1862,
         regarding money Anderson owed to a northern company, but which
         under an act by the Confederate government, would be
         confiscated by the government.</p>
      <p>Also includes an agreement, 1862, between Tredegar and
         George W. Randolph, Secretary of War for the Confederate
         States of America; a listing of amounts due for slaves and
         laborers hired, 1 April 1862; letter, 17 September 1863, from
         J.A. Campbell, Confederate States of America War Department,
         authorizing Tredegar to purchase grain, beef, and other
         supplies for Tredegar; receipt, 24 November 1863, for an
         advertisement to hire slaves at Tredegar; promissory notes,
         January 1864, for the hire of a slaves to work at Tredegar;
         correspondence regarding the blast furnaces, 1864 April 28,
         from Joseph R. Anderson; and a proposed price list for
         Tredegar, 1 January 1864.</p>
      <p>These materials were received from W.F. Hasse, whose father
         had worked for Tredegar.</p>
      <p>Many of these records are duplicates of originals which may
         be found in the main collection of Tredegar Iron Works
         Records, 1801-1957 (acc. 23881, 24808).</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
