<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vi00186">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00186::A Guide to the Graves Family Papers, 1731-1863)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00186.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00186::A Guide to the Graves
             Family Papers, 1731-1863)//EN" "vi00186.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Graves Family Papers, 
            <date>1731-1863</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Graves Family Papers, 1731-1863 
            <num type="collectionnumber">20563</num></subtitle>
            <author>Trenton Hizer</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>The Library of Virginia</addressline>
               <addressline>800 East Broad Street</addressline>
               <addressline>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archdesk@lva.lib.va.us
               (Archives)</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">6 KB</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         record. Created by Miriam B. Spectre, 
         <date>28 February 2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00186::A Guide to the Graves Family Papers,
            1731-1863)//EN" "vi00186.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Graves Family Papers, 
         <date>1731-1863</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">20563</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Trenton Hizer</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Graves Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1731-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Accession number">20563</unitid>
         <physloc label="Physical Location">Personal Papers Collection,
         Acc. 20563</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">57
         items.</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Graves Family Papers, 1731-1863. Accession 20563,
            Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia,
            Richmond, Virginia.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Gift of Mrs. William Butler Bonham, Gordonsville,
            Virginia, 23 March 1933.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>The Graves family was among the earliest settlers of what
         is now Madison County, Virginia. Captain Thomas Graves first
         settled there about. 1732 and built the family home, "Spring
         Hill," near the present community of Graves' Mill. Asa W.
         Graves (d. 1840) served as postmaster.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>Papers, 1731-1863, of the Graves family of Madison County,
         Virginia, consisting of: deeds for property in Madison County,
         Virginia, including when it was part of Spotsylvania, Orange
         and Culpeper Counties, Virginia, as well as deeds for property
         in Rockingham and Shenandoah Counties, Virginia, and in
         Arkansas; land grants for land in Spotsylvania and Culpeper
         Counties, and in Arkansas; receipts for the purchase of land
         and for the purchase of slaves; receipts for bank deposits;
         receipts for tuition for school; surveys and plats for tracts
         in Madison, Culpeper, Orange, and Spotsylvania Counties;
         correspondence concerning land in Arkansas, the price of
         tobacco, and the Virginia General Assembly; slave deeds of
         sales, including the names of the slaves purchased; lists
         containing the names, ages, and value of slaves owned by
         various members of the Graves family; militia roster of
         Captain Francis E. Graves' Company, 82nd Regiment, Virginia
         militia; business accounts; accounts for the estate of Asa W.
         Graves; accounts and costs for Sarah Graves in regard to the
         suit Lindsay and wife vs. Sarah Graves; and miscellaneous
         notes.</p>
         <p>1) Land grant, 26 June 1731, 400 acres in Spotsylvania
         County, Virginia, from Governor William Gooch to Thomas
         Stanton of Spotsylvania County; 2) deed, 24 March 1747, land
         in Orange County, Virginia, from Henry Downs, Sr., to Richard
         Downs, both of Orange County; 3) bond and deed, 8 October
         1759, from Joseph Edens and Thomas Graves, both of Culpeper
         County, Virginia, to John Buckner, Samuel Buckner, and Mary
         Buckner for 2 tracts of land in Culpeper County; 4) deed, 2
         May 1760, 601 acres in Culpeper County from Thomas and Sarah
         Graves to Joseph Edens; 5) deed, 6 February 1762, 160 acres in
         Culpeper County from William and Ann Stowers of Culpeper
         County to Thomas Graves; 6) deed, 16 February 1781, 51 acres
         in Culpeper County from Michael and Mary Snyder to Edward
         Graves, all of Culpeper County; 7) deed, 1 March 1791, 100
         acres in Culpeper County from John and Sarah Crigler of
         Culpeper County to Edward Graves; 8) deed (incomplete), n.d.,
         50 acres in Madison County, Virginia, from Adam and Milly
         Snyder to George Bailey, all of Madison County; 9) deed, 26
         June 1806, 2 acres in Madison County from Paschal Early and
         others to Thomas Graves, Sr., Joseph Eddins, and others
         representing the Baptist Rapidan Meeting House; 10) bond,
         April 1808, from Asa Graves to Thomas Graves, Sr., with
         condition for Asa Graves receiving 639 acres in Madison
         County; 11) Deed, 20 December 1808, 639 1/2 acres in Madison
         County from Thomas Graves, Sr., to Asa Graves; and 12) deed, 6
         October 1815, tracts of land in Rockingham and Shenandoah
         Counties, Virginia, from James Clerk, executor of Thomas
         Graves, Sr., to Benjamin Graves, Thomas Graves, and Asa
         Graves.</p>
         <p>13) Deed, 20 January 1826, 160 acres in the Arkansas
         Territory from Reuben Berry and others to Asa Graves, all of
         Madison County; 14) Military bounty land grant, 17 January
         1825, 160 acres in the Arkansas Territory to Reuben Berry and
         other heirs of Philemon Berry; 15) copy of deed, 5 June 1795,
         land in Madison County from Adam Banks to John Graves; 16)
         receipt, 7 August 1819, from Asa W. Graves to William
         Thornton; 17) survey, 16 April 1835, 30 acres of land in
         Madison County for Asa W. Graves; 18) Memorandum, n.d.,
         concerning the rights of Sarah Graves, widow, and her deceased
         husband's estate; 19) plat and survey, 1 May 1756, of 280
         acres in Culpeper County by Zachary Taylor by order of the
         General Court in Thomas Morris and others vs Buckner and
         others; 20) survey notes, 1749, of properties in Culpeper
         County, incomplete; 21) Survey, 14 and 15 April 1803, tracts
         of land owned in Madison County by Thomas Graves, Sr.,
         (incomplete) 22) survey, 31 August 1840, of land in Madison
         County formerly owned by Asa W. Graves, deceased; 23) fragment
         of plat, n.d., of 644 acres for Thomas Graves, Sr.; 24)
         copies, n.d., of surveys made of property conveyed first by
         Isaac Smith to Benjamin Smith, 18 September 1754, and second
         by Benjamin Smith to Adam Banks, 19 October 1778; 25) survey,
         12 August 1819, of 268 1/4 acres in Madison County owned by
         Asa W. Graves; 26) copy, 15 December 1825, of a survey, 14 and
         15 April 1803, of 639 acres in Madison County owned by Thomas
         Graves, Sr.; 27) receipt, 5 January 1826, for $420 from Joel
         S. Graves to Asa W. Graves for the sale of a slave; and 28)
         receipt, 22 April 1826, for $10 from Morgan Sisk to Asa W.
         Graves for his profit from sale of land.</p>
         <p>29) Receipts, March-April 1826, for $10 each from Rhodes
         Berry, John C. Sisk, Rowland Berry, and Susannah Berry to Asa
         W. Graves for their profits from sale of land; 30) deed of
         sale, 27 September 1804, for four slaves sold by John Hisle to
         James Pulliam, both of Culpeper County, for $1000; 31) deed of
         sale, 1 October 1804, for three slaves sold by James Pulliam
         to Asa W. Graves for 190 pounds; 32) deed of sale, 23 October
         1815, for one slaves sold by John and Elizabeth Sampson to
         John Glassell, all of Madison County, for $400; 33) bond and
         condition, 10 January 1833, from Lewis T. Cropp of Rockingham
         County to Asa W. Graves for property in Page County, Virginia;
         34) deed of sale, 13 February 1816, for one slave sold by
         Simeon Graves of Orange County, Virginia, to Asa W. Graves for
         $550; 35) deed of sale, 11 November 1816, for two slaves sold
         by James Booker of Shenandoah County to Asa W. Graves for
         $600; 36) deed, 20 August 1831, for a tract of land in Madison
         County from Adam Snyder to John Keister, both of Pendleton
         County, (West) Virginia; 37) receipt, 27 August 1863[?], from
         Joseph B. Willis to Francis E. Graves; 38) deposit slip, 7
         February 1863, for $7914.70 deposited by Francis E. Graves in
         the Farmers Bank of Virginia; 39) receipt, 25 January 1854,
         for $12 from William A. Banks to Francis E. Graves for George
         M. Bohannon for payment of tuition for Bohannon's son; 40)
         order and receipt, 31 March and 7 April 1863, for sugar from
         Clark and Mayo of Knoxville, Tennessee; 41) letter, 7 April
         1835, from Joseph Watson of the General Land Office to Asa W.
         Graves concerning taxes on Graves' land in Arkansas; and 42)
         letter, 2 March 1839, from James Whitcomb of the General Land
         Office to Linn Banks and letter, 2 March 1839, from Banks to
         Asa W. Graves concerning Graves' land in Arkansas.</p>
         <p>43) Letter, 17 March 1837, from Linn Banks to Asa W. Graves
         concerning property Graves owns, the price of tobacco in
         Richmond, Virginia, and the session of the General Assembly;
         44) Land Office Treasury Warrant, 2 January 1830, to James
         Clark for 200 acres, includes Clark's transfer of that acreage
         to others; 45) letter, 19 January 1825, enclosing patent for
         military bounty land in the Arkansas Territory for Reuben
         Berry from George Graham of the General Land Office; 46)
         letter, 24 August 1825, enclosing patent for military bounty
         land in the Arkansas Territory for Reuben Berry from the
         General Land Office; 47) Roster, 1858, of Captain Francis E.
         Graves' Company, 82nd Regiment, Virginia militia; 48) accounts
         of sale, n.d.; 49) account and receipt, 17 May 1847, for
         $243.89 from Sarah Graves to pay court costs in Lindsay and
         wife vs Graves and others; 50-51) account, 1845-1848, of Sarah
         Graves with Angus R. Blakey for legal costs in Lindsay and
         wife vs. Graves; 52-53) list, n.d., apparently of slaves
         received by various members of the Graves family possibly from
         the estate of Asa W. Graves and includes value; 54) account,
         19 December 1843, of the estate of Asa W. Graves, including
         list of slaves with ages and value; 55) list, n.d., of slaves,
         including ages and value, belonging to Francis E. Graves and
         Sarah Graves; 56) account, 1863-1864, of Strickler and Graves
         with Moore, Payne and Company; and 57) account, 1863, of sale
         of slaves for Francis E. Graves as attorney for the legatees
         of Asa W. Graves by Hill, Dickinson and Company.</p>
      </scopecontent>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
