<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi00762">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00762::A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1899)//EN" "vi00762.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782-1899</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1899
<num type="collectionnumber">Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-001-1899-030
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2018 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 November 2018</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782-1899</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-001-1899-030
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2018
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Louise Jones
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782-1899
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-001-1899-030 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Greensville County  (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
<p>Greensville County  (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1900-1913 are available in original format at the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1899. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Greensville County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780. The county court first met on 22 February 1781. Subsequent additions were made from Brunswick (1787) and Sussex (1802) Counties. The county courthouse is in the city of Emporia.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Greensville County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1899, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
     </descgrp>
    
 <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Causes of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1819-002: Joseph G. Wall vs. Andrea Rhea etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Joseph G. Wall was sent to the University at Chapel Hill in North Carolina in 1806. One of the teachers, Andrew Rhea was in charge of Joseph's tuition and expenses. The accounts of what Joseph C. Wall were messed up and Andrew Rhea sued in Greensville County to receive payment for Joseph's debts. Joseph disagreed with the outcome of Mr. Rhea's suit. There are receipts and accounts of Joseph's expenditures filed with the cause.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1823-004: Overseers of the Poor vs. heirs of Nathaniel Mabry, Sr.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Nathaniel freed Cate in his will and said his estate would support her. The Overseers claim that Nathaniel's heirs have failed to comply with the will and are suing for repayment of Cate's support. A copy of the bill for Cate's support is included with this cause.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1828-005: Nancy Sturdivant etc. vs. Admr. of Nathaniel Peebles, etc.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>George Rives first loaned and then gave his daughter Anne Peebles an enslaved child named Liddia (Lydia) and after Anne died her daughter Winnifred was to inherit Liddia.  Winnifred Shelton and her husband James had died and their children wanted to receive Liddia and her descendants. The answers and depositions contain information about Liddia and her descendants and also about George Rives' descendants.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1835-002: Dolley Fielding, widow, etc. vs. Thomas Davis etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ensign Thomas Davis served in the Continental Army in the Revolutionary War. He died in 1778. He was entitled to a Bounty Land Warrant for 2666 1/3 acres. The bounty warrant was issued in the name of Thomas and John Davis, the sons of Ensign Thomas Davis' eldest brother. The scrip was sold and the children of Ensign Davis' other siblings want their part of the proceeds of the sale.    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1837-001: Exr. of John Avery vs. Ann Avery etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Mr. Avery was a co-partner in a business to buy "blood horses" in England with A. T. Merritt and William H. E. Merritt. The partners hoped to raise horses to compete in races. On one occasion, Mr. Avery went to England and bought one horse and three mares and had them shipped to the United States. He failed to insure the horse completely.  Unfortunately, the horses were lost at sea and the business suffered. Mr. Avery was a co-partner in other ventures to buy horses in England. The answers of William H. D. Merritt, A. T. B. Merritt, and William and Edward Townes give the information about all the ventures involving Mr. Avery. This suit was an attempt to determine the value of Mr. Avery's partnership in these ventures so that the money from his part could be used to pay his bills.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1837-003: John D. Maclin and wife vs. Exr. of Theophilus Field: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>One of the exhibits is an Account Current recorded Feb. 28, 1831. The May 25, 1829 entry states that the following enslaved people Griffin, Easter, Kenny and Julia, belonging to the estate were sold in New Orleans. Additional enslaved names are found in this Chancery Cause.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1840-001: William Dunn vs Comt. of James Blanks, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> A copy of James Blanks' will recorded in 1829 is included in this cause. Mr. Blanks' left his property to Molly Wickham, a "free person of color" and her children and grandchildren.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1840-005: Robert Murrell, etc. vs. Becky Stewart, alias Becky Dimry, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Viney G. Stewart, a "free person of color," inherited 50 acres of land in Greensville County from her mother, Cressy Stewart. Viney moved to Ohio and died there in 1825. Her sisters Salley, widow of Britton Jones, and Nancy, wife of Anthony Banks; and her brother Peyton Stewart also moved to Ohio. Her brother, Henry lived in Brunswick County.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1847-020: James Brown vs Laura Brown by etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Laura Brown is James Brown's daughter. Laura owns an enslaved woman named Patsy, and Laura's father fears that Patsy is trying to poison the family. Mr. Brown asked permission to sell Patsy.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>

<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1848-003: Gdn(s) of Elizabeth Bailey etc. vs. Elizabeth Baileyand others by etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Elizabeth, Frances and Mary M. Bailey, the children of Zadoc M. Baily, deceased, owned an enslaved person named Davy. Davy was emancipated in the will of Nancy Cain. She wanted Davy, his wife, and eight children to be sent to Africa. The executor of Nancy Cain's will is willing to buy Davy and send the family to Africa.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1849-012: Admr. of Richard Hill, etc vs. Curator of William Hill, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Henry Hill left his wife, Elizabeth enslaved people and follwing her death they and their issues were to be freed. The bill of complaint lists the children of the emancipated slaves that were not freed. It also list enslaved people that were to be freed who were sold. This cause was an attempt to emancipate the enslaved people.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1853-011: Gdn. of Edmund M. Vick, etc. vs. Edmund W. Vick and others by etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Hubbard Vick died leaving two minor children Edmund M. and Alatanta Vick. Mr. Vick received a Land Warrant Number 46,811, for 80 acres, dated December 23, 1852, from the Commissioner of Pensions of the United States. The land was granted under the Act of Congress passed September 1, 1850 in an act granting bounty land to certain officers and soldiers who have been engages in the military service of the United States. This land warrant was given for Mr. Vick's service in the War of 1812 as a Private in Captain Pescud's Company of Virginia Militia. The guardian, Thomas J. Garner, felt it would be too expensive to go through the process of getting the bounty land which was located in Arkansas, Illinois and Missouri. As a result, he asked permission of the court to sell the Bounty Land Warrant.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1857-009: Exr. of Rebecca Hardaway vs. James Johnson and wife, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rebecca Hardaway was the widow of Captain Littleberry Mason and received a pension for his service in the Revolutionary War. The suit was to determine if her two living children should receive her final payment or if her grandchildren, the children of her deceased children, were to receive a share. Mrs. Hardaway died in Sussex County.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1862-002: Gdn of John H. Murfee vs. John H. Murfee, by etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mrs. Elizabeth B. Murfee is the mother and guardian of her son John H. Murfee. John owns an enslaved girl name Cherry who fled from Southampton County (or Northampton County) in an attempt to get to the United States Army in Nansemond County. Cherry was apprehended and was in the Greensville County Jail in September 1862. Mrs. Murfee obtained permission to sell Cherry in Richmond. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1863-006: Gdn. of James D. F. Brown etc. vs. James D. F. Brown and others by etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> James D. F. and Mary L. H. Brown are the orphans of James Brown. Their enslaved man, Dick wants to join the public enemy. Henry T. Jarratt, the children's guardian wants to sell Dick.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1864-001: Rebecca Morriss vs. children of William T. Person, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rebecca Morriss, the orphan children of William T. Person and Virginia A. Clarke, orphan of Thomas M. Clarke own an enslaved man named George in common. George ran away and nearly escaped to the Enemy. Rebecca Morriss is asking permission to sell George.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1866-001: George Nave vs. Sarah Nave:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce cause. Defendant had an affair while plaintiff served in the Confederate army.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-002: Dorothy Flythe, widow, etc. vs. Admr. of Solomon Flythe.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause started in 1864. Condis (Candis), her child and Lewis, were enslaved to Solomon Flythe. They escaped with other self-liberated people to North Carolina where they were apprehended. They were arrested in a camp in North Carolina while in the possession of the public enemy. It was reported that Condis' young child was accidently killed at the time the enslaved people were arrested. It was decided that it would be unsafe to retain Condis and Lewis so near the enemy's lines in Greensville County, so it was decided that they should be sold. Condis was sold for 4500 dollars in Richmond, VA. Lewis was not sold, but retained by the parties.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1886-003: Davenport and Morris vs. Admr. of John H. Weaver, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>John H. Weaver and his wife, Sarah J., ran a hotel and house of public entertainment in Hicksford called "Cato Hotel." The bill of complaint describes the duties of the proprietor of the hotel and house of public entertainment. The house of public entertainment had a bar where liquor was sold to be drunk where it was sold.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1886-007: Pierce R. Farley vs. Benjamin D. Tillar, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mr. Farley and his wife agreed to lease the Cato Hotel in Hicksford from Benjamin D. Tillar. The parties did not have a written lease. Mr. Tillar tricked Mrs. Farley into signing an agreement with him. The Farleys were sued by Mr. Tillar because they refused to pay more rent and he wanted them to move out of the hotel. During the time Mr. Farley rented the hotel, Mr. Tillar had an addition built to the existing Hotel building. The workmen building the new addition greatly damaged the roof of the existing building. The leaks from the holes in the roof caused damage to the building and the Farley's furniture. The leaks caused damage in the eight rooms that were used as hotel room. In the deposition of W. E. Bailey, he detailed the construction problems of the "Cato Hotel" (which was also called the "Central Hotel.") He statesdwhich rooms had plaster damage, parts missing from the building, problems with the window sashes, etc. Additional depositions were given concerning the problems in the building. Copies of the floor plan and the buildings front elevation are exhibits in this suit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
