<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
]>
<ead id="vi00821">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00821::A Guide to the Arlington County Chancery Cause, John Mason versus John Muncaster and others, 1821-1822)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi00821.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi00821::A Guide to the Arlington
             County Chancery Cause, John Mason versus John Muncaster
             and others, 1822)//EN" "vi00821.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County Chancery
            Cause, John Mason versus John Muncaster and others, 
            <date>1822</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Arlington County Chancery Cause, John
            Mason versus John Muncaster and others, 1822 
            <num type="collectionnumber">1150929</num></subtitle>
            <author>Greg Crawford</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>The Library of Virginia</addressline>
               <addressline>800 East Broad Street</addressline>
               <addressline>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives
               Reference)</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archdesk@lva.lib.va.us
               (Archives)</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2003 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">ca. 04 Kilobytes</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         Record. Created by Greg Crawford 
         <date>28 January 2003</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-14">Feb 14, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi00821::A Guide to the Arlington County Chancery
            Cause, John Mason versus John Muncaster and others,
            1822)//EN" "vi00821.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-27">Feb 27, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County Chancery Cause,
         John Mason versus John Muncaster and others, 
         <date>1822</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Barcode Number">1150929</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2003</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>The Library of Virginia</item>
            <item>800 East Broad Street</item>
            <item>Richmond, Virginia 23219-8000</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (804) 692-3888 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item>Fax: (804) 692-3556 (Archives Reference)</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archdesk@lva.lib.va.us">
            archdesk@lva.lib.va.us (Archives)</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/">
            http://www.lva.lib.va.us/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Greg Crawford</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head><repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Arlington County Chancery Cause, 
         <title render="italic">John Mason versus John Muncaster and
         others</title>, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1822</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Barcode number">1150929</unitid>
         <physloc label="Physical Location">The Library of Virginia,
         Local Government Records Collection, Arlington
         County</physloc>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.15  cubic
         feet </physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <origination label="Collector">Arlington County</origination>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>CLOSED FOR REFORMATTING.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p><title render="italic">John Mason versus John Muncaster and
            others, 1822</title>. Arlington County Chancery Cause 1822-018. Local government records collection, Arlington County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Arlington County.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Historical Information</head>
         <p>The chancery case had its origins in the purchase of glebe
         land by James Mason from the Protestant Episcopal Church of
         Alexandria at an auction held in 1815. The source of
         contention was the boundary lines of the land which would
         affect the price Mason would pay. Both the Protestant
         Episcopal Church and Mason had the land surveyed separately
         with the former showing a greater number of acres than the
         latter. The Protestant Episcopal Church refused to accept
         Mason's survey. Mason believed he was being treated unfairly
         by the Church and brought his case before the chancery court
         in Alexandria County, now Arlington County, to settle the
         matter.</p>
         <p>When Fairfax County was formed from Prince William County
         in 1742, the area of the new county, including the village of
         Belle Haven, which became the town of Alexandria in 1749, was
         embraced by the Parish of Truro. In 1765 Truro Parish was
         divided and boundaries for the parish of Fairfax were
         established. The parish contained two places of worship, one
         in Falls Church and the other in Alexandria. In 1767, the
         parish vestry ordered the construction of new buildings in
         Falls Church and Alexandria. The Falls Church building was
         designed by James Wrenn and completed in 1769. The Alexandria
         church was designed by James Parsons and completed in 1773 by
         John Carlyle. It was given the name Christ Church on January
         1, 1814. The parish vestry held meetings at both churches
         until October 1, 1792 when it began to meet exclusively in
         Alexandria. Following the disestablishment of the Anglican
         church in 1784, the Falls Church congregation went into
         gradual decline and was virtually abandoned. The vestry made
         vain efforts to revive the church during the 1790's and the
         first decade of the 1800's and decided to abandon further
         attempts. In the 1820's, the doors of Falls Church were
         reopened under the leadership of Francis Scott Key and Henry
         Fairfax.</p>
<p>Arlington County was formed in 1789 from Fairfax County and was at that time named Alexandria County. The county was ceded to the federal government in 1801 and was part of the District of Columbia until 1846 when it was returned to the state of Virginia. Alexandria County changed its name in 1920 to Arlington County.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p><title render="italic">John Mason versus John Muncaster and others, 1822</title> was a chancery suit that originated in Alexandria County, now Arlington County, and was heard in the Circuit Court of the District of Columbia. It involves a dispute related to the purchase by Mason of glebe land in Fairfax Parish from the Protestant Episcopal Church of Alexandria, or as it became known in 1814, Christ Church. The source of contention between the plaintiff and the defendants was the question of whether Christ Church of Alexandria had jurisdiction within Fairfax Parish and therefore had the authority to sell the land. The plaintiff in his bill and amended bill and the defendants in their answer provided very detailed legal and historical arguments to support their claims. Both provided evidence to support their arguments such as a copy of a bill from a previous chancery case involving Christ Church, a copy of a Supreme Court mandate, a copy of a deed, and correspondence. The chancery cause also includes miscellaneous papers related to the case such as subpoenas, affidavits, and depositions.</p>
         <p>The defendants in their answer presented a history of how
         Christ Church acquired land in Fairfax Parish from the
         parish's inception in 1765. In the process of doing so, they
         discussed the nature of the relationship between the two
         churches in the parish, Falls Church and Christ Church; how
         the parish was governed; and the decline in membership of
         Falls Church.</p>
         <p>For additional information on this cause and other chancery
         records, please consult the  
         Chancery Records Index found on the Libray of Virginia web site.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Organized by bill, answer, and decree followed by
         miscellaneous papers.</p>
      </arrangement>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
