<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01362">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01362::A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 circa)//EN" "vi01362.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 circa
</titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 circa
<num type="collectionnumber">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">circa 01 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives database, created by Eddie Woodward and edited by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 October 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 circa
</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Numbers">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Eddie Woodward
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799-1870 circa
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1.35 cubic feet
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 circa Local Government Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Albemarle County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle, and governor of Virginia from 1737 to 1754. It was created by a statute of 1744 and formed from Goochland County; part of Louisa County was added in 1761 and islands in the Fluvanna (now the James) River in 1770. The court met for the first time on 8 February 1745. The county seat is the city of Charlottesville.
</p>
<p>All order books except the first and many loose papers between 1748 and 1781 were destroyed by British general Banastre Tarleton's raid on Charlottesville in 1781 during the Revolutionary War.
</p>
<p>In 1806, the General Assembly moved to remove the "free Blacks" and "free persons of color" from Virginia with a law that stated that all emancipated enslaved people, freed after May 1, 1806, who remained in the Commonwealth more than a year, would forfeit their right to freedom and be sold by the Overseers of the Poor for the benefit of the parish. "Free people" wanting to stay were to petition the General Assembly through the local county court. Beginning in 1837, emancipated people could petition the local courts for permission to remain.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Materials in the Library of Virginia’s collections contain historical terms, phrases, and images that are offensive to modern readers. These include demeaning and dehumanizing references to race, ethnicity, and nationality; enslaved or free status; physical and mental ability; religion; sex; and sexual orientation and gender identity.</title></p>
      <p>Albemarle County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1799-1870 cica, include affidavits and certificates of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color" (1815-1870, undated), committee regarding carrying of arms by Blacks and "persons of color" papers (1865), deeds of emancipation (1841-1864), delinquent tax list "free Blacks" and "free persons of color"(1853), list of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color" (1853), nonresident list of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color" (1853), patrol
papers (1799-1864, undated), petition to be classified as white (1869), petitions for voluntary enslavement (1858-1864), petitions to remain in county or Commowealth (1816, 1850, 1852), freedom seeker papers (1845), sale of enslaved people (1843), and registrations of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color" (1804-1864, undated).
</p>
      <p>Affidavits and Certificates of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," 1815-1870, undated, record the name of the person, sometimes their age and a brief physical description, and a statement based either on another person's knowledge or on other official documentary evidence seen by the certifier that this person was either born free or was emancipated. If born free, reference is sometimes made to parents. If emancipated, emancipating enslaver, place and date of emancipation, and prior registration are usually mentioned.
</p>
      <p>Court order, 1865, appointing members to a committee regarding carrying of arms by Blacks and "persons of color." No names are contained.
</p>
      <p>Deeds of emancipation or manumission, 1841-1864, record the name of the former enslaver, the name of the enslaved person, the date or age at which the enslaved person will be freed, the date the deed was written, and the date the deed was proved. The age of the enslaved peson at the time the deed was written, a surname assigned to the freed enslaved person by the enslaver, and the enslaver's reason for emancipation are sometimes given.
</p>
      <p>The list of delinquent "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," 1853, records the names of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," recorded by the Commissioner of Revenue and listing the known effects and the amount of taxes owed by each person listed.
</p>
      <p>The list of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," 1853, records the names of male and female "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," male children, female children, place of abode, and trade or occupation for the adult males and females.
</p>
      <p>The list of free nonresident "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," 1853, records the names of free negroes, recorded by the Commissioner of Revenue and listing the known effects and the amount of taxes owed by each person.
</p>
     <p>Patrol papers, 1799-1864, undated) record patrol orders with specific instructions for a patrol to convene and list all of the persons summoned to participate; patrol appointments listing persons appointed or summoned to participate; and patrol returns listing the names of the patrollers and recording the hours of services and expenses incurred.
</p>
      <p>The petition to be classified as white, 1869, records the name of the petitioner. Tthe petitioner's parents, and/or persons who can attest to their claim to be reclassified are sometimes included.
</p>
     <p>The petitions for voluntary enslavement, 1858-1864, record the name of the petitioner, and the potential enslaver. Sometimes a former enslaver is mentioned.
</p>
      <p>The petitions to remain in county or Commonwealth, 1816-1852, record the name of the petitioner. Sometimes the names of witnesses that can vouch for the character of the petitioner are mentioned. Free registrations and other supporting documents may also be included.
</p>
      <p>The freedom seeker papers, 1845, include court documents such as notices and orders and include the name of the enslaved. The enslaver is sometimes recorded.
</p>
      <p>The sale of enslaved people papers, 1843, record the account of the sale, the name of the seller, the name of the purchaser and the date of the transaction. The name and/or sex and/or age of the enslaved being sold may also be included.
</p>
      <p>The registrations of "free Blacks" and "free persons of color," 1804-1864, undated record the following: name, age, complexion, stature in feet and inches, apparent marks or scars, whether emancipated or free born, and date information was certified by the court.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by record type.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Albemarle County amd other localities are available on <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan/search-the-narrative">Virginia Untold</extref>.
</p>
        <p>Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Albemarle County Court Records may be found in the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/">Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia</extref>.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    
  </archdesc>
</ead>
