<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01960">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01960::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, 1842-1843)//EN" "vi01960.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1843</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Gregory, John M., Executive Papers of Governor, 1842-1843
<num type="collectionnumber">43537
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2007 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Craig S. Moore, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 December 2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1843</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">43537
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2007
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Craig S. Moore
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1843
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">43537
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.90 cubic feet (4 boxes)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia Governor (1842-1843 : Gregory)
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>For preservation purposes, please use microfilm (Miscellaneous Reels 6648-6651).
</p>
      </userestrict>

<altformavail>
<head>Alternate Form Available</head>
<p>Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reels 6648-6651.  Interlibrary Loan copies of microfilm also available.</p>
<p>Miscellaneous Reel 6648 - Box 1, Folders 1-5 (1842 Apr 1-Jun 14)</p>
<p>Miscellaneous Reel 6649 - Box 1, Folders 6-10 (1842 Jun 16-Sep 30)</p>
<p>Miscellaneous Reel 6650 - Box 2, Folders 1-4 (1842 Oct 1-Nov 30)</p>
<p>Miscellaneous Reel 6651 - Box 2, Folders 5-8 (1842 Dec 1-1843 Jan 5, undated)</p>
<p>Miscellaneous Reel 6651 - Box 3 (Oversize, 1842)</p>

</altformavail>





      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Virginia. Governor's Office. Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, 1842-1843 (bulk 1842). Accession 43537. State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Acquired prior to 1905
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>John Munford Gregory was born in Charles City County, Virginia, on 8 July 1804, to John M. Gregory, Sr., and Letitia Power Graves.  A teacher in James City County, Gregory later graduated from the College of William &amp; Mary with as a Bachelor of Law in 1830.  He was elected to represent James City County in the House of Delegates for the sessions of 1832-1833 through 1835-1836.  Gregory married Amanda M. Wallace of Petersburg, Virginia, on 9 November 1835.  He returned to the House of Delegates for the sessions of 1839-1840 and 1840-1841, resigning on 18 March 1841 to become a member of the Council of State.  As a member of the Council, Gregory served as lieutenant governor and succeeded John Rutherfoord as acting governor on 31 March 1842.  Gregory was succeeded as governor by James McDowell who began his three-year term on 5 January 1843.  In 1853, Gregory was appointed United States District Attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia until 1860.  He was then elected judge for the Sixth Judicial Circuit of Virginia until 1866.  He served as Commonwealth's attorney for Charles City County until his retirement in 1880.  Gregory died on 9 April 1884 and is buried in Shockoe Hill Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>John M. Gregory's Executive Papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his term as acting governor from 31 March 1842 until 5 January 1843.  The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments &amp; recommendations for state positions; the Virginia Penitentiary; arms and ammunition; the militia; Revolutionary War bounty land claims; banks and banking; resignations; extraditions; state expenses &amp; revenue; elections; and others.  In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate &amp; House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; contracts; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns &amp; certificates; qualifications; lists; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; opinions; and other sundry items.     
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>I. Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory, 1842-1843</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography
</head>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1836-April 15, 1869, VOL. XI, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1893. 
</bibref>
      </bibliography>
      <separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Separated Material
</head>
        <p>Oversized materials have been separated to boxes 3-4.
</p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01>
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Executive Papers of Governor John M. Gregory</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1842-1843</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Boxes" type="box">1-4
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 4 boxes.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states.
Federal government correspondents include <emph render="bold">Walter Forward</emph>, Secretary of the Treasury, &amp; <emph render="bold">Daniel Webster</emph>, Secretary of State. Walter Forward encloses a resolution of the House of Representatives requesting information showing the progress in the cultivation, manufacture, &amp; consumption of tobacco in the United States (1842 Apr. 2).  Forward also writes requesting a tabular statement of the tobacco inspected in Virginia since 1820 (1842 Apr. 12).  Daniel Webster writes requesting copies of the laws of Virginia for 1821-1822 &amp; 1823-1824 (1842 Dec. 6).
</p>
          <p>The majority of correspondence in John M. Gregory's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government.  Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Robert G. Scott, President of the Board of Directors of the Penitentiary; John B. Richardson, Superintendent of Public Edifices &amp; Superintendent of the Armory; George W. Munford, Clerk of the House of Delegates; James E. Heath, Auditor of Public Accounts; and Fabius M. Lawson, Treasurer. 
</p>
          <p><emph render="bold">Robert Scott</emph>, President of the Board of Directors of the Penitentiary, encloses statements showing the operation of the Penitentiary for the fiscal year ending 30 September 1842 (1842 Dec. 9).  Scott also encloses an account current of James E. Watson, the report of Charles S. Morgan, the physician &amp; Superintendent's report, the superintendent's general statement, and various tables regarding prisoners in the Penitentiary.  Scott also writes regarding the case of Alexander Bogart, a prisoner in the Penitentiary for forgery (1842 Dec. 14). 
</p>
          <p><emph render="bold">John B. Richardson</emph>, as Superintendent of Public Edifices, writes regarding the white washing of several offices in the basement story of the Capitol and the reglazing of many of the windows (1842 Sept. 26).  In his role as Superintendent of the Armory, Richardson writes regarding a break in the culverts which pass off the water from the Armory &amp; Boring Mill (1842 Sept. 27).
</p>
          <p><emph render="bold">George W. Munford</emph>, as Clerk of the House of Delegates, transmits a certificate of election for James McDowell as governor for three years (1842 Dec. 15).  In addition, Munford encloses a resolution that the Executive be requested to inform the House whether he has received the standard of liquid measurers ordered to be distributed by the General government (1842 Dec. 29). 
</p>
          <p><emph render="bold">James E. Heath</emph>, Auditor of Public Accounts, corresponds with Governor Gregory transmitting a statement of receipts &amp; disbursements at the Auditor's Office (1842 Apr. 18), his absence from office (1842 July 2), and carpeting for his office (1842 Sept. 13).   
</p>
          <p><emph render="bold">Fabius M. Lawson</emph>, Treasurer, writes requesting loans to meet the exigencies of the Treasury (1842 Apr. 4 &amp; Dec. 24).  In addition, Lawson writes concerning Treasurer's bonds given for the payment of a loan borrowed by his predecessor (1842 Apr. 5).  Lastly, encloses a letter from J. Brown, Jr., 2nd Auditor, and an estimate of the certain &amp; probably receipts &amp; disbursements on account of the revenue of the Board of Public Works (1842 Apr. 16). 
</p>
          <p>Governors from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor.  Included are letters from the following governors: <emph render="bold">Tilghman Tucker</emph>, Mississippi; <emph render="bold">William H. Seward</emph>, New York; <emph render="bold">Robert P. Letcher</emph>, Kentucky; and <emph render="bold">Francis Thomas</emph>, Maryland.
</p>
          <p>Governor Tilghman Tucker, Mississippi, encloses resolutions regarding the annexation of the Republic of Texas to the United States (1842 Apr. 8).  Governor William H. Seward, New York, transmits resolutions of the New York Legislature concerning the regulations of the Post Office Department in the government in the United States (1842 May 6).  Governor Robert P. Letcher, Kentucky, writes regarding a demand for the surrender of Moses Thompson &amp; James Johnson (1842 July 2).  Lastly, Governor Francis Thomas, Maryland, writes regarding his demand for Isaac Goudkop, a fugitive from justice in Virginia (1842 Nov. 15 &amp; 22).
</p>
          <p>Additional significant correspondence includes the following: John Brown, Jr., 2nd Auditor, requesting an improvement to his office (1842 Apr. 4) and the act appropriating a sum of money for defraying the expenses incurred by the enlargement of his office (1842 Aug. 16); John F. Wren, Superintendent of the Public Warehouse, enclosing an estimate of the cost of work for repairs (1842 Sept. 13); J. A. Early to William H. Richardson, State Librarian, re. a book he borrowed which was lost (1842 Nov. 29); Henry A. Wise re. a bill refunding to General Andrew Jackson the amount of a fine with interest imposed on him at the time of the attack &amp; defense of New Orleans (1842 Dec. 24); and S. S. Baxter, Attorney General, re. his opinion on the right of the state proxies to vote for directors of banks (1842 [N.D.]).  
</p>
          <p>Other noteworthy items include: report of the Committee on the Action of the General Assembly on the subject of the Constitution by the Rhode Island General Assembly (1842 Apr. 4); a proclamation of Governor Gregory for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of Charles J. Faulkner (1842 Apr. 6); proclamation regarding an election to supply the vacancy in the Virginia Senate occasioned by the resignation of James Lyons (1842 Apr. 4); proclamation for an election in Nansemond County to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the death of Joshua M. Harrell (1842 Sept. 26); contract &amp; bond of Francis H. Deane as vaccine agent (1842 Nov. 18); proclamation requiring the sheriff of Henrico County to arrest Isaac Goudkop, a fugitive from justice from the State of Maryland (1842 Nov. 19); and proclamations by the governor offering rewards for the apprehension of escaped convicts (1842 Dec. 24 &amp; 27).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Arranged in chronological order.
</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">1842</emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>April
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-15
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>16-30
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>May
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-14
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>16-30
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>June
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-14
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>16-30
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>July
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-16
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>24-29
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>August
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">9
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>September
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">10
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>October
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-15
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>17-28
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>November
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-15 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>16-30
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>December
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>1-10 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>11-30
			<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
			</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">1843</emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>January
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04>
              <did>
                <unittitle>2-5
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">2
		</container>
                <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
		</container>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">Undated </emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <emph render="bold">Oversized (Newspaper Box)</emph>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">1842</emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Nov. 15
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">3
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <emph render="bold">Oversized (Newspaper Box)</emph>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">1842</emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>July 16
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">3
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Nov. [N.D.]
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">3
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
