<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01973">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01972::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, 1781 November 23-29)//EN" "vi01973.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781 November 23-29</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Jameson, David, Executive Papers of, 1781 November 23-29
<num type="collectionnumber">44653
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Craig S. Moore, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 January 2010</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781 November 23-29</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44653
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010 
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Craig S. Moore
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781 November 22-29
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44653
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">32 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia Governor (1781 : Jameson)
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Virginia. Governor's Office. Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, 1781 November 22-29. Accession 44653. State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Acquired prior to 1905
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
        <p>Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 2969.
</p>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>Miscellaneous Reel 2969 - 1781 October 12-November 30</item>
        </list>
      </altformavail>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>David Jameson was the third-born son of James and Margaret Jameson, residents of St. Anne's Parish, Essex County, Virginia. Jameson's exact date of birth is unknown, but his elder brother James was born in 1720. A graduate of Princeton College, Jameson became a prominent merchant in Yorktown involved in shipping tobacco, importing goods, and buying and selling slaves. An inventor who developed the first instrument to measure dew and rainfall, Jameson was named treasurer of the Society for the Advancement of Useful Knowledge, an organization he helped organize with John Clayton &amp; John Page in Williamsburg. Elected to represent the district of Elizabeth City, Warwick, and York counties in the state senate in 1776, 1781, 1782, &amp; 1783, Jameson instead accepted an appointment to the Council of State and was sworn in on 12 December 1776. Jameson served on the Council for over five years with an increased role as lieutenant governor during the formidable period leading up to the capitulation of Lord Cornwallis after the siege of Yorktown. During Governor Thomas Nelson's absence to command the Virginia militia at Yorktown, Jameson handled the essential duties of the office including supplying the French &amp; American armies with equipment &amp; supplies for the coming battle. Upon Nelson's resignation on 22 November 1781, Jameson served briefly as acting governor until Benjamin Harrison's appointment on 30 November 1781. Jameson continued on the Council until his resignation on 30 March 1782. Jameson returned to the state senate for the October to December 1782 session and the subsequent session in 1783. He was also served as justice of the peace &amp; coroner for York County in 1782 &amp; 1783.Jameson married Mildred Smith (1733-1778), daughter of Edmund &amp; Agnes Sclater Smith. Jameson's exact date of death is unknown but his will was probated on 22 July 1793. Jameson left no issue, but bequeathed his portions of his estate to his nephews John Jameson, David Jameson of Culpeper, &amp; David Jameson of Caroline.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Acting Governor David Jameson's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the rear of the collection. These papers consist of incoming correspondence during Jameson's brief term as acting governor of Virginia between 23 and 29 November 1781. The correspondence primarily relates to the Revolutionary War, supplies, prisoners, and miscellaneous topics. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions of Congress, returns, lists, nominations, and other sundry items.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>I. Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson, 1781 November 22-29</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography
</head>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Palmer, William P., ed., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, 1781 April 1-December 31, VOL. II, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1881. 
</bibref>
      </bibliography>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01>
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Executive Papers of Acting Governor David Jameson</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1781 November 22-29</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Boxes" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Noteworthy are the following items: resolutions of Congress that the Superintendent of Finance &amp; Board of War be authorized to take order for the safekeeping &amp; support of the prisoners of war in possession of the United States by Charles Thomson, Secretary of the Continental Congress (1781 Nov. 23); resolutions of Congress recommending that the several states enact laws for punishing certain infractions of the laws of nations and recommending that a court be established or empowered to decide on such offenses (1781 Nov. 23); a letter of Maj. Richard Claiborne, Deputy Quarter Master, encl. letters from William McGraw &amp; Reuben Turner re. the transport of spirits &amp; the removal of sick prisoners from Todd's Bridge to Fredericksburg (1781 Nov. 23); a letter of Joseph Prentis, Williamsburg, re. the return of residents who joined the British Army (1781 Nov. 24.); a letter of Richard Claiborne re. forage in possession of Richard Taylor (1781 Nov. 25); a letter of A[lexander] Ross, aid de camp, New York, to Maurice Simmons re. Lord Cornwallis's passports for sending tobacco from the Chesapeake to Charleston for the purpose of discharging the debts contracted by American prisoners (1781 Nov. 25); a letter of A[braham] Kirkpatrick, Hanover Town, re. depredations by British prisoners and requesting a guard (1781 Nov. 25); a letter of Garret Van Meter, Hampshire, re. the surrender of Robert Smith, one of the ringleaders of the late insurrection (1781 Nov. 26); a letter of Dr. Mathew Pope, Richmond, requesting a hospital for the sick &amp; wounded (1781 Nov. 26); nominations for the offices of governor, delegate to Congress, councilors, judge, &amp; auditor (1781 Nov. 29); list of refugees from Princess Anne &amp; Norfolk counties confined for treason (1781 Nov. 29); and a return of recruits raised under the act of October 1780 (undated - ca. Nov. 26).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Arranged in chronological order.
</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">1781</emph>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
            </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>November 23-29
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
		</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
