<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY lost SYSTEM 
"http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01426">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi01426 ::A Guide to the Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births, 1864-1867)//EN" "[vi01426.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births, <date>1864-1867 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births, 1864-1867
<num type="collectionnumber">1104575
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sherri Bagley
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 01 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives Database, created by Sherri Bagley, <date>23 June 2005</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births, <date>1864-1867 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Number">1104575
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sherri Bagley
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sherri Bagley
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1864-1867
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode number">1104575
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 vol. (56 p.)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Use microfilm copy, Caroline County, Reel 36.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Caroline County (Va.) Register of Births, 1864-1867. Caroline County Reel 36, Local Government Records Collection, Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Caroline County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Caroline County was formed in 1728 from Essex, King and Queen, and King William Counties. Additional parts of King and Queen County were added in 1742 and 1762.
</p>
<p>Laws requiring the recording of births and deaths in Virginia were enacted as early as 1632, when a law directed ministers or churchwardens in each parish to present a "register of all burialls, christenings,
and marriages" yearly at the June meeting of the court.  these early decades.
</p>
<p>In 1713 the General Assembly noted that earlier acts had "for a long time been disused" and once again directed the recording of births and deaths by the minister or clerk of each parish. A return made the same
year noted that the list of births was not complete since many parishes failed to make returns "for tis a thing so new to the people that neither they care to Register their Births  nor are
the Parish Clerks yet brought into a regular method of transmitting them."
</p>
<p>The recording of vital statistics continued to be an ecclesiastical function throughout the colonial period. With the disestablishment of the Anglican church after the American Revolution and the rise of other
religious denominations, the record-keeping process for vital statistics fell more and more to the individual family. By the mid-nineteenth century, however, medical science began to recognize the advantages of
accurate birth and mortality information in controlling and treating communicable diseases. Pressure from local and national health organizations and medical professionals resulted in the passage of vital
statistics registration laws. Virginia was one of the earliest states to pass such a law.
</p>
<p>A law requiring the systematic statewide recording of births was passed by the General Assembly on April 11 1853. Every commissioner of revenue registered births in his district annually,
at the same time personal property subject to taxation was ascertained. The commissioner recorded births that had occurred prior to 31 December of the preceding year and returned the record to the clerk
of court by 1 June. Information was obtained from heads of family, physicians and surgeons. The law imposed penalties for failing to furnish or collect the information.
</p>
<p>The clerk of court in each locality entered the information supplied by the commissioner into registers and prepared an accompanying alphabetical index. A copy of each register was forwarded to the Auditor of
Public Accounts. The law went into effect on 1 July 1853, and continued until 1896, when an economy-conscious legislature repealed the recording provisions
</p>
<p>Birth registers at the Library of Virginia are copies of those records made by local clerks from the lists compiled by the commissioners and forwarded to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor
turned the lists over to the Bureau of Vital Statistics in 1918, and the registers were later transferred to the state archives. The records are an indispensable source for the most basic biographical facts about
earlier generations of Virginians.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Birth registers contain headings for: date and place of birth; name of child (if named); color (if "colored," whether slave
or free); sex; whether born alive or dead; name of father or owner; father's occupation; father's residence (county or locality in the county); mother's name; how many infants at this birth (whether this was a
multiple birth); deformities or any circumstances of interest; name of the person giving the information; and the relation of the informant to the person born.
</p>
<p>Information is often missing from the records. If an infant had not been named at the time of birth, the entry would record only the surname or note "Smith, infant." Only the month appears for the date
of birth in some instances. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Chronological.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Caroline County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Caroline County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref entityref="lost">Lost Records Localities Database</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
