<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01007">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01007::A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vi01007.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of
             Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01007::A Guide to the Virginia
             Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903)//EN"
             "vi01007.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey,
            Records, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834-1903</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Geological Survey, Virginia, Records,
            1834-1903 
            <num type="collectionnumber">24815</num></subtitle>
        <author>Lois R. Angeletti</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2003 By the Library
            of Virginia.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">12 KB</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC
         record and paper finding aid. Created by Lois Angeletti 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 May 14</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 14, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT
            (US::Vi::vi01007::A Guide to the Virginia Geological
            Survey, Records, 1834-1903)//EN" "vi01007.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-01-08">2014-01-08</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey,
         Records, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834-1903</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Library of Virginia 
         <num type="Accession Number">24815</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>John Salmon</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Records, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1834-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">24815</unitid>
      <physloc label="Physical Location">State Government Records
         Collection, Virgninia Geological Survey (Record Group
         51)</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">3.45 cubic
         feet [7 boxes]</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator">Virginia Geological
         Survey.</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903.
            Accession 24815, State Government Records Collection, The
            Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Emma Savage Rogers, May 10, 1903.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Geological Survey of Virginia was conducted in two
         phases. First, under an act passed by the General Assembly on
         March 6, 1835, a geological reconnaissance of the state was
         made to compile data of a general nature on geological
         features, and chemical compositions of soils, minerals and
         mineral waters for a report to the next session of the General
         Assembly.</p>
      <p>Then the geological survey itself, which was devoted to a
         more detailed study than the reconnaissance, was established
         by an act of the General Assembly on February 26, 1836. This
         survey was to provide a careful and accurate chemical
         examination and analysis of various soils, and principal ores,
         marls, saline and mineral waters. Other goals of the survey
         were to determine the height of principal mountains, construct
         a complete geological map of the state for engraving, and to
         collect and catalog specimens of rocks, fossils, ores,
         mineral, compounds, and organic remains, so that there would
         be a sufficient amount to distribute to institutions of higher
         learning. Both acts called for the appointment of a geologist
         by the Board of Public Works, and in each case Professor
         William Barton Rogers of the University of Virginia was
         appointed. He was responsible for supervising the survey,
         submitting annual reports on its progress, rendering
         geological sections and a geological map of the state,
         analyzing minerals and waters for their chemical content, and
         distilling all the collected data into a final report at the
         conclusion of the survey. Members of his staff included
         William A.E. Aikin, George W. Boyd, Caleb Briggs, Jr., Charles
         B. Hayden, James Rogers and Israel Slade.</p>
      <p>William Barton Rogers was born in Philadelphia,
         Pennsylvania, on December 7, 1804, the son of a professor of
         physical sciences. He attended the College of William and Mary
         in 1820 and 1821, taught school at Windsor, Maryland, in 1826,
         was appointed a lecturer at the Maryland Institute in
         Baltimore in 1827, and succeeded his father in 1828 as
         professor of chemistry and physics at the College of William
         and Mary. On February 9, 1835, when enthusiasm for a
         geological survey of Virginia was running strong in the
         General Assembly where a bill had been introduced, Rogers
         appeared before a House committee appointed to study the
         matter and drafted the committee's report to the House of
         Delegates recommending the establishment of the survey. The
         next evening, February 10, 1835, Rogers delivered an
         extemporaneous address to a joint session of the House and
         Senate describing the benefits of a geological survey to the
         state. As a result of Rogers's efforts, the General Assembly
         passed a bill on March 6, 1835, authorizing the Board of
         Public Works "to appoint a suitable person to make a
         geological reconnoissance of the state, with a view to the
         general geological features of our territory . . . and to
         report to the next general assembly a plan for the prosecution
         of a geological survey of the state." The board appointed
         William B. Rogers to the position on March 25, and he accepted
         it on April 2. His brother Henry Darwin Rogers was appointed
         as his assistant.</p>
      <p>The geological survey was continued by annual
         appropriations of state funds until 1842, when the General
         Assembly terminated the project because of a financial
         recession. In 1844 Rogers engaged Russell Smith, a
         Pennsylvania artist, to draw sketches and sections for the
         final report. Unfortunately, the money necessary to complete
         the report was never authorized by the General Assembly,
         although Rogers continued to hold the records of the survey
         until his death in the hope of receiving funds.</p>
      <p>Rogers spent the summer of 1835 in the field, making notes
         for his report, collecting samples of rocks, ores, and mineral
         waters for chemical analysis, and compiling data for
         geological sections of the state to show the different mineral
         strata. In August he accepted a call to the chair of natural
         philosophy at the University of Virginia. The first half of
         the school year was employed in teaching and in drawing
         sections, analyzing specimens, and drafting his report to the
         General Assembly. The report was submitted to the House of
         Delegates by Governor Littleton W. Tazewell as president of
         the Board of Public Works on January 11, 1836. The report met
         with the approval of the General Assembly, which passed an act
         on February 29, 1836. Rogers was expected to make annual
         reports on the progress of the survey, as well as a final
         report when the survey was completed.</p>
      <p>In the spring Rogers gave his assistants their orders for
         the season, pointing out particular areas for investigation.
         Until the school year ended Rogers was confined to the
         University, maintaining contact with his assistants in the
         field through the unreliable mail system. The assistants tried
         their best to keep Rogers informed as to their activities and
         whereabouts, their problems with sick horses, broken
         instruments, and lack of funds. As soon as he could, Rogers
         took to the field himself, visiting his assistants, conducting
         his own investigations and traveling to other states to study
         and compare the geology of Maryland, Pennsylvania, and New
         England. When the University reconvened Rogers returned to
         Charlottesville, once again relying on the mails to
         communicate with his asistants. As winter approached the
         assistants visited Rogers on their way to their homes, turning
         reports and specimens over to him for study during the winter.
         By the first of the new year Rogers had prepared his annual
         report for the General Assembly and was making plans for the
         ensuing season. After the Panic of 1837, Rogers was forced to
         worry each year about whether the survey would be continued
         for another year.</p>
      <p>In 1853 Rogers resigned his position at the University of
         Virginia, wishing to move to Boston, Massachusetts, to work
         with his brother Henry. Before leaving Virginia, however,
         Rogers spent almost three months in early 1853 in Richmond, in
         a last, futile attempt to persuade the General Assembly to
         fund the final report. On March 8, 1854, Rogers left Virginia
         for Boston and a new career as a founder and first president
         of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Even after he
         left Virginia, Rogers continued to seek funding for the final
         report, but did not succeed. On May 30, 1882, as he was
         delivering a commencement address at MIT, Rogers collapsed and
         died.</p>
      <p>Rogers's widow, Emma Savage Rogers, began a time consuming
         project of sifting through her husband's papers, selecting
         some for publication and destroying others. She presented the
         surviving papers to the Virginia State Library in two lots,
         the first aobut 1900 and the second on May 10, 1903. At first
         the papers were supposed to be the personal papers of William
         B. Rogers and were so described. However, the Archives staff
         came to realize that the documents were in fact state records
         which Rogers kept in his possession pending the writing of his
         final report. Accordingly, the records are now regarded as a
         subgroup within the records of the Board of Public Works.
         Records primarily concerned with the adminstration of the
         funds for the survey by the second auditor and the Board of
         Public Works have been described already by John S. Salmon,
         comp., in Board of Public Works Inventory (Richmond: Virginia
         State Library, 1978), entry 21, "Geological Survey."</p>
      <p>William E. A. Aikin, of Maryland, appointed assistant
         geologist effective June 1, 1837. Resigned April 13, 1839. Was
         teaching at the Baltimore Medical School in 1873; George W.
         Boyd, of New York, appointed assistant geologist on May 1,
         1838. He died of asthma on September 23, 1840, in the home of
         William B. Rogers at the University of Virginia,
         Charlottesville; Caleb Briggs, Jr., of New York, appointed
         assistant geologist on June 1, 1839. He was paid for his
         services to July 1, 1842; Charles B. Hayden (January 22,
         1817-January 28, 1883), of Connecticut, attended the College
         of William and Mary, and probably was a student of William B.
         Rogers, 1834-1835. Appointed assistant geologist effective
         April 1, 1837. Board of Public Works received notice that he
         had "retired from the service" on June 11, 1840. He taught
         school in Smithfield, Virginia, and later became a lawyer;
         Samuel Lewis, appointed assistant geologist effective June 1,
         1840. He was paid for his services to March 1, 1841; Thomas S.
         Ridgeway, Jr., appointed assistant geologist on April 15,
         1840. He was paid for his services to June 2, 1842; Henry
         Darwin Rogers (August 1, 1808-May 29, 1866), of Philadelphia,
         Pennsylvania, appointed assistant geologist on April 2, 1836.
         Resignation received by the Board of Public Works on May 8,
         1837. Directed New Jersey and Pennsylvania state geological
         surveys, later collaborated with William B. Rogers on a paper
         concerning mountain elevation; James Blythe Rogers (February
         11, 1802-June 15, 1852), of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
         appointed assistant geologist in May 1837. Resignation
         received by the Board of Public Works on April 15, 1840.
         Reappointed assistant geologist on May 1, 1841. He was paid
         for his services to August 1, 1842. The major contribution of
         his career was the development of methods of chemical
         analysis.</p>
      <p>Robert Empie Rogers (March 29, 1813-September 6, 1884), of
         Baltimore, Maryland. He was a chemist with the Pennsylvania
         Geological Survey and was professor of chemistry at the
         University of Virginia, where he collaborated with William B.
         Rogers, and at the University of Pennsylvania; Israel Slade,
         of Pittstown, New York. Employed by William B. Rogers
         (accepted offer on April 16, 1838) who paid him with his own
         funds. Appointed assistant geologist on April 15, 1840. He was
         paid for his services to July 1, 1842; A Maxwell Walker,
         appointed topographical surveyor on May 5, 1836. His
         resignation was received by the Board of Public Works on March
         11, 1837; William Thompson Russell Smith (April 26,
         1812-November 8, 1896), known as Russell Smith, was born in
         Glasgow, Scotland, but moved to Pennsylvania in 1819 with his
         parents. The family eventually settled in Pittsburgh, where
         Smith became interested in painting and drama. He combined the
         two interests by painting scenery for the stage, and had a
         successful career that took him eventually to Philadelphia,
         Baltimore, and Washington, D.C. It was probably while he lived
         in Milestown near Philadelphia during the late 1830's and
         early 1840's that Smith became acquainted with William B.
         Rogers on one of the geologist's visits to the area. Rogers
         engaged Smith to execute a series of drawings of significant
         geological formations in Virginia for use in Rogers's
         projected final report on the state geological survey. Smith
         travelled to Charlottesville in June 1844, and from July to
         September he and Rogers explored western Virginia. Smith used
         the resulting sketches for his own benefit as well as for
         Rogers's, making them the basis for oil landscapes for
         exhibition. Eventually he mailed the sketches to Rogers for
         him to keep.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The records are divided into three series: Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903; Series II: Reports, sections, lists, and field notes, 1834-1884; and Series III: Drawings of Russell Smith, c. 1844.</p>

<p>Series I: The correspondence to Rogers was primarily from his assistants. Also included are letters from George W. Summers, member of the House of Delegates, and James Brown, Jr., Second Auditor of Virginia. There were also letters from Rogers and a letter from Emma Rogers, his wife, to William W. Scott, Librarian of the State Library.</p>
      <p>Series II: The field notes and reports are from 1834 to 1884. William B. Rogers was one of four brothers, all of whom were noted chemists and geologists. Two brothers, Henry Darwin Rogers and James Blythe Rogers, served as his assistants at different times during the conduct of the survey, while the third, Robert Empie Rogers, contributed his observations on the geology of the Northern Neck. Rogers's other assistants, appointed by the Board of Public Works, were: William E. A. Aikin, George W. Boyd, Caleb Briggs, Jr., Charles B. Hayden, Samuel Lewis, Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., Henry Darwin Rogers, James Blythe Rogers, Robert Empie Rogers, Israel Slade and A. Maxwell Walker. In the spring, Rogers gave his assistants their orders for the season, pointing out particular areas for investigation, and as winter aproached the assistants gave him reports on the geological, chemical and topographical discoveries which they had made.</p>
      <p>Series III: Rogers personally hired a Pennsylvania artist, Russell Smith, to make drawings for the final report; Smith and Rogers spent most of the summer of 1844 afield for this purpose. The 51 sketches depict geographical features and are done on paper and cardboard, in ink, pencil, pastels, oils and watercolor.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Organization</head>
      <p>Organized into the following three (3) series: I.
         Correspondence of William B. Rogers from 1836 to 1903; II.
         Field notes and reports from 1834 to 1884; and III. Drawings
         of Russell Smith, c. 1844.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Correspondence of William B.
               Rogers, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1836-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The correspondence to Rogers was primarily from his
               assistants. Also included are letters from George W.
               Summers, member of the House of Delegates, and James
               Brown, Jr., Second Auditor of Virginia. There were also
               letters from Rogers and a letter from Emma Rogers his
               wife, to William W. Scott, Librarian of the State
               Library.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1836</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Summers, Richmond, to
                     [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 15,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Summers, Richmond, to [William
                     B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, notifying him
                     that the bill providing for a geological survey
                     has passed the House of Delegates and is expected
                     to pass the Senate easily; also discussing the
                     printing of Rogers's geological report by order of
                     the General Assembly. 2 pp. with address leaf.
                     Summers was a member of the House of Delegates
                     from Kanawha County in 1836.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames]Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 5,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, enclosing a copy of the act providing
                     for a geological survey of Virginia; informing him
                     that the Board of Public Works had, on April2,
                     1836, appointed him geologist; and asking for a
                     written proposal of how he intended to caryy out
                     the intentions of the Act. 1 p. with address leaf.
                     James Brown, Jr. (June 1780-January 3, 1859) was
                     Second Auditor of Virgniia from March 1, 1823, to
                     December 31, 1852, and Secretary of the Board of
                     Public Works from March 1, 1823, to March 31,
                     1851.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James E. Heath, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 6,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James E. Heath, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning a check
                     written for Rogers on the Bank of Virginia and the
                     safe arrival of some geological profiles for the
                     engraver; also mentioning "the pleasure afforded
                     me" in meeting "Mr. Bancroft," to whom he showed
                     some of "our ancient state records." 2 pp. with
                     address leaf. James E. Heath (July 8, 1792-June
                     28, 1862) was First Auditor of Virgniia from
                     January 8, 1820, to February 28, 1850. George
                     Bancroft (October 8, 1800-January 17, 1891),
                     American historian and diplomat, author of a
                     ten-volume History of the United
                     States.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>R[obert] E[mpie] R[ogers], Westmoreland
                     Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 24,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>R[obert] E[mpie] R[ogers], Westmoreland
                     Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing his observations of the
                     geology of the Fredericksburg--King
                     George--Westmoreland area, particularly in regard
                     to the Stratford cliffs on the Potomac River,
                     where he found fossil vertebra and ribs. 4 pp.
                     Robert Empie Rogers (March 29, 1813-September 6,
                     1884), chemist and geologist, was a brother of
                     William Barton Rogers.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 28,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     concerning the bad weather, his lack of clean
                     clothes, observations of a geological nature, and
                     his plans for travel. 3 pp. with address leaf.
                     Charles B. Hayden was appointed assistant
                     geologist by the Board of Public Works on May 4,
                     1837, to be effective retroactively to April 1,
                     1837. A Charles B. Hayden was a student at the
                     College of William and Mary during the 1834-1835
                     session while William Barton Rogers taught
                     there.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>A. M[axwell] Walker, Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 11,
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>A. M[axwell] Walker, Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, giving
                     his address as "Mr. Duvals Powhatan House," and
                     discussing his progress in drawing maps. 2 pp.
                     with address leaf. Walker was appointed
                     topographical surveyer by the Board of Public
                     Works on May 5, 1836. His resignation was received
                     by the Board on March 11, 1837.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Hezekiah Daggs, Botetourt Springs, to
                     Professor [William B.] Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 23,
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Hezekiah Daggs, Botetourt Springs, to
                     Professor [William B.] Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, sending him five bottles of sulphur
                     water, a sample of limestone, and a piece of
                     shale; describing the strata encountered in
                     sinking his shafts; asking whether Rogers thinks
                     he will strike coal; and inviting Rogers to stay
                     at his house if he visits Botetourt Springs in the
                     summer. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Smithfield, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 6,
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Smithfield, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing his plans to survey the branches of
                     Pagan Creek for blue marl; complaining of the
                     difficulty of making adequate notes on such small
                     maps as he has to use; and commenting on the
                     general business of the survey. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 9,
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, correcting an error in his previous
                     letter to Rogers concerning the salaries of Rogers
                     and his assistants, and acknowledging with regrets
                     the receipt of Henry Rogers's resignation as
                     assistant geologist. 1 p. with address leaf. Henry
                     Darwin Rogers (August 1, 1808-May 29, 1866),
                     geologist, was best known for his 1858 report on
                     the geological survey of Pennsylvania. Brother of
                     William Barton Rogers. He was appointed assistant
                     geologist for the Virginia geological survey on
                     April 2, 1836.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Hot Springs, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 9,
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Hot Springs, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     concerning the lack of mail from his family and
                     reporting on his progress in examining Dibbrell's,
                     Sweet, and other springs in the region near
                     Covington. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1838</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 20,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, informing him of the Board of Public
                     Works's approval of his plans for the ensuing
                     season and reviewing matters concerning Rogers's
                     expense account. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Timothy Taylor, Jr., Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 22,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Timothy Taylor, Jr., Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking
                     for an analysis of a sample of limestone which
                     Taylor had given Rogers for James McIlhaney. 1 p.
                     with address leaf. Timothy Taylor was a member of
                     the House of Delegates from Loudoun County in
                     1838. James McIlhaney had been a State Senator
                     representing Loudoun and Fairfax counties and
                     again held that office during the 1839-1840
                     session.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>V.[two initials illegible] Alexander,
                     Baltimore, Maryland, to Dr. W[illiam] E. A. Aikin,
                     Charlottesville, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 7,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>V.[two initials illegible] Alexander,
                     Baltimore, Maryland, to Dr. W[illiam] E. A. Aikin,
                     Charlottesville, recommending Septimus Norris of
                     Havre de Grace, Maryland, formerly employed by
                     Benjamin Henry Latrobe, for any position which
                     might be available with the Virginia Geological
                     Survey. 1 p. with address leaf. William E. A.
                     Aikin was appointed an assistant geologist by the
                     Board of Public Works effective June 1, 1837.
                     Benjamin Henry Latrobe, Jr. (December 19,
                     1806-October 19, 1878), son of the architect and
                     engineer, was assistant engineer for the
                     construction of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in
                     1838.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Judge J. M. Allen, Syracuse, New York,
                     to William Taylor, Washington, D. C., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 9,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Judge J. M. Allen, Syracuse, New York,
                     to William Taylor, Washington, D. C., asking
                     Taylor to obtain a copy of William Barton Rogers's
                     report on the geological survey of Virginia, or
                     that part of it dealing with "Brine Springs, and
                     the manufacture of Salt"; offering to reciprocate
                     the favor by sending Rogers any geological reports
                     he might want; and reviewing a report on salt he
                     had just obtained. 1 p. with address leaf. William
                     Taylor (October 12, 1791-September 16, 1865)was a
                     physician as well as a member of the U. S. House
                     of Representatives, March 4, 1833-March 3, 1839,
                     from Onondaga County.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 14,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     accepting his offer of a position as assistant
                     geologist with the geological survey of Virginia;
                     desiring a change in the terms of employment with
                     regard to travel expenses and servants; stressing
                     that his geological experience has not included
                     minerals of the tertiary region; describing his
                     immediate travel plans; and enclosing letters of
                     recommendation from James Renwick and John Torrey.
                     3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James Renwick, Columbia College, New
                     York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 14,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James Renwick, Columbia College, New
                     York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville,
                     recommending George W. Boyd for the position of
                     assistant geologist. 1 p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>John Torrey, College of Physicians and
                     Surgeons, New York, to W. B. Rogers,
                     Charlottesville, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 14,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>John Torrey, College of Physicians and
                     Surgeons, New York, to W. B. Rogers,
                     Charlottesville, recommending George W. Boyd for
                     the position of assistant geologist. 1 p. with
                     address leaf. George W. Boyd was appointed
                     assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works
                     on May 1, 1838. He died on September 23, 1840, at
                     the home of William Barton Rogers in
                     Charlottesville. James Renwick (May 30,
                     1792-January 12, 1863), a leading topographical
                     engineer and chemist. John Torrey (August
                     1796-March 10, 1873), physician, chemist, and
                     botanist whose naturalist system of classification
                     had great influence on American
                     botanists.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Pittstowne, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 16,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Pittstowne, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     accepting his offer of employment and expressing
                     his gratitude. 2 pp. with address leaf. Israel
                     Slade served as an assistant geologist and was
                     paid in part by Rogers with his own personal
                     funds.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 16,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for an
                     analysis of Rawley Springs water and describing
                     the characteristics of a new spring he had
                     discovered last fall. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>E. Foreman, Baltimore, Maryland, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 16,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>E. Foreman, Baltimore, Maryland, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking
                     for a response to his earlier letter seeking
                     employment. 2 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 18,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, discussing amounts due and amounts
                     already paid to Rogers and his assistants in
                     salary and stating that only 1,000 copies of
                     Rogers's report will be printed. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 24,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging his receipt of and response to a
                     letter from Rogers and stating that he is prepared
                     to accept Rogers's original offer of employment. 1
                     p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 30,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning letters which apparently crossed in the
                     mail and repeating his acceptance of Rogers's
                     original offer. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Broadside. Medical College of Richmond,
                     Virginia. Winter term of lectures, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Broadside. Medical College of Richmond,
                     Virginia. Winter term of lectures ... [list of
                     faculty and information on term to begin November
                     5, 1838, of the medical department of
                     Hampden-Sydney College] Aug. L. Warner, M.D., Dean
                     of the Faculty. 1 p. with address leaf to Dr.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 2,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letters of April
                     25 and 27, informing him that he will leave New
                     York by May 6 and giving instructions as to where
                     to direct mail to him in Virginia. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Hot Springs, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 9,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Hot Springs, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     thanking him for sending a check; discussing his
                     financial needs; describing his geological
                     observations in the neighborhood of Fincastle; and
                     mentioning his plans to visit Catawba Iron Works.
                     3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>E[ben] N. Hosford (?), Troy, New York,
                     to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 14,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>E[ben] N. Hosford (?), Troy, New York,
                     to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, referring
                     to an earlier letter to Rogers seeking employment
                     and to an expected response from Rogers which
                     probably had miscarried and informing Rogers that
                     since he has been induced to take the position in
                     New York vacated by George W. Boyd, he will not be
                     able to work with Rogers this summer but would
                     like to be taken on the following summer if the
                     opportunity is available. 2 pp. with address leaf.
                     Eben Norton Horsford (?) (July 27, 1818-January 1,
                     1893), chemist, graduated from Rensselaer (?)
                     Polytechnic Institute in 1838, then worked on the
                     New York State Natural History Survey. After
                     further study in Germany, 1844-1847, he introduced
                     European chemical knowledge and methods to America
                     at Harvard and later made a fortune in Rumford
                     Chemical Company.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 18,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, mentioning amounts deposited in the Bank
                     of Virginia to Rogers's and William E. A. Aikin's
                     credit, describing the fiscal problems of the
                     geological survey, and speculating upon the
                     likelihood of the General Assembly's dropping the
                     survey from the budget. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Lafayette, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 17,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Lafayette, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing a peculiar conglomerate found on
                     McAfee's Knob on Catawba Mountain; mentioning a
                     box of specimens he sent from Catawba Iron Works
                     and a box of speciments from the foot of North
                     Mountain; reporting on plaster dug near Buford's
                     Gap; and outlining his plans to proceed through
                     Salem, Lafayette, Montgomery Courthouse, and
                     Christiansburg. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Sweet Springs, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 19,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Sweet Springs, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing
                     him that he was unable to inspect a fault line
                     because the letter from Rogers instructing him to
                     do so arrived too late; describing his geological
                     investigations around Covington and Callaghan's
                     and Peters Mountain; discussing his plans to
                     continue along the western side of Peters
                     Mountain; and commenting on the general business
                     of the survey and on his financial problems. 6 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Grey Sulphur, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 23,
                     [1838]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Grey Sulphur, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating his
                     disappointment in finding no mail waiting for him;
                     reporting on the geology of Peters Mountain; and
                     announcing his plans to proceed to Callaghan's. 2
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 26,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>John Sites, Rawley Springs, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for the
                     analysis of the Rawley Springs water which he
                     wants to publish. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J. W. Dibrell, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 26,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J. W. Dibrell, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, giving a
                     description of Daggers Springs in Botetourt
                     County, their location, and several routes to get
                     to them and complaining about his financial
                     misfortunes. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Newbern, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 26,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Newbern, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing his procedures and the results of his
                     analysis of a sample of Yellow Springs water
                     through evaporation and the collection of residue;
                     mentioning a box of specimens sent to Lynchburg;
                     describing plans to go to Wythe Courthouse by way
                     of the Lead Mines; and complaining of financial
                     problems. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 29,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, concerning funds deposited to the
                     account of James B. Rogers, and commenting on an
                     address Rogers had given. 1 p. with address leaf.
                     James Blythe Rogers (February 11, 1802-June 15,
                     1852), chemist, brother of William Barton Rogers,
                     was best known for his contributions to the
                     development of methods of chemical analysis. He
                     was appointed assistant geologist by the Board of
                     Public Works in May 1837. He resigned in April
                     1840 and was reappointed assistant geologist by
                     the Board of Public Works on May 1,
                     1841.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William Seymour, Moorefield, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 30,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>William Seymour, Moorefield, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for the
                     results of the chemical analysis of water from
                     Howard's Lick Spring. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Samuel McCamant, Grayson Courthouse, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 3,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Samuel McCamant, Grayson Courthouse, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking
                     for the results of the chemical analysis of spring
                     water for the Grayson Sulphur Springs Company. 1
                     p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Saltville, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 11,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Saltville, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     concerning the breaking down of his horses;
                     describing the geology of the Macks Mountains and
                     Dry Run Gap; discussing the contents of a specimen
                     box; and mentioning the roads made almost
                     impossible by rain. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Seyberts, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 17,
                     [1838]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Seyberts, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his
                     recent travels; complaining of the lack of mail
                     from Rogers; discussing his financial problems;
                     and describing the geology around Augusta Springs.
                     3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 20,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], Richmond, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, explaining the problems
                     resulting from his having forgotten some weights
                     for use in chemical analysis; giving the analysis
                     of some spring water and describing the methods
                     used to obtain it; mentioning plans to depart for
                     the Blue Sulphur Springs; discussing the geology
                     of Augusta Springs; describing a meeting with Dr.
                     Daubeny; and referring to the state of his own
                     health. 3 pp. with address leaf. Charles Giles
                     Bridle Daubeny (February 11, 1795-December 13,
                     1867), M.D., F.R.S., was professor of chemistry
                     and botany at Oxford University.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 26,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs],
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     expressing his concern about not receiving a
                     letter from him; giving an analysis of Blue
                     Sulphur Springs water; asking for instructions on
                     how to proceed at the Salt and Red Sulphur Springs
                     and a question about sandstone found on Muddy
                     Creek Mountain; amd stating his immediate plans
                     for collecting samples. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Tazewell Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 27,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Tazewell Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing his travels of the last ten
                     days in eastern Tazewell County, in particular the
                     geology of Abbs Valley; outlining his plans to
                     proceed to Russell County in hope of meeting with
                     General Johnson there; and mentioning financial
                     matters. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William Robertson, Jr., Salt Sulphur
                     Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 3,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>William Robertson, Jr., Salt Sulphur
                     Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing a new spring opened by
                     Erskine and Caruthers, informing him of the
                     imminent arrival of a sample of water from it; and
                     requesting an analysis as soon as convenient. 1 p.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Stephen Grubs, Nineveh, Frederick
                     County, to James B. Rogers, University of
                     [Virginia], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 7,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Stephen Grubs, Nineveh, Frederick
                     County, to James B. Rogers, University of
                     [Virginia], writing Rogers to call upon him on his
                     next trip to the area, as he knows more about
                     minerals in the area and has more samples in his
                     possession than anyone else in the vicinity. 1 p.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 9,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs],
                     to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, giving an
                     analysis of old and new springs there; describing
                     the geology of the Crows Ferry-Sweet Springs
                     region; and asking for information concerning his
                     family. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Russell Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 10,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Russell Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, thanking him for his recent letters;
                     discussing their proposed excursion down
                     Guyandotte River; complaining about the local
                     food; and mentioning samples sent by way of
                     Lynchburg. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Osborn's Ford,
                     Scott County, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 19,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Osborn's Ford,
                     Scott County, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing the geology of Russell County
                     and his plan to explore Scott and Lee Counties. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Pearisburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, Fincastle, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 23,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Pearisburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, Fincastle, describing the geology of
                     the New River Gap and Peters Mountain area and
                     hoping to see him in Fincastle. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>R. H. Toler, J. N. Brooks, and William
                     S. Reid, Jr., Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers,
                     [Lynchburg], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 21,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>R. H. Toler, J. N. Brooks, and William
                     S. Reid, Jr., Lynchburg, to William B. Rogers,
                     [Lynchburg], thanking him on behalf of the
                     Lynchburg Young Men's Society for the lecture
                     "delivered before them this evening," and
                     requesting a copy for publication. 1 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Cove Creek,
                     Scott County, to [William B. Rogers], n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 26,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Cove Creek, Scott
                     County, to [William B. Rogers], n.p., expressing
                     surprise that Rogers had not received his earlier
                     letters; describing his work between New River and
                     Cove Creek; outlining his plans for exploring
                     Tazewell and Mercer counties and Abbs Valley; and
                     discussing the geology of Little Stoney Creek, the
                     Clinch Mountain area, and the Powell's Valley
                     vicinity. 4 pp., incomplete.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], Fincastle, to
                     "Dear Sir" [Lynchburg Young Men's Society,
                     Lynchburg], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 27,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], Fincastle, to "Dear
                     Sir" [Lynchburg Young Men's Society, Lynchburg],
                     regretting that he left Lynchburg in such haste
                     that he forgot to reply "in form" to the request
                     of the society. 1 p., incomplete.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Scott Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 12,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Scott Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing his work in Scott and
                     Washington counties and the family problems which
                     will require him to return to Baltimore in
                     mid-October; discussing the geology of Lee County;
                     and mentioning his trouble with his horses and
                     servant. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Hedgesville,
                     Berkeley County, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 25,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Hedgesville,
                     Berkeley County, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing what remains to be done in
                     the area; discussing the hot and bug-infested
                     mountains; mentioning smome varieties of slate he
                     has seen; and disagreeing with Rogers about olive
                     slate alleged to exist between Little and Big
                     Timber Ridge. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Waynesboro, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 10,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Waynesboro, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     receipt of Rogers's letter of September 8 and
                     presenting a day by day account of his travels and
                     observations of the geology of the mountains
                     around Lexington and the Tye River Gap. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Luray, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 19 and 20,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Luray, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his
                     route from Waynesboro to Luray; mentioning a two
                     to three week old forest fire still burning near
                     Brown's Gap and his visit to the Shenandoah Iron
                     Works; and charting the relationship between the
                     temperature at which water boils and varous
                     altitudes in the Blue Ridge. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, University of Virginia,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 22,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, University of Virginia,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning a visit to Blackford's iron furnace and
                     describing a ride up Stony Manpeak and the
                     greenstone and various minerals found there. 2 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, University of Virginia,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 27,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, University of Virginia,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     stating that he had left specimens under the
                     dining room table in a champagne bucket and noting
                     other details for Rogers's benefit in concluding
                     the season's work on the survey. 1 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1839</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 3,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's
                     letters of January 13 and 29; discussing financial
                     matters, particularly those of Dr. [William E. A.]
                     Aikin; speculating on the possibility that the
                     General Assembly will suspend the continuation of
                     the survey, and giving Aikin's account current
                     with the state and with Rogers. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 20,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, relating that on
                     his way north he had seen both Henry D. Rogers and
                     Robert Rogers in Philadelphia; giving prices for
                     certain chemicals; presenting his plans for
                     returning to Virginia in April; discussing mineral
                     specimens he plans to bring; reviewing
                     sarcastically a recent article concerning red
                     sandstone; and mentioning a new book on silurian
                     rocks. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, Baltimore, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 13,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>William E. A. Aikin, Baltimore, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing him that he must resign from the survey
                     because he has been appointed Governor of the
                     Infirmary at the University of Maryland, a
                     position which requires his continuous presence. 2
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 15,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, concerning financial
                     matters; informing him that his reports have been
                     printed and are at hand; and a postscript
                     expressing his regrets over Rogers's having been
                     thrown from a carriage and urging him not to
                     overwork. 2 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to "Dear Henry" [D. Robers], n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 17,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to "Dear Henry" [D. Robers], n.p.,
                     reporting on the "results of my experiments in
                     regard to the composition and hydraulic character
                     of our secondary limestones ... with an account of
                     the method [used to separate] the magnesia and
                     lime." 3 pp., incomplete [draft].</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Millborough, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 15,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Millborough, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, referring to
                     his lame horse; describing the geology of Panther
                     Gap and Buffalo Gap; detailing his plans to
                     proceed through Clifton Forge to the vicinity of
                     Rich Patch; and discussing his need of a dentist.
                     3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to [Caleb Briggs], n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 20,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to [Caleb Briggs], n.p., offering him a
                     position as assistant geologist, in place of
                     Aikin, and describing the requirements of the job.
                     3 pp., incomplete.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Scottsville, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 28,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Scottsville, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of the country between Charlottesville and
                     Scottsville and between Scottsville and Warren
                     along the James River and Kanawha Canal; reporting
                     on some durable sandstone found at Green Mountain
                     twelve miles west of Scottsville; and mentioning
                     iron ore found at Scottsville. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., New York, New York,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 28,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Caleb Briggs, Jr., New York, New York,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     accepting the offer of the position of assistant
                     geologist; explaining the necessity of his
                     visiting Boston and Ohio before coming to
                     Virginia; stating his experience as head of the
                     chemistry and natural history department at
                     Rensellaer (sp.?) Polytechnic Institute and as
                     assistant geologist on the geological surveys of
                     New York and Ohio; and inquiring about a position
                     on the faculty of Emory and Henry College. 3 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 12,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his
                     travels and the geology of the country between
                     Scottsville and New Market, in the vicinity of New
                     Market, between New Market and Warminster, and
                     between Warminster and Maysville. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Maysville, Buckingham
                     County, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 19,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Maysville, Buckingham
                     County, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing the geology of the country
                     between Maysville and Lynchburg and discussing the
                     Buckingham County gold mines. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Wythe County, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 21 and 22,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Wythe County, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his
                     analysis of the limestone of Blacksburg,
                     Christiansburg, Newbern, Robison's Tract, and
                     Little Walkers Mountain and asking for further
                     instructions. 7 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 23,
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, concerning his lame horse, Dragon, and
                     accusing William E. A. Aikin of mistreating him;
                     presenting extracts from his notes describing
                     Panther Gap, the gap at Clifton Forge, Brands
                     Mountain, and Falling Spring Valley; and
                     discussing the new construction at White Sulphur
                     Springs. 8 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Albany, New York,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 24,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Albany, New York,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of May
                     13; enclosing a testimonial letter from Professor
                     [Amos] Eaton [sent to Board of Public Works by
                     Rogers and returned to Briggs on July 21, 1843, at
                     his request]; and asking for further instructions.
                     1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 26,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the
                     geology of Buckingham, Cumberland, and Prince
                     Edward counties; discussing his lack of funds; and
                     listing the contents of four boxes of specimens. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Broadside. Western Enquirer, Lewisburg,
                     Virginia. To the Publick. White Sulphur Springs,
                     Greenbrier County, Va. 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 31,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Broadside. Western Enquirer, Lewisburg,
                     Virginia. To the Publick. White Sulphur Springs,
                     Greenbrier County, Va. [Testimonials as to the
                     storage and keeping quality of water from the
                     springs.] On reverse: Prof. Wm. B. Rogers,
                     University, Va. 1 p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 2,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Maysville, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of Buckingham, Cumberland, and Prince
                     Edward counties. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Frankfort, to [William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 4 and 5,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Frankfort, to [William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia], giving him bad
                     news of a broken down horse, bad weather, and a
                     broken altitude thermometer; reporting on the
                     geology of the Greenbrier River-Greenbrier
                     Mountain area; discussing his plans to proceed
                     toward New River; and mentioning his health.
                     Attached is a section of the area described in the
                     letter and a request for money and for a small
                     pocket thermometer. 5 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 5,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, White Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his recent
                     letter; answering questions posed about the
                     geology of the mountains around Covington;
                     commenting on Beard's Mountain and the new spring
                     at White Sulphur Springs; asking for a new
                     thermometer; and discussing the mail. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Columbus, [Ohio],
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 6,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Columbus, [Ohio],
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing Rogers that he had sent him a letter [on
                     May 24] enclosing a testimonial from Professor
                     Eaton, which he feared had miscarried, and asking
                     if his presence on the survey was still desired. 1
                     p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Wythe Court House, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 8,
                     [1839]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Wythe Court House, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     receipt of Rogers's letter of May 28; describing
                     his suffering resulting from a piece of rock
                     imbedding itself in his eye; and discussing the
                     geology of Lick Mountain, New River, and Iron
                     Mountain. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 10,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, informing him that the Board of
                     Public Works had that day confirmed Rogers's
                     appointment of Caleb Briggs as assistant
                     geologist; discussing financial matters; and
                     rendering an account of contingent expenses due
                     Rogers. 1 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 10,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the
                     geology of Amherst County, especially in the
                     vicinity of Buffalo Ridge, White's Gap, Cold
                     Mountain, Mount Pleasant, and Long Mountain;
                     mentioning various persons he encountered on his
                     way; outlining his plans to travel through
                     Bedford, Campbell, Charlotte, Franklin, and
                     Pittsylvania counties to Halifax County; hoping
                     Rogers can join him; and discussing financial
                     matters. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur
                     [Springs], to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 14 and 15,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Blue Sulphur [Springs],
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing the geology of the area of Frankfort,
                     the Great Levels, Culbertsons Creek, Brushy Ridge,
                     Sinking Creek, and Greenbrier Mountain; including
                     a section of the same area; including a section of
                     the same area; and discussing the Blue Sulphur
                     Springs. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Liberty, Bedford
                     County, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 17,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Liberty, Bedford County,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing the affliction of his horse, Dragon,
                     and how he treated it and listing the contents of
                     two sample boxes. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Wythe C[ourt] House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 20,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Wythe C[ourt] House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     complaining that his trunk has been lost;
                     discussing his problems with horses; mentioning
                     his plans to examine Little Walkers Mountain; and
                     describing the geology of the area around Walkers
                     Creek, Burk's Garden, and Brushy Mountain. 3 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Campbell Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 22,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Campbell Court House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing minerals found in Beford and Campbell
                     counties. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 26,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of June 13;
                     describing his plans to proceed to Danville,
                     Leaksville, and back to Lynchburg to spend a few
                     days drawing sections; and asking that his
                     quarter's salary be sent to Lynchburg. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, Millers Locust Grove,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 27 and 28,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>James B. Rogers, Millers Locust Grove,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     discussing the lameness of his horse, Billy, and
                     describing the geology of Muddy Creek Mountain,
                     Meadow Mountain, Guinn's Spring, the falls of New
                     River, and the Little and Big Sewells. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 27,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Charlotte Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing the geology of parts of Albemarle,
                     Nelson, Buckingham, Cumberland, Amherst, Prince
                     Edward, Bedford, Campbell, and Charlotte counties
                     and describing what remained to be examined in
                     those counties. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, Yellow Springs, Chester County,
                     Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 9,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, Yellow Springs, Chester County,
                     Pennsylvania, describing the geology of the areas
                     around Leaksville, Smith River, White Oak
                     Mountain, Pittsylvania Court House, Danville, and
                     Campbell Court House. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[harles] B. Hayden, Woodstock, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 9,
                     [1839]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[harles] B. Hayden, Woodstock, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, concerning his
                     treatment of and recovery from a recent "digestive
                     affection"; referring obscurely to the "Smoot
                     affair," of which he took no "public notice;" and
                     describing his plans to proceed to Strasburg,
                     Martinsburg, and Winchester. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 11,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that
                     he hoped Rogers could join him before September 1
                     and mentioning that he had visited Bedford and
                     Franklin counties and planned to go to Patrick and
                     Henry counties next. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Pittsylvania Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Pittsylvania Court
                     House, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, concerning the geology of Campbell,
                     Bedford, Franklin, Pittsylvania, and Halifax
                     counties; mentioning limestone used in Ross's new
                     iron works and at the Rocky Mount furnace;
                     commenting upon the proper stone to use as a
                     hearthstone in an iron furnace; and mentioning the
                     sections he had been drawing. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 3,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     regarding Rogers's trunk; describing coal beds
                     along the Ohio River on the Virginia side;
                     mentioning residents eager to render assistance to
                     the geologists; and touching upon his health. 3 p.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Danville, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 15,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Danville, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, briefly describing
                     limestone found in Patrick and Henry counties;
                     mentioning an iron furnace and forge on Goblintown
                     Creek in Patrick County; and noting globular
                     greenstone found near Danville. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Wellsburg
                     [Wellsville], Ohio, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 17,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Wellsburg
                     [Wellsville], Ohio, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, describing limestone and
                     coal ground near Wheeling, Virginia, and
                     speculating on the extent of these seams and
                     discussing an iron furnace and mines formerly in
                     operation above Steubenville in Virginia. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 22,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Lynchburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     Rogers's letter of September 7; describing a
                     curious, large piece of sandstone with depressions
                     like those caused by horses hooves near White Oak
                     Mountain in Pittsylvania county and mentioning his
                     plans to go by way of Amherst and Nelson counties
                     to the University. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Middletown,
                     Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 14,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Middletown,
                     Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, describing the geology of
                     Virginia along the Ohio River; presenting a table
                     showing coal and other minerals found at various
                     levels in the "Pittsburg Coal Series" near
                     Wheeling; and mentioning his financial problems. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 30,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing Rogers of his plans to proceed to
                     Charlottesville because he has run out of money
                     and discussing the problems of tracing the various
                     "strata composing the Wheeling Series." 2 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 28,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, concerning the financial affairs of
                     the survey and discussing the problems facing the
                     General Assembly about to convene. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 7,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     regretting his leaving his section drawings and
                     notes with Rogers when he had the means of working
                     on them in New York and returning them to Virginia
                     and proposing a four to six week visit to the
                     University to catalog fossils. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, to W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 13,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, to W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, n.p.,
                     enclosing as much of the money demanded by Aikin
                     as Rogers was able to procure and asking for a
                     receipt; recalling his past liberality with Aikin
                     in financial matters; reminding him that he was
                     paid $200. more per year than any other assistant
                     geologist; and stating that the amount and quality
                     of work produced by Aikin was not worth the extra
                     pay and the trouble he had caused Rogers. 2 pp.,
                     draft.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 19,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, concerning the financial affairs of
                     the survey and predicting a great reduction of
                     funds for the survey or its complete elimination
                     as a result of economic conditions and the
                     depleted state of the Treasury. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 26,
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, wishing
                     him "many happy returns of the season"; noting
                     that he had received no response from Rogers to
                     his letter of December 7; informing him that he
                     had almost accompanied a friend to Trinidad; and
                     saying that he planned to spend part of the winter
                     in Charleston and Savannah and hoped to stop by
                     Charlottesville on his way there. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>E. C. Howard, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 28,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>E. C. Howard, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of
                     January 23; referring to financial affairs; and
                     telling him that James Brown, Jr., would have
                     written Rogers himself if it were not for the
                     press of business. 1 p. with address leaf. E. C.
                     Howard was the second clerk in the Second
                     Auditor's Office.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., University of
                     Virginia, to William B. Rogers, Richmond, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 6,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., University of
                     Virginia, to William B. Rogers, Richmond,
                     describing specimens of limestones and including
                     the amount of carb[olic?] acid found in each
                     sample. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 19,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter
                     of March 16 and noting the deposit of funds to the
                     credit of Rogers and Caleb Briggs, Jr.; wishing he
                     would come to Richmond to settle his accounts for
                     the year; and repeating what he had heard from
                     members of the General Assembly: "that you will
                     complete your duties during the year commencing 2d
                     April next." 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 31,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing Rogers that Henry D. Rogers's opinions
                     of the Hudson River slates have been vindicated by
                     New York geologists; presenting his plans to leave
                     for Virginia on April 15 by way of Philadelphia,
                     Baltimore, and Richmond; offering to take care of
                     any business for Rogers that might need doing in
                     those cities; and enclosing his account due April
                     1 (not found). 2 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 17,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's
                     letter of April 7; mentioning financial matters;
                     informing him that the Board of Public Works had
                     approved all of his plan of operation for the
                     coming year except that part requesting an
                     additional assistant; acknowledging receipt of
                     James B. Roger's resignation and expressing his
                     regrets; and expressing concern for his health. 1
                     p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Harrisonburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 19,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Harrisonburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the
                     geology of Turk's Gap and Payne's Run and
                     including rough pencil sketches of sections of the
                     area described. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Robert Mills, Washington, D.C., to
                     [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 25,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Robert Mills, Washington, D.C., to
                     [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     asking for copies of Rogers's reports or other
                     information pertaining to the geology of Jackson's
                     River, in particular around Warm Springs and Hot
                     Springs, and commenting on the importance of the
                     survey and the mineral wealth of Virginia. 2 pp.
                     with address leaf. Robert Mills (August 12,
                     1781-March 3, 1855), architect and engineer, was
                     at this time Architect of Public Buildings for the
                     federal government.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Luray, to W. B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 28,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Luray, to W. B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, describing the geology of
                     the mountainous area around Luray. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 3,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology observed along the roads from
                     Charlottesville to Richmond and mentioning repairs
                     made to his buggy. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Cloverdale, to
                     William Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 5,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Cloverdale, to
                     William Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning
                     his baggage which had gone on the wrong stage and
                     a $20 bank note which he had lost. 2 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Culpeper Court House,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 11,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Culpeper Court House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     discussing the geology along the roads from
                     Richmond to Culpeper by way of Fredericksburg. 1
                     p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Front Royal, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 13,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Front Royal, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the
                     charms of springtime in the mountains and
                     describing the geology observed by taking
                     different routes between Front Royal and Strasburg
                     via Middletown. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Snickers Ferry, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 20,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Snickers Ferry, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     receipt of his letter of May 4 and explaining why
                     he must vary from Rogers's directions with regard
                     to collecting specimens around Strasburg;
                     discussing the geology of the country between
                     Front Royal, Winchester, and Snickers Ferry;
                     describing a sulphur spring at Fort Valley; and
                     commenting on the state of his own and Rogers's
                     health. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Brocks Gap, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 23,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Brocks Gap, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of the country around Hardy County,
                     Virginia, including the Alleghany Mountain, the
                     North Fork of the South Branch of the Potomac
                     River, and various creeks. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Paris, Fauquier County,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 24,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Paris, Fauquier County,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     discussing the geology of the country along his
                     route from Culpeper County through Fairfax to
                     Fredericksburg and from there through Warrenton to
                     Paris; stating his intention to travel to
                     Alexandria, then up the Potomac River through
                     Harper's Ferry; noting that some instruments he
                     wanted had not yet arrived at Fredericksburg; and
                     relating an encounter with a Louisa Railroad train
                     in which his horse lay down with fright. 3 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 28,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating
                     that the horse and buggy arranged for him by
                     Rogers had proved unsatisfactory and that he had
                     had to purchase new ones; asking for money for
                     these purchases and for hiring a guide
                     occasionally; and commenting on his health and the
                     safe transportation of his boiling point
                     thermometer. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Leesburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 7,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Leesburg, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning Boyd's
                     health; giving an account of the geology
                     encountered on his way around Upperville,
                     Middleburg, Aldie, Leesburg, and Dranesville; and
                     describing the superior qualities of a turnpike
                     paved with serpentine instead of the usual
                     greenstone and quartz. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 13,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter
                     of June 4; saying that $500 had been deposited to
                     his credit; and warning him of a forthcoming
                     request for additional explanations and vouchers
                     before his expense account could be approved. 1 p.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 14,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning his
                     geological observations in Loudoun County and
                     along the Potomac River near Harper's Ferry. 2 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Milford, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 16,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Milford, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, complaining of
                     being delayed by a lame horse and discussing the
                     geology around Harper's Ferry and Shanandale
                     Springs. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 4,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Marietta, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letters of June 4 and
                     21; discussing a check enclosed in the first
                     letter and his concern over Rogers's health;
                     concluding that there are no valuable coal beds
                     along the Ohio River from Fishing Creek to Carr's
                     River; describing the geology of the same area;
                     and mentioning that he had recovered Rogers's
                     trunk. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Letart, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 15,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Letart, Ohio, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
                     acknowledging receipt of his recent letter;
                     explaining why he could not follow Rogers's
                     instructions with regard to the trunk; and
                     describing the distribution of coal along the Ohio
                     River above and below Parkersburg. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Carr's or Kerr's
                     Run, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia,
                     Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 18,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Carr's or Kerr's
                     Run, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia,
                     Pennsylvania, stating that he had determined that
                     the center of the coal basin lay somewhere between
                     Big Mill Creek and Letart Falls and describing the
                     geology of the area; giving an account of his
                     recent illnesses; and answering, mostly in the
                     negative, Rogers's inquiry as to the abundance of
                     "fair ladies and interesting damsels" in western
                     Virginia. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Point Pleasant, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 25,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Point Pleasant, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
                     hoping to meet with him soon to discuss matters
                     pertaining to the geology of that part of the
                     state; discussing the Carr's Run coal seam and the
                     record of a boring for a salt well at the mouth of
                     Leading Creek; and informing him of his plans to
                     proceed to Guyandotte and his hopes of receiving a
                     letter there. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Buchanan, to W. B.
                     Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 29,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Buchanan, to W. B.
                     Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, asking for a
                     new thermometer to replace one which had been
                     broken; describing the geology of Botetourt and
                     Alleghany counties around Short Hill, Purgatory
                     Mountain, Craig's Creek, Rich Patch Mountain, and
                     Covington; discussing the lack of adequate maps
                     and the difficulty of mapping the region; and
                     mentioning the geology of the James River Gap. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 20,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning the length of time required to complete
                     his survey of the Ohio River; discussing the coal
                     seams in the region; mentioning a financial
                     matter; giving news of his broken boiling point
                     thermometer; and describing the sickness in the
                     area which he had thus far escaped. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Christiansburg, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 26,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Christiansburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     intricate geology of the region from Buchanan to
                     Christiansburg and asking for a letter and more
                     detailed instructions as to what course to follow.
                     4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 5,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing his
                     increasingly severe attacks of asthma, his
                     attempts to carry on his wrok despite his health,
                     and his hopes of joining Rogers at the University
                     in a few days. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 8,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the
                     difficulties encountered in making a section
                     drawing of the strata along the Little Kanawha
                     River and describing the geology of the region. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 12,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     receipt of his two letters from White Sulphur
                     Springs; outlining the difficulty of his work
                     because of the rugged and wild terrain; and
                     describing his route near New River. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 18,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     discussing his work and the geology in the
                     vicinity of Weston and Parkersburg and mentioning
                     his plans for proceeding to Clarksburg and his
                     need for money. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Jeffersonville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 27,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Jeffersonville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of the area around New River, East River,
                     Mercer County, and Abbs Valley. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 28,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning the lack of mail; describing his work
                     along the route of the North Western Turnpike;
                     discussing his plans to proceed to Morgantown; and
                     asking again for money. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Morgantown, to
                     William B. Rogers, Richmond, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 8 and 10,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Morgantown, to
                     William B. Rogers, Richmond, commisserating with
                     him over the sickness and death of George W. Boyd;
                     describing the geology of the country between
                     Bridgeport and Morgantown; mentioning a map of a
                     portion of Harrison County which he had drawn; and
                     describing the coal beds found on Scot's Creek. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Scott Court House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 12,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Scott Court House, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing his sufferings and those of his horse
                     caused by the rough terrain between Tazewell Court
                     House and Scott Court House and by the small
                     amounts of food "served up in the most filthy and
                     loathesome manner"; discussing the geology of Bear
                     Town, Baptist Valley, and the Clinch River area;
                     and mentioning a man he met named Wells who was
                     examining coal seams and claimed to be employed by
                     the state. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Monongalia County,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October [17],
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Monongalia County,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     describing his exploration of Decker's Creek and
                     the iron ores found there and revealing that he
                     had hired Moses Wells, a resident of the area, to
                     assist him. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Smithfield,
                     Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 29 and November
                     1, 1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Smithfield,
                     Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers,
                     University of Virginia, mentioning that he has
                     completed a section drawing from Morgantown to the
                     headwaters of Scots River; describing iron ore and
                     coal seams found in the vicinity of Henry Clay
                     Furnace and a forge near Ice's Ferry; stating that
                     he has traced the strata of the area around White
                     Day Creek; and telling of his need for more money
                     and relief from foul weather. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 31,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging
                     receipt of Rogers's letter of September 28;
                     answering, in response to Rogers's question, that
                     he had filled almost five boxes full of specimens;
                     and discussing the relative heights of Balsam
                     Mountain and the Peaks of Otter and the cold
                     weather. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Palatine Hill, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 14,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Palatine Hill, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing Rogers that he had gathered enough data
                     for a section drawing of the Monongalia River
                     region about 25 miles long and stating that the
                     weather had turned so cold that he was about to
                     start for the University but would need more money
                     first. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 21,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of
                     November 10 and the enclosed check and announcing
                     his intention to complete the tracing of the
                     Morgantown Coal Seam despoite the increasingly
                     disagreeable weather. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Charlottesville, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 16,
                     [1840]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Charlottesville, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking
                     Rogers to make arrangements for him to draw his
                     salary since deep mud on the road prevented Slade
                     from coming himself. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 21,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of
                     December 17 concerning Israel Slade's salary;
                     expressing his regrets over Rogers's ill health;
                     and voicing his fears of "great curtailments" in
                     spending by the General Assembly. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, to Henry D. Rogers, Philadelphia,
                     Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 22,
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, to Henry D. Rogers, Philadelphia,
                     Pennsylvania, informing him that Israel Slade is
                     about to leave for Philadelphia with iron ore
                     samples for analysis, that Slade is highly nervous
                     and needs adequate space in which to work, and
                     that their brother Robert Rogers might "understand
                     best how to get along with him"; wishing James or
                     Robert Rogers might aid in the analysis;
                     commenting on the coal fields near Richmond;
                     noting that he always fretted over observations
                     omitted by his assistants in the field and felt
                     that he could satisfy his mind more with one week
                     of his own field work than with "months" of that
                     done by his assistants; worrying about the lack of
                     news from Richmond on the fate of the survey in
                     the General Assembly; and referring to family
                     matters. 4 pp. [draft or copy?]</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1841</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W. H. Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 13,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W. H. Brown, Second Auditor's Office,
                     Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, advising him that before the Board of
                     Public Works can pay the amount due Rogers as
                     administrator of George W. Boyd's estate, he must
                     submit an affidavit as to the date of Boyd's
                     death; stating that the health of Brown's farther
                     (James Brown, Jr.) is improving; and informing him
                     that the survey survived for another year by a
                     close vote in the House of Delegates, but that it
                     had not yet passed in the Senate. 1 p. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Temple Gwathmey, Richmond, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 19,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Temple Gwathmey, Richmond, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, saying that he had
                     heard that Rogers's report concerning the coal of
                     Chesterfield County placed the coal taken from Mr.
                     Heth's deep mine in a category inferior to any
                     other south side coal; that it was the impression
                     in Richmond that Heth's coal was in fact superior
                     rather than inferior; that there may have been an
                     error in the Printing of Rogers's report; that if
                     such was the case it should be corrected through
                     early publication in the newspapers; and that
                     Gwathmey would be glad to see to this correciton
                     for Rogers. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, Pittstown, New York, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 20,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, Pittstown, New York, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing
                     the rigors of winter in upstate New York and
                     believing that spring was well advanced in
                     Virginia; revealing that he had spent so much time
                     in the company of his friends over the winter that
                     he had hardly thought of geology; and regreting
                     that the snow has prevented him from examining the
                     strata in his neighborhood. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., McGee's Inn, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 29,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., McGee's Inn, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning a letter he forgot to mail and asking
                     for a copy of Rogers's report for 1837-1838. 1 p.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Evan T. Ellicott, Monogalia Iron Works
                     near Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Evan T. Ellicott, Monogalia Iron Works
                     near Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, stating that he had read Rogers's
                     last report and found it of great practical
                     interest since he is engaged in iron
                     manufacturing; that Caleb Briggs, Jr., had
                     examined the area near the iron works last season;
                     that a vein of hematite ore had been found on a
                     hill near the Henry Clay furnace; that he would
                     like to have a geologist come to examine the cleft
                     in Laurel Mountain made by Cheat River, while
                     Ellicott was at the iron works; and offering to
                     send a sample of the hematite ore to Rogers. 2 pp.
                     with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 3,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, informing him that his and Israel
                     Slade's claims had been allowed and the money
                     deposited and that his brother James B. Rogers had
                     been appointed assistant geologist effective May
                     1. 1 p. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>I[srael] Slade, N. W. Turnpike at
                     Kuykendall's, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 8,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>I[srael] Slade, N. W. Turnpike at
                     Kuykendall's, to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, giving an account of the observations
                     made by Slade and Caleb Briggs, Jr., on their
                     route from Massanutten Mountain through Winchester
                     to Kuykendall's. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 16,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     mentioning his journey from Winchester to
                     Clarksburg in the rain and giving an account of
                     the production of a salt well near Cheat River
                     Bridge. 2 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 1,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 20;
                     informing him that he had completed the tracing of
                     the Morgantown and Clarksburg coal seam;
                     discussing a fossil stratum which he had traced
                     last season; mentioning his plans to proceed to
                     Morgantown, hire Moses Wells again, and visit Evan
                     T. Ellicott; and expressing his need for another
                     boiling point thermometer and an efficient
                     assistant. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Williamsport, Maryland,
                     to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 4,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Williamsport, Maryland, to
                     W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 17;
                     replying, in answer to Rogers's question, that he
                     had written Rogers twice in May; stating that he
                     had visited the Massanutten Range; describing the
                     mountains around Harpers' Ferry in both Virginia
                     and Maryland; and informing Rogers that he had
                     lost his letter of May 17 and asking him to repeat
                     his instructions concerning the work to be done
                     around Woodstock. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 8,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter
                     of May 28, and informing him that he had deposited
                     the salaries of Caleb Briggs, Jr., and Samuel
                     Lewis in the Bank of Virginia; and adding a
                     personal note concerning Brown's recent illness,
                     Rogers's health, and the approach of the raspberry
                     season, and urging Rogers to come to Richmond and
                     visit him there. 2 pp. with address leaf. Samuel
                     Lewis was appointed by the Board of Public Works
                     on July 11, 1840, to be assistant geologist in the
                     room of Charles B. Hayden, effective June 1,
                     1840.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 15,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     informing him that he had completed his survey
                     along Cheat River near Ellicott's iron works and
                     that he had hired Moses Wells as a guide; noting
                     that he hoped to complete the work in Lewis and
                     Randolph counties within six seeks; and givinig
                     Rogers directions for joining him in Clarksburg. 3
                     pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Strasburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 21,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Strasburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, complaining about
                     the heat and describing the geology of the country
                     between Williamsport, Maryland, and Strasburg. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., Weston, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 27,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating that he
                     had broken his boiling point thermometer by
                     setting it down next to a hornet's nest on a bank
                     of the Monongahela River, then upsetting it when
                     he was stung on the ear; asking Rogers to bring a
                     new one if he came to join them; and requesting
                     more money. 2 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 27,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, seconding
                     Ridgeway's request for another boiling point
                     thermometer; suggesting places for a rendezvous;
                     and describing the coal seam at Weston. 1 p. with
                     address leaf. Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., was appointed
                     assistant geologist on April 15, 1840, in the room
                     of Israel Slade, who had been appointed to the
                     assistantship resigned by James B.
                     Rogers.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Woodstock, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 1,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Woodstock, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that
                     he had finished his survey of Cedar Creek and had
                     boxed the fossils and other specimens for
                     shipment; describing the geology of the area, some
                     iron ore seen and collected, and the beauty of the
                     country; and asking for more money. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly, to
                     William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 14,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly, to William
                     B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
                     acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letters of June
                     27 and July 5; giving a detailed analysis of the
                     geology found between Clarksburg and Beverly; and
                     noting that Moses Wells will soon be leaving him
                     to attend to urgent business. 6 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Beverly, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 19,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Beverly, to William B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the
                     safe arrival of the new thermometer and discussing
                     the geology of the Little North Mountain range. 2
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>T[homas] Ridgeway, Jr., [Beverly], to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 19,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>T[homas] Ridgeway, Jr., [Beverly], to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     thanking him for sending the thermometer and
                     mentioning his plan to obtain a letter waiting for
                     him at Weston. 2 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Bath County, on Bull
                     Pasture [River], to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 31,
                     [1841]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Bath County, on Bull
                     Pasture [River], to W. B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, describing the geology of the country
                     between Tygart's Valley and Bath County;
                     mentioning a climb to the top of some
                     perpendicular rocks overlooking Seneca River; and
                     noting the inaccuracy of current maps in
                     delineating the topography of the Crab Bottom
                     region. 3 pp. with address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly and
                     Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July [26] and August 1,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly and Weston,
                     to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of July 12;
                     reporting that contrary to what Rogers supposed,
                     the survey of Randolph and Lewis counties had not
                     been completed, due to Moses Wells's leaving the
                     survey; describing what remained to be done; and
                     discussing his illness and his plans for
                     completing the work remaining. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 8,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him
                     that he had almost completely recovered from his
                     illness; presenting the points which must yet be
                     examined in order to complete the survey of
                     western Virginia; and suggesting a program to
                     accomplish this. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Panther Gap, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 16,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Panther Gap, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of the country between Bull Pasture River
                     and Staunton and the difficulties he encountered
                     in trying to observe the strata between Great Cow
                     Pasture Mountain and Jennings Gap; acknowledging
                     receipt of his letter in Staunton; discussing the
                     hospitality of some gentlemen in the neighborhood
                     of Staunton who would like Rogers to come give a
                     lecture on geology to them; and presenting a
                     request form Mr. Dudley, tavern keeper at Jennings
                     Gap, that he be paid for the use of a horse by
                     James B. Rogers over a year earlier. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Callahan's, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 30,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Callahan's, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the
                     structure of Mill, Sideling, Walker's and Chestnut
                     Ridge mountains near Cow Pasture River and
                     describing the geology of the mountains and
                     valleys between Panther Gap and Callahan's. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Monroe County, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 2,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Monroe County, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, enclosing residue
                     obtained by evaporating crimson sulphur water
                     which Mr. John Mahon of Union would like for
                     Rogers to analyze. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisport, N. W.
                     Turnpike, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 9,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisport, N. W.
                     Turnpike, to William B. Rogers, University of
                     Virginia, announcing that he had completed the
                     survey of the region; stating that almost all the
                     area near Elk River had been examined and what
                     remains will be inspected by Wells and Ridgeway;
                     complaining that his health had been almost ruined
                     by the hard labor in the field; mentioning the
                     coal measures in Preston and Monongalia counties
                     having been traced; and noting that he planned to
                     write Rogers again in a few days. 3 pp. with
                     address leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, Parisburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 13,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Israel Slade, Parisburg, to W. B.
                     Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the
                     geology of the country between Callaghan's and
                     Parisburg. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Guyandotte, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 25, 1841
                     P.M.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Guyandotte, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of September
                     14; outlining his plans for Wells and Ridgeway to
                     join him in examining the country around
                     Guyandotte River, Logan Court House, Pigeon Creek,
                     Charleston, Summersville, Point Ridge, the Falls
                     of the Kanawha, and Lewisburg; mentioning the
                     geology observed on the Little Kanawha and Elk
                     rivers; asking for more money; considering having
                     Wells examine a narrow coal basin in his travels;
                     and giving news of Rogers's friends in the
                     vicinity. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 17,
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisburg, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter containing a
                     check for $75.; describing the travels of Wells,
                     Ridgeway, and himself as outlined in his letter of
                     September 25; and hoping to return to the
                     University about November 1. 3 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1844-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">7</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 23,
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's
                     Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University
                     of Virginia, recalling that Rogers had planned to
                     communicate to the legislature his views
                     concerning the final report on the geological
                     survey; informing him that several prominent
                     members of the legislature had approached him on
                     that subject; and urging Rogers to leave "your
                     darling University" for a few days as soon as
                     possible to come to Richmond for a personal
                     conversation with the members. 1 p. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 25,
                     1845</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him
                     that the bill before the General Assembly for
                     publication of his final report on the geological
                     survey died for want of zealous support and giving
                     news of the Brown family. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to
                     William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 17,
                     1849</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to William
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, inquiring after
                     his health; informing him that some members of the
                     legislature might attempt to provide for the
                     publication of his geological report and that he
                     doubted there would be concerted opposition,
                     especially if Rogers would come to Richmond and
                     speak to the members, as there were only a few of
                     them who even recalled that there had been a
                     geological survey made; asking him that if he
                     could not come himself, to send Brown such
                     published reports as he could spare and a brief
                     sketch of his plans for a final report so that
                     Brown might argue in his favor. 2 pp. with address
                     leaf.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to James Brown, Jr., [Richmond], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 25,
                     1849</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], University of
                     Virginia, to James Brown, Jr., [Richmond],
                     mentioning a separate bundle of reports sent to
                     Brown; enclosing a copy of his geological map
                     which had excited much favorable comment when it
                     was shown at the British Association, the Royal
                     Geological Society, and the French Academy by
                     Henry D. Rogers; stating that a "nervous debility"
                     prevented him from speaking to the General
                     Assembly, but that he would speak to a few members
                     if Brown thought it needful; and presenting an
                     elaborate outline of the proposed report,
                     consisting of a map, section drawings, and
                     illustrations to exhibit the "geological anatomy"
                     of the state, and a text describing the various
                     regions in detail, with chemical analyses of the
                     ores, minerals, and waters. 6 pp., incomplete
                     draft.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], Boston,
                     Massachusetts, to [Josiah Parsons Cooke, Harvard
                     University], 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 26,
                     1853</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], Boston,
                     Massachusetts, to [Josiah Parsons Cooke, Harvard
                     University], declaring his intention of returning
                     briefly to Virginia to reorganize the geological
                     survey and provide for the publication of the
                     final report in response to a query from Cooke
                     about organizing and supervising a geological
                     survey of Massachusetts; cautioning supporters of
                     the survey from exaggerating the immediate
                     economic benefits of such a survey; stressing the
                     importance of looking to the long, rather than
                     short, term value of the survey; and outlining in
                     seven points the long term benefits which would
                     result from the survey to the advantage of the
                     entire state and her citizens. 5 pp., incomplete
                     draft. Josiah Parsons Cooke (October 12,
                     1827-September 3, 1894), founder of the department
                     of chemistry at Harvard in 1850 at the age of 23
                     and later president of the American Academy of
                     Arts and Sciences.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>[William B. Rogers], Boston,
                     Massachusetts, to Frank G. Ruffin, n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 27,
                     1853</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>[William B. Rogers], Boston,
                     Massachusetts, to Frank G. Ruffin, n.p.,
                     acknowledging receipt of his letter of December 6;
                     expressing his gratitude for the interest
                     displayed by Ruffin and the Agricultural Society
                     in Rogers's geological map and planned report;
                     informing Ruffin of his intention to ask the
                     General Assembly for funds to revise the map and
                     publish his report and of his plans to visit
                     Richmond during the session; declaring that while
                     he appreciates the interest and ehop of anone so
                     inclined, he prefers that his work stand on its
                     own merits and on his reputation, rather than
                     depending upon the testimony of some foreign
                     expert for it s success or failure in the
                     legislature; and discussing the pros and cons of
                     proposed county geological maps and of a
                     scientific department Ruffin was interested in
                     organizing. 7 pp., typescript. Frank Gildart
                     Ruffin (December 1, 1816-June 4, 1892), was at
                     this time editor of the Southern Planter magazine
                     and served as Second Auditor of Virginia from
                     January 1, 1884, until his death.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>W. B. Rogers, Boston, Massachusetts, to
                     F[rank] G. Ruffin, n.p., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 29,
                     1853</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>W. B. Rogers, Boston, Massachusetts, to
                     F[rank] G. Ruffin, n.p., acknowledging receipt of
                     his letter of December 25; mentioning Rogers's
                     lengthy reply on December 27; saying that one
                     reason he left his teaching post at the University
                     of Virginia was so he might concentrate on having
                     his report published; advising Ruffin's society
                     not to attempt too much; and agreeing in principle
                     to Ruffin's request that he give some lectures
                     when in Virginia. 2 pp., typescript.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>D. T. Bisbie, Mecklenburg County, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 15,
                     1854</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>D. T. Bisbie, Mecklenburg County, to W.
                     B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing a
                     copper mine "in an adjoining County" which he and
                     some other men own; giving an unsubstantiated
                     report of an analysis of the ore; and asking for
                     an opinion, based on his description, as to
                     whether the geological indications point to yellow
                     pyrites or sulphuret. 3 pp. with address leaf,
                     torn.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Emma Rogers (Mrs. W. B. Rogers),
                     Boston, Massachusetts, to W[illiam] W. Scott,
                     Librarian of State Library, Richmond, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 10,
                     1903</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Emma Rogers (Mrs. W. B. Rogers), Boston,
                     Massachusetts, to W[illiam] W. Scott, enclosing
                     letters relating to the geological survey of
                     Virginia, to be placed with similar material sent
                     by her to the library two or more years earlier. 2
                     pp. William Wallace Scott (1845-1929) was acting
                     state librarian in 1903. He resigned to become
                     state law librarian in that year.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Reports, sections, lists and field
               notes, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1834-1884</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The reports, sections, lists and field notes are from
               the geologists including William B. Rogers. Many are
               undated. Bound volumes are included.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Arranged by geologist.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">8</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     [1837]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report on the geology of Lee, Russell,
                     Scott, and Washington Counties. 90 pp.,
                     incomplete.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     [1837]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Geological sections of Lee, Russell,
                     Scott, and Washington counties, to accompany the
                     report above. 19 parts, of which numbers 10 and 13
                     are missing.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1838</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">9</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     [1838]</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report on the geology of Lee, Russell,
                     Scott, and Washington Counties, intended in part
                     as a revision of the report of 1837. 32
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William E. A. Aikin, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Geological sections of Lee, Russell,
                     Scott, and Washington counties, to accompany the
                     report above. 13 parts.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1839-1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">
                  10</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Southern Primary Region.
                     Volume I. 1 vol., 116 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Southern Primary Region.
                     Volume II. 1 vol., 42 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Rough notes on geology of
                     northern Virginia, April 28-September 19, 1840. 60
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Northern Primary District.
                     Finished transcription of rough notes above,
                     covering same dates. Entries from September 11
                     through September 19 in the handwriting of James
                     B. Rogers, June 24- August 14, 1841. 1 vol., 132
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>George W. Boyd, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Fossils of Virginia. Arranged by
                     strata, in the handwriting of George W. Boyd. 1
                     vol., 23 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Boxes [of specimens] collected by
                     C. Briggs. Also contains notes by Charles B.
                     Hayden on the geology of Hampshire County, n.d. 1
                     vol., 42 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Catalogue of Rocks. 1 vol., 125
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Catalogue of Rocks. Vol. IV. 1
                     vol., 163 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Valley River and Buffalo Creek
                     Section. Includes sketch map of the area. 47
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. White Day Creek Section and
                     Prickets Creek. Includes sketch map of the area.
                     28 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Geological Examinations on the
                     Monongalia and its Tributaries, Deckers Creek and
                     Scots Run. Includes sketch map of the area. 58
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Appendix to Notes. In vicinity
                     of Cheat River. 3 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Of the Big Sandy Section. 20
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Clarksburg to Parkersburg. 46
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. North Western Turnpike. Cheat
                     River to Clarksburg and the Head of Limestone
                     Creek. 20 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Section from Beverly by Weston
                     to Parkersburg. 33 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Section from the Rich Mountain
                     by Bullstown to the Ohio at Parkersburg. 35
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Section from the North Fork of
                     the South Branch of the Potomac by the way of
                     Clarksburg to the Ohio River at the mouth of
                     Fishing Creek. 41 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. [Geology of the Proctors
                     Run-Fishing Creek area near the Ohio River]. 30
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Main Coal Seam, Upper Coal
                     Series [near the Ohio River]. 30 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Valley of the Ohio. 44
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Caleb Briggs, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Formation XII. Conglomerate on
                     the Eastern Margin of the Ohio Basin. 25
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1836-1837</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. No. 2. Gold Region [of
                     Louisa and Buckingham Counties]. August 8-20. Some
                     entries in the handwriting of William B. Rogers
                     and A. Maxwell Walker. 1 vol., 68 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Rappahannock. [Hanover
                     County to Gloucester County.] September 12-October
                     29. Inverted and at back of volume: field notes of
                     William B. Rogers, July-August 1838, on the
                     geology observed in the vicinity of Lynchburg,
                     Botetourt County, and Lexington. 1 vol., 136
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the Shenandoah
                     Valley region from Rockingham County to Harpers
                     Ferry. September 15-October 3. 1 vol., 35
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Rough notes, undated,
                     covering much the same territory as the volume
                     immediately above. 1 vol., 46 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Tertiary Region [of
                     Tidewater Virginia near James River]. March-May. 1
                     vol., 132 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Continuation of volume
                     immediately above. 1 vol., 28 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Tertiary Region.
                     Continuation of volume immediately above. 1 vol.,
                     43 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the Shenandoah
                     Valley region from Augusta County to Jefferson
                     County, and westward to Hampshire County. July. 1
                     vol., 84 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Continuation of volume
                     immediately above. 1 vol., 21 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Springs. Charts showing
                     date, time, and temperature for various hot
                     springs in western Virginia. November. 1 vol., 21
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1838-1839</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report on the Northern District and the
                     James River Tertiary. January. In two parts:
                     Northern Appalachian Region, 54 pp., with 15 pp.
                     of sections; on the country bordering on James
                     River and its tributaries, 23 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Appalachian Region [largely
                     Hampshire and Frederick counties]. July-September.
                     1 vol., 112 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Continuation of volume
                     immediately above. Also contains April 1851, in
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers, Trip to Rivanna
                     Mills. 1 vol., 29 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Pendleton and Bath counties. 22
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Charles B. Hayden, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Miocene Tertiary of the counties
                     south of James River. 48 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Lewis, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Samuel Lewis, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Notes of Geological
                     examinations in Virginia Commenced June 24, 1840,
                     Chesterfield coal field. June 24-November 4. 2
                     vols., 179 and 47 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Lewis, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Samuel Lewis, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Report of Samuel Lewis, one of
                     the assistant geologists of the State of Virginia
                     for the year 1840, containing a brief account of
                     his operations during the summer and fall seasons.
                     November 9. 7 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A. McCall, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>A. McCall, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Description of salt production,
                     especially of William King's salt well, Washington
                     County. See also letters of July 25, 1840, and May
                     16, 1841, for mention of other salt wells. 2
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1839-1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Bath and
                     Highland counties. Also contains: notes on the
                     rocks of the Potomac Coal Basin, in the
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers, n.d.; notes on
                     the geology of northwestern Virginia, primarily
                     Hampshire and Preston counties, in the handwriting
                     of Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., n.d.; Measurements of
                     Rocks, in the hnadwriting of William B. Rogers,
                     n.d.; Maatinal Series, in the handwriting of
                     William B. Rogers, n.d,; and geological sections
                     to accompany the notes on Bath and Highland
                     counties first mentioned above, in the handwriting
                     of Thomas S. Ridgeway, n.d. 1 vol., 239
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Coal Sections on Big
                     Kanawha River. April 23- . 1 vol., 55
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840-1841</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Description of a part of the
                     section from Abbs Valley by Logan Court House to
                     Guayandotte on the Ohio River. 3 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Sections. (Nos. 1-5 filed oversize). 1.
                     Section at the Burning Spring on the Kanawha
                     River. 1 p.; 2. Section at Mr. Joel Shrewsbury's
                     Salt Works on the Kanawha River. 1 p.; 3. Section
                     at Keller's Creek on the Kanawha river, 1 p.; 4.
                     Section of Vineyard Hill. 1 p.; 5. Profile Section
                     from Parkersburg along the Little Kanawha to
                     Bulltown. 1 p.; 6. Profile Section from Round
                     Bottom on Big Sandy along Tug Fork to Pigeon
                     Creek. 1 p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Notes of the Geological
                     Survey conducted in the North Western District of
                     Virginia. 1 vol., 48 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry D. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1834-1836</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Henry D. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1834</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Journey to the coal region
                     [of Pennsylvania, from Philadelphia]. April 5-6.
                     Also contains: Geological Rambles in New Jersey,
                     May 3-28; Journey from Richmond to Fredericksburg,
                     etc., to Philadelphia, n.d.; From New York to
                     Albany, n.d.; notes of electrical experiments made
                     in October 1833 with William B. Rogers, and in his
                     handwriting; and notes on the geology of
                     Pennsylvania in the vicinity of Harrisburg. 1
                     vol., 138 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Henry D. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the State of New
                     Jersey, 1 vol., 150 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837-1838</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">7</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Rough notes in handwriting
                     of Charles B. Hayden on Tertiary Region of
                     Tidewater Virginia near James River, May 26-27, 7
                     pp. Notes in handwriting of James B. Rogers on
                     geology of Monroe and Giles counties, June 19- ,
                     80 pp. Inverted at back of volume: geological
                     sections and notes on vicinity of Bath County in
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers, n.d., 38 pp. 1
                     vol.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Augusta, Bath,
                     and Highland counties. July. 1 vol., 84
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Fragment of "A Map of the State of
                     Virginia" by Herman Boye, 1827, showing part of
                     southside Virginia, from Cumberland County south
                     to Mecklenburg County, Mounted on linen and marked
                     "JBR 1837."</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. On the Middle District. Part
                     1st. January. Geology of Augusta, Bath, and
                     Highland, Pendleton, and Pocahontas counties. 35
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1838-1841</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">8</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the Warm Springs
                     region, including Bath, Botetourt, Giles, and
                     Monroe counties. April. 1 vol., 28 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Alleghany, Bath,
                     Craig, and Rockbridge counties, with particular
                     attention to iron works. July-August. 1 vol., 63
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Middle district. Geology of
                     Alleghany, Augusta, Bath, Botetourt, and
                     Rockbridge counties. August-September. 1 vol., 68
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the region along
                     the Jackson's, New, Gauley, Kanawha, and Elk
                     rivers, with particular attention to coal seams.
                     Includes instructions for the season in the
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers. May. 1 vol., 130
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Geological sections of Greenbrier and
                     Fayette counties. 10 parts.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Potomac Furnace to
                     Leesburg, and then to Dranesville. August 4-7. 4
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>James B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of northern
                     Virginia and Maryland between Frederick and
                     Boonesboro. 1 vol., 31 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert E. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1836</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Robert E. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Northern Neck. April-June.
                     Second volume also contains field notes in
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers on geology from
                     Charlottesville to Alleghany County, September
                     8-27. 2 vols., 232 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Robert E. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Fairfax County
                     and vicinity. August. Also contains "Journey from
                     Luray across the Massanutten Mn." in the
                     handwriting of James B. Rogers, n.d., and
                     "Memoranda, January 1837" in the handwriting of
                     William B. Rogers on a coal seam discovered near
                     Leakesville, North Carolina. 1 vol., 38
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Robert E. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of northern
                     Virginia, including Berkeley, Jefferson, Loudoun,
                     and Morgan counties. September. 1 vol., 62
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Robert E. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "Summary of Swift Run Gap."
                     Also contains instructions for the season in the
                     handwriting of William B. Rogers. 1 vol., 30
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1835-1836</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1835</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of region along the
                     Pamunkey River, including King William and Hanover
                     counties. July. Also contains a list of "Rocks of
                     the Blue Ridge," n.d., and "Minutes of Analysis of
                     soils," November. 1 vol., 39 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1835</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Analyses of Marl, Sand, and Soils. 1
                     vol., 43 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of part of North
                     Carolina, Carroll County, the lead mines in Wythe
                     County, the coal seams of southwestern and
                     northwestern Virginia, and coal mines of
                     northwestern Virginia and Maryland in the vicinity
                     of Westernport. 1 vol., 202 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Notes respecting the geology, etc., of
                     the Miocene Marl region of Virginia [Tidewater]. 1
                     vol., 13 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Lower Tertiary or eocene of the
                     Pamunkey. 16 pp. See Report of the Geological
                     Reconnoissance of the State of Virginia, 1836, pp.
                     38-43.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Materials collected for a
                     detailed Report of the Survey in 1836: 1) Northern
                     Neck and counties on south side of Rappahannock;
                     2) Coals of Chesterfield, etc., Analysis. 138
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1836</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Eocene and Miocene Marls
                     [Tidewater Virginia, 1836-1837]. 1 vol., 218
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Mercer and
                     Monroe counties in the southwest, and Shenandoah
                     and Hampshire counties in the north. August. 1
                     vol., 78 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1837</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Augusta, Bath,
                     Hardy, Highland, and Pendleton counties. August. 1
                     vol., 100 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1839</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. Drafts of Reports of the
                     Progress of the Geological Survey of the State of
                     Virginia for the year 1839, in the handwriting of
                     William B. Rogers and Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr. 78
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Miscellaneous notes on
                     rocks, slates, and coke. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Geological sections along Brandywine and
                     Wissahickon creeks, Chester County, Pennsylvania.
                     William B. Rogers visited this area in 1839. 7
                     parts.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1839?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Geological sections in Pennsylvania from
                     Pottstown west in the general direction of
                     Reading, in handwriting of Willliam B. Rogers, who
                     visited this area in 1839. 1 part,
                     incomplete.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1841-1844</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1841</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of New York and
                     eastern Canada, by William B. Rogers and Henry D.
                     Rogers, August. Also contains notes on the
                     Tertiary near Richmond, July, and notes made on a
                     "Journey from Baltimore to Harper's Ferry," n.d.
                     First page contains a list of "Boxes of Minerals,
                     1840." 1 vol., 123 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1841?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of western Virginia
                     along the North Western Turnpike. 1 vol., 21
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1843</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of northwestern
                     Virginia. June-August. 1 vol., 225 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geological Memoranda.
                     Summer of 1843[4]. July-September. Concerns
                     primarily the travels of William B. Rogers with
                     the Pennsylvania artist Russell Smith, from
                     Albemarle County to Alleghany County, then to
                     Kanawha County, and returning by way of Highland
                     County. Also contains expense accounts of Russell
                     Smith, and lists of sketches made by him (see
                     Oversize, Box 6).</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1853-1877</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1853</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of route between
                     Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Baltimore,
                     Maryland; the vicinity of Warrenton; near Bellona
                     Arsenal in Chesterfield County; along the North
                     Western Turnpike near Cheat River; and notes on
                     fossil collections (1854). 1 vol., 134
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1877</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology observed during
                     train journey from Richmond to Philadelphia. April
                     18-22. 1 vol., 20 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Report. "Copy of the Report made by
                     Prof. Wm. B. Rogers relative to Walton's Gold Mine
                     in Louisa Co., Virginia." Copied by Forrest
                     Shepherd. 2 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "Notes respecting Hot
                     Springs and vicinity." 8 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "Thickness of No. XI on the
                     Potomac below Westernport." 1 p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of Augusta Springs
                     vicinity, Little Mountain on the Staunton and
                     Parkersburg Road, and Backbone Mountain. 24
                     p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Vicinity of Sweet Springs,
                     Monroe County. 8 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "James and Appomattox
                     Rivers in the vicinity of Richmond and
                     Petersburg." 28 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Geology of the western
                     Virginia Appalachian region. 3 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "From Richmond to
                     Charlottesville by stage." Inverted and at back of
                     book, notes on geology of Alleghany and Greenbrier
                     counties. 1 vol., 58 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. "Register of Analysis" of
                     minerals, and analyses not connected with the
                     survey. 1 vol., 212 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. "Levant Series" of rocks,
                     including sections of western Virginia. 1 vol., 85
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. Promedidicil, Levant, Matinal
                     rocks. 1 vol., unnumbered.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William B. Rogers, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>List. "Matinal Rocks," including
                     sections of the Valley of Virginia. 1 vol., pages
                     unnumbered, 3/4 blank.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Israel Slade, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1838</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1838</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. "Notes on the Burkett's
                     Hole Mountain," in Hardy and Pendleton counties.
                     19 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Israel Slade, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Israel Slade, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1840</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Field notes. Observations along the
                     mountains from Harpers Ferry to southwest
                     Virginia. 3 vols. 1) Harpers Ferry to Wythe
                     County. 158 pp. 2) Smyth and Wythe Counties. 68
                     pp. 3) Montgomery, Pulaski, Roanoke, Smyth,
                     Tazewell, Washington, and Wythe Counties. 336
                     pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1850-1884</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">7</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1850?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Photography of Thomas Jefferson Campbell
                     (1786-April 13, 1850) of Tennessee, Clerk of
                     United States House of Representatives, Thirtieth
                     and Thirty-First Congresses
                     (1847-1850).</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1852</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>A description of Weyer's Cave in Augusta
                     County, Virginia. 1 vol., 11 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1853-1854</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Thirty-eight annual report of the Board
                     of Public Works to the General Assembly of
                     Virginia, with the accompanying documents. January
                     28, 1854. 1 vol., 28 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     185?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Smithsonian Institution, Washington,
                     D.C. Registry of Periodical Phenomena. Printed
                     form, not filled in. 4 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1884?</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Typescripts of material excerpted from
                     earlier records. 1) List of boxes put up by Dr.
                     Jas. B. Rogers and G.W. Boyd, 1838. 1 p. (3
                     copies) 2) Boxes collected in 1839. 2 pp. (2
                     copies) 3) Analyses unconnected with the survey,
                     1836. 4 pp. (3 copies) 4) Section at Scholham
                     taken by John Gebhard, Jr., 1839. 1 p. (3 copies)
                     5) Springs, 1839. 3 pp. (3 copies) 6) Matinal
                     Series, Virginia, n.d. 1 p. (3 copies) 7)
                     Envelope, n.d. 1 item.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Profile of the Works on Vein no. 4.
                     Plate 2. Shows level of the Rappahannock River. 1
                     p.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Sketch map showing Monogahela, Cheat,
                     and Youghogany rivers. Possibly by Charles B.
                     Hayden. 2 pp.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Scrap of paper and cardboard, with notes
                     in handwriting of William B. Rogers. 2
                     items.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Drawings of Russell Smith, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c.
               1844</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rogers engaged Smith to execute a series of drawings
               of significant geological formations in Virginia for use
               in Rogers's projected final report on the state
               geological survey. There are 51 sketches on paper and
               cardboard, in pencil, ink, watercolors, pastels and
               oils.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c.
                  1844</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Monticello and University Va. July
                     4th/44. Ink. Also light pencil sketch of a
                     fireplace and pencil sketch of U.Va. - Monticello
                     on reverse. Albemarle.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Turner's mountain in the extreme
                     distance. High top of left. Pencil. (Albemarle) No
                     date.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Interior of cavern, illuminated by
                     torches, with "tourists." "Russell Smith 1844."
                     Oil.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Distant Mt. Bull Pasture. Hills are
                     Slate. "Foreground Paving Stones, grass and
                     Accassia. Light from L.H." "Near Col. 'Bill'
                     Dyer's." "1. White walnut. 2. Elm. 3. Buttonwood.
                     4. Elm. 5. Dark Linden. 6. Sycamore. 7. Water
                     Willow." Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View of valley through gap in mountains,
                     possibly near Waynesboro? Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Falls of the Kanowha. Russell Smith
                     1844. Ink.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View across valley to cultivated
                     mountains in distance. Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Brown's Gap. N.W. by W. Ink. Undated.
                     (Albemarle Co., p. 113)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Looking NW. Bull Past. Mn. and Thorn Mn.
                     No[rth] Fork Mn. Alleghany Mn. From top of Shen
                     Mn. Dry River Gap. "Russell Smith 1844."
                     Ink.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Pencil sketch of stream surrounded by
                     trees. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Piney Mtn. North of Charlottesville.
                     Ink. Undated. (Albemarle Co.)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Black Thorn Creek. Gag's Mill. South
                     Branch Potomac. Pencil and Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>From the house of Co. Jef. Randolph.
                     Edgehill. July 9th/44. Notes locations of
                     Monticello, Shadwell Hill, Rivanna River, and
                     birthplace of T. J. Ink. (e. of
                     Charlottesville)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Callaghan's meadow. Pencil. Undated.
                     (Shenandoah Co., p. 308)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Cane Hill. Augusta Cy. VA. Russell Smith
                     1844. Ink.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Pencil and Ink sketch of rock
                     formation.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Ink and watercolor. House in foreground,
                     view across valley to mountains.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Pencil sketch. River with log bridge in
                     foreground, frame buildings on bank. Undated.
                     Reverse: pencil portrait, woman's head and
                     neck.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Devil's Backbone. Crab Bottom. July
                     1844. "South Branch of the Potomac, Va. Russell
                     Smith 1844." Ink.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Shenandoah mountains from Col. William
                     Ayer's. Looking S&gt;E&gt;" Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>North Mtn. in distance. Piney Mtn.
                     Looking S.E. from Kaisers. Pencil.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>South fork of the south Branch of the
                     Potomac. Pencil. Undated. Notes on reverse: No. 1
                     and 2. Two very large tulip trees. No. 1 over 100
                     feet high. 3. Black walnut. 4. Sycamore. Color of
                     Gold. 5. Decayed sycamore also very large. The two
                     spots on Bullpasture mountain are smooth walls of
                     light grey Rock. The River is low, leaving in the
                     foreground pools of water with every variety of
                     plants. The dark shadow on Mt. falls in
                     beautifully with the tall dark poplar and spreads
                     out up over the mountain to the night. The general
                     tone is dark. Principal light high up in the sky
                     and the 2nd on the shore. Sky Constable like or
                     English like. From the presence of so much walnut
                     and Sycamore I see none of the cold heavy greens
                     noticed in Cole's 2nd picture of the "Voyage of
                     life" but all is warm and harmonizing with the
                     shadows.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View of mountains, looking across
                     valley. Stunted tree in foreground. Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Rocks at the Rawly Springs on Dry River.
                     July 1844. Pencil.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Pencil sketch of rock formation.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Cliff at Callaghan's. Pencil, ink, and
                     watercolor. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Russell Smith 1844. Cliff at
                     Callaghan's, Va.: Pencil.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Cave Hill looking South West. Ink.
                     Undated. (Page County, Luray, pp.
                     409-414)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Photograph of Mr. Campbell, Clerk of the
                     House, Washington, D.C.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c.
                  1844</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="Folder">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Pencil and ink sketch of interior of
                     cavern. Undated. Notes on reverse: Bright lights
                     caused by lights reflected from the sky on wet
                     leaves and pieces of wood; dry light in distance
                     cool and comes over an irregular rocky sruface. It
                     only terminates in half lights at the lower left
                     hand corner; some bright warm lights touching the
                     edges and lower ends of the stalactites. They
                     being wet give in places sharp lights. Brightest
                     and warmest light to right of dark columns on
                     right and on he roof above them.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View across farm lands to mountains.
                     Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Mass[anuten]Mountain from Miller's Iron
                     Works near cave. Wheat field. Ink. Undated. (Page
                     County, p. 408)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Rock formation, fence and gate. Pencil
                     and watercolor. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Stream and mountains from valley.
                     Pencil. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>From Harsbergers [?] Jackson's River [?]
                     and Rocks. Pencil. Undated; "Crab Bottom." Pencil.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Interior of cavern, with miscellaneous
                     coloring notes. Watercolor. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Interior of cavern, with color key. Ink.
                     Undated. Notes on reverse: the light and shadow of
                     this piece is very broad and soft and the whole
                     column is warm and rich. The middle tint is the
                     most cool although not cold. A figure in white is
                     necessary to produce a bright light. The celing
                     [sic] is remarcably [sic] rich in fine stalictites
                     [?] by small [?] of the most fantastic forms
                     occasionally showing white cristals.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Interior of cavern. Pencil, ink, and
                     watercolor. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Hillside rock formation. Pencil.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Rock formation on top of mountain, with
                     view of valley. Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Wooded, rocky glen with waterfall.
                     Pencil. Undated. Notes on reverse: Water falls
                     white and half light. Distant fall on the right
                     hand little more than rain and of a grey colour.
                     The rocks are of a grey yellowish colour but one
                     [?] with light green vegetation all front of the
                     falls. Where their have surface appears it is
                     yellowish brown and very dark and rich in the
                     shadows. The cliffs are grey, yellow, and slate
                     colour. All left of the falls being light yellow
                     and grey. That to the right is dark green and
                     purpleish grey, almost black in places. The light
                     is from the right and high. The trees are Buckeye,
                     Sycamore, and Elm. Some with raies[?]. Although
                     the work yellowish is used there is nothing yellow
                     appearing in the whole ruin except the R.'s hat.
                     Portions of the falls are shaded by tree tops and
                     jutting rocks. Small portions received the
                     sunlight and are of the brightest
                     white.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1844</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Cascade near the Falls of the Kanawha.
                     Russell Smith 1844. Ink and chalk.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View from bottom of valley across
                     cleared fields, forest, to mountains. Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>The Rivanna River looking S.E. from Col.
                     Jefferson Randolph's. Pencil and ink. Undated.
                     (Albemarle Co.)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Falls or rapids, with building across
                     river on right, mountains all around. Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View of the Blue Ridge from the Mansion
                     of Jno. C. Carter, Esqr. Albemarle Co. Virginia.
                     Landmarks noted: "Buck's Elbow, Turk's Gap,
                     Pasture Fence Mtn., Browns Cave." Ink. Undated.
                     (1875-"Profitt's" on Pigeion Mtn.)</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Continuation of same view, to right.
                     Landmarks labeled: "Brown's Gap, Lemon's Gap."
                     Ink. Undated. 46 and 47 together form
                     panorama.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View across valley to mountains, portion
                     of collonaded house in foreground. Ink.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View of University of Virginia and
                     Monticello Mountain, taken from back and to the
                     left of 1. Ink. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View across bottom to hills, with
                     buildings, bridge. Pencil. Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>View of river or meadow, trees left and
                     right, hills in background. Pencil.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Russell Smith, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
              <abstract>Rocky, wooded, river gorge. Pencil.
                     Undated.</abstract>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
