<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01956">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01956::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Charles T. O'Ferrall, 1894-1897)//EN" "vi01956.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Charles T. O'Ferrall, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1897</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">O'Ferrall, Charles T., Executive Papers of Governor, 1894-1897
<num type="collectionnumber">43210
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2007 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS-Word document, created by Donald Chalfant, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 May 2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Charles T. O'Ferrall, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1897</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">43210
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Donald Chalfant
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Executive Papers of Governor Charles T. O'Ferrall, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1897
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">43210
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">2.2 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia Governor, (1894-1897 : O'Ferrall)
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Virginia. Governor (1894-1898 : O'Ferrall). Executive papers of Governor Charles T. O'Ferrall, 1894-1897. Accession 43210. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Aquired prior to 1905
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information 
</head>
      <p>Charles Triplett O'Ferrall was born 21 October 1840 in Frederick County, Virginia. In 1855, O'Ferrall was appointed clerk pro tempore of the Morgan County (West) Virginia circuit court and served for two years before being officially elected to that position which he held until 1861. At the start of the Civil War, he joined the 12th Virginia Cavalry as a private but was rapidly promoted, achieving the rank of major by August of 1862.  During his recuperation for a wound received at the Battle of Upperville in Enterprise, Mississippi, O'Ferrall met Miss Annie Hand.  Following their marriage on 8 February 1865, he returned to active service as commander of all cavalry forces in the Shenandoah valley and served until the end of the war achieving the rank of colonel.
</p>
      <p>In 1868 he entered Washington College (Washington &amp; Lee) and graduated with a law degree in 1869.  After practicing law for two years in Harrisonburg, O'Ferrall ran as a Democrat for the Virginia House of Delegates and won a two year term (1871-1873).  In 1874, he was appointed judge of the Rockingham Count Circuit Court, a position he held until 1880.  Following the death of his first wife, O'Ferrall remarried in 1881 to Miss Jennie Knight.  The couple had four children in addition to the two children from his first marriage.  After failing in his first bid for U.S. Congress ten years prior, O'Ferrall won the 7th District's congressional election in 1882 and began serving the first of five consecutive terms in the United States House of Representatives.
</p>
      <p>In 1893, running on the bimetallic currency ticket opposed to free silver and proposing support for agriculture, roads and schools, O'Ferrall was elected governor of Virginia.  As governor, he received praise in 1894 for his response to the conflict with Maryland over commercial fishing in the Chesapeake bay as well as for his deployment of militia to Alexandria to disperse a vagrant encampment know as "Coxey's Army" or "Commonwealers."  O'Ferrall also advocated the concept of the "right to work" and in May of 1895, sent troops to southwest Virginia to protect non-striking miners from violence.  He also used troops on separate occasions to suppress the lynching of blacks and proposed anti-lynching statutes in 1896 and 1897, both of which lacked legislative support.  In direct opposition to his own party, O'Ferrall spoke out against the "Free Silver" movement and the 1896 presidential candidacy of William Jennings Bryan therein lessoning his popularity and weakening his effectiveness as governor during his final two years of office.  Upon completion of his term in 1897, O'Ferrall retired to Chesterfield County, where he operated a law practice in partnership with Samuel Regester.  He died 22 September 1905 in Richmond. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection includes records from accession 23349</p>
      <p>The Charles Triplett O'Ferrall executive papers are arranged chronologically and primarily consist of incoming correspondence and receipts during his one term as governor from January 1894 to December 1897, with additional undated material at the end of the collection.  Included are requests for appointments to a variety public offices including Notaries Public, local judgeships, educational and military command positions.  The collection also contains letters regarding Virginia's delegation to the 1896 Cotton States International Exposition held in Atlanta including travel arrangements for the woman's delegation (November 1894, January/February/June 1895).  Newspaper clippings of interest to the governor are found throughout the collection. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>Series I: Chronological Files, 1894-1897</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography
</head>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Younger, Edward and James Tice Moore, ed., THE GOVERNORS OF VIRGINIA 1860-1978. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1982. 
</bibref>
      </bibliography>
      <separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Separated Material
</head>
        <p>Separated materials have been relocated to Box 5.
</p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I: Chronological Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1894-1897</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Boxes" type="box">4
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 4 boxes.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Much of the correspondence addresses law and order topics including requests for military protection of civilian prisoners threatened by lynch mobs (5 February 1894, 29 April 1894); issuance of rewards from the civil contingent fund to encourage public assistance to find and capture criminals; letters regarding extradition proceedings of fugitives captured outside of Virginia as well as requests for monetary reimbursement from both individuals and law enforcement involved in locating, apprehending, and incarcerating criminals.  Notable is correspondence and documentation related to a train robbery in Aquia Creek (Stafford County) on 12 October 1894.  Included is the governor's proclamation of reward for information leading to the arrest of the robbers (13 October 1894), subsequent correspondence detailing the search, arrest and extradition of the accused, reward claims from citizens (June, September 1895), and an application for pardon for one of the two men convicted of the crime (1 November 1897).
</p>
          <p>There are documents highlighting O'Ferrall's use of the military to quell civil unrest including his role in the Jacob Coxey affair and the related "Commonwealer" situation in Alexandria from April through August 1894.  Reports on the size and location of the vagrant Commonwealer encampment (4 August 1894) as well as the actions of the vagrants are documented from a variety of sources including military and local law enforcement.  A draft of the governor's proclamation justifying the removal of the men (8 August 1894) is included.  Also included is correspondence noting O'Ferrall's response to a mine strike in southwest Virginia as well as his reaction to the threat imposed by striking West Virginia mine workers (May - July 1895). 
</p>
          <p>Coastal matters associated with oysters and fishing are also documented.  Of note are several documents concerning an oyster pirating controversy involving the detention of a Maryland-based fishing vessel by Virginia authorities (19 February 1894) and the subsequent negotiation with the state of Maryland over fishing rights in the Chesapeake Bay. Correspondence with Governor Frank Brown about the incident (September 1894) as well as resolutions by the Maryland legislature (February 1894) and Virginia legislature (September 1894) are included.  Also included is a petition for amendment of the federal Geodetic survey to include omitted oyster beds in Warrick County (April 1895) and agreement by the US Geological Survey to re-survey the area (May 1895).  There is additional correspondence with Maryland governor Lloyd Lowndes addressing the hiring of an engineer to replace buoys in the Pocomoke and Tangier sounds to demarcate the boundary lines between the two states (October, November 1897).
</p>
          <p>Also of note are correspondence highlighting race, gender, and educational issues including a response to criticism resulting from a reception at the governor's mansion involving a black delegate from Massachusetts known publicly as the Teamoh affair (21 March 1895); a survey and comparison of costs associated the state's purchase of school textbooks (February 1895); a petition by a group of women appealing for higher education opportunities for women in Virginia including admittance into UVA (25 November 1895) and the governor's response declining their request (27 November 1895).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 January - June
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 July
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 August
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 September - October
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 November - December
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 January
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 February
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 March - April
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 May - June
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 July - August
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 September - October
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 November - December
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 January-February
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 March-April
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 May-June
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 July-September
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 October-December
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1897 January - March
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1897 April
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1897 May - September
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1897 October - December
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">3
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Undated Correspondence
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Undated Newspaper Clippings
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 Official Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 Official Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 Official Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1894 Personal Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1895 Personal Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1896 Personal Finance
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Oversized (Clamshell Box)</emph>, 
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">5
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>28 February 1894 
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">5
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>30 March 1895
	</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">5
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>25 November 1897</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">5
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
