<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01144">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01144::A Guide to the Pendleton Family Papers, 1775-1881)//EN" "vi01144.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pendleton Family Papers, <date>1775-1881 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Pendleton Family Papers, 1775-1881
<num type="collectionnumber">31622
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 6 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>31622 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pendleton Family Papers, <date>1775-1881 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">31622
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Pendleton Family Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1775-1881
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">31622
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">28 pages
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Pendleton Family Papers, 1775-1881. Accession 31622, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Purchased from Bookworm and Silverfish, Wytheville, Virginia, 3 December 1982.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Edmund Pendleton was born 9 September 1721 in Caroline County, Virginia, to Henry Pendleton (1683-1721) and Mary Taylor Pendleton (1688-1770). He married first Elizabeth Roy 21 January 1741/2 and she died in
childbirth 17 November 1742. Pendleton then married Sarah Pollard (1725-1815) in June 1743. Pendleton was licensed to practice law in front of the general court in 1745, and was appointed a justice for Caroline
County in 1751. He was elected to the House of Burgesses in 1752. Pendleton was a member of all five Virginia Conventions in 1775-1776, and was a member of the 1788 convention and supported ratifying the federal
Constitution. He also served on the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals. Pendleton died in Richmond, Virginia, 26 October 1803.
</p>
<p>Pendleton's nephew Nathaniel Pendleton was born in New Kent County, Virginia in 1756 to Nathaniel Pendleton (1715-1793) and Elizabeth Clayton Pendleton. He served in the army during the American Revolution,
becoming aide-de-camp to General Nathanael Greene (1742-1786) during the southern campaign. After the war, Pendleton settled in Savannah, Georgia, and studied law. he was appointed a district judge, then a federal
judge in 1789. He resigned his judgeship in 1796 and moved to New York, New York, where he practiced law. Pendleton was elected a delegate to the 1787 Federal Constitutional Convention and to Congress in 1789, but
did not attend either. He served as a second to Alexander Hamilton (1757-1804) in his duel with Aaron Burr (1756-1836). Pendleton died in Hyde Park, New York, 20 October 1821.
</p>
<p>Nathanael Greene Pendleton was born 25 August 1793 in Savannah, Georgia, to Nathaniel Pendleton and Susan Bard Pendleton. He graduated from Columbia College in 1813, and served as an aide-de-camp to General
Edmund Pendleton Gaines (1777-1849) during the War of 1812. Pendleton moved to Cincinnati, Ohio, in 1818 and practiced law there. He was a member of the Ohio state senate from 1825 to 1829, and served in the
United States Congress from 1841 to 1843. Pendleton died in Cincinnati 16 June 1861. His son Edmund Henry Pendleton (22 June 1843-14 March 1910) resided in Cincinnati.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1775-1881, of the Pendleton family of Caroline County, Virginia; Savannah, Georgia; New York, New York; and Cincinnati, Ohio, consisting of correspondence of Edmund Pendleton (1721-1803) of Caroline
County, Nathaniel Pendleton (1756-1821) of New York, and Edmund Henry Pendleton (1843-1910) of Cincinnati. Correspondence of Edmund Pendleton consists of a letter, 22 December 1775, to Colonels Robert Howe and
William Woodford commanding the Virginia militia at Norfolk, Virginia; and a letter, 9 December 1786, to James Madison (1751-1836) regarding state and national affairs. Correspondence of Nathaniel Pendleton
contains letters to various attorneys concerning his legal and financial affairs in Savannah, Georgia, and New York; a letter, [1813], to his son Nathanael Greene Pendleton (1793-1861) offering career advice to
him as he enters the military; and a letter, 18 December 1814, to Archibald McIntyre asking McIntyre to remove land Pendleton owns from an advertisement for a land sale. Correspondence of Edmund Henry Pendleton
consists of a letter, 1 November 1881, from Townsend MacCoun of Chicago, Illinios, stating that a pamphlet entitled "Address of Hon. E. Pendleton 1799" is being sent to Pendleton, and offers advice for
conservation.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 December 1775,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Colonels Robert Howe and William Woodford, commanding at Norfolk, Virginia, stating that [John Scarsbrook] Wills is the bearer of a letter to the them
and the Virginia Convention has the same confidence in him as it did in [Joseph] Prentis, the intended bearer.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>9 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton, Caroline County, Virginia, to James Madison, Richmond, Virginia, discussing Virginia and national politics, including legislation for various matters such as taxation and
commerce.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>16 March 1793,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton, Savannah, Georgia, to William H. Gibbes requesting securities for the purchase of Fenwicke's Island as opposed to bonds in payment of debt to Pendleton.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 June 1799,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton, New York, New York, to Charles Harris, Savannah, discussing his legal and financial matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 May 1805,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton, New York, to Morris Miller, Savannah, stating that he is upset about learning about the dismissal of a suit 18 months ago, commenting on other legal matters, and mentioning
that a ruling against him under the dueling law of New York will not prevent his practicing.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>[1813],
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton to his son Nathanael Greene Pendleton offering advice to his son who has been appointed aide-de-camp to General Edmund Pendleton Gaines. The father provides detailed points to
help the son perform better in his military duties.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 December 1814,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton, Hyde Park, New York, to Archibald McIntyre asking McIntyre to remove a listing for land from a land sale advertisement as Pendleton has already purchased it.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 November 1881,
</unitdate>from Townsend MacCoun, Chicago, Illinois, to Edmund Henry Pendleton, Cincinnati, Ohio, stating that a pamphlet entitled
<title render="italic">Address of the Hon. E. Pendleton, 1799
</title> is being sent to him. MacCoun also offers some advice on how to conserve the pamphlet.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
