<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01058">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01058::A Guide to Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford, 1926-1944)//EN" "vi01058.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford, <date>1926-1944</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford.
<num type="collectionnumber">41485
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft Word, created by Laura E. Drake, <date> 3 November 2004</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford, <date>1926-1944</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">41485
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Laura E. Drake
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1926-1944
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">41485
</unitid>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia Divison of the Budget. Correspondence of J.H. Bradford, 1926-1944. Accession 41485, State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>Established by an Act of Assembly in 1976, the Dept. of Planning and Budget was created through the merging of the Division of the Budget and the Division of State Planning and Community Affairs. The duties of
the Dept. of Planning and Budget include: the development and direction of an integrated policy analysis, planning and budgeting process within State government; the development, storage, retrieval and
dissemination of data on the social, economic, physical and governmental aspects of the State; the formulation of an executive budget; conduct policy and program analysis for the Governor; the establishment of
planning districts and standard metropolitan statistical areas; and the development and operation of a system of standardized reports of program and financial performance for management.
</p>
<p>The concept of a "modern budget system" was developed in the early part of the 20th century. In 1916, Governor Westmoreland Davis appointed the Commission on Economy and Efficiency to study the organization and
administration of government on both the local and state levels. In 1918, the Commission recommended the creation of a formalized budget system, and the office of the Secretary of the Budget was created by an act
of the General Assembly in that same year. The Secretary of the Budget was appointed by the Governor to serve as the Governor's chief budget assistant, with the Governor being the Chief Budget Officer of the
state. In 1927, the Division of the Budget was created, with its Director being appointed by the Governor.
</p>
<p>The Division of the Budget had responsibility over many areas over the years including: personnel, now held by the Dept. of Human Resource Management; the Insurance Advisory Board, now called the Office of Risk
Management within the Dept. of General Services; Industrial Engineering and Grounds and Buildings, now governed by the Dept. of General Services; and records management, now overseen by the Library of Virginia.
</p>
<p>In 1976, the Division of Budget merged with the Division of State Planning and Community Affairs to form the Dept. of Planning and Budget.
</p>
<p>J. H. Bradford, a native of Alabama, came to Virginia in 1919 to work on Virginia's first state budget and remained as a statistician in the budget office, under the state budget director, LeRoy Hodges.
Following Mr. Hodges' resignation in 1924, Bradford was appointed to the position of acting state budget director by Governor E. Lee Trinkle, a position he was later permanently appointed to by Governor Harry
Flood Byrd. In 1939, in a political move, Governor James Herbert Price appointed Rowland A. Egger to the position of budget director, giving Bradford a minor role in the budget office. In 1940, the General
Assembly created the position of Legislative Director of the Budget with Bradford in mind. Bradford remained in this position until 1942, when Governor Colgate Darden reappointed Bradford as the state budget
director, a position he held until his retirement in 1958.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Contains the correspondence of J. H. Bradford, Director of the Division of the Budget. Correspondents include Harry F. Byrd, Sr., and E. Lee Trinkle. Included is general correspondence as well as letters of
congratulations to Mr. Bradford on his reappointment to the post of budget director in 1942.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Byrd, Harry F., 1930-1931
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Byrd, Harry F., 1932-1937
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters of Congratulation, 1942-1944
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">3
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Trinkle, E. Lee, 1926-1928
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
