<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01637">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01637::A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1714-1857)//EN" "vi01637.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787-1857</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1787-1857
</subtitle>
        <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Sarah Nerney, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 April 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787-1857</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Library of Virginia staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787-1857
</unitdate></unittitle>
      
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.40 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Essex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1787-1857. Local government records collection, Essex County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Essex County in an undated accession.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Starting in 2023, Library of Virginia archival staff in partnership with the Virginia Untold Project Manager began efforts to describe records related to free and enslaved Black and multiracial people in a manner that improved the historical context of the records. In doing so, in some cases material once described within the "Free and Enslaved" record group for a locality may no longer be described within this record. When this has occurred, please see the Processing Information and Related Materials section for records that have been described separately.</emph></p>

<p>"Free Negro" Registrations were removed from this record in April 2024 and are now described in Essex County (Va.) Records Related to the Registrations of Free Persons, 1810-1861.</p>

<p>Deeds of Emancipation were removed from this record in April 2024 and are now described in Essex County (Va.) Deeds of Emancipation, 1848.</p>
<p>Bills of Sale were removed from this record in July 2024 and are now described in Essex County (Va.) Deeds, 1674-1855.</p>

<p>Encoded by G. Crawford, 2015; Updated by M. Mason, April 2024; Updated by M. Mason, July 2024</p>

</processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Records Type:</emph></p>
<p><emph render="underline">Free and Enslaved Records</emph></p>

<p>The Free and Enslaved Records collection is comprised of miscellaneous records related to the regulation and policing of both enslaved and free Black and Multiracial people in Orange County. The localities/local government authorities were largely responsible for enforcing laws that restricted the movement of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people and the resulting documentation was often filed in the circuit courts. The ways in which local authorities enacted legal measures against or on behalf of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people varied from locality to locality; therefore, records were not necessarily standardized or filed and retained in a consistent manner. This collection is topical and a means by which to compile miscellaneous documents related to free and enslaved people that are not established local government record types.</p>
<p><emph render="underline">Bills of Sale and Deeds:</emph></p>

<p>This collection includes transactions of enslaved people that may include the additional transfer of money or another commodity or may be a non-monetary transfer. Bills of sale are written agreements which convey title of property, including enslaved people, from seller to buyer. Under the system of chattel slavery, laws permitted enslavers to treat enslaved people as personal possessions in the same manner as livestock, farm equipment, or household items. Enslaved people could be bought or sold without regard to their personal relationships or free will. Bills of sale record the name of the seller, the names of enslaved people being sold and their price, and the name of the buyer. Given that they involved a property transaction, bills of sale were commonly recorded and filed with deeds in the local court. However, there was no official requirement that the transfer of an enslaved person be recorded unless necessary for legal purposes such as a court case or an estate settlement.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Essex County was formed in 1692 from Rappahannock County, a now extinct Virginia county.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1787-1857, include Bills of Sale , 1787-1771;  and patrol returns, accounts and commissions, 1787-1857.
</p>
      <p>Bills of Sale, 1787-1771, consist of about 22 items which document the name(s) of the seller enslaved persons, the name(s) of the purchaser, usually the name of the enslaved individuals being sold, the price, the date of the deed, and the date the bill of sale was registered or proved with the court and on what page it is recorded. Enslaved named include Beck, Frank, Mingo, Jamey. Bess. Judy, Bacchus, Hannah, Harry, James, George, Betty, Moll, Lilly, Rose, Tom, Judy, Winea, Kate, Essex, Lucy, Pendar, Dinah, Frank, Jenny, Tom, Hannah, Goerge, Liddy, Winney, Lillou, Rachel, Dick, Frank, Suckey, and Hannah.
</p>
      <p>"Slave patrol" records, 1787-1857, consist of records generate by patrols acting as a policing force that monitored the movement of free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals. The records include returns, accounts, and commissions for those acting on the patrols. The patrol returns and accounts list the names of patrollers and the dates and/or hours served on the patrol. Sometimes other information is listed such as the name of the captain of the patrol, how much money is owed to the patrollers, locations patrolled, and any actions taken. The patrol commissions are orders from a justice of the peace for a patrol to form and patrol. The name of the ordering justice is given along with the appointed captain, names of the men named to patrol, the duties of the patrol, and the length of time the patrol is to serve. Often a patrol commission is sealed onto the return of that patrol with sealing wax.
</p>
      
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged <list type="simple"><item>Series I: Free and Enslaved Records, 1787-1857, arranged by record type then chronologically</item></list>
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
       <p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01636.xml">Essex County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1810-1861 </extref>  </p>
    <p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06326.xml">Essex County (Va.) Deeds of emancipation, 1748 </extref>  </p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01634.xml">Essex County (Va.) List of Negroes Belonging to Those Under a Guardian and Unsettled Estates, 1821-1825 </extref>  </p>

<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Essex County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>

<p>Additional Essex County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Free and Enslaved records,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1787-1857</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc> Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent> .40 cubic feet </extent>
</physdesc>
</did> 
<arrangement>
<p> arranged by record type then chronologically
</p>
</arrangement>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1137639">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1787-1857
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
	
</c01>
   </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>





