<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01335">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01335::A Guide to the Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records, 1865-1870)//EN" "vi0135.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records, <date>1865-1870</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records, 1865-1870
<num type="collectionnumber">Chancery Records Index - Rockbridge County Chancery Cause, 1885-001
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 2 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date>20 April 2005 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records, <date>1865-1870</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index ">Rockbridge County Chancery Cause, 1885-001
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1865-1870
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Chancery Records Index">Rockbridge County Chancery Cause, 1885-001 
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">Digital images.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Houston, Alexander, and Company Business Records, 1865-1870. Local Government Records Collection, Rockbridge County Court Records, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Digital images were generated by Crowley Micrographics through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.There are no restrictions.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>A. Alexander and Company was a mercantile partnership formed in 1865 between Archibald Alexander and Edward M. Houston. It was a commission company that received and forwarded merchandise on behalf of merchants
and individuals. The company also operated a retail store at Clifton Warehouse near Lexington, Virginia. The partnership was mutually dissolved on July 15, 1868. The company was reorganized under the name of
Houston, Alexander, and Company adding a third partner, James D. Anderson. It continued to function as commission business and retail store until June 10, 1869 when the three partners agreed to dissolve the
company.
</p>
<p>The business records of A. Alexander and Company and Houston, Alexander, and Company were used as evidence in the chancery case, Executor of Edward M. Houston versus A. Alexander and Company, heard in the
Circuit Court of Rockbridge County.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>A collection of business records, 1865-1870, of Houston, Alexander, and Company that prior to mid-1868 was known as A. Alexander and Company. The collection consists of two ledgers, one journal, one account
book, and one record book.
</p>
<p>Journal, 1865-1868, of A. Alexander and Company that records transactions monthly and then alphabetically by customers' surnames within each month. Each entry includes name of customer, date of transaction,
items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost per item, amount owed, form of payment, and total amount paid. Items sold include soda, spices, dry-goods, axes, brooms, hatchets, chocolate, rope, and food.
Forms of payment include cash, credit, and barter of items such as linsey, bacon, oats, and butter. Entries include page numbers where information was transferred to the customer's individual account in the
corresponding ledger. The transactions recorded in journal come from the company's business activities at its Clifton Warehouse location.
</p>
<p>Ledger, 1865-1868, of A. Alexander and Company that records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes month of
transaction, the total amount owed for items purchased that month, total amount paid for items purchased made that month, and amount paid. Entries include page numbers where information was transferred from the
corresponding journal. The volume includes an index listing the names of customers in alphabetical order and the page number where their accounts can be found.
</p>
<p>Ledger, 1868-1870, of Houston, Alexander, and Company that records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes month of
transaction, the total amount owed for items purchased that month, total amount paid for items purchased made that month, and amount paid. Entries include page numbers where information was transferred from a
corresponding journal which is missing. The volume includes an index listing the names of customers in alphabetical order and the page number where their accounts can be found.
</p>
<p>Storekeeper's record book, 1868, of a bonded warehouse owned by A. Alexander and Company. The warehouse was used for the storage of goods until duties or taxes are paid and the goods are properly released by
Federal Customs officials. Information found in the record book includes the name of individual or company who placed items in the warehouse for storage or who withdrew the items from storage, date of receipt or
withdrawal of items, names of items, quantity and weight of items, and the amount of tax to be paid on items. Items stored at the warehouse were primarily alcoholic beverages. The volume includes an index listing
the names of customers in alphabetical order and the page number where their entries can be found.
</p>
<p>Account book, 1866-1869, that records in chronological order the transactions of A. Alexander and Company from 1866 to 1868 and continues to record transactions after the company became Houston, Alexander, and
Company from 1868 to 1869. The transactions involve the company's activities as a commission agent. Entries contain the following information: date of transaction; name of boat with whom the company conducted
business; names of merchants, businesses, and individuals and the amount of freight charge and tolls owed to the company; and form of payment.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>For additional information see the Rockbridge County Chancery Cause, Executor of Edward M. Houston versus A. Alexander and Company. It can be found in the <extref entityref="chancery">Chancery Records Index</extref> at the Library of Virginia web site. The index number is 1885-001.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Persons:</head>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Alexander, Archibald</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600$a">Houston, Edward M.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Houston, Alexander, and Company (Rockbridge County, Va.)</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Alcoholic beverages -- Taxation -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Barter -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Commission merchants -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Consumer goods -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Dry-goods -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Merchants -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Warehouses -- Management -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Rockbridge County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Account books -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Bookkeeping records -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Business records -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Journals (accounts) -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Ledgers (account books) -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Rockbridge County</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">A. Alexander and Company (Rockbridge County, Va.)</corpname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
