<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01126">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01126::A Guide to the Magruder Family Letters, 1856-1865)//EN" "vi01126.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Magruder Family Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1856-1865</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Magruder Family Letters, 1856-1865
<num type="collectionnumber">21150
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 6 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 July 2004 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Magruder Family Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1865 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">21150
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Magruder Family Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1865
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">21150
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">71 leaves, negative photostats
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Magruder Family Letters, 1856-1865. Accession 21150, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Lent for copying by Mrs. J. D. Micks, Orange, Virginia, 11 March 1937.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Benjamin Henry Magruder (1808-1885) of Glenmore in Albemarle County, Virginia, married Maria Louisa Minor 15 December 1836, and they had several children including Julia Virginia Magruder (1837-1873) who
married George Tyler (1817-1889) of Caroline County, Virginia; John Bowie Magruder, Eva M. Magruder who married E. H. DeJarnette of Caroline County, and Henry Minor Magruder (1845-1891). John Bowie Magruder was
born 24 November 1839. He attended the University of Virginia, and was a teacher in Culpeper County, Virginia, when the Civil War began. He was a captain in the 57th Virginia Infantry, and was promoted to colonel
before his death from wounds received at the battle of Gettysburg on 3 July 1863. James Watson Magruder, a cousin, was born 2 February 1839. He attended the University of Virginia in 1857-1858. A merchant in
Fluvanna County, Virginia, when the Civil War began, he enlisted in Company K, 2nd Virginia Cavalry. A lieutenant, he was killed leading his company at Meadow Bridge, Virginia, 12 May 1864. Another cousin George
Shelton Magruder was born 25 September 1842, and was a student when the Civil War began. He enlisted in the 13th Virginia Infantry and was wounded at the battle of Gaines Mill. George Shelton Magruder was cited
for distinguished service at Fredericksburg in May 1863. He was killed in battle at Winchester, Virginia, 19 September 1864.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Letters, 1856-1865, of the Magruder family of Albemarle County, Virginia, consisting of: a letter, 27 March 1856, from John Bowie Magruder (1839-1863) to his sister Eva M. Magruder describing life at the
University of Virginia; letters, 1862-1863, from John Bowie Magruder to his father Benjamin Henry Magruder (1808-1885) and his sister Eva providing news of his Civil War experiences while serving with the 57th
Virginia Infantry from service in Suffolk, Virginia, to the days before the battle of Gettysburg; and letters, 1862-1864, from George Shelton Magruder (1842-1864) to his cousin Eva M. Magruder commenting on his
service with the 13th Virginia Infantry. Also includes a letter, 12 May 1863, from Eva M. Magruder to John Bowie Magruder concerning the war in Albemarle County; a letter, 8 August 1863, James W. Magruder (1839-
1864) to Eva M. Magruder commenting on the probable death of John Bowie Magruder at Gettysburg and on the war; a letter, 29 June 1864, from Eva M. Magruder DeJarnette to her father Benjamin Henry Magruder
concerning Union raids in Caroline County, Virginia; a letter, 14-20 March 1865, from Henry Magruder (1845-1891) to his sister Eva M. Magruder DeJarnette concerning Union raids in Albemarle County; and a letter,
n.d., from Eva M. Magruder to her sister Julia Magruder Tyler (1837-1873) detailing the death of their brother John Bowie Magruder at the battle of Gettysburg. Also contains a letter, 25 April 1863, from Robert
Johnston (1830-1902) for General George Pickett (1825-1875) commending Magruder and the 57th Virginia for actions during a skirmish.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Magruder Family Letters, 1859-1863. Accession 21243. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 March 1856,
</unitdate>from John Bowie Magruder at the University of Virginia to Evy [Eva] M. Magruder, Albemarle County, Virginia, commenting on his year at school and telling her a tale about one of his old roomates.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 February 1861 [1862],
</unitdate>from John Bowie Magruder, Suffolk, Virginia, to Benjamin Henry Magruder, discussing his regiment's movement to Suffolk, providing a description of the town, and commenting on life in camp, as well as
offering some business and financial suggestions.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 March 1862,
</unitdate>John Bowie Magruder, Fort Dillard, Gates County, North Carolina, to Evy [Eva] M. Magruder, Albemarle County, commenting on elections concerning the Confederate constitution and a poll tax. He comments
on military events and news of Suffolk, Virginia, and Gates County.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 December 1862,
</unitdate>from John Bowie Magruder, Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Benjamin Henry Magruder, Albemarle County, commenting on his health and travels, the second battle of Manassas, the Maryland Campaign of 1862, and
the opposing armies at Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>18 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 December 1862,
</unitdate>from John Bowie Magruder, Fredericksburg, to Bejamin Henry Magruder, Albemarle County, discussing business, the withdrawal of Union forces from across the river from Fredericksburg, and his impending
promotion to colonel.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 March 1863,
</unitdate>from George Shelton Magruder, Hamilton's Crossing, Virginia, to Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, commenting on the future of the war and of himself, mentioning
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Extra Billy
</title> Smith, and asking about Benjamin Magruder's run for Congress.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">13 April 1863,
</unitdate>from George Shelton Magruder, Hamilton's Crossing, to Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, discussing camp life and commenting on family news.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 April 1863,
</unitdate>from Robert Johnston for Major General George Pickett commending Colonel John Bowie Magruder and the 57th Virginia for action in a skirmish.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 May 1863,
</unitdate>from Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, to John Bowie Magruder discussing rumors of Union troops coming to Albemarle County, effects of the war on the area, and family news.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 May 1863,
</unitdate>from John Bowie Magruder, Hanover Junction, Virginia, to Benjamin Henry Magruder, Albemarle County, commenting on business and financial matters and regretting that Benjamin Magruder is not running for
Congress.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 August 1863,
</unitdate>from James W. Magruder, near Fredericksburg, to Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, commenting on the condition of Fredericksburg, remarking the role of women in the Confederacy, and regretting the death
of John Magruder at Gettysburg.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 September 1863,
</unitdate>from George Shelton Magruder, near Pisgah Church, Virginia, to Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, stating that his regiment might be sent to Tennessee, commenting that he had a furlough and visited his
family, and sending other news.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Eva M. Magruder DeJarnette, Caroline County, Virginia, to Benjamin Henry Magruder, Albemarle County, describing Union raids into Caroline County and how the local popoulation responds to them.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>9 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14-20 March 1865,
</unitdate>from [Henry Minor?] Magruder, Albemarle County, to Eva M. Magruder DeJarnette, Caroline County, detailing Union raids into Albemarle County and the reactions of the inhabitants.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>8 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 September, n.y.,
</unitdate>from George Shelton Magruder to Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, discussing the movements of his regiment and other military news.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Eva M. Magruder, Albemarle County, to Julia Magruder Tyler sending news of their brother's (John Bowie Magruder) death at the battle of Gettysburg.
</unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
