<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01118">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01118::A Guide to the Custis-Lee-Mason Family Papers, 1756-1863)//EN" "vi01118.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Custis-Lee-Mason Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1756-1863 </date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Custis-Lee-Mason Family Papers, 1756-1863
<num type="collectionnumber">20975
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">20 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 June 2004 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Custis-Lee-Mason Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1756-1863 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">20975
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Custis-Lee-Mason Family Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1756-1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">20975
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.1 cubic feet
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Custis-Lee-Mason Family. Papers, 1756-1863. Accession 20975, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Gift of Douglas Southall Freeman, Richmond, Virginia, 16 May 1935.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis was born 22 April 1788 to William Fitzhugh (1741-1809) and Ann Randolph Fitzhugh (1747-1805). She married George Washington Parke Custis (1781-1857) in 1806, and they were the parents
of Mary Randolph Custis (1808-1873) who married Robert E. Lee (1807-1870). Mary Fitzhugh Custis died 23 April 1853 at Arlington in Alexandria County, Virginia, and was buried there. George Washington Parke Custis
was the son of John Parke Custis (1755-1781), and the grandson of Daniel Parke Custis (1711-1757) and Martha Dandridge Custis Washington (1731-1802).
</p>
      <p>Mary Randolph Custis Lee was born 1 October 1808 at Annedale, Clarke County, Virginia to George Washington Parke Custis (1781-1857), the grandson of Martha Washington, and Mary Lee Fitzhugh (1788-1853). She
married Robert E. Lee (1807-1870) at Arlington House 30 June 1831, where they lived off and on for many years before the Civil War began. Mary Custis Lee died 5 November 1873 in Lexington, Virginia. She was buried
in the Lee Chapel at Washington and Lee University, Lexington. The Lees had seven children including George Washington Custis Lee (1832-1913).
</p>
      <p>James Murray Mason was born 3 November 1798 in Georgetown, District of Columbia, to John Mason and Anna Maria Murray. Educated at schools in Georgetown, he graduated from the University of Pennsylvania in 1818.
Mason studied law at the College of William and Mary, then moved to Winchester, Virginia, in 1820 to practice law. Mason served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1826 to 1831, except for 1827-1828. Elected
to Congress, he served from 1837 to 1839. The Virginia state senate sent Mason to the United States Senate in 1847, and he became chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations and Finance Committees. When the Civil War
began, Mason left the Senate and offered his services to the Confederate States of America. He was appointed the Confederate diplomatic commissioner to Great Britain. Taken from the British ship Trent, Mason spent
a brief time in U.S. custody before being released. He went to Great Britain to carry out his duties. After the Civil War, Mason moved to Canada where he stayed before returning to Virginia in 1868. Mason died
near Alexandria, Virginia, 28 April 1871, and was buried at Christ Episcopal Church. He married Elizabeth Margaretta Chew (1798-1874) 25 July 1822, and they had eight children.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Papers, 1756-1863, of the Custis, Lee, and Mason families of Virginia, consisting of correspondence to and from members of these families. Collection is divided into three series: Series I: Custis Family
Papers, 1756-1844. Series II: Lee Family Correspondence, 1832-1863. Series III: Mason Family Papers, 1822-1846.
</p>
      <p>Custis family correspondence, 1756-1844, contain mainly correspondence to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis (1788-1853) of Alexandria County, District of Columbia and Virginia. Letters deal mainly with social, family,
and personal news of her correspondents, who include her daughter Mary Custis Lee (1808-1873), Robert Randolph, Eleanor Parke Custis Lewis, T. James, Anna Maria Fitzhugh, S. E. Goldsboro, M. Meade, Lucy Jane
Randolph, Rosalie [Fizhugh?], and William W. Meade. Many of the letters from Mary Custis Lee portray life as the wife of a military officer in the United States army during the 19th century. Of particular interest
are: a) a letter, 27 May 1756, from Daniel Parke Custis of New Kent County, Virginia, to Robert Cary and Company, merchants of London, England, concerning his tobacco crop; b) a letter, n.d., from Mary Fitzhugh
Lee Custis at Old Point Comfort, Virginia, to her husband George Washington Parke Custis, at Arlington, in Alexandria County, District of Columbia, concerning the status of one of their slaves; and c) a letter,
n.d., from William W. Meade to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis concerning a contribution to the American Colonization Society.
</p>
      <p>Lee family correspondence, 1832-1863, containly mainly correspondence to Mary Randolph Custis Lee (1808-1873) of Alexandria County, District of Columbia and Virginia, containing social, family, and personal
news of her correspondents, who include: A. T. Hale, Mary B. Carter, Henrietta Dimmock, Julia C. Stuart, M. F. Powell, Robert E. Lee, Lloyd N. Rogers, Anna Maria Fitzhugh, S. E. Goldsboro, E. C. Huger, Mary C.
Goldsboro, and George Washington Parke Custis. There are three letters, one from Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis and two from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, to George Washington Custis Lee while he was a cadet at the United
States Military Academy at West Point, New York. Letter, 12 July 1837, from Robert E. Lee (1807-1870) to his wife Mary Randolph Custis Lee describes an exhibit on George Washington at a Baltimore museum, for which
her father George Washington Parke Custis had lent items. Also included letter, 1 March 1863, from T. G. B. to Mary describing a family's life during the Civil War.
</p>
      <p>Mason family correspondence, 1822-1846, containing mainly correspondence to James Murray Mason (1798-1871) concerning the estate of his father-in-law, Benjamin Chew (d. 1844), including the dispute surrounding ownership of the Chew home, "Cliveden," Germantown, Pennsylvania, and other legal matters involving the estate of Chew, for whom Mason was an administrator. Also includes letters concerning Elizabeth Chew (1798-1874), Mason's future wife; one, 6 March [1819], possibly from Elizabeth's sister Anne Chew regarding Elizabeth's health and her relationship with Mason; and one, 9 July 1822, from Elizabeth's father Benjamin Chew to Mason regarding Mason's upcoming marriage to Elizabeth. Also includes the answer, n.d., of Benjamin Grayson, John W. Grayson, and George M. Grayson to a bill in chancery in the Superior Court of Chancery, Winchester District, and addressed to the honorable Henry St. George Tucker (1780-1848).
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Collection is organized into three series. Series I: Custis Family Correspondence, 1756-1844. Series II: Lee Family Correspondence, 1832-1863. Series III: Mason Family Papers, 1822-1846
</p>
      <p>Arranged chronologically in each series.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Custis Family Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1756-1844, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 May 1756,
</unitdate>from Daniel Parke Custis, New Kent County, Virginia, to Robert Cary and Company, London, England, regarding business and his tobacco crop.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis at Old Point Comfort, Virginia, to George Washington Parke Custis at Arlington, Alexandria County, District of Columbia, concerning a slave named Philip and other personal
matters.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 March 1814,
</unitdate>from Robert Randolph, Fauquier County, Virginia, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, concerning his personal life and religion.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 October 1823,
</unitdate>from Eleanor Parke (Nelly) Custis Lewis, Fairfax County, Virginia, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, discussing her husband's health and other family news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 November 1823,
</unitdate>from Eleanor Parke (Nelly) Custis Lewis, Fairfax County, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 April 1832,
</unitdate>from M. Meade, White Post, Virginia, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, sending news of family and friends.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 September 1833,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis discussing family news, including the health of Mary Custis and George W. P. Custis, and Mary Lee's family.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 May 1844,
</unitdate>from T. James [?], Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, relating society news from Philadelphia, family and personal news, as well as discussing an attack on part
of the Episcopal Church.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 February, n.y.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh [Battaile?], Cambridge, Maryland, to Mary Fitzhugh Custis and Mary Randolph Custis [Lee], Alexandria County, describing Cambridge and discussing society, family, and personal
news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 June n.y.,
</unitdate>from T. E. Goldsboro, Easton, Maryland, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, describing the visit of Mary Custis' daughter Mary Randolph Custis [Lee] to the Goldsboros' home.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee to Mary Lee Fizthugh Custis, Alexandria County, discussing family and personal news and the Lee family travels west, including to Cincinnati, Ohio.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages, fragmented.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18th June n.y.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Fort Hamilton, New York, New York, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, describing life at Fort Hamilton and in New York City, including society, family, and
personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 August n.y.,
</unitdate>from L. J. Randolph to Mary Custis in Baltimore, Maryland, containing personal and family news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 August n.y.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Washington, D.C., to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, containing family and personal news
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, St. Louis, Missouri, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, sending news of the Lee family during its time in St. Louis while Robert E. Lee was stationed there.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Fort Monroe, Elizabeth City County, Virginia, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, discussing life at Fort Monroe and describing the society life around the Lee family, including
information on some of the other military officers there.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Fort Hamilton, New York, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, sending society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 September n.y.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis providing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 November n.y.,
</unitdate>from Rosalie [Fitzhugh?], Easthampton, Massachusetts, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, describing Easthampton and containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Fort Hamilton, New York City, to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, providing news of the Lee family and discussing an upcoming trip.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from William Meade to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, concerning a bequest that a relative left for them to leave to a worthy cause. Meade suggests the American Colonization Society.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee to Mary Lee Fitzhugh Randolph, Alexandria County, containing Lee family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lee Family Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832-1863.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 October n.y.,
</unitdate>from Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, to Cadet George Washington Custis Lee, United States Military Academy, West Point, New York, concerning some trouble he is in at West Point.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 December, n.y.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee, in Baltimore, Maryland, to George Washington Custis Lee, West Point, New York, regarding trouble he is in at West Point.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Randolph Custis Lee to George Washington Custis Lee, West Point, asking him to remember her to family friends. Possibly a not complete letter.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 August 1832,
</unitdate>from A. T. Hale, Glastonbury, Connecticut, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, at Old Point Comfort, containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 January 1833,
</unitdate>from unidentified person to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, sending society and family news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 February 1833,
</unitdate>from Mary B. Carter, Shirley, Charles City County, Virginia, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, discussing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 January 1835,
</unitdate>from A. T. Hale, Glastonbury, Connecticut, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 April 1835,
</unitdate>from Henrietta Dimmock, Old Point Comfort, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Washington, D.C., sending news of events and people in Old Point Comfort, and family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 May 1835,
</unitdate>from Julia C. Stuart to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, discussing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 June 1835,
</unitdate>from Henrietta Dimmock, Fort Monroe, Elizabeth City County, Virginia, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Washington, D.C., containing society, family, and personal news and events in Old Point Comfort.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 December 1835,
</unitdate>from M. F. Powell, Loudoun County, Virginia, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, discussing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 May 1836,
</unitdate>from Henrietta Dimmock, Old Point Comfort, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Washington, D.C., providing society, family, and personal news from Old Point Comfort.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 December 1836,
</unitdate>from Henrietta Dimmock, Washington D.C., to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, sending society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 July 1837,
</unitdate>from Robert E. Lee, in Baltimore, Maryland, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, discussing an exhibit on George Washington, including some items donated by George Washington Parke Custis, in
a Baltimore museum.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 July 1837,
</unitdate>from Lloyd N. Rogers, Baltimore, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, concerning the death of his daughter.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 September 1838,
</unitdate>from Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, St. Louis, Missouri, asking why she has not heard from her daughter, and sending family news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 January n.y.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh, in Cambridge, Maryland, to Mary Randolph Custis [Lee], Alexandria County, thanking her for her letter and sending society and family news from Cambridge.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 March n.y.,
</unitdate>from S. E. Goldsboro, Easton, Maryland, to Mary Randolph Custis [Lee], providing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 July n.y.,
</unitdate>from E. C. Huger, at White Sulphur Springs, (West) Virginia, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, sending her news of events at the springs and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 July n.y.,
</unitdate>S. E. Goldsboro, Easton, to Mary Randolph Custis [Lee], Alexandria County, regarding society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 September n.y.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh, Fairfax County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, at Old Point Comfort, discussing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 November n.y.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh, Fairfax County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Old Point Comfort, regarding society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 November n.y.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh, at Arlington, Alexandria County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Old Point Comfort, concerning society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 November n.y.,
</unitdate>Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, St. Louis, Missouri, containing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary C. Goldsboro, Easton, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, sending society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from either S. E. or Mary C. Goldsboro, Easton, to Mary Randolph Custis [Lee], providing society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Anna Maria Fitzhugh, Fairfax County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Old Point Comfort, sending society, family, and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from an unidentified correspondent to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, St. Louis, Missouri, sending family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Eugenia [?] to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Alexandria County, asking Mary Lee to visit.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis, Alexandria County, to Mary Randolph Custis Lee, Old Point Comfort, discussing family and personal news. Contains a postscript by George Washington Parke Custis.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 March 1863,
</unitdate>from T. G. B. to Mary [?] describing how his/her family is coping with the events of the Civil War.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mason Family Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822-1846.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 March [1819],
</unitdate>from an unknown correspondent (possibly Anne Chew) to James Murray Mason, Williamsburg, Virginia, discussing Elizabeth Margaretta Chew's (Mason's future wife) recent illness and her relationship with Mason.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 July 1822,
</unitdate>from Benjamin Chew, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to James Murray Mason, Winchester, Virginia, concerning the upcoming marriage of Mason to Chew's daughter Elizabeth.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 July 1841,
</unitdate>from Benjamin Chew, Cliveden, Germantown, Pennsylvania, to James Murray Mason, Winchester, discussing family news and a possible visit.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 May 1845,
</unitdate>from Daniel Agnew, Beaver County, Pennsylvania, to James Murray Mason, Winchester, concerning the estate of Benjamin Chew, including lands in Beaver County.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 August 1845,
</unitdate>from William W. Chew, Philadelphia, to James Murray Mason concerning a dispute within the Chew family and a mayor's order for Benjamin Chew to keep the peace toward his sister.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 October 1845,
</unitdate>from William W. Chew, Germantown, to Elizabeth Margaretta Chew, Winchester, containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 October 1846,
</unitdate>from William C. Chew, Germantown, to James Murray Mason concerning the affairs of the estate of his father, Benjamin Chew.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">31 October 1846,
</unitdate>from William C. Chew, Philadelphia, to James Murray Mason, Winchester, concerning the affairs of his father's estate.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>from Elizabeth Margaretta Chew Mason to James Murray Mason, Winchester, containing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Answer,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.,
</unitdate>of Benjamin Grayson, John W. Grayson, and George M. Grayson to Henry St. George Tucker of the Superior Court of Chancery, Winchester District to answer complaint of William Richards and others.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
