<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01748">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01748::A Guide to the Cooke Family Papers, 1855-1871)//EN" "vi01748.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Cooke Family Papers, <date>1855-1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Cooke Family Papers, 1855-1871
<num type="collectionnumber">23896
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>5 June 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Cooke Family Papers, <date>1855-1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">23896
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Cooke Family Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1855-1871
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">23896
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">50 leaves, negative photostats
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Cooke Family
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Cooke Family Papers, 1855-1871.  Accession 23896.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Lent for copying, 24 October 1952, by Baskerville Bridgforth, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Philip St. George Cooke (1809-1895) was born in Loudoun County, Virginia. He graduated in 1827 from the United States Military Academy and served in the United States Army well over 50 years. He was commissioned a colonel in 1858 and a brigadier general in 1861. Cooke commanded the cavalry around Washington D.C. early in the Civil War and led a division during the Peninsular Campaign in 1862. For the remainder of the war, Cooke held various district commands and as the general superintendent for recruiting. Cooke and his wife Rachel Wilt Herzog Cooke had 3 daughters and one son. One daughter, Flora (1837-1923), married the famous Confederate General Jeb Stuart (1833-1864). Cooke's son John R. Cooke (1833-1891) graduated from Harvard in 1855 and was commissioned a 2nd lieutenant in the 8th Infantry in 1856 and a first lieutenant in the same regiment in 1861. He resigned his commission and entered the Confederate service, rising to the rank of brigadier general. John R. Cooke became a merchant in Richmond, Virginia, after the war. He was buried in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1855-1871, of the Cooke family of Missouri and Virginia consisting of letters, 1855-1871, concerning John R. Cooke's (1833-1891) military career in the United States army; his service as an officer in the Confederate army, including correspondence with his brother-in-law Jeb Stuart (1833-1864) discussing the war and his father, Union General Philip St. George Cooke (1809-1895); Virginia's secession; the battle of Big Bethel; John R. Cooke's post-war recollections; and a recommendation of Cooke as superintendent for the Richmond and Petersburg Railroad. Papers also include commissions, 1855 and 1861, for Cooke as 2nd and 1st lieutenant in the United States army; invoice for ordnance; plan of the battle of Fredericksburg; Robert E. Lee's (1807-1870) General Order no. 9 announcing the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia; and a sketch map of Holly Shelter Creek and vicinity, Pender County, North Carolina.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Philip St. George Cooke Letters, 1891-1894 (LVA accession 24143).
</p>
<p>Philip St. George Cooke Papers, 1835-1878 (LVA accession 24101).
</p>
<p>Philip St. George Cooke Papers, 1837-1942 (LVA accession 28674, miscellaneous reel 251).</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>2 April 1855, 
</unitdate>from Philip St. George Cooke at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, to his son John R. Cooke of St. Louis, Missouri, concerning a request for a commission for John R. Cooke in the United States Army, includes a letter, dated 1 March 1855, from Secretary of War Jefferson Davis to Philip St. George Cooke informing him that John R. Cooke had been placed on a list of applicants for a commission.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Commission, 
<unitdate>23 July 1855, 
</unitdate>for John R. Cooke as 2nd lieutenant in the 8th Infantry, U.S. Army to date from 30 June 1855 signed by President Franklin Pierce and Secretary of War Davis.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>15 July 1858, 
</unitdate>from Philip St. George Cooke to John R. Cooke containing news and advice.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Commission, 
<unitdate>29 March 1861, 
</unitdate>for John R. Cooke as 1st lieutenant in the 8th Infantry, U.S. Army to dated from 28 January 1861 signed by President Abraham Lincoln and Secretary of War Simon Cameron.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Invoice, 
<unitdate>20 April 1861, 
</unitdate>for ordnance from John R. Cooke, 1st lieutenant 8th Infantry to Jeb Stuart, 1st lieutenant 1st Cavalry.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>21 April 1861, 
</unitdate>from John R. Cooke at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, to his mother containing news of Virginia's secession, the situation at Fort Leavenworth, and advice to his mother for her safety.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>13 June 1861, 
</unitdate>from John R. Cooke to his sister Flora Cooke Stuart at Wytheville, Virginia, sending personal news and news of the battle at Big Bethel, Virginia.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>12 July 1861, 
</unitdate>from John R. Cooke to Flora Stuart asking for shirts and news about their parents and containing personal news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>18 January 1862, 
</unitdate>from General Jeb Stuart to John R. Cooke informing Cooke that Stuart is proud and supportive of him and expressing mortification that Cooke's father, Philip St. George Cooke, fighting for the Union.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>20 March 1862, 
</unitdate>from John R. Cooke to Flora Stuart informing her that he has been promoted to major and chief of artillery for the Aquia district.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Ltter, 
<unitdate>4 December 1862, 
</unitdate>from Mary Anston Taliaferro to John R. Cooke informing him that a Union soldier wishes to get out of the war and wants to arrange a parole.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>plan of the Battle of Fredericksburg, 
<unitdate>13 December 1862.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>January 1863, 
</unitdate>from General John R. Cooke to Jeb Stuart concerning Cooke's command at Kinston, North Carolina and efforts to prevent a Union advance on Wilmington, North Carolina.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>28 February 1863, 
</unitdate>from Jeb Stuart to John R. Cooke sending news of Stuart's cavalry and advising Cooke to stay out of army politics.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>2 June 1863, 
</unitdate>from General D. H. Hill to John R. Cooke ordering Cooke and his command to Richmond, Virginia, and the Army of Northern Virginia, and regretting losing Cooke.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>9[?] June 1863, 
</unitdate>from D. H. Hill to John R. Cooke suggesting a possibility of keeping Cooke and his command
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>8 October 1863, 
</unitdate>from General Robert E. Lee ordering John R. Cooke to be ready to move his command.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>15 December 1864, 
</unitdate>from John R. Cooke to Flora Cooke containing army and personal news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>General Order No. 9, 
<unitdate>10 April 1865, 
</unitdate>by Robert E. Lee informing the Army of Northern Virginia that it is surrendered.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>21 December 1868, 
</unitdate>from John O. Steger of Richmond, Virginia, to the President and Directors of the Richmond and Petersburg Railroad recommending John R. Cooke as superintendent of the railroad.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>21 June 1871, 
</unitdate>from Richard S. Ewell of Spring Hill, Maury County, Tennessee, to John R. Cooke sending personal news and asking for Cooke's thoughts on the late war.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>16 May [1863?], 
</unitdate>from General James Longstreet to John R. Cooke informing Cooke that he is trying to get Cooke's troops back under his command.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Rough sketched map, 
<unitdate>no date, 
</unitdate>of Holly Shelter Creek and vicinity in Pender County, North Carolina.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
