<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01131">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01131::A Guide to the Robinson-Steptoe Family Papers, 1689-1826)//EN" "vi01131.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Robinson-Steptoe Family Papers, <date>1689-1826 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Robinson-Steptoe Family, Papers, 1689-1826
<num type="collectionnumber">19793
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 13 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>5 August 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Robinson-Steptoe Family Papers, <date>1689-1826 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">19793
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Robinson-Steptoe Family Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1689-1826
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">19793
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">31 leaves and 45 pages
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Robinson-Steptoe Family Papers, 1689-1826. Accession 19793, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift of Gladys Redwood Pollard of Asheville, North Carolina, 12 July 1926.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Christopher Robinson (1645-1692/3) arrived in Virginia from England around 1666. He quickly established himself and a plantation called "Hewick" in Middlesex County, named after his family's Hewick Estate in
England. His descendants became influential landholders, tobacco traders, and political leaders in the colony. Christopher I had eight children, including Christopher II (1681-1726/7) who married Judith Wormeley,
daughter of Colonel Christopher Wormeley, and Ann (ca. 1682-1753) who married Dr. John Hay (ca. 1677-1709). Christopher II had eight children, including Christopher III (1705-1768) who married Sarah Wormeley,
daughter of John Wormeley of "Rosegill," Middlesex County. Christopher III had children including Elizabeth (ca. 1756-1832) who married William Steptoe (ca. 1753-1805). Elizabeth and William Steptoe inherited
"Hewick" from her father.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1689-1826, of the Robinson-Steptoe family of Caroline and Middlesex Counties, Virginia, consisting of bonds, court orders, court proceedings, decrees, deeds, depositions, judgments, land grants,
letters, petitions, statements, summonses, surveys, warrants, wills, and writs. Papers concern a dispute by Robinson and Steptoe families with the Taliaferro family over inheritance of Robinson family land. The
case began as a suit by Christopher Robinson against Francis Taliaferro and Lawrence Taliaferro, then became a suit by William Steptoe (ca. 1753-1805) against Charles Champe Taliaferro. Includes correspondence
from Edmund Pendleton (1721-1803) and John Taylor (1753-1824) to William Steptoe concerning the legal aspects of his suit. Papers also involve the Hay family.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>20 January 1688/9,
</unitdate>for 2500 acres in (Old) Rappahannock County, Virginia, from John Curtis of Northumberland County, Virginia, to Christopher Robinson of Middlesex County, Virginia. Deed recorded in (Old) Rappahannock
County 15 August 1689. Includes bond from Curtis to Robinson.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Land patent,
<unitdate>29 April 1692,
</unitdate>for 959 acres in (Old) Rappahannock County from Lieutenant Governor Francis Nicholson to Christopher Robinson of Middlesex County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Petition,
<unitdate>[1696],
</unitdate>from John Curtis to Governor Edmund Andros to obtain land by escheat from the estate of Elizabeth Haslewood of Middlesex County and daughter of Abraham Moon. Includes warrant, 7 January 1696/7, from
Andros to escheator of the county and report, 7 May 1697, of inquisition.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Warrant,
<unitdate>2 April 1700,
</unitdate>from Francis Nicholson, Governor of Virginia, to Matthew Page, escheator of Essex County, Virginia, to impanel a jury concenring land owned by Elizabeth Haslewood at the of her death. Includes report,
11 October 1700, of inquisition.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Will,
<unitdate>29 January 1702,
</unitdate>of Francis Hay.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>2 April 1707,
</unitdate>for 300 acres in Middlesex County from Christopher Robinson to John Hay, both of Middlesex County. Deed recorded in Middlesex County 7 April 1707.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deposition,
<unitdate>7 May 1728,
</unitdate>of Ruth Owens of Middlesex County concerning the marriage of John Hay and Ann Robinson and the birth of their son Francis Hay. Recorded in Middlesex County 7 May 1728.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deposition,
<unitdate>18 April 1728,
</unitdate>of Isbell Schooler of Essex County concerning the family of John Hay and Ann Robinson Hay, including their son Francis Hay. Recorded in Caroline County, Virginia, 12 September 1728.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Land patent,
<unitdate>27 September 1729,
</unitdate>for 12,000 acres in Spotsylvania County, Virginia, from Governor William Gooch of Virginia to John Grymes.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Will,
<unitdate>22 May 1751,
</unitdate>of Ann [Robinson] Hay of Caroline County. Will was recorded 8 March 1753 in Caroline County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Survey,
<unitdate>3-6 May 1758,
</unitdate>of 2645 acres in Caroline County in dispute between Lawrence Taliaferro and Francis Taliaferr. Survey made by Edward Vawter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Decree,
<unitdate>11 August 1758,
</unitdate>of the Caroline County Court in chancery in the suit of Lawrence Taliaferro vs. Francis Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 April 1762,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton of Caroline County to Christopher Robinson containing Pendleton's opinion on Robinson's title to certain land.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Proceedings,
<unitdate>31 January 1765,
</unitdate>declaration of John Doe against Lawrence Taliaferro and Francis Taliaferro, being the copy to Francis Taliaferro and Zachary Benson Deposition, 11 March 1765, of John Miller, Jr. Abatement, 12 October
1778, in General Court due to death of Christopher Robinson.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Summons,
<unitdate>15 February [1771],
</unitdate>to appear before the General Court in the suit of John Doe, lessee of Christopher Robinson, vs. Lawrence Taliaferro and Francis Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 February 1771,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton to Richard Corbin requesting a copy of the will of Christopher Robinson and discussing the suit of the disputed land.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>5 June 1771,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton to David Kerr, King and Queen Count, Virginia, concerning John Doe, lessee of Christopher Robinson, vs. Lawrence Taliaferro and Francis Taliaferro. Includes a General Court order
for the deposition of John Robinson and survey of the land.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 February 1774,
</unitdate>from James Mercer to Edmund Pendleton concerning the suit of Robinson vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 January 1783,
</unitdate>from Edmund Pendleton to William Steptoe, Middlesex County, concerning the suit of Robinson vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Proceedings,
<unitdate>16 July 1785,
</unitdate>declaration of John Doe against Charles Champe Taliaferro, filed by John Taylor. Copy sent to Joshua Claxton, including deposition, 13 October 1785, of Robert Buckner concerning delivery. Continuation
of Robinson vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 April 1786,
</unitdate>from William Steptoe, Middlesex County, to John Taylor, Richmond, Virginia, concenring his suit against Charles Champe Taliaferro, orginally Christopher Robinson vs. Lawrence Taliaferro and Francis
Taliaferro
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Order of General Court,
<unitdate>24 April 1786,
</unitdate>in Joe Doe vs. Richard Roe stating that Joshua Claxton is to appear before the General Court. Includes deposition, 10 September 1786, of Thomas Howard, Caroline County, that he delivered a copy to
Claxton.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 July 1786,
</unitdate>John Taylor to William Steptoe concerning his suit against Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21 August 1786,
</unitdate>John Taylor, Caroline County, to William Steptoe, Middlesex County, concerning Steptoe's suit against Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>13 October 1786,
</unitdate>from William Steptoe, Middlesex County, to John Taylor regarding Steptoe's suit against Taliaferro and Taylor's difficulty in tracking down documents for it.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 November 1786,
</unitdate>from John Taylor, Caroline County, to William Steptoe, Middlesex County, concerning Steptoe's suit against Taliaferro and Taylor's correspondence regarding its proceedings.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>[4 April 1787],
</unitdate>William Steptoe, Middlesex County, to John Taylor concerning delivery of a subpoena to Joshau Claxton, a deposition made by Steptoe, and a copy of a declaration in 1771 that John Robinson was a material
witness in Robinson vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21 April 1787,
</unitdate>from James Mercer, Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Jerman Baker, Richmond, concerning legal proceedings by Charles Champe Taliaferro against William Steptoe and Elizabeth Steptoe.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Order of the General Court,
<unitdate>9 October 1787,
</unitdate>discharching the rule obtained by Taliaferro in the last court.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 August 1788,
</unitdate>from John Taylor, Caroline County, to William Steptoe, Middlesex County, concerning the status of Steptoe's suit against Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 August 1789,
</unitdate>William Steptoe, Middlesex County, to John Minor, Fredericksburg, concerning Steptoe's suit and the need to take a deposition from Edmund Pendleton.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 April 1791,
</unitdate>James Mercer to William Steptoe regarding Steptoe's suit against Mercer's ward Charles Champe Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 April 1791,
</unitdate>James Mercer to William Steptoe concerning a survey to be made of land in the suit of Steptoe vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>26 April 1791,
</unitdate>William Steptoe, Middlesex County, to John Warden concerning a survey made of disputed land in Steptoe vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Judgment,
<unitdate>April 1794,
</unitdate>of Fredericksburg District Court in William Steptoe and Elizabeth Steptoe vs. Charles Champe Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Declaration,
<unitdate>1806,
</unitdate>in the suit of John Doe vs. Richard Roe in the Fredericksburg District Court.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 June 1826,
</unitdate>R. S. Chew, Fredericksburg, to [Elizabeth?] Steptoe, Middlesex County, regarding the possible success of a suit for land against Charles C. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Writ,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of the General Court in the suit of John Doe vs. Richard Roe.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Statement,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of Edmund Pendleton concerning the suit of Robinson vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Statement,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of John Taylor regarding the suit of Steptoe vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Statement,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of [James Mercer?] concerning the suit of Steptoe vs. Taliaferro.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Survey,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>containing courses and boundaries of a deed from Lawrence Taliaferro to Charles Stern.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages, copy.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Certification,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>by William Gooch possibly concerning the depositions made by Ruth Owens and Isbell Schooler concerning John Hays, Ann Robinson Hays, and Francis Hays.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
