<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01425">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01425::A Guide to the King George County (Va.) Marriages, 1786-1863)//EN" "vi01425.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the King George County (Va.) Marriages, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1786-1863 </date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">King George County (Va.) Marriages, 1786-1863
<num type="collectionnumber">1146591
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 01 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives Database, created by Callie Lou Freed, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 December 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the King George County (Va.) Marriages, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1786-1863 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Number">1146591
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Callie Lou Freed
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">King George County (Va.) Marriages,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1786-1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode number">1146591
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 vol. (74 leaves) This volume is a negative photostatic copy.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Use microfilm copy, King George County, Reel 43.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>King George County (Va.) Marriages, 1786-1863. King George County Reel 43, Local Government Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>A microfilm copy of the original volume and a positive photostatic copy (made by the Virginia State Library) were generated by The Genealogical Society of Utah--while filming at the King George County Circuit Court Clerk's Office.
</p>
        <p>The internal index to the volume and the negative photostatic copy of the entire volume were created by the Virginia State Library's (now the Library of Virginia) Archives Division from the original volume found in the King George County Circuit Court Clerk's Office.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>King George County was formed in 1720 from Richmond County. Part of Westmoreland County was added in 1777. The county was named in honor of George I of England.
</p>
      <p>Prior to 1853, when the Commonwealth began recording vital statistics, Virginia marriages were recorded at the county or city level. Beginning in 1661, in order to be married by license, the groom was required to go before the county clerk and give bond with security that there was no lawful reason to prevent the marriage. The license, issued then by the clerk, was given to the minister who performed the service.
Written consent from a parent or guardian was needed for individuals younger than twenty-one years.
</p>
      <p>Until 1780, marriages could be performed only by ministers of the Established Church, who were required by law to record marriages in the parish register. In 1780, dissenting ministers (only four per county from each sect) were first permitted to perform marriage ceremonies. Ministers' returns were required by law beginning in 1780, so all marriages from that date would be of record in the county court clerk's
office-- thereby creating an official record. Some ministers adopted a custom of making collected returns--a list of marriages performed within a period of time such as a year or several years.
</p>
<p>Created by an act of 1720 to take effect on May 19, in 1721. Most loose records prior to 1830 are missing.Volumes that record deeds, court orders, and wills exist.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Marriages, 1786-1863, are comprised of three separate sections. The first section, pages 1-69, 1786-1863, is a typescript index. This index contains the first and last names of both parties. It is arranged alphabetically from A-Y and in addition, lists alternate spellings of last names. This index is a resource for the next section of this volume. The second section, pages 1-45, 1786-1863, is a register of marriage licenses issued by the county clerk. The licenses are recorded alphabetically (A-Y) by year and date--only the first and last names of the parties are listed. The third section, pages 46-74, 1786-1850, is comprised of individual marriage certificates and ministers' returns. The marriage certificates record the names of both parties celebrating the rites of matrimony, the date of the marriage, the name of the
minister who performed the ceremony and sometimes, the minister's religious denomination. The ministers' returns are made by individual ministers of marriages performed within the county. Sometimes, these returns are in the form of lists which record the names of all parties and the dates of the marriages.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional King George County Marriage Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"</extref>.
</p>
        <p>King George County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional King George County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/">Lost Records Localities Database</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Access Terms
</head>
      <corpname>King George County (Va.). Circuit Court.
</corpname>
      <subject>Christian sects--Virginia--King George.
</subject>
      <subject>Clergy--Virginia--King George.
</subject>
      <subject>Marriage--Virginia--King George.
</subject>
      <geogname>King George County (Va.)--History.
</geogname>
      <genreform>Indexes (reference sources)--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Local government records--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Marriage certificates--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Marriage records--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Marriage registers--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Ministers' returns--Virginia--King George.
</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
