<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01057">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01057::A Guide to the Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War
Service Records, 1917-1920)//EN" "vi01057.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War Service Records, <date>1917-1920</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War Service Records, 1917-1920
<num type="collectionnumber">41509
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Laura E. Drake
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft Word, created by Laura E. Drake, <date>2 November 2004</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War Service Records, <date> 1917-1920</date>;
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">41509
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Laura E. Drake
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War Service Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1917-1920
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">41509
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">State Records Collection, Accession 41509
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia State Library. Office of the State Librarian. American Library Association Library War Service Records, 1917-1920. Accession 41509, State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond,
Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the
century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond. Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library"
drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use.
Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass. The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the
sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located
in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The
Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903. The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of
funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General W.H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic
principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters. Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly
passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a
library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an
act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor. While many public records somehow survived the Commonwealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages
of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to
the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them. The new facility
quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for the current facility on December 7,
1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public. The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more
adequately reflect its mission and purpose today. In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia. It serves as a general reference and research library, as the official repository of state
archives and publications, and as a repository of state and federal documents. It provides assistance and advice to libraries around the state, and it administers state and federal library funds. The Archives and
Records Division of the library administers the state records management program, arranges and describes records deposited in the division, and provides assistance and advice to state and local government agencies
concerning the management of their records. Additionally, the agency produces many publications. The most notable among those regularly issued are the quarterly VIRGINIA CAVALCADE and the annual accession reports
of the Archives and Records Division showing its most recent records and manuscript acquisitions.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Contains the records of H.R. McIlwaine, State Librarian, in his function as the Virginia coordinator for the American Library Association Library War Service between 1917 and 1920. The state coordinators were
responsible for encouraging public libraries in patriotic activities including the distribution of government and war-related bulletins, and the solicitation of donations of published materials for troops and
money for the purchase of additional materials. Contents include correspondence with prospective local coordinators, correspondence with publishers regarding purchased and donated materials. The collections
includes correspondence with various officials from the American Library Association Library War Service. Also included are correspondence of the Richmond War Library Committee, one of the many community groups
throughout the state working to provide materials for the military. Correspondence includes requests for donations and responses from members of the local community.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Alphabetical.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I.">Administrative Records
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains notes and invoices related to the work of H.R. McIlwaine as the Virginia administrator for the American Library Association Library War Service. Also contains records from the Richmond War Library
Committee. The invoices reflect donations and purchases from publishers to support the war effort.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>alphabetical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Administrative Notes
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Invoices
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Richmond War Library Committee
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">3
</container>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="II.">II. Correspondence
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains correspondence with citizens of Virginia and staff of the American Library Association Library War Service. Included are records of donations, both monetary and property, as well as efforts to recruit
citizens to aid in the gathering of books, magazines and other printed materials for the military.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Alphabetical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>A, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>B, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">5
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>C, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">6
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>D, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">7
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>E - F, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">8
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>G, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>H - J, 1917
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>H - J, 1918
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>H - J, 1919-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>K - L, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">5
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>M, 1917
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">6
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>M, 1918
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">7
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>M, 1919-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">8
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>N - O, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>P - Q, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>R, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">3
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>S, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>T - V, 1917-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">5
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>W, 1917
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">1
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">6
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>W, 1918-1920
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">7
</container>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Y, 1917-1919
</unittitle>
<container label="box" type="box">3
</container>
<container label="folder" type="folder">8
</container>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
