<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01371">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01371::A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861)//EN" "vi01371.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons,<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1728, 1853-1861</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861 
</subtitle>
        <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Eddie Woodward, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 September 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons,<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1728, 1853-1861</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>LVA Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1728, 1853-1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 volume; 2 folders
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Northampton (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>IN PROCESS: Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861, are digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/discovery/search?vid=01LVA_INST:VU">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection</extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861. Local government records collection, Northampton County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These records were transferred to the Library of Virginia from Northampton County (Va.) in 2024 under accession number 54199 and as part of an undated accession. </p>
<p>Digital images of the register were produced by the Library of Virginia Imaging Services in 2024 and accessioned under accession number 54202.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>The Northampton County (Va.) “Register of Free Negroes,” 1853-1861, is available on microfilm, Northampton County (Va.) Reel No. 81. 
</p>
</altformavail>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>The Northampton County (Va.) “Register of Free Negroes,” 1853-1861, was transferred to the Library of Virginia from the Circuit Court of Northampton County in 2024 under accession number 54199 for digitization. The register was returned to the locality in 2024 by request of the clerk of the Circuit Court. 
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The microfilm of the “Register of Free Negroes” was originally described as Northampton County (Va.) “Register of Free Negroes,” 1840-1847, but was removed to the present Northampton County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861, to enhance the context between record types in July 2024. 
</p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registration Records, 1728, 1859, were originally described as part of the Northampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1728-1866, but were removed to the present Northampton County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861, to enhance the context between record types in July 2024.</p>
<p>These records have been processed, scanned, and indexed by L. Neuroth and other LVA staff for the purposes of digitizing them for the digital project Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative.</p>
<p>Encoded by E. Woodward, September 2006; updated by C. Collins, July 2024.</p>
</processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph></p>
<p><emph render="underline">"Free Negro" Registers</emph>
</p>
	<p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify "age, name, colour, and stature, by whom, and in what court the said negro or mulatto was emancipated; or that such negro or mulatto was born free." The process was extended to counties in 1803. Although some clerks were already recording such features, an 1834 Act of Assembly made it a uniform requirement to record identifying marks and scars and the instrument of emancipation, whether by deed or will. This bound register often coincided with a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information. Both the registration system and the process of renewal was enforced differently in the various Virginia localities. Thus, the information found in these registers may differ from year to year and across localities.
</p>
	<p>The register books resulting from the administration of the 1793 and 1803 Act of Assembly are evidence of Virginia legislators' reaction to a quickly growing free Black and multiracial population in Virginia in the post Revolutionary War period. Acts such as these allowed white officials to police the activities and movement of free Black community members throughout the state thereby restricting their autonomy.</p>

<p><emph render="underline">"Free Negro" Registrations</emph>
</p>
	<p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to "be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify age, name, color, status and by whom, and in what court emancipated." These entries often coincided with the creation of a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information.</p>
	<p>Documents in this record group differ from the bound volumes referred to as "registers." These registration records typically appear in the form of certificates or handwritten statements recording the free status of a Black or multiracial person. They can include the free person's name, sometimes age, a brief physical description, and the circumstances of the person's freedom or emancipation, parents, former enslaver, place or date of emancipation. There are also affidavits that were given by individuals affirming a free person's status, as well as written descriptions of free people. In some cases, a person would not have a registration to submit to the court. Instead they produced some other form of identification proving their free status, for example, a deed of emancipation, a will, an apprenticeship indenture, or an affidavit of someone testifying to their character and status.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Northampton County was named probably for the English county, of which Obedience Robins, a prominent early resident of the Eastern Shore, was a native. The county, which originally included all of the peninsula south of Maryland and which was one of the eight shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634, was first called Accomack. The General Assembly changed the name to Northampton County in 1643. Accomack County was created from Northampton County about 1663, but in October 1670, the General Assembly temporarily reunited the two counties as Northampton County. In November 1673, Accomack County was again separated from Northampton. The county seat is Eastville.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Northampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861, consist of one “Register of Free Negroes,” 1853-1861; a freedom certificate, 1728; and a list of “free negroes” ordered to be registered, 1859.
</p>
<p>The Northampton County (Va.) “Register of Free Negroes,” 1853-1861, kept by the clerk of the circuit court records the Registration number; Age [records birth date]; Names; Color; Stature [in feet and inches]; Apparent marks or scars on face, head, or hands; By what instrument emancipated and where recorded; In what county or place born free; and If emancipated since May 1st 1806, whether permission has been granted to reside in this state, and by what court and when. Some clerks recorded additional information not required by the law. There is no index or pagination for the volume.</p>
<p>The date registered is not recorded by the clerk, only the individuals date of birth and sometimes age at registration. [Library of Virginia staff cross-referenced the register with the Northampton County Order Books No. 43 and No. 44 to determine the date range of the book to be 1853-1861].</p>
<p>The freedom certificate, 1728, documents the status of Will, who, according to writing on the back of the certificate, was considered a “runaway negro.” Purportedly written by a justice of the peace in New York, the certificate asserts that Will was "free born."</p>
<p>The records are also comprised of a list of “free negroes” ordered to be registered, 1859. The list includes the names - listed alphabetically - of about 90 free Black and multiracial individuals residing in Northampton County. The latter pages of the list document familial relationships between several of those named and include additional names not present in the foremost list.</p>
    </scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged
</p>
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1728, 1853-1861, arranged loosely by record type then chronologically.</item></list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
    
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/lva/vi02198.html">Northampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1728-1866</extref>
</p>
<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Northampton County and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/discovery/search?vid=01LVA_INST:VU">Virginia Untold: The African American Digital Collection</extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
<p>Additional Northampton County court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">“A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.”</extref></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Records related to the Registration of Free Persons,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1728, 1853-1861</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc> Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent> 1 volume; 2 folders</extent>
</physdesc>
</did> 
<arrangement>
<p> arranged loosely by record type then chronologically 
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007886862">“Register of Free Negroes,” 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1853-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007532553">Free and Enslaved Records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1728-1866
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
 </c01>
   </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
