<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01971">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01971::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, 1781)//EN" "vi01971.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, <date>1781</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Fleming, William, Executive Papers of Acting Governor, 1781
<num type="collectionnumber">44393
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Craig S. Moore, <date>1 October 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, <date>1781</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44479
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009 
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Craig S. Moore
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1781
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44479
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">24 items
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia Governor (1781 : Fleming)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Governor's Office. Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, 1781. Accession 44479. State Records Collection, The Library of Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Acquired prior to 1905
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 2964-2965.
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Miscellaneous Reel 2964 - 1781 April 17-June 9
</item>
<item>Miscellaneous Reel 2965 - 1781 June 9-July 25
</item>
</list>
</altformavail>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William Fleming was born 18 February 1729 in Jedburgh, Scotland and educated at a school in Dumfries, Scotland.  Fleming studied medicine at the University of Edinburgh and became a doctor.  After finishing his education Fleming may have served in the British navy, but there are no extant records.  Fleming arrived in Virginia no later than 1755, and may have settled in Suffolk, Virginia, as early as 1751.  Commissioned an ensign in the Virginia militia in 1755, Fleming served as an officer and doctor during the French and Indian War.  After the war, he settled in that part of Augusta County, Virginia, which later became Botetourt County (and then became Roanoke County long after his death).  In 1774, he commanded militia troops at the battle of Point Pleasant and was wounded.  Because his wounds prevented him from practicing medicine, the Virginia Legislature awarded him 500 pounds for compensation.  When the Revolution began, Fleming helped organize the defenses of Virginia's frontiers.  He served in the Virginia Senate from 1777 to 1779, and was appointed to the Council of State in 1780.  During Col. Banastre Tarleton's raid of Charlottesville, Fleming, the most senior member of the Council, served as acting governor in place of Thomas Jefferson whose term expired.  Fleming only served as governor between 4 and 11 June 1781, when the Assembly reconvened in Staunton and elected Thomas Nelson as governor on 12 June.  After the Revolution, Fleming was appointed a commissioner for Virginia's western lands (now Kentucky). He was a member of the Danville, Kentucky, Convention of 1784 which eventually led to Kentucky statehood.  Fleming was a member for Botetourt County at the 1788 federal constitutional convention.  He married Anne "Nancy" Christian (1744-1815), daughter of William Christian, on 9 April 1763, and they had 7 children who lived past infancy.  Fleming died either 5 or 24 August 1795 in Botetourt County, Virginia.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Acting Governor William Fleming's Executive papers are organized chronologically. These papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during Fleming's eight days as acting governor of Virginia between 4 and 11 June 1781. The correspondence primarily relates to the Revolutionary War.  In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions, a statement, and a militia return. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple"><item>I. Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming, 1781</item>
</list></arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Palmer, William P., ed., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, Apr.1, 1781-Dec. 31, 1781, VOL. II, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1881.  
</bibref>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01>
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Executive Papers of Acting Governor William Fleming</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1781</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Boxes" type="box">1
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Noteworthy are the following items: a letter of Arthur Campbell, Washington, re. problems in raising militia, threats of attacks by Indians &amp; Tories, &amp; the need for ammunition (1781 June 4); a letter of Samuel Huntington, President of the Continental Congress, enclosing a resolution that all bills of credit issued in pursuance of the act of 18 March 1780 be marked or stamped before they are issued (1781 June 6); a letter of William Fleming, Staunton, to James Wood re. the removal of the convention Troops to Rutland in Massachusetts Bay and the officers to Connecticut (1781 June 6); a letter of William Fleming, Staunton, to county lieutenants directed by Col. James Wood re. the removal of the Convention Troops from the state and the furnishing of a sufficient guard to prevent an enemy rescue (1781 June 6); a letter of James Wood, Albemarle, re. the removal of the German prisoners to Shepherdstown and the need for a guard &amp; provisions (1781 June 8); a letter of Stephen Southall, Assistant Quartermaster, Staunton, to William Davies, War Dept., re. the delivery of an iron chest containing his valuable papers and the storage of powder, dry goods, bridles, &amp; saddles in Staunton (1781 June 9); a letter of William Fleming, Staunton, to James Wood re. provisions &amp; a guard to escort the prisoners to York, Pennsylvania (1781 June 9); a letter of George Rogers Clark, Yohogania Courthouse, recommending Capt. Bentley to supply Fort Jefferson with provisions (1781 June 10); a letter of Robert Morris, Philadelphia, re. the plan for establishing a national bank (1781 June 11); and a resolution from John Beckley, Clerk of the House of Delegates, that the Commercial Agent purchase arms, ammunition, &amp; military stores (1781 June 11).
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged in chronological order.
</p>
</arrangement>
	<c02>
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">1781</emph>
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03>
		<did>
		<unittitle>June 4-11
		<unitdate type="inclusive">
		</unitdate></unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
		<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
