<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01125">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01125::A Guide to the Olney Winsor Letters, 1786-1788)//EN" "vi01125.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Olney Winsor Letters, <date>1786-1788 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Winsor, Olney, Letters, 1786-1788
<num type="collectionnumber">21137, 22764
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 12 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>7 July 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Olney Winsor Letters, <date>1786-1788 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">21137, 22764
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Olney Winsor Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1786-1788
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">21137, 22754
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.1 cubic feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Olney Winsor Letters, 1786-1788. Accessions 21137, 22764. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Accession 21137 purchased from James A. Tyson, Old and Rare Books, 319 Caesar Michigan Boulevard, Providence, Rhode Island, 21 January 1937.
</p>
<p>Accession 22764 purchased from the John Carter Brown Library, Providence, Rhode Island, through the Rhode Island Historical Society, 1947.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Olney Winsor was born 24 August 1753 in Providence, Rhode Island, to Samuel Winsor (1722-1803) and Lydia Olney (1726-1753). He became a successful merchant in Rhode Island. Winsor married first Freelove
Waterman 30 November 1777, and they had four children. He married second Hope Thurber, and they had one child. Winsor died in Providence 15 March 1837.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Letters, 1786-1788, from Olney Winsor (1753-1837) of Providence, Rhode Island, and temporarily living in Alexandria, Virginia, to his wife, Hope Winsor, in Providence discussing his journey to Alexandria,
social and religious life in Alexandria, as well as his business concerns as a merchant. Winsor comments on personal and family matters. Winsor writes about his legal entanglement over a condemned brig which
required him to travel to Williamsburg, Virginia, and he describes the towns of Fredericksburg and Richmond, Virginia, and Williamsburg as he travelled through them. Winsor comments on a local election in
Alexandria, politics in Rhode Island, and Maryland's ratification of the federal Constitution. He mentions a fire in Richmond in January 1787, comments on funerals in Alexandria, and remarks on Virginia
Episcopalians. Winsor describes a dinner he attended with George Washington at which they discussed the new federal Constitution. Also includes a memorandum of his return voyage from Alexandria to Providence.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Olney Winsor, Papers, 1808-1847. Accession 36202; Misc. Reel 58. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 September 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife describing his voyage from Providence to Alexandria, mentioning whom he has met, and sending his love to his family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7, 11, 16, 17, 18, 20, 27 September and 1 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on his boarding house, the weather, religious services he attended and family matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on his health, friends, and family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>5 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife stating that Captain Wheaton has arrived and sending love to his family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>9 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife stating that he is sending items by way of Captain Wheaton, noting that the Alexandria horse races are commencing, and commenting on his business.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on her health, his desire to see his family, and items he has sent home. Winsor comments on Rhode Island politics and difficulties in the state.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>12 November 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife stating that he will be travelling to Williambsurg, Virginia, to attend a trial concerning a brig and its cargo that he has an interest in.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 November 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife concerning her health and his family. He mentions the death of his grandmother.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 November 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife regarding his absence from home, his wife's letter writing, the rent for the home, and other family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>5 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife describing his journey from Alexandria to Williamsburg and back.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>9, 10, 11, 16, 17, 19 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife concerning their health and family news. He also comments on his business, including the unloading and loading of cargo for shipment.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife thanking her for the gifts sent and mentioning items he sent to her. Winsor also comments on his health and his business.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on his daughter Nancy's education.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>10, 11 January 1786 [1787],
</unitdate>from Owen Winsor, Alexandria, Virginia, to his wife, Hope Winsor, Providence, Rhode Island, commenting on his activities in Alexandria and stating that he misses his wife and family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 July [January], 19 January 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor, Williamsburg, to his wife concerning his treatment in Alexandria, the necessity for another journey to Williamsburg concerning the trial relating to the brig and its cargo, and fire which
swept through Richmond 15 January 1787.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>26 January 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor, Alexandria, to his wife concerning the trial for the brig and family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7, 13, 18, 22 February, 2, 3, 4, 6 March 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on the trial concerning the brig, Rhode Island politics, Alexandria politics and elections, prostitution and women in Alexandria, funerals, African Americans, and
personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>6 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18, 19 February 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife concerning family and business matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>23 March 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife discussing the condemnation of the brig and the fate of its cargo, as well as business and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 March 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife discussing his business dealings and family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 March 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife concerning his fitting of the brig for sailing and thanking her for clothes she sent.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 April 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife stating that he is shipping her some flour and cloth and adding he hopes to be home in May, but is uncertain. Winsor also sends family and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 April 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife sending his love to the family and asking her to forward a letter (not present) to his father.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 April 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife discussing his wife's his daughter's and his own health and commenting on his possible return to Providence.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 April 1787,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife stating that he had bought most of the sugar and coffee from the brig's cargo ordered sold.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 January 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife informing her that he has arrived in Alexandria after a long sea voyage and stating many arrived at his store to see him.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>9, 13 January 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife providing more details about his voyage from Providence to Alexandria.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>25 January 19 February 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to a friend in Baltimore, Maryland, discussing the Rhode Island governor's view of the federal Constitution. He also comments on Episcopalians and Methodists in Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 February 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on a fire in Alexandria which threatened his store, and that the Potomac River is closed because of ice. He adds that he hopes for more letters from home and sends
family and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>10 March 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife concerning his health and business, commenting on his daughter's education, and sending personal and family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 March 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife reflecting on death and commenting on personal, family and business news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21, 22, 23, 24, 25 March 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on family matters, including noting that he has written his father and brother. Winsor comments on friends, business, and his health. He adds that he has sent a book
for his daughter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>31 March 5 April 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on George Washington and the Constitution. He also mentions news from Providence that he has seen.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages, incomplete.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>31 March 4, 5, 8, 10, 17, 18, 19 April 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife describing a dinner he attended with George Washington. He comments on the new federal Constitution and Virginia's stand. Winsor also sends personal and business news. This is
accession 22764.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>16 leaves, positive and negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>26, 27, 28, 29 April 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife thanking her for items sent and mentioning items he has sent to her. Winsor mentions that Maryland has adopted the Constition. He asks after family and sends personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>3, 4, 5 May 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on his social life in Alexandria and mentioning that he had been to Sunday meeting.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>8 May 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife sending social news and asking after the family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>11, 16, 18, 19, 20, 21 May 1788,
</unitdate>from Winsor to his wife commenting on his social life and his religious life, and discussing his business affairs.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Memorandum,
<unitdate>10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 June 1788,
</unitdate>of Winsor's voyage from Alexandria, Virginia, to Providence, Rhode Island.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
