<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01578">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01578:: John R. Cary Records,  1832-1869)//EN" "vi01578.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the John R. Cary Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832-1869</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Cary, John R., Records, 1832-1869
<num type="collectionnumber">1096181, 1096186, 1096192, and 1132396
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 March 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the John R. Cary Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832-1869</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers">1096181, 1096186, 1096192, and 1132396
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John R. Cary Records, 1832-1869
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832-1869
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">1096181, 1096186, 1096192, and 1132396
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">5 vol. (730 p.)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Cary, John R.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>John R. Cary Records, 1832-1869. Local government records collection, Gloucester County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These materials came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Gloucester County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
      <p>John R. Cary served as clerk of Gloucester County from 1837 until his death in 1867.
</p>
      <p>The records were used as evidence in a chancery case heard in Gloucester County Circuit Court in 1874 entitled John S. Cooke, Executor of John R. Cary versus Widow of John R. Cary and others. The suit originated from Cary's wish in his will that an inventory on his estate not be performed to determine its value before selling it to pay off his debts. Upon assuming executorship of Cary's estate, Cooke was unable to carry out Cary's wish due to the numerous debts Cary incurred personally and as representative of both Matthew W. Kemp's estate and Thomas Cary's estate. Cooke asked the court to assist him in determining the value of Cary's estate and the debts Cary owed. The court ordered all papers and books kept by Cary related to his estate, and as representative of both Kemp's estate and Thomas Cary's estate, audited by a special commission and a report made.
</p>
<p>Created in 1651. All records were destroyed by an 1820 fire, and most of the records created after 1820 were destroyed by fire on April 3, 1865, in Richmond, where they had been moved for safekeeping during the Civil War.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Records, 1832-1869, maintained by or related to John R. Cary and recording financial, agricultural, and miscellaneous information concerning Cary's estate in Gloucester County.
</p>
      <p>Account book of Thomas Cary's estate, perhaps kept by his nephew John R. Cary, who became representative of his uncle's estate following his death. Portion of volume dated 1832-1840 records accounts of individuals who did business with the Thomas Cary estate and the accounts of the estate itself. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each account includes date of transaction, style of transaction, form of payment, amounts owed and paid. Transactions include loans, payment of loans, house expenses, payment of laborers, and slave sales and hires. Pages in volume, dated 1868-1869, record transactions perhaps related to a church fundraiser.
</p>
      <p>Two memorandum books of John R. Cary. One dated, 1847-1852, records payments to laborers; purchases of merchandise, groceries, and guano; debts; and sale of wheat. A second memorandum book, dated 1860, records cash paid and cash received by Cary. Transactions are listed in chronological order and include purchases of food, whiskey, nails, guano, and spices, repairs to carriage, spices, and miscellaneous expenses. Cary received cash from payment of debts, sale of slaves, slave hires, and fees from court suits. The last few pages of memorandum book record payments made to laborers who were perhaps doing work on Cary's home. Several pages list dimensions of various rooms, such as the parlor, portico, and porch. The second memorandum book also includes a list of slaves hired out by Cary as personal representative of Matthew W. Kemp and a list of slaves owned by Cary in January 1860.
</p>
      <p>Account book, 1868-1869, kept by John S. Cooke, executor of John R. Cary. The volume records Cooke's transactions both personal and as executor of Cary's estate. Information found in volume includes name of account, date of transaction, cash paid, cash received, and names of individuals paid or from whom cash was received. Accounts, kept by Cooke as Cary's executor, record payment of debts owed by Cary at the time of his death. Volume includes receipts for payment of debts. Cooke's personal accounts record loans made to individuals many of whom were African-American. Repayment of loans were made by labor such as cutting wood, hauling goods, and washing clothes or by hiring themselves or children to Cooke for a period of time.
</p>
      <p>Account book, 1847-1864, of John R. Cary, recording the accounts of individuals and companies Cary had transactions with, both personal and as representative of Matthew W. Kemp's estate. Information found in volume includes name of account, date of transaction, style of transaction, amount paid, amount received, and name of individuals paid or from whom cash or items were received. Transactions relate to Cary's personal debts, maintenance of house and other buildings on his estate, agricultural supplies and debts incurred by Cary as Kemp's representative. Account book also contains detailed information related to the planting of wheat and production of pork by Carey's estate. In addition, there is miscellaneous information related to history of Cary family, and remedies for diseases such as cholera and scrofula. There are also loose papers in volume, one of which is a letter written by Cary during Civil War era in which he recounts a Northern raid on the town of Gloucester.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>For additional information see the Gloucester County Chancery Cause, John S. Cooke, Executor of John R. Cary versus Widow of John R. Cary and others available on the Library of Virginia's Chancery Records Index.  The index number is 1874-004.
</p>
<p>Gloucester County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Cloucester County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/">Lost Records Localities Database</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname encodinganalog="600$a">Cary, John R. d. 1867</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Executors and administrators--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Farm layout--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Planting (Plant culture)--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Swine--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Wheat--Virginia--Gloucester County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Gloucester County (Va.)--History--19th century.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Account books--Virginia--Gloucester County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Correspondence--Virginia--Gloucester County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Estate administration records--Virginia--Gloucester County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Gloucester County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Memorandums--Virginia--Gloucester County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1096186">Account book, 
<unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832-1869
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1096192">Memorandum book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847-1852
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1096192">Memorandum book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1096181">Account book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868-1869
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1132396">Account book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847-1864
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
