<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01392">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01392::A Guide to Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1781-1866, undated)//EN" "vi01392.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1866, undated</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1781-1866, undated
<num type="collectionnumber">1160443, 1160466, 0007416401
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. .01 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives database, created by Sarah Nerney, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 November 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1866, undated</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Numbers">1160443, 1160466, 0007416401
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Callie Lou Freed
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1866, undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers">1160443, 1160466, 0007416401
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">0.45 cubic feet ca.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records, 1781-1866, undated, Local Government Records Collection, Amelia County Court Records, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Amelia County under the accession numbers 37990, 37993, 37995, and 41507.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Amelia County was formed in 1734 from Brunswick and Prince George counties.
</p>
      <p>The General Assembly passed a law as early as July 1, 1861, calling for the enrollment of free Black persons to work in the public service. From 1862 to 1863, at the request of the president of the Confederate States, the General Assembly passed three more laws that requisitioned enslaved persons to work on fortifications and other works of the public defense. Each county and city were alloted a certain number of enslaved persons that had to be provided to the government under the requisition.
</p>
<p>In 1806, the General Assembly moved to remove the free Black population from Virginia with a law that stated that any emancipated enslaved persons, freed after May 1, 1806, who remained in the Commonwealth more than a year, would forfeit the right to freedom and be sold by the Overseers of the Poor for the benefit of the parish. Families wishing to stay were to petition the legislature through the local county court. Beginning in 1837, emancipated enslaved persons could petition the local courts for permission to remain.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Materials in the Library of Virginia’s collections contain historical terms, phrases, and images that are offensive to modern readers. These include demeaning and dehumanizing references to race, ethnicity, and nationality; enslaved or free status; physical and mental ability; religion; sex; and sexual orientation and gender identity.</title></p>

      <p>Amelia County (Va.) Enslaved and Free Records include "Free Negro Certificates and Registrations" ((1794, 1801, 1806, 1809, 1816, 1820, 1823, 1829-1833, 1835, 1837, 1843, 1847, 1847, 1849-1852, 1854-1856, 1863, 1866, and undated),"Free Negro Tax Records" (1801-1803, 1851-1853, 1855-1856, 1858-1859), "List of slaves belonging to Lyman Hall" (1781), "List of slaves belonging to Frances Tabb" (1804), “Requisitions for Public Use” (1860-1865, and undated), "Petitions to remain in the Commonwealth" (1816), and a "Slave Schedule" (1850).
</p>
      <p>"Free Negro Certificates and Registrations," 1794, 1801, 1806, 1809, 1816, 1820, 1823, 1829-1833, 1835, 1837, 1843, 1847, 1847, 1849-1852, 1854-1856, 1863, 1866, and undated, record the free person’s name, sometimes age, a brief physical description, and the circumstances of the  person’s freedom or emancipation. If born free, a reference is sometimes made to the parents.  If emancipated, emancipating enslaver, place and date of emancipation, and prior registration are usually recorded. There may also be affidavits that were  given by individuals affirming a free person’s status, as well as written descriptions of free persons. In  addition, there are registrations that are loose papers matching information found in the bound volumes of  registered “free negroes” kept in the court house. The 1863 affidavit contains a list of names and birthdates of about twenty people.
</p>
      <p>"Free Negro Tax Records," 1801-1803, 1851-1853, 1855-1856, 1858-1859, were compiled by the commissioner of the revenue for tax purposes, and records the names of free adult Black persons and persons of color within a district, as well as children, place of abode, and trade or occupation for the adult males and females.
</p>
   
      <p>"List of slaves belonging to Lyman Hall of South Carolina," 1781, contains names, ages, and whether the enslaved person is a man, woman or child. The list was compiled to comply with an Act of Assembly entited "An Act to authorize the Citizens of South Carolina and Georgia to remove their slaves into this state."
</p>
      <p>"List of slaves belonging to Frances Tabb," 1804, contains the names of persons enslaved by Tabb, however, no surnames are given. The reverse of the document states that these enslaved persons were enlaved by the dower of Frances Tabb.
</p>
      <p>“Requisitions for Public Use,” 1860-1865, and undated, include requisition lists filed in local courts and payroll records of the Virginia Engineer. Information found in these records include names of free persons of color and enslaved people,  locality of origin, occupation, location of fortification, names of enslavers, and monetary value of enslaved  people.  Other records in this group include orders, letters, and reports to the Amelia County court and clerk of court from the Amelia County committee appointed to apportion slaves, the Secretary of the Commonwealth, the Confederate Engineering Department, the General Assembly, and individuals.(Accession 37990, 37993, 37995).
</p>
<p>"Petition to remain in the Commonwealth," 1816, filed by Tinsley and other enslaved persons emancipated by the will of Ann Hughes record the name of the petitioner, the circumstances  of free status, and a request  to remain in the county. May include accompanying  names of citizens who can testify  to the free status or who support  the request of the  petitioner to remain. Free registrations and other supporting documents may also be included.
</p>
      <p>"Slave Schedule," 1850, contains two pages from the 1850 census of enslaved inhabitants. This is not a complete copy. It records the name of the enslaver and then enumerates but does not name individual enslaved persons.  A column exists to record a number of enslaved persons manumitted if any.  Information is recorded about the unnamed enslaved persons including age, sex, color, whether a fugitive from the state, and whether "deaf, dumb, blind, insane or idiotic."
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by record type.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also:  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00797.xml"> Amelia County (Va.) Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands Records, 1868 </extref> </p>

        <p>Additional Amelia County Enslaved and Free Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA009">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site.</p>

<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Amelia County and other localities are available on <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan/search-the-narrative">Virginia Untold</extref>
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    
    <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1160443">
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> "Free Negro Certificates and Registrations" ((1794, 1801, 1806, 1809, 1816, 1820, 1823, 1829-1833, 1835, 1837, 1843, 1847, 1847, 1849-1852, 1854-1856, 1863, 1866, and undated),"Free Negro Tax Records" (1801-1803, 1851-1853, 1855-1856, 1858-1859), "List of slaves belonging to Lyman Hall" (1781), "List of slaves belonging to Frances Tabb" (1804), “Requisitions for Public Use” (1860-1865, and undated),
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 0007416401">
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>“Requisitions for Public Use” (1864), "Petitions to remain in the Commonwealth" (1816)
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1160466">
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> "Slave Schedule" (1850).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
