<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01120">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01120::A Guide to the Ross Family Correspondence, 1861-1864)//EN" "vi01120.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Ross Family Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864 </date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Ross Family, Correspondence, 1861-1864
<num type="collectionnumber">21089
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 40 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 June 2004 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Ross Family Correspondence, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1864 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">21089
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Ross Family Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1865
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">21089
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.225 cu. ft. and 1 box
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Ross family. Correspondence, 1861-1864. Accession 21089. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Gift of Dr. J. Ross Perkins, Richmond, Virginia, on 22 January 1936
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>James Ross (1791-1859) and Frances Hudson Loving Ross, married 22 February 1827) in Fluvanna County, Virginia, had six children. Their sons, James Eastin Ross (ca. 1834-1863), Nathaniel Wheeler Ross (ca. 1838-
1863), and William David Ross (ca. 1837-1863) enlisted in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry at the beginning of the Civil War. James Eastin Ross was a carpenter before the war, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross a farmer, and
William Daniel Ross a manager. James Ross and William Ross were killed in Pickett's Charge at the battle of Gettysburg on 3 July 1863. Nathaniel Ross died of disease two months earlier, 2 April 1863, at the Ross
home, in Wilmington, in Fluvanna County. Their sisters Cornelia F. Ross, Lucy W. Ross (1848-1921), and Mary Eliza Ross (1828-1872) remained at home. Mary Eliza Ross married James White (1824-1905). Lucy W. Ross
married Philip D. Perkins (1845-1915). One of their children was Joseph Ross Perkins (1877-1949) who graduated with a degree in dentistry from the Medical School of the University of Virginia. He resided in
Richmond, Virginia. Perkins and his wife Maggie Parrish Perkins (1884-1973) had at least one child. Perkins is buried in Oakwood Cemetery in Richmond.
</p>
      <p>The sons of Pleasant White (1810-1869) and Martha Loving White, Richard Pleasant White (ca. 1840-1864) and Luther C. White were cousin of the Ross brothers. A sergeant in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry,
Richard P. White was wounded 10 May 1864 at Chester Station, and died of his wounds five days later on 15 May. Luther C. White served in the 22nd Virginia battalion and was captured in 1863 at Falling Waters,
Maryland, and was released in February 1865. William P. Ryals (ca. 1842-1863) of Company C died of disease 25 February 1863. Benjamin C. Richardson (ca. 1834-1862), a farmer who enlisted in Company C was killed at
the battle of Seven Pines on 1 June 1862.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Correspondence, 1861-1864, of the Ross family of Fluvanna County, Virginia, consisting mainly of letters from James Eastin Ross, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross, William Daniel Ross, and their cousin Richard P. White,
soldiers in Company C, 14th Virginia Infantry, to the Rosses' mother, Frances H. Ross, and sisters, Lucy W. Ross, Mary Eliza Ross, and Nela F. Ross. The Rosses and White describe camp life, including their health,
food, clothing, religion, and guard duty. They recount the movements of their regiment from Jamestown, Virginia; Mulberry Island (now Fort Eustis) and Land's End in Warwick County, Virginia; to Suffolk, Virginia;
to the Peninsula campaign, including the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks) and the Seven Days Battles; from the Maryland campaign and the battle of Antietam (Sharpsburg) to the battle of Fredericksburg to the
campaign leading to the battle of Gettysburg. They also comment on other battles both in and outside of Virginia, including: Big Bethel, Virginia; the West Virginia campaigns of 1861-1862; first and second Bull
Run (Manassas); Lexington, Missouri; Burnside's North Carolina expedition; Fort Donaldson (Tennessee) Monitor-Merrimack fight; Corinth, Mississippi; Morgan's Kentucky raid of 1862; Murfreesboro (Stones River),
Tennessee; Vicksburg, Mississippi; Chancellorsville; Brandy Station; and the battle of Winchester, Virginia, in June 1863. They also discuss the Trent Affair when the United States Navy removed two Confederate
diplomats from a British vessel.
</p>
      <p>Letters comment on Union raids into Fluvanna County; the burning of Hampton, Virginia, by Confederate troops; a religious revival in camp; the use of African American labor in building fortifications and in
company camps; and slaves in Fluvanna County. They mention various generals, including General John Magruder's ineptness; a brigade review by General George Pickett; the manuevers of General Jeb Stuart and his
cavalry; the death of General Stonewall Jackson; and the military strategies of General Robert E. Lee. They mention President Abraham Lincoln and Union generals George McClellan and Joseph Hooker. Letters describe
fraternization with Union troops while on picket duty and hopes for peace. They also discuss social life in Fluvanna County and in Richmond during the war. Other correspondents inlcude Callie Bragg, James Brainard
Taylor Bragg, John Micajah Bragg, R. J. Bragg, Benjamin C. Richardson, William P. Ryals, and Luther C. White. Also includes a letter, 22 January 1936 from J. Ross Perkins, nephew of the Ross brothers and donor,
giving information on the brothers' fate in the Civil War.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May-August 1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">13 May 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel W. Ross, in camp in Richmond, Virginia, to his family and friends in Fluvanna County, Virginia, commenting on life in the army. Includes a postscript from William Daniel Ross.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 May 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his brother James Eastin Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his quarters, food, and military drilling.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 May 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his brother James Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on drilling and camp life, and describing an encounter between a U.S. Navy vessel and Virginia militia in
Portsmouth, Virginia. Includes a postscript commenting on the company's weapons.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 May 1861,
</unitdate>from William Daniel Ross (hereinafter Daniel), Richmond, to the Ross family, Fluvanna County, discussing a false report of a clash in Hampton Roads, and a rumor that his regiment will be heading to
Fredericksburg or Manassas, Virginia.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 May 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to his family, Fluvanna County, mentioning the rumored battle at Hampton Roads, discussing the preachers they have heard, and their orders to be prepared to move out.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 June 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, on Jamestown Island, Virginia, to their family, Fluvanna County, commenting on their health, the regiment's preparedness, lack of a post-office, and describing
Jamestown and the James River.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 June 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's health, describing the island's fortifications and crops, mentioning the battle of Big Bethel, Virginia, and
asking that he be sent tobacco.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 June 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, asking that he be sent some
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">pantloons,
</title> and stating that Dick White would like some socks, drawers, and a waistcoat.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 July 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Jamestown, to his family, Fluvanna County, commenting on camp life, his enlistment, hopes for visiting home, and pay. He mentions a Confederate defeat in western Virginia (West
Virginia).
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 July 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Jamestown, to his sisters, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life, acquaintances at home and in the army, and news of the battle at Manassas, Virginia between Confederate and Union
troops. He mentions the family's slaves.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 July 1861,
</unitdate>from John Micajah Bragg, Camp Monterey, [Virginia], to his cousins commenting on army and camp life and food. He asks for letters.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">13 August 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, Virginia, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing his regiment's movements and their first skirmish as the Confederates burned the town of Hampton, Virginia
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 August 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's new camp site at Mulberry Island and their hike there and provides news of friends. Mentions the African
Americans there.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September-December 1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">2</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 September 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing their camp and their closeness to the ships of the United States Navy in Hampton Roads. He also mentions friends in the regiment.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 September 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to their family, Fluvanna County, discussing their activities and marches. They mention several acquaintances.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 September 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life and friends.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 October 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross and Lucy Ross, Fluvanna County, conerning camp life; a Confederate victory in Lexington, Missouri; and asking for items. He asks James to remember him to
the slaves.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 October 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending news and thanking her for items sent. Notes that there has been no skirmishes in the area, but he and his company are ready.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 November 1861,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and wishing he could get a furlough to return home for a while. He mentions acquaintances at home and in camp.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 November 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his family, Fluvanna County, discussing another camp move by his regiment, and other news of friends and family.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending news of camp, family, and friends. He mentions the blockading vessels of the U. S. Navy.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on his health, his regiment's movements, and a skirmish between a Confederate vessel and Union ships. He also comments on
fighting in South Carolina and Florida.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, remarking on camp life and news of family and friends.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning camp life and mentioning the the Union blockade and a confrontation between the Patrick Henry, a Confederate vessel, and
Union ships.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and news on family and friends. He mentions the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Trent
</title> Affair.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to their family, Fluvanna County, sending camp news, asking for items from home, and mentioning a skirmish between Confederate and Union soldiers.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 December 1861,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, providing camp news and news of family and friends.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January-February 1862
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">3</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] 1862,
</unitdate>from James Eastin Ross, [near Richmond?], to his family, Fluvanna County, containing news of the camp life of the company, including the news that the men hired an African American cook.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 January 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. Nathaniel reports a box James sent him had been stolen. He mentions an exchange of
prisoners between the Confederate and Union armies.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 January 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna, complaining of the continual movement from camp to camp and about General John Magruder. He comments on men hiring substitutes to fight, and
notes that the culprits who stole the box were found.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 January 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning his poor health, the company's new camp, and the stolen box. He mentions the continued excitement over the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Trent
</title> Affair, and that Union troops under Ambrose Burnside have left Fort Monroe.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White and Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to Ross' sister, Fluvanna County, concerning their new camp. Nathaniel reports that he might not reenlist in his current company, but take a 30
day furlough and get an enlistment bonus of $50.00.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages, incomplete.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the regiment's new camp, the battle of Mills Spring, Kentucky, the death of John Tyler, and the Ambrose Burnside expedition.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing efforts to reenlist the 14th Virginia Regiment, reports that Burnside's expedition had failed, and war news from Tennessee.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the fall of Roanoke Island to Burnside's expedition, efforts to reenlist Company C, 14th Virginia as a cavalry unit, and
news of friends and family.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Warwick County, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news and efforts to reenlist the company. White hopes that James Eastin Ross will join the company.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 February 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross (
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Crack
</title>), Fluvanna County, concerning his reenlistment and James' possible enlistment. He mentions the capture of Fort Donaldson.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March-April 1862
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">4</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 March 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Warwick County, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Richard White's and Nathaniel Ross' reenlistment in the 14th Virginia. He discusses his concerns over Union victories in
Tennessee and North Carolina.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 March 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Suffolk, Virginia, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, describing the regiment's relocation to Suffolk, mentioning the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Merrimack's
</title> attack on the Union Navy, and discussing family and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 March 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Suffolk, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move to Suffolk, describing the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Merrimack's
</title> assault on the Union Navy, and personal news, including his reenlistment.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">20 March 1862,
</unitdate>from Benjamin C. Richardson, Suffolk, to Cornelia F. Ross (hereinafter Nela), Fluvanna County, saying how much he would like to see her and other friends at home.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 March 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his brother James Ross (
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Crack
</title>), Fluvanna County, concerning reenlistment and the draft.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 March 1862,
</unitdate>from James E. Ross to his sister Mary E. Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on his joining the 14th Virginia, and stating that he has little news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 April 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, noting that nothing is happening and wishing that he could come home and visit with the ladies.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 April 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Suffolk, to his father, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and informing his father of his illnesses.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 April 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Suffolk, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his journey from Fluvanna County to Suffolk to join the 14th Virginia, and telling her that he has seen his brothers
and cousins in camp.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 April 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Suffolk, to John Bragg, Fluvanna County, discussing his trip from Fluvanna County to the camp of the 14th Virginia in Suffolk, including a stop in Richmond to settle Bragg's bill with
the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Enquirer
</title>.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 April 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Suffolk, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and his responsibility to drill a militia unit.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 April 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and noting the possibility of a battle on the Peninsula.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May-June 1862
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">5</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 May 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Suffolk, to his mother and sisters, Fluvanna County, informing them of the impending loss of Norfolk, Virginia, a battle on the Peninsula, a reorganization of the 14th Virginia, and
Daniel's convalesence in Petersburg.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 May 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Petersburg, Virginia, to his mother Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning his convalescence in Petersburg.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 May 1862,
</unitdate>from Callie [Bragg], Richmond, Virginia, to Nela Ross, Fluvanna County, sending family news and expressing her concern that the Union army is very close to Richmond.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 May 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Petersburg, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move from Suffolk to Petersburg and noting that he had little to eat while on the march.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 May 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Petersburg, to Francis H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of himself and his brothers, and stating that they are sending some clothing they don't need home.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 May 1862,
</unitdate>from R. J. Bragg to his cousin and uncle discussing camp and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 May 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, stating that Daniel hopes to get a furlough and remarking on the fighting on the Peninsula and how Joseph Johnston's withdrawal up the Peninsula has
upset many soldiers.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 June 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Richmond, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the 14th Virginia's first action during the battle of Seven Pines, including news of the death of Ben C. Richardson and
James' wounding in battle.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 June 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the 14th Virginia, battle of Seven Pines and the death of Ben Richardson. He describes the location of the regiment's
camp and mentions possible future battle.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 June 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Daniel's poor health and sickness among the company. He mentions a skirmish between Union troops and the 53rd Virginia
and Stuart's ride around McClellan.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July-September 1862
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">6</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 July 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the Seven Days Battles, including the battle of Malvern Hill. He provides the regiment's casualties.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] July 1862,
</unitdate>from an unknow correspondent to an unknown recipient containing camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages, fragment.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 July 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, near Richmond, to Daniel Ross, Fluvanna County, stating he hopes Daniel is feeling well, updating him of James' wound, and commenting on the decline of the regiment since Seven
Pines.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 August 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross to the Ross family, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, whether the Union army will move on Richmond, and whether England and France will recognize the Confederacy.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 August 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 August 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Fauquier County, to Daniel Ross, concerning the regiment's and army's maneuvering, and skirmishes with Union troops.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 September 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Loudoun County, Virginia, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, concerning the second battle of Manassas (Bull Run) and his regiment's movements.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 September 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Frederick County, Maryland, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning the Confederate army's move into Maryland and sending camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 September 1862,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Ross, Frederick County, Virginia, to James Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the army's battle at Sharpsburg, Maryland (Antietam), and retreat. He adds that the army is tired and he hopes
for peace.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October-December 1862
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">7</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 October 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White to nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 October 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross and Nela Ross, Fluvanna County, to Nathaniel Ross informing him how Fluvanna County is suffering from the war in terms of the deaths of many of its sons.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 October 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross and Daniel Ross, Fluvanna County, to Nathaniel Ross, regarding crops in Fluvanna County, news of a battle at Corinth, Mississippi, John Hunt Morgan's raid in Kentucky, and the brothers'
hopes for peace.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 December 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White and William P. Ryals to Nathaniel Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of the company.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 December 1862,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing his return to Company C, 14th Virginia, in the days after the battle of Fredericksburg.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 December 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, near Fredericksburg, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 December 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, Virginia, to Nathaniel Ross, Fluvanna County, stating that both armies apparently have gone into winter quarters and sending other camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 December 1862,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, to Luther C. White, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. He doesn't believe there will be much fighting during the winter.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">31 December 1862,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning his health and his travel back to his company.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January-February 1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">8</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 January 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Guinea Station, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing news of the company.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 January 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Guinea Station, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news, asking where his brother Daniel is, enclosing news of the battle of Murfreesboro, Tennessee and of Vicksburg,
Mississippi, and adding that he thinks peace soon come.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 January 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Huguenot Springs hospital, to his sisters, Fluvanna County, concerning his stay in the hospital and his belief that peace is near.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages, incomplete.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 January 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Guinea Station, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending company news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 January 1863,
</unitdate>Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning his return to his regiment and their greetings. He notes that the Union army is north of the Rappahannock River.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 January 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to Nathaniel[?] Ross, Fluvanna County, sending him company news, mentioning a rumor of a Union troop movement, and hoping that his brother will soon rejoin the
regiment.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">26 January 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, near Guinea Station, to his sister, Fluvanna County, describing Fredericksburg, detailing picket duty there and conversations with Union pickets, and sending other news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 February 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp life and news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 February 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending news of camp life.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 February 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross to his sister, Fluvanna County, providing camp and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 February 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news. He notes that the regiment is moving south.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 February 1863,
</unitdate>from Luther C. White, near Guinea Station, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and stating that rumor is the Union army will cross the Rappahannock River when the weather gets warm.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March-May 1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">9</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 March 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Petersburg, Virginia, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and informing her how friends and family in the regiment are faring.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 March 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Petersburg, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, sending camp and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">20 March 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Petersburg, to his sister, Fluvanna County, sending regimental and army news, including movements of various brigades.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 March 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Southampton County, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's move towards Suffolk and speculations. He notes that the Union army in Mississippi is
focusing on Vicksburg. He hopes for peace by summer.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 April 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Southampton County, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing Nathaniel's death at home, deaths in camp, and news about the regiment's movements towards Suffolk.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 April 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Nansemond County, Virginia, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, describing the fighting around Suffolk, providing camp news, and hoping that someone might be able to come to camp and
take his winter clothes home.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 May 1863,
</unitdate>from James and Daniel Ross, near Richmond, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's departure from Suffolk, General Lee's victory at the battle of Chancellorsville, and news of a
Union cavalry into Fluvanna County.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 May 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Richmond, to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing someone to get their winter clothes, Union troops in Fluvanna County, Stonewall Jackson's death, views on the war, and
camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 May 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Hanover County, Virginia, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, complaining that he has not received any mail from home, discussing the regiment's movements, and other camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 May 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Hanover County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing the Union cavalry raid on Fluvanna County, and camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 May 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, Hanover County, to Lucy W. Ross, Fluvanna County, commenting on camp life, news about Vicksburg, Mississippi, his hopes for peace, and the African American attitude towards the Union
troops raiding Fluvanna County.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 May 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Hanover County, to Lucy W. Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, news of fighting around Vicksburg, a brigade review by General George Pickett, and the regiment's new hats.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 May 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Hanover County, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, discussing camp news, the marriage of a love interest of White's, news of Vicksburg, and speculation of fighting the enemy.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
</c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June, August, November-December 1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">10</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 June 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, Hanover County, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning Vicksburg, the contrast in the military situation from the year before, a religious revival in camp, and efforts to get
back pay for his deceased brother Nathaniel.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 June 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross to Mary Eliza Ross, Fluvanna County, discussing the activities of his regiment, news of Union raids in King and Queen and King William Counties, Virginia, and news that General Lee is
moving north.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 June 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, near Culpeper Court House, to his sister, Fluvanna County, commenting on the army's movement northward and his speculation on its aim. he also includes camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 June 1863,
</unitdate>from James Ross, near Culpeper Court House, to Nela F. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning news about the regiment's movements and camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">20 June 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, near Warrenton[?], Virginia, to his sister, Fluvanna County, informing her of the regiment's movements and sending camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 June 1863,
</unitdate>from James[?] Ross, Ashby's Gap, Virginia, to Frances H. Ross, Fluvanna County, concerning movement of the Confederate and Union armies, including news of a fight at Winchester, Virginia.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages, incomplete.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">30 June 1863,
</unitdate>from Daniel Ross, near Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, to his sister, Fluvanna County, concerning the army's invasion of Pennsylvania, including the local inhabitants' fright and news that General Richard
Ewell has invested Harrisburg, Pennsylvania.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 August 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing news of the regiment, including the possible return of prisoners from the battle of Gettysburg.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 August 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White to his cousin, Fluvanna County, sending camp news and personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 November 1863,
</unitdate>from James B. T. Bragg, Richmond, sending personal news and offering a look at Richmond during the Civil War.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 December 1863,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Richmond, to his brother, Fluvanna County, discussing the regiment's movements between Petersburg and Richmond and mentioning General Pickett.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">11</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 February 1864,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White[?], Richmond, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, containing camp news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages, incomplete.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 March 1864,
</unitdate>from James B. T. Bragg, Richmond, to is cousin, Fluvanna County, commenting on his life in Richmond and describing his work on the railroad, as well as personal news.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 April 1864,
</unitdate>from Richard P. White, Richmond, to his cousin, Fluvanna County, commenting on regimental news and news on the military situation in Virginia, including another possible invasion of Maryland.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1936
</unitdate></unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">12</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 January 1936,
</unitdate>from Dr. J. Ross Perkins, Richmond, providing genealogical information on James Eastin Ross, Nathaniel Wheeler Ross, and William Daniel Ross, and the Ross family in connection with the Civil War era
letters.
</unittitle>
            <physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
