<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01362">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01362::A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 circa)//EN" "vi01362.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 circa
</titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 circa
<num type="collectionnumber">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">circa 01 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives database, created by Eddie Woodward, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 October 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 circa
</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Number">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Eddie Woodward
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799-1870 circa
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode number">1144734, 1156122, 1156108
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1.35 cubic feet
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Albemarle County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 circa Local Government Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Albemarle County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle, and governor of Virginia from 1737 to 1754. It was created by a statute of 1744 and formed from Goochland County; part of Louisa County was added in 1761 and islands in the Fluvanna (now the James) River in 1770. The court met for the first time on 8 February 1745. The county seat is the city of Charlottesville.
</p>
<p>All order books except the first and many loose papers between 1748 and 1781 were destroyed by British general Banastre Tarleton's raid on Charlottesville in 1781 during the Revolutionary War.
</p>
<p>In 1806, the General Assembly moved to remove the free negro population from Virginia with a law that stated that all emancipated slaves, freed after May 1, 1806, who remained in the Commonwealth more than a year, would forfeit his right to freedom and be sold by the Overseers of the Poor for the benefit of the parish. Families wishing to stay were to petition the legislature through the local county court. Beginning in 1837, freed slaves could petition the local courts for permission to remain.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Albemarle County (Va.)Free Negro and Slave Records, 1799-1870 cica, include affidavits and certificates of freedom (1815-1870, undated), committee regarding carrying of arms by negroes papers (1865), deeds of emancipation (1841-1864), free negro delinquent tax list (1853), free negro list (1853), free negro nonresident list (1853), miscellaneous (1863), slave patrol
papers (1799-1864, undated), petition to be classified as white (1869), petitions for voluntary enslavement (1858-1864), petitions to remain in county(1816, 1850, 1852), runaway slave papers (1845), sale of slaves (1843), and free negro registers (1804-1864, undated).
</p>
      <p>Affidavits and Certificates of free negroes contain the name of the person, sometimes their age and a brief physical description, and a statement based either on another person's knowledge or on other official documentary evidence seen by the certifier that this person was either born free or was emancipated. If born free, reference is sometimes made to parents. If emancipated, emancipating owner, place and date of emancipation, and prior registration as a free negro are usually mentioned.
</p>
      <p>Court order appointing members to a committee regarding carrying of arms by negroes. No names are contained.
</p>
      <p>Deeds of emancipation or manumission may contain the name of the former slave owner, the name of the slave, the date or age at which the slave will be freed, the date the deed was written, and the date the deed was proved. The age of the slave at the time of the deed was written, a surname assigned to the freed slave by the slave owner, and the slave owner's reason for emancipation are sometimes given.
</p>
      <p>The list of delinquent free negros contains the names of free negroes, recorded by the Commissioner of Revenue and listing the known effects and the amount of taxes owed by each person listed.
</p>
      <p>The list of free negroes contains the names of male negroes or mulattoes and female negroes or mulattoes, male children, female children, place of abode, and trade or occupation for the adult males and females.
</p>
      <p>The list of free negroes non residents contains the names of free negroes, recorded by the Commissioner of Revenue and listing the known effects and the amount of taxes owed by each person.
</p>
          <p>The slave patrol papers contain patrol orders with specific instructions for a patrol to convene and listing all of the persons summoned to participate, patrol appointments listing persons appointed or summoned to participate, and patrol returns listing the names of the patrollers and recording the hours of services and expenses incurred.
</p>
      <p>The petition to be classified as white contains the name of the petitioner. The petitioner's parents, and/or persons who can attest to their claim to be reclassified are sometimes included.
</p>
     <p>The petitions for voluntary enslavement contain the name of the petitioner, and the potential master or mistress. Sometimes a former slave owner is mentioned.
</p>
      <p>The petitions to remain in county (or state) contain the name of the petitioner. Sometimes the names of witnesses that can vouch for the character of the petitioner are mentioned. Freedom papers and other supporting documents may also be included.
</p>
      <p>The runaway slave papers contain court documents such as notices and orders and include the name of the slave. The slave owner is sometimes mentioned.
</p>
      <p>The sale of slaves papers contains the account of the sale, the name of the seller, the name of the purchaser and the date of the transaction. The name and/or sex and/or age of the slave being sold may also be included.
</p>
      <p>The free negro registers contain information on a single person as to the name, age, complexion, stature in feet and inches, apparent marks or scars, whether emancipated or free born, and date this information was certified by the court.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by records type.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>An index for Albemarle County Free Negro and Slave records is available at the Manuscript Reading Room Reference Desk.
</p>
        <p>Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Albemarle County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/">Lost Records Localities Database</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Access Terms
</head>
      <corpname>Albemarle County (Va.). Circuit Court.
</corpname>
    <subject>Firearms--Law and legislation--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Free African Americans--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Fugitive slaves--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Slaves--Emancipation.
</subject>
      <subject>Slaves--United States--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Tax collection--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Taxation--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History.
</geogname>
      <genreform>Affidavits--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Bills of sale--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Certificates--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Deeds of manumission--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Lists--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Local government records--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Petitions--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
