<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01136">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01136::A Guide to the Henry Lee Papers, 1768-1816)//EN" "vi01136.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Lee papers, <date>1768-1816 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Lee, Henry, Papers, 1768-1816
<num type="collectionnumber">26824
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 20 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>8 September 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry Lee Papers, <date>1768-1816 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">26824
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Henry Lee Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1768-1816
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">26824
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 volume (172 leaves), negative photostats
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Henry Lee Papers, 1768-1816. Accession 26824, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Lent for copying by Charles Carter Lee, Rocky Mount, Virginia, 16 November 1967.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Also on Miscellaneous Microfilm reel 1, as part of the Charles Carter Lee Collection.
</p>
</altformavail>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Henry Lee was born 29 January 1756 at Leesylvania in Prince William County, Virginia, to Henry Lee (1729-1787) and Lucy Grymes Lee (1734-1792). He graduated from Princeton in 1773. During the American
Revolution, Lee was appointed a captain of cavalry in the Virginia militia and served in the Continental Army. Lee impressed George Washington (1732-1799) who convinced Congress to appoint Lee to an independent
cavalry command. Lee and his legion served under Washington in New Jersey and New York, then under command of Nathanael Greene (1742-1786) in North Carolina and South Carolina. Lee's Legion earned itself and its
commander fame. After the war, Lee entered politics and represented Virginia in the Continental Congress from 1786 to 1788 and sat in the Virginia ratifying convention for the Constitution in 1788. From 1791 to
1794 Lee served as Governor of Virginia. He represented Westmoreland County in the Virginia House of Delegates in 1785-1786, 1789-1791, and 1795-1799. He retired from politics in 1801 and returned to Westmoreland
County. However, bad business decisions and poor health eventually forced Lee to remove to Barbados, leaving his family behind. In 1818, he determined to return home, but got only as far as Cumberland Island,
Georgia, where he died at Dungeness, home of the widow of General Nathanael Greene, on 25 March 1818. He was buried at Dungeness, but was reinterred in the Lee family crypt at the Lee Chapel at Washington and Lee
University in Lexington, Virginia, 30 May 1913. Lee married first Matilda Lee (1763-1790) in 1782, and they had four children. He married second Ann Hill Carter (1773-1829) 18 June 1793 and they had six children,
including Robert E. Lee (1807-1870).
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1768-1816, of Henry Lee (1756-1818) of Westmoreland County, Virginia, and Barbados, containing bonds, correspondence, deeds, depositions, notes and reminiscences. Correspondence includes transcripts of
letters and depositions discussing the the quartering of British troops in Boston, Massachusetts, possible efforts by British officers to encourage African Americans to rebel, and general unrest in Massachusetts,
all before the Revolution. Also contains letters from George Washington (1732-1799), the Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834), and Nathanael Greene (1742-1786) regarding the military situation in New York, North
Carolina, and South Carolina during the American Revolution; letters concerning politics in the United States during the 1780s and 1790s; and correspondence containing recollections by other officers of the
Continental Army about campaigns in North Carolina and South Carolina, including the battles of Guilford Court House and Hobkirk's Hill. Letters from Barbados deal with Lee's health; advice to his wife Ann Hill
Carter Lee (1773-1829) and sons Henry Lee, Jr., (1787-1837) and Charles Carter Lee (1798-1871); and Lee's business concerns. Letters also discuss the death of Lee's first wife Matilda, his marriage to Ann Hill
Carter, and the death of his father-in-law Charles Carter (1732-1806). Letters, bonds, and deeds concern Lee's land interests in western Virginia, Washington D. C., and Santo Domingo. Also includes notes and
reminiscences about Revolutionary War campaigns in North Carolina and South Carolina, including Andrew Jackson's (1767-1845) recollection of the battle of Hobkirk's Hill near Camden, South Carolina. The letters,
notes and reminiscences dealing with the Revolution were used in Lee's MEMOIRS OF THE WAR IN THE SOUTHERN DEPARTMENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc>
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Originals are located at the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia.
</p>
</originalsloc>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcripts of letters,
<unitdate>1768,
</unitdate>from Samuel Adams (3 October), P. Cory (22 September), and Thomas Cushing (27 September) to Dennys De Bert, colonial agent for Massachusetts in London, England, concerning the quartering of troops in
family homes in Boston, Massachusetts.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcripts of depositions,
<unitdate>31 October 1768,
</unitdate>from Robert McIntyer, John Boyles, William Warden, William Foster, Grace Foster, John Geyer, James Jones, and William Tyler stating that British military officers had encouraged African Americans to
rebel.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcript of letter,
<unitdate>21 March 1775,
</unitdate>from Thomas Cushing, Boston, Massachusetts, to Richard Henry Lee, [Westmoreland County], Virginia, discussing the unrest in the colonies.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcript of letter,
<unitdate>30 September 1779,
</unitdate>from General George Washington, Headquarters, West Point, New York, to Henry Lee discussing recent military actions.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcript of letter,
<unitdate>16 October 1780,
</unitdate>from the Marquis de Lafayette to Major Henry Lee expressing pleasure that Lee's Legion has been placed under his command and sending small gifts for Lee and his officers.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcript of letter,
<unitdate>12 January 1781,
</unitdate>from General Nathanael Greene to Colonel Henry Lee reviewing military affairs in the Southern colonies during the American Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcript of letter,
<unitdate>22 May 1781,
</unitdate>from General Nathanael Greene to Colonel Henry Lee discussing Lee's raid on Augusta, Georgia, and the military situation in South Carolina.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 April 1786,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, New York, New York, to an unknown recipient discussing current political affairs.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 May 1786,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to [Mrs.?] Fendall, sending family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 October 1786,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, New York, to an unknown recipient commenting on the current political situation and criticizing domestic affairs.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>11 November 1786,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, New York to [?] Lee commenting on the Continental Congress and politics.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 December 1786,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee to Richard [Bland Lee?] discussing family news and his reelection to the Continental Congress.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 March 1790,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, Virginia, to [James Madison?] criticizing the Secretary of the Treasury's funding plan and commenting on public finances and the economy.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>14 August 1791,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Alexandria, Virginia, to [James Madison?] commenting on stock speculation.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>8 December 1791,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee to [James Madison?] discussing the defeat of the army in Ohio and business matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>8 January 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, Virginia, to [James Madison?] discussing President George Washington, politics and the agricultural and manufacturing prospects of the country as proposed by the Secretary of
the Treasury.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 January 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, to [James Madison?] commenting on political and military matters, including the defeat of the army by Indians in Ohio.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 January 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, to [James Madison?] commenting on the United States Constitution, Congress, and public finances. He remarks on the possibility of his accepting command of the army on the
western frontier.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 February 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, to [James Madison?] discussing the powers of Congress and Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton's funding and assumption plans.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 April 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, to [James Madison?] commenting on funding and assumption, the Secretary of the Treasury, and other political matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>10 September 1792,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Richmond, to [James Madison?] mentioning a personal tragedy and discussing current affairs, including the Bank of the United States.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Agreement,
<unitdate>6 June 1792,
</unitdate>between Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge County, Virginia, and Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, concerning 960 acres of land in Botetourt County, Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 June 1792,
</unitdate>from Walter Jones to Governor Henry Lee discussing politics and the
<title render="doublequote">rights of the people.
</title>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 September 1792,
</unitdate>from J. Holcombe, Cumberland County, Virginia, to Governor Henry Lee, Richmond, inquiring about purchasing land in the Dismal Swamp owned by Lee.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 October [1792],
</unitdate>from Thomas Lee Shippen, Berkeley, Charles City County, Virginia, to Governor Henry Lee, introducing a Mr. Howell.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 April 1793,
</unitdate>from the committee of correspondence for the [Culpeper?] Society to Governor Henry Lee accepting his offer of land for granaries.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 May 1793,
</unitdate>from Charles Carter, Shirley, Charles City County, to Governor Henry Lee consenting to Lee's marriage to his daughter Ann Hill Carter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>25 September 1794,
</unitdate>from Walter Jones to Governor Henry Lee regarding the Whiskey Rebellion and his sons' service in the militia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Agreement,
<unitdate>22 May 1795,
</unitdate>between Henry Banks and Henry Lee stating that Banks will secure titles for Lee for 15,000 acres of land patented in Harrison County, (West) Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>16 November 1795,
</unitdate>from Senator Rufus King of New York, to Henry Lee, Philadelphia, stating that he will not consider any government department, but will remain where he is.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>29 May 1796,
</unitdate>for all right in the estate of William Dolman from John James Maund to Henry Lee, both of Westmoreland County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bond,
<unitdate>27 December 1796,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, to William Glassell, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bond,
<unitdate>1798,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, to George Keith Taylor, Prince George County, Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Bond,
<unitdate>1798,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, to George Keith Taylor, Prince George County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 March 1798,
</unitdate>from George Keith Taylor, Petersburg, Virginia, to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, concerning business matters and land.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Agreement,
<unitdate>22 August 1798,
</unitdate>between John Tayloe, Richmond County, Virginia, and Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, concerning lots in Washington, D.C.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 July 1806,
</unitdate>from Ann Hill Carter Lee, Shirley, Charles City County, to Henry Lee lamenting the death of her father Charles Carter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Notes,
<unitdate>1808,
</unitdate>by Colonel Howard concerning Lee's Legion, the battle of Guilford Court House and the battle of Eutaw Springs.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 April 1808,
</unitdate>from Robert Goodloe Harper, Senate, Washington, D.C. to Henry Lee, Alexandria, Virginia, regretting that he was unable to visit Lee.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 May 1809,
</unitdate>from John Pratt, Jr., of Camden, South Carolina, to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, commenting on mutual acquaintances.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>8 June 1809,
</unitdate>from Charles Simms, Alexandria, to Henry Lee, Spotsylvania Courthouse, Virginia, providing an account of the battle of Red Bank, or Fort Mercer, New Jersey, in October 1777.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>29 January 1804,
</unitdate>for land in Bath County, Virginia, from Philip Richard Fendall and Robert Young, Alexandria, to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County. Recorded in the United States Circuit Court, District of Columbia, on 10
August 1809.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>16 November 1809,
</unitdate>from John F. Mercer to Henry Lee recounting the battle of Brandywine, Pennsylvania, in September 1777.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>22 November 1809,
</unitdate>for 15,040 acres in Bladen and Brunswick Counties, North Carolina, from Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, to Richard B. Lee, Fairfax County, Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>9 January 1810,
</unitdate>from William Richardson Davie, Lancaster Courthouse, South Carolina, to Henry Lee, Fredericksburg, commenting on Revolutionary War battles in North Carolina, including Guilford Courthouse.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>22 January 1810,
</unitdate>for certain land in Santo Domingo from Henry Lee to Henry Lee, Jr., and Robert Sanford, all of Westmoreland County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 February 1810,
</unitdate>from John Blackwell, Fauquier County, Virginia, to Henry Lee presenting a chronology of the Third Virginia Regiment's performance during the Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21 February 1810,
</unitdate>from William Richardson Davie, Catawba, South Carolina, to Henry Lee reviewing his military services and battles in North Carolina during the Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 February 1810,
</unitdate>from an unidentified correspondent to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, discussing the actions of a mutual acquaintance.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>12 March 1810,
</unitdate>from William Goddard, Providence, Rhode Island, to Richard Jackson, [Washington D.C.] providing sketches of men and events in Rhode Island during the American Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>15 March 1810,
</unitdate>from William Richardson Davie, Catawba, to Henry Lee commenting on battles in North Carolina during the Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>31 March 1810,
</unitdate>from Christopher R. Greene, Providence, to Henry Lee, Fredericksburg, providing biographical notes on General Nathanael Greene.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 April 1810,
</unitdate>from William Goddard, Providence, to Henry Lee congratulating Lee on his proposed memoirs about the Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 May 1810,
</unitdate>from Christopher R. Greene, Providence, to Henry Lee providing information on Christopher Greene of Rhode Island, who was killed in the Revolution. Includes a postscript by William Goddard.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 June 1810,
</unitdate>from Christopher R. Green, Providence, to Henry Lee, [Westmoreland County], providing more biographical detail about Christopher Greene.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>September [1810],
</unitdate>from William Goddard to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, providing biographical notes on William Prescott who fought in the battle of Bunker Hill.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>November 1810,
</unitdate>from Joseph Wheaton, Washington, to Henry Lee, Alexandria reviewing the battle of Springfield, New Jersey, in June 1780.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>31 December 1810,
</unitdate>from William Goddard, Providence, to Henry Lee, Alexandria, commenting on Lee's writings.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 April 1811,
</unitdate>from Ludwell Lee to Henry Lee, Westmoreland County, inquiring about land in Westmoreland County.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 April 1811,
</unitdate>from Nathaniel Pendleton to Henry Lee, Alexandria, concerning the execution of Colonel Isaac Hayne of South Carolina by the British on 4 August 1781.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 August 1813,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to President James Madison informing Madison of his health and expressing his appreciation of favors Madison has done for him.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>13 August 1813,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to Anne Hill Carter Lee, Alexandria, concerning family news and personal notes to the family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>14 August [1813?],
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to William Yeaton, Alexandria, discussing business matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>15 August 1813,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to Charles Carter Lee, Alexandria, providing fatherly advice to his son.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>16 August 1813,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to [Ann Hill Carter?] Lee discussing personal and family matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>3 September 1813,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Barbados, to [Henry Lee, Jr.?] providing fatherly advice to be applied to Charles Carter Lee.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>7 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>15 November 1813,
</unitdate>from Secretary of War John Armstrong to Major General Wade Hampton concerning military intelligence during the War of 1812.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>2 May 1816,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Port au Prince, Haiti, to Henry Lee, Jr., concerning financial matters. Includes a postscript by J. G. Chappell.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>[21 June 1816],
</unitdate>from William Jenner to P. Lane concerning Henry Lee's health.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>8 August 1816,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Turk's Island, to [Charles Carter Lee?] concerning his health, his travels, and family matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7 December 1816,
</unitdate>from [Henry Lee?], Havana, Cuba, to Henry Lee, Jr., Alexandria, concerning the elder Lee's activities and travels.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostat.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>23 June, n.y.,
</unitdate>from Henry Lee, Boston, to John Maund, Westmoreland County, discussing financial matters.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>from Joseph Wheaton to Henry Lee discussing Wheaton's military service in the American army and his father's military service in the British army up to and during the American Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Account,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of Andrew Jackson, a prisoner of the British army, during the battle of Hobkirk's Hill near Camden, South Carolina.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Account,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of the surprise and defeat of Thomas Sumter near Rocky Mount, South Carolina, possibly by loyalist forces under Colonel David Fanning.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous notes,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>on Revolutionary War officers, and on battles in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Virginia during the Revolution.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
