<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01363">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01363::A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1785-1919)//EN" "vi01363.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1785-1919</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1785-1919
<num type="collectionnumber">1156109, 1156110, 1156111, 1156146, 1156145, 1156123
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 01 Kilobytes
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Archives database, created by Eddie Woodward, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 8 November 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1785-1919</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode Number">1156109, 1156110, 1156111, 1156146, 1156145, 1156123
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Eddie Woodward
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Eddie Woodward
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1785-1919
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode number">1156109, 1156110, 1156111, 1156146, 1156145, 1156123
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2.45 cubic feet ca.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Albemarle County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1785-1919. Local Government Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This item came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Albemarle County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Albemarle County was formed in 1744 from Goochland County. Parts of Louisa County were added in 1761 and 1838.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Amnesty Oaths (1865), Free Negroes Drafted (1863-1864), Free Negroes Enrolled in Militia (1861), Free Negroes Laboring for Confederate Government (1861), Free Negroes Requisitioned for Militia (1861), Free
Negroes quisitioned for Public Defense (1863), Horse Claims (1865), Military Committee Papers (1862-1866), Military Correspondence (1861-1866), Military Passes (1865), Military Service Exemptions (1864), Military
Service Records (1921), Muster Rolls (n.d.), Oaths of Allegiance (1865-1866), Oaths of Allegiance Reports (1865), Officer's Appointment (1794, 1801), Officer's Appointments &amp; Commissions (n.d., 1860, 1866),
Paroled Soldiers (1865), Pension Papers (n.d., 1785-1915), Pension Rolls (n.d., 1900-1914), Petitions (1859, 1907-1909), Petitions for Draft Exemption (1864), Roll of Members (1896-1897), Roster of Surviving
Members (1904), and Slaves Requisitioned for Public Defense (1862-1864).
</p>
      <p>Amnesty oaths contain the name of the applicant seeking amnesty and the clerk.
</p>
      <p>Free Negroes drafted contains the names of free blacks between the ages of 18 and 50 years old.
</p>
      <p>Free Negroes enrolled in militia contains the names of free blacks between the ages of 18 and 50 years old.
</p>
      <p>Free Negroes laboring for Confederate government contains the names of free blacks ordered to report for service.
</p>
      <p>Free Negroes requisitioned for militia contains orders, lists and various other papers pertaining to free blacks and their service in the local militia. These papers contain the names of free blacks eligible
for service in the militia.
</p>
      <p>Free Negroes requisitioned for public defense is an order summonsing justices, ordering Sheriff's to create a list and notifying slave owners that they will supply slaves for the defense of Richmond. The names
of the justices are included.
</p>
      <p>Horse claims contains the name of the claimant and often the circumstances involving the loss of their horse.
</p>
      <p>Military committee papers contain the reports of the proceedings of the meetings and frequently include statements of the incomes and dispersal of funds.
</p>
      <p>Military correspondences contain letters to and/or from military or militia personal.
</p>
      <p>Military pass contains the name of the bearer with authorization to return to his/her home.
</p>
      <p>Military service exemptions contain the names of the applicants for exemption. The reason for exemption is sometimes included.
</p>
      <p>Military service records contain the name of the applicant, his date and place of birth, name of father and place of birth, name of mother and place of birth, race, whether a citizen, whether a voter, religious
enomination, name of wife (if married), date and place of marriage, date and place of birth of wife, names of children, date and place of birth of children, college fraternities belonged to, name of high school,
name of university, occupation before military service, place of residence before military service, current place of residence, date and location of induction into military, branch of military service, unit name,
military training received, transfer and promotion information, where in military action, decorations and other honors, if killed, military medical records, occupation after war and other information.
</p>
      <p>Muster rolls contains the names of soldiers enlisted in the 3rd Regiment Virginia Volunteers and 88th Regiment Virginia Militia. The 3rd Virginia Volunteers list contains the members of Monticello Guard
exempted from jury duty.
</p>
      <p>Oaths of allegiance contain the names of the applicants. Some oaths of allegiance contain the age, occupation and place of residence of the applicant. The name of the Provost Marshall is sometimes included.
</p>
      <p>Oaths of allegiance reports are lists of the names, occupation, place of residence and date of taking the oath. Also included is the name of the Provost Marshall.
</p>
      <p>Officer's appointments and commissions contain the names of the officers, rank, military unit, and date of appointment or commission. In some instances the name of a resigning officer is included.
</p>
      <p>Paroled soldiers papers contain the names of prisoner's of war paroled by the Provost Marshall's office. The lists include their names, rank and military unit. In some instances only the total numbers (no
names) of those paroled or taking the oath of allegiance are indicated.
</p>
      <p>Military pension records contain the name of the applicant and sometimes the applicant's wife or other family members may be mentioned. The circumstances surrounding their military service, birth date and place
of birth, financial condition of the family, living conditions, work conditions, and health of the soldier are very often mentioned. Disability claims and widow's claims are included with pension records.
</p>
      <p>Pension Rolls vary in the degree of information provided, from simple lists of names to names with the amounts awarded each, and/or why the soldier's application was approved or rejected. Sometimes the
applicant's military unit, rank, or place of residence are mentioned.
</p>
      <p>Petitions include petitions to enlarge the Monticello Guards, and petitions to have the roll of members of the Charlottesville Artillery, Carrington's Battery, Cutshall's Battery, 10th Virginia Cavalry, Blue
Ridge Rifles, Sturdivants Virginia Battery and the Border Guards recorded among the county court records. Some include the names of the members of the units.
</p>
      <p>Petitions for draft exemption include the name of the applicant and testimonials as to why he should be exempted.
</p>
      <p>Rolls of members include the names of the members of the Monticello Guards.
</p>
      <p>Roster of surviving members of the Albemarle Light Horse Co. (Co. K), 2nd Virginia Cavalry, includes the names of the soldiers and their place of residence.
</p>
      <p>Slaves requisitioned for public defense includes orders, applications for exemption and lists of slave owners and the number of slaves requisitioned from each. Applications for exemption may mention the name of
the slave and the slave owner.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by record type.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>An index for Albemarle County Military and Pension records is available at the Manuscript Reading Room Reference Desk.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Access Terms
</head>
      <corpname>Albemarle County (Va.). Circuit Court.
</corpname>
      <subject>Confederate States of America--Defenses.
</subject>
      <subject>Confederate States of America--Politics and government.
</subject>
      <subject>Draft--Confederate States of America.
</subject>
      <subject>Free African Americans--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Military pensions--United States--Civil War, 1861-1865.
</subject>
      <subject>Military pensions--United States--Revolution, 1775-1783.
</subject>
      <subject>Military pensions--United States--War of 1812.
</subject>
      <subject>Military pensions--United States--World War, 1914-1918.
</subject>
      <subject>Military pensions--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <subject>Militia.
</subject>
      <subject>Slaves--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</subject>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History.
</geogname>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
</geogname>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.
</geogname>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History--War of 1812.
</geogname>
      <geogname>Albemarle County (Va.)--History--World War, 1914-1918.
</geogname>
      <geogname>United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
</geogname>
      <geogname>United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.
</geogname>
      <geogname>United States--History--War of 1812.
</geogname>
      <geogname>United States--History--World War, 1914-1918.
</geogname>
      <genreform>Legislative acts--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Local government records--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Loyalty oaths--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Military commissions--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Military passes--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Military records--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Muster rolls--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
      <genreform>Orders (military records)--Virginia--Albemarle County.
</genreform>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
