<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01133">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01133::A Guide to the Achilles James Tynes Letters, 1864-1951)//EN" "vi01133.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Achilles James Tynes Letters, <date>1864-1951 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Tynes, Achilles James, Letters, 1864-1951
<num type="collectionnumber">27936
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 15 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>19 August 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Achilles James Tynes Letters, <date>1864-1951 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">27936
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Achilles James Tynes Letters,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1864-1951
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">27936
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">159 leaves, negative photostats
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Achilles James Tynes Letters, 1864-1951. Accession 27936, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Lent for copying by Harriet Louisa Tynes, 1009 Carolina Street, Greensboro, North Carolina, 23 March 1972. Originals owned by A. Lacy Tynes of Leesburg, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Achilles James Tynes was born 29 November 1833 in Montgomery County, Virginia, to Smuel Tynes (1811-1879) and Frances Herndon Haythe Tynes (1812-1869). Tynes moved to Tazewell County, Virginia, from Roanoke
County, Virginia, in 1857. When the Civil War began, Tynes enlisted in the 8th Virginia Cavalry 25 July 1861, helping to form Company H. Appointed a captain 15 May 1862, he served until the end of the war and was
paroled 22 May 1865 in Charleston, West Virginia. After the war, Tynes returned to Tazewell County to farm. He established a woolen mill factory in the county and also helped establish the county's public schools.
He served as president of the Tazewell Street Railway Company which brought electricity to the county. Tynes married Harriet Louisa Fudge (1842-1922) 2 March 1864, and they had eleven children. Tynes died 11
November 1914 in Tazewell County.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Letters, 1864-1951, of Achilles J. Tynes (1833-1914) of Tazewell County, Virginia, to his wife Harriet Louisa Fudge Tynes (1842-1922) discussing military life, including campaigns in southwest Virginia, the
Shenandoah Valley, and West Virginia. He describes various fights, including the battles of Lynchburg, 3rd Winchester, Fisher's Hill, Cedar Creek, and Waynesboro. He comments on various Confederate generals such
as Robert E. Lee (1807-1870), John McCausland (1836-1927), Albert Gallatin Jenkins (1830-1864), Jubal Early (1816-1894), Thomas Rosser (1836-1910), Lunsford Lindsey Lomax (1835-1913), and Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905),
and their Union army counterparts Ulysses S. Grant (1822-1885), George Crook (1828-1890), William Averell (1832-1900), David Hunter (1802-1886), and Philip Sheridan (1831-1888). Tynes details his day-to-day
activities and offers advice to his wife regarding the homefront difficulties she faces during the war. Also includes a letter to his father Samuel Tynes (1811-1879) concerning the war. Also contains a letter, 15
September 1910, from William S. Grimes concerning Toland's Raid and the 26th Virginia Infantry Battalion. Also includes letter, 1 November 1950, from W. Edwin Hemphill (1912-) of the Virginia State Library to
Buford C. Tynes (1884-1954) of Huntingdon, West Virginia, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes (1837-1891) to alert inhabitants of Tazewell County about Toland's Raid, and Tynes' reply to Hemphill, 3 November 1950.
Also includes a letter, 15 May 1951, from Buford C. Tynes to Achilles L. Tynes (1873-1952) of Staunton, Virginia, regarding the Kanawha Valley during the Civil War.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Edwin H. Harman, Letters, 1860-1864 (LVA accession 27935)
</p>
<p>Historic Crab Orchard Museum papers, [1598?]-1922 (LVA accession 34648)
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate>17 May 1864-18 June 1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 May 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Jenkins' Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Louisa Fudge Tynes, Tazewell County, Virginia, sending camp news including a skirmish troops had with Union troops and the capture of
prisoners.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>24 May 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes , Jenkins Cavalry, to Harriet Tynes informing her of the death of General Albert Gallatin Jenkins, the movements of the Union army under Generals Averell and Crook, and other camp
news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 May 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Jenkins Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes discussing Confederate and Union troop movements. He mentions his health and concern over her wellbeing.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>3 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp and personal news. Tynes expresses concern about his wife's health.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes describing a skirmish between Confederate and Union forces in Alleghany County, near Covington and mentioning other military manouvers. He
also sends personal and camp news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>13 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, Rockbridge County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the movements of troops now located in Rockbridge County. He describes camp life.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>14 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes describing a fight between Confederate and Union troops that he is in.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>14 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Bedford County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes regarding fighting in the Shenandoah Valley between Confederate troops and Union troops.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, [Lynchburg, Virginia], to Harriet Tynes describing the battle of Lynchburg between Confederate troops under the command of General Jubal Early and Union troops under the command
of General David Hunter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate>22 June 1864-10 August 1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 June 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Early's Army Corps, to Harriet Tynes discussing the pursuit by General Early's Confederate troops of Union forces under General Hunter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 June 1864,
</unitdate>Achilles J. Tynes, Staunton, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes concerning the pursuit of Union troops. He also comments on life in camp and gives her an account of his business concerns.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Rosser's Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes commenting on Jubal Early's Maryland Campaign in the summer of 1864.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the 1864 Maryland campaign and discussing personal and family business.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>10 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>18 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes concerning the theft of horses from camp and other camp news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, Warren County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp life and mentioning fighting in the Shenandoah Valley.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>25 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on camp life and fighting in the Shenandoah Valley.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 5th Cavalry Brigade, to Harriet Tynes discussing the current campaign, noting that he is leaving his baggage behind on the move, and stating there was a false alarm of a Union
army attack.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 July 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes informing her of the movement of Early's army across the Potomac River into Maryland and Pennsylvania and sending news of the campaign.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>12 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>10 August 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, McCausland's Brigade, to Harriet Tynes describing a fight in the Shenandoah Valley, commenting on the campaign, and sending other news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate>30 August 1864-26 October 1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
</container>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 August 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes stating that he has visited relatives in the area where he is now camped and sends news of them. He also expresses concern about her wellbeing.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 September 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Woodstock, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes sending news of the defeat of Early's army at the 3rd battle of Winchester. Includes a note that he has a new horse.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>24 September 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes describing the fighting between Confederates under General Early and Union troops under General Philip Sheridan, including the battle of Fisher's Hill.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>26 September 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Albemarle County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes lamenting the string of Confederate defeats and fulminating against a lack of discipline in the army.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>30 September 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Nelson County, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes sending news of friends in the area and informing her of fighting between Early's troops and Sheridan's forces.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the fighting in the Shenandoah Valley between Confederate and Union forces. He expresses concern for her wellbeing.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>6 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending news of himself and others and of the army's preparations. He mentions an attempted Union raid on the salt works in
southwestern Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>16 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending news of himself, commenting on the army, and stating that he misses her.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes commenting on his life in the army.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>21 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes sending personal and family news. He also discusses the battle of Cedar Creek.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>26 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on his situation for rooms, the war, and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate>27 October 1864-11 Februart 1865
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
</container>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 October 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes discussing family and personal news and commenting on the army.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Augusta County, to Samuel Tynes, Tazewell County, concerning the health of Achilles' wife Harriet and where she will live during the winter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>4 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, to Harriet Tynes concerning her accomodations for the winter months. Also sends news about the war.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>19 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning his move to new quarters, people he has met, and his routine. He also comments about where she will stay
during winter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>20 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes commenting on his quarter and routine. He metions his clothes and asks about his family.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>22 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning deteriorating social conditions, wishing the war were over, and commenting on her situation for winter.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes regarding his health, news in her letters, and other family and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>28 November 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes discussing his declining hopes to visit home, his health, and his hopes for a letter. He also comments about gathering
supplies for the troops.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 December 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes discussing their marriage and his devotion to her. He was disappointed in not receiving a letter from Harriet. Tynes
also mentions his military duties.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>10 December 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning the army, his duties gathering supplies, and other news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>12 December 1864,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lomax's Cavalry Division, Augusta County, to Harriet Tynes concerning her letter and forgiving her for some action. He also metions that General John McCausland will be taking
command of part of his old cavalry brigade.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>27 January 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Union, Monroe County, West Virginia, to Harriet Tynes stating that he has rejoined his old command. He also sends family news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>31 January 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, West Virginia to Harriet Tynes stating that he misses her and their child. He mentions the Hampton Roads Peace Conference and hopes that
it will lead to peace.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7 February 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, to Harriet Tynes concerning his transfer from Lomax's Cavalry Division headquarter to the 16th Virginia. He also sends other news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>11 February 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, McCausland's Brigade, to Harriet Tynes stating he is disappointed in not receiving a letter from her and that he misses her. Tynes adds that there is a dispute between Generals
McCausland and Lomax about him.
</unittitle>
<physdesc> leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Letters,
<unitdate>17 February 1865-1951
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
</container>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>17 February 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, 16th Virginia Cavalry, Greenbrier County, to Harriet Tynes commenting on the cold and snowy weather and mentioning other aspects of camp life.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>5 March 1865,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes, Lexington, Virginia, to Harriet Tynes informing her of Early's defeat at the battle of Waynesboro. He describes his trip from Monroe County to Lexington, including meeting
relatives and a narrow miss from drowning.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>15 September 1910,
</unitdate>from William S. Grimes, Wapello, Iowa, to Achilles J. Tynes, Tazewell County, commenting on Grimes' service in the 26th Virginia Battalion.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 November 1950,
</unitdate>from W. Edwin Hemphill, Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia, to Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, West Virginia, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes 17-18 July 1863 to warn people in Tazewell County of
Toland's Raid on the area.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>3 November 1950,
</unitdate>Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, to W. Edwin Hemphill, Richmond, concerning the ride of Molly Tynes and the possibilty of mapping it.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>15 May 1951,
</unitdate>from Buford C. Tynes, Huntington, to Achilles L. Tynes, Staunton, Virginia, concerning the Kanawha Valley during the Civil War, their father Achilles J. Tynes, and a proposed visit by Buford Tynes to
Staunton.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>from [Achilles J. Tynes] to [Harriet Tynes?] describing a fight between Confederate and Union forces.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to [Harriet Tynes} concerning military life.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>from Achilles J. Tynes to Harriet Tynes concering clothes that Tynes wants.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>from [Achilles J. Tynes] to [Harriet Tynes?] concerning military matters, stating that he has seen a relative, and informing her that he has frostbitten toes.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Envelope,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>addressed to Harriet Tynes, Tazewell C.H. Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 leaves, 2 copies, negative photostats.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
