<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01114">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01114::John D. Blair Papers, 1781-1823)//EN" "vi01114.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John D. Blair Papers, <date>1781-1823 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Blair, John D., Papers, 1781-1823
<num type="collectionnumber">41008
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 2 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>17 May 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the John D. Blair Papers, <date>1781-1823 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">41008
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">John D. Blair Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1781-1823
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">41008
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2 microfilm reels
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector">Robert Alonzo Brock
</origination>
<note label="Note" audience="external">
<p>This collection forms part of the Robert Alonzo Brock Collection at The Huntington Library, San Marino, California.
</p>
</note>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Should you wish to quote from or reproduce images of any of the materials, you must write to the Librarian of the Huntington Library, 1151 Oxford Road, San Marino, CA 91108, requesting formal permission to do
so. Please note that you do not have to obtain permission if you are quoting fewer than fifty words, or if you are only citing the document. Images made with microfilm-reader printers are for research use only and
may not be used for publication without permission.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>James D. Blair Papers, 1781-1823, Robert Alonzo Brock Collection, Henry E. Huntington Library, San Marino California.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The Robert Alonzo Brock Collection was filmed by The Huntington Library in cooperation with The Library of Virginia with funding provided by The Library of Virginia Foundation with the support of The Roller-
Bottimore Foundation and The Robins Foundation. Microfilm received 12 May 2004.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>John Durbarrow Blair was born 15 October 1759 in Chester County, Pennsylvania, to John Blair and Elizabeth Durbarrow Blair. Educated by his father, Blair entered the College of New Jersey (Princeton) from where
he graduated in 1775. He taught at schools in New Jersey and New York for five years before moving to the Washington-Henry Academy in Hanover County, Virginia, where he taught from 1780 to 1790. Blair was licensed
to preach in the Presbyterian Church 28 October 1784, and served at Pole Green Church in Hanover County. Blair moved to Richmond, Virginia, in 1790, but continued to conduct services at Pole Green Church. He
continued teaching after moving to Richmond. The House of Delegates appointed him chaplain and he served from 1799 to 1802. Blair was one of the movers for building Monumental Church on the site of the Richmond
Theater fire of 26 December 1811. After sharing the church with the Episcopals of Richmond for ten years, the Presbyterians established the First Presbyterian Church in Richmond in 1821. Blair married Mary Winston
of Richmond on 4 March 1785, and they had eight children. Blair died in Richmond in 10 January 1823, and was buried in Shockoe Cemetery.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1781-1823, of John Durbarrow Blair (1759-1823) of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of: Series I: Papers and Series II: Sermons. Series I: Papers consists of abstracts, accounts, articles, clippings,
eulogies, letters, lists, orations, poems, and receipts. Letters discuss Richmond, Virginia, religious and social life; requests for Blair to perform baptisms and weddings and to assist in communion; a merchant
from Abingdon, Virginia; medical treatment of a patient by a physician; a possible duel; John Rutherfoord's acceptance into the College of New Jersey; and a slave owned by Blair. Letters also include a description
of a camp meeting and a humorous discussion of Blair's choir. Other papers include a subscription list circulated for Blair; accounts and receipts concerning Blair's academy; abstracts from Blackstone's
Commentaries; article by Blair on marriage; a Fourth of July oration; letters by "Simplex" on Virginia, the United States, and government; and Jesse H. Turner's funeral sermon on Blair. Series II: Sermons contains
copies of some of Blair's sermons, including a sermon preached on the death of George Washington; on the Fourth of July; on the Richmond Theater Fire; on the death of Moses Hoge; and a thanksgiving sermon based on
the President's proclamation. Other sermons are based on Biblical texts. Some of these sermons do not appear in <title render="italic">Sermons Collected From The Manuscripts of the Late Rev. John D. Blair</title>.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Organized into two series. Series I: Papers. Series II: Sermons. 
</p>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc>
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Originals are located at the Henry E. Huntington Library, San Marino California.
</p>
</originalsloc>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
