<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01123">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01123::A Guide to the Charles Fenton Mercer Papers, 1807-1866)//EN" "vi01123.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Charles Fenton Mercer Papers, <date>1807-1866 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Mercer, Charles Fenton, Papers, 1807-1866
<num type="collectionnumber">21120
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 10 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>28 June 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Charles Fenton Mercer Papers, <date>1807-1866 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">21120
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Charles Fenton Mercer Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1807-1866
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">21120
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">38 pages
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer Papers, 1807-1866. Accession 21120, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Purchased from J. Mercer Garnett, Baltimore, Maryland, 14 December 1936.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer was born 16 June 1778 in Fredericksburg, Virginia to James Mercer (1736-1793) and Eleanor Dick Mercer (d. 1780). He attended the College of New Jersey (Princeton University), and received
a Bachelor's of Arts in 1797, and a Master's in 1800. Mercer was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates, representing Loudoun County, Virginia, from 1810 to 1817. During the War of 1812, he served in the
Virginia militia, rising to the rank of general. After the war, Mercer was elected to the United States Congress in 1817 and remained until 1839. Mercer founded the American Colonization Society in 1817 along with
Francis Scott Key. An advocate of internal improvements, he was named president of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal in 1828. Mercer attended the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1829-1830 as a reform delegate.
After his retirement from Congress, Mercer continued to travel and work for the American Colonization Society. He died 4 May 1858 in Loudoun County.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1807-1866, of Charles Fenton Mercer (1778-1858) of Loudoun County, Virginia, consisting of a letter, 5 April 1843, from Charles Fenton Mercer to his niece Eliza Lucinda Garnett (1815-1847) of Essex
County, Virginia, describing his life in Tallahassee, Florida, and letters, 1853-1854, from Mercer to his nephew Theodore S. Garnett (1812-1885) describing his travels in Italy and in Switzerland, discussing his
land holdings in Texas and Kentucky. Papers also contain a prayer, n.d., possibly written by Mercer. Papers also consist of a letter, 1 November 1807, from James Mercer Garnett (1770-1843) to his wife Mary Garnett
(1774-1837) concerning her health; a deed, 17 June 1840, for 1411 acres in Mason County, Virginia, from John James Chew, for the heirs of Thomas Sedden, to Theodore S. Garnett; and a letter, 15 June 1866, from R.
M. T. Hunter (1809-1887) to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia recommending James M. Garnett (1840-1916) for assistant professor of ancient languages.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer Autobiographical sketch, 1849. Accession 20452. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer Journals, 1853-1858. Accession 21119. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer Letter, 29 April 1813. Accession 21490. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
<p>Charles Fenton Mercer Letters, 1854-1857. Accession 21778. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>1 November 1807,
</unitdate>from James Mercer Garnett, Georgetown, D.C., to Mary Eleanor Dick Mercer Garnett, Essex County, Virginia, asking how she is and worrying about her health.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Deed,
<unitdate>17 June 1840,
</unitdate>of release for 1411 acres in Mason County, (West) Virginia, from John James Chew, Fredericksburg, Virginia, for the heirs of Thomas Sedden to Theodore S. Garnett of Loudoun County, Virginia. Deed
recorded 8 July in the Mason County Court.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>5 April 1843,
</unitdate>from Charles Fenton Mercer, Tallahassee, Florida, to Eliza Lucinda Garnett, Essex County, containing personal news, discussion of religion, and other Virginians in Florida, including a grandson of
Thomas Jefferson.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>25-26 December 1853,
</unitdate>from Charles Fenton Mercer, Florence, Italy, to Theodore S. Garnett, Hillsborough, North Carolina, discussing his travels in Italy and in Europe and commenting on his life and people he has met during
it.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>11 February 1854,
</unitdate>from Charles Fenton Mercer, Rome, Italy, to Theodore S. Garnett, Hillsborough, discussing his travels to Rome and personal news.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7 August 1854,
</unitdate>from Charles Fenton Mercer, Interlachen, Switzerland, to Theodore S. Garnett, Hillsborough, concerning his business dealings involving his land holdings in Texas and Kentucky.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>7 August 1854,
</unitdate>from Charles Fenton Mercer, Interlachen, to Theodore S. Garnett, Hillsborough, discussing the people he has seen and met on his travels in Europe.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter of recommendation,
<unitdate>15 June 1866,
</unitdate>from R. M. T. Hunter to the Board of Visistors of the University of Virginia recommending James M. Garnett for assistant professor of ancient languages.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Prayer,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>possibly written by Charles Fenton Mercer.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
