<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01733">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01733::A Guide to the Barron Family Papers, 1802-1841)//EN" "vi01733.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Barron Family Papers, <date>1802-1841</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Barron Family Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">22126
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>12 May 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Barron Family Papers, <date>1802-1841</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">22126
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Barron Family Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1802-1841
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">22126
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">52 leaves
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Barron Family
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Barron Family Papers, 1802-1841. Accession 22126.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Given by the Valentine Museum, Richmond, Virginia, in exchange, 1943.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Samuel (1765-1810) and James Barron (1769-1851) were the sons of James Barron (1740-1787)and Jane Cowper Barron. James senior, commanded part of the naval forces of Virginia during the American Revolution. His sons served under their father, then served in the Virginia navy until it disbanded in 1789. The Barrons joined the merchant marines. In 1798, they joined the United States Navy; Samuel as captain of the frigate Richmond and James as a lieutenant aboard the frigate United States. Samuel Barron commanded the Philadelphia as part of the Mediterranean squadron under Commodore Richard Dale (d. 1832) during the first year of the Tripolitan war. Command of the squadron passed to Edward Preble (1761-1807), then to Samuel Barron. Barron established his Mediterranean headquarters at Syracuse on Sicily and on Malta. Barron's orders were to blockade and negociate with Tripoli for the return of the captain and crew of the Philadelphia, which had run aground and been captured after Barron's tenure. Plagued by ill health, Barron eventually surrendered command of squadron to John Rodgers (1773-1828). Samuel Barron died in 1810. His son, Samuel Barron (1808-1888) served in the Confederate navy.
</p>
<p>James Barron, who also served in the Mediterranean squadron, commanded the frigate Chesapeake during its encounter with the British ship the Leopard. After the British attack, Barron faced a court-martial and was found guilty of neglecting to clear decks for battle. Suspended without pay from the navy for five years, Barron served aboard commercial vessels. Upon his return to the United States in 1818, he found his requests for active duty blocked by Stephen Decatur. Frustrated, Barron challenged the popular hero to a duel, killing Decatur 22 March 1820. Although given command of the Philadelphia Naval shipyard in 1824, Barron never commanded a naval vessel again. He died 21 April 1851 in Norfolk, Virginia.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1802-1841, of Samuel Barron (1765-1810) and James Barron (1769-1851), officers in the United States Navy, consisting of papers, 1802-1805, of Samuel Barron during his service in the Mediterranean Squadron as commander of the U.S.S. Philadelphia and as squadron commander including requests from sailors; pay for marines; the U.S. frigates Philadelphia, Constitution, Congress, and President; serving in the Mediterranean; and U.S. relations with Tripoli and Tunisia. Also includes letters, 1807-1841, to James Barron regarding the U.S.S. Chesapeake; politics and the election of 1824; the U.S.S. Pennsylvania; the Philadelphia Naval Yard; gifts, naval matters, personal news, and a letter from John Floyd (1783-1837) to Commodore Jesse Elliot (1782-1845) requesting his pistols. Papers also include a letter, 31 May 1805, from Tobias Lear, U.S. Consul-General and Peace Commissioner, to Don Gerardo Joseph de Souza, Spanish Consul at Tripoli and Commissioner on behalf of the Bashaw of Tripoli, concerning an exchange of persons held by the United States and Tripoli.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Samuel Barron Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1802-1805
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>29 June 1802, 
	</unitdate>from James Nicholson to Samuel Barron requesting a furlough.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>26 September 1804, 
	</unitdate>from Lieutenant J. Johnson, commanding the marines aboard the U.S.frigate Argus, to Samuel Barron, commanding the American Squadron in the Mediterranean Sea, requesting a transfer to the U.S.frigate Philadelphia or a return to the United States.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>27 September 1804, 
	</unitdate>from Lieutenant John Howard, commanding the marines aboard the U.S.frigate Siren, to Samuel Barron requesting fund to pay the marines.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>24 November 1804, 
	</unitdate>from George Davis, U.S. charge d'affaires at Tunis, to Samuel Barron, informing Barron of a complaint made to the Bey of Tunis concerning a Tunisian prize recaptured by an American ship
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Report, 
	<unitdate>29 December 1804, 
	</unitdate>on the U.S.frigate President, declaring it unfit for service.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>2 June 1805, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore John Rodgers, commanding the U.S.frigate Constitution, to Samuel Barron commenting on the use of vessels to convey funds.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>6 June 1805, 
	</unitdate>from Tobias Lear, U.S. consul-general at Algiers, to Samuel Barron, reviewing articles of a treaty negotiated between the U.S. and Tripoli.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>12 June 1805, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore Rodgers to Samuel Barron noting that the U.S.frigate Congress has arrived.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>14 June 1805, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore Rodgers to Samuel Barron commenting on the payment of ransom and the return of prisoners.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>James Barron Letters, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1807-1841
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>28 March 1807, 
	</unitdate>from Secretary of the Navy Robert Smith to James Barron inquiring about powder for the U.S. frigate Chesapeake; includes a notation by Barron
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>11 December 1821, 
	</unitdate>from John Floyd to Commodore Jesse D. Elliot requesting Elliot's pistols.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>20 March 1824, 
	</unitdate>from J. B. Mower to James Barron concerning politics and the election of 1824.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>8 April 1824, 
	</unitdate>from Floyd to Barron concerning an incident in New York.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>9 December 1828, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore William Bainbridge  introducing Dr. Sims to Barron.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>11 December 1828, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore James Biddle introducing Dr. Sims to Barron.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>19 May 1829, 
	</unitdate>from Secretary of the Navy John Branch to Barron discussing personal business.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>5 August 1829, 
	</unitdate>from Branch to Barron acknowledging the receipt of the "stick."
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>1 October 1829, 
	</unitdate>from Branch to Barron noting that he is pleased with the plan of the ship house.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>22 March 1831, 
	</unitdate>from acting Secretary of the Navy John Boyle to Barron noting a report and calendar sent to Barron.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>3 June 1837, 
	</unitdate>from James Buchanan to Barron concerning the emblem for the U.S.S. Pennsylvania.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letters, 
	<unitdate>30 June 1837, 
	</unitdate>signed by various officers at the Philadelphia Naval Yard expressing regret over Barron's retirement.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letters, 
	<unitdate>1 July 1837, 
	</unitdate>signed by various officers at the Philadelphia Naval Yard expressing regret over Barron's retirement.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>15 January 1841, 
	</unitdate>from Thomas Gatewood of Norfolk, Virginia, to Barron concerning personal business.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter, 
	<unitdate>17 May no year, 
	</unitdate>from Commodore James Biddle to Barron.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Broadside letter, 
	<unitdate>no date, 
	</unitdate>defending Barron from charges made by a Captain Lewis, noting that Lewis had once signed a letter regretting Barron's transfer to a different command.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Tobias Lear Letter, 
<unitdate>31 May 1805, 
</unitdate>from Lear, U.S. Consul-General and Peace Commissioner, to Don Gerardo Joseph de Souza, Spanish Consul at Tripoli and Commissioner on behalf of the Bashaw of Tripoli, offering $60,000 and all Tripoli citizens held by the United States in exchange for all U.S. citizens held by the Bashaw.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
