<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01636">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01636::A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1810-1861)//EN" "vi01636.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons,<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810-1861</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1810-1861
</subtitle>
        <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Sarah Nerney, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 April 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons,<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810-1861</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810-1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">digital images; 32 items
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Essex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons,1810-1861, are digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images. 

</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Essex County (Va.) Record Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1810-1861, Local government records collection, Essex County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>"Free Negro" Registrations came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Essex County in an undated accession.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>"Register of Free Negroes," 1810-1843 is available on microfilm Essex County (Va.) Reel No. 119 and No. 123</p>
<p>"Register of Free Negroes," 1843-1861 is available on microfilm Essex County (Va.) Reel No. 120 and No. 132</p>

</altformavail>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>"Register of Free Negroes," 1810-1843 and 1843-1861 came to the Library of Virginia as a loan for digitization in 2024 under accession 54160 and was then returned to locality by request of the Clerk. 
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The microfilm copy of these records was generated by The Library of Virginia's Imaging Services Branch.
</p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registration Records, 1812-1850, were originally described as part of the Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, but were removed to the present Essex County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, to enhance the context between the record types.</p>
<p>These records have been processed, scanned, and indexed by L. Neuroth and other LVA staff for the purposes of digitizing them for the digital project Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative.</p>
<p>Encoded by Sarah Nerney, 2006 May 12; updated by M. Mason, April 2024</p>
</processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
 <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph></p>
  <p><emph render="underline">"Free Negro" Registers</emph>
</p>
 <p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify "age, name, colour, and stature, by whom, and in what court the said negro or mulatto was emancipated; or that such negro or mulatto was born free." The process was extended to counties in 1803. Although some clerks were already recording such features, an 1834 Act of Assembly made it a uniform requirement to record identifying marks and scars and the instrument of emancipation, whether by deed or will. This bound register often coincided with a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information. Both the registration system and the process of renewal was enforced differently in the various Virginia localities. Thus, the information found in these registers may differ from year to year and across localities.</p>

 <p>The register books resulting from the administration of the 1793 and 1803 Act of Assembly are evidence of Virginia legislators' reaction to a quickly growing free Black and multiracial population in Virginia in the post Revolutionary War period. Acts such as these allowed white officials to police the activities and movement of free Black community members throughout the state thereby restricting their autonomy.</p>

 <p><emph render="underline">"Free Negro" Registrations</emph>
</p>
 <p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to "be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify age, name, color, status and by whom, and in what court emancipated." These entries often coincided with the creation of a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information.</p>

 <p>Documents in this record group differ from the bound volumes referred to as "registers." These registration records typically appear in the form of certificates or handwritten statements recording the free status of a Black or multiracial person. They can include the free person's name, sometimes age, a brief physical description, and the circumstances of the person's freedom or emancipation, parents, former enslaver, place or date of emancipation. There are also affidavits that were given by individuals affirming a free person's status, as well as written descriptions of free people. In some cases, a person would not have a registration to submit to the court. Instead they produced some other form of identification proving their free status, for example, a deed of emancipation, a will, an apprenticeship indenture, or an affidavit of someone testifying to their character and status.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Locality History Note:</emph> Essex County was named probably for the English county or perhaps for Algernon Capell, second earl of Essex. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Essex County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1810-1861, consists of "Register of Free Negroes," 1810-1843; "Register of Free Negroes," 1843-1861; and "Free Negro" Registrations, 1812-1850 </p>

<p>"Register of Free Negroes," 1810-1843, kept by the clerk of the circuit court, the volume consists of 166 pages with an index both at the beginning and at the end of the volume [The index at the beginning is a more complete index although both should be checked]. The volume records the registration number, age, name, color, stature, marks or scars, in what court the person was emancipated or whether the person was born free. Some clerks recorded additional information not required by law. There are approximately 339 individuals recorded [No. 1-339]. </p>

<p>"Register of Free Negroes," 1843-1861, kept by the clerk of the circuit court, the volume consists of about 89 pages and has an index at the end of the volume. The indexes list in alphabetical order by surname the names of registered free persons and the page number where their registration information can be found. The volume records the registration number, age, name, color, stature, marks or scars, in what court the person was emancipated or whether the person was born free. Some clerks recorded additional information not required by law. There are approximately 188 individuals recorded [No. 340-527]. </p>

<p>"Free Negroes" Registration Records, 1812-1850, consist of 32 items. These records largely consist of loose registrations that contain the same information present in the two "Register of Free Negroes" volumes. Addition records include affidavits or certificates swearing to or providing evidence of an individual's free status. Many of these document familial connections particularly based upon the legal status of the individual's mother. </p>

    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged <list type="simple"><item>Series I: Records related to the registration of free persons, 1810-1861, arranged by records type then chronologically</item></list>
</p>
    </arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
   <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p> Original "Register of Free Negroes," 1810-1843, and "Register of Free Negroes," 1843-1861 volumes retained in locality by retained in locality by Clerk of the Circuit Court for Middlesex County.</p>


</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>

<p>
See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01637.xml">Essex County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1714-1857 </extref>  </p>
<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Essex County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
<p>Additional Essex County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>

</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, ,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 1810-1861</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc> Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent> digital images, 32 items </extent>
</physdesc>
</did> 
<arrangement>
<p> arranged by record type then chronologically
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007880070">"Register of Free Negroes," 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1810-1843
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007880075">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1843-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1137639">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1714-1857
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
	
</c01>
   </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>




