<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://eagle.vsla.edu/bible/virtua-basic.html" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01121">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01121::A Guide to the Angus William McDonald Papers, 1860)//EN" "vi01121.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Angus William McDonald Papers, <date>1860 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">McDonald, Angus William, Papers, 1860
<num type="collectionnumber">21098
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">ca. 10 Kilobytes
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>24 June 2004 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Angus William McDonald Papers, <date>1860 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">21098
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Angus William McDonald Papers,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1860
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">21098
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.1 cubic feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Angus William McDonald Papers, 1860. Accession 21098, Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift of Rose McDonald of Berryville, Virginia, on 21 March 1936.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Angus McDonald was born 14 February 1799 in Winchester, Virginia, to Angus McDonald (1769-1814) and Mary McGuire (d. 1809). He attended Old Winchester Academy and was appointed to the United States Military
Academy 30 June 1814. Graduating 17 July 1817, McDonald was appointed 3rd lieutenant and eventually rose to the rank of 1st lieutenant. He resigned his commission 31 January 1819. He surveyed lands in Illinois and
Missouri with his brother Edward Charles McDonald (1803-1862), then became a partner in the Missouri Fur Company in 1821. When the company failed, McDonald returned to Virginia, settling in Hampshire County, where
he became deputy sheriff. One 11 January 1827 he married Leacy Ann Naylor (d. 1843) of Hampshire County. After her death, he married Cornelia Peake (1822-1909) of Missouri. McDonald relocated to Winchester 9
September 1856. Two years later, 26 March 1858, Governor Henry A. Wise (1806-1876) appointed him a commissioner for Virginia in a boundary dispute with Maryland. In 1860, McDonald travelled to England with his son
William Naylor McDonald (1834-1895) to get copies of records held by the British government. He returned and was in Richmond, Virginia, when the state seceded from the Union. He went to Harper's Ferry and raised a
regiment of cavalry for service. After seeing active military duty early in the Civil War, he returned to Richmond and became a military advisor in the War Department. Because of illness, he travelled to
Lexington, Virginia, to be with his wife in December 1863. The following June, Union troops captured McDonald and he was imprisoned until released on 7 November 1864. He returned to Richmond, where he died 1
December 1864 and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1860, of Angus McDonald (1799-1864) of Winchester, Virginia, and commissioner of Virginia in the Virginia-Maryland boundary dispute, consisting of account, affidavits, correspondence, indexes, land
patent transcripts, lists, and other records related to his research conducted in London, England, regarding colonial Virginia and the on-going border dispute between Virginia and Maryland. Lists are of items on
colonial Virginia McDonald was having copied at the State Paper Office in London. Index is of headings of all papers contained a volume relating to Virginia. Papers contain accounts due for items McDonald had
copied in the State Paper Office. Correspondence consists of rough drafts of a letter of introduction to the Archbishop of Canterbury, John Bird Sumner (1780-1862) and a letter to Goveror John Letcher (1813-1884).
Transcripts are of land patents for grants along the Potomac River made between 1654 and 1670. Other records include an affidavit in the United States consulate concerning copies of documents checked by William
Naylor McDonald (1834-1895) of Virginia and a description of the church in Tring, England. Papers also include a transcript of a document pertaining to a report, 1739, by the Board of Trade regarding the dispute
over the Northern Neck boundary which was copied from a manuscript in the library of Peter Force of Washington D.C.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial>
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Angus William McDonald Papers, 1860. Accession 21877. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Item List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>List of items in the State Paper Office to be examined for possible copying.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 volume.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>An index containing the Heads of all the papers entered in this Second Volume of Virginia.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>7 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Accounts due for copying documents from State Paper Office,
<unitdate>n.d.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>6 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Lists of items to be copied.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 leaves and 2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Rough draft of letter,
<unitdate>16[?] September 1860,
</unitdate>from Angus McDonald to John Bird Sumner, Archbishop of Canterbury, introducing himself and asking to examine records in the Archbishop's possession.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf and 2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous papers,
<unitdate>1860,
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>29 January 1860,
</unitdate>from Angus McDonald, Richmond, Virginia, to Governor John Letcher, regarding McDonald's initial research into the colonial records on the Virginia-Maryland boundary.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Address,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of Angus McDonald in Winchester, Virginia, for his newspapers.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Affidavit,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>of G. B. Hopper and William N. McDonald concerning documents examined in the State Paper Office.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Notes,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>on old Virginia churches in Northampton and Northumberland Counties, Virginia from various sources.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter,
<unitdate>14 September 1860,
</unitdate>from Augustus Bran to an unknown recipient regarding his German grammar book.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 leaf.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Notes,
<unitdate>n.d.,
</unitdate>on the church in Tring, England, containing a description of the building and a transcript of various inscriptions.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Transcripts of land patents,
<unitdate>1654-1670,
</unitdate>from land patent books for land along the Virginia side of the Potomac River.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>15 leaves and 2 pages.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>
<title render="doublequote">Copy of the Report of the Board of Trade,
</title>
<unitdate>1739,
</unitdate>concering efforts by Thomas Lord Fairfax and Lieutenant Governor Sir William Gooch of Virginia to settle the boundry line of the Northern Neck. Transcript made from a manuscript in the library of Peter
Force of Washington, D.C.
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 volume.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
