<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01210">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01210::A Guide to the Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1923-1952)//EN" "vi01210.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural Drawings and Plans, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1923-1952</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Lindner, Carl Max, Sr., Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1923-1952
<num type="collectionnumber">41527, 42255, 44576
</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Library of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 1 KB
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Vincent T. Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 10 November 2004, 27 October 2005, 4 November 2009.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural Drawings and Plans, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1923-1952</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">41527, 42255, 44576
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004, 2005, 2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Vincent T. Brooks
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural drawings and plans,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1923-1952
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">41527, 42255, 44576
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">Accession 41527 consists of 67 sheets, primarily pencil and paper, some blueprints (107 x 79 cm. and smaller); Accession 42255 consists of 175 sheets, primarily pencil and paper, some blueprints and linens (94 x 61 cm. and smaller); Accession 44576 consists of 11 sheets, blueprints (95.25 x 91 cm. and smaller), and specifications (52 leaves). 
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator">Carl Max Lindner, Sr.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Carl Max Lindner, Sr. Architectural drawings and plans, 1923-1952. Cite specific accession. Business records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Gift of Carl Max Lindner, Jr., Richmond, Virginia, 4 November 2004 (Accession 41527); Gift of Carl Max Lindner, Jr., Richmond, Virginia, 22 August 2005 (Accession 42255).
</p>
        <p>Gift of William A. Royall and Pamela Kiecker, Richmond, Virginia, 19 October 2009 (Accession 44576).</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Carl Max Lindner, Sr. (1895-1973), a Richmond, Virginia, native, learned the architectural profession while working for his uncle, Carl Ruehrmund. A graduate of Richmond's Virginia Mechanical Institute, Lindner
began private practice around 1919. Most notably associated with Charles H. Phillips in the early 1920s, Lindner also partnered with Bascom J. Rowlett and Ivan Alten. On a number of commissions, Lindner and
Phillips are listed as architects and contractors, a consequence of their being involved in a number of speculative projects.
</p>
      <p>As an architect, Carl M. Lindner practiced in a number of styles including Art Deco, Tudor, Colonial Revival, Cotswold, and California Mission. A few of Lindner's notable commissions are the Lord Fairfax
Apartments (1923), 3117-3133 Monument Avenue (all 1928), and 306 East Grace Street (1928).
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Accession 41527 consists of five sets of architectural drawings by Richmond, Virginia, architect Carl M. Lindner, Sr. Four of the commissions were executed by Lindner; the fifth set depicting the rebuilt
Governor's Palace at Williamsburg is by the Boston firm of Perry, Shaw &amp; Hepburn. These blueprint copies are a reference work that Lindner held in his office. The four projects by Lindner include residences for Dr. Randolph Elam, a dentist, in Hampton Gardens, Virginia; Mrs. John T. Wilson, Richmond; Mr. Leon L. Strause, Richmond; and alterations to a Sunday School building for St. John's Evangelical and Reformed Church (now St. John's United Church of Christ), Richmond.
</p>
      <p>
Accession 42255 consists of eleven sets of architectural drawings by Lindner. The projects include drawings for Mr. Philip Strause, Westover Road, Richmond, Virginia; Mr. Morton G. Thalhimer, Monument Avenue, Richmond; nine residences on Monument Avenue, Richmond; Mr. Herbert Hill, Hampton Garden, Virginia; Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Richmond; Mr. and Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, Virginia; Mr. A. L. McClellan, Hampton Gardens; Mr. M. D. Nunnally, Jr., Windsor Farms, Virginia; Ms. M. M. Kratz, Richmond; Mr. Carl M. Lindner, Grove Avenue, Richmond; Mr. C. A. Baylor, Hampton Gardens.</p>
      <p>Accession 44576 consists of seven sheets of architectural drawings and specifications (52 leaves) for the residence of Mr. and Mrs. J.P. Hummel, Hill Crest by the James, Westhampton [Richmond], Virginia. Also included are 4 landscape architectural drawings of the gardens by Charles F. Gillette. Also available on CD #195 and in photocopy format.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Accessions 41527, 42255</emph>.</unittitle>


<container label="Folders" type="folder">1-16
</container>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 16 folders.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>





      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Abraham L. McClellan, Hampton Gardens, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1923
</unitdate></unittitle>
                 <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 76 x 62 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: ink on linen, pencil on paper; Sheets: 15;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[Nine Residences on Monument Ave.], Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 1925
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 84 x 58 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 19;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Leon L. Strause, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1925
</unitdate></unittitle>
     
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 91 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 16;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Carl M. Lindner, Grove Ave., Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 1926
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  56 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 16;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Morton G. Thalhimer, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 1926
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 94 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 20;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>House for Mr. C. A. Baylor, Hampton Gardens, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1927
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  72 x 47 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 11;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Philip Strause, Westover Rd., Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1929
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  80 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 21;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Williamsburg Restoration for the Williamsburg Holding Co.- Governor's Palace,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1931
</unitdate></unittitle>
        
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 107 x 79 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: Blueprints; Sheets: 10;
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Drawn By: Perry, Shaw &amp; Hepburn, Architects, 141 Milk St., Boston &amp; Williamsburg, Virginia.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mrs. John T. Wilson, Richmond, Virginia,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1936
</unitdate></unittitle>
      
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">9
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 53 x 76 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 18;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Ms. Madeline M. Kratz, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1936
</unitdate></unittitle>
        
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">10
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  57 x 46 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 9;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Herbert Hill, Hampton Gardens, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1937
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">11
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  58 x 41 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 11;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Dr. Randolph Elam, Hampton Gardens, Virginia,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1938
</unitdate></unittitle>
          
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">12
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 48 x 65 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 11;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 1949
</unitdate></unittitle>
          
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">13
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 16;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Alterations to Sunday School Building for St. John's Evangelical Church, Richmond, Virginia,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1950
</unitdate></unittitle>
       
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">14
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions: 53 x 89 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 12;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. and Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1950
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">15
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  76 x 46 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, blueprint; Sheets: 18;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>
      <c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. Moses D. Nunnally, Jr., Windsor Farms, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 1952
</unitdate></unittitle>
        
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  89 x 53 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, blueprint; Sheets: 19;
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>

</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Accession 44576</emph>.</unittitle>


<physdesc><extent>Extent: 2 folders and 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>



<c02 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Residence for Mr. and Mrs. J.P. Hummell, Hill Crest by the James, Richmond, VA,
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1934
</unitdate></unittitle>
         
          <container label="Folders" type="folder">1-2
</container>
          <physdesc>Dimensions:  95.25 x 91 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: blueprint; Sheets: 11. Also includes 7 photocopies of drawings and 52 leaves of specifications (blueprints and photocopies). Available on CD #195.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c02>

<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Specifications (originals and copies)</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
</did>
</c02>



</c01>




    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
