<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi01825">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01825::A Guide to the Hunter Holmes McGuire Letters, 1861-1871)//EN" "vi01825.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hunter Holmes McGuire Letters, <date>1861-1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">McGuire, Hunter Holmes, Letters, 1861-1871
<num type="collectionnumber">24207
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>8 June 2006</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hunter Holmes McGuire Letters, <date>1861-1871</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">24207
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Hunter Holmes McGuire Letters, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1861-1871
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">24207
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">34 leaves, negative photostats
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Hunter Holmes McGuire
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Hunter Holmes McGuire Letters, 1861-1871.  Accession 24207.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Lent for copying, 27 August 1954, by Hunter McGuire, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Hunter Holmes McGuire was born 11 October 1835 in Winchester, Virginia, to Hugh Holmes McGuire (1801-1875) and Ann Eliza Moss McGuire (ca. 1808-1878). He attended Winchester Academy and then studied medicine at the Winchester Medical College. After receiving his degree there in 1855, he went to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to study at the University of Pennsylvania and Jefferson Medical College. Poor health forced McGuire to leave Philadelphia and return to Winchester where he became professor of anatomy at Winchester Medical College in 1857. Returning to Philadelphia to continue his studies, McGuire led a walkout of 300 southern medical students because of John Brown's Raid at Harper's Ferry. Many of these students ended up at the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond, Virginia. McGuire went to New Orleans, Louisiana to continue his education and career, but returned to Virginia when the Civil War began. He enlisted as a private soldier, but was appointed medical director of Stonewall Jackson's (1824-1863) Army of the Shenandoah. He served as Jackson's medical director and his personal physician until Jackson's death. He then served as medical director for the II Corps of the Army of Northern Virginia under Richard Ewell (1817-1872) and for the Army of the Valley under Jubal Early (1816-1894). McGuire was captured by Union troops in March 1865 but was quickly paroled and released. In 1865 he was appointed professor of surgery at the Medical College of Virginia, and served until his resignation in 1878. That year he founded St. Luke's Hospital in Richmond. The Medical College of Virginia appointed McGuire professor emeritus in 1880. McGuire wrote on medical matters and on the Civil War. He led a campaign to rework Virginia's educational system to remove what he perceived to be northern bias. McGuire married Mary Stuart (1844-1933) of Staunton,Virginia, and they had nine children. McGuire died in Richmond 19 September 1900 and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Letters, 1861-1871, of Dr. Hunter Holmes McGuire (1835-1900) concerning the first battle of Manassas including a map sketch; a visit to the troops by Jefferson Davis (1808-1889), McGuire's health, and Stonewall Jackson's (1824-1863) thanks to McGuire's mother for grapes; Jackson's health; Jubal Early's (1816-1894) post-war activities and opinion on articles by former Confederates concerning the war; thanks from Robert E. Lee (1807-1870) for a package; Confederate morale; and Turner Ashby (1828-1862). Papers also include a letter, 26 February 1862, from Stonewall Jackson to General Daniel Harvey Hill's (1821-1889) position at Harper's Ferry, and a letter, 29 March 1864, from General Robert E. Lee to his son General George Washington Custis Lee (1832-1913) concerning a promotion for G. W. C. Lee and war news.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>24 July 1861, 
</unitdate>from McGuire to his father Hugh Holmes McGuire describing the fighting during the first battle of Manassas and including a sketch of the battlefield.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>2 October 1861, 
</unitdate>from General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson to McGuire hoping that he will feel better, describing a visit from President Jefferson Davis to the troops, and thanking McGuire's mother for grapes she sent.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>26 February 1862, 
</unitdate>from Jackson to General Daniel Harvey Hill concerning Hill's position at Harper's Ferry, (West) Virginia.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>4 August 1862, 
</unitdate>from Anna Morrison Jackson near Charlotte, North Carolina, to McGuire regarding the health of her husband, Stonewall Jackson.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>3 February 1864, 
</unitdate>from McGuire to his mother Ann Eliza Moss McGuire containing general news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>16 February 1864, 
</unitdate>from McGuire to his sister Getty McGuire containing general news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>21 February 1864, 
</unitdate>from McGuire to his sister Getty McGuire containing general news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>29 March 1864, 
</unitdate>from General Robert E. Lee to his son General George Washington Custis Lee concerning a promotion for G. W. C. Lee and war news.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>30 October 1865, 
</unitdate>from Jubal A. Early to McGuire stating that he is leaving for Nassau, New Providence and providing details of his movements after the surrender at Appomattox.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>15 September 1866, 
</unitdate>from Robert E. Lee to McGuire thanking McGuire for a package and asking to whom he can send a letter for Early.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>9 April 1871, 
</unitdate>from Early to McGuire concerning articles written by other former Confederates concerning the war.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate>no date, 
</unitdate>probably from McGuire to an unknown correspondent concerning Confederate morale and Turner Ashby.
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
