<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi01819">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi01819::A Guide to the Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette Letters, 1781-1825)//EN" "vi01819.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1825</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, Letters, 1781-1825
<num type="collectionnumber">24034
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6 June 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette Letters, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1825</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">24034
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette Letters, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1825
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">24034
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">48 leaves, negative photostats
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette Letters, 1781-1825.  Accession 24034.  Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Lent for copying, 4 August 1953, by Stuart W. Jackson, Gloucester County, Virginia.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette was born 6 September 1757 at the Chateau de Chavaniac, Haute-Loire, Avergne, France. He inherited a vast estate when orphaned at age 13 and joined the French army at age 14. When the American Revolution began, Lafayette, 19, offered his services to the Continental Army and was commissioned a major-general. He served ably throughout the Revolution and was instrumental in convincing Franch to join the war on the American side. After the Revolution, Lafayette returned to France and later sat in its assembly. Commander of the French army int he early stages of the French Revolution, Lafayette fell out of favor with the more radical elements of the revolutionaries and was declared a traitor. Escaping France, he was held prisoner by the Austrians and the Prussians from 1792 to 1797. Returning to France in 1799, Lafayette participated off and on in French politics as a liberal. Lafayette returned to the United States for a triumphal tour in 1824-1825. He married Marie-Adrienne-Francoise de Noailles, and they had three children. Lafayette died 20 May 1834.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Letters, 1781-1825, of Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834) of France, consisting of letters, 1781, from Lafayette to Governor Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826) of Virginia concerning the military situation in Virginia; letters, 1781, to General Robert Lawson (1748-1805) of the Virginia militia calling on the militia to cooperate in opposing the British army; and a letter, 2 July 1781, to General "Mad" Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) praising the ground reconnoitered by Wayne for use of the army. Papers also include a certification, 18 August 1778, by John Paul Jones (1747-1792) regarding  Benjamin Hill; letter, 10 December 1781, from Charles Alexander de Colonne (1734-1802), Arras, France, to Louis Philippe count de Segur (1753-1830) regarding a Te Deum for French successes in the American Revolution; a letter, 27 September 1781, from Armand Louis de Gontaut, duc de Lauzun (1747-1793) to Antoine Charles du Houx, baron de Viomenil (1725-1793) commenting on the comte de Rochambeau (1725-1807) and discussing the Franco-American siege of the British in the town of Gloucester, Virginia; and a letter, 16 July 1825, from President John Quincy Adams (1767-1848) to Lafayette regarding the latter's United States tour. The 1781 letters include typed transcripts and translations of letters written in French.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 March 1781, 
</unitdate>from Lafayette to Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826), Governor of Virginia, concerning the British navy and military maneuvers in eastern Virginia.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 April 1781, 
</unitdate>from Lafayette to Jefferson regarding the military situation in Virginia, Lafayette's plans, and the need for supplies.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 May 1781, 
</unitdate>from Lafayette to General Robert Lawson (1748-1805) of the Virginia militia concerning the army's need for men and supplies and the need for the army and the Virginia militia to cooperate in opposing the British under Lord Charles Cornwallis (1738-1805).
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 May 1781, 
</unitdate>from Lafayette to Lawson informing Lawson that Lafayette has directed the calling of the militia in Amelia and Brunswick Counties, Virginia, and ordered them to first prevent British depredations in the area, then join Lafayette' forces, directing to Lawson to have other militia forces activated, and informing Lawson of Cornwallis's movements in Virginia.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 July 1781, 
</unitdate>from Lafayette to General "Mad" Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) praising the ground reconnoitered by Wayne for use of the army.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Certification, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 August 1778, 
</unitdate>by John Paul Jones (1747-1792) regarding the naval service of Benjamin Hill under Jones's command.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 December 1781, 
</unitdate>from Charles Alexander de Colonne (1734-1802), Arras, France, to Louis Philippe count de Segur (1753-1830) declining to attend a Te Deum to be sung at Lille for French successes in the American Revolution, noting the lack of precedent for such, and noting that he had already attended two.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 September 1781, 
</unitdate>from Armand Louis de Gontaut, duc de Lauzun (1747-1793) to Antoine Charles du Houx, baron de Viomenil (1725-1793) expressing his unhappiness serving under Jean-Baptiste-Donatien de Vimeur, comte de Rochambeau (1725-1807) and discussing the Franco-American siege of the British in the town of Gloucester in Gloucester County, Virginia, located across the York River from Yorktown.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 July 1825, 
</unitdate>from President John Quincy Adams (1767-1848) to Lafayette regarding the latter's tour through the United States in 1824-1825.
</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
