<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02602">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02602::A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, 1863-1869)//EN" "vi02602.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1869</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, 1863-1869
<num type="collectionnumber">Barcode number 1100408/ Arlington County (Va.) Reel 269
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Sarah Nerney, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7 April 2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1869</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection numbers:">Barcode number 1100408/ Arlington County (Va.) Reel 269
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863-1869
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">Barcode number 1100408/ Arlington County (Va.) Reel 269
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1 v. (143 p.)  and 1 microfilm reel.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Use microfilm copy, Arlington County (Va.) Reel 269. 
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected, 1863-1869. Arlington County (Va.) Reel 269, Local government records collection, Arlington County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This item came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Arlington County. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Arlington County was formed in 1789 from Fairfax County and was at that time named Alexandria County. The county was ceded to the federal government in 1801 and was part of the District of Columbia until 1846 when it was returned to the state of Virginia. Alexandria County changed its name in 1920 to Arlington County. 
</p>
      <p>Reverend Albert Gladwin of Connecticut was appointed the first Superintendent of Contrabands by the military governor of Alexandria in 1862 to help deal with the influx of escaped slaves who had flooded the city after the beginning of the Civil War. Two of his duties were to record the deaths of freedmen and to assist poor and destitute people with coffins, headstones, and burial. Gladwin was removed from his position in 1865 after he insisted on burying deceased United States Colored Troops in the Freedmen's Cemetery instead of in the newly established soldiers' cemetery at Arlington. 
</p>
      <p>The Freedmen's Cemetery was established in 1864 on land seized by the military government of Alexandria from Francis L. Smith. Located on south Washington Street just outside of the then city limits, it was established as a burial ground for contrabands and placed under the charge of the Superintendent of Contrabands.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Arlington County (Va.) Book of Records Containing the Marriages and Deaths That Have Occurred Within the Official Jurisdiction of Rev. A. Gladwin Together With Any Biographical or Other Reminiscences That May Be Collected,, 1863-1869, is a marriage and death register kept by the Superintendents of Contrabands in Alexandria, Virginia, during and directly after the Civil War. Reverend Albert Gladwin was the first Superintendent of Contrabands and his successors kept up the register after his departure. The book records death, burial, and marriage information about freedmen and free blacks in the Alexandria area.  The book is often referred to as the Gladwin Record.
</p>
      <p>Page 2 contains a monthly reporting on the number of deaths from 1862 May through 1865 December.
</p>
      <p>Pages 3-23 and 51-79 are a Personal Record of Deaths. Information recorded is month, day and year of death, name, age in years, months or days, and a remarks column. The remarks column (called varyingly the Residences, etc. column) contains varying information including location of funeral, place of death, cause of death, or occasionally place of burial. A few persons are noted as being white. The remarks column is not always filled in. Many of the burials of the deceased certainly took place in the large Freedmen's Cemetery.
</p>
      <p>Pages 15-39 are a Record of Deaths in the New Freedmen's Hospitals, Etc. Information recorded is month, day and year of death, name, age in years, months and days, and a remarks column. The remarks column records which hospital the death occured in and sometimes other notes about the place of burial or the funeral. A great number of the deceased were members of the United States Colored Troops. Regiment is given for soldiers. Named hospitals include Commissary Hospital, New General Hospital, Quarter Master Hospital, L'Ouverture Hospital, and Bartlott's Division Hospital. Some of the deceased soldiers were buried in the Freedmen's Cemetery but most are interred at Arlington National Cemetery.
</p>
      <p>Pages 80-83 are a history and explanation of the death and funeral responsibilities of the Superintendent of Contrabands and gives a brief history of the founding of the Freedmen's Cemetery. The name of the first gravedigger is listed as Randall Ward, colored. Page 83 contains an account of coffins which have been received and expended.
</p>
      <p>Pages 84-119 are a Record of Deaths and Burials among the Freedmen in Alexandria, Va. Information recorded is month, day and year of death, a number, name of deceased person, age, name of parent or near relation, residence of person at time of death, charges, and remarks. The remarks are usually limited to charges for the burial or whether the person was destitute and therefore buried at the expense of the Superintendent of Contrabands. Some few remarks concern cause of death. The remarks column is not always filled in.
</p>
      <p>Pages 129-143 are a Record of Marriages. Information recorded includes date of marriage, names of parties married, by whom married, place of marriage, and a remarks column. Remarks usually concern fees paid and marriage licenses. Some parties are noted as white. Other remarks are about the ceremony or situation of the couple such as "travelled over a hundred miles from vicinity of Richmond on foot together to get married." Marriage information exists only for the years 1863-1864.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Arlington County vital statistics records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA015">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site. 
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Arlington County (Va.). Circuit Court. </corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Freedmen. -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington County (Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865. </geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Cemetery records -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Marriage records -- Virginia -- Arlington County. </genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Added Entry - Personal Name:</head>
        <persname encodinganalog="700$a">Gladwin, Albert. </persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Alexandria (Va.) </corpname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
