<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02673">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02673::A Guide to the Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913))//EN" "vi02673.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913)
<num type="collectionnumber">Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-001-1932-002
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 October 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-001-1932-002
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Louise Jones
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-001-1932-002 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Portsmouth (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Portsmouth Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by OCLC through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Portsmouth was located in Norfolk County, which is now extinct. It was named by its founder, William Crawford, for the English seaport and was established in 1752. Portsmouth was incorporated as a town in 1836 and as a city in 1858.
</p>
      <p>The chancery causes of Portsmouth (Va.) described in this collection were created by the following courts: Hustings Court and Circuit Court.
</p>
      <p>The Hustings Court was the city equivalent of the County Court. It was dissolved in 1904 and its functions were assumed by the Circuit Court.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Portsmouth (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-1932 (bulk 1859-1913) are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed. The predominant number of chancery causes in this collection were created by the Hustings Court prior to its dissolution in 1904.
</p>
      <p>Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Portsmouth Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm">the Chancery Records Index</extref> to find the chancery records of additional Virginia localities.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Portsmouth (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Portsmouth.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Portsmouth (Va.)--History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Portsmouth (Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Portsmouth.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
 <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1865-003: Virginus A. Haynes vs. Olivia F Haynes: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Virginus came home from the Civil War and found his wife pregnant.  The depositions include reports of his life in the Army.  There is a report on divorce laws in other states.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1874-020: John Nash, etc. vs. City of Portsmouth, etc.     
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The people living on London Street between Middle and Crawford Streets did not want the Seaboard and Roanoke Rail Road to lay tracks on their street.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889-018: Gdn. of William T. Maurice, etc. vs. Thomas J. Maurice and wife, etc.
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Sale of farm at Langley's Point in Norfolk County. It was sold to a wealthier owner because the north eastern's (storms) were washing away the shore line and the Maurices did not have the money to shore up the land.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889-052: Fanny Umstadter vs. Trustees of the Congregation Obed Sholem
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mrs. Umstadter and her husband sold the Congregation land for a cemetery and after his death, she found her key did not work to enter the cemetery. She hired a lock smith to cut open the lock and the blacksmith was being tried in Norfolk County Court for breaking and entering.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889-054: Widow of Samuel T. Hartt vs. Admr. of  Samuel T. Hartt
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Louise W. Hartt signs a power of attorney to Thomas W. Peirce of Norfolk, Virginia.  She lives in the Kingdom of Saxony, City of Dresden.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1895-015: Taylor Bros. vs. Griffin and Pierce, etc.
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This suit concerns the building of the Independent Engine House, a fire station. There are list of materials used and the price of the products.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1898-015: George A. Martin vs. Scott Riddick and wife
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This suit has a deposition by Ann Majette, a former slave. She compares people's ages with "Nat's War." She also talks about her family.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1899-031: Margaret McVeigh, etc. vs. Admr. of John O'Neill, etc.  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The deceased defendant's heirs live in Ireland, Chicago, Illinois, and in Australia. There is a power of attorney in the oversize box from the heirs in Australia.   
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1901-006: L. A. Bilisoly, for etc. vs. Comt. Of Margaret Pruden, etc. 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Margaret was a freed slave that lived with George Ricks (Rix) and according to her relative was married to him under the law 1873 (Section 4, Chapter 103, Code of 1873) They are trying to get out of paying her doctor's bills.    
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1902-008: Thomas J. Brady vs. Cincinnati Architectural Iron Work Co.   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit concerns the iron work purchased for St. Paul's Roman Catholic Church.   
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-015: Harry Freedman vs. Mirel Freedman.    
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Harry and Mirel were married in Kovne, Keidan, Russia. Harry came to the United States in 1904 and has sent tickets for his wife to come to the United States. She refuses to come so he divorced her.  
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-018: Livius Lankford, for etc. vs. Admr. of Charles E. Richardson, etc.   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The letter concerns paying Mr. Richardson's debts and dividing his estate among his relatives on his mother's and father's side of his family. Exhibit D with the depositions is a letter from Enigal, Gawagh, County Derry, Ireland from Thomas Boyle. Since there are no entries in the church registers before 1846, he talks about the inscriptions on tombstones instead. He also talked to people in the community about the McCredy family. There are other letters about the McCredy family in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and other states.     
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-034: George Joiner, Jr. vs. Cornelia Eley.  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>George, Jr. was the son of George, Sr., a free man and a slave woman. George, Jr. was trying to prove he was a legitimate son of George, Sr.     
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1911-027: Pauline Bond vs. Oliver Thomas Bond.  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Evidence for the divorce included 6 pictures of women. One picture is on tin and one has been painted so that the flowers on the hat are pink and yellow.      
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
             </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
