<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02001">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02001::A Guide to the Records of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, 2001-2006 (bulk 2001-2005))//EN" "vi02001.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, Records of the
<num type="collectionnumber">42406
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Chris Abraham
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Chris Abraham, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8 August 2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">42406
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Chris Abraham
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Chris Abraham
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Records of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2006
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">42406
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1 cu. ft. (1 box)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention 
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Records, 2001-2006, Accession 42406. State records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Transferred by Marilyn P. Harris and M. Gene Miles, Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, 202 North Ninth Street, 4th Floor, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, 12 January, 2006
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The creation of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention was authorized by the 2000 General Assembly, signed into law by Governor James S. Gilmore III., and codified through 2.2-118 of the Code of Virginia. The code notes the governor's responsibility to authorize, direct, and coordinate the Commonwealth's substance abuse prevention activities. To assist the governor in meeting this responsibility, the code also authorizes the creation of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention; an office designated to coordinate the substance abuse prevention activities of Commonwealth agencies, to review substance abuse prevention activity expenditures, and to determine new directions for future substance abuse prevention funding.  Initially, the office reported to the Governor's Chief of Staff and was overseen by Benjamin W. Smith, whom Governor Gilmore appointed as the office's first director. To give the office more public visibility, Governor Mark R. Warner opted to place it within the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety as an autonomous and independent entity. In April 2002, Governor Warner appointed Marilyn P. Harris, Deputy Secretary of Public Safety for Secretary of Public Safety John W. Marshall, to the post of Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention. As of December 2005, the office had a staff of three at-will employees and several interns. 
</p>
      <p>The Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention fulfills two primary functions. One primary function is to coordinate the prevention activities of Commonwealth agencies.  In 2003, the office formed the Governor's Office of Substance Abuse Prevention Collaborative from thirteen Commonwealth agencies charged with substance abuse prevention activities. The purpose of the Collaborative as designed is to improve interagency communication, facilitate cooperation, increase consistency, and ensure that all member agencies work together towards a common set of substance abuse prevention goals.  The member agencies are as follows: The Department of Education, The Department of Criminal Justice Services, The Department of Juvenile Justice, The Department of Alcohol and Beverage Control, The Virginia State Police, The Virginia Department of Health, The Department of Social Services, The Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation Substance Abuse Services, The Department of Motor Vehicles, The Virginia Department of Fire Programs, The Virginia Tobacco Settlement Foundation, and The Virginia National Guard. The other primary function of the office is to solicit, review, and award grants to organizations working in support of substance abuse prevention initiatives. As of 2005, the office administered two federal grants; the Governor's portion of the Safe and Drug-Free Schools and Communities Act funding as granted by the U.S. Department of Education, and the State Incentive Grant Cooperative Agreement as granted by the U.S. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Service Administration. </p>
      <p>The Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention also administers or participates in several statewide substance abuse prevention programs. The Virginia State Incentive Grant Project was created in October of 2000 to work in conjunction with the federal Center for Abuse Prevention and to award local prevention coalitions grants to implement substance abuse prevention programs. The Safe and Drug-Free Schools and Communities Program of the No Child Left Behind Act of 2001 is intended to award grants for projects in support of youth substance abuse and violence prevention efforts. KidSafe Virginia, a program launched in late 2002, is targeted towards educating children about personal safety (inclusive of online safety and fire safety) and crime prevention.  The Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council was created in 2003 to allow Virginia's adolescents a forum to voice concerns over school violence, gangs, substance abuse, and other safety issues. The Protect and Respect program was launched in May of 2003 to promote personal safety and awareness among Virginia's older residents and allows adolescents and senior citizens to work collaboratively to promote the safety of both through crime prevention education. Also beginning in 2003, the Youth Alcohol and Drug Abuse Prevention Program received funding from the Office for Substance Abuse Prevention to provide leadership opportunities for students interested in substance abuse prevention efforts. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Correspondence, reports, grants, agency publications, meeting minutes, and conference presentation materials created or sponsored by the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, 2001-2006. This collection consists of 11 series of records documenting the activities of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>Series I. Annual Reports, 2002-2004</item>
        <item>Series II. Meetings- Agendas and Minutes, 2002-2005</item>
        <item>Series III. Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001 Grant Subaward Records, 2001-2006</item>
        <item>Series IV. State Incentive Grant (SIG) Subaward Records, 2001-2005</item>
        <item>Series V. Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Grant Award Notifications, 2000-2006</item>
        <item>Series VI. Memoranda- Appropriation and Allotment, 2002-2006</item>
        <item>Series VII. Director's Correspondence, 2002-2006</item>
        <item>Series VIII. Agency Publications and Supporting Documentation, 2004-2005</item>
        <item>Series IX. Transition Files, 2005</item>
        <item>Series X. Conference and Training Records, 2003-2005</item>
        <item>Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation, 2003-2005</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Archived website files pertaining to the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (2004-2005) are part of The Library of Virginia's collection and can be retrieved through a subject search of the library's archival holdings catalog for "substance abuse prevention."
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Annual Reports</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2002-2004</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">1-3
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 3 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains the annual reports (published December first) of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention. Each report contains a front piece including a letter to the Virginia General Assembly from Director Marilyn P. Harris and an executive summary describing in brief the substance abuse prevention accomplishments of the office during the fiscal year ending in December. Though the reports differ in format from year to year, there are some commonalities among them. The office's accomplishments for a given year are discussed in detail in each report's main body. The reports contain the office's statutory authority, a brief description of the organization of the office, and descriptions of current states of prevention programs (KidSafe and the Virginia State Incentive Grant Project are mentioned in all three reports) planned, created, administered, and managed during the year. This series is arranged chronologically. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annual Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annual Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annual Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Meetings- Agendas and Minutes</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2002-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">4-5
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 2 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> This series contains the agendas and minutes (minutes are sometimes called proceedings) of meetings of the Virginia State Incentive Grant Advisory Council and the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Collaborative. Agendas are outlines of a meeting's purpose, are created prior to a meeting, and include lists of presenters and topics to be addressed. Minutes are a record of what actually transpired during a meeting and are usually recorded while a meeting is in progress. Meeting agendas and minutes are interfiled in this series, but not all minutes have accompanying agendas. The meetings of the Virginia State Incentive Grant Advisory Council highlight the status of the State Incentive Grant Project at given points in time and welcome new members to the project. They record instances of grant recipients highlighting their groups' work. One Virginia State Incentive Grant Advisory Council meeting of note took place on March 17, 2003 and was attended by Governor Mark Warner. Governor Warner made the meeting's opening remarks and signed legislation concerning substance abuse. 
</p>
          <p> Meetings of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Collaborative are shown to be attended by representatives of the thirteen agencies within the Collaborative. Major topics addressed include member agency updates on substance abuse prevention techniques, suggested techniques to improve the administration of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, and the design of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention's website. Items in this series are arranged first by the meeting body and then chronologically. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia State Incentive Grant Advisory Council,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 19, 2002- May 14, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Collaborative,  
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 18, 2004 - December 8, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001 Grant Subaward Records</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2001-2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">6-14
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 9 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> This series contains grant proposal requests written by the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, grant award lists, grant approval letters, and possible inactive grants. The grants in this series are funded through the Governor's designated portion of Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001 funding, allocated to Virginia by the U.S. Department of Education. Accordingly, grant money is released to the office before the office disperses it to substance abuse prevention programs. Each proposal request provides a statement disclosing the total amount of available funds for the year, the intended purpose of the funds, and the types of programs the office deems appropriate for funding. Further, each request provides detailed information regarding how proposals are to be prepared, organized and written. Application forms as well as the score sheets grant readers used to assign scores to the proposed grants are included with the proposals. The proposal requests are of interest as they illustrate the process the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention uses to solicit community organizations desirous of implementing substance abuse prevention programs. The requests also illustrate the process the office uses to evaluate substance abuse programs. Grant proposal requests are organized chronologically. </p>
          <p> Each grant approval letter in this series notes the total amount of funds granted to individual recipients along with an account number by which each individual grant is to be referenced. The letters, where necessary, also add stipulations that require alterations in the expenditure of funds. Further, they remind the recipient of his or her organization's duty to adhere to the expenditure regulations set forth by the federal government in the Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001. All letters within each fiscal year bear the same date. Grant approval letters are of interest as they record the amount of funding awarded to individual grantees while also illustrating which aspects of a given grant proposal were unacceptable. Most groupings of grant approval letters are accompanied by a grant awardees list that provides an overview of all the grants issued for a given fiscal year. The grant approval letters in this series are organized alphabetically within fiscal years. </p>
          <p>Also included in this series are possible inactive grants that were apparently awarded but never implemented. They appear in all respects to be exactly like the grants described above. They do not, however, appear on the grant awardees lists and bear different dates between them. They are arranged by fiscal year. Several grant proposals in this series are for the Protect and Respect Program, a program designed to promote personal safety and awareness among older Virginians. More information regarding the Protect and Respect Program in particular can be found in Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation, 2003-2005.</p>
          <p>Grant recipients in this series include: Alliance for Families and Children; Alternative House; Alternatives Inc.; Appalachian Agency for Senior Citizens (AASC); Bedford Youth and Family Services (YFS); Big Brothers/Big Sisters of Harrisonburg and Rockingham; Bland County Administrator; Blue Ridge Behavioral Healthcare; Boys and Girls Club of Emporia/Greensville, Inc.; Brighton's Solid Rock, Inc.; C. Waldo Scott Center for H.O.P.E.; Central Virginia Community Services; Charlottesville Redevelopment and Housing Authority; Chesapeake Community Services Board; Chesterfield County Public Schools; Child and Family Services of Eastern Virginia; City of Richmond, Danville-Pittsylvania Community Services; Colonial Community Services Board; Commonwealth ChalleNGe; County of Dinwiddie; Cumberland Mountain Community Services; Department of Correctional Education; District 19, Community Services Board; Eastern Virginia Medical School; Employment Resources Incorporated (ERI); Essex County Public Schools; Fairfax-Falls Church Community Services Board; Fairfax Partnership for Youth, Inc.; Falls Church City Public Schools; Family Services of Roanoke Valley; Floyd County Public Schools; Garfield F. Childs Memorial Fund; Giles County Public Schools; Grayson County Public Schools; Halifax County Public Schools; Hanover Community Services; Horizons Unlimited Youth and Family Development; Lion of Judah Ministries International; Loudoun County Public Schools; Manassas City Public Schools; Middle Peninsula- Northern Neck Community Service Board; Montgomery County Schools; Mount Rogers Community Services Board; Mountain View Youth and Family Services; Nelson County Middle School; New River Valley Community Services; Newport News Office on Youth Development; Newport News Public Schools; Page County Sheriff's Office; Portsmouth Coalition for Youth; Prince William County; Prince William County Office on Youth; Prince William County Public Schools; Rappahannock Big Brothers Big Sisters; Richmond Behavioral Health Authority; Roanoke County Public Schools; Roanoke Valley Juvenile Detention Center; Senior Connections; Shenandoah Valley Juvenile Detention Center; Substance Abuse Free Environment, Inc.; United Community Ministries; University of Virginia; Virginia Beach City Public Schools; Virginia Beach Department of Human Services, Mental Health Substance Abuse Division; Virginia Beach Police Department; Warren County Community Health Coalition; Washington County Public Schools; West Point Elementary School; West Point Public Schools; Winchester Public Schools and Wise County Public Schools</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Request for Proposals, Youth and Drug Violence Prevention, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> March 2003 - March 2005 </unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Request for Proposals, Protect and Respect, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> July 2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2002-2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2003-2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2004-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2005-2006</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">10
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards - Protect and Respect, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2003-2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">11
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards - Protect and Respect, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2004-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">12
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards - Protect and Respect, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2005-2006</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">13
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards - Inactive Grants, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2003-2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">14
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Awards - Inactive Grants, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> FY 2004-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">14
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. State Incentive Grant (SIG) Subaward Records</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2001-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">15-17
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 3 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains a list of State Incentive Grant awardees, open letters addressed to grant recipients, and progress reports. Grant awards in this series were funded through the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.  Accordingly, monies released to grant recipients were first awarded to the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention. A form letter possibly intended for distribution to the named recipients is included. 
</p>
          <p>Grant recipients include: The Alliance for Children and Families; Alternatives Inc.; Blue Ridge Behavioral Healthcare; Colonial Services Board; Danville Pittsylvania Community Services; Fairfax/Falls Church Community Service Board Alcohol and Drug Services; Hanover County Community Services; Hampton-Newport News Community Services Board; Henrico Area/Charles City/ New Kent MHMR Services; Middle Peninsula-Northern Neck Community Service Board Prevention Services; Piedmont Community Services; Portsmouth Department of Behavioral Healthcare Services Rockingham Memorial Hospital and The Warren Coalition.
</p>
          <p> Open letters in this series are addressed to all award recipients and describe funding obligations, clarifications of policy, and other matters. Of particular interest is an undated letter clarifying the usage of funds for faith-based initiatives. 
</p>
          <p>The semi-annual progress reports in this series are valuable for the insight they provide into the State Incentive Grant. Each report records events regarding the grant program over six month period. The reports note goals and progress made during the period covered. The reports also include a chronology of important State Incentive Grant events taking place during the period covered, findings from State Incentive Grant data collection efforts, meeting dates, and meeting minutes. Items in this series are arranged chronologically.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>State Incentive Grant Sub-Recipient Letter, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 2, 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Grant Award Form Letter and Grant Awards List, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 10, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>State Incentive Grant Sub-Recipient Letter, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">No Date</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 2001 - March, 2002</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 2002 - September 2002</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 2002 - March 2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 2003 - September 2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 2003 - March 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 2004 - September 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 2004 - March 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">17
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Progress Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 2005 - September 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">17
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series V. Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Grant Award Notifications</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2000-2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">18
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1 folder.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains grant award notifications issued directly to the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention by the federal government. It is from these grants that the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention is able to disperse funds to local prevention groups. The two grantors represented in this series are the U.S. Department of Education and the U.S. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Award notices issued by the U.S. Department of Education include information regarding the amount of the grant award and copies of regulations governing how the money is to be spent. Grant award notices issued by the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration provide an approved budget detailing how the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention is to disperse the grant.  Items in this series are arranged chronologically. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>United States Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration Notices of Grant Awards - Virginia State Incentive (SIG) Project, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">18
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>United States Department of Education Grant Award Notifications - Governor's Grants, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">18
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VI. Memoranda- Appropriation and Allotment</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2002-2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">19
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains office memoranda directed to Virginia's State Comptroller. All of the memoranda in this series are requests for loans to finance the office's administrative expenses in advance of the receipt of federal grant monies. This series is arranged chronologically. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Treasury Loans, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2006</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">19
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VII. Director's Correspondence</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2002 - 2006</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">20
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1 folder.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains the outgoing correspondence of Marilyn P. Harris, the director of the Governor's Office or Substance Abuse Prevention. Most of the correspondence in this series consists of letters written in gratitude to private individuals, representatives of various Commonwealth agencies, and corporations to recognize work done on behalf of the office. Other instances of correspondence include staff salary requests and recommendations written on behalf of interns. Notable instances of correspondence include a letter addressed to the DCE Adult School at the Mecklenburg Correctional Center offering thanks for notepads created for use as prizes and a letter denying a FOIA request. This series is arranged chronologically. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Outgoing Correspondence, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 - 2006</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">20
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series VIII.  Agency Publications and Supporting Documentation</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2002-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">21-23
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 3 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains the publications and supporting documentation of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention and its subsidiary programs. Publications in this series include an educational bookmark, two Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention program pamphlets, a Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council program summary report, a 2005 Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention mid-term progress report entitled, "Touching Down at Midway," and a KidSafe school safety packet and accompanying documentation. The KidSafe school safety packet is designed for parents and educators and includes a CD-ROM with a compilation of federal and state documents offering advice on curbing school violence and what to do during an emergency at school. Also included in the packet are magnets and a notepad embossed with the program name, K-12 lesson plans on personal safety, and a plastic bag designed to hold the materials within the kit. Supporting documentation for the KidSafe program is included in this series and consists of an issue brief written for Governor Mark. R. Warner by Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Governor's Office, thank-you form letters written by Secretary of Public Safety John W. Marshall and addressed to individuals to assisted in launching the program, and a calendar noting the times and locations of KidSafe promotional activities. Items in this series are arranged chronologically. Other materials regarding the KidSafe program are located in Series X. Conference and Training Records, 2003-2005. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Publications and Correspondence, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">21 (1 of 2)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Publications and Correspondence, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">22 (2 of 2)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Pamphlets, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">23 
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Speakout! Program Summary Report, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">23 
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention Strategic Plan, "Touching Down At Midway"
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">23 
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IX. Transition Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">24
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 1 folder.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series is comprised exclusively of a transition notebook prepared for internal office usage. Transition notebooks are typically created for the benefit of new staff members who fill vacant positions. The purpose of a transition notebook is to provide new staff with enough information to immediately fit in with organizational culture and continue working towards predetermined goals. Accordingly, the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse transition notebook is a valuable resource for researchers because it provides an overview of the office's mission, values, budget, problem issues, and accomplishments at a set point in time. It also includes an organizational chart and employee biographical sketches. It appears to have been disassembled at some point and is missing eleven of its twelve appendices. Appendix F, Community Profile Database, is all that remains of the appendices section. The Community Profile Database is an online interactive database on the office website and is designed to allow website visitors to organize statistical information regarding Virginia youths by several choices of indicators and limiters. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transition Notebook, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">December 1, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">24
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series X. Conference and Training Records</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2003-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">25-31
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 7 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series includes the conference and training records of programs administered by the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention. Most of this series is comprised of KidSafe conference packets containing conference schedules, topics, and PowerPoint handouts. The packets were presumably given to conference attendees to record notes. Registration information and letters written in gratitude by Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, to individuals who helped bring about a given conference are included with some packets. Further information regarding the KidSafe program is available in Series VIII.  Agency Publications and Supporting Documentation, 2002-2005.</p>
          <p>Also included in this series are records relating to the Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council Summit, Gang Awareness and Intervention Training, and the Protect and Respect Statewide Summit. The Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council Summit records include a press release, an events schedule, a list of attendees, and letters written in gratitude by Secretary of Public Safety John W. Marshall to individuals who helped bring about the summit. The Gang Awareness and Intervention Training records include a training schedule, memoranda addressed to presenters and written by Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, and an event briefing paper. The records of the Protect and Respect Statewide Summit are limited to an agenda. This series is arranged chronologically. Further information regarding the Protect and Respect program can be found in Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation, 2003-2005.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 19, 2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">25 (1 of 2)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 19, 2003</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">26 (2 of 2)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference 2, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 4, 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">27
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 16, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">28 (1 of 3)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 16, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">29 (2 of 3)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 16, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">30 (3 of 3)
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council (GYPSAC) Summit, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 30, 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">31
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Gang Awareness and Intervention Training, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 30, 2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">31
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Protect and Respect Statewide Summit, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 12, 2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">31
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2003-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">32-33
</container>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 2 folders.</extent>
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> This series is comprised of what the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention refers to as project files. Records included in this series include records of the 2004 National Night Out Governor's Youth Essay Contest, the Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup, and the Protect and Respect Program. 
</p>
          <p>National Night Out is a crime and drug prevention event sponsored by the National Association of Town Watch. The event is designed to heighten awareness about local anticrime efforts through a night of neighborhood activities and front porch vigils.  The records of the National Night Out essay contest include a contest flyer, an entry form, a rule sheet containing guidelines and eligibility criteria, and a letter from Governor Mark R. Warner to an entrant who is in all likelihood the contest winner. A letter from Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention to a contest entrant offers thanks for having entered the contest.  </p>
          <p>The Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup is a consortium of Commonwealth agencies under the Public Safety Secretariat. It is tasked with sharing information and promoting anti-gang activities between member agencies. The Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention is one member agency within the consortium. The records of the Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup include notices for anti-gang workshops and a 2005 booklet outlining the goals and accomplishments of the workgroup. </p>
          <p>The records of the Protect and Respect program are the most extensive set of records in this series. Protect and Respect is a Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention personal safety and awareness program for older Virginians. One aspect of Protect and Respect includes a mentoring program between older Virginians and adolescents.  Records include a brochure outlining the purpose of the Protect and Respect program, an event program for the May 25, 2004 grand opening of the Protect and Respect Public Safety Institutes, two certificates noting the graduation of an individual enrolled in one of the Protect and Respect Public Safety Institutes, an event briefing information sheet, and PowerPoint presentations designed for both program grantees and those interested in the background and purpose of the Protect and Respect Intergenerational Mentoring Program. Also included is an independent needs assessment study done by an outside contractor and designed to identify crime issues affecting older Virginians. Further information on the Protect and Respect program can me found in Series III. Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001 Grant Subaward Records, 2001-2006.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Protect and Respect, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003-2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">32
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Governor's Youth Essay Contest, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">33
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005</unitdate>.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">33
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
