<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02779">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02779::A Guide to the Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), 1790-1808)//EN" "vi02779.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790-1808</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), 1790-1808     
<num type="collectionnumber">0007573136</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">©2015 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">13 April 2015</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790-1808</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number:">0007573136</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790-1808 
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007573136
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">.35 cu. ft.        
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images found at <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan/">Virginia Untold: the African American Narrative</extref>.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Accomack County (Va.) District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), 1790-1808. Local government records collection, Accomack County (Va.) County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Accomack County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Accomack County was named for the Accomac Indians, who lived on the Eastern Shore at the time of the first English settlement in Virginia. The word means "on-the-other-side-of-water place" or "across the water." It was one of the original eight shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634 and spelled Accomac without the k. The county's name was changed to Northampton County in 1643. The present county was formed from Northampton about 1663. In October 1670, the General Assembly temporarily reunited Accomack and Northampton Counties as Northampton County. In November 1673, Accomack County was again separated from Northampton. In early records, the county's name was spelled many ways. In 1940 the General Assembly adopted the present spelling, Accomack. The county gained a small part of the southern end of Smith's Island from Somerset County, Maryland, in 1879, after the United States had approved boundary changes between Virginia and Maryland that had been agreed to in 1877. The county seat is Accomac.
</p>
  <p>The District Court was created in 1788. The purpose of the creation of the District Court was to alleviate congestion in the General Court which had caused unreasonable delays in the adjudication of common law cases. Virginia was divided into eighteen districts, each composed of several counties, plust the district of Kentucky. Courts were held in each district twice yearly and cases were heard from the several counties in that district. The District Court always met at the same place in each district, and its records were kept at that one location. The District Courts were abolished in 1808 and were replaced by the Superior Courts of Law.
</p>
      <p>Slaves could sue for emancipation if they were descendant(s) of a free female ancestor, typically a Native American (Hening Statutes, volume 2, p.170.)
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Accomack County (Va.) County District Court Judgments (Freedom Suits), 1790-1808, consist of suits initiated by slaves seeking to gain their freedom in the district court. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Also identified are names of slaves and slaveowners identified in suit as well as whether slave(s) won their freedom. Predominant documents found in freedom suits include petitions, records of suits, depositions, affidavits, wills, among other items. Information found in documents include slave's argument for freedom, acquisition of slaves by slaveowners, slave ancestry, and relationship between slaves and slaveowners. 
</p>
         </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Accomack County court records can be found at the Library of Virginia.</p>
              </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans -- History -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slavery -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Accomack County (Va.) -- History.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Civil actions -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Freedom suits -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Accomack County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
       <controlaccess>
        <head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Accomack County (Va.) District Court</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
        <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1794 Oct., Thomas (slave) vs. Edward Roberts:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Thomas sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  He petitioned for his freedom claiming that he had been set free by Roberts' mother's last will and testament.  She became a Quaker while living in Philadelphia, PA and her new religious convictions influenced her to free her slaves.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1795 May, Mary (slave) vs. Edward Roberts:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mary sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  He petitioned for his freedom claiming that he had been set free by Roberts' mother's last will and testament.  She became a Quaker while living in Philadelphia, PA and her new religious convictions influenced her to free her slaves.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1796 May, George alias George Cook (slave) vs. John Walker, Jr: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>George sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  He petitioned for his freedom from slavery claiming he was a descendant of Native Americans.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1801 May, Major (slave) vs. Anna Maria Andrews: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Major petitioned for freedom from slavery claiming he was a descendant of Native Americans. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1802 May, Petition of Cyrus (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cyrus petitioned for freedom from slavery claiming he was a descendant of Native Americans. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
     <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1804 Oct, Mary (slave) vs. Robert Andrews: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mary sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  She petitioned for her freedom from slavery claiming she was a descendant of Native Americans.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1805 Oct, Ibby alias Abby Harmon (slave) vs. William S. Roberts: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Ibby sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  She petitioned for her freedom from slavery claiming she was a descendant of Native Americans.  The suit includes a deposition that recounts Ibby's genealogy.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1806 May, Lydia (slave) vs. John Mears: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Lydia sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  She petitioned for her freedom from slavery claiming she was a descendant of Native Americans.  She successfully won her freedom. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1808 May, Joe (slave) vs. Exr. of Jacob Lilliston, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Joe sued for damages claiming false imprisonment.  He petitioned for his freedom from slavery claiming that he had been set free by Lilliston's last will and testament.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>