<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02414">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02414.xml::A Guide to the Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1754-1861)//EN" "vi02414.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1861</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1754-1861</subtitle>
        <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Catherine OBrion, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">07 May 2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1861</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>LVA staff   
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records,      
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1861
</unitdate></unittitle>

      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1.15 cu. ft. (3 boxes)      
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Southampton County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Southampton County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1754-1861. Local government records collection, Southampton County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Southampton  County, accession number 31913.</p>
        
      </acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Starting in 2023, Library of Virginia archival staff in partnership with the Virginia Untold Project Manager began efforts to describe records related to free and enslaved Black and multiracial people in a manner that improved the historical context of the records. In doing so, in some cases material once described within the "Free and Enslaved" record group for a locality may no longer be described within this record. When this has occurred, please see the Processing Information and Related Materials section for records that have been described separately.</p>
<p>Apprenticeship Indentures were removed from this record in June 2024 and are now described in Southampton County (Va.)Aprrenticeship Indentures, 1813-1904</p>
<p>Certificates of Importation were removed from this record in June 2024 and are now described in Southampton County (Va.) Certificates of Importation, 1790-1816</p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registrations were removed from this record in June 2024 and are now described in Southampton County (Va.) Records Relating to the Registration of Free Person, 1794-1864 </p>
<p>Petitions to Remain were removed from this record in June 2024 and are now described in Southampton County (Va.) Petitions to Remain in the Commonwealth, 1818-1853 </p>
 <p>Records relating to the Nansemond and Nottoway Indian tribes once included with this collection have been removed [on an unknwon date] and can now be found in barcode number 1119712 and in Southampton Chancery Causes index numbers 1830-064, 1835-038, 1837-054, 1837-055, 1840-027, 1841-043, 1849-045, 1851-032, 1851-033, 1856-048, 1870-042, 1871-076, and 1871-077. The Southampton Chancery Causes are available on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/"> Chancery Records Index </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.
</p>

<p>Encoded by C. OBriean, 2015; Updated by M. Mason, June 2024.

</p>
</processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph></p>

<p><emph render="underline">Free and Enslaved Records</emph>
</p>

<p>The Free and Enslaved Records collection is comprised of miscellaneous records related to the regulation and policing of both enslaved and free Black and Multiracial people in Orange County. The localities/local government authorities were largely responsible for enforcing laws that restricted the movement of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people and the resulting documentation was often filed in the circuit courts. The ways in which local authorities enacted legal measures against or on behalf of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people varied from locality to locality; therefore, records were not necessarily standardized or filed and retained in a consistent manner. This collection is topical and a means by which to compile miscellaneous documents related to free and enslaved people that are not established local government record types.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">See:</emph> <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://virginiamemory.com/collections/aan/aan_record_types.pdf?v=5.0l">  The Virginia Untold Record types </extref>on the Library of Virginia website for additional context concerning Deeds; Fiduciary Records; "Free Negro" Tax records; and "Runaway" Records</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Southampton County was named, in the opinion of many authorities, for Henry Wriothesley, third earl of Southampton and treasurer of the London Company from 1620 to 1624. It is more likely, however, that the county was named for the borough of Southampton in England. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
  
<p>Southampton County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1754-1861, consist of Deeds, 1822 and 1845; Fiduciary records, 1848,; "Free Negro" Tax records, 1791-1861; Patrol Records, 1754-1861; "Runaway" records, 1798 and 1852; and additional records of various record types, 1798-1852. </p>
<p>Deeds, 1822 and 1845, consist of two bills of sale the first, 1822, between William Owens and Leaonard Cobb, for the transfer of Tom, Davy, Ben, and Simon, four Black men enslaved by William Owens; and the last, 1845, between Eglantine Joyner, a free Black woman, and William Babb, transferring Henry Joyner to Babbs, until Henry arrives at the age of 21. </p>
<p>Fiduciary records, 1848, contain dower records, 1848, of Mary W. Kellos, which consist of a list of names and birth dates of 17 individuals enslaved by Kellos with addition documents providing information as to the birth and death dates of some of the enslaved individuals. </p>
<p>"Free Negro" Tax records, 1791-1861, consists of "Free Negro Tax Lists",1801-1831, and "Free Nego Delinquent Tax Lists,"1791-1861</p>
<p>"Free Negro Tax Lists," 1791-1860, are lists Black and multiracial individuals compiled by a revenue commissioner for tax purposes. Lists may contain name only; they may also include gender, age, place of residence, and occupation. Lists of individuals who haven't paid taxes sometimes contain amount of tax levied, and remarks about why the tax was not paid. Theses records contain lists from Nottoway Parish, 1801 and 1817, 1821, 1822 and 1826 [oversize]; St. Luke's Parish, 1801, 1803, 1812 [oversize], and 1819; the District of Samuel Calvert, 1804-1805; the District of Ephraim Lee, 1807; a list dated 1821 Sep 6, and a list dated 1831 Dec.</p>
 <p>Also included "Free Negro Delinquent Tax Lists," 1791-1861, which consist of  list of "Insolvent Free Negroes," 1791-1792; lists of "Insolvents and Non-Inhabitants," in the St. Luke's Parish, 1800 and 1858-1860; Upper District, St. Luke's Parish, 1852-1857; Lower District, St. Luke's Parish, 1857 and undated; Nottoway Parish, 1800-1801 and 1859-1860; lists of "Individuals Returned Delinquent," 1814-1815; 1821, and undated; and lists of Individuals "Ordered for sale for Non-Payment of Taxes," 1826-1828.</p>
<p>Patrol Records, 1754-1861, undated, consist of one box of patrol reports, appointments, orders, and warrants. These patrols generally acted as the policing force that monitored the movement of free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals. These record the names of the individuals on patrol; who authorized their patrol; dates of patrol; the number of hours on patrol; general geographic area patrolled; and compensation awarded. Some returns specifically note the objective to "apprehend all slaves and other disorderly persons," or "to visit all negro quarters, and other places suspected of entertaining unlawful assemblies of servants, slaves, or of disorderly persons."</p>
<p>"Runaway" records, 1798 and 1852, consists of a commit order, 1798, committing Robert, a Black man enslaved by Joel Judkins of North Carolina, to jail for suspicion of self-emancipating; and a jailor's report, 1852, concerning  Dennis Sycamore, a Black man, stating his legal status is free  but has been charged with self-emancipating. </p>
<p>Additional records of various record types, 1798-1852, consist of a bond, 1814, for James Jones under condition of allowing Joice, Esther, Harry, Jenny, Annah, and Mary currently enslaved by Jones to petition for their freedom at the next court. </p>
<p>Also includes, a certificate, 1824, of good character made on behalf of Stepney, a formerly enslaved Black man [possibly made in effort to petition to remain in the commonwealth, petition noted as rejected].</p>
<p>Also, includes an order, 1804, to recover Cato and Henry, two Black men enslaved by William Blake, suspected of being transported illegally to South Carolina (illegally sold to Blake by John Derring).</p>
<p>Also, includes, a petition, 1830, of Moses Pretton, "a free man of colour," made in an effort to secure license to carry a firearm.</p> 
<p>Lastly, includes records concerning James Brooks, 1759-1760, consist of a will, bills of sale, and affidavits, related to James Brooks, a formerly enslaved Black man, being purchased by James Brooks, Jr., his son, from John Buckner. </p>

    </scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged
</p>
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Free and Enslaved Records,1754-1861, arranged loosely by record type then chronologically</item></list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06331.xml">Southampton County (Va.) Certificates of Importation, 1790-1816 </extref>  </p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06332.xml">Southampton County (Va.) Petitions to Remain in the Commonwealth, 1818-1853</extref>  </p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00764.xml">Southampton County (Va.) Records related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1794-1864</extref>  </p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi05028.xml">Southampton County (Va.) Apprenticeship Indentures, 1813-1904 </extref>  </p>

<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Southampton County  (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>

<p>Additional Southampton County  (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>

</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold"> Free and Enslaved Records,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold"> 1754-1861</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc> Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent> 1.15 cubic feet (3 boxes)</extent>
</physdesc>
</did> 
<arrangement>
<p> arranged loose by record type then chronologically 
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1119722">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1759-1866
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1185512">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1812-1826
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1119725">Free and enslaved records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1754-1860 [oversized]
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
   </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>








