<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY lost SYSTEM "http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi02842">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02842::A Guide to the Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, 1871-1875)//EN" "vi02842.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, <date>1871-1875</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, 1871-1875
<num type="collectionnumber">1111946, 1111966, 1111970-1111971, 1111973-1111974, 1111976
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Sarah Nerney, <date>20 December 2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, <date>1871-1875</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers:">1111946, 1111966, 1111970-1111971, 1111973-1111974, 1111976
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1871-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">1111946, 1111966, 1111970-1111971, 1111973-1111974, 1111976
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">State Records Center - Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">7 v.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Sussex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, 1871-1875. Local government records collection, Sussex County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Sussex County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Sussex County was named for the English county, and was formed from Surry County in 1753.
</p>
<p>The 1870 Virginia Constitution required that each county in the state be divided into no less than three townships (see Article VII, section 2). Based on the New England administrative organization of a county, each township would elect the administration officials for the offices of supervisor, clerk, assessor, collector, commissioner of the roads, overseer of the poor, justice of the peace, and constable. The supervisors of each township would comprise the board of supervisors for the county, and would be responsible for auditing the county accounts, examining the assessors' books, regulating property valuation, and fixing the county levies. The Acts of Assembly provided that each township be divided into school and electoral districts (see Acts of Assembly 1869-1870, Chapter 39). A constitutional amendment in 1874 changed the townships into magisterial districts and each district elected one supervisor, three justices of the peace, one constable, and one overseer of the poor. The supervisors of the districts made up the county board of supervisors whose duties were identical as those set out in 1870. The published Acts of Assembly appended a list of township names by county following the acts for every year that townships existed in Virginia.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Sussex County (Va.) Township Records, 1871-1875, consist of seven volumes of minutes and accounts relating to the administrative functions of the township boards of the county.
</p>
<p>Henry Township Board Minutes, 1871-1875, consist of minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes township collector accounts, election returns, division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, establishment of tax and levy rates, accounts allowable against the township board, examination of road overseer accounts, bridge building and repair proposals, reports on delinquent taxes, and examination of the treasurer's accounts. Following the minutes on pages 28-55 are Applications for Purchase of Delinquent Land, 1898-1899. Information recorded includes name of attorney, applicant name, name in which land sold, mortages or trustees, description of land, date of filing, years due, fees and costs, and when collected. There is a separate index volume inserted at the front of this volume that relates only to these applications.
</p>
<p>Newville Township Board Minutes, 1871-1875, consist of minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes division of the township into road districts, road petitions, election precincts and orders for elections, appointment and election of road overseers, road overseer reports, accounts allowable against the township board, establishment of rates allowable for road work, special levys for bridge repairs, bridge and road inspection reports, reports of township warrants paid, acquisition of supplies for the township board (stationery, desk, room for office, etc), and reports of township assessor and collector. Following the minutes are an index and several pages of charters and articles of incorporation, 1890-1891. The index applies to the charters and not to the minutes.
</p>
<p>Newville Township Warrant Books, 1872-1875, are two volumes of warrants issued by the the township board to individuals so they could receive payment from the collector. Information recorded includes the warrant number, date, account of (individual's name), reason for warrant, and amount.
</p>
<p>Stony Creek Township Warrants, 1872-1875, are warrants issued to individuals by the township board so they can receive payment for services provided the board. Recorded information includes warrant number, date, name paid to, reason for payment, amount, and the signatures of the township clerk and board chairman. Following are Sussex County warrants for 1882-1885. The bindings of this volume have been heavily water damaged. Please use with care.
</p>
<p>Sussex Courthouse Township Board Minutes, 1871-1875, consist of minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, calling of elections for road overseers, accounts allowable against the township, establishment of levys to support the township, road overseer reports, redivision of the township into road districts, road and bridge reports, and examination of treasurer's reports.
</p>
<p>Waverly Township Board Minutes, 1872-1875, consist of minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, proposal to buy a lot of land to build township offices, specifications for the township office building, calling of election for road overseers, orders to inspect bridges, establishment of tax rates, accounts allowable against the township board, reports on bridge inspections, road overseer reports, proposals for the building of a township hall, and settlement of township treasurer accounts. Following the minutes is a Register of Physicians and Surgeons, 1891-1908, that contains entries of physicians and surgeons who presented their certificate to the county court from the state Boards of Medical Examiners showing that they are legally permitted to practice medicine in the state.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Sussex County (Va.). Circuit Court.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">County government -- Records and correspondence -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Local finance -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Local government -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Physicians -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Sussex County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Accounts -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Minute books -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Registers (lists) -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Tax and fiscal records -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Township records -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Warrants -- Virginia -- Sussex County.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Henry (Sussex County, VA)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Newville (Sussex County, VA)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Stony Creek (Sussex County, VA)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Sussex Courthouse (Sussex County, VA)</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Waverly (Sussex County, VA)</corpname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="analyticover">
<head>Contents List
</head><c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111946">Henry Township Board Minutes, 1871-1875
<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1875.  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Includes Applications for Purchase of Delinquent Land, 1898-1899
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111976">Newville Township Board Minutes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1875.  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Includes charters and articles of incorporation, 1890-1891
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111970">Newville Township Warrant Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111974">Newville Township Warrant Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111966">Stony Creek Township Warrants, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111971">Sussex Courthouse Township Board Minutes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1111973">Waverly Township Board Minutes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1875.  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Includes Register of Physicians and Surgeons, 1891-1908
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
