<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY lost SYSTEM "http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi02797">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02797::A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, 2009 June)//EN" "vi02797.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, <date>2009 June</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, 2009 June
<num type="collectionnumber">1201201
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Sarah Nerney, <date>10 June 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, <date>2009 June</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number:">1201201
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2009 June
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">1201201
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">.35 cu. ft. (1 box)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Richmond (Va.) City Council.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, 2009 June. Local government records collection, Richmond (City) City Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>This item came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer from the Richmond City Council under the accession number 44364.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The James River Park System Conservation Easement represents the first action by a city in Virginia to place approximately 280 acres of a major urban park system under a conservation easement. Protection is now in place for properties including the Historic Falls of the James State Scenic River, substantial undeveloped land adjacent to the river, significant habitat for wildlife including bald eagle nesting sites, historic resources include remnants of Foushee Mill, the first canal built in the United States including a stone arch from the 1790s, foundations of the Belle Isle Iron Mill built in the 1840s, traces of a 1902 hydroelectric plant on Belle Isle, the site of a Civil War prison on Belle Isle, the site of a Confederate shipyard, the site of the first railroad in Virginia that dates to the late 1700s, a ship lock created in the 1850s as the easternmost part of the Kanawha Canal, and the Three-Mile Locks that are the earliest part of the Kanawha Canal.
</p>
<p>The James River Park system is a 550 acre park composed of several parcels stretching about eight miles along the river and Kanawha Canal from the western boundaries of the city down through the river rapids that mark the falls of the James, to the tidal reaches at the eastern boundary of the city. The city began acquiring the parcels that make up the park in the 1960s and 1970s. It is largely undeveloped, being retained as much as possible in its natural state.
</p>
<p>An easement is a device by which the owner of property, in this case the city of Richmond, agrees voluntarily to give up some ownership rights, including the right to sell the property and the right to develop or permit to be developed commercial, industrial or residential properties in the park. The city gives to a second party, the easement holders, the right to enforce the terms of the agreement. The easement holders in this deed are the Richmond Recreation and Parks Foundation, the Capital Region Land Conservancy, and the Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Richmond (Va.) James River Park System Conservation Easement, 2009 June, consists of a photocopy of the deed of easement, a ceremonial copy of the deed of easement, and a magazine article about the history of the easement project.
</p>
<p>The photocopy of the deed of conservation and open-space easement between the City of Richmond, Virginia and Capital Region Land Conservancy, Inc., Richmond Recreation and Parks Foundation, and the Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation contains the text of the deed as well as fifteen maps and plats, and the first page of Exhibit A, a Conservation Easement Baseline Document produced by the Richmond Recreation and Parks Foundation. The original deed was recorded amongst the deeds of the City of Richmond on 2009 June 9.
</p>
<p>The ceremonial copy of the deed is from the official signing ceremony on 2009 May 29. It features a description of the intent of the conservation easement and the original signatures of the mayor of Richmond, the president of Richmond City Council, the acting chief administrative officer of Richmond, the governor of Virginia, the director of the Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation, the president of the Richmond Recreation and Parks Foundation, and a board member of the Capital Region Land Conservancy.
</p>
<p>The April 2009 issue of Virginia Town and City: The Magazine of the Virginia Municipal League (Vol. 44 No. 4) features a cover article on the history of the project to create the park system conservation easement including the major efforts of city council member Kathy Graziano and Charles Price of the Sierra Club of Richmond.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Richmond (Va.). City Council.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Conservation easements -- Virginia -- Richmond.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">James River (Va.)</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Parks -- Virginia -- Richmond.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records -- Virginia -- Richmond.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Richmond (Va.) -- History -- 21st century.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Magazines (periodicals) -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Maps -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats (land) -- Virginia -- Richmond.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
