<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi02258">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02258.xml::A Guide to the Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1780-1866)//EN" "vi02258.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, <date>1780-1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1780-1866
<num type="collectionnumber">1177495, 1188800-1188802/Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 45</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Catherine OBrion, <date>13 June 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, <date>1780-1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection number:">1177495, 1188800-1188802/Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 45
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>C. G. OBrion and E. Woodward
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title"  encodinganalog="245$a">Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records,    
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1780-1866
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">1177495, 1188800-1188802/Powhatan County (Va.) Reel 45
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1.80 cu. ft. (4 boxes); 1 v. (111 p. and 21 leaves), and 1 microfilm reel (72 images).    
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Powhatan County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Use microfilm copy, Powhatan County Reel 45, of the Register of Free Negroes and Mulattoes, 1820-1865.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1780-1866. Local government records collection, Powhatan County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court records from Powhatan County.</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>In part, photocopies.
</p>
</altformavail>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Powhatan County was named for the Indian chieftain who ruled the Native American inhabitants of tidewater Virginia in the early seventeenth century. It was formed from Cumberland County in 1777, and part of Chesterfield County was added later.
</p>
<p>An act passed by the Virginia legislature in 1803 required every free negro or mulatto to be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the county clerk.
</p>
<p>An act passed in 1806 required freed slaves to leave the state within a year.</p>
<p>The General Assembly of Virginia passed a law as early as July 1, 1861, calling for the enrollment of free negroes to work in the public service.
</p>
<p>Slaveholders who brought slaves into or out of Virginia were required to register the slaves with the county court and sign an oath agreeing not to bring slaves into or out of the state with the intent of selling them.
</p>
<p>An act passed by the Virginia legislature in 1856 allowed free persons of color who desired to remain in Virginia to petition for reenslavement and choose a master or owner and remain in the state.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Powhatan County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1780-1866. The collection is comprised of free negro registrations, affidavits, and certificates, 1798-1866; additional free negro and slave records, 1780-1865; and a Register of Free Negroes and Mulattoes, 1820-1865.
</p>
<p>Free negro registrations, affidavits, and certificates include name, sometimes age and a brief physical description, and the circumstances of the person's freedom or emancipation. If born free, reference is sometimes made to parents. If emancipated, the emancipating owner, place and date of emancipation, and prior registration as a free negro are usually mentioned. The Register of Free Negroes and Mulattoes documents name, age, color, height, date registered, mars or scars, and circumstances of freedom or emancipation.
</p>
<p>Additional free negro records are comprised of free negro lists, 1801-1857; petitions to remain in Virginia, 1816-1852; miscellaneous free negro petitions, 1818-1860; and papers regarding free negroes requisitioned for public use, 1861-1863. Free negro lists were compiled by the Commissioner of the Revenue for tax purposes. They include full name, place of residence, and occupation. Petitions to remain in Virginia were filed by individuals petitioning for an exception to laws requiring newly freed or emancipated slaves to leave the state within twelve months. They include information about families, emancipations, and testaments to the character of the petitioner. The collection also contains the petition of Frank (no surname given) to carry a gun and ammunition for it (granted in 1818 and revoked in 1831); the petition of Judith Collins for reenslavement, 1858; and a petition, 1860, to provide funds to settle children emancipated by the Watkins family in a free state.   Also included is a motion, 1851 Dec. 3, made by Bob, a negro man who was emancipated by the Court of Appeals (to be free at the age of thirty years) by the wills of John and Jonathan Pleasants, to be registered as a free man. The motion was opposed by Robert H. Mayo on the grounds that the the said Bob was not yet thirty years of age. Papers regarding free negroes requisitioned for public use contain orders summoning free negroes to work on fortifications at Richmond, 1861 and 1863, and lists of those summoned. Also included is a requisition from the Quartermaster Department in Richmond for free negroes to bale provender, 1863 Sep. 24.
</p>
<p>The collection also contains slave records, as follows: certificates of importation and non-importation, 1780-1817; an order for removing Bradby's Rachel from the county and returning her to her owner, 1824; and warrants of commitment of slaves as runaways, 1830-1874. Certificates of importation and non-importation include a list of slaves brought into the state from Georgia by Samuel Elbert, 1780; a list of five slaves brought into Virginia from South Carolina by Henry W. Watkins, 1814; and a declaration of John Nunnally of his intent to move to Georgia with 26 slaves, 1817. Warrants of commitment of slaves as runaways consist of warrants for Littleberry Ellison, 1830, and John Kennedy, 1839, both proved free men; and an unknown negro man, 1847.
</p>
<p>The collection includes photocopies of records from other series that pertain to free negroes and enslaved people, as follows: deeds of emancipation, 1789-1855; free negro apprenticeships, 1809-1855; free negro registration; summonses against free negroes delinquent on the county levy for the years 1818, 1819, and 1850; agreements to hire slaves, 1812-1824; bills of sale and deeds of gift for enslaved people, 1810-1865; coroners' inquisitions for deceased slaves, 1810-1864; fiduciary records documenting slave property, 1809-1853; a list of the taxable property (slaves) of William Ronalds, 1789; an order to place a slave on the poor list, 1825; an order to issue a free negro registration, 1809; an affidavit pertaining to the deed of gift of an enslaved girl, 1819; a recognizance to answer a charge of permitting a slave to go at large, 1861; and a report of the sale of a runaway, 1865.</p>
<p>Free negro apprenticeships document the hiring out of children and persons unable to pay the county levy. They include information on the age and name of children and the families to which they were apprenticed, as well as the trade they were intended to learn.</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Powhatan County Register of Free Negroes and Mulattoes, 1800-1820, is available on Powhatan County Microfilm Reel 58.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Powhatan County (Va.) Circuit Court</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Powhatan County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Powhatan County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slavery--Law and legislation--Virginia--Powhatan County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Emancipation--Virginia--Powhatan County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Powhatan County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Affidavits--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Agreements--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Articles of apprenticeship--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Bills of sale--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Certificates--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Coroners' inquisitions--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Fiduciary records--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro and slave records--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro lists--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro registers--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free papers--Virginia--Powhatan County. 
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Powhatan County.
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Petitions--Virginia--Powhatan County.
</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Tax and fiscal records--Virginia--Powhatan County.
</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
