<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi02779">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02779::A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1785-1860)//EN" "vi02779.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, <date>1785-1860</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1785-1860
<num type="collectionnumber">1186868
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Sarah Nerney, <date>30 July 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, <date>1785-1860</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number:">1186868
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1785-1860
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">1186868
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">.45 cu. ft. (1 box) 
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1785-1860. Local government records collection, Isle of Wight County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Isle of Wight County. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Isle of Wight County was most likely named for the Isle of Wight off the south coast of England. It was first known as Warrosquyoake and was one of the eight shires established in 1634. The present name was given in 1637. Part of Nansemond County was added in 1769. 
</p>
<p>An act passed by the Virginia legislature in 1803 required every free negro or mulatto to be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the county clerk.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Isle of Wight County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, 1785-1860, consist of deeds of emancipation and bonds to keep freed negroes from becoming chargeable to the parish (1796-1802); free negro registrations and affidavits and certificates (1812-1849); lists of free negroes delinquent in various taxes (1806-1860); mittimuses for free negroes and slaves suspected of crimes (1785-1860); Overseers of the Poor free negroes bound out (undated); patrol returns (1809-1841); petitions to remain in the state (1840, 1856); and miscellanous records (1811-1854). 
</p>
<p>Deeds of emancipation or manumission (1796; 1799; 1802) include the name of the slaveowner, the name of the slave, the date or age at which the slave will be freed, the date the deed was written, and the date the deed was proved. The age of the slave at the time of the deed was written, a surname assigned to the freed slave by the slaveowner, and the slaveowner's reason for emancipation are sometimes given. Bonds to prevent freed negroes from becoming chargeable to the parish (1796) are assurances made by the emancipators that the freed slaves will not have to be supported by the parish or county for their survival. The bonds include the name of the slaveholder, the names and ages of the slaves emancipated, and the amount of the bond.
</p>
<p>Free negro registrations and affidavits and certificates contain the name of the free person, their age and a brief physical description, and a statement based either on another person's knowledge or on other official documentary evidence seen by the certifier that this person was either born free or was emancipated. If born free, reference is sometimes made to parents. If emancipated, emancipating owner, place and date of emancipation, and prior registration as a free negro are usually mentioned. </p>
<p>Lists of free negroes delinquent in various taxes are lists compiled by the commissioners of the revenue indicating free negroes who had not paid various county and state taxes. The name of the delinquent person is always listed and sometimes the amount of the tax and which tax is delinquent. Some of the lists instruct that the delinquent persons are to be sold or hired out to pay the tax.
</p>
<p>Mittimuses for free negroes and slaves suspected of crimes are orders or warrants sent to the sheriff or jailer directing that a person be detained until ordered otherwise. The crimes range from larceny to assault to being a runaway or not being registered as a free person. Further decisions and decrees are sometimes noted on the reverse.
</p>
<p>Overseers of the Poor free negroes bound out are four undated notes indicating certain free negro children to be bound out to avoid them being chargeable to the county and to teach them a trade. The notes include the names and ages of the children, sometimes who their parents are, and other notes about amounts to be paid.
</p>
<p>Patrol returns list the names of patrollers, dates and/or hours served on the slave patrol, and occasionally the amount of money to be paid. The captain of the patrol is usually indicated. There are several notes from patrolers about their patrol tickets.
</p>
<p>Petitions to remain in the state exist for Dawson Boykin (1840) and James Patrick (1856). The records do not actually contain the petitions but orders for the justices to convene to consider the petitions of these individuals.
</p>
<p>Miscellaneous records include a John Derring's certificate of negroes from Warren County, North Carolina (1811); a printed letter from the Board of Commissioners in re: a ship of the American Colonization Society sailing to Liberia (1833); a pass for Thomas Verlines between Portsmouth, Norfolk County and Smithfield, Isle of Wight County in order to work (1841); a promissory note from Sam English, free negro, to E. Eley (1841); three tax tickets exempting certain slaves ([1844]; 1849; undated); and a certificate to court about the slave Willis alias Willis Riddic, property of Solomon Junius Wilson, who had run away to the north (1854).
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.). Circuit Court. </corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans. -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Freedmen. -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Fugitive slaves. -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders. -- Psychology. -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves -- Emancipation -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Tax collection -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) -- History. </geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Affidavits -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Bonds (legal records) -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Certificates -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro and slave records -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro lists -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Free negro registrations -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Lists -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Patrol returns -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Petitions -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Registers (lists) -- Virginia -- Isle of Wight County. </genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
