<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi02213">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi02213::A Guide to the Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, 1856-1896)//EN" "vi02213.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1896</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, 1856-1896
</subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 June 2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1896</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1896
</unitdate></unittitle>
      
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images; 1 volume (286 p.)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Cumberland County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Cumberland Baptist Church Record Book, 1856-1896, is digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images. 
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, 1856-1896, [cite volume title]. Local government records collection, Cumberland County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The Cumberland Baptist Church Record book came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Cumberland County in 2005 under the accession number 41989.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Cumberland Baptist Church Record Book, 1856-1896 is available as microfilm Cumberland County (Va.) Reel 88.
</p>
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Conservation was performed by the Library of Virginia Conservation Lab in 2020 and funded by a donation made by Georga S. Williams to the Library of Virginia Foundation's Adopt Virginia History Program.
</p>
<p> Encoded by G. Crawford, 2007; Updated by M. Mason, May 2024 </p>
</processinfo>

      
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Organizational Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by officers/ leaders in the organization. In other cases, Organizational records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. This organizational records appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for debut suits, and contract disputes. 
</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Cumberland County was named for William Augustus, duke of Cumberland, third son of King George II. It was formed from Goochland County in 1749.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Cumberland County (Va.) Organizational Records, 1836-1856, currently consists of one record. This is the Cumberland Baptist Church Record Book, 1856-1896, which records the church's monthly and quarterly meetings as well as additional church related activities. 
</p>
  
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged 
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Cumberland Baptist Church Minute Book, 1856-1896</item></list>

</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>See also: Cumberland Baptist Church Minute Book, 1836-1856, at the Library of Virginia under the accession number 24200 [negative photostats] and accession number 43813 [original volume].
</p>
<p>See also:<extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04033.xml">Cumberland County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1753-1865</extref>  
</p>
<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Cumberland County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>

<p>Additional Cumberland County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Cumberland Baptist Church Minute Book,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1856-1896
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>Digital images; 1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Cumberland Baptist Church was founded in 1810 by Joseph Jenkins. The church first met in a log building. Members of Cumberland Baptist church met alternately at Booker's Meeting House and Tar Wallet Meeting House between 1836 and 1843 when the congregation divided. The members living near Tar Wallet formed a separate church and the remaining members constituted Cumberland Baptist Church. The congregation met at Booker's Meeting House from 1856 until 1858 when the congregation began meeting at Jenkins' Meeting House.</p>


<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> Cumberland Baptist Church Record Book, 1856-1896, kept by various members of the church, consists of 286 pages and largely records the church's monthly and quarterly meetings and additional church business. 
</p>
<p>Church business activities documented in the volume includes: date and location of meetings; names of members attending meetings; election of church officers; reports of church officers; reports to James River Association providing the number of both white and Black members; resolutions passed by church membership; and decisions made by the church membership related to the activities of the church such as excommunication of members, reconciliation of church members, and baptism of new church members. </p>
<p>The church's membership included Black and multiracial individuals, most of whom were enslaved by white church members. The record book lists the names of enslaved individuals baptized and their enslaver. The volume also records the withdrawal of Black and multiracial members from the church in 1866 for the purpose of forming a Baptist church for the Black community.</p>
<p>The record book includes an index that lists in alphabetical order the names of church members. The index includes additional information such as the year the individual joined the church, the year they were removed from the membership roll, and the reason for their removal (excommunication, death, transfer of membership, etc.)</p>
<p>Families indicated as members of Cumberland Baptist Church include: Jenkins family, Anderson family, Reynolds family, Dowdy family, Dunkum family, Meador family, Nunnally family, Parker family, Sanderson family, and Talley family.</p>

<p><emph render="bold"><extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01LVA_INST/altrmk/alma990015691590205756">Cumberland Baptist Church Record Book, 1856-1896,</extref>
is digitized and available through the Virginia Untold Digital Collection. Please use Digitial Images</emph></p> 

</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1177638">Cumberland Baptist Church record book, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1856-1896
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc></archdesc>
</ead>

