<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi03132">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03132::A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, 1878-1881)//EN" "vi03132.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, <date>1878-1881</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Holliday, Frederick, W. M., Executive Papers of Governor
<num type="collectionnumber">45053
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Craig S. Moore, <date>22 July 2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, <date>1878-1881</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">45053
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Craig S. Moore
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010 
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Craig S. Moore
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1878-1881
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">45053
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">20 items (2 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Governor (1878-1882 : Holliday)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Governor (1878-1882 : Holliday), Executive papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, 1878-1881. Accession 45053, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Acquisition information unknown.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Frederick William Mackey Holliday was born on 22 February 1828 in Winchester, Virginia, to Dr. R. J. Holliday and Mary Catherine Taylor.  He attended Winchester Academy and graduated from Yale University in 1847.  After less than a year's enrollment, he acquired degrees in philosophy, political economy, &amp; law from the University of Virginia in 1848.  He began a law practice and was elected to three consecutive terms as Commonwealth's Attorney for Frederick County in 1851.  An avid secessionist, Holliday lost his election to represent Frederick County in the Virginia Secession Convention.  During the Civil War, Holliday served as captain of Company D, 33rd Virginia Regiment, Stonewall Brigade.  Promoted to major and lieutenant colonel for his exemplary service, Holliday was wounded at the Battle of Cedar Mountain resulting in the amputation of his arm.  Holliday was forced to resign his commission.  Holliday defeated Alexander R. Boteler to represent Virginia's 10th District in the Second Confederate Congress from 1864 to 1865.  
</p>
<p>Following the Civil War, Holliday returned to his law practice and married Hannah Taylor McCormick of Clarke County in 1868.  Upon the death of his first wife, Holliday married Caroline Calvert Stuart of King George County in 1871.  Holliday's second wife died in childbirth, along with their infant child.   In 1876, he served as a commissioner at the Centennial International Exposition in Philadelphia.  The following year, Holliday, a Conservative, was elected governor of Virginia unopposed as the Republican Party concentrated on legislative seats.  Holliday took office on 1 January 1878.  Like his predecessor, Holliday's term as governor was dedicated to Virginia's state debt from the war.  He fought against the Readjusters who sought to renegotiate the state debt.  Holliday left politics at the end of his governorship and devoted the rest of his life to traveling the world.  Holliday suffered a stroke and died on 20 May 1899 and is buried in Mount Hebron Cemetery in Winchester, Virginia.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the rear of the collection. These papers consist of incoming correspondence during Holliday's four-year term as governor of Virginia between 1 January 1878 and 1 January 1882. The correspondence primarily relates to appointments of commissioners to the Lee Monument Association and notaries public. In addition to correspondence, there are recommendations, applications, agreements, resolutions, acts, appointments, commissions, and other sundry items. Governor Holliday's Executive papers are extremely sparse compared to the executive papers of other Virginia governors.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Series I. Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday, 1878-1881
</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Separated Material
</head>
<p>Oversized item has been separated to Box 2. 
</p>
</separatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Executive Papers of Governor Frederick W. M. Holliday</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1878-1881</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Boxes" type="box">1-2
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 2 boxes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Noteworthy documents include the following: a letter of Governor John M. Stone, Mississippi, to S. Bassett French, Secretary of the Lee Monument Association, re. the appointment of commissioners on the part of Mississippi (1878 Apr. 17); Governor James B. McCreary, Kentucky, to S. Bassett French, re. the appointment of commissioners on the part of Kentucky of the Lee Monument Association (1878 Apr. 22); William W. Corcoran, Washington, D.C., re. the painting The Storming of a British Redoubt by American Troops at Yorktown by the French painter Eugene Louis Lami (1878 May 22); the appointment of Capt. Henry Jackson of Atlanta, Georgia, as commissioner of the Lee Monument Association (1879 Mar. 11); an act authorizing the governor to appoint a special agent to collect claims due the state of Virginia from the United States (incl. contract with Dr. J. J. Moran as special agent) (1880 Mar. 3); and an issue of the Providence Journal featuring a speech of Senator Henry B. Anthony of Rhode Island regarding suffrage (1881 Feb. 19).
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>1878 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>1879 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>1880 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>1881
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Undated
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate></unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oversized, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1881</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
