<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03295">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03295::A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1789-1942)//EN" "vi03295.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1942</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1789-1942
<num type="collectionnumber">1167991, 0007288481-0007288489 
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 May 2011</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1942</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers:">1167991, 0007288481-0007288489
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Ed Jordan
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1942
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">11167991, 0007288481-0007288489
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">4.50 cu. ft. (10 boxes)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Henrico County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1789-1942. Local government records collection, Henrico County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, VA 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court records from Henrico County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Henrico County was named for Henry, Prince of Wales, eldest son of King James I. It was one of the eight original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. The county seat is in the western part of the county. 
</p>
      <p>The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance.  The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death.  Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve.  Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six.   The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses.  The coroner was required to write down witness testimony.  After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition.  After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death.  He could require physicians to assist him with determing cause of death.  If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
</p>
<p>Recognized in 1634 as an original shire. All county court records prior to 1655 and almost all prior to 1677 are missing. Many records were destroyed by British troops during the Revolutionary War. Post–Revolutionary War county court records exist. Almost all circuit superior court of law and chancery and circuit court records were destroyed by fire during the evacuation of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War. The county’s circuit court held its sessions at the state courthouse in Richmond.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Henrico County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1789-1942, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance.  Causes of death found in coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God.  Documents commonly found in coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons.  Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions.  Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death.  If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known.  If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence.  Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased.  Slaves were deponents in coroner investigations. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
</p>
    </arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Henrico County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Henrico County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/">Lost Records Localities Database</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>



    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Coroners--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Death--Causes--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Infanticide--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder victims--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Suicide--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women--Virginia--Henrico County</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Henrico County (Va.)--History</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records--Virginia--Henrico County</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Henrico County</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports--Virginia--Henrico County</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Coroners' Inquests of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1810 Sep. 30, Death of Joe (slave):  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Joe, a slave owned by Thomas H. Prosser of Henrico County, died from a mortal blow received about the body administered by the overseer in self-defense. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1819 July 13, Death of Solomon Jones (free negro):   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Solomon Jones, a free negro, died at Deep Run Coal Pits in Henrico County from being whipped and burned in a most horrid and shocking manner by Thomas Lawther being moved and seduced by the instigation of the Devil.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1815 Oct. 5, Death of Nancy Major:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Nancy Major died by severe beatings she received from her husband, a negro slave named John owned by Thomas Cowls.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1821 Dec. 20, Deaths of George V. Angel and George Shurn: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Angel and Shurn drown while crossing or attempting to cross Gillees Creek in a wagon. They accidently got out of the wagon and into the creek being very much intoxicated.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1825 Sept. 5, Death of William C. Murphy: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Murphy died when casually or accidently fell overboard from a steam boat into the James River and drowned or was killed by machinery of steam boat.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1834 April 15, Death of infant child of Kesiah (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The infant was killed and murdered by its mother Kesiah by smothering or by stopping its breath by putting her hand on its face and keeping it there until dead.  She did not have the peace of God before her eyes, but was moved and seduced by the instigation of the Devil to kill her child.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1854 July 15, Death of John McRae (a slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>McRae was the property of the widow of Allen M. Lyons. Died from being taken with a cramp while bathing in the James River Canal.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1858 July 8, Death of Cola (a slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cola was the property of James Hix. She died of congestion of the brain while fastened to a tree with a chain around her neck by Richard H. Barnes and James W. Baker.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889 Nov 14, Death of Spott Cluff: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Died from strokes from blunt instrument in the hands of a mob.    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1892 Dec 15, Deaths of William Judson Wilkinson and James Wills: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilkinson and Wills died by drowning in the James River. The drownings were brought about by reason of three holes bored in the bottom of the boat by P.W. Nicholas. He filled the holes with corn cobs. Nicholas removed the corn cobs from when Wilkinson and Wills rowed from shore with the intention of drowning Wills.  Nicholas was having an illicit affair with Wills' wife.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1901 July 10, Death of Nick Lewis: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Lewis died when he was hit by a south bound train on the R.F. and P. Railroad while he was asleep on the track.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1904 Aug 27, Death of John Heath: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death was due to injuries caused by a blow from a rock thrown by Isaac Stocker over a ten cents debt.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1910 Jan 4, Death of Junius Fagan: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Fagan died due to an accidental explosion of dynamite while warming himself at a fire which had been kindled for the purpose of thawing the dynamite.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1916 Oct. 3, Death of Willie Kenzie: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Kenzie died from acute poisoning from eating large quantity of raw green butterbeans, hulls included.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1918 Feb. 12, Death of Steve Bellas: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bellas died from falling on a wood saw which sawed his head into two parts.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1921 Sept. 21, Death of Sue Tinsley Hadley: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Hadley died as the result of being drugged and drowned by her husband, Wilmer Amos Hadley.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1923 Sept. 3, Death of William Henry Brown: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Brown was accidently killed at Hermitage Golf Club by being struck on the neck by a golf ball. Death probably due to rupture of cerebral artery.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1937 Dec. 28, Death of Dabney B. Shaw: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Shaw died from acute streptococeus infection of the brain due to infected teeth.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
