<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY lost SYSTEM "http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi03286">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03286::A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1801-1947)//EN" "vi03286.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date>1801-1947</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1801-1947
<num type="collectionnumber">1208495-1208497
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2011 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Greg Crawford, <date>11 May 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date>1801-1947</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers: ">1208495-1208497
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Ed Jordan
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1801-1947
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">11208495-1208497
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1.00 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Brunswick County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Brunswick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1801-1947. Local government records collection, Brunswick County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, VA 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court records from Brunswick County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Brunswick County was named for the duchy of Brunswick-Luneburg, one of the German possessions of King George I. It was formed by statute in 1720 from Prince George County and on 31 October 1723 the boundaries of the county were ordered to be laid out, but, because of the sparse population, the county court first met in June 1732. Brunswick County was enlarged by the addition of parts of Surry and Isle of Wight Counties in 1733. The county seat is Lawrenceville. 
</p>
<p>The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance.  The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death.  Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve.  Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six.   The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses.  The coroner was required to write down witness testimony.  After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition.  After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death.  He could require physicians to assist him with determing cause of death.  If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the Coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Brunswick County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1801-1947, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance.  Causes of death found in Coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God.  Documents commonly found include in Coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons.  Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions.  Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death.  If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known.  If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence.  Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased.  Slaves were deponents in coroner investigations. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Brunswick County County Court Minute and Order Books, Superior Court of Law Order Books and Common Law Order Books have references to the Coroners' Inquest and Commonwealth Causes where persons accused of murder were tried. Copies of these books can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref entityref="microfilm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"</extref> 
</p>
<p>Brunswick County criminal suits are filed with Brunswick County Judgments, 1782-1947, located at the Library of Virginia. </p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Brunswick County (Va.) Circuit Court</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Coroners--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Death--Causes--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Infanticide--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder victims--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Suicide--Virginia--Brunswick County</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Brunswick County (Va.)--History</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records--Virginia--Brunswick County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Brunswick County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports--Virginia--Brunswick County</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest 
</head><c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1812 Nov. 1, Death of Jenny (slave):  
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Jenny, a slave owned by Benjamin Lewis of Brunswick County, died from repeated blows received from a cow hide whip administered feloniously by Benjamin Taylor.  Taylor was Lewis' overseer.  The inquisition includes depositions of witnesses who offered detailed testimony concerning Jenny's death.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1840 Mar. 17, Death of unknown child:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The deceased was the child of a slave named Martha owned by H.E. Merritt of Brunswick County.  Death caused either by suffocation during birth or strangulation after birth.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1845 May 26, Death of unknown infant:  
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The deceased was the child of a slave named Mary owned by Thomas D. Edmunds of Brunswick County.  Mary had the child while working in the field.  Mary buried the child in the field.  The child's body was discovered after it was pulled up by a dog.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1859 Sep. 5, Death of Hannah (slave): 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Hannah was a slave owned by the late Elizabeth H. Harrvell of Mecklenburg County hired out to James Clary of Brunswick County.  Death caused by repeated beatings by Clary. The inquisition includes depositions of witnesses who offered detailed testimony concerning Hannah's death. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1901 July 1, Death of Joseph Walton: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Death by strangulation caused by a rope from which he was hanging by the neck.  Joseph Walton, a black male, was accused of breaking and entering into the bedroom of his white boss' teenage daughter.  He was forcibly removed from his jail cell by a lynch mob.  They took Walton to Gholson bridge where he was hung.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1918 Aug. 26, Death of A.J. Osborne: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Death caused by effects of gunshot wound inflicted by C.S. Reaves.  The inquisition includes a sketch of Osborne' body showing the shot wounds.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1919 Aug. 23, Death of Minnie McClellan: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Death caused by an accident.  Her buggy was hit by a car driven by Alber R. Moseley.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1921 Aug. 5, Death of unknown black male: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Death by hanging by the neck from a tree limb.  The act was committed by an unknown mob.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1929 April 9, Death of John Bland: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Death from natural causes while pushing his automobile up a hill.    
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1946 March 27, Death of John Atwell Hubbard: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Hubbard was white male who died at age 59 by unknown causes.  He lived on a farm owned by Peter and John Poarch with his African American niece who was a child of Hubbard's unidentified sister.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>





