<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03933">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03933::A Guide to the Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913))//EN" "vi03933.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913)
<num type="collectionnumber">Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-001-1913-080
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2013 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 January 2013</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-001-1913-080
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2013
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field processors and LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-001-1913-080
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Rockingham County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
<p>The majority of post-1913 chancery records are available at the Circuit Court Clerk's Office. Contact clerk's office for availability.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Rockingham County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Rockingham County was named for Charles Watson-Wentworth, second marquis of Rockingham, who supported the colonies during the years before and during the Revolutionary War. The county was formed from Augusta County in 1778. The county seat is the city of Harrisonburg.
</p>
      <p>A courthouse fire in 1787 destroyed primarily wills and estate records. In June 1864 during the Civil War, court records (mostly volumes) were removed from the courthouse and loaded on a wagon to be taken to place of safety on or beyond the Blue Ridge. The wagon was overtaken by Union troops near Port Republic and set afire, which was put out by local citizens. Many order books, deed books, will books, and fiduciary books, however, were lost or severely damaged by the fire. The loose records that remained at the courthouse were undamaged. Pre-1865 records including deeds and wills were rerecorded following an act of assembly passed in November 1884.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Rockingham County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1781-1913 (bulk 1819-1913), are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Rockingham County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>
        <p>Rockingham County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Rockingham County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> found at the Library of Virginia web site.
</p>
        <p>For more information and a listing of lost records localities see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/guides/rn30_lostrecords.pdf">Lost Records research note</extref>. 
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Rockingham County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans -- History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises. -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law) -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Rockingham County (Va.) -- History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Rockingham County (Va.) -- Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills -- Virginia -- Rockingham County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1850-002, John R. Plecker vs. Peachy Harrison, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Case involving the Methodist Episcopal Church and slavery. There was an argument over which side (northern anti-slavery or southern pro-slavery) would have access to church in Harrisonburg. The suit provides detailed background on the creation of the Methodist Episcopal Church South for the churches in slave-holding states. Numerous depositions discussing the split. A "large minority" wanted to stay with the Northern branch of the church. The suit contains exhibits such as correspondence, newspapers, and print of the Resolutions of the General Conference of 1844..  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1854-020, Henry Phillips vs. Admr. of Andrew Newman, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves the untimely death of a slave named Bill. He was purchased by Phillips from Newman, a resident of Missouri. Includes depositions of doctor that detail his illness and death. Other depositions illustrate the poor treatment of the sick man, all related to Bill's value.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1874-007, Jacob Whitesel, etc. vs. Admr. of Peter Whitesel, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Most of the Whitesel family are from Indiana, but father and one son are living in Rockingham County. This son convinces the father that his current will would be confiscated by the Confederate government which views his family as alien enemies, and would take over his estate. He convinces the father to hand over rights to all his estate to him, promising he would divide it equally after the war.   The son insisted that his father did intend for him to have the bulk of the estate, as he was the one who cared for him in his decline. Suit includes numeorus depositions. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1894-005, Abraham J. Eddins, etc.  vs. Adms. of John Cook and Henry Lingle, etc. vs. Adms. of John Cook: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The suit includes a petition to the District Court of the Confederate States of America in the Western District of Virginia seeking the seizure of property from "alien enemies" residing in Indiana, Ohio, and Illinois based in the Sequestration Act of 1861.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1907-073, Franklin L. Shuler v. Allie Ella Shuler: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Defendant left husband for Robert Sampson after longstanding affair and three children. She fled to Erie, PA with Robert Sampson. Suit includes letters to her oldest son that recount everyday life and mother's regrets.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
