<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi03000">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03000:: A Guide to the Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928)//EN" "vi03000.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1850-1928</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sherri Bagley
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Sherri Bagley, <date> 22 July 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records,<date>1850-1928</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: 
</label>
<item>Bari Helms
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia 
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia 
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1850-1928
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">State Record Center 
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent> 12 volumes</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Pulaski County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled. <emph render="bold">please check alternative form available heading for volumes that have been microfilmed.  Please use microfilm if available</emph>.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p> There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928.  [include volume title].  Local government records collection, Pulaski County Court Records.  The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Pulaski County in 2008 under accession number 43684. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p> <emph render="bold"> Please see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA017"> Pulaski County Microfilm </extref> index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.</emph> </p>
<p>Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855 is available as microfilm Pulaski County (Va.) Reel 56 </p>
<p>Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928 is available as microfilm Pulaski County (Va.) Reel 56 </p> 
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.
</p>
<p>The records in this collection were processed at different times in 2008 by Bari Helms.  Efforts have been taken to identify chancery causes related to these business records as some of these records were used as evidence in court proceedings.
</p>
<p>Encoded by Sherri Bagley, July 2024</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information 
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph>
Business Records, both volumes and loose records are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers.  These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners.  In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit.  These business records exhibit appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments.  These records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
</p> 
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Pulaski County was named for Casimir, the Polish patriot who served in the American army during the Revolutionary War and who was killed during the siege of Savannah in 1779.  It was formed from Montgomery and Wythe Counties in 1839.  Its area is 318 square miles, and the county seat is Pulaski.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content 
</head>
<p>Pulaski County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1928, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Pulaski County (Va.).  Represented records largerly consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, minute books and account books.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855</item>
<item>Series II:  J. Farmer Physician Ledger, 1867-1898</item>
<item>Series III:  Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers, 1889-1896</item>
<item>Series IV:  Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 1899-1907</item>
<item>Series V:  Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928</item></list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also:  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02692.xml"> Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1905-035</extref>
</p>
<p> See also:  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02693.xml"> Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1884-027</extref>
</p>
<p> See also:  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02733.xml"> Pulaski County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1859-006</extref>
</p>
<p>Additional Pulaski County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm." </extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp> 
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1850-1855  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>3 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers, 1850-1855, were used by the railroad's engineering department to record the work performed by various contractors hired to perform grading and masonry work on specific sections of the railroad during its construction. Accounts were recorded for each contractor and include the contractor's name and the section and division of the railroad worked on. Each account entry includes a detailed list of the worked performed and the amounts paid for the service. Work performed by these railroad workers included earth excavation, rock excavation, and the building of culverts. Monthly Estimates Ledger, 1850-1852, contains a small account book that details the numbers of employees and equipment provided by the contractors. Accounts were kept for the number of overseers, mechanics, men, boys, hand carts, and teams used by each contractor. The number of workers who became sick during the construction was also noted. Monthly Estimates Ledger, 1853-1855, includes an article of agreement composed specifically for the work performed by contractors. The document provides a detailed description of the standards and quality expectations of the grading and masonry work.
</p>
<p>Also see:  Pulaski County Chancery Cause, Pryde and Jones versus Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company.  It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1859-006.  Available Digitally through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=145-1850-008"> Chancery Records Index. </extref></p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode numbers 1185494-1185496">The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Monthly Estimates Ledgers 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1850-1855
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">J. Farmer Physician Ledger, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1867-1898
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>J. Farmer Physician Ledger, records the accounts of individual patients. Entries are arranged in chronological order under the individual account name. Each entry includes the date, type of transaction, and the monies debited and credited. Each entry documents the name of the patient treated by listing self for the account holder, wife, child, or the patient's first name. Transactions include services rendered such as examinations, extraction of teeth, dressing wounds, and setting broken bones. Medicine purchases are also recorded and include such items as alcohol, castor oil, pills, cod liver oil, whiskey, iodine, pepsin, liniment, carbolic acid, and laudanum. There are also purchases for items not related to medicine -- corn, hay, lard, and butter. Also included in the ledger is a loose letter from J. B. Jordan dated 7 January 1883 and addressed to Dr. Farmer. Jordan, most probably James B. Jordan (born about 1850) another physician in nearby Newbern, Virginia, requests that Farmer visit a sick patient while he is away attending to an obstetrical case.  
</p>
<p>Also see:  Pulaski County Chancery Cause, Jerry Farmer versus Heirs of Elbert S. Trinkle.  It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1884-027.  Available Digitally through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=145-1850-008"> Chancery Records Index. </extref> </p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1185436">J. Farmer Physician Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive">1867-1898
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1896
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>4 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Lee L. Summers and Company records consist of two daybooks and two ledgers. Daybooks, 1889-1890 and 1892-1893, record transactions on a daily basis as they occurred. Information found in each entry includes date, customer name, merchandise purchased, and monies debited and credited. Items purchased include hay, straw, meal, chop, and oats. Account information was transferred to the corresponding ledgers and listed under the customer's name. Employee accounts were often recorded in the daybooks and note the wages paid for tasks such as hauling hay. Also recorded in the Daybook are entries for the company's incidental expenses such as postage and the costs of sending telegrams. Ledgers, 1889-1891 and 1891-1896, record the accounts of individual customers. Entries are organized in chronological order under the individual account name. Each entry includes the date the transaction occurred, items purchased, and monies debited and credited. Also included in the ledgers are lists of bills receivable and a record of deposits and withdrawals from the Pulaski National Bank.     
</p>
<p>Also see:  Pulaski County Chancery Cause, L. L. Summers versus James Gemmell and others.  It can be found in the Local Records Collection at the Library of Virginia. The index number is 1905-035.  Available Digitally through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=145-1850-008"> Chancery Records Index. </extref> </p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode numbers 1186184, 1186185, 1186197, 1185498 ">Lee L. Summers and Company Daybooks and Ledgers 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1896
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV">Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1899-1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>3 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Fizer and Hall Ledgers, 1899-1904, 1901-1905, and 1902-1907, record the accounts of individual customers at the butcher shop. Each account lists transactions in chronological order as they occurred. Entries document date, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, and monies debited and credited to the accounts. Items purchased include various types and cuts of meat such as beef, pork, chicken, turkey, sausage, veal, mutton, bacon, and oysters. Other items sold include butter, lard, potatoes, cabbage, beans, onions, and eggs. Ledger, 1899-1904, also includes several loose papers dated 1905 and 1906. Most of these are James K. Polk Fizer's account receipts with area merchants for clothing and advertising. There are also several freight bills for Fizer and Hall. In addition, there is a letter addressed to James K. Polk Fizer, 27 August 1906, written by his aunt and uncle, M. N. and C. O. Carper, who were living in Greenwood, Indiana. The letter seeks advice on how to divide land inherited after the death of a distant relative, Virginia Carper Wright.              
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode numbers 1185438-1185439, 1185497">Fizer and Hall Ledgers 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1899-1907 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series V">Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book,  
<unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1928>
</unitdate> 
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>The Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book, 1906-1928, records the meetings of the company's board of directors and stockholders. Early meetings, beginning in December 1906, concern the formation of the company and include such business as the election of officers and board members, drafting by-laws, hiring employees, fixing salary rates, selling stock, and raising money to construct the storage plant. The majority of meetings concern the state of the company, the election of officers, the selling of stock, and the hiring of employees. Annual statements were provided at meetings of the stockholders. These statements documented the resources (real estate, machinery, bills receivable, cash) and liabilities of the company. Reports of receipts (stock sold, storage fees) and disbursements (rent, labor, fuel) were also provided. The final meeting of the stockholders, 29 February 1928, details the sell-out of the company to the Jervian Corporation.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1185499">The Hygienic Ice and Cold Storage Company Minute Book
<unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1928
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
 
