<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY lost SYSTEM "http://www.lva.virginia.gov/whatwehave/local/lost/" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi03382">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03382::A Guide to the Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1831-1946)//EN" "vi03382.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date>1831-1946</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1831-1946
<num type="barcodenumbers">0007310622-0007310624
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Laura Travis
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2012 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Laura Travis, <date>10 January 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date>1831-1946</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers: ">0007310622-0007310624
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Laura Travis
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library of Virginia staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1831-1946
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">0007310622-0007310624
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1.35 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Page County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Page County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1831-1946. Local government records collection, Page County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, VA 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court records from Page County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Page County  was named according to most sources, for John Page, revolutionary patriot, congressman, and governor of Virginia from 1802 to 1805. It was formed from Rockingham and Shenandoah counties in 1831. 
</p>
<p>The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance.  The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death.  Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve.  Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six.  The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses.  The coroner was required to write down witness testimony.  After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition.  After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death.  He could require physicians to assist him with determing cause of death.  If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the Coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Page County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1831-1946, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance.  Causes of death found in coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God.  Documents commonly found in coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons.  Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions.  Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death.  If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known.  If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence.  Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased.  Slaves were deponents in coroner investigations. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
</p>
</arrangement>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Page County (Va.) Circuit Court</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Coroners--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Death--Causes--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Infanticide--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder victims--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Page County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Page County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Suicide--Virginia--Page County</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women--Virginia--Page County</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Page County (Va.)--History</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records--Virginia--Page County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Page County</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports--Virginia--Page County</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest 
</head><c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1842 February 25, Death of John Wesley Bell: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Feloniously killed and murdered by Martin and Captain (slaves of John Bell). They hit him with a heavy object behind the right ear producing extensive fracture of the bones in the area and violent contusion of the soft parts. Then, they threw him in the Shenandoah River a short distance from where he was found. Martin and Captain were indicted for murder. One was believed to be the actual killer, while the other was "aiding and abetting."
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1880 March 16, Deaths of Willie Hilliard and Allison Jackson:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Jackson took Willie Hilliard, age 3, with him and later the child was found dead. He died from strangulation by drowning. Alison Jackson, black, was charged with the willful murder of the child and taken into custody. Mr. Lucas testified that before he could return with the papers a mob (75-100 men), had taken Jackson from the guards in whose keeping he was, and hung him to a gum sappling where he was found hanging dead the next morning. A Mr. Mace testified the mob were both black and white men, he thought.     
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1886 November 11, Death of Unnamed infant of Eaevard and Milly Williams:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to its death from exhaustion due to loss of blood from an improperly tied umbilical cord, as well as the manner in which the supernumerary (extra) fingers were amputated by Eliza Clarke. Clarke was the midwife in attendance for the birth. Clarke testified that she "did the best she knew how, and tied the navel after the child was born." She also stated that, "Ed [father of the child] wanted me to go and cut the extra fingers off the baby". She told him, "Ed, the baby is all right." He said, "No, I want you to go on up and cut them fingers off- I don't want them on there." He said, "Take the scissors and cut them off." She then stated, "I took the scissors and cut them off; they did not bleed at first and I thought there was no blood in them. I washed and dressed the baby at that time and the navel had not bled any then."     
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1905 February 26, Death of Henry Henderson:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to his death by drowning in the Shenandoah River after having been pursued by Harry Keyser. John  Callary testified that, "Miss Malone and Maudie were on the porch and they said they are running a Negro. They are taking him off the railroad, and bringing him down the County Road." She said, "get up and go out and stop those boys or they will kill that Negro."  "I then went out and up toward the County Road, thinking I would stop the boys from bothering the Negro. My wife came and said the Negro had drowned, and that I had better go out and get the names of the boys. I took their names."     
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1917 August 28, Death of Bessie Ford:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to her death from causes unknown. Bessie Smith was struck by her husband and "knocked senseless for five minutes." She then complained of her head hurting her. Dr. George Long testified that he did not think the blow from her husband caused her death but may have hastened it since she had been weak from an influence of diseases.       
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1933 October 20, Death of Mrs. Ashby Lee Algers:   
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to her death from acute indigestion. Her husband, Mr. Algers testified that his wife had been at her sister's, Mrs. Turner's, peeling pears to make a couple of gallons of preserves. When she returned later, she became "right ill." She had indigestion from eating sweet potatoes and some pears. Mr. Algers offered to call a doctor, but she shook her head, as it was four of five miles away to a phone. He went to her sister's house to tell her that his wife was very ill and he did not expect her to live. She refused to come, and said "If she dies, you killed her." Mrs. Turner confirmed in her testimony that is what she said.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1933 April 11, Death of T.O. Kibler:    
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Suicide. Mrs. Kibler and her grandson returned home to find Mr. Kibler sitting with a muzzle toward the back of a shed with his head bleeding. A note was found written and signed by him saying he was taking his life. The suicide note, written on the back of an old envelope, is included in inquisition. The note states, "I done it. Am no good. Will get out of the way. All I want is a old box. Times are hard. No 'preching.'" It is signed "T.O. Kibler"
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1934 January 26, Death of Louise Cubbage:    
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to her death by a gunshot wound inflicted upon her by Robert Alger. Alger was under the accountable age for crime (under age 7). When questioned why he shot her, Robert stated, "he didn't like Louise and did not want her to come over to get his 'eatings'."
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1936 September 14, Death of Ambrose Good:    
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Came to his death from burns received in an accidental explosion. Good and some friends went to a dance hall in Luray. On the way back, they ran out of gas. They were able to walk to a store to get some gas. When they returned, Good was putting the gas in the car, and since it was dark Daniel Lewis struck a match. Good said, "don't do that; it is dangerous." Lewis struck the match again anyway, and Good's clothes caught fire. He was burned to death.  When asked if they had been drinking, Carl Davis answered, "yes, we had about three pints." 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1946 June 19, Death of Roy Joseph Sturgeon:    
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Died in a plane crash at a spot on the side of a mountain called, "The Devil's Tan Yard or Raccoon's Head." He was piloting a plane from Norfolk, Virginia to Reedsburg, Wisconsin. The crash was attributed to heavy fog on the mountain.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>