<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="Vi03316">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::Vi 03316::A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1994-1998)//EN" "Vi 03316.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Administration, Correspondence and Subject Files, <date>1994-1998</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">Administration, Virginia Secretary of, Correspondence and Subject Files
<num type="collectionnumber">35870
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Erin Faison
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;

<date type="publication">&copy; 2012  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 


<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from created in EAD by Erin Faison, <date>02 April 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, <date>1994-1998</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">35870
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Erin Faison
</author>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2012 
</date> &contact;

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Erin Faison
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>


<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1994-1998
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">35870
</unitid>
<physloc label="">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia. Secretary of Transportation
</origination>
</did>


<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia Secretary of Administration, Correspondence and Subject Files, 1994-1998. Accession 35870, State Government Records Collection, Tha Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Accession 35870 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Administration, by Arlene Smith, on 19 June 1998, to the Library of Virginia for permanent retention.
</p>
</acqinfo>


<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>This collection has been processed using minimal processing standards: the original arrangement has been maintained, the container list is brief and simple, and the records have not been refoldered and fasteners have not been removed.</p>

<p> Material found loose in the boxes was foldered and given a title determined by the archivist. In cases where folder titles were inaccurate, the titles have been corrected to more adequately describe the material.
</p>
</processinfo>


</descgrp>


<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the chief executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. This system was inadequate. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.</p>
 <p>Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. The Office of Administration was made one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated. The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Currently, the Secretary of Administration is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Charitable Gaming, Compensation Board, State Board of Elections, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Public Broadcasting Board, and the Department of Veterans Services.</p>
 <p>T. Edward Temple, the first Secretary of Administration, announced in August 1973 that he was leaving state service effective January 1974. In December 1973, Governor-elect Mills E. Godwin, Jr., announced the appointment of Maurice B. Rowe, III, as Secretary of Administration. Rowe had served as Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Holton administration. On July 1, 1976, the secretariates of administration and finance were combined. Rowe served until the end of the Godwin administration in January 1978 when he became Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Dalton administration. In December 1977 Governor-elect John N. Dalton picked Charles B. Walker, the state comptroller, as Secretary of Administration and Finance. The office wielded great influence and authority under Walker who was known as the "Little Governor". Walker resigned in June 1981 to become a vice-president for Ethyl Corporation. Stuary Connock, state budget and planning director, served as Secretary of Administration and Finance until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. </p>
<p> Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Wayne F. Anderson, a former Alexandria city manager, Secretary of Administration and Finance. Anderson announced his resignation in May 1984 to join the faculty of George Mason University. His resignation was prompted by a cabinet reorganization to take effect on July 1, 1984 which divided the Secretary of Administration and Finance into separate secretariats and combined the secretariats of transportation and public safety. Governor Robb appointed Secretary of Transportation Andrew B. Fogarty as new Secretary of Administration. Fogarty served until June 1985 when he became Sectretary of Transportation and Public Safety following the resignation of Franklin E. White. David K. McCloud, Robb's chief of staff, assumed the duties of Secretary of Administration for the remainder of Robb's term. </p>
 <p>In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles chose Carolyn J. Moss, head of the Office of Minority Business Enterprise under Governor Robb, as Secretary of Administration. Moss served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. Governor-elect L. Douglas Wilder appointed Ruby G. Martin, a Richmond attorney, as Secretary of Administration. In January 1994 Governor-elect George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed his campaign manager, Michael E. Thomas, Secretary of Administration. Thomas served until the end of Allen's term in January 1998. Governor James S. Gilmore appointed Thomas Deputy Secretary of Technology in August 1998. In January 1998 Governor-elect James S. Gilmore III named G. Bryan Slater as Secretary of Administration. Slater also served as Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff. He worked on Gilmore's campaign for attorney general in 1993 and served as his director of administration when Gilmore was Virginia Attorney General (1994-1997). Slater resigned in March 2001 to work for the Republican National Committee which Gilmore chaired. He was replaced by his deputy, Donald L. Moseley who served until the end of the Gilmore administration in January 2002.</p> 
 <p>Governor-elect Mark R. Warner selected Sandra Bowen as Secretary of Administration in January 2002. Bowen had previously served as Special Assistant to Governor Charles S. Robb, and as Secretary of the Commonwealth during the administration of Governor Gerald L. Baliles. She was also the Director of Gubernatorial Transition between the Robb and Baliles administrations. Secretary Bowen served under Governor Warner for his entire term, and was replaced in 2006 when Governor-elect Timothy Kaine selected Viola Baskerville as his Secretary of Administration.
</p>
</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of: Correspondence with Secretary of Administration Agencies, Governor's Working Papers, Correspondence with other Secretariats, Subject Files, General Assembly and Legislative Studies.
</p>
</scopecontent>


<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
<list type="simple"><item>Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files</item></list></arrangement>

<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1994-1998</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>


<container label="Boxes" type="box">1-2
</container>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: 2 cu. ft (2 boxes).</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>

<arrangement>
<p>The originial arrangement of the organization has been maintained.
</p>
</arrangement>


	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Charitable Gaming Commission, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1996</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Charitable Gaming Commission - Spring NAGRA Conference, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1995</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Commonwealth Competition Council, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Compensation Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Elections, State Board of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1996</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Employee Relations Counselors, Department of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - Capitol Outlay, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">8
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General  Services, Department of - Real Property Issues, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - Chesapeake Builders and DMV Lease, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">10
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - (DPS Miscellaneous), 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">11
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - (DPS Travel Policy), 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">12
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Services, Department of - Division of Risk Management, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">13
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Human Rights, Council on, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">14
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Information Management, Council on, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Information Management, Council on - VIPNet, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Information Technology, Department of - Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">17
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Information Technology, Department of - Virginia Public Broadcasting Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">18
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Information Technology, Department of - E-Mail Capabilities, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">19-22
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Local Government, Commission on - Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">23
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Local Government, Commission on - Assessment of Mandates on Local Government, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">24-25
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">26
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Combined Virginia Campaign, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">27
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Classification and Compensation, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">28
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Fair Labor Standards Act, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">29
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Trainging, Department of - Health Insurance Premium, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1999</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">28
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Medical Savings Account, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">29
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Personnel and Training, Department of - Virginia Executive Institute and Commonwealth Management Institute, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">30
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Veterans Affairs, Department of - Virginia Veterans Care Center, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">31
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Veterans Affairs, Department of - Virginia Veterans Cemetery, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">32
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Governor's Working Papers - Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1996</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">33
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Commerce and Trade, Secretary of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Education, Secretary of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Education, Secretary of - Higher Education Decentralization, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Health and Human Resources, Secretary of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Natural Resources, Secretry of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Natural Resources, Secretry of - Enviromental Impact Reports Approvals, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1997</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5-8
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Public Safety, Secretary of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">9
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Transportation, Secretary of, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">10
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Virginia Liason Office, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">11
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Virginia Retirement System, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">12
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>African Trade Office Trip, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">13
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Commonwealth Competition Council, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">14
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Congressional Delegation Briefing, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">15
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Decision Brief, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">16
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>ESOP, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1997</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">17
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Executive Order - Memorandum, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">18
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Intellectual Property, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">19
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Intellectual Property - Requests from Agencies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">20
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memorandum to Agency Heads, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">21
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memorandum to Governor's Cabinet, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">22
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memorandum to Governor's Office, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">23
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">24
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Phone Bill, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">25
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Presentation by Michael E. Thomas - Speeches, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">26
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Surplus Property, Governor's Commission on, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">27
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Travel - General Study, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">28
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Travel - Vehicles Study, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">29
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Utility Audit, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">30
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Legislative Studies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1997</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">31
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Legislative Studies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1996</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">32
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Legislative Studies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1994-1995</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">33
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Assembly - Development of Legislation, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1998</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">34
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Assembly - Regular and Veto Sessions, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1997</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">35
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Assembly - Review of Agency Submissions, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1996</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">36-37
	</container>
	</did></c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>General Assembly, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1995</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">2
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">38
	</container>
	</did></c02>


	
	
	



















	




</c01>



</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>