<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi03451">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03451::A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1818-1839)//EN" "vi03451.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, <date>1818-1839</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions
<num type="barcodenumber">0007845048
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2012  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record by Greg Crawford, <date>17 February 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, <date>1818-1839</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2012 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Eddie Woodward; McKenzie Long
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Albemarle (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1818-1839
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007845048
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.45 cu. ft. (1 box)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1818-1839. Local government records collection, Albemarle County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Albemarle County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1818-1839 were removed from the Albemarle County Court papers and processed by Eddie Woodward. Declarations filed by former soldiers rather than their widows and heirs, ranging from 1818 to 1833, were reprocessed and indexed as a distinct unit by McKenzie Long.
</p>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: February 2012; updated by M. Long: December 2023.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:</title> In 1818, Congress passed the first of three major Revolutionary War pension acts. The act granted lifetime pensions to all men who had served as regular army soldiers in the Continental Line and who could demonstrate financial need. Prior to the passage of this act, pensions had been restricted to former soldiers who were no longer able to support themselves due to injuries sustained while in service. The second act, passed by Congress in 1820, required applicants to provide more concrete evidence of this financial need in the form of a certified inventory of his property and income. They also had to include an account of all members of the applicant's family, including their health and ability to contribute to household income. In 1832, the third act extended pension benefits to include soldiers who had served in the state troops or militia. Congress also passed a related act in 1836 granting pensions to the widows and orphans of Revolutionary War veterans.
</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle, and governor of Virginia from 1737 to 1754. It was created by a statute of 1744 and formed from Goochland County; part of Louisa County was added in 1761 and islands in the Fluvanna (now the James) River in 1770. The court met for the first time on 8 February 1745. The county seat is the city of Charlottesville.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Lost Locality Note: </title> Albemarle is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. All order books except the first and many loose papers between 1748 and 1781 were destroyed by British general Banastre Tarleton’s raid on Charlottesville in 1781 during the Revolutionary War.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Albemarle County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1818-1839 primarily record the declarations of individuals seeking to obtain Revolutionary War pensions provided by various acts of Congress. The applicants present detailed testimony of their time of service during the Revolutionary War. Information found in the Declarations include date and location applicants entered into service, names of military companies they served in, names of military commanders they served under, names of fellow soldiers they served with, length of service, their age, and their place of birth. The predominant portion of the declarations are narratives of their tours of duty during the Revolutionary War with emphasis on battles they fought. The declarations also include affidavits from witnesses who could verify information provided by applicants.
</p>
<p>Significant materials in this collection include the pension declarations of two free Black soldiers, Richard Spinner and Sherard Goin. Other notable trends include records related to a military movement referred to as "Lafayette's Wild Goose Chase," soldiers who became ill during the war and suffered from lifelong symptoms as a result, the hiring of substitutes to cover mandatory militia service, and a substantial number of men who were engaged in service at the prisoner-of-war camp known as the Albemarle Barracks.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Albemarle County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
<p>Albemarle is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Albemarle Records may be found in the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available on the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1818-1839</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.45 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007845048 ">		Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1818-1839	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>