<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03052">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03052::A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Society Ledger, 1875-1882)//EN" "vi03052.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Society Ledger, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1882</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Ledger, 1875-1882
<num type="collectionnumber">Barcode numbers 1108247 and 1108250/Henrico County (Va.) Microfilm Reel 213
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Callie Lou Freed, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">05 June 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Society Ledger, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1882</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection numbers:">Barcode numbers 1108247 and 1108250/Henrico County (Va.) Microfilm Reel 213
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Library of Virginia staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Society Ledger, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1882
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">Barcode numbers 1108247 and 1108250/Henrico County (Va.) Reel 213
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">State Records Center - Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 v. (215 p.); 1 microfilm reel 
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Use microfilm copy, Henrico County (Va.) Reel 213.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary  Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid Society Ledger, 1875-1882.  Henrico County (Va.) Reel 213, Local government records collection, Henrico County Court Records.  The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These volumes came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of papers from Henrico County.
</p>
        <p>Microfilm Reel 213 was generated by the staff of OCLC while filming at the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Henrico County was one of the eight original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634.  The county was named for Henry, Prince of Wales, eldest son of James I.
</p>
      <p>Historically, after Emancipation, African Americans established separate congregations and church facilities to create their own communities and worhip in their own culturally distinct ways. African American churches have long been the centers of communities, serving as schools in the early years after the Civil War and taking up social welfare functions, such as providing for the indigent. The Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church was organized in March 1875 by members of the 2nd Baptist Church. The church was organized to give facilities to a section known as "Sheep Hill." Now known as the Carver neighborhood, it became a thriving black community and is now part of the Greater Richmond area.
</p>
      <p>On March 17th 1875, church deacons purchased an old soap factory consisting of three buildings on a lot on Moore Street. The center building was used as a church. The church was dedicated on April 18, 1875 and the congregation was officially recognized. The first pastor Rev. William Troy, 1875-1881, was a student at the Virginia Union Theological Seminary. In 1878, elaborate improvements were made to the building including galleries. In 1878, the deacons decided to run an industrial school in connection with the church and in April 1880, two-thirds of the church property was deeded to the Moore Street Industrial School. The school was a community response to the needs of African American children.
</p>
      <p>The transference of the deed of the property from the church to the school caused the congregation trouble and resulted in a long suit which was finally settled in favor of the church. The property was returned to the church in 1901. The noise of the nearby railways caused the congregation to move to their present site. The church was dedicated on May 31, 1908. The Ministers' Aid Society was funded by a fee paying membership. The organization combined church and charity--providing aid and helping people adjust to and deal with the demands of life through religion.
</p>
      <p>The minute book and ledger were used as evidence in the chancery case, Charles J. Clarke and others versus John Oliver and others and John W. Williams versus Coleman Smith, trustee, and others, heard in the Circuit Court of Henrico County.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Henrico County (Va.) Moore Street Missionary Baptist Church Minute Book and Ministers' Aid  Society Ledger, 1875-1882, includes a Minute Book, 1875-1881, that contains a handwritten index in the front. The volume records the meetings with the church moderator and clerk about church business. In addition, the volume includes financial information such as bills due, subscriptions, the pastor's salary, the expenses paid, the collections received, a list of deceased members, names of the church sisters and a list of new members. Loose papers, dating from 1887 and 1888, are found between pages 21 and 22. These papers refer to the industrial school found on the church grounds. There are 156 pages in this volume.
</p>
      <p>The Ministers' Aid Society Ledger,1881-1882, contains a handwritten index in the front. The ledger notes the officers and the members of the society. The volume also records minutes as well as financial records--such as subscribers, bills paid and debts and church income.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>For additional information see the Henrico County Chancery Cause, Charles J. Clarke and others versus John Oliver and others and John W. Williams versus Coleman Smith, trustee, and others. It can be found in the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm">Chancery Records Index</extref> at the Library of Virginia web site. The index number is 1896-053.
</p>
        <p>Henrico County is one of Virginia's Lost Record Localities.  Additional Henrico County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.
</p>
        <p>For more information and a listing of lost records localities see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/guides/rn30_lostrecords.pdf">Lost Records research note</extref>. 
</p>
        <p>For a history of African American Baptist churches, consult the "Inventory of the Church Archives of Virginia: Negro Baptist Churches in Richmond," Historical Records Survey of Virginia, Work Projects Administration, June 1940.
</p>
        <p>These volumes are located at the State Records Center.  Contact Archives Research Services for access information, directions and hours.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African American Baptists--Virginia--Henrico County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African American churches--Virginia--Henrico County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History--1863-1877.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History--1877-1964.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--Virginia--Henrico County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Fraternal organizations--Virginia--Henrico County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Henrico County (Va.)--History--19th century.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Financial records--Virginia--Henrico County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Ledgers (account books)--Virginia--Henrico County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Henrico County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Minute books--Virginia--Henrico County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Organization records--Virginia--Henrico County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
