<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03242">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03242::A Guide to the Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-1899)//EN" "vi03242.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1795-1899</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-1899
<num type="collectionnumber">Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-001-1899-081
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2020 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">05 August 2020</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1795-1899</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-001-1899-081
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2020
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field processing and LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1795-1899
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-001-1899-081 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Grayson County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Grayson County  (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-1899. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Grayson County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Grayson County was named for William Grayson, a delegate to the Continental Congress from 1784 to 1787 and one of the first two United States senators from Virginia. It was formed from Wythe County by a statute adopted on 7 November 1792. The county court first met on 21 May 1793. A portion of Patrick County was added in 1810. The county seat is Independence.
</p>
       </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Grayson County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1795-1899, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Grayson County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>      
      </relatedmaterial>
     </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Grayson County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
	<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Grayson County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Grayson County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Grayson County (Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Grayson County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
 <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
    
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1808-005: Stephen Jones vs Frederick Yost:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Jones complains that Yost offered to sell him a still but twice failed to follow through. The peaches, Jones picked for peach brandy in anticipation of having a still delivered by Yost, would have rotted had he not rented a still in desperation and at a very extravagant price to complete production rather than lose the harvest.  
  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1811-005: Frederick Idle vs. Philip Gaines:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause references a freedom suit filed by an enslaved woman named Hagar against Philip Gaines. The cause was appealed to the Superior Court of Chancery in Staunton. See Augusta County Chancery Cause 1815-030 available on the Chancery Records Index. Add info to Augusta County suits of interest.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1839-009: Isaac Parson, etc. vs. Waughs and Co.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included with this cause is Alfred Cornutt's Petition for Habeas Corpus for the return of his wife Elizabeth from the home of her mother, Rebecca Russell. Mrs. Russell refused to allow his wife and child to return to his home. Mr. Cornutt and his wife Elizabeth Russell, daughter of Philp and Rebecca Russell, were married April 9, 1837. Mr. Cornutt took his wife to her parents on June 24, 1837 for a visit with them. Mr. Russell decided she should not return home and threaten to kill Mr. Cornutt. Mr. Russell also refused to allow Mr. Cornutt to see his son, who was born after Mrs. Russell went to visit her parents, and continued to keep the couple separated until his death in 1839. Afterwards, Mrs. Russell refused to allow Mr. Cornett to bring his wife and son home and also threaten him with "great personal violence."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1863-001: James Dickey vs. Jesse A. Reeves
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mr. Reeves sold Mr. Dickey interest in the minerals at the mouth of Bruth Creek. Mr. Dickey though he was buying part of a silver mine.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1864-001: May Morgan vs Caroline Morgan: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>May Morgan married Caroline Hall in March 1861. Soon after their marriage, Mr. Morgan became a soldier in the Confederate Army and was absent more than twelve months. On February 14, 1864, Mrs. Morgan gave birth to a male child by another man. Mr. Morgan sued for divorce. Mrs. Morgan gave an answer to the Bill telling her experiences doing the Civil War. Included in this suit is a deposition dated 28 September 1863, of a male prisoner in the Jail complaining that he was suffering with the cold. He was asking for bedding to keep him warm.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-008: Heir(s) of David Cornutt vs Reuben Cornutt: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Reuben Cornutt moved to his father's home to avoid getting small pox which was infecting people along Elk Creek.  Reuben's siblings and in-laws accuse him of taking advantage of his father David Cornutt to get land from him. Many of the people giving depositions for this cause lived out of state.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-015: Mathew Dickey and wife vs Joseph Cox and wife, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This cause concerns the division of the land and enslaved people of Alexander Phipps among his children. Found in this cause is a letter dated April 27, 1870 from the Virginia Senate Chamber by John M. Davis to his brother.  He recounts the events when the floor of the Courts of Appeal gave way and fell into the Hall of the House of Delegates below it. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-020: Harvy Carrico vs. Alfred Carrico etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>  William Carrico and his wife Martha were separated. His son Harvy claimed his father gave him a tract of land to support of Harvy's mother, Martha Carrico. On December 28, 1854, William Carrico married Elesay (Louisa) Forkner (Fortner) in Grayson County, Virginia. He claimed to be a widower and she claimed to be a widow. He was born in Grayson County and she was born in Surry County, North Carolina. According to the deposition of Hardin Hickman, Louisa Forkner was the wife of Jefferson Forkner who moved from North Carolina to Missouri and afterwards to the Kansas Territory. Mr. Hickman last heard from Jefferson Forkner in November 1857. Joseph Parker's deposition states that Jefferson Forkner sold his wife, Louisa to William Carico for five dollars and gave him a bill of sale for her. Mr. Parker was a witness to the bill of sale. Mr. Carico then took Louisa to Grayson County to live. Jessee Riggs' deposition stated that he attended the marriage of Jefferson Forkner and Louisa Parker in 1835 at the house of Squire Jarvis in Surry County, North Carolina. There are other depositions included in this Chancery Cause that give more information about Mrs. Martha Carrico, Jefferson Forkner, William Carrico, and Mrs. Forkner Carrico's children.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
  <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1871-042: Adms. of John Long vs. Martin Van Buren Long, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This cause contains nine letters written between July 30, 1861 and October 6, 1861. Mr. Long, a solder in the Confederate Army, wrote to his wife and other family members telling them about his war experiences during that time.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1874-017: David Sexton vs Adms of A.B. McMillan etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>On March 3, 1865, A. B. McMillan sold David Sexton an enslaved woman named Violet and her children Ann, Linda, Franky, and Vina for 600 dollars. In August 1870, Mr. McMillan's administrators sued Mr. Sexton and Peyton G. Hale his security of his bond, for the 600 dollars. Mr. Sexton claimed since the enslaved people were free, he did not owe the money.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1877-021: Rosa Smith VS Kimbrough Smith.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rosa Smith was the daughter of William Rankin by his second wife. Kimbrough Smith was the grandson of William Rankin. Kimbrough's mother was the daughter of Mr. Rankin by his first wife. Rosa wanted a divorce based on the Virginia Statute that says an aunt cannot marry her nephew.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1899-072: Thomas Phipps, etc. vs J.P. Gore, etc:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The cause concerned dispute between the parties over a reward offered for the arrest and delivery to the jailor of Grayson County of one Lee N. Hash for the killing of plaintiff's son. Hash was captured in North Carolina.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>

          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
