<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03354">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03354::A Guide to the Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1779-1927)//EN" "vi03354.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779-1927</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1779-1927
<num type="collectionnumber">1016883, 0007286612
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Bari Helms
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Bari Helms, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 September 2011</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779-1927</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers:">1016883, 0007286612
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Bari Helms
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Bari Helms
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779-1927
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">1016883, 0007286612
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">.50 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Frederick County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Frederick County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1779-1927. Local government records collection, Frederick County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, VA 23219. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court records from Frederick County.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Frederick County was named for Frederick Louis, Prince of Wales and eldest son of George II.  It was formed from Orange County in 1738, but the county government was not organized until 1743.  Part of Augusta County was added later.  Its area is 426 square miles, and the county seat is Winchester.
</p>
      <p>The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance. The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death. Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve. Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six. The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses. The coroner was required to write down witness testimony. After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition. After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death. He could require physicians to assist him with determining cause of death. If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Frederick County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1779-1927, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance. Causes of death found in coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God. Documents commonly found in coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons. Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions. Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death. If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known. If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence. Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased. Slaves were occasionally deponents in coroner investigations. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Frederick County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Coroners--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Death--Causes--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Infanticide--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder victims--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Suicide--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women--Virginia--Frederick County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Frederick County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records--Virginia--Frederick County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Frederick County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports--Virginia--Frederick County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1801 Nov. 24, Death of Yender:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Yender, a distiller, was murdered by repeated strokes to the head supposedly inflicted by "two Mulatto persons namely William Weller Taylor and George Weller Taylor."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1807 March 2, Death of Catherine Gregory:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>"She not having God before her eyes, but being moved by the instigation of Devil, had drank whiskey to extreme intoxication, fell into the fire, and was by it burned to death."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1808 Aug. 25, Death of William Whittenton/Whittington:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>While interfering in a dispute between his wife and slave Flora, the property of Nathaniel Jackson, Whittenton was struck in the head and stomach with a club by Flora. Includes testimony from his wife who claims that Flora stated that "she had long owed him a spite, that he was always going at her like a dog at a opossum that she intended to kill him, and was ready to be hung tomorrow for doing so."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1809 June 3, Death of Alexander (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>John Thompson "being in liquor was making sport and trifling with the said Negroe and with a piece of a board gave the said negroe a stroke on the side of the head" which "against his will, and therefore casually and by misfortune" did kill Alexander. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1809 June 28, Death of infant child of Patty (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The infant's mother Patty, a slaved owned by Ben Powel, struck the child's skull with a stone and "did break and pierce so as to occasion its death."  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1812 Feb. 25, Death of Peter (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Slave Peter, owned by his free mother Sarah, was killed by a blow to the head with a stick resulting from an altercation with slave Jack owned by William Taylor.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1813 May 3, Death of Fanny Smith: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cut herself in the neck with a razor after having been much "distressed in mind" over the loss of three of her children.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1814 Aug. 17, Death of George Copenhaver: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>It was concluded that "Sgt. John Breedlowe was a principle cause of his death" while he was under guard as a deserter. Includes testimony from other soldiers.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1814 Sept. 5, Death of Bob (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Slave Bob, owned by John Wilson of Kentucky, died from fatigue by traveling in the heat of the day and by drinking water being at the same time overheated.    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1819 Sept. 18, Death of James Hunter: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Assaulted by person unknown, "supposed to be a coloured man named Jerry," who made "many mortal wounds" and left his body "horribly mangled."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1826 June 11, Death of Richmond (slave):   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The slave of Mrs. Bushrod Taylor died "by providential visitation" which caused him to drown by either being "strangled with the water" or being "seized with a sudden spasm." 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1829 May 15, Death of Cain (slave):  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cain drowned while endeavoring to escape his pursuers who were trying to apprehend him upon a charge of theft.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1830 March 22, Death of Unknown: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The parts of a human body found were discovered to be "remains of a subject buried there by Dr. Stephens after dissection of a dead body not known to him." 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1832 Sept. 17, Death of Ambrose (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ambrose was hired out to Jacob McCoy and was engaged in thrashing rye when he was reprimanded by McCoy who struck him several times in the faces with his open hand and caused him to fall to the barn floor. The examination of the body showed no signs of violence except for a mall cut to the upper lip and a contusion on the left eye. Death was determined to be a case of chance "occurring without any design or intention."  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1833 Sept. 19, Death of Lucy (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Earlier on the day of her death, Lucy had been whipped, mostly about the thighs, by her master as punishment for stealing some "trifling article" from a neighbor. While working over the fire she fainted from "exertion or sickness from the fire and whipping" and struck her head on the hearth. It was determined that the whipping and fall were the cause of her death but that there was "no intention to kill on the part of her master."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1834 April 3, Death of Joe (slave): 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The slave of Philip T. Burwell was killed by a "blow given him on the head by a stone thrown at him by a certain yellow man slave called George Quickly said to be the property of the estate of Col. N. Burwell." Includes testimony from other slaves.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1842 Aug. 23, Death of Jesse Spence: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Free African American Jesse Spence died from wounds "inflicted by the hands and feet of a certain negro man slave" W. Singleton.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1851 March 8, Death of John Griffitte: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Died "from drunkenness and exposure by laying out in a pool of water during the night and in a snow storm."    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1852 July 29, Death of Bob Massie: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death "by a blow with a stone thrown at him by John Bracus a free man of colour."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1854 May 1, Death of Westly Dunmore:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death caused "by a fit produced by long habits of intemperance."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868 Feb. 15, Death of Charles Brooks:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death caused by "accidentally falling through the mill where he is supposed to have frozen."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868 Feb. 28, Death of Hunter Robinson: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death by a blow to the head with a fist inflicted by his uncle Robert Webb. Incident took place at school and includes depositions. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868 Dec. 21, Death of Julia Nevel: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Died of "child bed fever" resulting from an abortion.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1888 March 23, Death of William and Maria McClure: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Murder/suicide. Maria McClure died of a blow to the head with a poker and a razor cut across the right jugular inflicted by William McClure. William died of a self-inflicted gunshot to the head.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889 March 9, Death of infant child of Mary McCormack: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause of death not given but inquest includes testimony describing how the infant was found shoved in a washstand. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1913 April 17, Death of Vernon W. Hausenfluck: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death caused by being struck by a smoke stack of the M. J. Grove Lime Co. that was pulled from its place by a car of the Baltimore &amp; Ohio Railroad striking a supporting guy wire.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1915 Aug. 21, Death of John W. Brown: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death by two gunshots inflicted by William J. B. Brown, who "lay in wait concealed near where said body was buried having previously determined in his mind to kill said John W. Brown."    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
