<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03762">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi03762::A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926)//EN" "vi03762.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1784-1926</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926
<num type="collectionnumber">0007396693
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Bari Helms
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2012 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Bari Helms, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 November 2012</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1784-1926</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number:">0007396693
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Bari Helms
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Bari Helms
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1784-1926
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007396693
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926. Local government records collection, Isle of Wight County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Isle of Wight County. 
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Isle of Wight County was most likely named for the Isle of Wight off the south coast of England.  It was first known as Warrosquyoake and was one of the eight shires established in 1634.  The present name was given in 1637.  Part of Nansemond County was added in 1769.  Its area is 319 square miles, and the county seat is Isle of Wight.
</p>
      <p>The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance. The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death. Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve. Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six. The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses. The coroner was required to write down witness testimony. After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition. After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death. He could require physicians to assist him with determining cause of death. If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Isle of Wight County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance. Causes of death found in coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God. Documents commonly found in coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons. Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions. Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death. If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known. If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence. Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased. Slaves were occasionally deponents in coroner investigations.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Coroners--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Death--Causes--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free African Americans--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Infanticide--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Murder victims--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaveholders--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Suicide--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Isle of Wight County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Death records--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Reports--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1784 June 19, Death of Jane Womble:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>A pregnant Jane Womble and her four children (Samson, Richard, Loyd, and Cary) were murdered by her husband, Mathen Womble, who struck them about the head and neck with an axe. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1805 April 18, Death of Peter (slave):   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Peter, a slave owned by Thomas Smith, was stabbed in the stomach by Isham, a slave owned by Emanuel Wills, after a game of "five corns."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1816 January 3, Death of Natt Herring: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Joe, a slave owned by Allen Fulgham, struck Herring in the neck with a stick, killing him instantly. Joe was found guilty of manslaughter in the criminal courts 5 February 1818 and sentenced to 39 lashes.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1827 September 13, Death of Unknown Infant:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Female infant's death found to be from unknown causes, but the jury believed it probably the infant's death was caused by "some improper conduct" of its mother Airy, a slave owned by Rebecca Jones, who buried the infant in a "secret manner." The jury found it equally probably that the infant's death was caused by Airy's fall down some stairs a few days before the infant's birth.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1829 April 6, Death of Unknown Infant:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Male infant died by the "inhumane conduct of its mother" Judea, a slave owned by John Womble, who wrapped the infant in cloths and placed it in a closed wooden box.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1829 November 2, Death of Caroline: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The cause of death of Caroline, a former slave freed by the will of Joseph Cutchin, was unknown, the jury stated there was evidence before them that William Hall, with whom Caroline lived, tied and whipped Caroline and that thereafter she became ill and fell into a "stupor state" until her death. The jury found no marks of violence upon her body.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1831 March 7, Death of Unknown Infant: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Infant died from neglect and a broken skull after its mother Letitia Briggs, a free person, placed the infant on the ground and covered it with pieces of wood.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1831 November 7, Death of Milly King and Unknown Infant:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Milly King, a free person, was murdered by Wyat Johnson, another free Negro, who struck her in the head and neck with an ax. The blows caused King to fall from her chair onto her infant son, causing the infant's death.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1840 January 4, Death of James Turner:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>James Turner escaped from the Lunatic Hospital at Williamsburg, resisted arrest with a hatchet, and was shot by John S. Lattimere, who was attempting to arrest him.   
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844 March 14, Death of Ruben (slave):
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ruben, a slave owned by Jeremiah Delh, ran away from the possession of Henry Callcote with his hands tied with a rope. A month later his body was found floating in the waters of a mill pond with his hands still tied. Ruben was believed to have gone into the water of his own accord. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844 April 2, Death of Dawson Teamer:    
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Dawson Teamer, a Free Negro, assaulted and beat a Free Negro woman, Mary Rix, leaving on the land of Henry H. Womble. Upon hearing of the attack, Womble confronted Teamer and "threatened to correct him." Womble tied said Teamer with a rope who then escaped into a swamp. Womble pursued and was stabbed by Teamer several times. Womble, with the aid of Josiah Beal, gave Teamer 35 lashes and released him. Coroner believed Teamer died from the beating, which was ruled as self-defense. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1871 May, Death of Margaret Ann Elizabeth White:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause of death unspecified, but the coroner believed her death by "violence supposed to have been caused at the hands of Lucas W. White and Ann P., his wife," parents of Margaret White. Inquisition includes testimony from neighbors who witnessed the child crying in the yard and unable to stand with the father, Lucas White, stating to her, "...if you don't hush you blaimed infurnal [sic] bitch I will come and stamp your blaimed infurnal brains out."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1892 April 4, Death of Agnes A. Williams:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death ruled to be from premature labor caused by ill treatment from her husband, James Williams, and from subsequent exposure in fleeing from husband. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1896 November 10, Death of Lucinta Holloway and Sallie Owens: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Deaths ruled to be from unknown causes, but testimony from family members suggest that the women were poisoned by an unknown African American male, thought to go by the name Hill. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1905 November 22, Death of William Duck: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death ruled to be by "organic disease of the heart" includes a detailed description of the postmortem examination. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1906 May 17, Death of Chestine (alias Booty) Edwards: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause of death of the child Chestine Edwards ruled to be from ill treatment by his father Henry Edwards. Testimony of witnesses claimed to have seen Edwards beating his son and leaving him to hang by his ankles.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1908 August 19, Death of Bennett Woodson: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause of death ruled to be from a "lick" with some blunt instrument to the head by some unknown person. Inquisition includes lengthy testimony from witnesses, including a detailed description of the postmortem examination. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
