<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi03000">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04515:: A Guide to the Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874)//EN" "vi04515.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1793-1874</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Richmond County (Va.) Business Records
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sherri Bagley
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Sherri Bagley, <date> 18 September 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Richmond County (Va.) Business Records,<date>1793-1874</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: 
</label>
<item>Gregory Crawford 
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia 
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia 
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1793-1874
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia 
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>7 volumes </extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Richmond County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled. <emph render="bold">please check alternative form available heading for volumes that have been microfilmed.  Please use microfilm if available</emph>.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p> There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874. [include volume title].  Local government records collection, Richmond County Court Records.  The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Richmond County in 2004.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p> <emph render="bold"> Please see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA017"> Richmond County Microfilm </extref> index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.</emph></p>
<p>Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger, 1847-1852 is available as microfilm Richmond County (Va.) Reels 221 and 222 </p>
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.
</p>
<p>The records in this collection were processed at different times in 2004 by Gregory Crawford.  Efforts have been taken to identify chancery causes related to these business records as some of these records were used as evidence in court proceedings.
</p>
<p>Encoded by Sherri Bagley, September 2024</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information 
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph>Business Records, both volumes and loose records are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers.  These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners.  In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit.  These business records exhibit appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments.  These records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
</p> 
<p><emph render="bold">Lost Records Note:</emph> During the burning of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War, Richmond circuit court judge John A. Meredith led efforts to save the circuit court records found at the State Court House. Rescuers successfully removed all the papers that were necessary to pending suits and many of the order books, but all of the wills and deed books were lost. Records of the superior court and circuit superior court of law and chancery were also destroyed. Most of the pre-Civil War Hustings Court records exist.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph>Richmond County was named either for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for the late-seventeenth-century duke of Richmond.  It was formed from old Rappahannock County in 1692.  Its area is 193 square miles, and the county seat is Warsaw.  
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content 
</head>
<p>Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Richmond City (Va.).  Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, journals, letter book, minute books and subscription books.   
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I:  Glenn and Brother Daybook, 1849-1851</item>
<item>Series II: Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book, 1873-1874</item>
<item>Series III: Moody and Price Letter Book, 1793-1796</item>
<item>Series IV: Plummer and Tapscott Journal, 1812-1814</item>
<item>Series V: Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger, 1847-1852</item></list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also:  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02212.xml"> Richmond County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1748-1958</extref>
</p>
<p>Additional Richmond City (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm." </extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp> 
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Glenn and Brother Daybook,    
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1851  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia 
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Glenn and Brother was a general store that conducted business in Farnham Church, Richmond County, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century. One of the owners was Matthew Glenn, Jr. Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well.   
</p>

</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1122733">Glenn and Brother Daybook 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1851  
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book,  
<unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1874 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Mangorike Wharf Company was organized in 1873 in Richmond County, Virginia, for the purpose of building a wharf along the Rappahannock River.  
</p>

</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1122790">Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1874 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Moody and Price Letter Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1793-1796
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia 
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Moody and Price was a shipping company headquartered in the city of Richmond, Virginia, during the late eighteenth century. The letter book was perhaps used as an exhibit in a court case heard in Richmond County. Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1122784">Moody and Price Letter Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1793-1796
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV">Plummer and Tapscott Journal, 1812-1814  First National Bank Ledger,   
<unitdate type="inclusive">1812-1814
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Plummer and Tapscott was a general store that conducted business in Farnham Church, Richmond County, Virginia, during the early 19th century.  Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well.            
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1122729">Plummer and Tapscott Journal 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1812-1814 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series V">Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger,    
<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1852
</unitdate> 
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>3 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Robert B. Sydnor was a merchant who owned a general store in Richmond County, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century.      
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1099717">Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger
<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1852
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>





















































