<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04758">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04758::A Guide to the Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-1912)//EN" "vi04758.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866-1912</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-1912
<num type="collectionnumber">Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-001-1912-023
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2014 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 July 2014</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866-1912</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-001-1912-023
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Callie Lou Freed 
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866-1912
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-001-1912-023 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Stafford County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-1912. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Stafford County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Stafford County was named for the English county. It was formed from Westmoreland County in 1664. Part of King George County was added in 1777. The county seat is Stafford.
</p>
<p>Many pre–Civil War court records were lost to vandalism by Union troops during the Civil War. A few volumes that record deeds, court orders, and wills exist.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Stafford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1866-1912, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Stafford County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>Stafford County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Stafford County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.
</p>
        <p>For more information and a listing of lost records localities see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/guides/rn30_lostrecords.pdf">Lost Records research note</extref>. 
</p>
        <p>See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">The Chancery Records Index</extref> to find the chancery records of additional Virginia localities.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Stafford County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Stafford County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Stafford County(Va.)--History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Stafford County(Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Stafford County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-005 Exr of Thomas Towson v. Edward M. Henry and wife: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause deals with debt. Plaintiff maintains that in April 1862 soldiers broke into your orator's house and destroyed and carried away many of his valuable papers-among which was defendants' bond dated December 1861.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868-003 Henry Moore v. Withers Waller: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves dissolution of business. Fishing operation between plaintiff and defendant was ended by "hostilities" between the Southern States and the U.S. Government. Plaintiff returned to family and home in Maryland.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1869-008 Reuben S. Denny v. Lydia Brown Denny: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff is seeking a divorce from defendant. Plaintiff maintains that defendant became a "decided, earnest and fanatical enthusiast" According to the plaintiff, his fell prey to one of the "prevalent 'isms' of the times" probably abolitionism. The plaintiff provides the names of prominent abolitionists such as Wendell Philips and Parker Pillsbury whom his wife invited to their home. She came to neglect her household duties and her obligations as a wife finally ending in a violent and avowed aversion toward him. He had his wife placed in an insane asylum for observation. The couple were married in Connecticut and initially lived in Massachusetts. Defendant filed suit for divorce in Massachusetts citing adultery and cruelty. She then moved to New York where her mother resided. Eventually, plaintiff left Massachusetts for Virginia. Plaintiff works in a gold mine.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1872-006 John Taliaferro v. James W. Tolson, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendant had in his possession captured horses and mules and offered to sell them to plaintiff and another defendant who were in the Confederate Service and could get them through the Confederate lines. The Confederate Quartermaster captured the property and deemed it as part of the Army. Plaintiff argues that there is no judgment (debt) to be enforced.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1883-008 Jacquelin M. Meredith v. Cooper Manufacturing Co., etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff charges defendant with false representation. Also files injunction against trustee, Bryan, to restrain and enjoin him from selling property-steam sawmill. Cooper Manufacturing Company is a company dealing with engine building, mill furnishers and contractors. The company was founded in 1833 by brothers Elias and Charles. Today, known as Cooper Industries, it is an American-based global electrical products manufacturer. Suit contains wonderful company catalogue. Property referred to in deed is known as "Providence."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1884-007 William H. Campbell and wife v. Annie P. Cash by etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit deals with estate dispute. Contains excellent additional genealogical information concerning numerous heirs of William Ingle.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1887-007 James W. Ellington v. Admr of William Ellington,etc.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>William Ellington was a Confederate veteran. His claim, filed with the Southern Claims Commission, resulted in this estate dispute as well as one heard in Stafford County Chancery Causes 1890-006. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1888-002 George W. Skinker v. Charles J. Henry, etc.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The cause involves a contract dispute over land. The will of Samuel Skinker dated 1856 is included as an exhibit and contains the names of slaves he owned. He wants one slave named Willie to learn a trade and then be sent to freedom in Liberia when he is 22 years. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1888-012 Joseph Wine v. Catharine E. Wine:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves a divorce. Plaintiff moved with family from Ohio to Virginia during first year of Civil War. Seeks a divorce based on desertion and robbery "leaving him at the age of sixty odd years, an outcast in society, homeless… and almost friendless."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889-014 Admr of Louis E. Latham v. Wesley Honey, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit contains a great deal of genealogical material-including seven letters and a hand drawn genealogical chart. Suit involves an estate dispute with Honey family migrating to state of Ohio.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1894-007 Inez M. Green, etc. v. John H. Gray, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiffs seek injunction against defendant and others to restrain them from using the property as a hoop yard and request that a perpetual injunction be issued against using said lot for any private benefit or convenience. The plaintiffs in the suit are adjacent land owners to a lot belonging to the county of Stafford for the use of a "courthouse and prison." Exhibits include a survey of courthouse and prison lot as laid out in 1783.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1897-008 Oliver Watson and Exx. of Henry Souther, etc. v. Albert O. Mays, etc. and Oliver Watson and wife, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit deals with one of Stafford's most historic properties, Chatham. Watson's suit involves a contract dispute. One of Souther's suits involves the "Shaker" note-regarding the Shaker community of Pleasant Hill, KY. The suit refers to a case from Circuit Court of the United States for the District of Kentucky, Oliver Watson and Henry Souther v. Society of Shakers at Pleasant Hill, KY. Suit subjected the property of the society to a charge for the payment of a note. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1904-001 Widow of Hector C. William Mithoff, etc. v. Heirs of William Mithoff, jr and J. Gertrude Hyman Mithoff, gdn v. Widow of Hector C. William Mithoff, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit was originally heard and filed in Caroline County's Circuit Court. The widow of Hector C. William Mithoff moved to Louisiana, along with her daughter and son-in-law. Other heirs moved to Illinois. Mentions the farms owned by Hector Willaim Mithoff-"Hayfield" and "Meadow Hill", later home to Sectretariat in Caroline County and "Holly Wood" and "The Point" in Stafford County.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-018 Charles Strother, etc. v. Admr of John Baalam, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>John Baalam died without heirs leaving over 200 acres of land. The plaintiffs are former slaves claiming to be related to Balaam seeking a portion of his property. Numerous former slaves and descendants of former slaves are deponents in the suit. They offer testimony providing the names of a slave ancestors and former slave owners. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1911-004 Joseph M Goldsmith, etc. v. Marianna Karsten, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves contract dispute. Topics include mimmigration and property. Defendants in cause immigrated to Stafford County from Germany. Plat refers to part of Snowden.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
