<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi04554">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04554::A Guide to the First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) register, 1826-1905)//EN" "vi04554.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>

<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) register, <date>1826-1905</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle id="sort">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.), Register, 1826-1905
<num type="collectionnumber">51334
</num>
</subtitle>

<author>Jessica Tyree
</author>

</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

</publicationstmt>

</filedesc>


<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Jessica Tyree, <date>9 July 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>

</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) register, <date>1826-1905</date>
</titleproper>

<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">51334
</num>
</subtitle>

<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>

<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>

<date type="publication">2014 
</date>

<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Jessica Tyree
</item>
</defitem>
</list>

</titlepage>

</frontmatter>


<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) register, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1826-1905
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">51334
</unitid>

<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.44 cubic feet (125 inkjet prints of digital images of original volume)</extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>

<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.)
</origination>
</did>


<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Copies may be made for research purposes only. Permission to publish must be obtained by First Baptist Church, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) Register, 1826-1905. Accession 51334. Church records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loaned for duplication by First Baptist Church, Richmond, Virginia, 16 April 2014.
</p>
</acqinfo>


</descgrp>


<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The <corpname encodinganalog="110$a">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.)</corpname> was organized in June 1780 as the Richmond Baptist Church. It had 14 charter members, and was led by pastor Joshua Morris. According to the Church's website (accessed in 2014), it was the first church of any denomination to be organized in Richmond, and the first Baptist church organized in a Virginia city. In its early years, the church met in a building at Cary and Second Streets, later erecting a building at 14th and Broad Streets. In 1841 a majority of the church's white members departed to a new First Baptist Church building at 12th and Broad Streets. The African American members continued to meet in the original building, forming the First African Baptist Church. In 1928, the First Baptist Church moved to its current location at Monument Avenue and Boulevard.
</p>
</bioghist>


<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Register, 1826-1905, of the <corpname encodinganalog="110$a">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.)</corpname>, consists chiefly of an alphabetized list of church members with dates (when known, or when applicable) for when and how a given member was received and/or dismissed from the church. The major categories of dismissal, as explained at the beginning of the register, are a member being "excluded" (excommunicated), "dropped" (withdrawn to join another congregation or otherwise withdrawn without "charge of immorality"), or "erased" (long absent without information on his or her current situation). One event of note given as a reason for several members leaving the church was an 1832 rift recorded as the "Campbellite Secession." Other notations are made for events such as baptism, marriage, divorce, and death, including several parishioners who died in Civil War service, and at least one (Julius A. Hobson) killed in the collapse of a balcony at the Virginia State Capitol on 27 April 1870 (the date appears to be erroneously recorded as "4/27/1871"). The register begins with a note that the church's books prior to 1825 had been lost, necessitating some of the information recorded in the register being reconstituted from the collective memory of the church body. The volume continues with a historical sketch of the church up to 1885; a list of its pastors, 1780-1905; a list of outside ministers who had been members of First Baptist; and a "Table of Church Statistics," 1780-1904, breaking down by year and by cause the number of members added and subtracted from the church rolls.
</p>
</scopecontent>

<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">First Baptist Church (Richmond, Va.) Register</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1826-1905</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>


<container label="Box" type="box">1 of 1
</container>

<physdesc><extent>Extent: .44 cubic feet (1 box containing 125 inkjet prints of digital images of original volume).</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>

</c01>



</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>




