<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY burned SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/burned/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi04398">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04398::A Guide to the King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-1913)//EN" "vi04398.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1868-1913</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-1913
<num type="collectionnumber">King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-001-1913-014
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Bari Helms
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2012 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Bari Helms, <date>28 January 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1868-1913</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index: ">King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-001-1913-014
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Bari Helms
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Bari Helms and Library of Virginia staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1868-1913
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-001-1913-014 
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">King William County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Patrons are to use digital images of King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref entityref="chancery">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-1913. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, King William County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Digital images were generated by Crowley Micrographics and Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
<p>King William County was named for William III and was formed from King and Queen County in 1701.  Its area is 285.7 square miles, and the county seat is King William.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>King William County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1868-1913, are indexed into the <extref entityref="chancery">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
<p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional King William County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref entityref="microfilm">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p> 
<p>See the <extref entityref="chancery">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">King William County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--King William County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">King William County(Va.)--History.</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">King William County(Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--King William County.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1885-008, William Maxwell and Patrons of Colored Public Schools of West Point vs. Board of School Trustees, West Point: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>A T. H. Jones was a 3rd grade teacher at the school and was then appointed as Principal. Jones was also a Pastor at a local church. The patrons of the school want him removed from the school as a teacher and principal for "living in a state of unlawfull [sic] cohabitation" and not fit or qualified to teach. They also hoped to remove him from the church too. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1886-019, Richmond Ice Company vs. Mrs. Hattie A. Marlow and husband:  
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Two representatives of the Richmond Ice Company are suing Mrs. Marlow for money owed to them for their products. Although Mrs. Marlow is being sued, her husband was appointed her business agent and is accused of being insane "is not a careful and prudent man in the conduct of his business affairs." She also owes money to The West Point Loan and Building Fund Association for lands they own. All business is in her name.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1886-025, A. S. Richardson, etc. vs. J. B. Jennings, etc.: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The local town council election is proven to have been fraudulent for various reasons; The judges of the election left the election room during the voting, votes were cast while some of the judges were missing from the room, the tally that the judges returned was incorrect because many of the votes were made by people that were not residents of the town and two non-residents nor citizens intimidated voters into voting for a specific candidate during the voting. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1888-010, B. N. Robinson, etc. vs. R. W. Trice, etc.:
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>From the election fraud of 1886, the defendants are claiming to be elected councilmen of the town of West Point but because the election was declared fraudulent, the plaintiffs (former councilmen) do not want the fraudulently elected councilmen to be recognized as councilmen of the town. Also, the plaintiffs want to still be recognized as councilmen until they are succeeded with newly elected councilmen. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>



















<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1907-006, Walter Miles vs. Alice Miles: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Divorce suit of a Native American couple. Walter Miles, a member of the Pamunkey tribe living on the reservation in King William County then known as Indian Town, was charged before the tribe's council with seducing Alice Myers under the promise of marriage. Walter claimed he was forced to marry Alice or face expulsion from the tribe.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1911-016, John L. Ware vs. Mamie Ware: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Divorce suit accuses wife of desertion and claims that Mamie Ware's mother will not allow her to return home to her husband. Suit contains several letters between husband and wife. In one letter, John Ware writes his wife as she is about to give birth to a child and asks if the child is his. Another letter written by Lucy S. Minter, the mother-in-law, asks that John Ware "never to enter our gate again" and that she "hopes never to see [him] in this world."
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>1913-014, Rose Cliff Fruit Farm vs. Town of West Point, etc.: 
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Rose Cliff Fruit Farm sues the town of West Point and its mayor, H. Anderson, for stopping their sales of cider and arresting one of their employees. The fruit farm claimed that according to Virginia law they were permitted to sell cider because it did not contain alcohol. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
