<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi04761">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04761::A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1832-1833)//EN" "vi04761.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, <date>1832-1833</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions
<num type="barcodenumber">0007845058
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Greg Crawford
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Greg Crawford, <date>25 August 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, <date>1832-1833</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library of Virginia staff; McKenzie Long
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1832-1833
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007845058
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.10 cu. ft. (1 box)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Northampton County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1832-1833. Local government records collection, Northampton County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Northampton County.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1832-1833 were removed from the Northampton County Court papers and processed by Library of Virginia staff, and were later reprocessed and indexed as a distinct unit by McKenzie Long.
</p>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: August 2014; updated by M. Long: December 2023.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:</title> In 1818, Congress passed the first of three major Revolutionary War pension acts. The act granted lifetime pensions to all men who had served as regular army soldiers in the Continental Line and who could demonstrate financial need. Prior to the passage of this act, pensions had been restricted to former soldiers who were no longer able to support themselves due to injuries sustained while in service. The second act, passed by Congress in 1820, required applicants to provide more concrete evidence of this financial need in the form of a certified inventory of his property and income. They also had to include an account of all members of the applicant's family, including their health and ability to contribute to household income. In 1832, the third act extended pension benefits to include soldiers who had served in the state troops or militia. Congress also passed a related act in 1836 granting pensions to the widows and orphans of Revolutionary War veterans. 
</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Northampton County was named probably for the English county, of which Obedience Robins, a prominent early resident of the Eastern Shore, was a native. The county, which originally included all of the peninsula south of Maryland and which was one of the eight shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634, was first called Accomack. The General Assembly changed the name to Northampton County in 1643. Accomack County was created from Northampton County about 1663, but in October 1670, the General Assembly temporarily reunited the two counties as Northampton County. In November 1673, Accomack County was again separated from Northampton. The county seat is Eastville. </p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Northampton County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1832-1833 primarily record the declarations of individuals seeking to obtain Revolutionary War pensions provided by various acts of Congress. The applicants present detailed testimony of their time of service during the Revolutionary War. Information found in the Declarations include date and location applicants entered into service, names of military companies they served in, names of military commanders they served under, names of fellow soldiers they served with, length of service, their age, and their place of birth. The predominant portion of the declarations are narratives of their tours of duty during the Revolutionary War with emphasis on battles they fought. The declarations also include affidavits from witnesses who could verify information provided by applicants.
</p>
<p>Significant materials in this collection include the pension declaration of a free Black soldier, James Carter.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Northampton County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1832-1833</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.10 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007845058 ">		Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1833	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>