<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxngschema"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     id="vi04345">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04345::A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, 1970-2014.)//EN" "vi04345.xml"
		</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, <date>1970-2014.</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Virginia.<num type="Accession Number">34743, 34883, 35466, 39056, 41519, 42374, 42722, 44932, 45393, 51229, 51743</num>
            </subtitle>
            <author>W. Clark</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
            <xi:include href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication">© 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
			</date>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record using MarcEdit by Ben Bromley, <date>2014</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, <date>1970-2014.</date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle id="sort">A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
			<num type="Accession Number">34743, 34883, 35466, 39056, 41519, 42374, 42722, 44932, 45393, 51229, 51743</num>
         </subtitle>
         <author>W. Clark</author>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2014
			</date>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:
			</label>
               <item>Library of Virginia Staff.
			</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" type="collection">Correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation,</unittitle>
         <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">1970-2014.</unitdate>
         <unitid encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">34743, 34883, 35466, 39056, 41519, 42374, 42722, 44932, 45393, 51229, 51743</unitid>
         <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation.</origination>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">111 cu. ft.</physdesc>


      </did>
      
<descgrp type="admininfo">
	<head>Administrative Information</head>

      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <p>Arranged alphabetically by subject.</p>
      </arrangement>

      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
		<head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>Privacy protected and other protected information is considered confidential and restricted from public access for 75 years. It may be necessary for an archivist to review any unprocessed, modern record collections (those collections less than 75 years old) that may contain confidential information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies of records can be made for patrons. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details before planning your research trip.</p>
      </accessrestrict>

      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
         <head>Preferred Citation
		</head>
         <p>Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, Office of the Director, Correspondence and subject files, [cite specific dates and accession used]. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>

      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition Information
		</head>
         <p>Accession 34743 was transferred by the Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation on 10/25/1994</p>

	<p>Accession 51743 was transferred by the Dept. of Professional and Occupation Regulation on 3/1/2016.</p>
      </acqinfo>


<processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>This collection has been processed using minimal processing standards: the original arrangement has been maintained, the container list is brief and simple, and the records have not been refoldered and fasteners have not been removed. 
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation was formed in 1948 under the Government Reorganization Act. On March 24, 1978, the agency’s name was changed to the Dept. of Commerce. Effective July, 1993, the Department regained its original name. Currently, the Department is responsible for the these Boards: Appraisers (real estate), Architects, Asbestos, Lead and Home Inspectors, Auctioneers, Barbers, Body Piercing, Branch Pilots, Cemetery, Common Interest Community, Contractors, Cosmetology, Fair Housing, Geology, Hearing Aid Specialists, Interior Designers, Land Surveyors, Landscape Architects, Opticians, Polygraph Examiners, Professional Boxing and Wrestling, Professional Engineers, Professional Soil Scientists and Wetland Professionals, Real estate brokers, Surveyor Photogrammetrist, Tattooing, Tradesmen Licensure, Waste Management Facility Operators, and Waterworks and Wastewater Works Operators and Onsite Sewage System Professionals.</p>
      <p>The primary function of the Department is to provide administrative support to the boards within the Department which are currently responsible for licensing and certification of occupations. The Boards have regulatory authority for the issuance, suspension and revocation of certificates, permits, and licenses. The Department is operated by a director who is appointed by the Governor. The Department’s activities are broken-down into sub-programs for each of the examining boards. Major activities include review and evaluation of the regulation of professions, examination of those wishing to enter one of the regulated professions, licensing, consumer complaint resolution, and investigation of alleged violations or laws. The mission of the Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation is to protect the health, safety and welfare of Virginians, while promoting a competent workforce, fair housing opportunities, and a productive economy. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Contains correspondence and subject files of the Director of the Virginia Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation that document the planning, direction, and implementation of agency and board programs and are evidence of actions and policy decisions. Includes correspondence with the agency boards, Secretary of Economic Development/Commerce and Trade, and the Governor’s Office. Also may include newsletters, weekly reports, strategic planning reports, agency study reports, and financial reports. 
</p>

<p>Accession 51743 consists of the correspondence and subject files of Director Gordon Dixon, who directed the agency from 2011-2014. These records include correspondence, newsletters, various plans and board information. This accession also includes 2 compact disks with correspondence and subject files.
</p>


    </scopecontent>
    
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      
<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1970-2014</emph></unitdate>.
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">Accession 51743 (2008-2014).
</emph>
            </unittitle>
          </did>

 

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Board profile summaries, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>
         
<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012-2013</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence - Tracking letters and Appeal letters, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence and subject files - Gordon Dixon - miscellaneous, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011-2014</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence and subject files - Gordon Dixon - compact disks, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011-2014</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>DPOR Continuity Plan, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 revised</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>DPOR Transition Manual, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>EAGLES Project Quality Plan, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 September 26</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>

<c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Newsletters (DPOR Voice), 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010-2013</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c03>







</c02>




</c01>


    
  
	</dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>