<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04065">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04065::A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899)//EN" "vi04065.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1786-1899</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899
<num type="collectionnumber">Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-001-1899-010
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18 November 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1786-1899</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-001-1899-010
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Greg Crawford
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1786-1899
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-001-1899-010 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Arlington County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Arlington County was originally named Alexandria County. It was formed from a portion of Fairfax County that Virginia in 1789 ceded to the federal government for use as the site of a new national capital. In 1801 the area officially became part of the District of Columbia, although Congress named it Alexandria County. By an act of 9 July 1846, Congress returned the county to Virginia, and the General Assembly extended the commonwealth's jurisdiction over the region effective 20 March 1847. By an act of assembly passed 16 March 1920, the county's name was changed to Arlington, the name of the Custis family mansion (the home of Robert E. Lee), which is located in the county.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities including city of Alexandria.
</p>
        <p>Additional post-1899 Arlington County Chancery Causes are available in their original format at the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Arlington County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington County (Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Arlington County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
<dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
    <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1805-039: Bazel, an enslaved person vs. James Kennedy, Jr., etc.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom suit.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1819-045: Ambrose Vasse vs. James English:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt suit involving the sale of a slave, William. Seller (Vasse) is afraid that buyer (English) will sell slave to a slave trader before fully repaying his debt. Vasse is also concerned that sale to trader will force William to leave his wife and child.   
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1822-018: John Mason vs. John Muncaster and others:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves a dispute related to the purchase by Mason of glebe land in Fairfax Parish from the Protestant Episcopal Church of Alexandria, or as it became known in 1814, Christ Church. The source of contention between the plaintiff and the defendants was the question of whether Christ Church of Alexandria had jurisdiction within Fairfax Parish and therefore had the authority to sell the land. The plaintiff in his bill and amended bill and the defendants in their answer provided very detailed legal and historical arguments to support their claims. The defendants in their answer presented a history of how Christ Church acquired land in Fairfax Parish from the parish's inception in 1765. In the process of doing so, they discussed the nature of the relationship between the two churches in the parish, Falls Church and Christ Church; how the parish was governed; and the decline in membership of Falls Church. Plaintiff and defendants provided evidence to support their arguments such as a copy of a bill from a previous chancery case involving Christ Church, a copy of a Supreme Court mandate, a copy of a deed, and correspondence. The chancery cause also includes miscellaneous papers related to the case such as subpoenas, affidavits, and depositions. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1827-036: Administrator of William Stewart, Jr. vs. Catherine Flood McCall and others,: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Stewart was the manager of nail factory in Alexandria owned by Catherine Flood McCall. The cause inludes correspondence between Stewart and McCall. The major themes found in Stewart's letters to McCall include: his affectionate feelings for McCall and desire to marry her; business matters related to McCall's nail factories in Alexandria and Richmond and her plantation in Tappahannock; his difficulties with McCall's enslaved property who worked for him at the factory; his constant lack of money to pay his personal debts; his efforts to make additional income outside the factory (one effort led to his being sued by the United States government for violating the Embargo Act of 1807); his repeated requests to be given total authority over McCall's financial interests; his poor health, both emotional and physical; and his great unhappiness with his life in Alexandria. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
  
      
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1845-017: Bank of Potomac, etc. vs. Edward Sheehy and wife, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ship manifest listing names of slaves to be transported from Alexandria to New Orleans. Includes depositions from a few slave traders acquainted with the slave markets of the Deep South.  eponents were examined in order to obtain knowledge regarding the fluctuating prices of enslaved people in various markets and their depositions provide information on the fluid nature of slave market value in relation to the rise of fall of other commodities such as sugar and cotton. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1848-006: Admr. of Robert Marshall vs. Exr. of Richard Marshall Scott, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves importation of enslaved people from Fairfax County to Charles County, Maryland. It also includes portion of Richard Marshall Scott' memoir sharing family history to his son and correspondence between Scott and his son.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1849-001: William Taylor, etc. vs. Admr. of Thomas Vowell:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Two African-Americans claimed to be illegally detained as enslaved people. Defendant forcibly removed the two from Washington, D.C. and put them a slave jail in Alexandria owned by James Bruin. The defendants threatened to sell African-Americans before their petitions for freedom could be heard in D.C. Circuit Court.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1850-008: Benoni Wheat, etc. vs. Phineas Janney, trst(s), etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Dispute between rival members of Methodist Episcopal Church in Alexandria for control of church property. One group supported Methodist Episcopal Church, South and the other remained loyal to Methodist Episcopal Church, North. Dispute centered over slavery. Court decided in favor of Methodist Episcopal Church, North.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1850-012: John E. Hughes, etc. vs. Joseph Bruin, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bruin was leading slave trader in Alexandria, Virginia. One of his agents purchased an enslaved girl named Mary Catherine from a Frederick Vaccari. The agent and Bruin were told she was enslaved for life. After a brief stay in Bruin's slave jail, they sent her to Georgia along with other slaves to be sold. Plaintiffs claimed the enslaved girl should not have been sold out of the state because she was not enslaved for life. Mary Catharine was to be freed when she reached the age of 25. One of the previous owners of Mary Catharine named her after his two daughters, Mary and Catharine. The suit offers insight into domestic slave trade.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1851-011: Catherine Jones vs. George Kephart, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom suit. Catherine Jones claimed to have been emancipated and unlawfully sold.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1852-024: Moses, an enslaved person, etc. vs. Exrs. of William H. Foote:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom suit. Moses and other enslaved persons of William H. Foote claimed to have been emancipated by Foote. They successfully won their freedom.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1856-022: Robert W. Carter, etc. vs. Exrs. Of John Tayloe, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Estate division suit that originated in Richmond County. John Tayloe was one of the wealthiest Virginians at time of death in 1828. Owned vast amount of real and personal property including Botetourt County. Includes will listing names and locations of multiple plantations. Built Mount Airy in Richmond County. Includes correspondence that discusses political environment in nation in 1852.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1859-017: Exr. of George Washington Parke Custis vs. Mary Ann Randolph Lee, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Custis was stepgrandson of George Washington. Robert E. Lee was his executor. Mary was daugter of Custis and wife of Lee. Additional defendants were Lee's children. R.E. Lee sought the court's help in settling Custis' vast estate in order to repay Custis' debt which was between 11,000 and 12,000 dollars. He had a question regarding whether or not he could sell slaves (200) to repay debt even though Custis' will stipulated all his slaves were to be emancipated 5 years after repaying debt. Lee writes about difficulties managing slaves who believed they were to be immediately emancipated. Cause includes inventory of Custis' slaves. Custis' will listed as exhibit but not found in suit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1860-003: Mary Ann Junius vs. Henry W.P. Junius:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Scandalous divorce suit. Defendant was a bigamist and con artist. His exploits are detailed in suit. Ranged from Virginia, South Carolina, Kentucky, Indiana, and New York.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1865-017: Moses Hepburn vs. Prudence Crandell Hepburn, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Moses Hepburn was a free African American. He was the son of William Hepburn, a white Quaker merchant who owned substantial property in Alexandria County, and an enslaved person named Esther. Cause contains William Hepburn's will in which he leaves most of his estate to his children by Esther. Cause centers on sale of property along Alexandria Canal and division of proceeds among Heburn's children by Esther. Moses Hepburn's claims to property disputed by Willaim Hepburn's legitimate children.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1866-011: Henry Grafton Dulany vs. Richard H. Dulany, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Henry Grafton sued Richard H. for failing to abide by will of Henry G.'s father Henry Rozier Dulany in order to inherit Henry R.'s estate Shuter's Hill. Will stipulated that in order for Henry R.'s daughter Rebecca Anne to inherit estate whoever she married had to change his name to Henry Rozier Dulany and build a monument to Henry R. on estate.  Otherwise, Rebecca's brother Henry G. would inherit Shuter's Hill.  Rebecca married her cousin Richard H. He refused to change his name and failed to build monument. Henry G. sued and won.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1866-013: Robert F. Roche vs. Fannie Roche:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Fannie refused to go with husband to his house on wedding day. Robert accused her of being a prostitute. She leaves for New York City. Cause includes tintype of Fannie used by processor to identify her.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1866-017: Phillipine Durand vs. Claudius Durand:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Couple from France who moved to U.S. in 1835. He left her. She started a new life making a living by sewing. She made enough money to purchase land in Fairfax County.  He returned and demanded she give him her property. Court sided in her favor.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-006: George W. Parker vs. Mary Jane Parker:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Married as enslaved people in Petersburg, VA in 1855 or 1856. White person performed marriage but was not licensed to do so. Wife left husband before passage of cohabitation act in 1866. Cause dismissed because couple were never legally married.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868-030: Sarah E. M. Field vs. George W. Field:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Husband abandoned wife to join Mount Vernon Confederate regiment in May 1861. He supported secession. She supported union. Cause includes letter written by wife to husband. She shares her hatred for secession "and all its hateful helpers."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1870-004: Nancy Hodges vs. John H. Broders:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contract dispute. Nancy Hodges was a free African American. Her husband was a slave named Tom Hodges owned by Broders. Nancy made an agreement with Broders to purchase her husband's freedom. She accused Broders of not abiding by agreement. He threatened to sell her husband to slave speculators.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1888-004: S. Ferguson Beach vs. Alexander Hunter, etc. and Alice A. Hunter, etc. vs. S. Ferguson Beach, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause contains a pamphlet for the sale of Abingdon Plantation, a property previously owned by the Custis family and the birthplace of Nelly Parke Custis Lewis.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1895-011: James Underwood vs. Thomas S. Clark, etc.:    
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt for the training of racehorses Clara Bell, Gladstone, and Brooklyn. Mentions racetracks at St. Asaph and Alexander's Island.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1897-006: Sarah G. Johnson vs. Louis H. Crowe, etc.:    
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Sarah G. Johnson sues her former husband, Louis H. Crowe, for not paying for land she deeded over to him while they were married. Johnson asserts she was the legal owner of the land before the marriage and that after she deeded the land to Crowe, he physically drove her off the property. However, Crowe claimed that he was driven from the land and was forced to jump from a second story window, breaking his leg, to save himself from her violence. See also 1891-002-Sarah G. Crowe vs. Louis H. Crowe.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>

          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>