<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi04425">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04425::A Guide to the Westmoreland County (Va) Election Records, 1902-1954)//EN" "vi04425.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Westmoreland County (Va) Election Records, <date>1902-1954</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Westmoreland County (Va) Election Records
<num type="collectionnumber">1042957, 1043042, 1101708, 1101719, 1101870, 1101872-1101874
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Louise Jones
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2018  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Louise Jones, <date>19 July 2018</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Westmoreland County (Va) Election Records, <date>1902-1954</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection Number">1042957, 1043042, 1101708, 1101719, 1101870, 1101872-1101874
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2018 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library of Virginia Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Westmoreland County (Va) Election Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1902-1954
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1042957, 1043042, 1101708, 1101719, 1101870, 1101872-1101874
</unitid>
<physloc label="Storage Location">State Records Center-Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 box and 94 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Westmoreland County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Westmoreland County (Va.) Election Records, 1902-1954. Local government records collection, Westmoreland County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These item came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Westmoreland County (Va.). 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Westmoreland County was formed from Northumberland County in 1653, and part of King George was added later. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Westmoreland County (Va.) Election Records, 1902-1954 consist of individual items; and volumes of General Registration, List of Voters, and Rolls of Registered Voters.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Westmoreland County Court Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Westmoreland County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records--Virginia--Westmoreland County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Westmoreland County</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="analyticover">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Election Records,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1903-1958</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="box">1042957
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This box contains individual election records. The records concern candidates, elections, primaries and an Oath of Office. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">General Registration</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1903</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1101719
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 volume.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Generation Registration, 1902-1903. This volume has the following columns: Date of Registration, Number, Name, Date of Birth (year only), Age, Occupation, Residence, Length of Residence in State, County, in Precinct, Is He Exempt from Payment of Poll Tax as a Perquisite To Voting. If Naturalized, Date of Papers, By What Court Issued, If Transferred, When and To What Precinct.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">List of Voters Registered</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1916</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="Volume">1101708
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 volume.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection contains the Rolls of Voters Registered in Baynesville, Colonial Beach, Hague, Kinsale, Montross, Oldhams and Warrensville Precincts for 1902-1918.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Roll of Registered Voters in all Westmoreland Precincts</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1903</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1043042
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: This collection contains 61 volumes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>There are two copies of the Rolls of Registered Voters for 1902. One copy is the original copy and the other is the Examined or Compared and Examined Copy. The eight White Precincts have each of the White Roll of Registered Voters in 1902. The eight Colored Precincts have each of the Colored Rolls of Register Voters in 1902.  The are two copies of the Rolls of Registered Voters for 1903. One is the original copy and the other is Recorded copy. The seven White Precincts have each of the White Roll of Registered Voters in 1903. Oldhams Precinct only has the Recorded volume.  Six of the Colored Precincts have each of the Colored Roll of Registered Voters in 1903.  The copies of the Roll of Registered Voters in Oldhams Precinct are missing. The two copies of the 1903 Roll of Registered Colored Voters in Warrensville Precincts do not have any names listed in them.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Rolls and Lists of Voters Registered at Colonial Beach and the Town of Colonial Beach Precincts</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1954</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1101870
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 7 volumes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection contains the Roll of White Voters Registered in Colonial Beach Precinct, 1902-1936; Town Register written in a Roll of White Voters Registered at Colonial Beach Precinct, 1902-1950; List of White Voters Registered in Colonial Beach Precinct, January 1, 1904-1932; County Colored written in a Roll of Colored Voters Registered in Colonial Beach Precinct, 1929-1954; State (County) Register in a List of White Voters Registered at Colonial Beach Precinct, 1902-1949; Roll of White Voters Registered in Colonial Beach Town, 1902-1954; and Roll of White Voters Registered in Colonial Beach Precinct, 10 October 1902-1918.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Rolls and List of Voters Registered at Colonial Beach Precinct, Town of Colonial Beach, and Montross Precinct</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1954</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1101874
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 4 volumes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection contains the Roll of White Voters Registered at Colonial Beach Precinct, 1902-1954; the Roll of Colored Voters Registered at the Town of Colonial Beach Precinct, 1929-1954: the List of Colored Voters Registered at Montross Precinct,1904-1928; and Roll of White Voters Registered at Colonial Beach Precinct, 1902-1932.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Rolls and List of Voters Registered at Hague, Oak Grove, and Warrinsville Precincts</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1954</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1101873
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 10 volumes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection contains the Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Hague Precinct, 1902-1903. Included in the volume is a Certificate of Registration in the Permanent Roll of Voters in Kinsale Precinct, County Poll Book for Use in General Elections at Hague Precinct 22 September 1914, and a Poll Book and Certificate of Judges; List of Colored Voters Registered at Hague Precinct since January 1st 1904, 1908-1929; Roll of White Voters Registered at Hague Precinct, 1902-1903. Included in this volume is a County Poll Book for Use in Primary Elections DEMOCRATIC, 14 items in front of this book include letters, certificates, Poll Tax Information; How To Vote, copy of Chapter 413, an Act approved May 24, 1922, five Certificates of Registration, a booklet titled Supplement to Virginia Election Law, Primary Poll Book, Certificates of Judges, 1902-1903; List of White Voters Registered at Hague Precinct since January 1, 1904, 1905-1930, Certificate of Registration; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Hague Precinct, 1902-1952, two Certificates of Registration; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Hague Precinct, 1902-1952, two Certificates of Registration; Roll of White Voters Registered at Hague Precinct, 1902-1954, two letters, a postcard and fifty six Certificates of Registration; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Oak Grove Precinct since January 1, 1904, 1930-1953; Roll of White Voters Registered at Oak Grove Precinct since January 1, 1904, 1902-1952, includes an "Omitted Capitation Tax Assessed by Commission of Revenue" receipt;  Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Warrensville Precinct, 1902; and Roll of White Voters Registered at Warrensville Precinct, 1902-1953.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Rolls and List of Voters Registered at Kinsale, Montross, and Oldhams Precincts</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1902-1954</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1101872
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 10 volumes.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection has the Roll of White Voters Registered at Kinsale Precinct, 1902-1929; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Kinsale Precinct, 1902-1929. Included in this book is a printed list of all person who had paid their Capitation Tax on or before the second day of May 1937 in Westmoreland County, Virginia, including the Town of Colonial Beach, There in According to Law, and eight pages for Montross District-White; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Kinsale Precinct, 1902-1952; Roll of White Voters Registered at Kinsale Precinct, 1902-1954; List of White Voters Registered at Montross Precinct updated, 1889-1901. This register ask if the voter has been naturalized, the date of his papers, and by what court were they issued. Included in the book is the Application of Inez M. McGinness and Registration Oath 10 August 1927; List of White Voters Registered at Montross Precinct, 1904-1930. Included with this volume is Registration Oaths (Females) for three women on 1 August 1921 and one woman on 28 April 1930. Receipt of Registered Articles No. 87-89. Application for Registration at Montross Precinct for Lawrence S. Cooke for the Board of Supervisor, Westmoreland County Bill of E. C. Healy, Registrar. Application for Registration in Montross Precinct of Ernest C. Mozingo;  Roll of White Voters Registered at Montross Precinct, 1902-1914. Included in this volume is a request for an absentee ballot which was mailed July 25, 1923; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Montross Precinct, 1902-1903;  Roll of White Voters Registered at Oldhams Precinct, 1902-1952; Roll of Colored Voters Registered at Oldhams Precinct, 1902-1953. Included with this volume is the County Poll Book Used In General Elections giving the Number and Name of Electors and Certificate of Judges, 4 June 1940. Also, a County Poll Book For Use In Primary Elections, DEMOCRATIC, 6 August 1935.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
