<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04794">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04794::A Guide to the Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913))//EN" "vi04794.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)
<num type="collectionnumber">Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-001-1919-001
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">24 April 2015</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-001-1919-001
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index:" encodinganalog="099$a">Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-001-1919-001
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Madison County Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Madison County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Madison County was named for James Madison, a Virginian statesman, author of the United States Constitution, and member of Congress when the county was formed from Culpeper County by a statute adopted on 4 December 1792. This was the second Virginia county to be named for future president Madison. The county court first met on 23 May 1793. The county seat is Madison. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1794-1919 (bulk 1803-1913), are indexed into <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">the Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, business records, or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Madison County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA161">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
        <p>See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">the Chancery Records Index</extref> to search for chancery suits of additional Virginia localities.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Madison County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Madison County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Madison County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1803-003, Exrs. Of Robert Beverley vs. Mackenzie Beverley
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contains will of Robert Beverley, Sr., Essex Co., builder of Blandfield Plantation. Frees enslaved personal attendant and "his wife."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1818-002, Simon B. Chapman vs. John Wright, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit concerns a contract for substitute militia service and discusses some generalities about the War of 1812.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1822-005, James P. Sims vs. William Jarrett, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit initiated because Jarrett was accused of murder by coroner's inquest and flees county. By law, coroner took possession of Jarrett's property and Sims sues to get title to land he paid Jarrett for.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1823-017, Mary Clark vs. William Davis, Asgn.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit references plaintiff boarding with defendant and raising several "young Negroes" for him. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1830-005, Joseph Good vs. J. B. Norton, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit invovles a patent dispute over rights to improvements to Bergen's self-sharpening plow.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1837-007, Moses~, etc. vs. Exr. of John Stockdell
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The plaintiffs, who were slaves, sued because Stockdell's will called for them to be turned over to American Colonization Society for transport to Liberia (with funds from estate for passage.) Executors continued to rent out the slaves even though there are no debts owed by estate. The court ruled in favor of the plaintiffs.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1839-004, Joseph Hume vs. Exrs. Of Joseph Clark, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Includes a genealogical chart and extensive explanation of familial relationships of whole and half-blood.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844-008, Henry Hill vs. Humphrey Taylor
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Hill and Taylor were business partners engaged "in the business of buying slaves in the state of Virginia … and selling in the southern part of the United States," specifically Mississippi and Louisiana. After the partnership dissolved, Hill sued Taylor to recover his fair share of the partnership's profits. Hill asked the court to perform an audit of all the partnership's transactions from the time of its commencement to its dissolution. Documents found in the suit such as Hill's complaint, Taylor's rebuttal, depositions, affidavits, commissioners' reports, and correspondence provide a "behind the curtain" look into the slave trade. Even more significant are the lists containing the names of hundreds of slaves who were bought in Virginia and sold in Mississippi and Louisiana by Hill and Taylor from 1830 to 1843 (See image numbers 172-189, 194, 206-211). The lists record the names of slaves, purchase price in Virginia, sale price in Mississippi and Louisiana, the date of sale, and the names of individuals who purchased the slaves.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844-014, Nathaniel Tatum, etc. vs. William H. Twyman, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves slave traders.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1854-011, William J. Carpenter, etc. vs. Admr. of Thomas Shirley, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The suit concerns the will of a woman under "fanatical influence of Shakers [sect]" who renounced her inheritance of a slave from Thomas Shirley.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-010, Jacob G. Weast, etc. vs. Admr. of Benjamin Burton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff found substitute for defendant in CSA Army ca. 1861 and was promised 500 dollars in three payments. The plaintiff collected one payment and dies. The plaintiff sued for remainder. The administrator contends that debt is invalid because it concerns service for the CSA, and the only true government of Virginia was the Restored Government now back in place in Richmond. The argument failed; the court ruled in favor of the plaintiff.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1891-032, Exrs. of Charles Hume vs. Hannah Sparks, etc.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit concerns the settlement of Charles Hume's estate. Hume died in 1860 and provided in his will for "two old negroes" Charles and Hay (later referred to as Hay Taliaferro). Charles dies before or shortly after Hume. There is some question as to an agreement between Hay and Hume's executors regarding his care and maintenance. Hay, a petitioner to the suit, claims to have been duped by the executors into signing an agreement that was not to his benefit. A decree from the Supreme Court of Appeals in the suit seems to imply that Hay has no standing in the suit since he was freed at the end of the Civil War. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1919-001, Adms. Of Thomas Shirley vs. Heirs of Thomas Shirley and Zachariah Shirley vs. Adms. Of Thomas Shirley
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The suit began in 1840's and continued to early 20th century. It was an estate dispute, so there is extensive genealogical information and slave relationships and occupations. The suit also includes letterhead depicting a political cartoon relative to the 1844 Presidential race. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
