<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi04273">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04273::A Guide to the Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records, 1815; 1829-1834//EN" "vi04273.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records,
<date>1815; 1829-1834.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Alexandria Free School Board of Guaruidans Records, 1815; 1829-1834   
<num type="collectionnumber">1043672
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion 
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy;2010 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Catherine G. OBrion, <date>17 June 2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records, <date>1815; 1829-1834</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number:">1205113</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Catherine G. OBrion 
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>LVA staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records, <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1815; 1829-1834 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">1205113 
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.25 cu. ft. (1 box)   
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records, 1815; 1829-1834. Local government records collection, Alexandria/Arlington County (Va.) Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Arlington  County. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Lancasterian, or Free School of Alexandria was established in 1812, as a branch of the Alexandria Academy. A separate Lancasterian School for females was also established in 1812. Both schools were operated by the trustees of the Alexandria Academy. The Alexandria Academy was built with funds donated by George Washington and chartered in1786. The Free School was intended to educate younger students. In 1829, the trustees of the Alexandria Academy conveyed to the Alexandria Common Council the lot and building of the school, along with the annual interest from four thousand dollars of stock of the Bank of Alexandria donated by General Washington for the purpose of educating "such orphan children or the children of such other poor &amp; indigent persons as are unable to accomplish it with their own means." The Council established a Board of Guardians to govern the school, which admitted boys and girls. After 1835, the Free School was governed by a commission appointed by the Alexandria City Council. Additional funds were allocated to the school by Elizabeth Washington, widow of Lund Washington, manager of Mount Vernon and a distant cousin of George Washington.
</p>
<p>Alexandria, in Fairfax and Arlington Counties, was named for John Alexander, an early owner of the tract on which the town was located. Alexandria was established in 1749. It was incorporated as a town in 1779 and as a city in 1852.
</p>
<p>Arlington County was originally named Alexandria County. It was formed from a portion of Fairfax County that Virginia in 1789 ceded to the federal government for use as the site of a new national capital. In 1801 the area officially became part of the District of Columbia, although Congress named it Alexandria County. By an act of 9 July 1846, Congress returned the county to Virginia, and the General Assembly extended the commonwealth's jurisdiction over the region effective 20 March 1847. By an act of assembly passed 16 March 1920, the county name was changed to Arlington, the name of the Custis family mansion (the home of Robert E. Lee), which is located in the county.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Alexandria Free School Board of Guardians Records, 1815; 1829-1834. The collection contains administrative records as follows: drafts and copies of legislation and petitions pertaining to financial support and governance of the school, 1829-1832; board meeting minutes, 1831-1833; correspondence, 1830-1832, much of which pertains to questions and reports about the Lancasterian, or monitorial method of educating poor children; reports, 1829-1834, and financial records, 1829-1831. The collection also contains a printed report of the Trustees of the Free School Society of New York, 1815; and a resolution, unsigned and undated, urging civic and Christian support of the Sabbath School movement.
</p>
<p>The draft Act of the Alexandria Common Council to establish a Board of Guardians for the Lancasterian, or Free School of Alexandria, 1829, contains information about the administrative history of the school and its financial support with annual interest from an endowment established by George Washington to educate orphan children and/or children of the poor. It also contains information about an agreement between the trustees of the Alexandria Academy and the Committee of the Alexandria Common Council, made 1812 April 11, to convey the ground and building of the Lancasterian school to the corporation of Alexandria.</p>
<p>The draft petition and copy of a petition to Congress is a plea for financial support for the school. Petitioners implore Congress to support the school in order to alleviate poverty and safeguard public morals in the nation's capitol. Petitioners complain about Congress' neglect of Alexandria since it was absorbed by the District of Columbia thirty years earlier.
</p><p>The minutes document the Board of Guardian's oversight of the daily operations of the school.</p>
<p>Correspondence is comprised mostly of letters between the Board of Guardians and Samuel Plummer, who was hired by the Board to teach at the school. In 1830, the Board sent Plummer to Philadelphia with a list of written queries to investigate the operations of the "monitorial system of education," particularly as applied to the operation of schools for the education of the poor. The letters contain the Board's instructions to Plummer, a copy of the questions they want him to investigate, and three letters from Plummer describing his findings. In one letter, Plummer lists the books used in the schools he visited in Philadelphia. Also included are letters, 1832, between Elias Harrison and Samuel Plummer concerning the Board's decision to change the method of compensation for the teacher due to a decline in the number of students attending the school.
</p>
<p>The collection also contains a letter from a congressman, 1830, February 22, concerning his presentation of the Board's petition to Congress; and a letter, 1830 July 18, from William H. Foote to the Reverend Elias Harrison, concerning a request to use money for the school from a bequest of Elizabeth Foote Washington left for the education of poor girls.
</p>
<p>Samuel Plummer's quarterly reports to the Board of Guardians, 1830-1833, contain average number of daily attendants, divided by city ward and gender, and general remarks, which discuss the challenges of getting children to attend on a regular basis, discipline, and progress of students. Some reports list furniture and books belonging to the school.
</p>
<p>Reports to Alexandria Common Council, 1830-1831, contain reports on the Board's investigation of systems of free education used in Baltimore, New York, and Philadelphia, as well as annual reports summarizing the quarterly reports from Samuel Plummer on the progress of the Alexandria Free School. The report dated 1831 February 25 includes a reference to increase the teacher's salary. Also included is a report on damage to the school building from a storm in January 1830.
</p>
<p>Reports of Sunday School enrollments, 1829-1834, circa, contain records of the number of scholars, boys and girls, enrolled in Sunday Schools or Sabbath Schools in churches in Alexandria, 1829-1834; and a report from the Sunday School Union, 1829 April 13, which estimates a total of 885 children enrolled in seven churches. Also included are reports from First Presbyterian Church, 1830 and undated; the Baptist School of Alexandria, undated; the Methodist Episcopal Church, undated; the Sunday School at Backlick, 1833; Second Presbyterian Church, 1834 April 7; Christ Church Sabbath School, 1834 and undated; and the Methodist Sunday School, 1830.</p>
<p>Financial records, 1829-1833, contain a treasurer's report, 1831; and records of accounts with the American Sunday School Union, 1829-1833.
</p>
<p>The Trustees of the Free School Society of New York Tenth Annual Report, 1815, documents the work of the society in educating poor children in New York City using the Lancasterian system.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Arranged by series. 
</p>
</arrangement>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head><controlaccess>
<head>Persons:</head>
<persname>Foote, William H.</persname>
<persname>Harrison, Elias.</persname>
<persname>Plummer, Samuel.</persname>
<persname>Washington, Elizabeth Foote, d. 1812.</persname>
<persname>Washington, George, 1732-1799.</persname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Alexandria Academy -- Trustees.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Alexandria Common Council -- Free School Board of Guardians.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">American Sunday-School Union.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Free School Society of New York -- Trustees.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">American students -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Benefactors -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Education -- curricula  -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Education -- statistics -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria  County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Endowments -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria  County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free schools -- New York -- New York City.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free schools -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Free schools -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Girls' schools -- Washington (D.C.) --Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Monitorial system of education -- New York --New York City..</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Monitorial system of education -- Pennsylvania -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Monitorial system of education -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Orphans -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Poor children -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Sabbath schools -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">School buildings -- Virginia -- Alexandria  County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">School discipline -- Virginia -- Alexandria  County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Schools -- records and correspondence --Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Sunday Schools -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Teachers -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Textbooks -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Women philanthropists -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Geographical Names:</head>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington County (Va.) -- History--19th century.</geogname>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Washington (D.C.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Annual reports -- Washington (D.C.) --Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Attendance records -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria  County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Correspondence -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Financial records -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Legislative acts -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Minutes -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Monthly reports -- Washington (D.C.) --Alexandria County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Petitions -- Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria  County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Quarterly reports -- Washington (D.C.) --Alexandria  County.</genreform>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">School records -- Washington (D.C.) --Alexandria County.</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Alexandria County (Va.) -- Circuit Court.</corpname>
<corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Washington (D.C.) -- Alexandria County -- Circuit Court.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
