<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04056">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04056::A Guide to the Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970 (bulk 1870-1930)//EN" "vi04056.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1803-1970 (bulk 1870-1930)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970 (bulk 1870-1930)
</subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">20 August 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1803-1970 (bulk 1870-1930)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field Processors
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1803-1970 (1870-1930)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Fairfax County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Chancery Causes 1803-1913 use digital images found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.  
</p>
<p>Chancery Causes 1914-1970 are processed and indexed information is available on the Chancery Records Index, but digital images are not available at this time. Contact the Fairfax County Circuit Court Clerk for availability.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions on use.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970 (bulk 1870-1930). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Fairfax County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970, were processed by field processors before 2008.  
</p>
<p>Digital images of Chancery Causes 1803-1913 were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program in 2008.</p>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: August 2009; updated by C. Collins: November 2023.</p>
</processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.
</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Fairfax County was named for Thomas Fairfax, sixth baron Fairfax of Cameron, proprietor of the Northern Neck. It was formed from Prince William County in 1742. Part of Loudoun County was added in 1798. The county seat is the city of Fairfax. 
</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Lost Locality Note:</emph> Original wills and deeds as well as many other loose papers were destroyed during the Civil War. Deed books for twenty-six of the fifty-six years between 1763 and 1819 are missing. Numerous pre–Civil War minute books are missing as well.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics. 
</p>
      <p>Commonly found surnames among the plaintiffs and defendants include Adams, Allen, Allison, Anderson, Ball, Ballenger, Barker, Beach, Brown, Buckley, Burke, Butler, Campbell, Carter, Chichester, Clark, Cockerille, Coleman, Daniel, Darne, Davis, Fairfax, Farr, Fitzhugh, Follin, Ford, Fox, Grigsby, Gunnell, Hall, Halley, Harris, Harrison, Henderson, Howard, Hunter, Hutchison, Jackson, Jenkins, Johnson, Johnston, Jones, Kidwell, Kincheloe, Lee, Lewis, Makely (also spelled Makeley), Marshall, Mason, Millan, Miller, Mills, Mitchell, Money, Moore, Nelson, Oliver, Payne, Phillips, Powell, Ratcliffe, Reid, Richards, Richardson, Riley, Roberts, Robinson, Rogers, Russell, Scott, Selecman, Simpson, Smith, Steele, Stewart, Stone, Taylor, Thomas, Thompson, Thornton, Trammell, Turner, Walker, Walters, Watkins, Wells, White, Willcoxen (also spelled Willcoxon), Williams, Wilson, Woodyard, Wrenn, Wright, and Young.
</p>
<p>The Commonwealth of Virginia is the primary plaintiff in 23 suits between 1870 and 1938; Fairfax County is the primary plaintiff in 15 suits between 1909 and 1925; the National Bank of Fairfax is involved in 17 suits between 1908 and 1934; the Peoples National Bank of Leesburg is involved in 10 suits between 1908 and 1938; and W. H. May &amp; Son (also called W. H. May &amp; Son Inc.) is the primary plaintiff in 15 suits between 1901 and 1932.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are generally as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)</p>
<p>Chancery Causes 1914-1970 are processed and indexed information is available on the Chancery Records Index, but digital images are not available at this time. Contact the Fairfax County Circuit Court Clerk for availability.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Original Fairfax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1803-1970, are retained in the locality. Contact the Clerk of the Circuit Court for access.</p>
</originalsloc>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Fairfax County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.</extref></p>
        <p>Fairfax County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Fairfax County Records may be found in the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available the Library of Virginia website.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
   <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is “of interest” is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.</title></p> 
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1846-033: George Kephart vs. Joseph Bruin:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Joseph Bruin and George Kephart were notorious slave traders based in Alexandria, Virginia. Kephart sued Bruin to recover money owed him for selling enslaved people on Bruin’s behalf. Numerous accounts and receipts document sales of enslaved persons, many of which contain the names of the enslaved and the individual who purchased them. The names of over 100 enslaved persons were found in the suit.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1859-050: Joseph Bruin vs. Samuel Wren:</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Samuel Wren sold Matilda Washington, an enslaved woman, to Joseph Bruin for over 700 dollars. Afterwards, Bruin accused Wren of fraudulently representing Matilda as being “sound and healthy in body and mind,” since she suffered from either menses or asthma. The deponent in the case was Benjamin Rose, a physician who provided medical care for the people enslaved by Wren. At the time the deposition was taken, Rose lived in Texas. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
            </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>