<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03654">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04869::A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015)//EN" "vi04869.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">
          <num type="collectionnumber">51854
</num>
        </subtitle>
        <author>Paige Neal
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2016  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from paper, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 September 2017</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2017-09-15</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">51854
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Paige Neal
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Paige Neal
</label>
          <item/>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">51854
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">XX
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">LVA
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, [cite specific recording used], Accession 51854, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
	<p>Accession 51854, transferred on 28 June 2016.
</p>
	
        
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>XX
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the General Assembly passed at the May 1779 session and has continued to the present day. Its antecedent was the General Court, which, after it was reestablished under the constitution of 1776, shared appellate jurisdiction with the Supreme Court until 1851, when the new state constitution abolished the General Court. Prior to that date the General Court had criminal jurisdiction, while the Supreme Court was restricted to civil cases. While the court now has concurrent original jurisdiction in issuing and hearing writs of habeas corpus, mandamus and prohibition, retirement, removal, and matters of judicial censure, its jurisdiction is almost exclusively appellate. An act of the General Assembly passed on March 16, 1971 changed the name of the court to the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>
	<p>Justices are elected by a majority vote of both houses of the General Assembly for a term of twelve years.  Vacancies on the court occuring between sessions of the General Assembly may be filled by the Governor for a term expiring thirty days after the commencement of the next session of the General Assembly.  By statute, the Chief Justice is chosen by a majority vote of the seven justices.</p>
<p>By statute, the court by designate a retired justice to serve as Senior Justice for a renewable one year term.  Senior Justices sit with the court during regular sessions hearing writs and sitting on merit cases, especially when an active member of the court is recused from hearing a particular case.</p>

<p>The Court of Appeals of Virginia was established on January 1, 1985.  It provides appellate review of final decisions of ghe circuit courts in domestic relations matters, appeals from decisions of an administrative agency, traffic infractions and criminal cases, except where a sentence of death has been imposed.  It also hears appeals of final decisions of the Virginia Workers' Compensation Commission.  Except in those cases where the decision of the Court of Appeals is final, any party aggrrieved by a decision of the Court of Appeals may petition the Supreme Court for an appeal.  The Court of Appeals consists of eleven judges.  The court sits in panels of at least three judges, and the membership of the panels is rotated.  The court sits at such locations as the chief judge designates, so as to provide convenient access to the various geographic areas of the Commonwealth.</p>

<p>Biographical information related to individuals documented in this collection (in alphabetical order):</p>

<p>Judge Rosemarie Annunziata (b. 1940) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1995-2005, and as a senior judge on the court from 2005 to 2015.  She was a circuit court judge in Fairfax County from 1989 to 1995.</p>

<p>Judge James W. Benton, Jr. (b. 1944) was appointed to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1985 and retired in 2007.  A native of Norfolk, Benton attended public schools there and participated in civil rights demonstrations while he was in high school.  He earned an undergraduate degree from Temple University and a law degree from the University of Virginia.  He worked for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund in Richmond and was a partner at the Richmond law firm of Hill, Tucker Marsh.</p>

<p>Justice Harry Lee Carrico (1916-1913) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1961 and was Chief Justice from 1981-2003.  He took senior status in 2003.  Before joining the court, he was a lawyer and judge in Fairfax County.  Carrico was born in Washington, D.C. and reared in rural Fauquier and Fairfax counties. He was an ensign in the Navy during World War II.</p>

<p>Justice George Cochran (1912-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1969 to 1987.  A life long resident of Staunton, he was a member of the House of Delegates from 1948 to 1966 and the Virginia Senate from 1966 to 1968.</p>

<p>Judge Samuel W. Coleman (b. 1940) served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 1985-2001.  He has served as a senior (retired) judge from 2001-2010 and 2013 to present.  Coleman was born in Kingsport, TN, and grew up in Gate City, VA, where he attended public schools.  He earned an undergraduate degree from the University of Virginia and a law degree from Washington and Lee University.  He practiced law in Gate City until he was elected circuit court judge in the Thirteenth Circuit (Lee, Scott, and Wise Counties).  In 1985, Coleman was elected to the first Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p>

<p>Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr. (b. 1944) was appointed to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 2002 and he retired in 2014.  He served as chief judge from 2006 to 2014.  A native of Suffolk, Felton attended public schools there, and college and law school at the University of Richmond.  He practiced law in Suffolk, taught law at the College of William and Mary, and worked in the Office of the Attorney General and the office of Governor James S. Gilmore before he was appointed to the court.</p>

<p>Judge Johanna L. Fitzpatrick (b. 1946) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1992 to 2006.  A native of Birmingham, Alabama, she attended Tufts University and earned a law degree from Catholic University.  She began working for the Fairfax Legal Aid Society in 1974.  In 1980 she was elected judge of the Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court in Fairfax County, making her the second woman elected judge in Virginia.  In 1982, Fitzpatrick was elected circuit court judge in Fairfax County.</p>

<p>Judge Robert P. Frank (b. 1944) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2005 to 2012, when he took senior status.  He was born and raised in Newport News, Virginia.  He earned his undergraduate and law degrees from the University of Virginia and then practiced law with his brother in Newport News from 1968 to 1986, when he was elected judge of the Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court, Seventh Judicial Circuit in Newport News.</p>

<p>Judge James W. Haley, Jr. (b. 1942) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2005-2012, when he took senior status.  He was born in Washington, DC and was raised in Arlington, Virginia.  Haley attended Washington and Lee University and the University of Virginia School of Law.  He was a law clerk for Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia John W. Eggleston, 1967-1968, and then worked as an assistant commonwealth's attorney in Arlington County.  He practiced law in Fredericksburg and was County Attorney for King George County.  In 1985, he was elected general district judge in the Fifteenth Judicial Circuit, and in 1989 because a circuit court judge in the same ciruit.  He was elected to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 2005.</p>

<p>Judge William H. Hodges (b. 1929) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985-1989.  He was a state delegate, 1962-1966, and a state senator, 1966-1972, when he was elected as a circuit court judge.  He practiced law in Norfolk and Chesapeake from 1960-1972.  He continued to serve as a substitute judge after he retired in 1989.</p>

<p>Justice Barbara Milano Keenan (b. 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1991 to 2010, when was confirmed as a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.  Previously she was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1991.  She was the first woman to serve as a circuit and appellate court judge in Virginia.</p>

<p>Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr. (b. 1940) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1995 to 2011, when he took senior status.  He was one of ten judges who served on the first Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1985 and served on that court until 1995.  He was the second chief judge of the court, serving from 1985 to 1993.  From 1976 to 1984, Koontz was a circuit court judge in the 23rd judicial circuit in Roanoke; from 1968 to 1976, he was a juvenile and domestic relations judge in the general distict court in Roanoke.</p>

<p>Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy (b. 1945) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1989 to 2007, when she took senior status.  She was the first woman to serve on the court, the first woman to serve as Deputy Attorney General in Virginia, and the first woman to as a judge on the State Corporation Commission.  Lacy was born in South Carolina and grew up in Wisconsin.  She worked in Texas as as an Assistant Attorney General and Division Chief (1972-1976) before moving to Virginia.  She was Virginia Deputy Attorney General overseeing civil litigation (1982-1985) and Judge, State Corporation Commission (1985-1989).</p>

<p>Justice Charles S. Russell (b. 1926) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1981.  He returned to the court as a senior justice in 2004.  Russell practiced law in Arlington and Fairfax from 1951 to 1967, and was appointed judge for the 17th Judicial District in 1967.  From 1967 to 1982 Russell was a circuit court judge in Fairfax County.  Russell was born in Richmond, Virginia, and served in the U.S. Navy in World War I and in the Korean War.</p>

<p>Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997, when he took senior status.  A lifelong resident of Covington, Va., Stephenson practiced law there and was Alleghany County Commonwealth's Attorney and a judge on the 25th judicial circuit befor his appointment to the Supreme Court.</p>

<p>Justice John Charles Thomas (b. 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1983 to 1989.  A native of Norfolk, Thomas graduated from the University of Virginia law school in 1975 and worked at Hunton and Williams law firm in Richmond, where he became the first African American to be named partner in a law firm in the South.  When Thomas resigned from the Supreme Court in 1989, he returned to private practice at Hunton and Williams.</p>

<p>Justice W. Carrington (William Carrington) Thompson (1915-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1980 to 1983.  A native of Chatham, Virginia, he attended law school at the University of Virginia and established a law practice in Chatham after returning from service in the Navy during World War II.  Thompson served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1959 to 1968 and the Virginia Senate from 1968 to 1973.  He was a circuit judge before his appointment to the Supreme Court.</p>

<p>Justice Henry H. Whiting (b. 1923) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1987 to 1995, when he took senior status.  Whiting was born in Fort Logan, Colorado, and spent most of his youth in Winchester, Virginia.  He atteneded Virginia Tech for one year before enlisting in the U.S. Army during World War II.  After the war, he attended the University of Virginia and earned a law degree in 1949.  He practices law in Winchester for much of his career.  In 1980 Whiting was appointed to the 28th Judicial Circuit by Governor John Dalton; in 1987 he was elected by the General Assembly to the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>
       
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>These recording include Supreme Court of Virginia and Court of Appeals of Virginia audio and video recordings of court ceremonies and oral history interviews, 1969-2015.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies, 1991-2011</item>
	<item>Series II.</item>
	<item>Series III. Audio recordings of court ceremonies, 1969-2005</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>



      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1991-2011</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 23 video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

	
          <p>This series contains 23 video recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1991-2011.  Includes investitures and swearing-in ceremonies, portrait presentation ceremonies, as well as retirement and anniversary ceremonies.  The ceremonies took place in the courtroom in Richmond unless otherwise noted. </p>
<p>Includes the following ceremonies:</p>

<p>Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Courtroom 5-E, Fairfax Judicial Center in Fairfax, Virginia, 1991 July 2.  Includes one video recording of the entire ceremony with poor audio (43 minutes) and two segments of the television show Law Weekly (60 minutes), a production of the Fairfax County Bar Association, moderated by Glenn C. Lewis, with highlights of the ceremony and interviews with guests.  The segments were broadcast on the Fairfax County public access television station, FCAC Channel 10.  The ceremony was the first televised session of the Supreme Court.  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; with remarks by Raymond Diaz, president of the Virginia State Bar; William D. Dolan, III, past president of the Virginia State Bar; Governor L. Douglas Wilder; Speaker of the House A. L. Philpott; State Senator Edward M. Holland; State Senator Richard L. Saslow; Retired Judge Arthur W. Sinclair; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Johanna Fitzpatrick; and Justice Keenan.  The second segment of the recording features host Glenn Lewis interviewing guests Emilie Miller, Virginia State Senator; Fairfax County Commonwealth's Attorney Robert H. Horan; Chief Justice Carrico; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Charles H. Duff; William Dolan, Raymond Diaz, Judge Sinclair, Judge Richard T. Horan, Justice Keenan, Ann Milano, retired Clerk Delores Testerman, Judith Wheat, and Jerry Phillips.</p>

<p>Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Olin Hall, Roanoke College, Salem, Virginia, 1995 August 16 (49 minutes and 30 seconds).  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by George W. Wooten; Judge Beverly T. Fitzpatrick; Michael Smith, president of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate C. Richard Cranwell; and Justice Koontz.  Invocation and benediction by Rev. R. Paul Hendrickson, Chaplain, Roanoke College.  The recording also includes clips of local television news coverage of the event (WDBJ News 7 and WSLS News 10).</p>

<p>Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Lee High School, Jonesville, Virginia, 1997 July 8 (1 hour, 32 minutes).  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor George Allen; Senior Judge Glenn Williams, U.S. District Court, Western District of Virginia; Justice Kinser, and others.  The recording includes footage before and after the ceremony and the following reception. Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997.  She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2010.  She is the first woman to serve as chief justice.</p>

<p>Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 2003 January 1 (43 minutes, 18 seconds).  Poor quality video recording.  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary; and Justice Donald W. Lemons; presentation of slideshow with photographs of family and court staff.</p>

<p>Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (36 minutes, 41 seconds). Justice Barbara Milano Keenan, presiding; invocation and benediction by George Martin; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Speaker of the House of Delegates, William Howell; Bernard DiMuro, president of the Virginia State Bar; Colonel George B. Mason, Jr., Virginia Capitol Police; Justice Keenan; and Chief Justice Hassell.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 265 Virginia Reports, vii-xviii. Produced by Craig Keeton, Community Idea Stations, Richmond, Va. Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011.  He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007.  He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (45 seconds).  Justice Barbara M. Keenan administering the oath of office, with Chief Justice Hassell's wife, Linda Hassell, holding the Bible.  Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011.  He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007.  He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.</p>


<p>Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, recorded at Roanoke College in Salem, Va., 2003 March 5 (1 hour, 5 minutes, and 35 seconds).  Chief Justice Hassel, presiding; remarks by State Senator Charles Hawkins, Delegate Robert McDonnell, Attorney General Jerry Kilgore, Delegate Lacy Putney, and Justice Agee.  G. Steven Agee served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 2003-2008, when he was appointed to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.  Previously, he was judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2001-2003.</p>

<p>Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 June 1 (47 minutes). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Senior Justice Harry L. Carrico; U.S. District Court Judge John A. Gibney; Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; Trish Harrington, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia; Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia; and David Beach. (Video in two parts)  David Beach was Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1984-2003.</p>


<p>Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2004 December 9 (41 minutes, 48 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., presiding; invocation by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Lt. Governor Timothy Kaine; Attorney General Jerry Kilgore; Senator Kenneth Stolle, Chair, Court of Justice Committee; Speaker of the House J. Morgan Griffith; David B. Bobzien, President of the Virginia State Bar; and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>


<p>Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2005 March 24 (1 hour, 11 minutes, 51 seconds).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Bill Howell, Speaker of the House; Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna Fitzpatrick; James Ullman, former chair, House Courts Committee; Retired Judge J.R. Zepkin, Judge Phillip Trompeter, and Larry Palmer, Clerk, Lynchburg Circuit Court.  (Video in two parts) Robert N. Baldwin was Executive Secretary for the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1976-2005</p>

<p>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell, 2006 February 28 (28 minutes, 8 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix-xii.  Harry L. Carrico (1916-2013) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1961 to 2003 and was Chief Justice from 1981 to 2003.  A. Christian Compton (1929-2006) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1975 to 2000.  Charles Russell served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1991, and returned as a senior justice in 2004.  Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997.</p>

<p>Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution, 2006 November 2 (46 minutes, 35 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding; remarks by Lt. Governor William Bolling; Attorney General Robert F. McDonnell; Speaker of the House William Howell; President of the Senate John H. Chichester; Senator Benjamin Lambert; Karen A. Gould, President of the Virginia State Bar; Governor Tim Kaine; and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2007 October 10 (12 minutes, 48 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy, R. Hassell, Sr., administering the oath of office to Goodwyn, who is accompanied by his wife, Sharon Smith Goodwyn, and his two children.  Brief remarks by Chief Justice Hassell, and greetings from Senior Justices Elizabeth Lacy and Charles Russell; Executive Secretary Karl Hade; and Patricia Harrington, Clerk.</p>

<p>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 February 22, Manassas, Virginia. (Length?).  Chief Judge William S. Fenton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Paul B. Ebert, Prince William County Commonwealth's Attorney; Senator Charles Colgan (presenting commission); William G. Petty, Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia; Robert J. Zelnick; John D. McGaven; and Justice Millette.  LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008.  He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.</p>

<p>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2008 September 5 (2 hours, 7 minutes).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Delegate Robert G. Marshall; remarks by Senator Henry L. Marsh, III; Manuel A. Capsalis, President of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate Jackson H. Miller; Delegate Jennifer L. McClellan; Governor Timothy M. Kaine; Senator Charles J. Colgan; and Justice Millette.  Benediction by Delegate Ward L. Armstrong.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 276 Virginia Reports, xi-xxii.  LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008.  He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.</p>

<p>Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 November 17 (48 minutes, 21 seconds).  Chief Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Senator Henry Marsh; First Lady Anne B. Holton; Governor Tim Kaine; Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr.; and Judge Powell.  Cleo Elaine Powell was the first African-American woman appointed to an appellate court in Virginia.</p>

<p>Investiture of William C. Mims as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2010 April 9 (1 hour, 10 minutes).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Stephen R. McCullough; remarks by Senator Thomas K. Norment, Jr.; Senator Richard L. Saslaw; Mark E. Rubin; Jon D. Huddleston, on behalf of the statwide bar associations from Virginia; Speaker William J. Howell; Govenor Robert F. McDonnell; Courney M. Malveaux; Judge Dean S. Worcester; Justice Mims; and Attorney General Mark L. Earley.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 279 Virginia Reports, xxv-xivi.  William C. Mims was elected to the Supreme Court of Virginia on March 10, 2010.  Previously he was Chief Deputy Attorney General under Attorney General Robert McDonnell, and Attorney General following McDonnell's resignation to campaign for Governor.</p>

<p>Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 February 16 (47 minutes).  Justice Donald W. Lemons, presiding; remarks by Governor Robert F. McDonnell; Senior Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; and Chief Justice Kinser.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 281 Virginia Reports, xi-xxiv.  Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997.  She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2011.  She was the first woman to serve as chief justice.</p>

<p>Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 September 1 (46 minutes, 28 seconds).  Chief Justice Cynthia Kinser, presiding; invocation by Reverend Betty C. Reiff; remarks by Retired Chief Judge of the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna L. Fitzpatrick; Senator William C. Wampler, Jr.; Delegate Terry G. Kilgore; Governor Robert F. McDonnell; former Attorney General Jerry W. Kilgore; Hon. Joseph P. Johnson, Jr.; benediction by Reverend Walter P. Weikel.  Elizabeth A. McClanahan was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 2011.  She was a judge on the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2003 to 2011.</p>





        </scopecontent>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1991 July 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Video" type="box">1
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1995 August 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1997 July 8</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 January 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 February 11</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 February 11</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

        <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 March 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 June 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2004 December 9</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>



<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2005 March 31</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>


<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2006 February 28</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2006 November 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>




<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 October 10</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 February 22</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 September 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 November 17</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of William C. Mims as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2010 April 9</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011 February 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011 September 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>







</c01>

	
 <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Miscellanous court video recordings,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">XX</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: XX video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

<p>Miscellaneous court video recordings include various presentations and speeches.</p>
           
  </scopecontent>   

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>XX,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">XX</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02> 

</c01> 

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Audio recordings of court ceremonies,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1969-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 18 digital audio recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

<p>This series contains audio recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia ceremonies, 1969-2005; and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1985-1989.  The ceremonies took place in the courtrooms of the Supreme Court of Virginia and the Court of Appeals of Virginia in Richmond.</p>

<p>The Supreme Court ceremonies include investiture and portrait presentation ceremonies, 1969-1985; the bicentennial of the court, 1979; and the dedication of the Supreme Court Building, 1981.  Investitures includ of those of Justice John Charles Thomas, the first African-American justice of the court, in 1983, and Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, the first female justice on the court, in 1989.</p>

<p>This series also contain recordings of three Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremnonies: the swearing-in ceremony of the first court, 1985; the swearing-in ceremony for Judge Jere M.H. Willis, Jr., 1989; and the portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, 1985.</p>

<p>This series includes the following audio files:</p>

<p>Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harmon as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice, 1969 October 1 (24 minutes).  Remarks by Justice W. I'Anson honoring Chief Justice Snead; Chief Justice Snead, presiding over investitures; remarks by Howard C. Gilmer, Harmon's former law partner.</p>

<p>Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1972 August 30 (11 minutes, 49 seconds).  Chief Justice Harold Snead, presiding; remarks by former Governor William M. Tuck and the Hon. Lewis F. Powell, Associate Justice, U.S. Supreme Court.</p>

<p>Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the founding of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1979 August 30 (29 minutes).  Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Chief Justice I'Anson; and U.S. Supreme Court Justice Lewis Powell, Jr., read by his son Lewis Powell, III.  The ceremony includes the presentation of the portrait of Henry Tazewell, who served on the court from 1785 to 1788 and 1793 to 1794.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 220 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan, 1980 April 17 (14 minutes, 22 seconds).  Chief Justice I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Justice Alexander Harmon.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xi.</p>
 
<p>Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1981 March 2 (23 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William S. Moffatt, Chief Judge, 25th Judicial Circuit; presentation of resolutions honoring Stephenson.</p>

<p>Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building, 1981 Dec 4 (35 minutes, 18 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Delegate George Allen, Jr.; State Senator Edward E. Willey; Governor John Dalton; and Chief Justice Carrico.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead, 1982 June 16 (50 minutes, 38 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William B. Poff; former Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and Governor Charles S. Robb.  A transcript of the ceremony in published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xix.</p>

<p>Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1983 April 25 (34 minutes, 28 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; T.S. Ellis, III; Dennis C. Montgomery; and Justice Thomas; presentation of resolutions honoring Thomas. John Charles Thomas was the first African-American to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, 1983 June 15 (45 minutes, 14 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Virginia Senator Edward E. Willey; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; and others.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 225 Virginia Reports, p. vii.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1985 January 4 (30 minutes, 4 seconds).  Chief Judge E. Ballard Baker, presiding; remarks by William D. Dolan, III, President of the Virginia State Bar; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia; Edward Willey, President Pro Tempore, Senate of Virginia; Delegate Theodore V. Marsden, Jr.; and Governor Charles S. Robb.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corporation Commission, 1985 April 1 (18 minutes).  Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice Supreme Court, Supreme Court of Virginia, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; Judge Thomas P. Harwood, Jr., member, State Corporation Commission; Commissioner Lacy; and Attorney General Gerald S. Baliles.  Commission read by G. Patrick Lacy.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1986 May 5 (19 minutes).  Chief Judge Lawrence Koontz, presiding; remarks by Chief Judge Koontz; Governor Gerald L. Baliles; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice, Supreme Court of Virginia; James C. Roberts, Past President of the Virginia State Bar; and Billy Jane Baker, widow of Judge Baker.</p>

<p>Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 January 4 (25 minutes, 52 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; invocation and benediction by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Balilies and Justice Lacy; presentation of resolutions honoring Lacy.  Elizabeth B. Lacy was the first woman to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court Justice George M. Cochran, 1989 April 20 (50 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by former Governor and retired justice Albertis S. Harrison; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; retired Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and others.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 238 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges, 1989 October 26 (22 minutes, 4 seconds, partially inaudible).  Chief Judge Koontz, presiding.</p>

<p>Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 Dec 28 (26 minutes, 30 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Baliles and Justice Hassell; presentation of resolutions honoring Hassell.</p>

<p>Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2000 April 3 (45 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by State Senator Walter Stosch; Governor James S. Gilmore; and Justice Lemons; presentation of resolutions honoring Lemons.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson and Henry Hudson Whiting, 2005 November 1 (11 minutes, 37 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, presiding.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

           
  </scopecontent>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harman as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1969 Oct q</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1972 Aug 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1979 Aug 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1980 Apr 17</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1981 Mar 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1981 Dec 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1982 June 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1983 Apr 25</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02> 

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Lawrence W. I'Anson,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1983 June 15</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1985 Jan 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corportion Commission,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1985 Apr 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for E. Baker Ballard, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1986 May 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>



<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Jan 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court George M. Cochran,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Apr 20</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Oct 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Dec 28</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2000 Apr 3</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>     

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson, and Henry Hudson Whiting,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2005 Nov 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  






</c01>             
              
<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Video recordings of Supreme Court Oral History Interviews,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2007-2015</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 8 video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

	
          <p>This series includes 8 video recordings of oral history interviews with retired Supreme Court of Virginia justices.  The interviews were conducted for the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission beginning in 2007.  The Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Advisory Committee (formerly Commission) was established in 2006 to preserve and promote the history of the court.  Oral history interviews of retired Supreme Court justices, Court of Appeals judges, other individuals associated with the court, and civil rights attorneys were begun in 2007 and the project is ongoing.</p>

<p>Includes the following oral history interviews:</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 April 12 (78 minutes, transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Carrico discusses changes he witnessed during his long tenure on the court, his experiences as a young lawyer and judge in northern Virginia (Alexandria, and Fairfax and Prince William counties) in the 1940s and 1950s, his work on the Judicial Conference of the U.S. and his relationships with U.S. Supreme Court Justices Warren Burger and William Rehnquist.  Toward the end of the interview, he reflects on his relationships with the justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia when he was appointed in 1961, his workflow and opinion-writing process, the creation of the Office of the Executive Secretary (court administrator), and the appointments of the first African American and women justices to the court.</p>	

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 November 8 (1 hour, 57 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Carrico discusses his family and early life on a dairy farm in rural Fairfax County, his father's work as a billboard artist for the General Outdoor Advertising Company and his business operating a riding stable.  He recalls going to a combined grade school and high school in Bailey's Crossroads and attending Lee-Jackson High School in Fairfax County, and working and attending law school in Washington, D.C.  He discusses his experience working in contract terminations in the Navy during world War II, his work as a lawyer and judge in Fairfax County before and after the war, and his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia 1961.  Toward the end of the interview, Carrico talks about the process of writing opinions, and his decision in Loving v. Commonwealth of Virginia, which upheld the state statute barring interracial marriage in 1967.  He reflects on the changes in the court during his tenure, including the appointment of the first African American and women justices, and his recollections of the justices who were on the court when he was appointed in 1961 (Chief Justice John Eggleston, Justice L. Warren I'Anson, Justice Claude V. Spratley, Justice Harold S. Snead).  The interview ends with a discussion of Carrico's work for the John Marshall Foundation and his thoughts about the historical importance of Marshall's contributions to the judiciary.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice George M. Cochran by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 March 30 (1 hour, 56 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Cochran talks about his family's roots in Staunton, his ancestor Alexander H.H. Stuart and Stuart's political career before and after the Civil War.  He reflects on his early life in Staunton, his education at Episcopal High School in Alexandria and at the University of Virginia, and his service in the navy in California and the Pacific during World War II.  He discusses being a state legislator during the 1950s and 1960s and efforts by a younger general of legislators to repeal the poll tax and segregation laws after World War II.  Cochran also reflects on Massive Resistance and working to establish a community college system in Virginia.  He talks about working with fellow state legislators Armistead Booth, Mosby G. Perrow, Tayloe Murphy, Mills Godwin and Albertis Harrison, and Governor Colgate Darden and Governor Lindsay Almond.  Toward the end of the interview, Cochran talks about his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia, his friendship with Albertis Harrison when they were both on the court, his thoughts about dissenting from the majority, and making the transition from writing legal briefs to writing judicial opinions.  The interview concludes with Cochran's recollections about organizing meetings of the Virginia State Bar Association in England and Scotland, the appointment of the first African Ameerican and women justices to the court, and socializing with other out-of-town justices at the John Marshall Hotel in Richmond.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge Barbara Milano Keenan by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2013 June 6 (2 hours, 38 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Judge Keenan talks about her family's history and the influence of their experiences as immigrants in West Virginia in the early twentieth century, attending Catholic high school in Arlington, Virginia, and college at Cornell University during the 1960s; and working at the U.S. Department of Justice while attending Law School at George Washington University.  She discusses her early career as an assistant commonwealth's attorney in Fairfax, and her service on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, the Supreme Court of Virginia and the Fourth Circuit, U.S. Court of Appeals.  She also reflects on the experience of being among the first women judges in Virginia and the influences of mentors and colleagues throughout her career.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., by Gail Warren, State Law Librarian, 2013 May 17 (55 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Koontz talks about growing up in Salem, Virginia, attending Virginia Tech and law school at the University of Richmond, and his early years as a lawyer, commonwealth's attorney, and judge in Roanoke.  He reflects on the experience of forming rules and procedures for the Court of Appeals of Virginia, serving on the Supreme Court of Virginia, and changes in the legal profession and the judiciary during his career.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2008 Sept 15 (1 hour, 56 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Lacy talks about growing up in Oshkosh, Wisconsin, where her parents owned a business in the 1950s; her education at Catholic schools in Oshkosh and St. Mary's College at Notre Dame; and attending law school at the University of Texas in Austin.  She talks about her early legal career working for the Texas Legislative Council and the Texas Attorney General's office, where she became the first woman division chief.  She reflects on the political atmosphere in Texas when she was in law school and in the early years of her legal career, and the influence of women such as Barbara Jordan, Kay Bailey Hutchinson, Sarah Weddinton, and others who were elected to public office in Texas in the late 1960s and early 1970s.  In the second part of the interview, Justice Lacy recounts moving to Virginia in the late 1970s, her work as Deputy Attorney General under Attorney General Gerald Baliles, her appointment to the State Corporation Commission in 1985 and her work there, and her subsequent appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989.  The interview ends with Lacy's reflections on her early experiences on the court and changes in the court during her tenure.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Charles S. Russell by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 April 23 (1 hour, 8 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Russell talks about his experience as a circuit court judge in Arlington County and his tenure on the Supreme Court of Virginia.  He discusses his election to the court by one vote in 1982 and reflects on the changes in the Virginia judiciary during his tenure as a justice, particularly a greater acceptance of dissent and declining deference toward older justices.  Russell also talks about the colorful personalities he remembers from his early years as a member of the Arlington County bar.  Russell also reflects on memorable cases and historical events during his career.  The interview closes with Russell's recollection of watching the attack on the Pentagon from his office window in Arlington in Arlington on September 11, 2001, and his thoughts about the lasting impact of the event.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Apr 30 (1 hour, 27 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Stephenson talks about his parents and siblings and growing up in Covington, Virginia, where his father was a lawyer.  He recalls attending Washingtong and Lee University as an undergraduate and working on a construction project in Hampton and a steamer out of Baltimore during the break between college and law school after he was discharged from the army on account of aheart murmer.  Stephenson recalls that he was only one of two students attending law school at Washington and Lee University in 1945 because of World War II.  He talks of returning to Covington after law school, practicing law there with his father in the 1950s, and being Commonwealth's Attorney and circuit court judge in Alleghany County.  Stephenson reflects on changes in the judiciary beginning in the 1970s, particularly the increase of women in the profession and the appointment of Elizabeth Lacy to the court as the first female justice in 1989.  In the second part of the interview, Stephenson talks about his approach to writing opinions and about cases that were particularly memorable.  He discusses the use of DNA evidence in the Spencer v. Commonwealth case, other death penalty cases, and cases involving the rights to mine coal and gas.  The interview closes with Stephenson's recollections of his relationships with other justices and law clerks, and memories of socializing with out-of-town justices at the John Marshall Hotel in Richmond when the court was in session.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice John Charles Thomas by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Aug 8 (2 hours, 21 minutes; transcript avaialable at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Thomas discusses his family's roots in the Huntersville neighborhood of Norfolk, growing up in segregated Norfolk, and the influence on him of his parents, grandparents, extended family, community, school and church.  He recalls his maternal grandfather, who taught him to recite poetry when he was a young boy, and the minister of the First Baptist Church.  He talks about his decision to attend Maury High School, a predominately white high school in Norfolk, in 1965, and his experiences as a student there; and attending the University of Virginia.  Thomas also reflects on clerking for the Civil Right Division of the Justice Department one summer when he was a law student, and how this experience helped him in his efforts to secure a position at a large law firm in Virginia after he graduated.  He recounts his early years working at the Richmond law firm Hunton and Williams, where he did legal work for Virginia Electric and Power Company, and becoming the first African American lawyer to make partner at a white law firm in the South.  Toward the end of the interview, Justice Thomas discusses his appointment fo the Supreme Court of Virginia and being the first African American appointed to the court.  He reflects on differneces between himself and the other justices, in style, training and age.  The interview closes with Thomas' thoughts on memorable opinions.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice W. Carrington Thompson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 November 14 (1 hour, 32 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Thompson talks about his parents and his early life in Chatham, Virginia, particularly the influence of his father; his experience as a student at Hampden-Sydney College, his professors, his religious education and the importance of his religious faith throughout his life.  He talks about attending law school at the University of Virginia and being in the Navy during World War II in the South Pacific.  Thompson recalls his career in Chatham as a lawyer, state legislator, and circuit court judge.  He reflects on the political circumstances of his appointments to the circuit court and the Supreme Court of Virginia, and his decision to retire after serving only three years.  The interview closes with Thompson's thoughts on writing opinions in two death penalty cases while he was on the court, his views on the death penalty, and his strict constructionist views on the Constitution and the role of the judiciary.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Justice Henry H. Whiting by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2011 December 12 (1 hour, 35 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Justice Whiting talks about his family, growing up in Winchester, Virginia; serving in the Army during World War II and witnessing the Battle of Remagen, and his thoughts on General George S. Patton, who knew his father and godfather; attending college at Virginia Tech and the University of Virginia and attending law school at the University of Virginia; and practicing law in Winchester.  Toward the end of the interview, he discusses being a circuit court judge in Winchester, his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia, and serving on the court.</p>
		 

</scopecontent>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 April 12</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Sept 28</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice George M. Cochran by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Mar 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge Barbara Milano Keenan by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2013 June 6</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>
		
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., by Gail Warren, State Law Librarian, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2013 May 17</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2015 Sept 15</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Charles S. Russell by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Apr 23</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Apr 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice John Charles Thomas by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Aug 8</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice W. Carrington Thompson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 Nov 14</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Justice Henry H. Whiting by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011 Dec 12</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>
		
            
            
	


</c01>

 

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series IV. Video recordings of Court of Appeals Oral History Interviews,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2009-2015</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 8 video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

	
          <p>This series includes 8 video recordings of oral history interviews with judges who served on the Virginia Court of Appeals.  Oral history interviews were conducted by Cassandra Newby-Alexander, Professor of History, Norfolk State University, for the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives.  The interviews were conducted for the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission beginning in 2007.  The Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Advisory Committee (formerly Commission) was established in 2006 to preserve and promote the history of the court.  Oral history interviews of retired Supreme Court justices, Court of Appeals judges, other individuals associated with the court, and civil rights attorneys were begun in 2007 and the project is ongoing.</p>

<p>Includes the following oral history interviews:</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge James W. Benton, 2009 March 12, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 12 minutes, transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia).  Judge Benton discusses growing up in the Huntersville neighborhood of Norfolk, Va., attending segregated schools, participating in sit-in protests to desegregate public facilities, and being among the first African American students to attend a formerly white high school in Norfolk.  He talks about attending Temple University in Philadelphia, graduate school at Northwestern University in Chicago, and law school at the University of Virginia in the late 1960s and the experience of being one of the first African Americans to attend the law school.  He relates his experiences working as an attorney for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund and at the Richmond law firm of Hill, Tucker and Marsh; his work on the Norfolk school desegration court cases; and his work on business cases and housing descrimination cases in the 1970s and 1980s.  Benton also talks about the circumstances leading to his appointment on the Court of Appeals of Virginia when it was established in 1985, the work of establishing the court, his approach to his role as a judge, his thoughts about writing dissenting opinions, and his views on constitutional rights and criminal cases.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge Samuel W. Coleman, 2013 Dec 6, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 27 minutes, transcript available).  Judge Coleman talks about his family's roots in Scott County and growing up in Gate City, Va., his education, law practice in Gate City, and serving as a circuit court judge.  He also discusses making the transition to an appellate court judge and his experiences serving as a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Chief Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr., 2014 Nov 7, conducted at the Supreme Court Building (1 hour, 40 minutes, transcript available).  Judge Felton discusses growing up in Suffolk, attending public schools there, attending college and law school at the University of Richmond, and his career as an attorney, a professor at William and Mary, a deputry attorney in the Office of the Attorney General, Counselor to Governor James S. Gilmore, and as a judge and chief judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge Johanna Levenson Fitzpatrick, 2009 July 13, conducted at her home in Alexandria, Virginia (2 hours; transcript available).  Judge Fiztpatrick discusses her early life and growing up in Birmingham, Alabama, where her father owned a department store; her education at Tufts University and Catholic University Law School; working as a legal aid lawyer and on revisions to the Code on neglect and abuse of children; and her work as a juvenile and domestic relations judge and her appointment to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1992; choosing and mentoring law clerks, the process of writing opinions, differences working as a trial judge and an appellate judge, her decision to retire in 2006, and her subsequent career as a mediator.</p>    

<p>Oral history interview with Judge Robert P. Frank, 2014 Dec 19, conducted at his chambers in Newport News (1 hour, 26 minutes; transcript available).  Judge Frank discusses his childhood in Newport News, his family's roots in Europe and their immigration to Baltimore and Newport News; his family's connections to the Jewish community in Newport News, playing sports, attending public schools in Newport News and attending the University of Virginia.  He also talks about his career, first as a lawyer in private practice with his brother, and then as juvenile and domestic relations judge, a circuit court judge, and a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p> 

<p>Oral history interview with Judge James W. Haley, Jr., 2013 Sept 11, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (1 hour, 45 minutes; transcript available).  Judge Haley discusses growing up in Arlington County, Virginia, and the influence of his parents (his father was a lawyer who worked as a lobbyist for coal mines, and his mother wa an attorney for the Treasury Dept. before Haley was born) and teachers at St. Stephen's Episcopal School for Boys, Washington and Lee University, and the University of Virginia.  He reflects on his experience clerking for Chief Justice Eggleston (Supreme Court of Virginia), and discusses working for Commonwealth's Attorney William Hassan and working as a county attorney in King George County, as well as his experiences in private practice and as a district, circuit and appellate judge.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge William H. Hodges, 2015 Mar 6, conducted at his residence in Norfolk (1 hour, 44 minutes; transcript available).  Judge Hodges discusses growing up in rural Norfolk County, where his father farmed and worked as a police officer; attending Randolph Macon Military Academy in Winchester and Randolph Macon College in Ashland, and then law school at Washington and Lee.  He also discusses his career practicing law in Norfolk and Chesapeake, serving in the Virginia House of Delegates and Senate, and as a circuit court judge, and his experience as one of the founding members of the Court of Appeals of Virginia.</p>

<p>Oral history interview with Judge Rosemarie Annunziata, 2015 Nov 18, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 53 minutes; transcipt available).  Judge Annunziata discusses growing up a first-generation American in Newark and Irvington, New Jersey; her family's roots in the Puglia region of Italy; her education, including French studies at the Sorbonne, Paris, and at Yale University; working at the Montgomery Advertiser newspaper in Montgomery, Alabama, from 1963-1966; her work on the Fairfax County Planning Commission and other community work; attending law school after having a family; practicing law in Fairfax County; and her career as a circuit court and appellate judge.</p>
            
 </scopecontent>          
		
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge James W. Benton,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2009 Mar 12</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge Samuel W. Coleman,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2013 Dec 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge James S. Felton,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2014 Nov 7</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge Robert P. Frank,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2014 Dec 19</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge Joanna Levenson Fitzpatrick,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2009 July 13</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge James W. Haley, Jr.,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2013 Sept 11</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge William H. Hodges,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2015 Mar 6</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Oral history interview with Judge Rosemarie Annunziata,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2015 Nov 18</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Interview" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>








</c01>             
		
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>


