<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi04425">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04428::A Guide to the New Kent County (Va) Election Records, 1851-1932)//EN" "vi04428.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the New Kent County (Va) Election Records, <date>1851-1932</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">New Kent County (Va) Election Records
<num type="collectionnumber">1045036, 1045079-1045080
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>L Jones
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2018  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Louise Jones, <date>4 June 2019</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the New Kent County (Va) Election Records, <date>1851-1932</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection Number">1045036, 1045079-1045080
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2019 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Library of Virginia Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">New Kent County (Va) Election Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1851-1932
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1045036, 1045079-1045080
</unitid>
<physloc label="Storage Location">State Records Center-Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2 boxes and 3 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">New Kent County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>New Kent County (Va.) Election Records, 1851-1932. Local government records collection, New Kent County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These item came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from New Kent County (Va.). 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>New Kent County may have been named either for the English county of Kent or for Kent Island, in the upper waters of the Chesapeake Bay. William Claiborne, a native of Kent who had been driven from Kent Island by Lord Baltimore, was a prominent resident of the New Kent area about 1654 when the county was formed from York County. Part of James City County was added in 1767. The county seat is New Kent.  
</p>
<p>Records were destroyed when John Posey set fire to the courthouse on 15 July 1787. Many records were lost when the courthouse was partially destroyed by fire during Civil War hostilities in 1862. Additional records were burned in Richmond on 3 April 1865, where they had been moved for safekeeping during the Civil War. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>New Kent County (Va.) Election Records, 1851-1932 consist of individual items concerning elections, Abstracts of Voters for specific elections, and List of Voters.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional New Kent County Court Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref>
</p>
<p>New Kent County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional New Kent County records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost"> Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610$a">New Kent County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records--Virginia--New Kent County.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--New Kent County</genreform>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="analyticover">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Election Records,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1871-1907</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="box">1042957
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>There are three volumes in this box. List of White Voters at the New Kent Court House Precinct in Cumberland Township, 1871-1885. List of Colored Voters Registered at in New Kent Court House Precinct Cumberland Township. List of Colored Voters Registered at New Kent Court House Precinct Cumberland District, 1871-1873. A volume entitled "List of ____ Voters Registered at ______ Precinct", has two notices of Candidacy for the November Election 1907 and one notice of Candidacy for Election 1905. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Election Records Miscellaneous Papers</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1851-1928</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="volume">1045079
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This box contains Certificate of Elections 1851-1863 which includes a Certificate certifying that two persons received a majority of votes; about the 4th Thursday 1861 Election Day where voters elected Delegate, Clerk, Commissioners of Revenue, Sheriff, Commonwealth Attorney, Surveyors of the County, Constables by Districts, Overseers of the Poor by District, Justices of the Pease, Commissioner of Public Works, Governor, Lieutenant-Governor, Attorney General, Magistrates, Clerks of County Court and Circuit Court, and the Ratification or Rejection of "an Ordinance to Amend the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Virginia to strike out the 22nd and 23rd Sections of the 4th Article of Present Constitution". Petitions and Notices 1870-1914 includes for the Voting Precincts removal of Court House (Precinct) to Windsor Shades on September 1908, for a highway, Certificates of Elections 1870-1900, Election Certificate 1873, and for Appointment of Commissioners of Election July, 14, 1864. Oath of Office and Election Bonds, 1884-1898. Clemency for serving time in the County Jail. Notary Public Certificate. Judges of Election 1872[1873] 1883-1884 (3 items). A List of District Officers 1891. Charter 1891. Election Abstracts, 1870-1900. Abstracts 1918-1928 for United States, Senate and Representatives in Congress of United States, Members of the Sate Corporation Commission, Senate of Virginia, House of Delegates, President and Vice President of United States, Amendment to Constitution of Virginia, Governor of Virginia, Lieutenant-Governor of Virginia. Abstract of Votes for and against Constitutional Convention, State Treasurer of Virginia, Superintendent of Public Instruction of Virginia, Attorney General of Virginia, Secretary of the Commonwealth of Virginia, Commissioner of Agriculture and Immigration of Virginia, Election of President &amp; Vice President of the United States At General Election. Other papers about re-elections (including accounts and claims 1859-1871-1928, undated.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Election Records Miscellaneous Papers</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1866-1932</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
<container label="Barcode number" type="Volume">1045080
</container>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 box.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This collection contains the 1866 Individual Lists of Voters in District 1-4 of New Kent County for ensuing election August 1, 1866. One list for all voters with Supplemental List. Notices of Candidacy for 1895-1907 for Delegates for the House of Delegates, Senate, House of Representatives, Overseers of the Poor, Justice of the Peace, Supervisors of Districts, Office of Commonwealth Attorney, Office of Treasurer for County, Sheriff, and Commissioner of Revenue.  Four folders 1901-1932 (1901-1909)have List of Persons who Paid Capitation Tax by District (Whites and Colored) 1910-1919, 1920-1929, and 1930-1932, undated. Declaration of Expenses of Marly H. Barnes, in Democratic Primary 1903 for County Court. Election Expenses 1903. Election January and May 1866, Appointment of Commissioners for Polls for Districts 3 and 4. Election on Saturday, 27 June 1866 for Magistrate and Constables for each District and list of Voters.  Elections 24 May 1866 for Sheriff, Commissioner of Revenue and Constable for District 1, Districts 2 and 3, and District 4. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
