<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04144">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04144::A Guide to the Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, 1870-1875)//EN" "vi04144.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870-1875</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, 1870-1875
<num type="collectionnumber">1107009, 1107013, 1155962, 1155972, 1155981, 1156098
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2010 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Sarah Nerney, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5 April 2010</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870-1875</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode numbers:">1107009, 1107013, 1155962, 1155972, 1155981, 1156098
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Sarah Nerney
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Sarah Nerney
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870-1875
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Barcode numbers" encodinganalog="099$a">1107009, 1107013, 1155962, 1155972, 1155981, 1156098
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">State Records Center - Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">6 v.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Fauquier County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, 1870-1875. Local government records collection, Fauquier County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Some of these items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Fauquier County. Some volumes came to the Library of Virginia under the accession number 40529.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Fauquier County was named for Francis Fauquier, lieutenant governor of Virginia from 1758 to 1768. It was formed from Prince William County in 1759.
</p>
      <p>The 1870 Virginia Constitution required that each county in the state be divided into no less than three townships (see Article VII, section 2). Based on the New England administrative organization of a county, each township would elect the administration officials for the offices of supervisor, clerk, assessor, collector, commissioner of the roads, overseer of the poor, justice of the peace, and constable. The supervisors of each township would comprise the board of supervisors for the county, and would be responsible for auditing the county accounts, examining the assessors' books, regulating property valuation, and fixing the county levies. The Acts of Assembly provided that each township be divided into school and electoral districts (see Acts of Assembly 1869-1870, Chapter 39). A constitutional amendment in 1874 changed the townships into magisterial districts and each district elected one supervisor, three justices of the peace, one constable, and one overseer of the poor. The supervisors of the districts made up the county board of supervisors whose duties were identical as those set out in 1870. The published Acts of Assembly appended a list of township names by county following the acts for every year that townships existed in Virginia.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Fauquier County (Va.) Township Records, 1870-1875, consist of six volumes of minutes, accounts, and tax records relating to township activities and duties.
</p>
      <p>Cedar Run Township Record, 1871-1875, contains minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, qualification of road overseers, appointment of election judges, accounts claimed against the township board for road work, other accounts claimed against the township board for business of the board, establishment of tax and levy rates, occasional overseer of the poor claims, payments to township officials, reports of taxes collected, and other financial reports of the township collector.
</p>
      <p>Cedar Run Township Tax Book, 1873-1874, consists of taxes kept by the township collector. The volume pages are divided in half down the center. The left side of the page contains the taxed person's name and the amount of tax due to land, town lots, and personal property. The right hand of the page contains a form for each taxed person calculating the amount of tax including acres of land and total value of that land as well as whether or not payment was received. This form was filled out by the collector and could be torn off and returned to the individual as receipt of payment. Some of these have been cut or torn out and presumably returned to the taxed person as their receipt of payment, but many have not. The volume is organized more or less alphabetically by surname for 1873 and then 1874. There is no index.
</p>
      <p>Centre Township Accounts, 1872-1875, consists of warrants issued by the township clerk (1872) and reports of the township in account with the clerk and treasurer (1873-1875). In the reports of the township, the reason for the payment is usually given, beginning in 1874. References are made to payments related to township officials, small pox, road work, and goods or services provided to township paupers.
</p>
      <p>Centre Township Board Minutes and Accounts, 1871-1875, contains minutes and accounts. Pages 2-51 consist of accounts with various merchants and banks. Pages 60-109 contain the township board minutes and records information such as division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, establishment of prices allowable for road work claims, appointment of election judges and clerks, establishment of levy and tax rates, accounts allowed against the township including what service the payment is made for, overseer of the road financial reports, town official compensation payments, ordering of supplies for township use, instructions on how to keep the various township record books, instructions to road overseers on how to keep their accounts and books, orders to issue various warrants for payment, orders to hold elections, and instructions to officials about how to handle an outbreak of smallpox (p. 87-88).
</p>
      <p>Rappahannock Township Board Minutes, 1870-1875, contain minutes and accounts. Information recorded includes an order for the clerk to post public notices of board meetings, an order for all persons having claims against the township to present them on the board meeting days, accounts allowed against the township board for such things as road work, supplying or attending on paupers, and township official duties, division of the township into road districts, appointment of road overseers, establishment of rates allowed for road work, division of the township into election districts, changes in the boundary lines of road districts, establishment of tax and levy rates, establishment of rates allowable for physician visits to paupers, an order to take bids to build a township hall, references to providing payments and locations for vaccinations that might related to small pox (p. 36), and an order for the collector to take the taxes. There is an index at the front of the volume but it was very little used.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Fauquier County (Va.). Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">County government -- Records and correspondence -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Local finance -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Local government -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Fauquier County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Account books -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Accounts -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Minute books -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Tax and fiscal records -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Tax records -- Virginia -- Fauquier County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Added Entry - Corporate Name:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Cedar Run (Fauquier County, Va.)</corpname>
        <corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Centre (Fauquier County, Va.)</corpname>
        <corpname encodinganalog="710$a">Township of Rappahannock (Fauquier County, Va.)</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1107013">Cedar Run Township Record, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871-1875
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1155962">Cedar Run Township Tax Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873-1874
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1156098">Centre Township Accounts, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1872-1875
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1107009">Centre Township Board Minutes and Accounts, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871-1875
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1155981">Centre Township Road Tax Book, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Barcode number 1155972">Rappahannock Township Board Minutes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870-1875
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
