<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxngschema"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     id="vi04675">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04675::A Guide to the Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, 1861-1864.)//EN" "vi04675.xml"
		</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, <date>1861-1864.</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Governor, Office of the. Virginia.<num type="Accession Number">37226</num>
            </subtitle>
            <author>Craig S. Moore</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
            <xi:include href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication">© 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
			</date>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record using MarcEdit by Benjamin Bromley, <date>2014</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, <date>1861-1864.</date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle id="sort">A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
			<num type="Accession Number">37226</num>
         </subtitle>
         <author>Craige S. Moore</author>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2014
			</date>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:
			</label>
               <item>Craig S. Moore
			</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" type="collection">Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, </unittitle>
         <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">1861-1864.</unitdate>
         <unitid encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">37226</unitid>
         <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Governor (1861-1865 : Pierpont)</origination>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1 v. (117 p.)</physdesc>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Francis Harrison Pierpont was born on January 25, 1814, just east of Morgantown, W. Va. After working on his father's farm and tannery business in Fairmont, W. Va., Pierpont studied law at Allegheny College in Meadville, Pa., in 1835. He was admitted into the bar in 1842 and served as counsel for the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad until 1856. Pierpont was also involved in various business ventures including mining and shipping coal by rail. In December 1854, Pierpont married Julia Robinson, the daughter of a Presbyterian minister. Pierpont was an active member of the Whig political party and an anti-slavery proponent. Although he did not hold political office, Pierpont acted as a spokesman for northwest Virginia delivering speeches and writing commentaries in the newspapers attacking the Democrats and slavery. When the Virginia Convention voted on April 17, 1861, to pass the Ordinance of Secession, mass meetings were held in opposition to secession in northwest Virginia. Pierpont took an active part in these meetings and in the Wheeling Convention on May 13, 1861, in which he represented Marion County. The Convention voted to defy the Secession Convention. The Second Wheeling Convention met on June 11, 1861, and Piepont was unanimously elected governor of the Restored Government of Virginia on June 20, 1861 with the recognition of President Lincoln.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>As governor of the Restored Government of Virginia at Wheeling, Pierpont concentrated on raising regiments and commissioning officers for the Union cause. Meanwhile, continued calls for a new state to be created from the existing state of Virginia resulted in "An Ordinance to Provide for the Formation of a New State out of a Portion of the Territory of this State" at the Second Wheeling Convention. A special session of the Assembly adjourned on May 15, 1862, and Congress was presented with the constitution and proposal for the new state of West Virginia. The Senate passed the bill admitting West Virginia on July 14, 1862, and the House of Representatives on December 10, 1862. With prodding by Pierpont, President Lincoln signed the bill creating the state. West Virginia did not officially enter into the Union until June 20, 1863. Arthur I. Boreman became the first governor of the new state at this time and Pierpont continued as governor of the state of Virginia (which consisted of the counties of Alexandria, Fairfax, Loudoun, Accomac, Northampton, and Norfolk) in the new capital at Alexandria.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Pierpont was again elected governor for a four-year term on May 28, 1863. During this time, Pierpont clashed with General Benjamin F. Butler who was appointed to command the eastern military district of Virginia and North Carolina in Norfolk. Butler abused his military authority, according to Pierpont, by controlling the liquor traffic in Norfolk and through his disregard for the civil authority there. President Lincoln intervened in this controversy and Butler was removed of his command following a Congressional investigation. Following Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, Pierpont called for a new Constitutional Convention. The Convention assembled on February 3, 1864, and adjourned on April 11, 1864, having adopted an amendment for the abolition of slavery. Following the Civil War and the death of President Lincoln, the Virginia government, under Pierpont, was removed to Richmond by an executive order of President Johnson on May 9, 1865. Pierpont finished his 4-year term on April 4, 1868. He died at the home of his daughter in Pittsburgh, Pa., on March 24, 1899.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>These records are part of the Governor's Office record group (RG# 3).</p>
      </odd>
      <odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>Indexed alphabetically by correspondent in front of volume.</p>
      </odd>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <p>Organized into the following series: I. Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, 1861-1864.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <altformavail encodinganalog="530">
         <p>Also available on microfilm (Misc. reel 6191)</p>
      </altformavail>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <p>For preservation purposes, please use microfilm (Misc. reel 6191)</p>
      </accessrestrict>
	  <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
	  <relatedmaterial><p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00167.xml">Francis H. Pierpont Restored Government Executive Papers, 1861-1865. Accession 36928, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</extref></p></relatedmaterial>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation
		</head>
         <p>Virginia. Governor (1861-1865 : Pierpont). Executive letter book of Governor Francis H. Pierpont, 1861-1864. Accession 37226. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition Information
		</head>
         <p>Acquisition information unknown</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Cameron, Simon, -- 1799-1889.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Chase, Salmon P. -- (Salmon Portland), -- 1808-1873.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Lincoln, Abraham, -- 1809-1865</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Meigs, Montgomery C. -- (Montgomery Cunningham), -- 1816-1892.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Pierpont, Francis Harrison, -- 1814-1899.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Rosecrans, William S. -- (William Starke), -- 1819-1898.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Stanton, Edwin McMasters, -- 1814-1869.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <famname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="600">Wheat, James S.</famname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="610">Virginia. -- Governor (1861-1865 : Pierpont)</corpname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">Alexandria (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1861-1865.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">West Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">West Virginia -- Politics and government.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <geogname source="lcsh" rules="scm" role="subject" encodinganalog="651">Wheeling (W. Va.) -- History -- 19th century.</geogname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Governors -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">State governments -- Virginia -- Officials and employees.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <genreform source="lcsh" encodinganalog="655">Letter books. -- aat.</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <genreform source="lcsh" encodinganalog="655">State government records -- Virginia. -- aat.</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700">Pierpont, Francis Harrison, -- 1814-1899.</corpname>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Executive letter book contains the outgoing correspondence of Governor Francis H. Pierpont between 1861 and 1864 with the majority of material documenting the year 1862.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Pierpont corresponded with a variety of individuals regarding numerous issues including supplies for Virginia Volunteers, misconduct of officers, and certificates of passport for transport of companies of soldiers. Noteworthy are three letters to President Abraham Lincoln (June 29, 1861; Sept. 3, 1861, &amp; May 20, 1862). In the first letter, Pierpont appoints Col. Benjamin Kelley Brigadier General of the Virginia Volunteers. Pierpont suggests the President call out the militia in West Virginia fearing an imminent Confederate attack in his second letter. In the last letter, the Governor asks that A.W. Campbell accompany General McClelland into Richmond in order to take possession of one of the printing presses. Pierpont wrote Secretary of War E.M. Stanton and his predecessor Simon Cameron on a few occasions regarding the commissions of U.S. Army officers into the Virginia Volunteers and an expedition by Union troops from the Kanawha Valley towards the Tennessee railroad. In another letter to Stanton on Feb. 23, 1864, Pierpont asks his help in procuring the McVey House in Alexandria for his family. Additional correspondents include Samuel P. Chase, Secretary of the Treasury; James Wheat, Adjutant General; M.C. Miegs, Quarter Master General; and General William S. Rosecrans.</p>
      </scopecontent>
   </archdesc>
</ead>