<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi04695">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04695::A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, 1776-1795)//EN" "vi04695.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers,<date>1776-1795</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, 1776-1795
<num type="collectionnumber">APA 204
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Renee M. Savits
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2017  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Renee M. Savits, <date>6 December 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, <date>1776-1795</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">APA 204
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2017 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Renee M. Savits
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - George Rogers Clark Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1776-1795
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">APA 204
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>  cu. ft. ( boxes)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Use the microfilm or photostat volumes in lieu of the originals.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928). George Rogers Clark Papers, 1776-1795. Accession APA 204. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Please use the microfilm or photostat volumes in lieu of the originals.
</p>
</altformavail>

</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>

<p>This is an artificial collection of records concerning George Rogers Clark and the conquest of the Old Northwest during and after the revolutionary war. The records, which are now so intermingled they defy any attempt to separate them, were brought together from two distinct sets of records. The first set contained Clark's original accounts and vouchers, which had been submitted to the auditors of public accounts for settlement in 1779. These records were misplaced by the auditors and when the Board of Western Commissioners sought to settle his accounts in 1783, Clark produced a second set of records consisting of copies of the materials submitted in 1779, in addition to the records he had created since then. The Clark papers, then, consist of the misplaced records (since found) submitted to the auditor, as well as the vouchers submitted to the Board of Western Commissioners.</p>

<p>Some of the material that had long been part of the Clark records was separated from it in 1975 and interfiled with the Office of the Governor records, in the Letters Received series. These records consist mostly of correspondence with the governor and Council of State; tracers or photocopies were left in the Clark papers in lieu of the original documents.</p>




<p>George Rogers Clark was born 19 November 1752 in Albemarle County, Virginia, to John Clark (1725-1799) and Ann Rogers Clark (1728-1798). Clark learned surveying from his grandfather in Caroline County, Virginia. He explored down the Ohio and Kanawha Rivers in what is now Kentucky and West Virginia and surveyed farms for settlers arriving in that territory. Clark served as a captain in the Virginia militia during Lord Dunmore's War in 1774, and the next year returned to Kentucky to survey lands for the Ohio Company. When the Revolution began, Clark encouraged Virginia to protect Kentucky from the British and indians. He captured Kaskaskia, Illinois, from the British 4 July 1778 and won the allegience of French settlers in Vincennes, Indiana. When the British took Vincennes in October 1778, Clark recaptured it 25 February 1779. He was responsible for the defense of the Northwest Territory during the rest of the American Revolution. After Kentucky troops were defeated at Blue Licks, Kentucky, by the Shawnee 19 August 1782, Clark retaliated with an attack on Chillicothe, Ohio, defeating the Shawnee 4 November 1782. After the American Revolution ended, Clark served on the Board of Commissioners which allotted the lands in Kentucky and the Northwest Territory granted by Virginia to its soldiers. Clark lived the last few years of his life with his sister and her husband outside Louisville, Kentucky, where he died 13 February 1818.</p>


</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p></p>


</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
  <c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unitdate type="inclusive"></unitdate>
	<container label="Box" type="box">1
	</container>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">
	</container>
	</did>
	</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>