<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxngschema"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     id="vi04350">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04350::A Guide to the Minutes of the Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, 1920-2010.)//EN" "vi04350.xml"
		</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Minutes of the Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, <date>1920-2010.</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, Board for<num type="Accession Number">43221, 44933, 45395, 45436, 51228</num>
            </subtitle>
            <author>Paige Neal</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
            <xi:include href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication">© 2014  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
			</date>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record using MarcEdit by Ben Bromley, <date>2014</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Minutes of the Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, <date>1920-2010.</date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle id="sort">A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
			<num type="Accession Number">43221, 44933, 45395, 45436, 51228</num>
         </subtitle>
         <author>Paige Neal</author>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2014
			</date>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:
			</label>
               <item>Library of Virginia Staff.
			</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" type="collection">Minutes of the Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects, </unittitle>
         <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">1920-2010.</unitdate>
         <unitid encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">43221, 44933, 45395, 45436, 51228</unitid>
         <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects.</origination>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">25 v.</physdesc>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">2.50 cu. ft.</physdesc>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">3 compact disks.</physdesc>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>The Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers and Landscape Architects promulgates regulations governing its own organization, the professional qualifications of applicants, the requirements necessary for passing examinations, the proper conduct of its examinations, the implementation of exemptions from license requirements, and the proper discharge of its duties. It also issues licenses to practice as a professional engineers, architect, land surveyor or certificates to practice as landscape architect or interior designer in the Commonwealth to applicants meeting specified requirements. The board was established in 1920 for architects, engineers and surveyors, but later added landscape architects in 1980 and certified interior designers in 1990. The Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation provides administrative support to the board.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>These records are part of the Virginia Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation record group (RG 17).</p>
      </odd>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <p>Attachments must be reviewed for personal information and redacted prior to serving.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <p>There are no use restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation
		</head>
         <p>Virginia Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers and Landscape Architects, Minutes, [cite specific dates and accession used], State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition Information
		</head>
         <p>Accession 34885 was transferred by Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, 3600 West Broad Street, Richmond, VA, 05/11/1995</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="610">Virginia. -- Board for Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Certified Interior Designers, and Landscape Architects</corpname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="lcnaf" rules="aacr2r" role="subject" encodinganalog="610">Virginia. -- Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation.</corpname>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Architects -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Engineers -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Interior decorators -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Landscape architects -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" rules="scm">Surveyors -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Virginia.</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <genreform source="lcsh" encodinganalog="655">Minutes. -- aat.</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <genreform source="lcsh" encodinganalog="655">State government records -- Virginia. -- aat.</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="710">Virginia. -- Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation.</corpname>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>This series consists of official minutes of the board and agendas and related attachments. Also includes section meeting minutes. May also include minutes from informal fact finding conferences and conflict of interest letters.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 34885 also includes section minutes for Architects, 1983-1989; Professional Engineers, 1973-1989; and Land Surveyors, 1974-1990.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 41925 includes official minutes, 1988 Mar-1999 Dec. (5 v.) Also includes minutes of the meetings of the various sections covered by the board, 1983-1999(10 v.), and related meeting materials, 1997-2001 (1 cu. ft.).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 42984 includes official minutes for the Boards of Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Landscape Architects and Interior Designers, 2000 February-2006 January. These minutes also include individual section proceedings for Architects, 2000 February-2006 May; Interior Designers, 2000 March-2006 May; Landscape Architects, 2000 February-2004 November; Land Surveyors, 2000 February-2006 August and Professional Engineers, 2000 February-2006 August.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 43221 includes official minutes for the Boards of Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Landscape Architects and Interior Designers, 2006 Sept-October. There are minutes of individual sections for Architects, 2006 July; October; Certified Interior Design, 2006 November; Land Surveyors, 2006 Sept; November and Professional Engineers, 2006 October.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 43398 includes the official minutes for the Boards of Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors, Landscape Architects and Interior Designers, 2007 March-May. Also includes minutes of individual section meetings for the Architect Section and Land Surveyors Section.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 45077 (1 cd) includes Board minutes, agendas with attachments, and section meeting minutes, 2001-2003.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 45395 (1 cd) includes Board minutes, agendas with attachments and section meeting minutes, 2007.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 45346 consists of Board minutes, 2008.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
         <p>Accession 51228 includes the Board minutes for 2009-2010 and a compact disk of the minutes from 2008.</p>
      </scopecontent>
   </archdesc>
</ead>