<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04064">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04064::A Guide to the Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912))//EN" "vi04064.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912)
</subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09 November 2009</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>K. Rowlett
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Bedford County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912, use digital images found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912 (bulk 1850-1912). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Bedford County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes 1755-1912 were processed in the field by K. Rowlett between 1999 and 2007.  
</p>
<p>Digital images were generated by Crowley Micrographics through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program in 2008.</p>
<p>In some instances, additional documents (e.g., plats) have been added but not scanned.
</p>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: 2009; updated by C. Collins: May 2023.</p>
</processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories. 
</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Bedford County was named probably for John Russell, fourth duke of Bedford, who served as secretary of state for the southern department from 1748 to 1751 and had general supervision of colonial affairs. It was formed from Lunenburg County in 1753, and parts of Albemarle and Lunenburg Counties were added in 1755. The county court first met on 5 May 1754. The county seat is the town of Bedford. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.
</p>
<p>Commonly found surnames among the plaintiffs and defendants include Adams, Anderson, Anthony, Arrington, Arthur, Austin, Ayers, Bell, Board, Bowles, Brown, Buford, Burks, Burroughs, Burton, Callaway, Calloway, Campbell, Carter, Clark, Claytor, Cofer, Creasy (also spelled Creasey), Cundiff, Davis, Dearing, Dickinson, Donald, Dooley, Early, Franklin, Fuqua, Goggin, Graves, Gray, Hancock, Hardy, Harris, Hatcher, Hawkins, Haynes, Holt, Hopkins, Hudnall, Hurt, James, Jeter, Johnson, Jones, Jordan, Kasey, Layne, Lee, Leftwich, Lowry, Martin, McDaniel, McGehee, Mead, Meador, Miller, Minor, Michell, Morgan, Musgrove, Nance, Nichols, Noell, Otey, Overstreet, Parker, Pate, Patterson, Payne, Poindexter, Preas (also spelled Prease), Preston, Price, Quarles, Reynolds, Roberts, Robertson, Robinson, Rucker, Sale, Saunders, Scott, Smith, St. Clair, Steptoe, Stevens, Stewart, Stiff, Tate, Thomas, Thompson, Thurman, Tinsley, Turner, Turpin, Wade, Walker, Watson, Watts, White, Wilkerson, Wilkes, Williams, Williamson, Wills, Wilson, Wingfield, Witt, Wood, and Wright. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are generally as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
     <originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Original Bedford County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1755-1912, are retained in the locality. Contact the Clerk of the Circuit Court for access. 
</p>
</originalsloc>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Bedford County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.</extref>
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
