<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi04309">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04309.xml::A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861))//EN" "vi04309.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1861</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861
<num type="collectionnumber">1208718, 1138047</num></subtitle>
        <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Catherine OBrion, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 April 2011</date>.
</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> Warren County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1861</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>Catherine G. OBrion
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Catherine G. OBrion; L. Neuroth
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Warren County (Va.) Free Negro and Slave Records,    
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
 
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">0.25 cu. ft. (1 box); 1 leaf (oversize)    
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Tax Records 1836-1861, are digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images. 
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861. Local government records collection, Warren County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Warren County in 2000 under accession numbers 37582.</p>
      </acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p> <emph render="bold">Starting in 2023, Library of Virginia archival staff in partnership with the Virginia Untold Project Manager began efforts to describe records related to free and enslaved Black and multiracial people in a manner that improved the historical context of the records. In doing so, in some cases material once described within the "Free and Enslaved" record group for a locality may no longer be described within this record. When this has occurred, please see the Processing Information and Related Materials section for records that have been described separately.  </emph>
</p>
<p>Certificates of Registration were removed from this record in December 2023 and are now described in the Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861.
</p>
<p>Petitions to Remain were removed from this record in December 2023 and are now described in the Warren County (Va.) Petitions to Remain in teh Commonwealth, 1847.
</p>


</processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">A Context for Record Type: </emph>
</p>
      <p>Free and Enslaved Records</p>
      <p>The Free and Enslaved Records collection is comprised of miscellaneous records related to the regulation and policing of both enslaved and free Black and Multiracial people in [this] locality. The localities/local government authorities were largely responsible for enforcing laws that restricted the movement of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people and the resulting documentation was often filed in the circuit courts. The ways in which local authorities enacted legal measures against or on behalf of enslaved and free Black and multiracial people varied from locality to locality; therefore records were not necessarily standardized or filed and retained in a consistent manner. This collection is topical and a means by which to compile miscellaneous documents related to free and enslaved people that are not established local government record types. 
</p>
      <p>"Free Negro Tax" Records</p>
      <p>In 1801, the Virginia Legislature passed an act requiring commissioners of the revenue to annually return a complete list of all free Black Virginians within their districts, with their names, sex, place of abode, and trades. 
</p>
<p>Delinquent tax lists include names of free Black individuals returned delinquent and sometimes why they were returned, such as "no property," "removed," or "not found." In 1853, the General Assembly passed a law allowing the taxes raised on free Black men and women to be collected in a fund to be applied to the removal of these individuals as a part of the recolonization effort.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality Note:</emph> Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Shenandoah and Frederick Counties in 1836.
</p>


    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861, is comprised largely of "Free Negro" tax records and additionally includes a memorandum, and order. 
</p>
      <p>"Free Negro" Tax records which include "A List of Free Negroes with the District of Daniel Stickley," 1836 compiled of Daniel Stickley a Commissioner of Revenue for Warren County (includes the names, sex, ages, and familial relations of free Black and multiracial individuals within the district); "A List of Free Negroes and Mulattoes in the County of Warren," 1837 compiled by Wm. Bray [? illegible] a Commissioner of Revenue for Warren County (includes the names, sex, ages, and distance from court house of free Black and multiracial individuals within the county); "A List of Free Negroes," 1855 (includes the names, sex, ages, and occupation of free Black and multiracial individuals within the county); "A List of Free Negroes over the age of 12 year," 1859 compiled by W. G. Settle a Commissioner of Revenue for Warren County (includes the names, sex, ages, and occupation of free Black and multiracial individuals within the county); "A List of Free Negroes," 1861 compiled by W. G. Settle a Commissioner of Revenue for Warren County (includes the names, sex, ages, and occupation of free Black and multiracial individuals within the county).
</p>
      <p>These tax records also include nine "Lists of Delinquent Free Negroes", 1837, 1840 [photocopy, from levy book], 1850-1854 and 1857, compiled by various sheriffs and deputy sheriffs for the county noting free Black and multiracial residents who are delinquent on their state tax/ revenue tax (generally in the amount is $1). The lists include the names of free Black and multiracial individuals, the amount due, and usually the reason the funds were not returned (such as "no property," "removed," or "not found").</p>
<p>Also, includes a memorandum, 1856, listing the names and ages of persons enslaved by and then emancipated by Lucy Hansbrough (includes Mariah, Sharlott, Rachel, Ann, Henry, Katharine, Attulinda, Mary, and Louisa)
</p>
<p>Lastly, includes an order, 1855, to transfer the apprenticeship indenture of James Franklin Lupton, a "free boy of color," from Charles D. Shambaugh, of Warren County, to Mary Lannick of Frederick County, Va.
</p>

    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06311.xml">Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861</extref></p>
<p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06312.xml">Warren County (Va.) Petitions to Remain in the Commonwealth, 1847</extref></p>
        <p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01355.xml">Warren County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons Cohabitating Together as Husband and Wife on 27th February 1866</extref></p>


<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Warren County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
<p>Additional Warren County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>

      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
   
    <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold"> Free and Enslaved Records </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1831-1861</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent> .25 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p> loosely by record type
</p>
</arrangement>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1138047 ">List of Free Negroes, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1855
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1208718 ">Free and Enslaved Records, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1836-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
