<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY chancery SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/chancery/index.htm" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY catalog SYSTEM "http://ajax.lva.lib.va.us/F/?func=file&file_name=find-b-clas05&local_base=CLAS05" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY microfilm SYSTEM "http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vi04238">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04238::A Guide to the Porter Family papers, 1766-1908, no date)//EN" "vi04238.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Porter Family papers, <date>1766-1924, no date</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Porter Family papers, 1766-1924, no date
<num type="collectionnumber">44163
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2010  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Trenton Hizer, <date>7 October 2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Porter Family papers, <date>1766-1924, no date</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">44163
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2010 
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Porter Family papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1766-1924, no date
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">44163
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">12 leaves and 70 pages
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Porter family
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Porter family papers, 1766-1924 and undated. Accession 44163. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift of James H. Chapman of Lexington, North Carolina.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Porter family resided in Bath County, Virginia.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Papers, 1766-1924 and undated, of the Porter family of Bath County, Virginia, consisting of fifteen deeds, 1766-1908, for property in Bath County including several for land along the Cowpasture River; a plat (copy), 17 October 1794, for 458 acres along the Cowpasture River in Bath County; a deed and an abstract, 29 July 1843, for property along Big Spring Fork of the Elk River in Pocahontas County, (West) Virginia; articles of agreement, 21 October 1880, for boundary line for property along the Big Spring Fork of the Elk River in Pocahontas County; two deeds, 1868 and 1881, for 1000 acres in Rockbridge County, Virginia, along the Calf Pasture River; a will, 11 March 1899, from Bath County; a brief history of the Porter family in Virginia; and a real estate brochure, no date, but post 1967, advertising Windy Cove Farm in Bath County for sale.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">18 March 1766 [1776?]and recorded 19 March 1776,</unitdate> for 195 acres on the Cowpasture River in Augusta County [later in Bath County], Virgina from Samuel Hamilton to Alexander Crawford, both of Augusta County (located in oversize box 104).</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">19 March 1776 and recorded 19 March 1776,</unitdate> for 195 acres on the Cowpasture River in Augusta County [later in Bath County], Virginia from Samuel Hamilton to Alexander Crawford, both of Augusta County (located in oversize box 104).</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Plat, <unitdate type="inclusive">17 October 1794,</unitdate> for 458 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County, Virginia, surveyed for John Dickinson.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">10 September 1799 and recorded September 1799,</unitdate> for 195 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from Alexander Crawford and Elizabeth Crawford to James Kelso, all of Bath County (located in oversize box 104).</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">21 June 1813 and recorded October 1813,</unitdate> for 195 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from James Kelso and Elizabeth Kelso of Goochland County, Virginia, to Robert Sitlington of Bath County (located in oversize box 104).</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">25 October 1833 and recorded 26 October 1833,</unitdate> for two tracts of land totalling 280 acres total on both sides of Mill Creek in Bath County from Elisha Williams and Sarah Williams to Andrew Sitlington, all of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">12 June 1841 and recorded 10 August 1841,</unitdate> for 120 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from Thomas F. Barnett and Mary Barnett of Bledsoe County, Tennessee, to Andrew Sitlington of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Abstract of deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">29 July 1843,</unitdate> for 1000 acres and 65 1/2 acres located on the Big Spring Fork of the Elk River in Pocahontas County, (West) Virginia, from John Beal and Ophelia Ann Beal of Pocahontas County to Andrew Sitlington of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">29 July 1843 and recorded 5 September 1843,</unitdate> for 1000 acres and 65 1/2 acres located on the Big Spring Fork of the Elk River in Pocahontas County, from John Beal and Ophelia Ann Beal of Pocahontas County to Andrew Sitlington of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated and recorded <unitdate type="inclusive">8 September 1849,</unitdate> for two tracts of land, 150 acres and 209 acres, in Bath County from John Sloan, commissioner for the circuit superior court of law and chancery of Bath County in four causes concerning land once owned by William Sitlington to Andrew Sitlington of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">9 January 1858 and recorded 9 February 1858,</unitdate> for 296 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from Stephen A. Porter and William C. Burger, executors of the estate of Andrew Crawford deceased, to William A. Cleek of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">20 March 1868 and recorded 6 April 1868,</unitdate> for 1000 acres on the Calf Pasture River in Rockbridge County, Virginia, from James Burk and Jane C. Burk of Alleghany County, Virginia, to Thomas N. Burk of Rockbridge County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">11 December 1869 and recorded 13 January 1874,</unitdate> for 600 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from W. W. Mooney and Virginia S. Mooney, Andrew S. Porter, and Elizabeth P. Porter to Joseph B. Dickinson, all of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">16 December 1869,</unitdate> for five tracts of land totalling 559 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from Charles Sitlington, Wililam Sitlington and Jane A. Sitlington, William W. Mooney and Virginia S. Mooney, Andrew S. Porter, Elizabeth P. Porter (all of Bath County), William A. Mann and Margaret A. Mann (of Augusta County), and Alexander D. Campbell and Esteline Campbell (of Rockbridge County) to Joseph B. Dickinson of Bath County.  Deed does not have a recordation date but it is certified by the justices of the peace in Bath, Augusta, and Rockbridge Counties.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated and recorded <unitdate type="inclusive">5 July 1871,</unitdate> for five tracts of land totalling 559 acres on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from Charles R. McDannald, special commissioner of the circuit court of Bath County, to Joseph B. Dickinson of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">25 July 1871 and recorded 13 January 1874, for 1/4 interest in a tract of land on the Cowpasture River in Bath County from John B. Porter to Joseph B. Dickinson, both of Bath County.</unitdate> </unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">24 October 1878 and recorded 10 June 1880,</unitdate> for interest in 209 acres on the Cowpasture River from Thomas J. Hyde and Eliza J. Hyde to Joseph B. Dickinson, all of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Articles of agreement, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">21 October 1880 and recorded 10 December 1880,</unitdate> between A. C. L. Gatewood and his wife Mary Gatewood of Pocahontas County and Joseph B. Dickinson and Margaret A. Dickinson of Bath County for the adjustment of the line between their properties along Big Spring branch of the Elk River in Pocahontas County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">1 October 1881,</unitdate> for 1000 acres on the Calf Pasture River in Rockbridge County from Joseph B. Dickinson and Margaret A. Dickinson of Bath County to G. W. Fraley of Rockbridge County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated and recorded <unitdate type="inclusive">20 January 1885,</unitdate> for 560 on Mill Creek in Bath County from C. R. McDannald, commissioner for the circuit court of Bath County to Margaret Ann Dickinson of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Will, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">11 March 1899 and recorded 15 January 1901,</unitdate> of Margaret A. Stoakley of Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Deed, dated <unitdate type="inclusive">31 October 1908,</unitdate> for 50 3/8 acres in Bath County between Stephen P. Wilson Bettie M. Wilson, and A. Houston Wilson of the first part, T. W. Black and Laura L. Black of the second part, and W. R. Neff of the third part.  Deed is incomplete.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle><title render="doublequote">Partial History of Porter Family,</title> <unitdate type="inclusive">16 September 1924</unitdate>.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file"><did>
<unittitle>Real estate brochure, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated, but post-1970,</unitdate> for Windy Cove Farm in Bath County.</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
