<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi03654">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi04869::A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015)//EN" "vi04869.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">
          <num type="collectionnumber">51854
</num>
        </subtitle>
        <author>Paige Neal
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2016  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from paper, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 September 2017</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2017-09-15</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number">51854
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Paige Neal
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Paige Neal
</label>
          <item/>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-2015
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">51854
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">XX
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">LVA
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, [cite specific recording used], Accession 51854, State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
	<p>Accession 51854, transferred on 28 June 2016.
</p>
	
        
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>XX
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the General Assembly passed at the May 1779 session and has continued to the present day. Its antecedent was the General Court, which, after it was reestablished under the constitution of 1776, shared appellate jurisdiction with the Supreme Court until 1851, when the new state constitution abolished the General Court. Prior to that date the General Court had criminal jurisdiction, while the Supreme Court was restricted to civil cases. While the court now has concurrent original jurisdiction in issuing and hearing writs of habeas corpus, mandamus and prohibition, retirement, removal, and matters of judicial censure, its jurisdiction is almost exclusively appellate. An act of the General Assembly passed on March 16, 1971 changed the name of the court to the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>
	<p>Justices are elected by a majority vote of both houses of the General Assembly for a term of twelve years.  Vacancies on the court occuring between sessions of the General Assembly may be filled by the Governor for a term expiring thirty days after the commencement of the next session of the General Assembly.  By statute, the Chief Justice is chosen by a majority vote of the seven justices.</p>
<p>By statute, the court by designate a retired justice to serve as Senior Justice for a renewable one year term.  Senior Justices sit with the court during regular sessions hearing writs and sitting on merit cases, especially when an active member of the court is recused from hearing a particular case.</p>
      
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>These recording include audio and video recordings of court ceremonies and oral history interviews, 1969-2015.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged into the following series:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>Series I. Audio and Audio-Visual recordings of court ceremonies, 1991-2011</item>
      </list>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>



      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1991-2011</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 23 video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

	
          <p>This series contains 23 video recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1991-2011.  Includes investitures and swearing-in ceremonies, portrait presentation ceremonies, as well as retirement and anniversary ceremonies.  The ceremonies took place in the courtroom in Richmond unless otherwise noted. </p>
<p>Includes the following ceremonies:</p>

<p>Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Courtroom 5-E, Fairfax Judicial Center in Fairfax, Virginia, 1991 July 2.  Includes one video recording of the entire ceremony with poor audio (43 minutes) and two segments of the television show Law Weekly (60 minutes), a production of the Fairfax County Bar Association, moderated by Glenn C. Lewis, with highlights of the ceremony and interviews with guests.  The segments were broadcast on the Fairfax County public access television station, FCAC Channel 10.  The ceremony was the first televised session of the Supreme Court.  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; with remarks by Raymond Diaz, president of the Virginia State Bar; William D. Dolan, III, past president of the Virginia State Bar; Governor L. Douglas Wilder; Speaker of the House A. L. Philpott; State Senator Edward M. Holland; State Senator Richard L. Saslow; Retired Judge Arthur W. Sinclair; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Johanna Fitzpatrick; and Justice Keenan.  The second segment of the recording features host Glenn Lewis interviewing guests Emilie Miller, Virginia State Senator; Fairfax County Commonwealth's Attorney Robert H. Horan; Chief Justice Carrico; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Charles H. Duff; William Dolan, Raymond Diaz, Judge Sinclair, Judge Richard T. Horan, Justice Keenan, Ann Milano, retired Clerk Delores Testerman, Judith Wheat, and Jerry Phillips. Barbara M. Keenan served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1991 to 2010, when she was confirmed as a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.  She was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1991.  She was the first woman to serve as circuit and appellate court judge in Virginia.</p>

<p>Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Olin Hall, Roanoke College, Salem, Virginia, 1995 August 16 (49 minutes and 30 seconds).  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by George W. Wooten; Judge Beverly T. Fitzpatrick; Michael Smith, president of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate C. Richard Cranwell; and Justice Koontz.  Invocation and benediction by Rev. R. Paul Hendrickson, Chaplain, Roanoke College.  The recording also includes clips of local television news coverage of the event (WDBJ News 7 and WSLS News 10).  Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1995 to 2011, when he took senior status.  He was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1995.</p>

<p>Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Lee High School, Jonesville, Virginia, 1997 July 8 (1 hour, 32 minutes).  Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor George Allen; Senior Judge Glenn Williams, U.S. District Court, Western District of Virginia; Justice Kinser, and others.  The recording includes footage before and after the ceremony and the following reception. Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997.  She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2010.  She is the first woman to serve as chief justice.</p>

<p>Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 2003 January 1 (43 minutes, 18 seconds).  Poor quality video recording.  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary; and Justice Donald W. Lemons; presentation of slideshow with photographs of family and court staff.  Harry L. Carrico (1916-2013) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1961-2003, and was chief justice, 1981-2003.  He took senior status in 2003.</p>

<p>Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (36 minutes, 41 seconds). Justice Barbara Milano Keenan, presiding; invocation and benediction by George Martin; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Speaker of the House of Delegates, William Howell; Bernard DiMuro, president of the Virginia State Bar; Colonel George B. Mason, Jr., Virginia Capitol Police; Justice Keenan; and Chief Justice Hassell.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 265 Virginia Reports, vii-xviii. Produced by Craig Keeton, Community Idea Stations, Richmond, Va. Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011.  He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007.  He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (45 seconds).  Justice Barbara M. Keenan administering the oath of office, with Chief Justice Hassell's wife, Linda Hassell, holding the Bible.  Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011.  He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007.  He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.</p>


<p>Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, recorded at Roanoke College in Salem, Va., 2003 March 5 (1 hour, 5 minutes, and 35 seconds).  Chief Justice Hassel, presiding; remarks by State Senator Charles Hawkins, Delegate Robert McDonnell, Attorney General Jerry Kilgore, Delegate Lacy Putney, and Justice Agee.  G. Steven Agee served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 2003-2008, when he was appointed to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.  Previously, he was judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2001-2003.</p>

<p>Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 June 1 (47 minutes). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Senior Justice Harry L. Carrico; U.S. District Court Judge John A. Gibney; Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; Trish Harrington, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia; Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia; and David Beach. (Video in two parts)  David Beach was Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1984-2003.</p>


<p>Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2004 December 9 (41 minutes, 48 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., presiding; invocation by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Lt. Governor Timothy Kaine; Attorney General Jerry Kilgore; Senator Kenneth Stolle, Chair, Court of Justice Committee; Speaker of the House J. Morgan Griffith; David B. Bobzien, President of the Virginia State Bar; and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>


<p>Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2005 March 24 (1 hour, 11 minutes, 51 seconds).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Bill Howell, Speaker of the House; Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna Fitzpatrick; James Ullman, former chair, House Courts Committee; Retired Judge J.R. Zepkin, Judge Phillip Trompeter, and Larry Palmer, Clerk, Lynchburg Circuit Court.  (Video in two parts) Robert N. Baldwin was Executive Secretary for the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1976-2005</p>

<p>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell, 2006 February 28 (28 minutes, 8 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix-xii.  Harry L. Carrico (1916-2013) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1961 to 2003 and was Chief Justice from 1981 to 2003.  A. Christian Compton (1929-2006) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1975 to 2000.  Charles Russell served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1991, and returned as a senior justice in 2004.  Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997.</p>

<p>Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution, 2006 November 2 (46 minutes, 35 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding; remarks by Lt. Governor William Bolling; Attorney General Robert F. McDonnell; Speaker of the House William Howell; President of the Senate John H. Chichester; Senator Benjamin Lambert; Karen A. Gould, President of the Virginia State Bar; Governor Tim Kaine; and Chief Justice Hassell.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2007 October 10 (12 minutes, 48 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy, R. Hassell, Sr., administering the oath of office to Goodwyn, who is accompanied by his wife, Sharon Smith Goodwyn, and his two children.  Brief remarks by Chief Justice Hassell, and greetings from Senior Justices Elizabeth Lacy and Charles Russell; Executive Secretary Karl Hade; and Patricia Harrington, Clerk.</p>

<p>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 February 22, Manassas, Virginia. (Length?).  Chief Judge William S. Fenton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Paul B. Ebert, Prince William County Commonwealth's Attorney; Senator Charles Colgan (presenting commission); William G. Petty, Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia; Robert J. Zelnick; John D. McGaven; and Justice Millette.  LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008.  He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.</p>

<p>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2008 September 5 (2 hours, 7 minutes).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Delegate Robert G. Marshall; remarks by Senator Henry L. Marsh, III; Manuel A. Capsalis, President of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate Jackson H. Miller; Delegate Jennifer L. McClellan; Governor Timothy M. Kaine; Senator Charles J. Colgan; and Justice Millette.  Benediction by Delegate Ward L. Armstrong.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 276 Virginia Reports, xi-xxii.  LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008.  He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.</p>

<p>Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 November 17 (48 minutes, 21 seconds).  Chief Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Senator Henry Marsh; First Lady Anne B. Holton; Governor Tim Kaine; Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr.; and Judge Powell.  Cleo Elaine Powell was the first African-American woman appointed to an appellate court in Virginia.</p>

<p>Investiture of William C. Mims as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2010 April 9 (1 hour, 10 minutes).  Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Stephen R. McCullough; remarks by Senator Thomas K. Norment, Jr.; Senator Richard L. Saslaw; Mark E. Rubin; Jon D. Huddleston, on behalf of the statwide bar associations from Virginia; Speaker William J. Howell; Govenor Robert F. McDonnell; Courney M. Malveaux; Judge Dean S. Worcester; Justice Mims; and Attorney General Mark L. Earley.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 279 Virginia Reports, xxv-xivi.  William C. Mims was elected to the Supreme Court of Virginia on March 10, 2010.  Previously he was Chief Deputy Attorney General under Attorney General Robert McDonnell, and Attorney General following McDonnell's resignation to campaign for Governor.</p>

<p>Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 February 16 (47 minutes).  Justice Donald W. Lemons, presiding; remarks by Governor Robert F. McDonnell; Senior Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; and Chief Justice Kinser.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 281 Virginia Reports, xi-xxiv.  Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997.  She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2011.  She was the first woman to serve as chief justice.</p>

<p>Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 September 1 (46 minutes, 28 seconds).  Chief Justice Cynthia Kinser, presiding; invocation by Reverend Betty C. Reiff; remarks by Retired Chief Judge of the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna L. Fitzpatrick; Senator William C. Wampler, Jr.; Delegate Terry G. Kilgore; Governor Robert F. McDonnell; former Attorney General Jerry W. Kilgore; Hon. Joseph P. Johnson, Jr.; benediction by Reverend Walter P. Weikel.  Elizabeth A. McClanahan was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 2011.  She was a judge on the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2003 to 2011.</p>




        </scopecontent>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1991 July 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Video" type="box">1
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1995 August 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1997 July 8</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 January 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 February 11</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 February 11</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

        <c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 March 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2003 June 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2004 December 9</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>



<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2005 March 31</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>


<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2006 February 28</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2006 November 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>




<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2007 October 10</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 February 22</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 September 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2008 November 17</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of William C. Mims as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2010 April 9</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011 February 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011 September 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02>







</c01>

	
 <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series II. Miscellanous court video recordings,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">XX</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: XX video recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

<p>Miscellaneous court video recordings include various presentations and speeches.</p>
           
  </scopecontent>   

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>XX,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">XX</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	</did>
		</c02> 

</c01> 

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Series III. Audio recordings of court ceremonies,</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1969-2005</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
          <physdesc>
            <extent>Extent: 18 digital audio recordings.</extent>
          </physdesc>         
        </did>

<scopecontent>

<p>This series contains audio recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia ceremonies, 1969-2005; and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1985-1989.  The ceremonies took place in the courtrooms of the Supreme Court of Virginia and the Court of Appeals of Virginia in Richmond.</p>

<p>The Supreme Court ceremonies include investiture and portrait presentation ceremonies, 1969-1985; the bicentennial of the court, 1979; and the dedication of the Supreme Court Building, 1981.  Investitures includ of those of Justice John Charles Thomas, the first African-American justice of the court, in 1983, and Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, the first female justice on the court, in 1989.</p>

<p>This series also contain recordings of three Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremnonies: the swearing-in ceremony of the first court, 1985; the swearing-in ceremony for Judge Jere M.H. Willis, Jr., 1989; and the portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, 1985.</p>

<p>This series includes the following audio files:</p>

<p>Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harmon as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice, 1969 October 1 (24 minutes).  Remarks by Justice W. I'Anson honoring Chief Justice Snead; Chief Justice Snead, presiding over investitures; remarks by Howard C. Gilmer, Harmon's former law partner.</p>

<p>Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1972 August 30 (11 minutes, 49 seconds).  Chief Justice Harold Snead, presiding; remarks by former Governor William M. Tuck and the Hon. Lewis F. Powell, Associate Justice, U.S. Supreme Court.</p>

<p>Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the founding of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1979 August 30 (29 minutes).  Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Chief Justice I'Anson; and U.S. Supreme Court Justice Lewis Powell, Jr., read by his son Lewis Powell, III.  The ceremony includes the presentation of the portrait of Henry Tazewell, who served on the court from 1785 to 1788 and 1793 to 1794.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 220 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan, 1980 April 17 (14 minutes, 22 seconds).  Chief Justice I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Justice Alexander Harmon.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xi.</p>
 
<p>Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1981 March 2 (23 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William S. Moffatt, Chief Judge, 25th Judicial Circuit; presentation of resolutions honoring Stephenson.</p>

<p>Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building, 1981 Dec 4 (35 minutes, 18 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Delegate George Allen, Jr.; State Senator Edward E. Willey; Governor John Dalton; and Chief Justice Carrico.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead, 1982 June 16 (50 minutes, 38 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William B. Poff; former Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and Governor Charles S. Robb.  A transcript of the ceremony in published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xix.</p>

<p>Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1983 April 25 (34 minutes, 28 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; T.S. Ellis, III; Dennis C. Montgomery; and Justice Thomas; presentation of resolutions honoring Thomas. John Charles Thomas was the first African-American to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, 1983 June 15 (45 minutes, 14 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Virginia Senator Edward E. Willey; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; and others.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 225 Virginia Reports, p. vii.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1985 January 4 (30 minutes, 4 seconds).  Chief Judge E. Ballard Baker, presiding; remarks by William D. Dolan, III, President of the Virginia State Bar; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia; Edward Willey, President Pro Tempore, Senate of Virginia; Delegate Theodore V. Marsden, Jr.; and Governor Charles S. Robb.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corporation Commission, 1985 April 1 (18 minutes).  Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice Supreme Court, Supreme Court of Virginia, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; Judge Thomas P. Harwood, Jr., member, State Corporation Commission; Commissioner Lacy; and Attorney General Gerald S. Baliles.  Commission read by G. Patrick Lacy.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1986 May 5 (19 minutes).  Chief Judge Lawrence Koontz, presiding; remarks by Chief Judge Koontz; Governor Gerald L. Baliles; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice, Supreme Court of Virginia; James C. Roberts, Past President of the Virginia State Bar; and Billy Jane Baker, widow of Judge Baker.</p>

<p>Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 January 4 (25 minutes, 52 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; invocation and benediction by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Balilies and Justice Lacy; presentation of resolutions honoring Lacy.  Elizabeth B. Lacy was the first woman to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court Justice George M. Cochran, 1989 April 20 (50 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by former Governor and retired justice Albertis S. Harrison; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; retired Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and others.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 238 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

<p>Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges, 1989 October 26 (22 minutes, 4 seconds, partially inaudible).  Chief Judge Koontz, presiding.</p>

<p>Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 Dec 28 (26 minutes, 30 seconds).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Baliles and Justice Hassell; presentation of resolutions honoring Hassell.</p>

<p>Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2000 April 3 (45 minutes).  Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by State Senator Walter Stosch; Governor James S. Gilmore; and Justice Lemons; presentation of resolutions honoring Lemons.</p>

<p>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson and Henry Hudson Whiting, 2005 November 1 (11 minutes, 37 seconds).  Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, presiding.  A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix.</p>

           
  </scopecontent>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harman as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1969 Oct q</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1972 Aug 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1979 Aug 30</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1980 Apr 17</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1981 Mar 2</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1981 Dec 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1982 June 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1983 Apr 25</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02> 

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Lawrence W. I'Anson,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1983 June 15</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1985 Jan 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corportion Commission,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1985 Apr 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for E. Baker Ballard, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1986 May 5</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>



<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Jan 4</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court George M. Cochran,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Apr 20</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Oct 16</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">1989 Dec 28</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2000 Apr 3</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>     

<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson, and Henry Hudson Whiting,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2005 Nov 1</unitdate>.</unittitle>
	<container label="Audio" type="box">X
	</container>
	</did>
		</c02>  






</c01>             
              
		
		
		
            
            
	


           
          


         
            
           
		
              
		
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>


