<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi05556">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05556::A Guide to the Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1718-1913)//EN" "vi05556.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1718-1913</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1718-1913
<num type="collectionnumber">1718-001-1913-056
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2007 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">06 September 2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1718-1913</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">1718-001-1913-056
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2007
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Library of Virginia staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1718-1913
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">1718-001-1913-056
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia Beach (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1718-1913. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Chesapeake (City)/Princess Anne County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from circuit court of Virginia Beach.
</p>
<p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Workss through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Princess Anne County was formed from Lower Princess Anne County in 1691. Now extinct, Princess Anne County was incorporated into the city of Chesapeake in 1963.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Princess Anne County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1718-1913, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Princess Anne County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA195">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
  
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1741-001 John Williams v. Moses Robertson: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause deals with debt related to medicine books and apothecary wares.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1767-006: Tamar Bruce v. Vestry of Princess AnneParish: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff in cause cannot work and support herself.  Needs annuity from vestry for help with indigent state.  Topics in suit deal with church and health.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1771-010 Thomas Brown v. Amos Etheridge: 
 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves contract dispute regarding property and slavery. Thomas Brown shipped enslaved person to Martinico (French islands) in 1768. He was free born and was given his liberty.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1802-001 John Murray and Son v. James Gillespie, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendant in cause was a French merchant residing in the town of Cape Francois in the French colony of Sainte-Domingue.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1835-011 Edy, an enslaved person v. Admr of Noah Maund, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause is a freedom suit. Enslaved people noted in suit were given freedom under Noah Maund's will of 1830. They were to be given to "the agent of the New Colonization Society of Africa," where the free African Americans of the United States would be colonized on the coast of Africa. Specific ships and destinations are included in Shields' deposition. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1836-008 F. Brette and Co. v. Admr of Mary Hibbert
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mary Hibbert ran extensive dry goods business.  Her store in Portsmouth was purchased in her own name and on her own credit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1840-007 Bernard (Barnard) ONeill v. Lewis Warrington, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff alleges a dispute between his land and land purchased by U.S Government for a Naval Hopspital. Suit mentions erection of Fort Nelson. Plaintiff, by seeking an injunction, wants U.S. naval officers in charge of land to stop burying dead bodies from the hospital on his property and erecting an enclosure around these lands. Injuctions typically deal with debt, but in this cause and various others beginning in 1754, a dispute arises from wanting to stop or halt a particular action.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1841-002: Thomas Green v. Admx of Isaiah Harris, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit references the appointment of complainant to recover the bounty land and half pay of William Hoffler, a major in the Revolutionary War.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1842-002 James Bridgers and wife, etc. v. Samuel Carson, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff is seeking injuction to injoin and restrain defendants from carrying enslaved people beyond the limits of the Commonwealth of Virginia. Defendant travelled from Virginia to North Carolina. The enslaved people were sent from North Carolina to Virginia to be sold in New Orleans.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844-018: American Bible Society, etc. v. Exr of Richard Carney, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Various charitable organizations (both inside and outside Virginia) and various enslaved people (emancipated by Richard Carney in his will) are suing Carney's executor claiming that he needs to render a proper account and adjust his transactions related to Carney's estate-essentially for the executor to honor what Carney intended in this will.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1853-008: Thomas Williams v. William N. Ivy, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves debt. Defendant proposes to complainant to form a slave trade co-partnership with him for the purchase of enslaved people to be sent to Louisiana. Two enslaved men with surnames, White and Shepherd, were bound for Mobile, Alabama aboard the schooner, Pelican. Cause also includes transcripts from St. Martin's Parish, Louisiana as exhibits filed by defendant. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1856-007: Petition of Gdn of Mary E. Woodhouse: 
 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Petition made to remove enslaved individuals of his ward, Mary E. Woodhouse, from Virginia to Currituck County in North Carolina. Court grants his petition.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1856-011: Zachariah Copeland v. Ann Copeland: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Marriage and divorce involving free people of color.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1856-017: Mary Harris, etc. v. Robert B. Bagby, etc. v. Robert B. Bagby v. Frederick Vincent, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves allowing by power of attorney a moiety on a Land Bounty warrant or claim by the state of Virginia for the Revolutionary services of their ancestor Simon Harris, surgeon in the Virginia State Navy during the Revolutionary War. Bagby files injunction against one of the defendants in second suit, Wilson, from issuing or delivering land warrants to other defendants in suit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1857-005: Exr of George Wilson, Sr. v. Dr. Asa Blood, sr., etc.:     
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause mentions Dr. Blood's original invention and patent for an obstetric chair.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1857-019: William C. Stewart and wife v. Exr of Henry Garrett, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves estate dispute. It mentions epidemic of yellow fever in town of Portsmouth in August 1855. Court was not held in county from August-November 1855 due to this epidemic.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>   
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1858-004: Eliza (Lissetor) Miller by, etc v. Daniel P. Miller: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Both plaintiff and defendant emigrated from Germany and were married in Baltimore, Maryland in 1855 and came to Virginia in 1858.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1859-013: Nancy Benn v. Exr of Thomas Tartt, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff wants  Thomas Tartt's will to be declared null and void so enslaved persons may not be granted their freedom. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1867-011: Widow of James Cuffee v. William J. (alias Johnson) Hodges, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves estate dispute related to validity of James Cuffee's will. Defendant, also a person of free color, was convicted of forgery in Princess AnneSuperior Court in 1829 and escaped from the county jail. Plaintiff contends that Hodges came back to the county during the occupation by the US Army. He pretended to practice law in the military court of courts of the Freedmen's Bureau.   
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1872-008: Charles W. Hare v. Sarah E. Hare: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff was forced to flee state of North Carolina. He claims defendant bought a bottle of poison home and threatened to take his life. She proceeded to mix the poison in whiskey and employed a man to give it to the plaintiff. Defendant was known to commit adultery and abandon her children.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1875-032: Eliza Jane Green by, etc. v. William Henry Green: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves divorce. Plaintiff and defendant (Free African Americans) were married in Goochland County in 1857. During the Civil War, defendant first deserted plaintiff but came back after the War. One daughter was born. In 1867, defendant left Virginia and moved to New York City. Plaintiff was abandoned again in 1868 and returned to Virginia. Plaintiff requests injunction against defendant and asks for custody of their child. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1877-003: R.W.Wright for, etc. v. Lewis Butt, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Trustees of the Divine Baptist Church at Deep Creek became possessed of a certain lot of land in the County of Norfolk. The congregation of the church wants to sell a portion of the land attached to the church to the Trustees of the Public Schools for the County to be used as a school house for the colored children of that section of the County of Norfolk. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1879-006: John Butt v. Sarah Shakleford: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves contract dispute between African Americans. Plaintiff alleges that he was forced to marry defendant. Plaintiff contends that defendant was not of chaste character. It was her desire, in his prosecution, to prevent his marriage with the person to whom he was engaged. Marriage was eventually declared null and void. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1881-002: George T. Wallace v. Heirs of Samuel Fisk, etc.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit involves debt, property and slavery. Samuel Fisk was the son-in-law of slave owner, Mitchell Phillips. John Duncan, a neighbor to both Fisk and Phillips, describes in detail in his deposition how Fisk attempted to save his father-in-law's property (enslaved persons) from the Yankees and in turn, how Fisk maneuvered to keep his own property.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1881-006: Polly Press by, etc. v. Charles Press, Sr.:
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit deals with divorce and separate maintenance of an African American couple. The defendant deserted plaintiff and moved to Princess Anne County. Plaintiff married defendant in Oct. 1864 but had cohabitated with plaintiff beginning in 1855-when both were enslaved. A child was born in 1866. Cohabitation becomes a legal argument in the cause.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1882-005: William C. Sawyer v. Serena Catherine Sawyer by, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff wishes to divorce defendant claiming she is insane and will remain insane-based on inherited traits from her father, R.B. Riell of the U.S. Navy. Unbeknownst to him, she spent time in an insane asylum. In 1874, she was committed to the Eastern Lunatic Asylum in the City of Williamsburg. The divorce is granted.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1883-010: W.D. Reynolds v. Admx of E.H. Hunter, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Land mentioned in bill and deed is found in the village of Berkley. A small portion of this land, to be served and excepted, is set aside as a burial ground "for persons of the Jewish religion."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1884-001: Marshall Fulton vs. Evaline Fulton:      
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff wanted a divorce because his wife was unable to have children. He informed the court that "the object of marriage was the procreation of children. And that by the impotency of the said Evaline Fulton, the said object of said marriage cannot be accomplished."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1886-026: William J. Bishop vs. Martha A. Fauth, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Includes a letter in which the writer provides negative commentary concerning the controversial 1876 Presidential election.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1889-026: Matilda Dorman vs. Henry Dorman: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Suit includes marriage license written in German. Plaintiff and defendant were married at an Evangelical Lutheran church in New York City called St. Lucas.    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1893-022: Alvah H. Martin, trustee vs. Berkley Hebrew Cemetery Association: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Depositions describe burial rituals for persons who died a natural death versus those who committed suicide or were murdered. Deponents were questioned on whether a member of the association, Abraham Liebman, murdered his wife or she committed suicide by poisoning. See also chancery cause 1893-012. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1897-022: Virginia Haley vs. Charles Warden, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiffs and defendants were descendants or related to a former enslaved person named John Haley. Deponents, answered questions concerning family relationships of enslaved people prior to and after the Civil War and migration of ex-enslaved people after the war. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1900-033: Laurence Waring vs. Alvah H. Martin: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendant was circuit court clerk for Princess Anne County. Plaintiff accused Martin of denying him access to deeds. Martin's response was that Waring was a nuisance in the office. He was making it difficult for the clerk's staff to do their job. Suit provides insight into the inner workings of a clerk's office.    
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1900-064: Fanny Haynes, etc. vs. Robert N.W. Keeling and wife, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Friendly suit concerning the removal of deceased family members from a burial ground located at Keeling farm to a cemetery in Portsmouth or Norfolk. Contains substantial genealogical information. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1902-017: Bertha Howell vs. Henry J. Howell: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Plaintiff accused defendant of visiting a house of ill fame and committing adultery on Christmas Day.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1902-061: Lehman Duncan and wife, etc. vs. John James Duncan and wife, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Genealogical chart used as exhibit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1904-014: Charles C. Sparks vs. Kathleen Sparks:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>- Divorce suit. Two photographs of defendant used as exhibit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1904-018: Nicodemus D. Lunsford vs. Lola P. Lunsford:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Plaintiff was African American and defendant was white. They were natives of Virginia. They went to Boston, Massachusetts to marry because the laws of Virginia forbade interracial marriage. The plaintiff said they did so "with the express intention of evading the laws of Virginia and with the intention of returning to Virginia and residing therein." They married in November 1878. The plaintiff stated that his wife abandoned him and their two daughters in July 1885 and moved to Maine. Suit includes attorney opinions regarding legality of the marriage.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01> 
     <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1905-042: Foster Black, etc. vs. Board of Supervisors of Princess Anne County, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>-  Defendants are current and former members of the Board of Supervisors for Princess Anne County. Plaintiffs accused defendants of fraudulent use of public funds. Exhibits include correspondence from other circuit courts concerning salaries of board of supervisors in other localities.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1906-015: Louis Dishart vs. Sarah Dishart:     
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit. Plaintiff and defendant are Russian immigrants. Plaintiff convicted of bigamy in Baltimore, MD.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1907-004: Columbia Amusement Co. vs. Pine Beach Investment Co., etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The plaintiff operated music and dancing pavilions, merry-go-rounds, shooting galleries, ball and baby galleries, scenic railways, and other amusements in Pine Beach. The defendants wanted to operate a hotel and/or bar at a skating rink on the resort that would sell intoxicating liquors. Plaintiff wanted an injunction to prevent the defendants from doing so. Suit includes correspondence with Columbia Amusement Company letterhead.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1907-055: Boer War Spectacle vs. S.W. Lyons, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff was a corporation chartered in Missouri engaged in reproducing, as public theatrical performances, certain fights and battles of the Boer War between England and the Boers which was waged in the Transvaal on the continent of Africa, including a panorama of certain scenes of the country in which said war was fought.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-031: Exx. Of John C. P. Edwards vs. Caroline Hatton Nash, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Includes will of John C. P. Edwards. Includes humorous requests. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-032: James W. Mackey, etc.  vs. I. E. Brothers, etc.: 
  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Litigants are descendants of George Mackey, a free African American before the Civil War. He was born in 1780. Suit includes depositions, genealogical chart and genealogical notes identifying descendants of George Mackey.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1909-099: S. Dimitro  vs. Robinson and Dilopoulo, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff states that he is the chief of all the Gypsy trips in the United States and his wife was the queen. They were working as fortune tellers at the Jamestown Exposition.     
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1911-072: Iva Robinson Fitzel vs. John A. Fitzel, Jr.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>- Divorce suit. "Flirtatious" postcards sent to the plaintiff by someone other than her husband used as exhibits.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1913-021: Philip L. Grasty vs. Electric Kitchen Cafe, Inc., etc:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Menu included as exhibit.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1913-055: Mary Augusta Barraud vs. Sallie T. Barraud, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Daniel Cary Barraud Wilson dropped "Wilson" from his name at the request of his grandfather who raised him from infancy. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1111-015: Mary Crump, etc. vs. John S. Williams, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff Mary Crump was an enslaved person prior to the Civil War. In a deposition, she testifies to event she recalled while enslaved such as the deaths of her children. She also gives the names of her parents and who owned them. Mary Crump gives a brief account of her travels during and after the Civil War and discovering family relations. Additional deponents are ex-enslaved persons who knew the plaintiff. In their testimony, they share events that they recall before and during the Civil War such as being sold or the death of a husband during the 1855 Yellow Fever epidemic as well as family relationships.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
