<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="https://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi05561">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05561::A Guide to the Pittsylvania County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1771-1890 (bulk 1848-1890)//EN" "vi05561.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Pittsylvania County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1771-1890 (bulk 1848-1890)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Pittsylvania County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1771-1890 (bulk 1848-1890)
</subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2022 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 February 2022</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2022">2022</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Pittsylvania County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1771-1890 (bulk 1848-1890)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
      <author>G. Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2022
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>G. Crawford, L. Jones and C. Freed
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Pittsylvania County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1771-1890 (bulk 1848-1890)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">89.52 cubic feet (198 boxes); Digital images.
</physdesc>
    
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Pittsylvania County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
 <p>Chancery Causes, 1771-1869 use digital images can be found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia. </p>

<p> Chancery Causes, 1870-1890 are unprocessed. Contact Archives Reference Services for availability.</p>

      </accessrestrict>

      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
   <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p> Pittsylvania (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1771-1890. (Cite style of suit [and chancery index no. if available]). Local government records collection, Pittsylvania Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
       
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Pittssylvania County (Va.) in 2017 under the accession number 52142.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo> 

<head>Processing Information
</head> 
<p>Processed by G. Crawford and L. Jones un 2017. Additional records were processed in 2018 by C. Freed.</p> 
<p> Chancery Causes, 1771-1869 were processed in two separate groups. The first group was processed by G. Crawford and L. Jones in 2017. The second group was processed by C. Freed in 2018. Post 1869 records are currently unprocessed and unindexed.</p> 

<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: 2022; Updated by E. Swain: June 2024.</p> 
</processinfo> 
      
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
   <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><title render="bold">Context of Record type:</title> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.</p> 
      <p><title render="bold">Locality History:</title> Pittsylvania County was named in honor of William Pitt, first earl of Chatham, the English statesman. It was formed from Halifax County in 1766. The county court first met on 26 June 1767. The county seat is Chatham.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p> Pittsylvania (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1771-1890, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>     
<arrangement encodinganalog="351"> 
      <head>Arrangement 
</head> 
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
</p> 
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder is as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found).</p> 
    </arrangement> 

  <descgrp type="add"> 
 <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data 

</head> 
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Pittsylvania County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA225">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>

<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03573.xml"> Pittsylvania County (Va.) Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery Records, 1832-1850</extref></p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi01515.xml"> Virginia Superior Court of Chancery (Richmond District). Records, 1806-1850</extref></p>

      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
     <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.</title></p> 
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1787-004: William Glass vs. Martin Armstrong, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Glass served in the North Carolina militia during the Revolutionary War. He wanted to be exempt from serving. He made an agreement with Armstrong who informed Glass he could find him a substitute. Armstrong also agreed to provide Glass with two horses in exchange for an enslaved man owned by Glass. Armstrong failed to provide a substitute to serve in the militia in Glass' place.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1790-009: Orlando Smith vs. John Sutherland, Sr.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Smith made an agreement with Sutherland to furnish a substitute in the militia for Smith's son. Both parties accused the other of not fulfilling their end of the agreement.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1790-011: Nathan Thurman vs. Jeremiah Ward: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Thurman lost a slander suit heard in common law to Ward. Thurman accused Ward of collecting bounties on dog ears and not wolf's ears. Thurman wanted the chancery court to overturn the law court's verdict.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1794-003: John Davis vs. Griffin Haynes and wife: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mary Haynes was an enslaved person who won her freedom from Davis in a lawsuit heard in Pittsylvania County court. She also won financial damages. According to Davis and witnesses, Haynes' attorney offered a deal to Davis: he would not have to pay damages or court costs in return for the freedom of Haynes' children and never trouble Haynes or her children regarding their freedom. Haynes did not acknowledge such an agreement. She claimed that once the court gave her freedom that here children were immediately freed as well. Haynes wanted Davis to pay the damages owed her.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1804-011: Daniel Fisher and wife vs. William Dunning, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Daniel Fisher's wife, Susanna, claimed to be the illegitimate daughter of William Dunning. She was sent to Loudoun County to live in order to avoid family embarrassment where she married Daniel Fisher. Dunning requested that they move to Pittsylvania County to take care of him in his old age. In return, he would leave them his estate when he died. Plaintiffs claimed Dunning reneged on the agreement.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1807-005: James Mitchell vs. Vincent Walker:  
</emph> </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The defendant was a doctor who Mitchell asked to cure his enslaved people alleged to have been poisoned. Cause includes depositions from individuals who hired Dr. Walker to cure their enslaved people who suffered from poisoning. The deponents shared ingredients for medicine Walker prescribed to cure their enslaved people.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1821-017: Mary Justice, etc. vs. Exrs of George Herndon, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom Suit. The Herndons joined the Society of Friends and Mr. Herndon offered to free Mary Justice. After he died, Mary stayed with his widow, Sarah Herndon, who refused to free Mary.

 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1822-020: Mark Anthony vs. James Arthur: 
</emph> </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mark Anthony, of Bedford County, sued James Arthur to prevent him from removing enslaved people fom the jurisdiction of the Pittsylvania County Court. The enslaved people had been given permission by the Court to sue for their freedom.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1828-007: Tom Butcher vs. Rice, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Tom Butcher was to be freed at 21 years of age by a manumission from Joshua Smith. After Mr. Smith died, his son-in-law, Josiah Askew, received Tom as part of his share in the division of Mr. Smith's estate. Tom was age 14 years when Josiah Askew transported Tom to North Carolina. Tom was sold a number of times and ended up the property of a Mr. Rice of Chester District, South Carolina. Tom fled to Dinwiddie County, Virginia to get his freedom papers. He was arrested in Pittsylvania County. Samuel M. Lovell wrote to Austin Billups of Dinwiddie County asking him to send money to Tom to pay the prison charges and obtain his freedom papers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1830-015: Sarah Fowlkes vs. James Fowlkes, Jr. etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>James Fowlkes hired an enslaved girl named Sarah from Martha Grigg and made her his mistress. Fowlkes' wife asked him to stop hiring the girl but he would not. Mrs. Fowlkes sued for divorce and asked for alimony.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1833-014: John Fowlkes vs. Martha Griggs: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Enslaved woman named Sarah was murdered as consequence of a contract dispute between the plaintiff and defendant. The cause includes multiple depositions that gave information regarding Sarah's death, the search to find the killer, and Fowlkes' agreement with Griggs.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1833-024: Frances Linn, by etc. vs. Thomas Linn: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Linns moved from Pittsylvania County to Grayson County Court House where he opened a tailor's business. Thomas Linn had and affair with one of his employees. They ran away to Philadelphia, Hiwassee District, Tennessee. The plaintiff sued her husband for divorce and custody of their three children.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1833-025: Susan E. Callaway vs. Henry Callaway:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The defendant had children by an enslaved woman named Ann. The cause includes affidavits identifying the defendant being with Ann in a building where the enslaved people lived. The cause was moved to Powhatan County by order dated 28 May 1833. See Powhatan Chancery Cause 1834-001: Henry Calloway and wife, etc. VS admx. of Francis Lewis, etc.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1838-032: Samuel Stone VS Samuel Edmundson, Jr., etc.  Samuel Edmundson, Jr.:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involves dispute over a enslaved runaway named Moses. Cause details circumstances surrounding Moses' efforts to be free.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1840-040: Morris Pollok vs. Reuben Hopkins:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Pollok and his brother's Robert and Allen were merchants from Scotland. Naturalization records of the Pollock family are filed as exhibits.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1846-013: William B. Banks, etc. vs. William B. Arthur, etc.:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendants in cause  were lawyers hired to defend William Bennet in a suit instituted and prosecuted by Milly Chavis, a free woman, for the purpose of establishing her right to freedom. The freedom suit had been instituted twenty years before the start of this cause. See Pittsylvania County Chancery Causes 1822-020, 1849-037, and 1851-011.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1848-033: Francis Williams vs. Julius Allen:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Per agreement, Williams and Allen were attempting to establish a slave trading business. According to deposition, enslaved people were bought in Richmond and sold in Alabama. Zachariah L. Hooper was identified as a slave trader by Samuel Cobb. Cause also relates to the selling of enslaved people in Georgia and North Carolina. Samuel Cobb and Henry Badgett, both based in North Carolina, were named as slave traders as well.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1848-034: William Worsham vs. Samuel Stone:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Parties in cause were slave traders. They purchased enslaved people in Richmond and sold them in South Carolina.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1849-037: Admr. of James Arthur vs Milly Chavis:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendant was a free person seeing to establish her freedom. See also Pittsylvania County Chancery Causes 1822-020, 1846-013 and 1851-011. Defendant was owned by plaintiff.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1851-011: John Arthur vs. Una or Unita Chavis:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freedom suit. Defendant is the daughter of Milly Chavis.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1851-031: Heir of Robert G. Tucker vs. Capt. Claiborne Tucker:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff cites that his brother, the defendant, has sold six enslaved people to George W. Hall who sold them in Georgia. According to depositions, the defendant emancipated an ensaved man named Tom in his will. However, Tom was one of the six enslaved persons sold in Georgia. 
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1854-061: John A. Adams vs. Nathaniel N. Witcher:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Parties in cause formed "a co-partnership, Witcher and Adams, for the purpose of carrying on the negro trade and buying negroes in Virginia and carrying them to the South for sale." In depositions, George W. Hall is also identified as a partner in the business. Slave Sam~, in receipt, is identified as a blacksmith.
 </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1855-038: George Hairston, etc. vs. Admx of Robert Hairston,etc. and 1855-039: Admr. of Robert Hairston v. Ruth S. Hairston:</emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Numerous defendants are not residents of Virginia. Peter Hairston died in North Carolina. He is the father of Ruth S. Hairston. According to cause, Ruth S. Hairston is in possession of and holds 684 enslaved people as executrix of her father's will. The enslaved people reside in North Carolina and Patrick, Henry, and Pittsylvania counties in Virginia. Heirs of Robert Hairston, Ruth's husband, are claiming 550 of those enslaved people. Other heirs reside in Henry County, Virginia. In the second cause, Robert Hairston left estates in Virginia, North Carolina, and Mississippi. He migrated from Virginia in 1841 for Mississippi and died there in 1852. His wife Ruth essentially ran his estates in Virginia and North Carolina.</p> 
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
<unittitle><emph render="underline">1855-041: Widow of Thomas Williams vs. Isaac Motley and wife, etc. and Adms. of Francis Williams, admr vs. Robert W. Williams, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Thomas Williams and Robert W. Williams owned a slave trading business. Robert W. Williams resides in Henry County, Virginia.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
<unittitle><emph render="underline">1866-012: Peter R. Riggs vs. Coleman D. Bennett, etc.: </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt suit that involves the establishment of a female seminary in the town of Chatham. At one point it was named the Female Academy of Chatham.</p> 
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
<unittitle><emph render="underline">1866-068: Edmund Fitzgerald and wife, etc. vs. Exr of John Wilson, etc.:  </emph> 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In John Wilson's will, he emancipated his enslaved people after 50 years. At the time of his death, he proposed measures to give his enslaved quasi freedoms. In an opinion filed in the cause, Richard Logan argued that "slaves born during the time of the testator making his will and the testator's death will be slaves for life."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>

             </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>