<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05389">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05389::A Guide to the Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1867//EN" "vi05389.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1836-1867</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Database, created by Callie Lou Freed, <date>08 August 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1836-1867</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine Obrion, Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1836-1867
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Location">State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>5 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Botetourt County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Many of these business volumes are fragile--some are in poor condition due to water damage. Please handle these volumes with extreme care.</emph>.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1867. Local government records collection, Botetourt County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Botetourt County in an undated accession.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the localtity.</p> 
<p>Encoded by C. Freed, August 2024
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Botetourt County was named for Norborne Berkeley, baron de Botetourt, the royal governor from 1768 to 1770. It was formed from Augusta County in 1769, and a part of Rockbridge County was added in 1785. The county court first met on 13 February 1770. The county seat is Fincastle. Area: 542.7 square miles. Population: 30,496 (2000), 31,800 (2005 estimate).
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Lost Records Locality: </emph> Created by an act of 1769 to take effect on February 13, 1770. Many of the loose records including pre-1830 chancery and pre-1854 judgments suffered tremendous water damage as a result of a courthouse fire on December 15, 1970. Because of the near loss of records, the General Assembly passed the Virginia Public Records Act in 1975 for the purpose of preserving local records. Volumes that record deeds, court orders, and wills exist.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Botetourt County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1867, are comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Botetourt County (Va.) Represented records consist of bound volumes such as an account ledger and account books.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Beneford and Wilson Account Ledger B, 1866-1867
 </item>
<item>Series II: McKnight and Galbraith Account Book, 1836-1846
 </item>
<item>Series III: Waskey Mills Account Book, 1840-1847
</item>
<item>Series IV: Williams and Woodville Account Books, 1849, 1852-1853
</item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Botetourt County(Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Botetourt County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Botetourt County records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Beneford and Wilson Account Ledger B,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1866-1867
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Benford and Wilson was a mercantile business that conducted business in Botetourt County during the mid-nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Benford and Wilson Account Ledger B, 1866-1867, contains information related to a mercantile business selling spices, dishes, cloth, clothing, sewing accessories, and other household items. It records the individual accounts of customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order, items purchased, and the amount owed and paid. Items purchased include calico, nutmeg, glasses, etc. Includes index.
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1102523">Beneford and Wilson Account Ledger B 
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1866-1867
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II ">McKnight and Galbraith Account Book,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1836-1846
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>McKnight and Galbraith was a mercantile business selling shoes and leather and repairing shoes. It conducted business in the town of Buchanan in Botetourt County during the mid-nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>McKnight and Galbraith Account Book, 1836-1846, contains information related to a leather and shoe-making business. It records the individual accounts of customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order, items purchased or services provided, and the amount owed and paid. No index.
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1102522">McKnight and Galbraith Account Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1836-1846
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Waskey Mills Account Book,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1840-1847
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Waskey Mills conducted business in Botetourt County during the mid-nineteenth century.  
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Waskey Mills Account Book, 1840-1847, records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Each entry records date of transaction, services rendered, quantity of oats, bran, flour, etc., processed, type of grain processed, amount owed, date of payment, form of payment, and amount paid. The mill processed bran, oats, flour, coffee, wheat, and shorts. Forms of payment include barter, labor, cash, and credit. Volume includes an index that lists in alphabetical order the names of customers and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1054887">Waskey Mills Account Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1840-1847
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV">Williams and Woodville Account Books,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849, 1852-1853
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Williams and Woodville was a medical practice formed by Charles Williams and James Lewis Woodville.
</p>
<p>James Lewis Woodville was born 8 Jan. 1820 in Augusta County, Virginia to James L. and Mary S. Lewis Woodville. He first attended the University of Virginia and then the University of Pennsylvania, where he graduated with a degree in medicine in 1844. Shortly thereafter he opened a medical practice in Botetourt County, Virginia. While there he also met and married Mary Ann Breckenridge (b. 1831) on 29 Sept. 1852. The couple had at least 6 children.
</p>
<p>At the start of the Civil War, Woodville volunteered his medical services to the Confederate Army. He served first in the 7th Virginia Infantry, and also at the Montgomery White Sulphur Springs Hospital near Blacksburg, West Virginia. Near the war's end Woodville was transferred to the Huguenot Springs Hospital near Richmond, Virginia. Following the war Woodville moved to Sweet Springs, Monroe County, West Virginia and began a new medical practice. He died there on 14 August 1904.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Williams and Woodville Account Book, 1849, records the accounts of individual patients. The accounts list charges and payments for visits to patients, medication, and other medical services. 
</p>
<p>Williams and Woodville Account Book, 1852-1853, records the accounts of individual customers. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Each entry records date of transaction, service rendered, and amount owed. Services rendered visits to patients, prescription for medication, and extracting teeth. volume includes an index that lists in alphabetical order the names of patients and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1102642">Williams and Woodville Account Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1849
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
  <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1054886">Williams and Woodville Account Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1852-1853
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
