<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05896">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05896::A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852)//EN" "vi05896.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, <date>1843-1852</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records
<num type="barcodenumber">0007843137
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>McKenzie Long
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
<date type="publication">&#169; 2023  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record by McKenzie Long, <date>22 September 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, <date>1843-1852</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>McKenzie Long
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1843-1852
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007843137 
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.45 cu. ft. (1 box)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone minimal processing. All records remain tri-folded or in original bundles and may be fragile. Contact Archives Research services for availability.  
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852. Local government records collection, Greensville County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a 2023 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 53810.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Encoded by M. Long: September 2023.
</p>
<p>Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes were processed using minimal processing standards: Locality records were organized by broad record category (election records, fiduciary records, etc.) with minimal other arrangement. These records have not been flattened, foldered, mended, or separated by individual record type (like summons, appraisements, etc.).
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:  </title> Mental Health Records may consist of a variety of documents that historically were referred to as "lunacy papers" in the courthouses of Virginia localities and municipalities. </p>
<p>In 1863, the Virginia General Assembly passed two pieces of legislation affecting persons committed to mental hospitals. In February, it passed legislation allowing for a committee to sell any stock and for any proceeds beyond that necessary for his/her care to be invested in any stock, to include Confederate bonds.  In March, the General Assembly widened the scope of this by passing legislation authorizing any fiduciaries such as the committee or trustee of the estate of any person to petition their circuit court to allow them to invest any part of estate funds in Confederate bonds or certificates.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p><title render="italic">These records contain historical language and contents that by modern standards are insensitive to those living with mental health issues.</title></p>
<p> Greensville County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852, are comprised of various mental health, medical, and public health records produced by the actions of individuals, medical professionals, and local officials which were then filed in the local court. The records have undergone minimal processing. This has allowed for the documentation of specific record types and various trends found in this set of records.</p>
<p>Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852 that have undergone minimal processing consist primarily of "lunacy papers," commitment papers which may include warrants, orders, petitions, depositions, reports, etc. for or by justices of the peace and others regarding the mental condition of individuals who were released to the recognizance of a family member or who were recommended to be committed to a mental hospital. Mental hospitals and facilities operating as such may be referenced throughout this collection, namely "Eastern Lunatic Asylum" [Eastern State Hospital], "Western Lunatic Asylum" [Western State Hospital], and "Central Lunatic Asylum" [Central State Hospital].</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series I: Minimally Processed Health and Medical Records, 1843-1852,</emph> are loosely arranged chronologically.</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Minimally Processed Health and Medical Records, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1843-1852</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.45 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Loosely arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007843137 ">Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Clerk; Commissioner of Revenue; Election; Fiduciary; Health and Medical; Jury; Justice of the Peace; Miscellaneous; Military and Pension; Overseers of the Poor; Property; Public Buildings; School; Sheriff; Treasurer; Wills,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1792-1870
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>