<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05810">




<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05810::A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Governor's Fellows Program, 2010-2011)//EN" "vi05810.xml"
</eadid>

<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Governor's Fellows Program Records,Secretary of the Commonwealth <date> 2010-2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Secretary of the Commonwealth, Records of the Governor's Fellows Program, 2010-2011
<num type="collectionnumber">51154</num></subtitle>
<author>Alan B. Arellano
</author>
</titlestmt>

<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2022  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 

</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>

<profiledesc>
<creation>Created by Alan B. Arellano, <date>8 March, 2022</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>


<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Governor's Fellows Program, <date>2010-2011</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession Number:">51154
</num>
</subtitle>


<author>Alan B. Arellano
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2022 
</date>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Alan B. Arellano
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Secretary of the Commonwealth, Governor's Fellows Program, Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2010-2011
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">51154
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"> .3 cu. ft. (1 boxes)
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per code of Virginia<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/vacode/title42.1/chapter7/section42.1-78/">42.1-78</extref>.  It may be necessary for an archivist to review records in this collection before they are served to patrons for research purposes in order to redact or remove privacy protected or confidential information.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no use restrictions. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virginia.Secretary of the Commonwealth, Administrative and Executive, Records of the Governor's Fellow Program, 2010-2011, Accession 51145, State Government Records Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, VA. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information</head>
<p>Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, accession 51154 transferred on 23 January 2014.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Original chronological arrangment maintained by archivist.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>

<p>The Governor's Fellows program aimed to provide high quality applied learning opportunities to students from the Commonwealth currently enrolled in undergraduate and graduate programs. Governor Charles S. Robb appointed A. E. Dick Howard as counselor to the Governor in 1982. One of his actions was to create the Governor's Fellows Program, a program that invited college and graduate students to apply to serve for a summer in the Governor's Office. Through professional mentorships, community service, and challenging projects, the mission was to strengthen ties of the office to Virginia communities. Some of the program's goals under Governor F. McDonnell included: Connecting with public and private institutions in a meaningful way throughout the recruitment process, creation of a formal alumni program, and increasing the number of applicants. To this end, the key changes to the program made by the Governor were: expansion of eligibility requirements; assigned mentor in an interest area, not in an assigned secretariat; weekly fellow meetings to gauge overall experience; a parallel internship program for rising sophomore and junior students not considered for the fellowship.</p>

<p>Robert F. McDonnell was elected 71st governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia in November 2009 and inaugurated on 16 January 2010. He served until 11 January 2014. Janet Vestal Kelly served as the Secretary of the Commonwealth throughout McDonnell's tenure. She had previsously served as the Chief Operations Officer during his gubernatorial campaign and as a staff member during his stint as Attorney General.</p>

<p>The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. The Office became a gubernational appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Other responsibilities include authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.</p> 
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>

<p>The Governor's Fellows Program Records are housed in 1 box. The collection is comprised of correspondence, documentation of the recruitment and interview process, applicant lists, orientation documents, and project papers/presentations. The two project presentations included are from 2011: <emph render="italic">Virginia's Drug Treatment Courts: Expanding a Proven Solution throughout the Commonwealth</emph>, and <emph render="italic">Making Southside Virginia the Freshwater Fishing Toursim Capital of the East Coast</emph>.</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>The <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://archive-it.org/collections/1655"><emph render="bold">Governor Robert F. McDonnell Administration Web Archive Collection, 2010-2014</emph></extref> contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries, including <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://wayback.archive-it.org/1655/*/http://www.commonwealth.virginia.gov/"><emph render="bold">Secretary of the Commonwealth Kelly</emph></extref>. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Maureen McDonnell), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Ken Cuccinelli).</p>

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi05801.xml"><emph render="bold"> Constituent Correspondence of Governor Robert F. McDonnell</emph></extref>Collection</p> 

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi05809.xml"><emph render="bold"> Correspondence and Supporting Documentation of the Executive Office of Governor Robert F. McDonnell</emph></extref>Collection</p> 

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04733.xml"><emph render="bold"> Records of the Executive Mansion of Governor Robert F. McDonnell</emph></extref>Collection</p>

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04740.xml"><emph render="bold"> Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secreatry of Transporation</emph></extref>Collection</p>

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi05508.xml"><emph render="bold"> Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secreatry of Administration</emph></extref>Collection</p>

<p>The<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi05508.xml"><emph render="bold"> Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secreatry of Administration</emph></extref>Collection</p>
</relatedmaterial>

<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle><emph render="bold">Records of the Governor's Fellows Program</emph>, 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">2010-2011</emph></unitdate>.</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
 	<unittitle>Governor's Fellows Program 
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2010</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
 	<container label="Box" type="box">1
 	</container>
 	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
 	</container>
 	</did>
 	</c02>
	
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
 	<unittitle>Governor's Fellows Program 
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
 	<container label="Box" type="box">1
 	</container>
 	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
 	</container>
 	</did>
 	</c02>
	
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
 	<unittitle>Governor's Fellows Pgoram - Presenations/Reports
 	<unitdate type="inclusive">2011</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
 	<container label="Box" type="box">1
 	</container>
 	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
 	</container>
 	</did>
 	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>