<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi05181">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05181::A Guide to the Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912)//EN" "vi05181.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1912</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912
<num type="collectionnumber">Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-001-1912-078
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2019 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">02 December 2019</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1912</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Chancery Records Index:">Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-001-1912-078
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2019
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field processing and LVA staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1912
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Chancery Records Index" encodinganalog="099$a">Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-001-1912-078 
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Carroll County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Patrons are to use digital images of Carroll County  (Va.) Chancery Causes found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local Government Records Collection, Carroll County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
</p>
      <p>Carroll County was named for Charles Carroll of Carrollton, a signer of the Declaration of Independence from Maryland. It was formed from Grayson County in 1842, and part of Patrick County was added in 1856. The county seat is Hillsville.
</p>
       </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912, are indexed into the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
</p>
      <p>Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Carroll County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  See <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref></p>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
</p>      
      </relatedmaterial>
     </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Carroll County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--History.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Business enterprises--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Debt--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Divorce suits--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Estates (Law)--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Equity--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Land subdivision--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
	<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Carroll County.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Carroll County (Va.)--History.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Carroll County (Va.)--Genealogy.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Chancery causes--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Deeds--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Judicial records--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Land records--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Plats--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Wills--Virginia--Carroll County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
 <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Selected Suits of Interest 
</head>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1866-005: Jesse Marion vs. Letitia Marion; 1866-006: Amos Bryant vs. Mary Bryant; 1866-011: Ephraim C. Wampler vs. Eliza Wampler; 1867-017: George W. Hendly vs. Jane Hendly; 1867-019: John T. Edwards vs. Isabella T. Edwards; 1868-018: Allen E. Bowers vs. Elizabeth W.G. Bowers; 1871-017: Julian Gordy vs. Sarah Gordy; and 1877-014: Wesley Sutphin vs. Lucy T. Sutphin:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiffs served in the Confederate army during the Civil War. They returned home after the war and accused wives of adultery while they were away in the service.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1868-005: John Early and wife vs. William C. Thornton and wife, etc.: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Documents in cause reference destruction of court records by Federal soldiers under the command of Major General Stoneman in April 1865.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1878-032: American Colonization Society vs. Edward Marshall:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Will found in cause originally recorded in Philadelphia. ACS alleges that sheriff covertly withheld a tax bill with intent to force delinquency and sale of property, purchased by him. Deceased was native Virginian, former governor of Illinois, had been on ACS board of directors and was a longtime antislavery proponent. His will bequeathed a large tract of land to the ACS so the organization could sell it and use the proceeds to further its colonization efforts.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1880-051: Sparrel Huff, etc. v. John Collier, etc.:  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Peter Huff died intestate, but leaving several enslaved people, one of which "was assigned to his widow Mary for her lifetime, in pursuance of the statute then in force allowing a widow a life estate in one third of the slaves of which her husband dies possessed." Later, "the said slave, becoming unmanageable and impudent was by consent and agreement of all parties, sold." The widow was to receive interest annually on the sale (slave was sold for 570 dollars in 1853.)  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1882-021: Thomas W. Bryant vs. Guardians of James McMurran: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause involved recovering 13 years of expenses for caring for boy whose father joined the Union Army during the late war and died in service, leaving pensions to his heirs.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1882-034: Ellis Dalton Vs. Lucy J. Dalton: 
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Husband seeks divorce from wife alleged of adultery, and who left for West Virginia while husband was "sick with the fever." When asked if she would at least come see him as he was very ill and may not survive, deposition notes that "before she would come one step back this way she would go ten thousand miles the other way."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1883-003: Joseph Norton vs. Sophina Norton:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Husband seeks divorce due to wife's infidelity and giving birth to child three months after marriage and "attempting to destroy" child. Wife gave birth outdoors in the snow in the middle of the night and left the infant near a log under some snow. Infant's frozen body was found the next day. Wife claimed she had been raped. She later fled Virginia. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
  <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1886-009: Alexander Smith vs. Martha F. Williams:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defendant's husband was still alive in Washington County. Depositions reference a divorce cause involving the defendant heard in Grayson County. See also Grayson County Chancery Cause 1860-039: Matilda Williams vs. William Williams. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1893-027: Milton Stoneman vs. John W. Stoneman, etc.:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wife of complainant died leaving property to her sons, and giving her husband lifetime rights to a portion. Will also directs sons to care for their father. Complainant charges that the sons are not doing so. Interesting cause where husband has no property or means of support other than that bequeathed by his wife.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1896-021: Elizabeth Dalton vs. Isaac Jennings:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff alleges that land sold by late husband was sold after her marriage so she believes she is due a dower interest. Depositions reference War of 1812 and Civil War. Transcript of Chancery Cause 1855-003: James Stafford etc. vs. Reuben Dalton etc.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1903-019: A.W. Westmoreland vs. Laura A. Westmoreland:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff claimed Laura Westmoreland moved to Utah "where she still lives in adultery and for aught he knows she may there in the land of Joe Smith and Brigham Young be trying to substitute the practice of polyandry for the more ancient practice of polygamy."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1903-041: Nancy E. Worrell, etc. vs. James A. Worrell and wife:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Nancy Worrell was mother of James A. Worrell. They made a contract that James would take care of her in her old age. James moved to Idaho seeking better opportunities. Cause includes correspondence between mother and son. Nancy pleaded with her son to return home. James wrote back saying he will never return describing saying Idaho was much better than Virginia was. The cause was dismissed at request of Nancy because her son returned home.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1904-069 and 1906-003: W.E. Jennings vs. Emily Jennings:   
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Emily Jennings was formerly married to John Oliver who left the state and was believed to be dead. He returned shortly after Emily married W.E. Jennings.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
