<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vi05023">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05023::A Guide to the Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910))//EN" "vi05023.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910)</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910)</subtitle>
        <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2017 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Greg Crawford, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09 February 2017</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia</subtitle>
      <author>Greg Crawford
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/lva_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Field Processors
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <physloc label="Location">State Records Center Archival Annex
</physloc>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">Digital images; 79.65 cubic feet (174 boxes) 
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Danville (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913, use digital images found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions on use.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913 (bulk 1880-1910). (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Danville (Va.) Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Danville (Va.) in 2009 under the accession number 44112.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913, were processed by field processors before 2009. 
</p>
<p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program in 2015.</p>
<p>Encoded by G. Crawford: February 2017; updated by C. Collins: October 2023.</p>
</processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.
</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Danville, in Pittsylvania County, was named for the Dan River on which the city is located. Danville was established in 1793, was incorporated as a town in 1830, and became a city in 1890. The town of North Danville, incorporated in 1877 and renamed Neopolis in 1894, was added in 1896.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Danville (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1913, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.</p>
      <p>Commonly found surnames among the plaintiffs and defendants include Adams, Anderson, Ayres, Bass, Bethell (also spelled Bethel), Boisseau, Boswell, Brown, Cabell, Carter, Claiborne, Clark, Coleman, Coles, Conrad, Corbin, Cosby, Crawley, Crews, Crumpton, Davis, Elliott, Ferrell, Fitzgerald, Freeman, Fuller, Gerst, Gravely, Graves, Green, Hairston, Hall, Harris, Harrison, Harvey, Hill, Holland, Hunt, Hutchings, Johnson, Johnston, Jones, Keen, Lawson, Lewis, Lipscomb (also spelled Lipscombe), Martin, Miller, Millner, Mitchell, Moore, Motley, Noell, Pace, Pairo, Patton, Penn, Richardson, Robertson, Robinson, Scott, Smith, Spencer, Stokes, Swanson, Talbott, Taylor, Thomas, Waddill, Walker, Walters, Watkins, Watson, White, Williams, Williamson, Wilson, Withers, Wood, Wooding, and Yates.
</p>
<p>The Bank of Danville is the primary defendant in 12 suits that ended between 1890 and 1912. The Town of Danville is involved in 13 suits that ended between 1860 and 1890 as the primary defendant, while the City of Danville is the primary defendant in 10 suits that ended between 1890 and 1913.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found.  Arranged chronologically.
</p>
      <p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Danville (Va.) Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.</extref></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
     </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>

  
