<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05388">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05388::A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Business Records, 1801-1839//EN" "vi05388.xml" </eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>
A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Business Records,
<date>1801-1839</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
Amelia County (Va.) Business Records
<num type="collectionnumber"> </num>
</subtitle>
<author>Callie Lou Freed </author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia </publisher>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. </date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>
Machine-readable finding aid derived from Database, created by Callie Lou Freed,
<date>07 August 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>
Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English </language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>
A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Business Records,
<date>1801-1839</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>
A Collection in
<lb/>
the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia </publisher>
<date type="publication">2024 </date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: </label>
<item>Greg Crawford </item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia </runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary </head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia </repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Amelia County (Va.) Business Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1801-1839 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Location">State Records Center; Library of Virginia </physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
<extent>3 volumes; 1 microfilm reel</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English </language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Amelia County (Va.) Circuit Court </origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information </head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions </head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled,
<emph render="bold">please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available</emph>.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions </head>
<p>There are no restrictions. </p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation </head>
<p>Amelia County (Va.) Business Records, 1801-1839. Local government records collection, Amelia County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219. </p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information </head>
<p>The Account Books came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Amelia County in an undated accession. </p>
<p>The Daybook came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Amelia County in 2001 under the accession number 37993.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available </head>
<p><emph render="bold">Please see<extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA009">Amelia County Microfilm </extref>index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
</emph></p>
<p>Office Tavern Post Office Account Book, 1832-1834 is available as microfilm Amelia County (Va.) Reel 106</p>
<p>Office Tavern Post Office Account Book, 1837-1839 is available as microfilm Amelia County (Va.) Reel 106</p>
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information </head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the localtity.</p>
<p>Encoded by C. Freed, August 2024 </p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information </head>
<p>
<emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph>Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph>Amelia County was named for Amelia Sophia Eleanora, daughter of King George II. It was formed from Prince George and Brunswick Counties by an act passed in 1734 to take effect on 25 March 1735. The county court first met on 9 May 1735. The county seat is Amelia. Area: 356.8 square miles. Population: 11,400 (2000), 12,100 (2005 estimate).
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content </head>
<p>Amelia County (Va.) Business Records, 1831-1904, are comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Amelia County (Va.) Represented records consist of bound volumes such as account books and a daybook. </p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement </head>
<p>
This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Office Tavern Post Office Account Books, 1832-1839 </item>
<item>Series II: Pridesville Tavern Daybook, 1801-1803 </item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data </head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material </head>
<p>Additional Amelia County (Va.) records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA009">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List </head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Office Tavern Post Office Account Books,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1839 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center </physloc>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>In 1741, Samuel Cobbs, the first Amelia County court clerk, was authorized to build an 'ordinary' (tavern) at the crossroads near his house. He maintained an office there as well as at Amelia, thus the location eventually became known as Office Tavern Post Office, and a small community grew up around it.</p>
<p>Egbert Giles Leigh, Sr., also served a term as Amelia County Court clerk.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>
Office Tavern Post Office Account Book, 1832-1834, records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each account includes dates of transactions, amount owed for mailing or receiving letters, location where letters were mailed and received, and form of payment. This account book was kept by postmaster Egbert Giles Leigh, Sr.
</p>
<p>Office Tavern Post Office Account Book, 1837-1839, records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each account includes dates of transactions, amount owed for mailing or receiving letters, location where letters were mailed and received, and form of payment. This account book was kept by postmaster Peter R. Leigh.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1104204">Office Tavern Post Office Account Book 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1834 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 1104205">Office Tavern Post Office Account Book
<unitdate type="inclusive">1837-1839 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">Pridesville Tavern Daybook,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1801-1803 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia </physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>
The Pridesville Tavern operated in Amelia County during the early nineteenth century.
</p>
<p>
<emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Pridesville Tavern Daybook, 1801-1803, records transactions on a daily basis. Information found in each entry includes name of customer, date of transaction, items purchased or services rendered, and amounts owed and paid. Services provided by the tavern included renting rooms, serving of meals and alcoholic drinks, and the feeding and livery of horses. Some alcoholic drinks served at the tavern were grog, whiskey, julep, wine, brandy, and rum.
</p>
<p>Located in the front of the volume is a list of students attending Jefferson College in 1801. Jefferson College, incorporated 26 December 1800, was located in Amelia County. The list includes student name, date student entered college, amount of tuition payment received, and, for a few students, a note on when a student quit the college.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle label="Barcode number 7315641">Pridesville Tavern Daybook
<unitdate type="inclusive">1801-1803 </unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>