<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05123">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05123::A Guide to the Chesterfield County (Va.), Health and Medical Records, 1780-1904)//EN" "vi05123.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Chesterfield County (Va.), Health and Medical Records, <date>1780-1904</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Chesterfield County (Va.), Health and Medical Records, 1780-1904
<num type="collectionnumber">0007770387
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Tracy S. Harter
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2020  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid created in EAD by Tracy S. Harter, <date>14 April 2020</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Chesterfield County (Va.), Health and Medical Records, <date>1780-1904</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
<num type="Collection Number">0007770387
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2020 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>T. Harter
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Chesterfield County Health and Medical Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1780-1904
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007770387
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.225 cf (1/2 hollinger)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Chesterfield County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Chesterfield County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 1780-1904. Local government records collection, Chesterfield County Court Records, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>This collection came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Chesterfield County Circuit Court.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Mental Health Records may consist of a variety of documents that historically were referred to as lunacy papers in the courthouses of Virginia localities and municipalities.
</p>
<p>A fiduciary is an individual who enters into a confidential and legal relationship which binds them to act on behalf of another. Guardians are legally invested to take care of another person, and of the property and rights of that person. Thus, some records referred to as insanity papers are housed with fiduciary records and not with mental health records.
</p>
<p>By 1792, Virginia's General Assembly enacted very strict laws governing the practice of inoculation. The new act required a license from the county court to administer vaccinations. It also included a penalty of $1,500 or six months of imprisonment for anyone willfully spreading smallpox in a manner other than that specified by the act.
</p>
<p>During its session begun in November 1769, the House of Burgesses passed an act establishing a hospital in Williamsburg for the mentally ill. The Eastern Lunatic Asylum (now Eastern State Hospital) was the first institution in America constructed as a mental hospital. The first patients were admitted in October 1773.
</p>
<p>In January 1825 the Virginia General Assembly passed legislation providing for the construction of an asylum in the western part of the state. The institution, which became known as Western Lunatic Asylum, was constructed close to the town of Staunton, west of the Blue Ridge Mountains, and was the second mental health facility built in the Commonwealth of Virginia. The buildings and surrounding gardens were designed to embrace the idea of "moral therapy" for mentally ill patients by providing an aesthetically pleasing and tranquil atmosphere in which patients lived comfortably, exercised and worked outdoors.
</p>
<p>Western Lunatic Asylum opened in 1828, accepting both male and female patients suffering from a variety of mental disorders. It should be noted that the hospital underwent a short-lived name change between 1861 and 1865, when it was known as Central Lunatic Asylum. (It should not be confused with an asylum of the same name later built in Petersburg, Virginia to house African American patients). From 1865 to 1894 the name was again Western Lunatic Asylum. However, in 1894 the General Assembly passed legislation changing the name to Western State Hospital.
</p>
<p>In March 1882 a 300 acre tract of land was purchased by the City of Petersburg and given to the state for the purpose of constructing a permanent mental health facility for African Americans. Construction of the new facility near Petersburg was completed in early spring 1885. This later included a special building to house the criminally insane apart from the rest of the hospital population. An early institutional history notes that treatment at Central Lunatic Asylum during the 1890s was humane and emphasized the value of work and the benefits of recreation. However, practices at the facility also included seclusion, mechanical restraints, and the administering of hypnotics.
</p>
<p> In 1894, Central Lunatic Asylum was officially renamed Central State Hospital. This piece of legislation also altered the names of the other mental health facilities in Virginia in and attempt to inspire a more positive image of the institutions, and of mental health treatment in general. It is important to note that another state institution located in Staunton, Virginia went by the name Central Lunatic Asylum between the years of 1861 and 1865. Its name later was changed to Western Lunatic Asylum, and is a separate facility with no connection to the Richmond/Petersburg hospital for African Americans.
</p>
<p>In March 1884 the Virginia General Assembly appointed a board of commissioners to select a site for a new lunatic asylum for white citizens to be built west of New River near Marion, Virginia. Dr. Harvey Black became the first superintendent of Southwestern Lunatic Asylum when it opened in May 1887. Dr. Robert J. Preston and Dr. John S. Apperson served as assistant physicians, and Mr. C.W. White was appointed as steward to oversee the day-to-day business operations of the hospital. The patient population grew steadily and over time several buildings were added to the hospital's campus including a tuberculosis treatment building, a building for the criminally insane, the Davis Clinic, and the Harmon Building. For much of its early history, the hospital was mostly self-sufficient through the utilization of its own farm for meat, milk, and vegetables. Other early hospital superintendents include Dr. Robert J. Preston (1888-1906), Dr. Daniel Trigg (1906-1908), Dr. J.C. King (1908-1915), Dr. E.H. Henderson (1915-1927), and Dr. George A. Wright (1927-1937). The hospital has gone through two name changes in its history. In 1894 the General Assembly passed legislation changing the name from Southwestern Lunatic Asylum to Southwestern State Hospital. In 1988, the name was changed to Southwestern Virginia Mental Health Institute.
</p>
<p>Chesterfield County was named for Philip Dormer Stanhope, fourth earl of Chesterfield, British statesman and diplomat, and was formed from Henrico County in 1749. The county seat is Chesterfield Court House. Part of Henrico County was added to Chesterfield in 1922.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p> Chesterfield County (Va.) Health and Medical Records, 1780-1904, consist of .225cf of Mental Health Records and Smallpox Epidemic Records.
</p>
<p>Mental Health Records, 1780-1904, n.d. consists of 4 folders, and may include warrants, orders, petitions, depositions, reports, etc. for or by justices of the peace and others regarding the mental condition of individuals who were released to the recognizance of a family member or who were committed to a mental hospital.  Includes references to several mental hospitals. Fiduciary records such as estate inventories of a person judged insane may also be present. 
</p>
<p>Smallpox Epidemic Records, 1829, 1836-1837, consist of three folders relating to smallpox hospitals and expenses associated with them regarding treatment of smallpox outbreaks in Chesterfield County. Minutes of a meeting of justices of the peace in 1829 provide details of establishing a makeshift hospital at the home of Mr. Frances Watkins, appointing a physician and manager and outlining their duties, fees to be assessed to patients, and proposals for universal vaccination. A hospital near the town of Manchester was established to house patients during an outbreak between Nov. 1836 and April 1837. In addition to several bills and receipts related to hospital supplies and patient treatment are two reports and a letter from the physician to the justices near the close of the outbreak. One detailed hospital statement lists names of patients admitted, the majority of whom were enslaved or free African Americans, and includes the number of days hospitalized and whether a patient survived. Another report lists payments to be made to various personnel, as well as bills to be paid by owners for enslaved people treated, including the number of days treated and burial expenses if applicable. One physician's report also included payments to five free African American nurses, including Katy Cheatham, whose petition to remain in the Commonwealth was granted in 1840 largely due to her commendable service during the 1837 outbreak. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Chronological by year, then alphabetically by last name of individual.
</p>
    </arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Additional Chesterfield County court records can be found on microfilm and in the Chancery Records Index at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"</extref> and <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/"> The Chancery Records Index</extref>.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
<controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head> 
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Chesterfield County (Va.) Circuit Court.</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Central Lunatic Asylum for Colored Insane, Virginia.</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Central State Hospital (Petersburg, Va.).</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Eastern State Hospital (Va.).</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Southwestern Lunatic Asylum (Marion, Va.).</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Southwestern State Hospital (Marion, Va.).</corpname>
       <corpname encodinganalog="610$a">Western State Hospital (Va.).</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">African Americans--Mental Health--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">County courts--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Insanity--Jurisprudence--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Jails--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Medical laws and legislation--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Mental illness--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Physicians--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Psychiatric hospitals--Virginia.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public health--Virginia.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public health administration--Virginia.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Public records--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Slaves--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Smallpox--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Smallpox prevention.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Chesterfield County (Va.)--History--18th Century.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Chesterfield County (Va.)--History--19th Century.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Health and Medical--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Local government records--Virginia--Chesterfield County.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
   <dsc type="analyticover">
     <head>Cases of Interest
</head>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph S. Dudley,  
<unitdate>1847
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Estate inventory includes valuations of five enslaved people:  George, Davy, Bill, Johnson, and Robert.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edward Wren,  
<unitdate>1856
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>The board of Eastern Lunatic Asylum determined that he was not ill and rejected him.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Charlotte Christian,  
<unitdate>1880
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Justices ordered that she be sent to the Lunatic Asylum at Richmond.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Sarah A. Rowlett,  
<unitdate>1884
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>She was declared a lunatic in November 1883 and taken into custody by the sheriff.  She petitioned the court for her own release.  In January 1884 the executive committee at Eastern State Lunatic Asylum in Williamsburg declared her to be of sound mind, and did not accept her.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John T. Cottrell,  
<unitdate>1889
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Includes a letter to Virginia Governor Fitzhugh Lee from R.J. Preston, Superintendent of Southwestern Lunatic Asylum (Marion, Va.), regarding this patient, but in which he writes primarily of the crowded conditions of the hospital and the types of rooms and patients they can accommodate. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Buck Ford,  
<unitdate>1892
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Includes a postcard to the sheriff from Randolph Barksdale, Superintendent and Physician of Central Lunatic Asylum (in Petersburg, for African Americans).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Unknown,  
<unitdate>1894
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>This file only includes a postcard from Randolph Barksdale, and documents the name change of Central Lunatic Asylum to Central State Hospital, also noting that the hospital is crowded. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mrs. L. Baker,  
<unitdate>1894
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Includes letter from superintendent of the Eastern Lunatic Asylum informing the Sheriff that they have no room, and suggests they apply for Mrs. Baker at Staunton.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Tom Watts and Winston Staten,  
<unitdate>1900
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Includes letter and postcard from Superintendent William F. Drewry of Central State Hospital explaining that these two people (most likely African Americans) cannot be admitted due to overcrowding.  Unlike postcards from just a few years prior, the postcard is pre-printed with text regarding reasons for being unable to admit patients, and has blanks on which to enter information.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Garthright,  
<unitdate>1900
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
<scopecontent>
          <p>Includes a handwritten statement signed by forty neighbors asserting that Garthright has recovered and that they fear no harm from him.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
        </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
