<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05391">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05391::A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1924)//EN" "vi05391.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1850-1924</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Callie Lou Freed
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Database, created by Callie Lou Freed, <date>09 August 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1850-1924</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Catherine Obrion, Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1850-1924
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Location">State Records Center; Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2 volumes; 1 microfilm reel</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Brunswick County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, <emph render="bold">please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available</emph>.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, 1850-1924. Local government records collection, Brunswick County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Brunswick County in an undated accession.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Please see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA039">Brunswick County Microfilm </extref> index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.</emph> </p>
<p>Unidentified Blacksmith and Drummondsburg Plantation Account Book, 1850-1870 is available as microfilm Brunswick County (Va.) Reel 137</p>
</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the localtity.</p> 
<p>Encoded by C. Freed, August 2024
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Brunswick County was named for the duchy of Brunswick-Luneburg, one of the German possessions of King George I. It was formed by statute in 1720 from Prince George County and on 31 October 1723 the boundaries of the county were ordered to be laid out, but, because of the sparse population, the county court first met in June 1732. Brunswick County was enlarged by the addition of parts of Surry and Isle of Wight Counties in 1733. The county seat is Lawrenceville. Area: 566.1 square miles. Population: 18,419 (2000), 18,400 (2005 estimate).
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Lost Records Locality: </emph>Brunswick County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Created in 1720 (county government established in June 1732). Most loose records prior to 1781 are missing. Pre-1781 volumes that record deeds, court orders, and wills exist.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Brunswick County (Va.) Business Records, 1831-1904, undated are comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Brunswick County (Va.) Represented records consist of bound volumes such as a contract book and an account book.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association Contract Book, 1921-1924
 </item>
<item>Series II: Unidentified Blacksmith and Drummondsburg Plantation Account Book, 1850-1870
 </item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Brunswick County (Va.) records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA039">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Brunswick County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Brunswick County records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Digital Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/lost">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref> available at Virginia Memory.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association Contract Book,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1921-1924
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>The Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association was a non-profit association of tobacco farmers organized in North Carolina in 1921 and administered by a board of twenty-five directors in Raleigh. It was organized for the purpose of promoting, fostering, and encouraging the business of marketing tobacco cooperatively: for reducing speculation; for stabilizing the local tobacco markets; for cooperatively and collectively handling the problems of tobacco growers, and for other pertinent purposes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association Contract Book, 1921-1924. The contract book contains the names of farmers who signed contracts, their address (name of community), the date of the contract, the number of pounds and type of tobacco (dark or bright) they pledged to produce each year, and the amount of acreage they planned to use to produce it. Index included. The book also contains the printed terms of marketing agreement made between tobacco growers and the Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association, recorded at the county court 1924 July 1.
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1103219">Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association Contract Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1921-1924
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II ">Unidentified Blacksmith and Drummondsburg Plantation Account Book,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1850-1870
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Unidentified Blacksmith and Drummondsburg Plantation Account Book, 1850-1870, records financial transactions of an unidentified blacksmith shop and a farm called Drummondsburg Plantation.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Unidentified Blacksmith Accounts, 1850-1854, record the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found includes date of transaction, services rendered or items sold, form of payment, and amount owed or paid. Services rendered include shoeing horses, setting axles, sharpening farm implements, and repairing tools and wagons. Includes index.
</p>
<p>Drummondsburg Plantation Accounts, 1863-1870, record the accounts of individuals who purchased goods from the plantation and individuals who worked on the farm. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found includes date of transaction, goods purchased, form of payment, amount owed or paid, wages paid to laborers, number of days missed, and reasons for loss labor. Several laborers on farm were former slaves. Forms of payment include cash, credit, and barter.
</p>
</scopecontent>
    <c02 level="item">
    <did>
    <unittitle label="Barcode number 1103214">Unidentified Blacksmith and Drummondsburg Plantation 
    Account Book
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1850-1870
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
</did>
    </c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
