<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi05262">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vivi05262::A Guide to the Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1831-1880)//EN" "vivi05262.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1831-1880</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes
<num type="collectionnumber">53639
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Vincent T. Brooks
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2023 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Vincent T. Brooks, <date>29 August 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1831-1880</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession number">53639
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>V. Brooks
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1831-1880
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">53639
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>Digital images</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Alleghany County (Va.) Circuit Court. 
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1831-1880, use digital images found on the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia. 
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1831-1880. (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Alleghany County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These materials came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Alleghany County in 2022 under accession number 53639.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p> Records transferred to the Library of Virginia from the Circuit Court of Alleghany County in 2022 for processing and reformatting. Original Records returned to the locality in 2023 by request of the clerk of the Circuit Court.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program in 2023.
</p>
<p>When transferred to the Library of Virginia, the Alleghany County chancery causes were housed in Mylar sleeves and organized in 3-ring binders. Field processing staff in the courthouse ca. 1990 implemented this organization. An index was created for the binders using a File and Packet number as a reference. The File and Packet numbers have been retained after reprocessing at the Library of Virginia. They are indicated in the Local Case File Number (LCFN) field of the Chancery Records Index. Ex: File # 61, Packet # 1 recorded in LCFN as File 61-1.
</p>
<p>Encoded by V. Brooks: August 2023</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p> <emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Alleghany County bears a variant spelling derived from the name of the Allegheny Mountains that pass along the county's western boundary. It was formed in 1822 from Bath, Botetourt, and Monroe (now in West Virginia) Counties. Subsequent additions were made from Monroe County in 1843 and Bath County in 1847. On 20 March 1991, the General Assembly authorized the consolidation of Alleghany County and the independent city of Clifton Forge into a new independent city of Alleghany. The citizens of both locales voted against the proposal on 5 May 1992, however, and the change did not take effect. In March 2001 Clifton Forge's citizens voted to relinquish city status, and Alleghany County regained the city (now town) of Clifton Forge on 1 July 2001. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1831-1880, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.
</p>
<p>Development of the upper Valley of Virginia, both pre- and post-Civil War, is reflected in these records. Suits involving hotel, turnpike, and railroad companies are noteworthy. Additionally, some land disputes reference colonial patents and early land grants.
</p>
<p>Additionally, there is a box of Orphan Chancery material.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found).
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Alleghany County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1831-1880, are retained in the locality. Contact the clerk of the Circuit Court for access. 
</p>
</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Alleghany County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Selected Causes of Interest
</head>
<p><title render="italic">Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.</title> 
</p>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1831-002: Abel Jackson etc. vs. George Mayse etc. </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contract suit. This case involves division of a large land patent originally granted by Governor Dunmore in 1773. Land was in Barbour County, then Bath County, and then Allegheny County.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1835-006: Exrs. Of Michael Mallow vs. Peter Pence etc. </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt suit. This suit references contracts for constructing a number of miles of the Lexington and Covington Turnpike.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1835-014: William Robinson and wife vs. Adms. Of George Sively </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Estate suit. Her father bequeathed Robinson's wife money, but the administrators say that Robinson refused to accept any notes except bank notes from The Bank of the United States.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1839-002: Robert Page vs. Mary Ker etc. </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt suit. The chancery cause concerns land containing the Rumsey Iron Works.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1844-007: Gray and Parkey] vs. Henry Anderson and wife, etc.
</unittitle>
 <unittitle><emph render="underline"> Henry Anderson vs. Gray and Parkey </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt suit. Suit is a simple debt suit, but contains information on the so-called "Saxon Colonization Project."  Over one million acres in western Virginia and Kentucky were acquired from James Swann (Boston), alleged agent of Lewis Eisenmenger. Various members of French and German royalty were involved in the speculation scheme designed to settle poor people from Saxony on the Virginia frontier. In addition to Alleghany County [see also 1836-006, George Seivley vs. Charles T. Taylor, etc], several other localities have chancery causes related to land allegedly owned by Eisenmenger and sold by Swann [Bath County, Tazewell County, and Wythe County].
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1874-008: Admr. Of John Larquey vs. John Kelly </emph>
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contract suit. The chancery cause concerns the construction of the Blue Ridge Tunnel.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
  </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
