<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi05435">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi05435::A Guide to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, 1970-2000)//EN" "vi05435.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, <date>1970-2000</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors papers, 1970-2000
<num type="collectionnumber">36851; 37959
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Trenton Hizer
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Library of Virginia staff, <date>27 March 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, <date>1970-2000</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession number">36851; 37959
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Trenton Hizer
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1970-2000
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">36851; 37959
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>58.05 cubic feet (126 boxes)</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors. Records, 1970-2000. Accession 36851, 37959. Organization records collection. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift of NAADAC Education and Research Foundation,  Arlington, Virginia
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The National Association of Alcoholism Counselors and Trainers (NAACT) held its first organizational meeting in Washington DC, in June, 1974, during a period when the alcoholism field was experiencing rapid growth as a result of a new federal program of grants for treatment, rehabilitation, and prevention of alcohol abuse and alcoholism. Matthew J. Rose, a retired government official and resident of Arlington, VA, led the effort to establish a national organization, and became Executive Director of the new association. Counselors sought recognition of their profession in the expanding field through nationally recognized certification standards and procedures. Advocacy through a national organization was perceived as necessary to advance the profession. Coinciding with efforts to organize a national association of counselors, the Virginia Association of Alcoholism Counselors (VAAC) was being formed. Individuals active at the national level were prominent in the Virginia association, including Virginia residents Edward Riordan and Mel Schulstad. The Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program (ADERP) at Virginia Commonwealth University, under Marcia Lawton, Ph.D., and the Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) also contributed to the organizational effort. The National Association of Alcoholism Counsleors and Trainers in June, 1976, changed its name to National Association of Alcoholism Counselors (NAAC), in a move to provide a sole focus on counselors.
</p>
<p>In August 1982, the board of directors changed the name to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (NAADAC), then adopted new by-laws providing for individual membership in addition to affiliation by state associations. Membership grew to 14,000 with affiliates in all 50 states. The Association played an integral role in the effort to establish a nationally recognized set of standards and procedures for the credentialing of counselors, culminating in 1990 when the NAADAC Certification Commission was established to administer the credential of National Certified Addiction Counselor. Some 8,000 counselors qualified initially for the certification.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Records, 1970-2000, of the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (NAADAC), consisting of its National Counselor Certification files, National Commission for Accreditation files, Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation (ADERP) files, ADERP/Richmond Focus files, ADERP/National files, Virginia Certification files, Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) files, NAADAC General Historical files, Board Mailings files, Correspondence/Miscellaneous files, Executive Director's files, NAADAC Foundation files, Government Relations/Public Policy Conference files, Government Relations/Treatment Works files, Government Relations/General files, and Publications.
</p>
<p>National Counselor Certification files include certification reports, committee reports, minutes, publications, organization by-laws, NAADAC Certification Commission meeting materials and minutes, and correspondence. National Commission for Accreditation files consist of correspondence, organization by-laws and information on hospitals and alcoholism programs. Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program files consist of history, quarterly reports, Virginia Commonwealth University courses and students, correspondence, plans, programs, publications, and directories. ADERP/Virginia Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (VAADAC) files include history, newsletters, conference information, programs, articles, and educational information. ADERP/Richmond Focus files include Richmond Focus files and publications. ADERP/National files consist of information on hospitals and alcoholism programs, guidelines, reports, organizations information, educational information, correspondence, surveys, articles, and publications. Virginia Certification files include accreditation information, conference information, proposals, correspondence, reports, educational information, organization by-laws and information, and publications. Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) files consist of history, constitution, by-laws, membership lists, board minutes, correspondence, and newsletters.
</p>
<p>NAADAC General Historical files include history, mailings, correspondence, organizations information, workshops, conference information, pins, buttons, and stamps. Board Mailings files include correspondence, meeting agendas, board minutes, financial budgets and information, by-laws, conference minutes and information, reports, and manuals. Correspondence/Miscellaneous files consist of correspondence, conference information, and legislative information. Executive Director's files include organization by-laws, membership rosters and directories, conference information and minutes, committee funding and membership, financial budgets and information, board minutes, training programs and surveys. NAADAC Foundation files consist of correspondence, board minutes, grant applications, financial information, as well as records for the NAADAC Education and Research Foundation (NERF). Government Relations/Public Policy Conferences files includes legislative conference materials and minutes, correspondence, reports, and biographies. Government Relations/Treatment Works! files consist of correspondence, brochures, photographs, programs, congressional briefings, press, releases, agendas, and notes. Government Relations/General files consist of fact sheets, position papers, correspondence, agendas, mailings, board and committee meetings, conference information, articles, notes, newsletters, legislation, congressional hearings, and proclamations. Publications include the <title render="italic">Counselor</title>, the <title render="italic">Journal</title>, the <title render="italic">US Journal</title>, <title render="italic">The Bottom Line</title>, and other books, manuals, and journals.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>
