<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06333">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06333::A Guide to the Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912 (bulk 1880-1912))//EN" "vi06333.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1838-1912 (bulk 1880-1912)</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912 (bulk 1880-1912)
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>26 June 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1838-1912 (bulk 1880-1912)</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>C. Freed and V. Brooks
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1838-1912 (bulk 1880-1912)
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>Digital images</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Clarke County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Chancery Causes 1838-1912, use digital images found electronically on <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref>available on the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912 . (Cite style of suit and chancery index no.). Local government records collection, Clarke County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. 
</p>
</prefercite>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Clarke County Circuit Court in 2021 under the accession number 53404 and were returned by request of the Clerk in 2024. 
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912 were processed by V. Brooks and C. Freed from 2021 through 2022.</p> 
<p>47.6 cubic feet (104 boxes) of original chancery records was transferred to the Library of Virginia in 2021 for the purposes of processing, indexing, and digitization.  After the completion of digitization in the 2024, the Clerk of the Court requested the material be returned to the locality.</p>
<p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.</p> 
<p>Encoded by M. Mason: June 2024. </p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories. </p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Clarke County was named for Lieutenant Colonel George Rogers Clark, who commanded the Virginia forces that secured control of the Northwest Territory for Virginia during the Revolution. He spelled his name without the terminal e. The county was formed from Frederick County in 1836. The county seat is Berryville.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint, decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics. </p>
<p>Clarke Chancery causes, contain a large number of cases concerning debts and estates where property is central to the activity of the case. Many of these cases prior to 1865 contain a substantial amount of information concerning enslaved Black men, women, and children. These cases largely represent the perspective of white enslavers and their disputes involving the sale, hiring, financial responsibilities, and legality of ownership of Black individuals. </p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged
</p>
<p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.) </p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1838-1912 are retained in the locality. Contact the clerk of the Circuit Court for access. 
</p>
</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Clarke County  (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
 <head>Selected Suits of Interest  
</head> 
<p><title render="italic">Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.</title></p> 
   
   <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1883-049: Champ Shepherd v. Margaret Burchell, etc.</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Deposition contains account of escape and recapture of formerly enslaved people during the Civil War. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1890-033: Admr. of Lucy M. Clayton vs. Evelyn Byrd Nelson Page, etc.</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suit concerns the English estate of Coryndon Carpenter [d. ca. 1776], including extensive genealogical notes. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1891-007: Augustus W. B. Sowers vs. Minnie Sowers	</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Divorce suit: Contains love letters from Minnie to her paramour.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
 <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1893-019: John Alexander &amp; wife vs. Heirs of Brister (Bristoe) Holmes	</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Concerning the estate of Brister (also Bristoe) Holmes. Holmes was formerly enslaved by William Taylor Milton's mother. Holmes is credited with establishing "Bristow" a historic African American community in Clarke County.   
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1874-027: County of Jefferson State of West Virginia, For Etc. vs. Shenandoah Valley Rail Road Co, Etc.
</unittitle>
 <unittitle><emph render="underline">1893-030: H.H. Crumlish &amp; J (Joseph) T. Griffith vs. Shenandoah Valley Rail Road Co] and Central Improvement Co], etc.		</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Original contract between Shenandoah Valley Railroad Company with offices in Philadelphia and Luray, Va. (chartered in Virginia, Maryland and West Virginia) and Central Improvement Company based in Pennsylvania. Consists of subcontractors of the Central Improvement Company who contracted for the construction and completion of the Shenandoah Valley Railroad extending from the Potomac River at or near Sheperdstown to the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad at or near the Big Lick Station. Whole of said Railroad to be completed on or before 10 August 1872, 2 years from original contract. Road work was suspended in September 1873 and never resumed. The amounts claimed due them are for work done &amp; materials furnished by them in the graduation &amp; masonry upon the said Railroad. Cause was originally filed in Warren County Circuit Court and removed to Clarke County in Oct. 1878. In further causes, individual stockholders on behalf of the Central Improvement Company are suing the law firm that they employed to settle the debts and selling of the Shenandoah Valley Railroad Company. Related causes are found in the circuit courts of Roanoke, Virginia. Jefferson County, West Virginia and Washington County, Maryland. The Shenandoah Valley Railroad was to be built by the Central Improvement Company in the states of Virginia, West Virginia &amp; Maryland [SEE ALSO: 1900-021, 1900-022, 1900-023, 1910-019].  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1894-010: Harriet E. Cazenove, creditor, etc. v. Washington, Ohio &amp; Western R R]	</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plaintiff is the holder of seven bonds executed by the County of Clarke for the extension of the railroad into the county. Plaintiff seeks payment. Originally, the defendant was known as the Alexandria, Loudoun &amp; Hampshire Rail Road Company which then became the Washington &amp; Ohio Rail Road. After a lawsuit in Richmond City, Henry Lewis, etc. v. Washington &amp; Ohio Rail Road, the railroad's name became the Washington, Ohio &amp; Western Rail Road Co. The railroad was supposed to extend from Alexandria to Clarke County by way of the town of Berryville (the county seat). The railroad, however, never extended beyond Loudoun County, as a portion was destroyed during the Civil War. The crossbill filed by the County of Clarke in the Richmond City suit is included with this cause. Eventually, the plaintiff transferred her bonds to Charles J. Philbin of Baltimore City. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1894-015: George E.S. Phillips vs. Admr of William A. Jackson, etc. </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>William A. Jackson and wife, Sarah S. are African Americans. Plaintiff built 2 story frame house for defendant and family. Due to his death, plaintiff files mechani's lien for money owed. Property is rented for awhile and eventually sold. Sarah S. was a teacher so not sure why she and her children had to lose property. Homestead Exemption waived. See master's thesis written by Donna Camille Dodenhoff. [See also: 1894-019, this is a similar suit where the defendant is able to purchase his house and lot].  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1894-015: George E.S. Phillips vs. Admr of William A. Jackson, etc. </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>William A. Jackson and wife, Sarah S. are African Americans. Plaintiff built 2 story frame house for defendant and family. Due to his death, plaintiff files mechanic's lien for money owed. Property is rented for awhile and eventually sold. Sarah S. was a teacher so not sure why she and her children had to lose property. Homestead Exemption waived. See master's thesis written by Donna Camille Dodenhoff. [See also: 1894-019, this is a similar suit where the defendant is able to purchase his house and lot].  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
          </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
