<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06321">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06321::A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908)//EN" "vi06321.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1789-1908</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>20 March 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1789-1908</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Bari Helms; Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1789-1908
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>79 volume; .45 cubic feet (1 box)</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, <emph render="bold">please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available</emph>. 
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Augusta County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Augusta County in 2008 under the accession numbers 43658 and 43836.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>

<p> John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247 </p>

<p>Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 253, 255, 256</p>
		
<p>Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244 </p>

<p>Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 248, 254, 255 </p>

<p>Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 249 </p>

<p>Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247 </p>

<p>Mictiow Sales Book, 183 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 255 </p>
<p>Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 249, 250</p>

<p>Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 247, 253 </p>

<p>Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244	</p>

<p>Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 257 </p>

<p>Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 244-245, 256-257	</p>

<p>William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 246, 252, 253 </p>

</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.
</p>
<p>The records in this collection were processed as different times from 2002-2015 mostly by Bari Helms as well Greg Crawford. Efforts have been taken to identify chancery causes related to these business records as some of these records were used as evidence in court proceedings.</p>

<p>Encoded by M. Mason, March 2024</p>


</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments , these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes. 
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Augusta County was named for Augusta of Saxe-Gotha, who married Frederick Louis, Prince of Wales, and was the mother of King George III. It was formed from Orange County by a statute of 1738 that stipulated that when the population was large enough the new county government would begin to function. The county court first met on 9 December 1745.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Augusta County (Va.) Business Records,1789-1908, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Augusta County (Va.). Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, minute books, cashbooks, invoice books, and account books. 
</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861</item>
<item>Series II: John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842</item>
<item>Series III: Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907</item>
<item>Series IV: John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837</item>
<item>Series V: John Frazier and Bath and Rockbridge Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854</item>
<item>Series VI: Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867</item>
<item>Series VII: Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810</item>
<item>Series VIII: Houff &amp; Holler Business Records, 1904-1908</item>
<item>Series IX: Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847</item>
<item>Series X: Nicholas C. Kinney Daybook and Ledgers, 1815-1830</item>
<item>Series XI: Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871</item>
<item>Series XII: Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856</item>
<item>Series XIII: Mictiow Sales Book, 1837</item>
<item>Series XIV: Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793</item>
<item>Series XV: Series XV: Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906</item>
<item>Series XVI: Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805</item>
<item>Series XVII: Tannehill &amp; Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874</item>
<item>Series XVIII: Series XIX: Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831</item>
<item>Series XIX: Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860</item>
<item>Series XX: Thornburg and Shafer Daybook, 1877-1879</item>
<item>Series XXI: Unidentified General Store Daybooks, 1828-1835</item>
<item>Series XXII: Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873</item>
<item>Series XXIII: Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875</item>
<item>Series XXIV:Virginia Express Company Minute Book and Cashbook, 1867-1869</item>
<item>Series XXV: John Wayt Invoice Book, 1828-1831</item>
<item>Series XXVI:William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826</item></list>
</p>

</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03473.xml"> August County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912 </extref>
</p>
<p>Additional August County(Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>

</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1857-1861
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> Based out of Hartford, Connecticut, the Aetna Insurance Company sold its first life insurance policy in 1850. In 1853, the company was incorporated as the Aetna Life Insurance Company with former Connecticut judge Eliphalet A. Bulkeley as its first president. In 1861, the company began offering participating life insurance policies, and at the end of the Civil War, Aetna was one of the nation's biggest life insurance providers. Today, Aetna is a diversified health care benefits company providing a range of health care insurance products and related services including dental, pharmacy, group life, and disability insurance.</p>

<p>Aetna Insurance Company established an insurance agency in Staunton, Virginia, in the mid-nineteenth century. Alexander F. Kinney served as an agent for the company. Kinney, a Virginia resident born about 1836, was also a bank teller and a circuit court clerk for Augusta County.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861, record the disbursements of the company for such expenses as advertising, express or freight charges, taxes, return premiums, etc. All vouchers were signed by Aetna's agent Alexander F. Kinney.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278963">Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1857-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1827-1842
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> John Armstrong, Sr. was a farmer in Augusta County, Virginia. He had a son, John Armstrong, Jr., who owned a neighboring farm. He died in 1842.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842, records Armstrong's personal finances along with the business activities of his farm. Each account records the transactions with individuals that Armstrong either hired or with whom he conducted business. Information found in each entry include the date, type of transaction, and monies debited or credited to the account. Armstrong recorded purchases for such items as wheat, bacon, brandy, tallow, butter, dry apples, and flour. There are also larger purchases such as livestock and furniture. In addition, Armstrong recorded the work done by white laborers which included such tasks as sawing wood, mowing, etc.
</p>

<p>Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Admr. of John Armstrong, Sr. vs Admr. of John Armstrong, Jr. , Etc.1860-074. Avaible Digitially through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/"> Chancery Records Index. </extref> </p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278959">John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1827-1842
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>

</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907
<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1907
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>20 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> The Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company financed loans for land purchases and building constructions in Augusta County, Va. The company was formed on 7 February 1885 at a meeting conducted at the city clerks office in Staunton, Va., by a group of citizens wishing to organize a building and loan association. Early officers of the company included M. Erskine Miller, president; John W. Stout, vice president; and Newton Argenbright, secretary. Later presidents included A. C. Gordon and J. N. McFarland. The company suspended operations and began a long process of voluntary liquidation in December of 1898.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907, consists of three daybooks, five cashbooks, four letter books, two ledgers, one index, one minute book, one statement book, two Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books, and one stock receipt book.
</p>

</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries A">Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1906
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>
Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books,1885-1906, were used to record both the money owed by the building and loan company and the money owed to the company by customers and shareholders. Both of the account books contain two separate halves -- one for bills payable and the other for bills receivable. Each entry includes the date, name of the customer or shareholder, and the bank where the payments were made. For bills payable, the company which is owed money to is noted along with the name of the building and loan employee responsible for the transaction. Some entries note that full statements of the accounts can be found in the accompanying letter books.</p>

</scopecontent>
               <c03 level="item">
               	<did>
               	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278957">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Co. Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Book, 
               	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1906
               	</unitdate>
               	</unittitle>
               </did>
               	</c03>

               <c03 level="item">
               	<did>
               	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278956">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Co. Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Book, 
               	<unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1895
               	</unitdate>
               	</unittitle>
               </did>
               	</c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries B">Cashbooks,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1907
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>5 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>
Cashbooks, 1885-1907, record cash received and cash disbursed. Transactions are listed chronologically as they occurred. Entries document monies credited and debited for such activities as bills received, costs of sales,and interest paid on accounts. Other entries track monies received and dispersed on individual accounts for dues and running shares, loans, interest, fines, and stock transfers. Company expenses were recorded for items such as employee salaries, taxes paid, rent, commissioners' fees, insurance premiums, attorney fees, advertising, and postage.</p>

</scopecontent>
	
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178207">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book, 1885-1887
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1887
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178206">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1888
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1187920"> Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cashbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1888-1893
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178316">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cashbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1894-1902
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178192">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1902-1907
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>


<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries C">Daybooks,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1906
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>3 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>
Daybooks, 1885- 1906, document business activities on a chronological basis as they occurred. Entries include date, account name, type of transaction, and monies credited and debited. Transactions recorded include real estate loans, costs of sales, stock values and stock purchases, interest due on individual accounts, profits and loss statements, and expenses such as insurance, taxes, and fines. Records of stock purchases contain the name of buyer, the dollar amount of stock purchased, and the entrance fees applied to the purchase.</p>

</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178310">Augusta Perpetual Building &amp; Loan Company Daybook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1890
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178203">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Daybook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1890-1897
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178176">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Day Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1897-1906
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries D">Ledgers,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1907
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p> Ledger, 1889-1898, records the accounts of "holders of paid up stock." Each entry includes the date, number of stock shares bought or sold, and the amounts debited or credited to the account. If stock shares were recorded as sold, the name of the buyer was listed in the transaction.</p>

<p> Ledger A, 1885-1907, records the accounts of individual stockholders and individual loan holders. Information found in the accounts of individual stockholders include the date of transaction and the amounts of stock purchased. Transactions in the accounts of individual loan holders document the loan purchase amount, interest fees, and fines. Payments on the accounts were also recorded and were made either with cash or redeemed stock. Some accounts include notations of actions taken on the account such as paid in full, case in litigation, or property sold at auction. The back of the ledger includes a totaling of representative accounts such as bills receivable, capital stock, subscribed stock, redeemed stock, expenses, and cash accounts. Account entries concerning stock include the name of the purchaser along with the amount of stock purchased.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1187937">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Ledger A,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1907
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1187937"> Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Index to Loans and General Accounts,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1907
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent> <p> Provides an index to the individual accounts found in Ledger A </p></scopecontent>
	</c03>
	
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178309">Augusta Perpetual Building &amp; Loan Company Ledger,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries E"> Letter books,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1886-1902
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>4 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p> Letter Books, 1886-1902, provide a record of out-going correspondence related to the company's business activities. Letter topics include requests for account balances to be paid, demands for the sale of land or property to settle a debt, and details of monies received and owed on individual accounts. The majority of the letters are signed by W. T. McCue, who was identified as the cashier for the company; however a few were signed by Taylor Bissell, a clerk for the company.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178209">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1886-1891
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178204">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1891-1895
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178308">Augusta Perpetual Building &amp; Loan Company Letter Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1895-1900
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178178">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1900-1902
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>

<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries F"> Minute books,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1903
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p>Records the meetings of the company's board of directors and meetings of the stockholders. Early entries in February of 1885 document the formation of the building and loan association and the creation of a constitution and by-laws for the government of the company. These early meetings also established stock prices and membership fees and elected officers and committee members. Business statements for the company were presented to the board of directors on a semi-annual basis. These statements documented the profits and loses of the company and documented such items as stock subscriptions, loans on real estate, stock dues, bills receivable, bills payable, loss and gain records, and company resources and liabilities. Applications to redeem stock and applications for loans on real estate were presented for approval at meetings. Because the company's constitution stipulated that "stockholders must be a white person," several meetings discussed the "legal right of the association to make loans to colored people through the intervention of a white applicant." It was ultimately decided that to protect the company both the white applicant and the colored borrower should execute the bond for loans. In December of 1898, a resolution was recommended to stockholders that the company suspend operations as a building and loan company and that it was in the best interest of the company to go into voluntary liquidation, collect the company's assets, and return money to stockholders. Meetings held from 1899 to 1903 concern the liquidation of the business.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178307">Augusta Perpetual Building &amp; Loan Company Board of Directors Minute Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1903
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries G"> Statement books,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1886-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p> Records the financial statements of the company at the end of each fiscal year beginning in December of 1886. The statement book was used by the committee appointed by the Board of Directors to examine the company's books and papers. The business statements document stock accounts, loans, interest due and unpaid on accounts, and fines unpaid for each fiscal year. The stock accounts and loan account statements include the name of the individual shareholder, the number of shares bought or sold, and the monies debited or credited to the accounts. For each fiscal year, balance sheets provide the company's profits and loss statements and include a list of resources (loans, bills receivable, cash, property) and liabilities (stock dues, bills payable).</p>
</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178313 ">Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Statement Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1886-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series III:Subseries H"> Stock Reciept books,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
<p> Includes duplicate stock certificates kept for the company's records of stock shares purchased. Each stock certificate includes a certificate number, date, name of buyer, and the number of shares purchased.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c03 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1178313"> Augusta Perpetual Building &amp; Loan Company Stock Receipt Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c03>
</c02>





</c01>







</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>













