<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06311">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06311::A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861)//EN" "vi06311.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, <date>1836-1861</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons

</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">&#169; 2023 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>13 December 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, <date>1836-1861</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia

</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>L. Neuroth 
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1836-1861
</unitdate>
</unittitle>

<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.25 cubic feet (1 box); Digital Images</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861, are digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images. </p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861. Local government records collection, Warren County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Warren County, in 2000 under accession number 37580 and 37581, as well as in 2023 under accession number 54002.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>The "Free Negro Registration" Records, 1836-1861, were originally described as part of the <emph render="bold">Warren County (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861</emph> but were removed to the present Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861 to enhance the context between the record types. 
</p>
<p>
These records have been scanned and indexed by L. Neuroth and other LVA staff for the purposes of digitizing them for the digital project Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative.</p>
<p>
Encoded by M. Mason, December 2023</p>
</processinfo></descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type: </emph>
</p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registers </p>
<p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify "age, name, colour, and stature, by whom, and in what court the said negro or mulatto was emancipated; or that such negro or mulatto was born free." The process was extended to counties in 1803. Although some clerks were already recording such features, an 1834 Act of Assembly made it a uniform requirement to record identifying marks and scars and the instrument of emancipation, whether by deed or will. This bound register often coincided with a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information. Both the registration system and the process of renewal was enforced differently in the various Virginia localities. Thus, the information found in these registers may differ from year to year and across localities. </p>
<p>The register books resulting from the administration of the 1793 and 1803 Act of Assembly are evidence of Virginia legislators' reaction to a quickly growing free Black and multiracial population in Virginia in the post Revolutionary War period. Acts such as these allowed white officials to police the activities and movement of free Black community members throughout the state thereby restricting their autonomy. </p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registrations</p>
<p>In 1793, the Virginia General Assembly specified that "free Negroes or mulattoes" were required to "be registered and numbered in a book to be kept by the town clerk, which shall specify age, name, color, status and by whom, and in what court emancipated." These entries often coincided with the creation of a loose certificate containing largely the same identifying information.</p>
<p>Documents in this record group differ from the bound volumes referred to as "registers." These registration records typically appear in the form of certificates or handwritten statements recording the free status of a Black or multiracial person. They can include the free person's name, sometimes age, a brief physical description, and the circumstances of the person's freedom or emancipation, parents, former enslaver, place or date of emancipation. There are also affidavits that were given by individuals affirming a free person's status, as well as written descriptions of free people. In some cases, a person would not have a registration to submit to the court. Instead they produced some other form of identification proving their free status, for example, a deed of emancipation, a will, an apprenticeship indenture, or an affidavit of someone testifying to their character and status.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality Note:</emph> Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Shenandoah and Frederick Counties in 1836.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Warren County (Va.) Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, 1836-1861 consists of pages of the "Free Negro Register," 1856-1859; "Index to County Court Minute Books A, B, and C from Free Negro Register, 1836-1859"; and "Free Negro" Registrations (includes affidavits of freedom, certificates of freedom, loose register certificates, and requests for free papers).
</p>
<p>The "Free Negro Register," 1856-1859, is incomplete and consists of four loose pages that appear to have been extracted from an original volume that recorded the registrations of free Black and multiracial people of Black descent in the Warren County. The original register likely covered the years 1836 to 1862 [based on the date range of loose registers] and is not extant. The clerk recorded name, age, height, complexion, marks and scars, and in what court the person was emancipated or if the person was born free. </p>
<p>Entries in Warren County Minute Book C align with the names and biographical information recorded in the registrations for years 1856 to 1859. Additional information on free Black and multiracial people who were recorded in pages of the register book no longer extant can be found in Warren County Minute Books A, B, and C. Additionally included, is a cross-reference document "Index to County Court Minute Books A, B, and C from Free Negro Register," compiled by an unknown researcher. This document provides names of the free individuals and references the page in which that registration was recorded in the Warren County Minute Books. </p>
<p>"Free Negro" Registrations, 1836-1861, consists of several affidavits of freedom (statements sworn before the court by an individual vouching for a Black or multiracial individual's legal status as a free person. This includes on of Hannah Henry, daughter of Delilah Henry who was enslaved and later emancipated by the estate of Robert Carter); several certificates of freedom and twenty-five loose register certificates (these are certified and recorded in the court and typically correspond to the bound "Free Negro Register" kept by the clerk) and a request for free papers, 1857, by Jas. W. Hendrick to Col. Robert Turner seeking to obtain free person for Nancy Walker. </p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into </p>
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons, loosely arranged by record type then chronological </item></list>

</arrangement>

<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
 <p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi04309.xml">Warren County (Va.)Free and Enslaved Records, 1836-1861</extref></p>
<p>Records related to free and enslaved people of Warren County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
<p>Additional Warren County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>

 <dsc type="analyticover">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold"> Records Related to the Registration of Free Persons </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1831-1861</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent> .25 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p> loosely by record type then chronological 
</p>
</arrangement>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 1208718 ">Free and Enslaved Records
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1836-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
