<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi06208">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vivi06208::A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, 1875-1898)//EN" "vivi06208.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1875-1898</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, 1875-1898
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jennifer Taylor
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Jennifer Taylor, <date>21 June 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1875-1898</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1875-1898
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>11 volumes</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Henrico County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, 1875-1898. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Augusta County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The majority of these records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Henrico County in an undated accession. One volume from Series II: James H. Barton Real Estate Business Records, 1889-1898, the James H. Barton Accounts Ledger, 1895-1896, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from the city of Richmond. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.</p>
<p>These records were processed by Greg Crawford in 2008.</p>
<p>Encoded by J. Taylor: June 2024.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph>Henrico County was named for Henry, Prince of Wales, eldest son of King James I. It was one of the eight original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. The county seat is in the western part of the county.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Lost Locality Notes: </emph>All county court records prior to 1655 and almost all prior to 1677 are missing. Many records were destroyed by British troops during the Revolutionary War. Post-Revolutionary War county court records exist. Almost all circuit superior court of law and chancery and circuit court records were destroyed by fire during the evacuation of Richmond on 3 April 1865 in the Civil War. The county's circuit court held its sessions at the state courthouse in Richmond. </p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Henrico County (Va.) Business Records, 1875-1898, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Henrico County (Va.). Represented records consist of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, journals, and account books.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged inot three series: 
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Edward Powers and Company Business Records, 1875-1878</item>
<item>Series II: James H. Barton Real Estate Business Records, 1889-1898</item>
<item>Series III: Richmond Chemical Works Business Records, 1875-1877</item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02575.xml">Henrico County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1770-1965.</extref></p>
<p>Additional Henrico County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA159">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
<p>Henrico County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Henrico County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva-virginia.libguides.com/lost-records">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref>available on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Edward Powers and Company Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1875-1878
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> Edward Powers and Company was a partnership formed in 1875 by John N. Van Lew and Edward Powers for the purpose of manufacturing paper bags. The partnership dissolved in 1877.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content: </emph>Edward Powers and Company Business Records, 1875-1878 consists of one account book.</p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=087-1886-019">Henrico County (Va.) Chancery Cause, 1886-019: John N. Vanlew etc. vs. Edward Powers and wife etc.</extref></p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108192">Edward Powers and Company Account Book, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1875-1878
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">James H. Barton Real Estate Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1898
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>8 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> James H. Barton was born in Pennsylvania in 1837. He served in the Union army during the Civil War. After the war, Barton became a real estate developer in Little Rock, Arkansas and Memphis, Tennessee. In 1889, Barton moved to Virginia and founded a real estate development on a site a north of Richmond in Henrico County that became known as Barton Heights. Barton was so successful that in less than six years Barton Heights had been incorporated as a town in Henrico County. Due to a depressed economy and poor financial decisions, Barton had a difficult time repaying loans he owed. Hounded by creditors and allegations of financial improprieties, Barton and his wife Elizabeth fled Virginia in 1896 February. Barton died in Chester, Pennsylvania in 1912 January.
</p>
<p>Founded in 1889, Barton Heights began as a late nineteenth-century suburban development named for its founder James H. Barton. It was built north of Richmond, Virginia on the heights above the confluence of Bacon Quarter branch and Cannon's branch of Shockoe Creek, which flow east and south to separate the high land from Richmond's Jackson Ward. Barton's goal was to attract middle class professionals seeking affordable homes and who wanted to move away from the turmoil of the city. Barton Heights was annexed from Henrico County by the city of Richmond in 1914.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>James H. Barton Real Estate Business Records, 1889-1898, consists of three ledgers, two volumes of bills receivable and payable account books, a journal, and a daybook.</p>
<p>See also:<extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=087-1921-001"> Henrico County (Va.) Chancery Cause, 1921-001: Home Building Company vs. James H. Barton and wife etc.</extref></p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108156">James H. Barton Ledger, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1890
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108155">James H. Barton Building Book No. 2,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1891
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James H. Barton Real Estate Ledger, 1889-1890 and Building Book Number 2, 1889-1891, recorded individual accounts of contractors, businesses, laborers, and Barton Heights homeowners with whom Barton conducted business. Transactions related specifically to home construction and repair. Each account lists debit and credit transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, type of transaction, amount owed, and amount paid. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108171">James H. Barton Jounral, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1891-1896
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James H. Barton Real Estate Journal, 1891-1896, recorded transactions in chronological order. Information found in transaction entries include dates of transactions, names of parties involved in transactions, types of transactions, amounts owed and paid.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1092270">James H. Barton Accounts Ledger, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1895-1896
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108178">James H. Barton Bills Receivable and Payable, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1892-1896
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108173">James H. Barton Bills Receivable and Payable,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1898
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James H. Barton Real Estate Ledger, 1895-1896, Bills Receivable and Payable, 1892-1896, and Bills Receivable and Payable, 1889-1898, records the names of individuals indebted to Barton or to whom Barton was indebted and whether or not debts were paid. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108193">James H. Barton Ledger,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1894
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James H. Barton Ledger, 1889-1894 recorded individual accounts of contractors, businesses, and Barton Heights homeowners with whom Barton conducted business. Each account lists debit and credit transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, type of transaction, line number of transaction entry found in corresponding journal, amount owed, and amount paid.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108178">James H. Barton Daybook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1894
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James H. Barton Daybook, 1894 recorded Barton's banking transactions with Richmond Perpetual Building Loan and Trust Company.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Richmond Chemical Works Business Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1875-1877
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> Richmond Chemical Works was a partnership formed in 1875 July by John N. Van Lew and Edward Powers for the purpose of manufacturing Benedict's Patent Car Axle Grease. Powers left the partnership in 1875 November. Van Lew continued operating the business until 1877. The company was also known as Richmond Drug, Paint, and Chemical Works.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>Richmond Chemical Works Business Records consists of two account books. The books recorded the receipts and disbursements of Richmond Chemical Works. One account book includes copious number advertisements of businesses that sold steam engines, brick machines, pumps, coffee, tea, fruit dryers, grist mills, and miscellaneous machine industries. It also includes newspaper clippings on miscellaneous topics and poems perhaps by van Lew.</p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=087-1886-019">Henrico County (Va.) Chancery Cause, 1886-019: John N. Vanlew etc. vs. Edward Powers and wife etc.</extref></p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108187">Richmond Chemical Works Account Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1875-1877
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1108177">Richmond Chemical Works Account Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1875-1876
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>









