<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06402">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06402::A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864)//EN" "vi06402.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, <date>1834-1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records
<num type="barcodenumber">0007843137
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>McKenzie Long
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
<date type="publication">&#169; 2023  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record by McKenzie Long, <date>5 October 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, <date>1834-1864</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>McKenzie Long
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1834-1864
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007843137 
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.45 cu. ft. (1 box)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone minimal processing. All records remain tri-folded or in original bundles and may be fragile. Contact Archives Research services for availability.  
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864. Local government records collection, Greensville County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a 2023 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 53810.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Encoded by M. Long: October 2023.
</p>
<p>Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes were processed using minimal processing standards: Locality records were organized by broad record category (election records, fiduciary records, etc.) with minimal other arrangement. These records have not been flattened, foldered, mended, or separated by individual record type (like summons, appraisements, etc.).
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:  </title>Keeping large bodies of militia in the field required an elaborate system of support based on the purchase of goods and services from civilians, in addition to the usual pay and allowances to officers and soldiers. The result was the creation of a large number of records concerning the state's disbursements to both soldiers and civilians. Many claims for payment went unsatisfied until 1821. Locality military and pension records consist largely of pay and muster rolls, accounts and vouchers concerning supplies, claims for reimbursement for services rendered, and military pension applications. Pension applications summarize the applicant's service record and may include medical evaluations; information about income and property; and, in the case of widows, the date and place of marriages.</p>
<p>During the Revolutionary War, commissioners were appointed in each county to impress supplies and non-military services (such as driving cattle or wagons) for the war effort. Officials provided certificates or receipts so that individual suppliers could be reimbursed by the state government. Beginning in 1782, claims for reimbursement could be submitted to county courts. These "publick claims," known as court booklets and lists, exist for almost all Virginia counties. Between 1777 and 1785, the Virginia General Assembly passed several laws authorizing pensions for disabled soldiers and for widows of soldiers who died while on active duty.</p>
<p>Throughout the Civil War, the principal responsibility for Virginia's indigent soldiers' families lay with the locality. The Virginia State Convention in 1861 gave the responsibility entirely to counties and incorporated towns and authorized whatever actions had already been taken. Acts of Assembly in 1862 and 1863 expanded the localities' powers to provide for their needy, and in 1863 some minimal state assistance was added in. The Virginia General Assembly passed several Confederate pension acts beginning in 1888. The initial act provided pensions to Confederate soldiers, sailors, and marines disabled in action and to the widows of those killed in action. A 1900 act broadened the coverage to include veterans disabled by "infirmities of age" and widows whose husbands died after the war. African Americans who had served "faithfully" as servants, cooks, laborers, hostlers, or teamsters for the Confederate army were eligible for pensions beginning in 1924. District of Columbia residents became eligible in 1926; previously, all pension applicants were required to be residents of Virginia.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p> Greensville County (Va.) Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864, consist of military service records, accounts and vouchers, and claims for reimbursement by civilians and service members. The records have undergone minimal processing. This has allowed for the documentation of specific record types and various trends found in this set of records.
</p>
<p>Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864 that have undergone minimal processing consist of the following:</p>
<list type="simple">
	<head>Record Types:</head>
<item>Certificates as pensioners (concerning the Revolutionary War)</item> 
<item>Lists of indigent families of soldiers and sailors</item>
</list>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series I: Minimally Processed Military and Pension Records, 1834-1864,</emph> are loosely arranged chronologically.</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi06412.xml">Greensville County (Va.) Declarations for Revolutionary War Pensions, 1833</extref> at the Library of Virginia.</p>
<p>Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Minimally Processed Military and Pension Records, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1834-1864</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.45 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Loosely arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007843137 ">Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Clerk; Commissioner of Revenue; Election; Fiduciary; Health and Medical; Jury; Justice of the Peace; Miscellaneous; Military and Pension; Overseers of the Poor; Property; Public Buildings; School; Sheriff; Treasurer; Wills,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1792-1870
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>