<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06336">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06336::A Guide to the Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865 )//EN" "vi06336.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1797-1865 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>26 August 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, <date>1797-1865 </date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Field Processors, V. Brooks, M. Long, and M. Mason
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1797-1865 
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>49 cubic feet (108 boxes) </extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Wythe County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Chancery Causes, 1797-1865 are digitized, use digital images found on the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/">Chancery Records Index</extref> available electronically at the website of the Library of Virginia.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1797-1865. (Cite style of suit). Local government records collection, Wythe County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These materials came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Wythe County in February 2022 under accession number 53538. A small amount of additional material came in August 2022 under accession number 53665
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program in 2024.
</p>
<p>Field processors completed original indexing throughout the 1990s-2000s. During reprocessing by Local Records staff, indexing was completed to Library of Virginia Standards, this required the moving of chancery causes to different years; changing styles of suit for individual causes; and combining and/or separating causes when necessary. Local Records staff also located non-chancery cases during reprocessing (including judgements and commonwealth causes) which were removed from the chancery and filed separately by record type. </p>
<p>During reprocessing, Local Records staff removed paper folders that contained notations and cross-references to information contain in volumes stored Wythe County Circuit Court house. These notes were not destroyed but are not digitized.</p>
<p>Wythe Chancery causes, 1797-1830, were processed by M. Mason and V. Brooks. Causes, 1831-1865, were processed by M. Long from March 2022 to July 2023.</p>
<p>Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes 1797-1865 are the first half of the chancery records for the locality to be processed. There are plans for Local Records Staff to later process the 1866-1912 records. </p>
<p>Encoded by M. Mason:  August, 2024.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the decision on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Types of Courts:</emph> </p>
<p>Wythe County was the site of a Superior Court of Chancery that held court in Wythe from 1812 to 1832. The Superior Courts of Chancery were created by an act of the General Assembly passed on 23 January 1802. In order to expedite the hearing of chancery suits, the High Court of Chancery was abolished and the state was divided into three chancery districts with a Superior Court of Chancery for each district. For this reason, these courts were sometimes called "District Courts of Chancery." Suits heard in these courts were typically cases appealed from the local courts. A transcript of the suit from the local court was commonly filed with the appeal. Litigants could by-pass the local courts and file their suits in the chancery district court directly. </p>
<p>From 1802 to 1812, Wythe fell into the Staunton district which consisted of localities found in the western half of the Commonwealth. In 1812, the General Assembly created additional Superior Courts of Chancery which included the Superior Court of Chancery in Wythe. The Wythe district include the counties of: Giles, Grayson, Lee, Montgomery, Russell, Scott, Tazewell, Washington, and Wythe.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Wythe County was named for George Wythe, a signer of the Declaration of Independence and chancellor of Virginia in 1789 when Wythe County was formed from Montgomery County. Part of Grayson County was added in 1825.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Wythe County (Va.) Chancery Causes,1797-1865, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.</p>

<p> For this set of causes, debt and contract suits are the most prevalent, and mostly concern disputes stemming from land transfers. Estate disputes are the next most documented cause of action. There are very few other causes of action represented. </p>
<p><emph render="underline">Superior Chancery:</emph>
 </p>
<p>A majority of the 1812-1833 Chancery Causes are Superior Chancery cases. These causes while heard in Wythe County (Va.) additionally document the activities of individuals and businesses from Giles, Grayson, Lee, Montgomery, Russell, Scott, Tazewell, and Washington counties. Apart from Wythe County, Washington County is the locality most documented in these records. </p>
<p>Due to the prevalence of Superior Chancery, there are also variations in the causes themselves that may not fit the normal make-up of a chancery cause as there causes throughout this 1812-1833 span that have matters heard in both Superior Court of Chancery and the Superior Court of Law. General this occurred when an issue in chancery was sent by the judge to law side of the court for verdict before a final decree was entered in Chancery. </p>
<p><emph render="underline">General Trends:</emph>
 </p>
<p>There is a substantial amount of information concerning enslaved Black men, women, and children. While there are several suits concerning the freedom of enslaved individuals, these cases largely represent the perspective of white enslavers and their disputes involving the sale, hiring, financial responsibilities, and legality of ownership of Black individuals. Specifically, there are many cases concerning estate disputes which over enslaved individuals.</p>
<p>Due to the geographic area represented in these records, many suits document the land struggles is western Virginia and general western migration after the Revolutionary War. Various cases (especially pre-1833) list the Loyal Company as plaintiff. These causes discuss land surveys (in (Virginia, North Carolina, West Virginia, Tennessee, Kentucky, Ohio) conducted when Virginia was a colony, including conflicts with the Indigenous Americans already living on the land, the effects of the French and Indian War on property rights, conflicts with the Ohio Company, and ownership disputes post-American Revolution. In these cases, there is fairly standardized language to describe the history of the land surveys on the part of the Loyal Company.</p>
<p>Additionally on this theme of western migration, many suits include issues of defendants moving beyond the commonwealth to Tennessee, Kentucky, or Ohio, complicating matters for the plaintiffs. Many suits discuss key issues and historical trends surrounding lead and gypsum mining, including: the working and living conditions experienced by both enslaved workers hired out to the mines and workers directly employed by the mining companies, including workplace dangers and long-term health risks; business inheritance issues facing recent immigrants, especially women; and the environmental effects of lead pollution on air quality, water sources, and plants and animals in surrounding areas.</p>
<p>There are multiple pre-1830 suits concerning Almerine Marshall and his estate after dying in the 1811 Richmond Theater fire. Other individuals and family frequently presented are William and James King, King family, Trigg, family, and Heiskell family.</p>
<p>These records also contain a box of "Orphan Chancery" which is processed but not indexed. These records contain parts, often single items, of chancery causes that could not be further identified as belonging to a certain case.</p>


</scopecontent>


<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically. 
</p>
<p>Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.) </p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Wythe County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/">Virgnia County and City Records on Microfilm</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>

<dsc type="in-depth">
 <head>Selected Suits of Interest  
</head> 
<p><title render="italic">Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.</title></p> 
   
   <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1803-007: Andrew Thompson vs. Charles Buster </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Concerns fines collected by Thompson while sheriff of the county, specifically a militia fine against Charles Buster a Captain in the local militia.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
   <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1805-007: John Towney vs. David Doak, Etc.</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Towney claims he should not have to pay a judgment brought against him by the overseers of the poor on behalf of John King as King agreed to care for the "bastard child" of John Towney at no cost.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
  <c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1806-006: John Claxton, Etc. vs Jesse Evans </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cause indicates the sometime in the late 1700s a local group of indigenous people [specific tribe or nation is not indicated] captured Bridget Claxton (formerly Bridget Williams), Martin Williams, and their children, allegedly killing Martin and the children. Bridget, then remarried, but seeks the compensation from her late husband's estate. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1808-001: Robert Ingledove vs. Almerine Marshall </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ingledove accuses Marshall of selling him an old and broken carriage and does not believe he should pay the balance of the cost of the carriage. Narrates his family's trip to Winchester, Va., and back, and the number of repairs necessary along the way. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1809-014: Barney Gullion vs. Hugh Fulton </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Heard in the superior court of chancery, John Gullion identified by Hugh Fulton as a Tory and supporter of King George III and attributes this and Gullion's belief in a British victory in the delays and issues in the land transfer [see August Co. 1811-103: Heirs of John Gullion vs Hugh Fulton]
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1810-001: John Thompson Sayers vs. Admr. of James Buchanan </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Concerns debt on bond owed the estate of James Buchanan for services performed by James, enslaved by Buchanan, during Buchanan's time as a guest in the Sayer's family home. Material contains descriptions of Buchanan's treatment of James and the unusual agency afforded to him.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1812-002-SC: Peter Rife vs Samuel Davis </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Concerns apprenticeship contract of Samuel Davis to learn trade of House-joiner and mill-right [millwright] and dispute of compensation after breaking his apprenticeship and questionable arbitration.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1815-009-SC: Mathew Dickey vs. George Reaves </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In an attempt to satisfy a debt owed to George Reaves, Mathew Dickey claims he mortgaged Edom, Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss, an enslaved family, to Reaves, but that this transfer was not a purchase. Dickey asserts that Reaves was to only maintain Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss, until Dickey could repay the debt. The depositions discuss Below, Edom, Sal, and Criss heavily, as well as the character of a William Sexton. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1815-019-SC: Cesar (enslaved) vs. Stephen Sanders, etc </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In this Freedom suit, Cesar [or Caesar] is seeking to secure his freedom after the death of his enslaver, James Campbell Jr., and death of Campbell's wife Mary Campbell. The terms of Campbell's will stipulated that his executors free Cesar upon the death of Mary Campbell should Cesar "in their opinion he has behaved towards her dutifully and with fidelity." Cesar argues he continued to do everything in his power to help Mary Campbell and run the estate efficiently; however, the executors turned to past disagreements between Cesar and Mary Campbell and decades old allegations to keep Cesar enslaved. The depositions primarily discuss the community perception of Cesar, and also reveals the legal counsel James Campbell received in constructing the terms of Cesar's manumission which shows the malicious intentions behind the stipulations. [See also: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/permalink/01LVA_INST/altrmk/alma9917819930505756">Legislative Petition of Caesar</extref>]
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1815-022-SC: Jacob Vanhooser vs. Jesse Evans </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Jacob Vanhooser claims legal ownership of Bob, an enslaved man, then in the hands of Jesse Evans. Vanhooser asserts that a group of "lawless bandits" took Bob during the Revolutionary War and therefore Jesse Evans cannot have a legal title. Evans argues that his understanding of events affirms that Bob came into the hands of the "board of officers" comprised of Colonel Lynch, Colonel Preston, and Colonel Wm. Campbell during the war as part of efforts to "distress rebels [loyalists]" in Southwest Virginia. Actions legitimized by the Virginia General Assembly in 1782, therefore providing Evans with a legal title to Bob. Appears the court ruled in favor of Vanhooser as there was no proof the board directed the sale of Bob. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1815-024-SC: Mary Hines vs Mathias Hines </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mary Hines is seeking an addition of dower to lands sold by her son [step-son] so she may have somewhere to live in her old age. Controversy concerns whether Mary was the legal wife of Adam Hines.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1815-025-SC: David Pierce vs. Thomas Jackson </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt: Concerns the death of Jack, an enslaved man, jointly enslaved by David Pierce and Thomas Jackson. Pierce believes he should not be responsible for the existing debts related to Jack as he asserts the mistreatment of Jackson caused Jack's sickness resulting in his death. Describes Jack's attempts at self-emancipation, his imprisonment in Wythe County jail, and mistreatment of Jackson after securing Jack from jail. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1817-010-SC: Andrew Baker, etc vs Douglass Baker</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt: The will of Andrew Baker stipulates terms of emancipation for Big Tom, Moses, Jack, Sukey and Sam. Andrew Baker's also notes that he desires apprenticeships to be obtained for his "negro children." 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1817-013: Trisham Henson vs. David Henson</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Debt: The case concerns money owed to Trisham by his brother David Henson. The brothers immigrated to the United States from Ireland along with Samuel Patterson, a neighbor. Samuel agreed to serve David Henson for three years in exchanged for passage. As David could not come up with the money, with Samuel's approval the contract of servitude transferred to Trisham. Trisham claims that after landing in Newcastle, Delaware, the brothers went their separate ways. However, David ended up selling Samuel's contract as well as linen sent along with the brothers and Trishman believes he is owed portions of the funds and he held the contract for Samuel and maintained joint ownership of the linen. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1818-002: Trst. for Wythe County vs John Johnston, Etc. </emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Other: Case begins in the Superior Chancery held in Staunton, Va., but is transferred to Wythe district. Francis Smith, Trustee for Wythe County, argues that John Johnston fraudulently sold lots of land in the newly formed town of Evansham [present day Wytheville, Va.]. Case contains information concerning the early history of the town, an 1812 map of the town of Evansham, Va., and provides information on the "academy" [Wytheville Academy].
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1818-006 : Exrs. of William Calfee, Etc. vs EXRS of George Carter, Etc.</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Estate Dispute: Largely concerns the estate of William Calfee and the distribution of his property as well as the people he enslaved. There is controversy in the family concerning the possible destruction of the original will. Some depositions of note include John Carnahan's concerning naturalization, as well as John Rice's which describes the whereabouts of Robert Patterson living within the bounds of the Cherokee Nation.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
<c01 level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="underline">1818-035-SC : Mary Cleghorn vs Valentine Griever</emph>  
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contract Suit: Mary Cleghorn claims that Valentine Griever used liquor on numerous occasions to first persuade her husband, Robert Cleghorn, into selling to Griever a tract of land, and for then delaying repayment. Mary Cleghorn even believes the heavy state of intoxication in which Griever frequently enabled Robert Cleghorn to stay in for days contributed to his death. Griever rebukes all claims and instead calls Mary Cleghorn's character into question. The case is eventually dismissed.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>



