<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06321">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06321::A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908)//EN" "vi06321.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1789-1908</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>20 March 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1789-1908</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2024
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Bari Helms; Greg Crawford
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1789-1908
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>79 volume; .45 cubic feet (1 box)</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, <emph render="bold">please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available</emph>. 
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Augusta County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Augusta County in 2008 under the accession numbers 43658 and 43836.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>

<p> John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247 </p>

<p>Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 253, 255, 256</p>
		
<p>Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244 </p>

<p>Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 248, 254, 255 </p>

<p>Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 249 </p>

<p>Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247 </p>

<p>Mictiow Sales Book, 183 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 255 </p>
<p>Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 249, 250</p>

<p>Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 247, 253 </p>

<p>Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244	</p>

<p>Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 257 </p>

<p>Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 244-245, 256-257	</p>

<p>William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 246, 252, 253 </p>

</altformavail>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.
</p>
<p>The records in this collection were processed as different times from 2002-2015 mostly by Bari Helms as well Greg Crawford. Efforts have been taken to identify chancery causes related to these business records as some of these records were used as evidence in court proceedings.</p>

<p>Encoded by M. Mason, March 2024</p>


</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments , these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes. 
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Augusta County was named for Augusta of Saxe-Gotha, who married Frederick Louis, Prince of Wales, and was the mother of King George III. It was formed from Orange County by a statute of 1738 that stipulated that when the population was large enough the new county government would begin to function. The county court first met on 9 December 1745.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Augusta County (Va.) Business Records,1789-1908, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Augusta County (Va.). Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, minute books, cashbooks, invoice books, and account books. 
</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged<list type="simple">
<item>Series I: Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861</item>
<item>Series II: John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842</item>
<item>Series III: Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907</item>
<item>Series IV: John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837</item>
<item>Series V: John Frazier and Bath and Rockbridge Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854</item>
<item>Series VI: Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867</item>
<item>Series VII: Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810</item>
<item>Series VIII: Houff &amp; Holler Business Records, 1904-1908</item>
<item>Series IX: Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847</item>
<item>Series X: Nicholas C. Kinney Daybook and Ledgers, 1815-1830</item>
<item>Series XI: Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871</item>
<item>Series XII: Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856</item>
<item>Series XIII: Mictiow Sales Book, 1837</item>
<item>Series XIV: Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793</item>
<item>Series XV: Series XV: Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906</item>
<item>Series XVI: Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805</item>
<item>Series XVII: Tannehill &amp; Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874</item>
<item>Series XVIII: Series XIX: Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831</item>
<item>Series XIX: Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860</item>
<item>Series XX: Thornburg and Shafer Daybook, 1877-1879</item>
<item>Series XXI: Unidentified General Store Daybooks, 1828-1835</item>
<item>Series XXII: Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873</item>
<item>Series XXIII: Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875</item>
<item>Series XXIV:Virginia Express Company Minute Book and Cashbook, 1867-1869</item>
<item>Series XXV: John Wayt Invoice Book, 1828-1831</item>
<item>Series XXVI:William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826</item></list>
</p>

</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p> See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi03473.xml"> August County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912 </extref>
</p>
<p>Additional August County(Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>

</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1857-1861
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> Based out of Hartford, Connecticut, the Aetna Insurance Company sold its first life insurance policy in 1850. In 1853, the company was incorporated as the Aetna Life Insurance Company with former Connecticut judge Eliphalet A. Bulkeley as its first president. In 1861, the company began offering participating life insurance policies, and at the end of the Civil War, Aetna was one of the nation's biggest life insurance providers. Today, Aetna is a diversified health care benefits company providing a range of health care insurance products and related services including dental, pharmacy, group life, and disability insurance.</p>

<p>Aetna Insurance Company established an insurance agency in Staunton, Virginia, in the mid-nineteenth century. Alexander F. Kinney served as an agent for the company. Kinney, a Virginia resident born about 1836, was also a bank teller and a circuit court clerk for Augusta County.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861, record the disbursements of the company for such expenses as advertising, express or freight charges, taxes, return premiums, etc. All vouchers were signed by Aetna's agent Alexander F. Kinney.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278963">Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1857-1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1827-1842
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> <emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> John Armstrong, Sr. was a farmer in Augusta County, Virginia. He had a son, John Armstrong, Jr., who owned a neighboring farm. He died in 1842.</p>

<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842, records Armstrong's personal finances along with the business activities of his farm. Each account records the transactions with individuals that Armstrong either hired or with whom he conducted business. Information found in each entry include the date, type of transaction, and monies debited or credited to the account. Armstrong recorded purchases for such items as wheat, bacon, brandy, tallow, butter, dry apples, and flour. There are also larger purchases such as livestock and furniture. In addition, Armstrong recorded the work done by white laborers which included such tasks as sawing wood, mowing, etc.
</p>

<p>Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Admr. of John Armstrong, Sr. vs Admr. of John Armstrong, Jr. , Etc.1860-074. Avaible Digitially through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/chancery/"> Chancery Records Index. </extref> </p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 7278959">John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1827-1842
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>

</c01>









</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>













