<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi06207">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vivi06207::A Guide to the Henry County (Va.) Business Records, 1841-1893)//EN" "vivi06207.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1841-1893</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Henry County (Va.) Business Records, 1841-1893
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jennifer Taylor
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169;  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Jennifer Taylor, <date>11 June 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1841-1893</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="Accession number">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Greg Crawford
</label>
<item>
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henry County (Va.) Business Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1841-1893
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">State Record Center-Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>4 volumes</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Henry County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions. 
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Henry County (Va.) Business Records, 1841-1893. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Augusta County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Henry County in undated accessions. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.
</p>
<p>These records were processed in 2003 by Greg Crawford. </p>
<p>Encoded by J. Taylor: June 2024.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Henry County was named for Patrick Henry, who was the first governor of the commonwealth of Virginia. It was formed from Pittsylvania County in 1776. The county court first met on 20 January 1777. Part of Patrick County was added later in 1858. The county seat was previously in Martinsville but has been moved near Collinsville.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Henry County (Va.) Business Records, 1841-1893, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Newport News (Va.). Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, day books, and account books.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into four series:
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: John H. Matthews Business Records, 1868-1875</item>
<item>Series II: John H. Matthews and Company Business Records, 1872-1874</item>
<item>Series III: T.C. Shelton Business Records, 1841-1843</item>
<item>Series IV: Trent and Davis Business Records, 1892-1893</item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Henry County records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA129">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">John H. Matthews Business Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1875
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume.</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>John H. Matthews was a businessman in Henry County involved in various business activities during the mid-nineteenth century. They included mercantile, blacksmithing, flour trade, and carding wool.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>John H. Matthews Business Records consists of an account book which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, type of transaction (goods sold or services rendered), quantity of goods sold, cost of each item, amount owed, and amount paid. Goods sold include spices, wheat, flour, hair pins, wool, beeswax, meat, dry goods, axes, and shoes. Services rendered include carding wool, shoeing horses, repairing and sharpening farm tools, and making coffins. Payments made by cash, credit, labor, and barter of such goods as apples, wood, and fodder.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1098508">John H. Matthews Account Book
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1875
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">John H. Matthews and Company
<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1874
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> John H. Matthews and Company was a general store that conducted business in the town of Horse Pasture Mills in Henry County, Virginia during the late nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>John H. Matthews and Company Business Records consists of a daybook which recorded in chronological order the daily transactions of John H. Matthews and Company. Information recorded in the daybook includes date of transaction, name of customer, merchandise purchased, quantity purchased, price of each item, form of payment, and amount owed or paid. Merchandise sold includes axes, rope, castor oil, sugar, scissors, clothing, bacon, nails, spices, and dry goods. Payments made by cash or barter of goods such as berries, corn, and beans.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1098512">John H. Matthews and Company Daybook
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1874
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>	
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">T.C. Shelton Business Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">1841-1843
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>T. C. Shelton was a physician in Henry County during the mid-nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>T.C. Shelton Business Records consists of an account book which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Information found in each account includes name of customer, dates of transactions, services rendered, amout owed and paid, and form of payment. Medical services rendered include visits to patients (many of whom were slaves), medication for illnesses, and extracting teeth. Medicines given to patients by Shelton include cream tartar, chamomile, peppermint, squills, purgative pills and powders, and hartshorn. Payments made by cash, credit, labor such as shoemaking, and barter of items such as corn, pork, and a coat.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1098553">T.C. Shelton Account Book
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1841-1843
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV">Trent and Davis Business Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">1892-1893
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>Trent and Davis was a grocery store that conducted business in Henry County during the late nineteenth century.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The Trent and Davis Business Records consists of a ledger which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, merchandise sold, quantity of items sold, amount owed and paid, and form of payment. Items sold include cigars, poultry, fruit, vegetables, fish, lard, ham, butter, chocolate, and meal. Payments made by cash, check, and barter of such items as chickens and pigs. Additional transactions of an unknown nature are found at the end of volume.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1098507">Trent and Davis Ledger
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1892-1893
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>



