<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxngschema"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     id="vi06390">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06390::A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Commissary of Stores, 1776-1785.)//EN" "vi06390.xml"
		</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Commissary of Stores, <date>1776-1785.</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Virginia.<num type="Accession Number">190, 54314</num>
            </subtitle>
            <author>Paige Neal</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
            <xi:include href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication">© 2024  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
			</date>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid, <date>2024 Oct 11</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Commissary of Stores, <date>1776-1785.</date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle id="sort">A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
			<num type="Accession Number">190, 54314</num>
         </subtitle>
         <author>Paige Neal</author>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2024
			</date>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:
			</label>
               <item>LVA Staff.
			</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" type="collection">Records of the Virginia Commissary of Stores,</unittitle>
         <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">1776-1785.</unitdate>
         <unitid encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">190, 54314</unitid>
         <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Commissary of Stores.</origination>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">xx volumes.</physdesc>


      </did>

<odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>These records are part of the Revolutionary War / Government record group (R.G. 2)</p>
      </odd>
      
<descgrp type="admininfo">
	<head>Administrative Information</head>

      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <p>Arranged alphabetically.</p>
      </arrangement>

      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
		<head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>Use microfilm when available.</p>
      </accessrestrict>

      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
         <head>Preferred Citation
		</head>
         <p>Records of the Virginia Commissary of Stores [cite specific date and accession used]. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>

      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition Information
		</head>
         <p>Acquired prior to 1905.</p>

	
      </acqinfo>




    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
	<p>The office of the state agent and commissary of stores was created by an ordinance passed by the third revolutionary convention on August 21, 1775. In 1777 the office was divided, and different persons were appointed state agent and commissary of stores. Initially the Public Stores were directed by the Commissary of Stores whose duties were closely related to those of the State Agent. Working under the authorizations from the Board of War and later the Commissioner of the War Office, the Commissary distributed all stores under his charge.  The office also received supplies imported from abroad or purchased by the State Agent.  William Aylett held the double position of State Agent and Commissary of Stores between 1775 and 1777.  Upon his resignation, two offices were created, with William Armistead being appointed to the latter in 1777.  He served as Commissary of Stores until the office was abolished in February 1782, and was responsible for the storage and distribution of supplies acquired by the state agent's office for the troops in the Illinois country, Pennsylvania, and in Virginia. After February 1782, the commissary's functions were assumed first by the Commercial Agent, being served at the time by David Ross, and taken over by William Hay in May 1782.  The Public Stores wer placed under the State Quartermaster General, Henry Young, in Oct 1782, when the office of the Commercial Agent was discontinued.</p>

<p>xx</p>

	  
      
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      

<p>xx</p>

<p>For additional records see the Governor's Executive Papers for this time period.</p>













    </scopecontent>
    
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      
<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Public Store - Fredericksburg Station,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1780 Feb-June.</emph></unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 1 v. (163 p.)</extent>
</physdesc>
        </did>


        
<scopecontent>
<p>This volume contains entries of supplies issued to Virginia regiments (1st, 2nd and 3rd), Col. Armand's independent legion, laborers then on furlough and discharged to Maryland divisions, Militia marching to the Southard, Major Mitchell, General Muhlenburg, the staff department, the Continental Hospital, Light Dragoons, and British prisoners, among others. Species and Quantities of Provision Received at Fredericksburg Station in the Southern Department and Provisions Received by Edward Herndon.
</p>

<p>Columns include date issued, number of orders, by whom ordered, number of rations, and quantity of beef, meal, mutton, rum, whiskey, salt, soap, molassas, tallow, flour, bacon, beer, rice, fish and vinegar. (Accession 54306)</p>

<p>Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 635.</p>

<p>Negative photostat also available (Accession 54314).</p>
</scopecontent>


<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Provisions and Stores Issued, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780 Feb-June.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>


</c01>

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Public Store - Illinois Department / Kaskaskie,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1776-1782.</emph></unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 3 v.</extent>
</physdesc>
        </did>


        
<scopecontent>
<p>Ledger, 30 Aug 1776-12 Mar 1782 (368 p.), accounts for the distribution of equipment and supplies to military officers. In addition, there is a list of bills drawn on the treasury of Virginia by William Shannon, and a memorandum of bills drawn on Col. George Rogers Clark, 1779. Account book maintained by William Shannon, Commissary and Quarter Master General, of stores furnished for use of the Illinois Department under George Rogers Clark. Clark, in an affidavit of 9 Nov 1779 attests to the authenticity of the accounts. Folio 165 includes Commonwealth in account with Shannon as settled by the Auditors of Williamsburg, Feb 1780; folio 169 includes a list of bills drawn on the Treasurer of Virginia after the first of Jan 1780 by William Shannon. Also includes various memoranda of purchases and certificates entered in the back. Restored. Indexed in the front of the volume and each separate account arranged chronologically. (Accession 190).
</p>

<p>Account book, 1780 (65 p.), with accounts against the state of Virginia. Volume records the issue of supplies to members of the Illinois regiment, many of whom are named. Some of the supplies mentioned: linen, muslin, combs, flannel, velvet, writing paper, metal buttons, rum, sugar, handkerchiefs, and ink pots. John Dodge and Israel Dodge are the agents who kept the accounts. Various accounts due John Dodge and Israel Dodge from the state for supplies furnished for use of the Illinois Department. Included inventories of sundries purchased in New Orleans and other places and transferred to the department; lists of sundries issued to various persons; abstracts of issues of merchandise; abstracts of vouchers; a listing of entries in an unspecified volume, some copies attested to in 1783. No arrangment and no index. (Accession 54314)</p>

<p>Receipt book, 1780 June 10-Nov 20 (90 p), for items received by John Dodge, Esq., agent for the state of Virginia at Fort Jefferson, Ill., mainly for clothin, material and weapons. Among the items received were salt, blankets, knives, broadcloth, and plain and ruffled shirts.  Receipts for sundries issued out of the public store at Fort Jefferson, Illinois by John Dodge, agent for the store. Includes an Aug 7, 1780 affidavit concerning articles lost by Israel Dodge in March when crossing the Ohio entered as a promissory note, and also a promissory note from George Rogers Clark to Don Fernando de leylia for furnishes dated 29 Apr 1779, and a later note instructing Dodge to pay the note. Also includes a list of some articles delivered to Joseph Pauley on account of the debt, July 1780. Restored and bound. No index. (Accession 54314)</p>

<p>Account book and Receipt book also available on Miscellaneous Reel 406.</p>

</scopecontent>


<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Ledger, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1776 Aug 30-1782 Mar 12.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Account book, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>
<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Receipt book, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780 June 10-Nov 20.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Public Store - Pennsylvania / Philadelpia,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1778-1780.</emph></unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 5 v.</extent>
</physdesc>
        </did>


        
<scopecontent>
<p>Daybook, 1779 Sept 4-1780 Apr 1, of John Moss, state agent in Pennsylvania, which records transactions and the issuing of uniform items to Virginia troops. (Accession 54314).
</p>

<p>Journals, 1778 Aug 1-1780 Apr 1, were kept by John Moss, state agent in Philadelphia, recording the issue of uniform items and sundries to officers of Virginia regiments. Volume 1, August 1, 1778 - August 30, 1779, is prefaced by an extract of an act of Congress of March 23, 1779, regulating the clothing department for the armies of the United States, by Charles Thomson, secretary. Volume 2, September 1779 - April 1780, is prefaced by an extract from acts of the General Assembly concerning officers, soldiers, and sailors, and marines regarding terms of enlistment and re-enlistment, and a statement concerning clothing entitlements, bounties, as a reward for service and the salary for recruiters. Also includes a memorandum of dimensions of soldiers' hats. Volumes are records of disbursements and receipts, indentifying each item and its value.  Total sales for each month are listed.Names of officers given in the journals. Volumes are in chronological and thereunder by regiment, and are not indexed.(Accessions 158, 54314)</p>

<p>Ledgers, 1778 Aug 4-1780 Sept, kept by John Moss, State Agent in Philadelphia, recording transactions of uniform items and sundries to officers and troops of Virginia regiments. Volumes show a record of cash receipts, with columns for purchaser, date, articles involved, price, and page of Journal on which the transaction is entered.  The credit side of the ledger includes the date on which the account was settled, by what means, amount, and again, a page reference to the Journal. (Accession 174, 54314)</p>

<p>Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 637.</p>

</scopecontent>


<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Daybook, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779 Sept 4-1780 Apr 1.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Journal, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1778 Aug 1-1779 Aug 30.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Volume" type="volume">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c02>
<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Journal, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780 Sept 7-1780 Apr.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Volume" type="volume">2
		</container>
            </did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Ledger, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1778 Aug 4-1779 Sept 1.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Volume" type="volume">1
		</container>
            </did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Ledger, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779-1780.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Volume" type="volume">2
		</container>
            </did>
		</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Public Store - Richmond,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">1780-1785.</emph></unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>Extent: 4 v.</extent>
</physdesc>
        </did>


        
<scopecontent>
<p>Daybook, 1780 June 14-Nov 30, is a record of daily business at the Public Store in Richmond and identifies good, to whom delivered and under what authorization.  This volume contains daily issue of items stocked in the Public Store, Richmond, to a variety of customers including Cherokee Indians (ribbon, rum, and nails) and the State Agent (tobacco and rum). Arranged chronologically.  No index. (Accession 54314).
</p>

<p>Journal, 1782 Nov 5-1783 May 21 (90 p.), is an account book kept by Captain Henry Young, Quartermaster General, for uniforms and other items issued from the Public Store in Richmond. Record of disbursements, both civil and military from the Store. In some instances value is attached. Names, chiefly officers, are given along with assigned account numbers. Under date 1 May 1783, are the individual entries for soldiers of Dabney's Legion for "difficiencies of clothing due to them." Arranged chronologically. No index.(Accession 54314)</p>

<p>Ledger, 1781 Mar 16-1785 Dec 30, contains an accounting of items issued from the Public Store in Richmond. Entries include date, transaction and sum.  Preceeding the accounts is an alphabetical list of all account holders, their residence, and account number. (Accession 54314)</p>

<p>Receipt book, 1782 Nov 5-1783 July 22, contains receipts for items issued by Captain Henry Young, Quartermaster General for the public store in Richmond, under both civil and military authorization. Items issued include woolen overalls, leather breeches, stockings, shoes, bark, and ipecac.  Includes an extensive list of persons in Dabney's Legion and State Regiments who have received clothing in full for all deficiencies against the State. (Accession 36171) </p>

<p>Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 636.</p>

</scopecontent>


<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Daybook, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780 June 14-Nov 30.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>

<c02 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Journal, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782 Nov 5-1783 May 21.</unitdate>.
		</unittitle>
            </did>
		</c02>



</c01>
    
  
	</dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>