<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxngschema"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     id="vi06356">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06356::A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work, 2016-2020.)//EN" "vi06356.xml"
		</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work, <date>2016-2020.</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Virginia.<num type="Accession Number">53940</num>
            </subtitle>
            <author>LVA Staff</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
            <xi:include href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication">© 2023  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
			</date>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid, <date>2023</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work, <date>2016-2020.</date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle id="sort">A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
			<num type="Accession Number">53940</num>
         </subtitle>
         <author>LVA Staff</author>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher>Library of Virginia
			</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2023
			</date>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:
			</label>
               <item>Library of Virginia Staff.
			</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia</repository>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" type="collection">Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work,</unittitle>
         <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f">2016-2020.</unitdate>
         <unitid encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">53940</unitid>
         <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia. Dept. of Health Professions.</origination>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">113 mb.</physdesc>


      </did>


<odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>Must make arrangements prior to arrival to view electronic records.</p>
      </odd>
      <odd encodinganalog="500">
         <p>These records are part of the Virginia Dept. of Health Professions record group (RG# 37)</p>
      </odd>
      
<descgrp type="admininfo">
	<head>Administrative Information</head>

      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <p>Arranged chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>

      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
		<head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>There are no access restrictions</p>
      </accessrestrict>

 




      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
         <head>Preferred Citation
		</head>
         <p>Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work, [cite specific dates and accession used]. State government records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </prefercite>

      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition Information
		</head>
	<p>Accession 53940 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 07/24/2023.</p>
	

	
      </acqinfo>


<processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>Electronic records are in original order with original file names.
</p>
      </processinfo>

    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
	<p>Regulation of the health professions began late in the nineteenth century. On January 31, 1884, the General Assembly passed an act creating the Board of Medical Examiners to certify physicians for practice in Virginia. Two years later, acts establishing the Board of Dental Examiners (now the Board of Dentistry) and the Board of Pharmacy were passed by the General Assembly on February 26 and March 3, 1886, respectively. The Board of Embalmers (now the Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers) was created by an act passed on March 5, 1894, and the Board of Veterinary Examiners (now the Board of Veterinary Medicine) was established by an act passed on February 27, 1896. On May 1, 1903, the General Assembly created the Board of Graduate Nurses (now the State Board of Nursing), and on March 11, 1916, the Board of Optometry was established by legislative action.</p>
      <p>The Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 31, 1977, to provide administrative services to the health regulatory boards of the state. The boards continue to regulate their professions through the examination, licensing, and disciplining of the practitioners of health science. In 1986, the Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards became the Dept. of Health Professions. Its mission is to enhance the delivery of safe and competent health care by licensing qualified health care professionals, enforcing standards of practice, and providing information to both practitioners and consumers of health care services.</p>

<p>The Virginia Board of Social Work consists of a 9-member Board,  administrative, enforcement, licensing, and support staff.  The Board regulates Licensed Baccalaureate, Licensed Clinical, and Licensed Master’s Social Workers.</p>


      
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Minutes, 2016-2020, documenting the meetings, activities, discussions, policy decisions and recommendations of the Virginia Board of Social Work.  Includes minutes and agendas for formal board meetings, as well as for formal hearings, informal hearings, telephone conference calls, public hearings, and for committees and and other group meetings (Informal Conference Committee, Regulatory Committee, Special Conference Committee). 
</p>


	

    </scopecontent>
    
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      
<c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle><emph render="bold">Minutes of the Virginia Board of Social Work,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold">2016-2020.</emph></unitdate>
</unittitle>

        </did>







        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <emph render="bold">Accession 53940 (2016-2020).
</emph>
            </unittitle>
          </did>

 <scopecontent>
<p> Minutes of the Board of Social Work, 2016-2020, are in electronic format (113 mb, 50 folders, 98 files) and include scanned copies of official, signed minutes and agendas for Full Board minutes, as well as for Formal Hearings, Informal Conference Committees, Public Hearings, Special Conference Committees, and the Regulatory Committee, and for Social Work Stakeholders.   For file inventory for this accession, see: <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva.primo.exlibrisgroup.com/view/delivery/01LVA_INST/12149529080005756"><emph render="bold">Inventory (53940)</emph></extref>.
</p> 
</scopecontent>


         
</c02>



</c01>











    
  
	</dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>