<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi06209">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vivi06209::A Guide to the Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, 1820-1947)//EN" "vivi06209.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1820-1947</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, 1820-1947
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jennifer Taylor
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169; 2024 By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Jennifer Taylor, <date>09 July 2024</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, <date>1820-1947</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: Greg Crawford
</label>
<item>
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1820-1947
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Location">State Record Center-Archives Annex, Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>12 volumes</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Gloucester County Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, <emph render="bold">please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.</emph>
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, 1820-1947. [include volume title]. Local government records collection, Gloucester County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Gloucester County in an undated accession. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Please see <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA101#BRC">Gloucester County Microfilm </extref> index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.</p>
<p>Daybook of the Tidewater Telephone Company, 1888-1891 is available as microfilm Gloucester County (Va.) Reel 50</p>
<p>Ledger of an Unidentified Business, 1820-1834 is available as microfilm Gloucester County (Va.) Reel 51</p>
</altformavail>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Prior to 2024, the various business records in this collection were originally described as individual records, but they have been consolidated into one large business record for the locality.</p>
<p>These records were processed by Greg Crawford in 2008. Efforts have been taken to identify chancery causes related to these business records as some of these records were used as evidence in court proceedings.
</p>
<p>Encoded by J. Taylor: July 2024.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Gloucester County was named probably to honor Henry, duke of Gloucester, the third son of King Charles I, or it may also have been named for the English county. It was formed from York County in 1651. The county seat is Gloucester.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Lost Locality Note:</emph> All records were destroyed by an 1820 fire, and most of the records created after 1820 were destroyed by fire in Richmond on 3 April 1865, where they had been moved for safekeeping during the Civil War.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Gloucester County (Va.) Business Records, 1832-1947 is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Glucester County (Va.). Represented records consist of bound volumes such as ledgers, cash books, memorandum books, and account books.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into two series:
<list type="simple"><item>Series I: Business Records of John R. Cary, 1832-1869</item>
<item>Series II: Business Records of R.C. Booker and Company, 1913-1920</item>
<item>Series III: Business Records of the Tidewater Telephone Company, 1888-1891</item>
<item>Series IV: Business Records of an Unidentified Blacksmith, 1883-1908</item>
<item>Series V: Business Records of an Unidentified Business, 1820-1834</item>
<item>Series VI: Business Records of an Unidentified General Store, 1861-1867</item>
<item>Series VII: Business Records of the United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company, 1925-1947</item>
</list>
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Additional Gloucester County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia.  Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA159">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref>
</p>
<p>See also: <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi02209.xml">"A Guide to the Gloucester County (Va.) Chancery Caues, 1866-1931."</extref></p>
<p>Gloucester County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Gloucester County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva-virginia.libguides.com/lost-records">Lost Records Localities Digital Collection</extref>available on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Business Records of John R. Cary,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1869
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>5 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>John R. Cary served as clerk of Gloucester County from 1837 until his death in 1867. The records were used as evidence in a chancery case heard in Gloucester County Circuit Court in 1874 entitled John S. Cooke, Executor of John R. Cary versus Widow of John R. Cary and others. The suit originated from Cary's wish in his will that an inventory on his estate not be performed to determine its value before selling it to pay off his debts. Upon assuming executorship of Cary's estate, Cooke was unable to carry out Cary's wish due to the numerous debts Cary incurred personally and as representative of both Matthew W. Kemp's estate and Thomas Cary's estate. Cooke asked the court to assist him in determining the value of Cary's estate and the debts Cary owed. The court ordered all papers and books kept by Cary related to his estate, and as representative of both Kemp's estate and Thomas Cary's estate, audited by a special commission and a report made.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>John R. Cary Business Records, 1832-1869 consists of three account books and two memorandum books. The records maintained by or related to John R. Cary, recorded financial, agricultural, and miscellaneous information concerning Cary's estate in Gloucester County
</p>
<p>See also:<extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/chancery/case_detail.asp?CFN=073-1874-004"> Gloucester County Chancery Causes, 1874-004: John S. Cooke, Executor of John R. Cary versus Widow of John R. Cary and others.</extref></p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series I: Subseries A">Account Books, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1869
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physloc>State Records Center
	</physloc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The account books related to John R. Cary's estate as well as the estate of Thomas Cary, for which John R. Cary was executor. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
				<c03 level="item">
				<did>
				<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096181">Account Book of John S. Cooke, executor of John R. Cary, 
				<unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1869
				</unitdate>
				</unittitle>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
				<p>The volume records Cooke's transactions both personal and as executor of Cary's estate. Information found in volume includes name of account, date of transaction, cash paid, cash received, and names of individuals paid or from whom cash was received. Accounts, kept by Cooke as Cary's executor, record payment of debts owed by Cary at the time of his death. Volume includes receipts for payment of debts. Cooke's personal accounts record loans made to individuals many of whom were African-American. Repayment of loans were made by labor such as cutting wood, hauling goods, and washing clothes or by hiring themselves or children to Cooke for a period of time.
				</p>
				</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096186">Account Book of the Thomas Cary Estate,
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1869
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>The account book was perhaps kept by his nephew John R. Cary, after he became the representative for his uncle's estate following his death. A portion of the volume dated 1832-1840 recorded accounts of individuals who did business with the Thomas Cary estate and the accounts of the estate itself. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each account includes date of transaction, style of transaction, form of payment, amounts owed and paid. Transactions include loans, payment of loans, house expenses, payment of laborers, and the sale/hire of enslaved people. Pages in volume, dated 1868-1869, record transactions perhaps related to a church fundraiser.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1132396">Account Book of John R. Cary,
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1860
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>The account book recorded the accounts of individuals and companies Cary had transactions with, both personal and as the representative of Matthew W. Kemp's estate. Transactions related to Cary's personal debts, the maintenance of his house and other buildings on his estate, agricultural supplies and debts incurred by Cary as Kemp's representative. The account book also contains detailed information related to the planting of wheat and production of pork by Carey's estate. In addition, there is miscellaneous information related to the history of Cary family, and remedies for diseases such as cholera and scrofula. There are also loose papers in volume, one of which was a letter written by Cary during the Civil War in which he recounted a Northern raid on the town of Gloucester.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
			</c03>

		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series I: Subseries B">Memorandum Books
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1860
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Two memorandum books of John R. Cary. One dated, 1847-1852, recorded payments to laborers, purchases of merchandise, groceries, and guano, debts, and sale of wheat. A second memorandum book, dated 1860, recorded cash paid and cash received by Cary. Transactions are listed in chronological order and include purchases of food, whiskey, nails, guano, and spices, repairs to carriage, spices, and miscellaneous expenses. Cary received cash from payment of debts, the sale/hire of enslaved people and fees from court suits. The last few pages of memorandum book record payments made to laborers who were perhaps doing work on Cary's home. Several pages list dimensions of various rooms, such as the parlor, portico, and porch. The second memorandum book also includes a list of enslaved people hired out by Cary as personal representative of Matthew W. Kemp and a list of people enslaved by Cary in January 1860.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Barcode Number 0007769392">John R. Cary Memorandum Book,
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1852
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096192">John. R. Cary Memorandum Book, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1860
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
			</c03>
		</c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">Business Records of the R.C. Booker Company,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1913-1920
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content: </emph>The business records of the R. C. Booker Company consists of a ledger which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found includes date of transaction, merchandise sold, quantity of merchandise purchased, form of payment, and amounts owed and paid. Merchandise sold includes food, lard, soap, dry goods, flour, gun shells, candy, meal, and tablets. Payments made by cash, check, credit, and barter (potatoes and eggs). Volume includes numerous loose slips of paper that record requests for merchandise by customers. Volume also includes an alphabetical index listing the names of customers and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> R. C. Booker Company was a general store operated by Robert Cary Booker that conducted business in the town of Ordinary, Virginia, during the early twentieth century.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096194">Ledger of R.C. and Company,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1913-1920
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Business Records of the Tidewater Telephone Company,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1888-1891
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> The business records of the Tidewater Telephone Company include an daybook. The volume records the company's monthly collections and earnings from 1888 to 1891. Information found in volume includes name of locality; money collected and/or earned from messages, telegrams, and commissions; and miscellaneous transactions.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096087">Daybook of the Tidewater Telephone Company, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1888-1891
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV">Business Records of an Unidentified Blacksmith,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1908
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume. </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph>This unidentified blacksmith conducted business in Gloucester County during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph>The daybook was used as an account book by an unidentified blacksmith. It records the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found includes date of transaction, service rendered, form of payment, and amount owed or paid. Services rendered include shoeing horses and mules, repairing ox carts and carriages, mending chains, and making crowbars and other tools. Payments made by cash, credit, barter (clover seed, pigs, beef, and sweet potatoes) and labor (hauling goods and plowing).</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096203">Unidentified Blacksmith Daybook
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1908
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series V">Business Records of an Unidentified Business, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1820-1834
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> The business records of an unidentified business consists of an account book. The business was located in the towns of Rock Landing and Weldon. Entries entered into volume similar to a daybook. It served as a daybook, recording transactions on an almost daily basis from January 1820-August 1834. Each entry contained the following information: date of transaction, name of customer or controlling account, style of transaction, amount owed and amount paid. Each entry also included page numbers where entries could be found in a missing corresponding ledger or ledgers. Merchandise sold included corn, flour, molasses, shingles, salt, and cotton. Controlling accounts included toll account, wagon account, merchandise account, expense account, and drayage account.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096334">Account Book of an Unidentified Business, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1820-1834
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series VI:">Business Records of an Unidentified General Store, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1867
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Record Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content: </emph>The business records of an unidentified general store consists of a daybook located at Gloucester Court House. The volume records in chronological order, the store's transactions from January 1861-May 1862 and sporadically from June 1862-December 1863. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, name of customer, merchandise purchased, quantity purchased, cost of items purchased, and total amount owed. Merchandise sold includes pencils, matches, violin strings, neck ties, castor oil, spices, food, and dry goods. The last hundred pages of volume records the individual accounts of customers for 1867. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity purchased, form of payment, amount owed, and amount paid. Items sold include iron spoons, eggs, coconuts, dry goods, spices, quinine, and soda. Payments made by cash, credit, and barter of items such as flour, bacon, cotton, and tea.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096193">Daybook of an Unidentified General Store, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1867
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>

	</c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series VII">Business Records of the United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company, 
<unitdate type="inclusive">1925-1947
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc>State Records Center
</physloc>
<physdesc><extent>2 volumes</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p><emph render="bold">Scope and Content:</emph> The business records of the United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company consist of two registers.  The volumes record the following information: bond or policy number, date bond or policy was issued or renewed, length of term, expiration date, name of bondholder or policyholder, address, occupation, amount of bond or policy, rate of interest, type and amount of premium, total amount, name of agent or broker, date premium paid, brokerage or commission paid, return premium, date canceled, and miscellaneous remarks. Registers also include numerous loose miscellaneous papers, mostly correspondence and policies related to insurance claims.
</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Historical Information:</emph> The United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company was an insurance company established in 1896 and continued operations under that name until 1981, when it changed its name to USF&amp;G. It became a subsidiary of Saint Paul Companies in 1998. The registers belonged to an agent of the United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company who worked in Gloucester County in the early twentieth century.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096364">United States Fidelity and Guaranty Register of Bonds and Policies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1925-1947
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode Number 1096365">United States Fidelity and Guaranty Company Register of Bonds and Policies, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1931-1945
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>



	
	
	
	
	
	
	





