<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vivi06302">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vivi06302::A Guide to the : Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, 1866)//EN" "vivi06302.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the : Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, <date>1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">: Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife
<num type="collectionnumber">0007855418
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mary Ann Mason
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Library of Virginia
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">&#169;  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Mary Ann Mason, <date>17 August 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the : Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, <date>1866</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/> the Library of Virginia
<num type="Barcode number">0007855418
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication"> 17 August 2023
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by: L. Neuroth
</label>
<item>
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a"> Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1866
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007855418
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 page (Facsimile) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Clarke County (Va.) Circuit Court.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">


<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, 1866, is digitized and available through <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No restrictions on use
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, 1866. Local Government Records Collection, Clarke County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Facsimile and digital images created in May 2022 by the Library of Virginia's Photographic and Digital Imaging Services.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p> Original register lent for creation of digital images and facsimile and returned to the locality upon completion.
</p>
<p>Encoded by M. Mason, August 2023.</p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>

<p><emph render="bold">Context for Record Type:</emph> A cohabitation register, or as it is officially titled, "Register of Colored Persons Cohabiting Together as Husband and Wife on 27th February 1866," was the legal vehicle by which formerly enslaved men and women legitimized both their marriages and their children. On February 26,1866, the General Assembly passed an act legitimizing marriages between enslaved people and the children that resulted from them. These records contain extensive information including the names of the husband and wife, as well as their ages, place of birth, residence, occupations, previous enslavers, previous enslaver's city or county residence, the name(s) of their children, the children's ages, and the date of commencement of cohabitation. </p>
<p>The federal Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands directed the Assistant Superintendents of the states to order the county clerks to make a registry of such cohabiting couples. See Circular No. 11, dated 19 March 1866, in Orders, Circulars, Circular Letters, and Letters of Instruction, vol. 2 (1866). Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands, Records of the Assistant Commissioner for the State of Virginia, 1865-1869. Miscellaneous reel 3880, Library of Virginia. National Archives microfilm M1048 (reel 41), Record Group 105.</p>
<p><emph render="bold">Locality History:</emph> Clarke County was named for Lieutenant Colonel George Rogers Clark, who commanded the Virginia forces that secured control of the Northwest Territory for Virginia during the Revolution. He spelled his name without the terminal e. The county was formed from Frederick County in 1836. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, on 27th February, 1866. Also commonly called Clarke County (Va.) Cohabitation Register. This register records the name of the husband, his age, place of birth, residence, occupation, last owner, last owner's residence; the name of the wife, her age, place of birth, residence, last owner, last owner's residence; the name of the children with the age of each; date of commencement of cohabitation.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Clarke County (Va.) Register of Colored Persons cohabiting together as Husband and Wife, on 27th February, 1866 is retained in locality by Clarke County Circuit Court.
</p>
</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p> Records related to free and enslaved people of Clarke County (Va.) and other localities are available through the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/aan">Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection </extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>

<p>Additional Clarke County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.lva.virginia.gov/public/local/results_all.asp?CountyID=VA131">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref></p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>






