<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vi06405">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Vi">PUBLIC "-//Library of Virginia//TEXT (US::Vi::vi06405::A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Wills, 1834-1959)//EN" "vi06405.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Wills, <date>1834-1959</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Greensville County (Va.) Wills
<num type="barcodenumber">0007843137, 0007843104
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>McKenzie Long
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/lva_address.xi.xml"/>
<date type="publication">&#169; 2023  By The Library of Virginia. All Rights Reserved. 
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record by McKenzie Long, <date>20 October 2023</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Wills, <date>1834-1959</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>the Library of Virginia
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/lva.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Library of Virginia
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2023 
</date>
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>McKenzie Long
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Library of Virginia
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">The Library of Virginia
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Greensville County (Va.) Wills, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1834-1959
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Barcode Number" encodinganalog="099$a">0007843137, 0007843104 
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Library of Virginia
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.9 cu. ft. (2 boxes)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Wills, 1834-1846 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone minimal processing. All records remain tri-folded or in original bundles and may be fragile. Contact Archives Research services for availability.  
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Greensville County (Va.) Wills, 1834-1959. Local government records collection, Greensville County Court Records. The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>These records came to the Library of Virginia in a 2023 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 53810.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Encoded by M. Long: October 2023.
</p>
<p>Wills, 1834-1846 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes were processed using minimal processing standards: Locality records were organized by broad record category (election records, fiduciary records, etc.) with minimal other arrangement. These records have not been flattened, foldered, mended, or separated by individual record type (like summons, appraisements, etc.).
</p>
<p>The remaining wills are still unprocessed.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Context for Record Type:  </title>In October 1776, entail was abolished, thereby prohibiting the automatic passing of estates through multiple
generations. On January 1, 1787, the English system of primogeniture ceased in Virginia. These two events
affected the content of probate records. Under primogeniture, Virginia wills may not always name the wife or the
eldest son of the testator. Their inheritance of real estate was set by law: the widow received her dower, or one
third share, for her lifetime and the eldest son, as heir at law, received the remaining two-thirds share unless
otherwise specified in the father’s will. After the Revolutionary War, when Virginia’s general inheritance law took
effect, all heirs of intestate estates inherited equally.</p>
<p>Individuals dying with a written will died testate. After the death of an individual, the deceased person’s will was
brought into court, where two of the subscribing witnesses swore that the document was genuine. After the will
was proved, the executor was bonded to carry out the settlement of the estate. The court then ordered the will
to be recorded. The executor’s bond was also filed with the court. If the witnesses to the will were dead or could
not be located, the will was lodged. These lodged wills were not recorded, but were kept by the court and the
estate was treated as an intestate estate.</p>
<p>Wills record the deceased's plan for how his or her estate was to be divided among his or her heirs following his or her death. Information commonly recorded in wills include the name of the deceased, also referred as the testator; names of heirs; a listing of real and personal property (including slaves) and how it was to be divided among the heirs; names of individuals who were to be the will's executors; the date will was written; and the date will was recorded at the court house.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Locality History:  </title> Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p> Greensville County (Va.) Wills, 1834-1959, includes wills and related probate records originating in the locality. A portion of the wills, 1834-1846, have undergone minimal processing. This has allowed for the documentation of specific record types and various trends found in this set of records. The remaining wills are completely unprocessed.
</p>
<p>Wills, 1834-1846 that have undergone minimal processing consist of the following:</p>
<list type="simple">
	<head>Record Types:</head>
<item>Wills</item> 
<item>Memoranda of wills</item>
<item>Wills rejected by probate</item>
</list>
<p>Significant materials include an 1834 will memorandum that includes the names of a large number of enslaved people.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged into the following series:
</p>
<list type="simple">
<item><emph render="bold">Series I: Minimally Processed Wills, 1834-1846,</emph> are loosely arranged chronologically.</item>
<item><emph render="bold">Series II: Unprocessed Wills, 1927-1959,</emph> are housed in boxes with other unprocessed court records for Greensville County.</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>A searchable database of indexed wills and administration records for Greensville County and fifty-two other Virginia counties and cities is available through the  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://lva-virginia.libguides.com/wills">"Wills and Estate Records Index"</extref> on the Library of Virginia website.</p>
<p>Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult  <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm">"A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."</extref> 
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Minimally Processed Wills, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1834-1846</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.45 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Loosely arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007843137">	Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Clerk; Commissioner of Revenue; Election; Fiduciary; Health and Medical; Jury; Justice of the Peace; Miscellaneous; Military and Pension; Overseers of the Poor; Property; Public Buildings; School; Sheriff; Treasurer; Wills,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1792-1870	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Unprocessed Wills, </emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1927-1959</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.45 cubic feet (1 box) </extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>Housed in boxes with other unprocessed court records for Greensville County.
</p>
</arrangement>

<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Barcode number 0007843104 ">	Miscellaneous Papers; Wills,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1903-1931; 1927-1959	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>