<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viuh00065">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8621" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU-H">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Health System::Claude Moore Health Sciences Library::Historical Collections//TEXT (US::ViU-H::viuh00065:: Von Frieling's Salve Collection//EN" "viuh00065.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Von Frieling's Salve Collection, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">circa 1500-1977, </date><date type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">bulk 1900-1932</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Von Frieling's Salve Collection<num type="collectionnumber">MS-65 </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2014 By the Rector and Visitors of
          the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Emily Bowden, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Von Frieling's Salve Collection, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">circa 1500-1977, </date><date type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">bulk 1900-1932 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <num type="Accession Number">MS-65 </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-hs-sm.png"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Historical Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Historical Collections, Claude Moore
        Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Von Frieling's Salve Collection, <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">circa 1500-1977, </unitdate><unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">bulk 1900-1932</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MS-65 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">1 box with the dimensions of 5.5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches, 1 folder with the dimensions of 8.5 inches by 14 inches, and 2 jars measuring 2 inches tall and 1.5 inches in diameter</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Languages">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language> and
        <language langcode="ger">German </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">University of Virginia</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>Some materials, including the Kräuter Atlas and the Gutenberg Museum Guide, may be subject to copyright restrictions. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Von Frieling's Salve Collection, Accession #MS-65,
          Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia,
          Charlottesville, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>This collection was donated to the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library at the University of Virginia in 2010 by Chris VonFrieling. Prior to the creation of this finding aid in 2014, two items from the collection were processed into the Historical Collections artifacts collection in 2012.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information </head>
      <p>This collection includes an untitled work that supposedly belonged to Dr. Albert Von Frieling, a physician living in Soltau, Germany, in the early 16th century. No additional information could be found related to Dr. Von Frieling’s life or medical practice. Documentation written by Edward Colman and George Von Frieling that accompanies the book describes its discovery in approximately 1902 on the Von Frieling estate in Soltau, Germany. Colman and G. Von Frieling write that the book, which included an ancient recipe for green butter salve, was found inside an iron box with several decaying, unreadable papers. Their record dates the book to 1512, but this date lacks additional authentication and should be considered unconfirmed.</p>
      <p>Much of the Von Frieling's Salve Collection pertains to the recipe for green butter salve, which supposedly was created by Dr. Albert Von Frieling in the 16th century. After the discovery of the untitled work on the estate in Soltau, Henry Von Frieling, a descendant of Dr. Albert Von Frieling, is said to have recreated the salve described by his ancestor. Heinrich (Henry) Von Frieling was born 21 September 1885 in Soltau, according to the inscription in the front of his notebook. He came to New York in the early 20th century, but little is know about his life, other than his business venture to market “Von Frieling’s Salve.” H. Von Frieling applied for a patent for the salve in 1911, and historical newspapers show that advertisements for Von Frieling’s Salve continued to run in several Iowa papers until at least 1931. An undated and unidentified newspaper clipping reports the filing of a bankruptcy petition for “Frieling Bros. (Henry’s Restaurant),” owned by "Henry V. and George V. Frieling" in the southern district, which possibly refers to the Southern District of New York.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection consists of 17 folders. In addition to the untitled book, designated the "Von Frieling Sammelband," the collection contains photocopies of the book and materials related to the 20th century version of Von Frieling’s green butter salve, also called Von Frieling’s plaster salve. These materials include documentation and packaging for the salve, patent paperwork, correspondence, and various items related to herbal medicine and early German printing, as well as two samples of the salve itself.</p>
      <p>The Von Frieling Sammelband is believed to have been owned by the Von Frieling family of Soltau, Germany. The book is a composite work in German with pages taken from at least three apparently separate works and sewn together into one bound volume. These texts include a work on the interpretation of dreams, another on the medicinal properties of various local waters, and other writings related to astrology and early medicine. In a description of the 20th century rediscovery of the Von Frieling Sammelband, the authors note that “this book contains quotations from philosophers of that period, notes upon the art of steel making and a formula for making a green butter salve that made Doctor Von Frieling famous as a man of healing power.” The book is bound in leather; the text is printed in Gothic-style German and includes small woodblock prints. Following the sections of printed text, the book includes an extensive section of handwritten notes, also in German, which appear to have been added by different hands and at various times up to the 1800s. Among the notes are several hand-drawn designs and sketches.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>Materials are arranged by approximate chronology.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Von Frieling Sammelband, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1500-1800s </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:1 [vault]</container>
          <physdesc>1 leather bound book, 4 inches x 6 inches </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Book is in poor condition; binding is very fragile and pages show substantial weather damage. </p></scopecontent>
        <separatedmaterial><head>Separated Materials Note</head><p>Item stored in the Historical Collections vault due to age and physical condition.</p></separatedmaterial>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Notebook of Heinrich (Henry) Von Frieling, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1900-1912 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          <physdesc></physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>The notebook contains undated writings in German possibly written by Heinrich Von Frieling, and a short “History of the Henry Von Frieling Plaster Salve” written in English by Edward Colman and George Von Frieling and dated March 1912. The notebook also includes a newspaper clipping of bankruptcy proceedings in the southern district (perhaps referring to New York) which lists the entity “Frieling Bros. (Henry’s Restaurant)” owned by Henry V. and George V. Frieling as filing a petition for bankruptcy.</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Two jars of Von Frieling's Salve, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1911-1930s </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:3 [artifacts collection]</container>
          <physdesc>Each jar measures 2 inches tall and 1.5 inches in diameter.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Instructions advise that the salve should be used "for cuts, boils, carbuncles, abscess and infection… for blood poisoning from shot wounds, snake, insect or animal bites and… for burns and scalds from water, grease, or acid."</p></scopecontent>
        <separatedmaterial><head>Separated Materials Note</head><p>Items catalogued and stored with the artifacts collection under artifacts01301.</p></separatedmaterial>      
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Image of two jars of Von Frieling's Salve, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          <physdesc></physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p></p></scopecontent>
      </c01>

      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Product information for Von Frieling's Salve, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1911-1930s </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          <physdesc>2 copies</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Includes "History" and "Directions" for the salve, written in English and German.</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Original packaging for Von Frieling's Salve, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1911-1930s </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          <physdesc>Cardboard box 1.5 inches x 1.5 inches x 2.75 inches</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p></p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>United States Patent Application No. 641.062, signed by Henry Von Frieling, <unitdate type="inclusive">1911 July 28 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
          <physdesc>1 original patent application, 2 photocopies of the application</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Petition to the US Patent Office regarding Henry Von Frieling's salve.</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Von Frieling’s Green Salve ingredients list and preparation directions, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
          <physdesc>1 page</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p></p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photocopies of pages from the Von Frieling Sammelband, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
          <physdesc>5 pages</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p></p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Henry Von Frieling, <unitdate type="inclusive">1912-1932 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
          <physdesc>6 pages</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Includes letters to Henry Von Frieling from E.A. Schmalz, Leo Kaulfuss, Thoralf Rosfjord, H. Koetter, Henry Isernhagen, and Ivan Clearwaters. Correspondence consists of testimonials and purchase requests for the Von Frieling salve. In English and German.</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>

      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound reproduction of the Von Frieling Sammelband, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:11</container>
          <physdesc></physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Photocopied contents of the Von Frieling Sammelband</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photocopies of pages from the Von Frieling Sammelband, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:12</container>
          <physdesc></physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p></p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>German cursive writing sample, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:13</container>
          <physdesc></physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Writing sample of two different types of German script</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kräuter Atlas of Johann Künzle, <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1952-1975 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:14</container>
          <physdesc>16 pages</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Cover description: "100 heilpflanzen in naturgetreuer, farbiger Darstellung, ausgewählt, von Kräuterpfarrer Johann Künzle” (100 medicinal plants in lifelike, colored representation selected by “herbs priest” Johann Künzle)</p>
          <p>The atlas includes illustrations and written descriptions of 100 medicinal herbs, in German. Johann Künzle (1857-1945) was a Swiss Catholic priest and botanist known as a “Kräuterpfarrer” (herbs priest) for his knowledge of herbal medicine. He drew and collected medicinal herbs and promoted alternative medicine remedies and practices.</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Museum Guide from the Gutenberg Museum of the City of Mainz, English Edition, <unitdate type="inclusive">1977 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:15</container>
          <physdesc>51 pages</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Short section on Early Printing in Germany on page 22</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Scenic postcards from Germany, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:16</container>
          <physdesc>2 postcards</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>Postcards depict Benediktinerkloster Ettal (Ettal Abbey, a Benedictine monastery in Ettal, Bavaria) and the city of Kufstein in Tyrol, Austria, with the Kaiser Mountains</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Donation List, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box:folder" type="box-folder">1:17</container>
          <physdesc>1 TD</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent><p>List of items that accompanied the Von Frieling donation</p></scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
