<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
    type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
    title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viuh00066">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU-H">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Health
      System::Claude Moore Health Sciences Library::Historical Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViU-H::viuh00066:: University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports//EN" "viuh00066.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports, <date
            era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970-2014</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort"> University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports <num
            type="collectionnumber">MS-66 </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2014 By the Rector and Visitors of
          the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Janet Pearson, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">2014</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1970-2014</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
          <num type="Accession Number">MS-66</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-hs-sm.png"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Historical Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Historical Collections, Claude Moore
        Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a"> University of Virginia School of Medicine
        Reports, <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1970-2014 </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MS-66 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">10 boxes measuring 5.5 inches x
        10 inches x 15.5 inches and 11 boxes measuring 5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches; total of 9.25
        linear feet </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">University of Virginia</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>No restrictions </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p> University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports, Accession #MS-66, Historical
          Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia,
          Charlottesville, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The documents in boxes 1-19, folder 7 arrived at the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
          in several installments from the School of Medicine prior to 2014. On December 2, 2014,
          Addeane Caelleigh, a Medical Education Case Writer at the School of Medicine, brought the
          materials in boxes 19, folder 8 through 21, folder 2 to Historical Collections.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>The collection consists of 104 folders of processed material. Series I contains annual
        reports of the School of Medicine from the 1970s and then biennial reports through the 1980s
        with a planning report that looks forward to 2000. The reports come from the various
        departments and divisions within the School of Medicine. Series II has only two documents
        concerning the development of biostatistics and epidemiology as well as a Family Medicine
        residency in Lynchburg. Series III includes documents on the methods taken to increase the
        number of minority medical students as well as minority faculty. One document concerns the
        entire university. Series IV has documents, reports, studies, questionnaire summaries, and
        data from self-studies. Self-studies were done for the Southern Association of Colleges and
        Schools, and in some cases those documents relate to the entire University with only
        sections that concern the School of Medicine. Other self-studies were done for the Liaison
        Committee on Medical Education (LCME) which represented the American Medical Association and
        the Association of American Medical Colleges. Documents in the collection are instructional
        in terms of how to prepare for the LCME site visits as well as documents submitted prior to
        the visits. Liaison Committee on Medical Education visits for reaccreditation occurred on
        October 11-15, 1998, October 8-11, 2006, and October 19-22, 2014. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The records are arranged in four series with the documents within each series arranged
        chronologically. The series are: <list type="simple">
          <item>Series I, School of Medicine Annual Reports and Biennial Reports, 1970-1990</item>
          <item>Series II, School of Medicine Proposals, 1977-1982</item>
          <item>Series III, School of Medicine Reports on Minority Affairs, 1984-1991</item>
          <item>Series IV, School of Medicine Self-Study Reports, 1974-2014</item>
        </list></p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: School of Medicine Annual Reports and Biennial Reports
              <unitdate>1970-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The annual reports contain individual reports from departments or divisions. The
            departmental reports include information about the faculty in terms of research,
            scholarly recognition of faculty, professional committees or offices held, publications,
            highlights or summary of the year, general considerations, changes in curriculum, and
            problem areas. </p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>School of Medicine Annual Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy,
              Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Clinical Pathology, Dermatology,
              Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurological Surgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and
              Gynecology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology,
              Physiology, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, and Urology. Internal Medicine was
              formally organized during the course of the year with the establishment of 12
              divisions: Biometrics, Cardiology, Clinical Pharmacology, Endocrinology and
              Metabolism, Epidemiology and Virology, Gastroenterology, Hematology, Infectious
              Diseases, Nephrology, Oncology, Pulmonary-Allergy, and Rheumatology. Ten medical
              students were dropped for academic deficiencies during 1969-1970. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">1971
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Internal
              Medicine, Medical Library, Microbiology, Neurology, Neurological Surgery, Obstetrics
              and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics,
              Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology,
              and Vivarium. No students were dropped for academic deficiencies. Special recruitment
              was done by the Admissions Committee and faculty who visited 13 colleges with
              predominantly black enrollment.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">1971-1972
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Internal
              Medicine, Medical Library, Microbiology, Neurosurgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and
              Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics,
              Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Student Health,
              Surgery, Urology, Vivarium, and Equal Opportunity Program. The report from the Equal
              Opportunity Program includes selection of new faculty and non-academic personnel of
              those underrepresented in the school. Specifically mentioned are women, black,
              Chicanos, Orientals, and Chinese.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Section I, Academic Affairs (Part I),
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1973-1975 </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology,
              Family Medicine, Internal Medicine, Health Sciences Library, and Microbiology. At the
              front of the report is the School of Medicine Annual Report, 1973-74 and 1974-75, Part
              II Academic Affairs , Section III Dean’s Summary and Recommendations. It states that
              due to new pressures and the need for better organization in the School of Medicine,
              and in response to University–wide programs, several tasks were completed by faculty.
              Some of these are included in the report including the identification and adoption of
              institutional goals, a report on plans and projections, a financial report to the
              President, and a preliminary policy report on promotions and tenure. The dean’s
              summary gives information on a variety of topics, but of note is the formation of the
              Department of Family Practice on July 1, 1975 and a Division of Dentistry in 1974, the
              completion of the new Health Sciences Library, an award toward the construction of a
              Primary Care Building, and an experimental or alternative curriculum for the School of
              Medicine.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Section I, Academic Affairs (Part II),
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1973-1975 </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Neurosurgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics,
              Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery,
              Psychiatry, Radiology, Student Health, Surgery, and Urology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>School of Medicine Annual Report, Section II, Equal Opportunity Programs,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1974-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The departments filled out reports addressing the selection of new faculty, the
              selection and promotion of non-academic personnel, and special efforts. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Section A, (Part I), <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1975-1976</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology,
              Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Health Sciences Library, and Microbiology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Department of Medicine, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1975 September 1 – 1976 August 31 </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Section A (Part II), <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1975-1976 </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Neurosurgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics,
              Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery,
              Psychiatry, Radiology, Student Health, Surgery, and Urology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Part C: Academic Planning, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1975 September 1 - 1976 September 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report includes a letter of request, summary of requests for faculty and
              space, and a one year extension of academic plan for the Departments of: Anatomy,
              Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology, Family
              Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and
              Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics,
              Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology,
              and Western State Hospital.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>

        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Dean’s Summary <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The Dean’s Summary includes Medical School Administration; Improving the Academic
              Environment for Students; Summary of Major Accomplishments in Instruction, Research,
              and Public Service; Summary of Major Modifications in Academic Programs, 1978-79;
              Major space considerations, 1978-79; Memorandum to Departments regarding Annual
              Report. Norman J. Knorr is the School of Medicine Dean.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Part III, (Book 1), <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Dentistry,
              Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurology, and Neurosurgery. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Part III, (Book 2), <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Obstetrics and Gynecology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics,
              Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology,
              and Roanoke.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">1977 September
                1 - 1978 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report includes a “Summary of Major Accomplishments in Instruction,
              Research, and Public Service” which highlights a few of the major accomplishments of
              the individual departments. Dean Norman Knorr mentions a major revision of the
              preclinical curriculum by the council on Medical Education and a new Division of
              Geriatrics under the leadership of Richard Lindsay with the anticipation of a special
              geriatric unit to be established at the Blue Ridge Sanatorium in the future. Currently
              there are established programs in epilepsy and outpatient Psychiatry at Blue Ridge.
              Another new Division is Geographic Medicine under the direction of Richard Guerrant.
              There is a report from the Office of Student Affairs and a break-down of SOM
              admissions.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Anatomy – Dentistry, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, and Dentistry. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Dermatology – Neurology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Dermatology, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, and Neurology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Neurosurgery – Plastic Surgery, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology,
              Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, and Plastic Surgery. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Psychiatry – Roanoke Program, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, Roanoke Program.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">1978 September
                1 - 1979 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> A memo inserted in front of the 1978-1979 Annual Report from Dean Norman Knorr,
              dated September 14, 1981, indicates that the School of Medicine Biennial Report
              (formerly Annual Report) is waived this year as the plan is to submit the Self-Study
              Report in its place. The 1978-1979 annual report includes a “Summary of Major
              Accomplishments in Teaching Programs, Research Programs, and Public Service
              Activities” and a report from the Office of Student Affairs. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Anatomy – Biomedical Engineering,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Biochemistry, and
              Biomedical Engineering.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Dermatology – Microbiology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Dermatology, Dentistry, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, and Microbiology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Neurology – Roanoke, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics,
              Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Radiology,
              Surgery, Urology, and Roanoke Program.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Annual Report, Pediatrics, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Pediatrics.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Summary, <unitdate type="inclusive">1981
                June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> This summary of the biennial report highlights a few of the accomplishments in
              teaching programs, training programs, clinical service programs, research programs,
              and public service activities. The School of Medicine did a self-study in preparation
              for the LCME accreditation site visit held in February 1982. The LCME conferred full
              accreditation of the program for 10 years. A new graduate program in Cell and
              Molecular Biology was established in 1982 and a number of new divisions were formed.
              New units opened at Blue Ridge Hospital and a Travelers Clinic and the Blue Ridge
              Poison Control Center were established at the University Hospital. UVa Medcial Center
              was designated a Level I Trauma Center in 1982. James W. Craig submitted a report from
              the Office of Student Affairs. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Anatomy – Family Medicine, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy,
              Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Comparative Medicine,
              Dermatology, and Family Medicine. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Internal Medicine, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Microbiology - Pathology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Microbiology, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology,
              Orthopaedics, Otolaryngology, and Pathology. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Pediatrics - Urology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Behavior Medicine and
              Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, and Urology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Curriculum Vitae, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The CVs are arranged alphabetically, but seem to be missing the beginning as the
              first name is Dickerson.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Anatomy – Biomedical Engineering,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy,
              Anesthesiology, Behavior Medicine and Psychiatry, Biochemistry, and Biomedical
              Engineering </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Comparative Medicine – Internal
              Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Comparative Medicine, Dentistry, Family Medicine, and Internal Medicine. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Microbiology - Pathology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Microbiology, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology,
              Orthopaedics, Otolaryngology, and Pathology. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Report, Pediatrics - Urology, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions:
              Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Radiology, Surgery, and
              Urology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Anesthesiology,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Robert M. Epstein, Chair of the Department of Anesthesiology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Behavioral Medicine &amp; Psychiatry, Volume I, (W.W. Spradlin, Chair), <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from W.W. Spradlin, Chair of the Department of Behavioral Medicine
              &amp; Psychiatry.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Behavioral Medicine &amp; Psychiatry, Volume II, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984
                July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from W.W. Spradlin, Chair of the Department of Behavioral Medicine
              &amp; Psychiatry which includes second-year course materials.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Anatomy &amp; Cell Biology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
              30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Anatomy &amp; Cell Biology prepared by
              Charles J. Flickinger.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Biochemistry, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department Biochemistry.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Biomedical Engineering, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
              30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Biomedical Engineering.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Central Electron
              Microscope Facility, <unitdate type="inclusive">1986 October</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The planning report is for 1988-1998 from Charles J. Flickinger regarding the
              Central Electron Microscope Facility.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Comparative Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Comparative Medicine.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Dentistry, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Byard S. Deputy, Chair of the Department of Dentistry and
              includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Dermatology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Dermatology and includes a planning report for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Fluorescent
              Activated Cell Sorter (FACS) Laboratory, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986
                June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The planning report is for the Fluorescent Activated Cell Sorter Laboratory for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Lymphocyte
              Culture Center, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:9</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The planning report is from John C. Herr for the Lymphocyte Culture Center for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:10</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Edward W. Hook, Chair of the Department of Medicine, and includes
              detailed reports from each of the 16 divisions of the Department with planning reports
              for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Microbiology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:11</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Microbiology and includes short term objectives
              for 1986-1988.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Neurological Surgery, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:12</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from John A. Jane of the Department of Neurosurgery and includes
              objectives for 1986-1988 by John A. Persing.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Neurology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from T. J. Johns, Chair of the Department of Neurology and includes a
              planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Neuroscience, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report states that the Department of Neuroscience was established in the SOM by
              the Board of Visitors in 1985. It includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Obstetrics and Gynecology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
              30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report for the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology includes a planning
              report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Ophthalmology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Brian P. Conway, Chair of the Department of Ophthalmology and
              includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
              30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report for Orthopaedic Surgery and Rehabilitation is dated 1982-1984.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Otolaryngology – Head and Neck Surgery, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986
                June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report for Otolaryngology – Head and Neck Surgery includes a planning report for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Pathology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Thomas W. Tillack, Chair of the Department of Pathology, and
              includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Pediatrics, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Robert M. Blizzard, Chair of the Department of Pediatrics, and
              includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Pharmacology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:9</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Pharmacology and includes a planning report for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Physiology, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:10</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Physiology and includes a planning report for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of
              Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
                30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:11</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from Gaylord S. Williams in Dr. Edgerton’s absence from the Department
              of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Protein and
              Nucleic Acid Research Facility, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June
              30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:12</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Protein and Nucleic Acid Research Facility and includes a
              planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Radiology,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:13</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from T. E. Keats, Chair of the Department of Radiology, and includes a
              planning report for 1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Surgery,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:14</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Surgery and includes a planning report for
              1988-1998.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Urology,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:15</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is from the Department of Urology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia Medical Center Biennial Evaluation and Long-Range
              Planning Report, 1984-1990, University of Virginia School of Medicine, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1985 January 18</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:16</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report includes accomplishments and shortfalls for the 1982-1984 bienniem.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation, 1986-1989, and Long-Range Planning
              Report, 1990-2000, <unitdate type="inclusive">1990 January 10</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:17</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report includes evaluation for 1986-1989.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: School of Medicine Proposals,
          <unitdate>1977-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>These papers are narrowly focused as opposed to the School of Medicine Annual/Biennial
            Reports. They are more proposals than reports.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Proposal to Establish a Program in Epidemiology and Biostatistics (Pratt
              Funds), <unitdate type="inclusive">1977 July 15</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report was prepared by Jules I. Levine, the director of the division of Health
              Services Research at the Medical Center. It proposed that a portion of the Pratt funds
              be used to improve capabilities in the fields of biostatistics and epidemiology.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Residency Program in Family Practice Lynchburg, Virginia, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1982 January</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Residency Review Committee for Family Practice approved the program with John H.
              Danby serving as the Program Director with Virginia Baptist Hospital being the parent
              hospital.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: School of Medicine Reports on Minority Affairs,
            <unitdate>1984-</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The documents mainly focus on increasing the number of minorities in medical school.
            One of the reports is university wide in its coverage.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>School of Medicine Summer Enrichment Program, 1984, Final Report, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1984 August 24</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The report was prepared by Wei Li Fang and Maurice Apprey. The course is a six-week
              program designed to provide minority students with the opportunity to experience the
              content, volume, and pace of the medical school curriculum.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> School of Medicine Summer Enrichment Program, 1985, Final Report, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1985 August 22</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The report was prepared by Wei Li Fang. The course is a program designed to provide
              minority and disadvantaged students with the opportunity to experience the content,
              volume, and pace of the medical school curriculum.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> An Audacious Faith: Report of the Task Force on Afro-African Affairs,
              University of Virginia, <unitdate type="inclusive">1987 June</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Maurey Apprey from the School of Medicine served on the task force which considered
              black students, faculty and staff at the University. A letter dated September 28,
              1987, from President Robert M. O’Neil is included.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> Strategies for Increasing Minority Representation in Medicine by Moses K.
              Woode and Kathleen Bodisch Lynch, Assisting Students Achieve Medical Degrees (ASAMD)
              Project, <unitdate type="inclusive">1988 February 25-27</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This paper was presented at the 16th Annual Meeting of the Sixteen Institutions
              Health Sciences Consortium in Norfolk, Virginia, February 25-27, 1988.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia School of Medicine Assisting Minorities Pursue
              Medical Education (AMPMED) Program, Supplemental Information for Robert Wood Johnson
              Foundation Site Visit, <unitdate type="inclusive">1988 March 25</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia School of Medicine Academic Enrichment Programs for
              Minority and Disadvantaged Students, 1984-1990, <unitdate type="inclusive"
              >1984-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Program Director: Moses K. Woode, Program Evaluator: Kathleen B. Lynch, Assistant
              Dean of Student Affairs: Maurice Apprey.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia School of Medicine Academic Enrichment Programs for
              Minority and Disadvantaged Students, 1984-1991, <unitdate type="inclusive"
              >1984-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:9</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Assistant Dean for Student Academic Support and Program Director: Moses K. Woode,
              Program Evaluator: Kathleen B. Lynch, Assistant Dean of Student Affairs: Maurice
              Apprey.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV: School of Medicine Self-Study Reports,
            <unitdate>1974-2014</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia Self-Study Summary Report, Edited by Elaine M.
              Hadden, <unitdate type="inclusive">1974 August 21</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is part of the reaccreditation process that is required every ten years
              by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. This report covers the entire
              university with only a part devoted to the School of Medicine.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> University of Virginia School of Medicine Summary of the Findings and
              Recommendations of the Institutional Self-Study Task Force, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1981-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Chair of the Steering Committee was Fritz E. Dreifuss. Also included is a
              Synopsis of Student Opinion.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> Report of the Survey of the University of Virginia School of Medicine By the
              Liaison Committee on Medical Education Representing the American Medical Association
              and the Association of American Medical Colleges, <unitdate type="inclusive">1982
                February 14-16</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Ad Hoc Survey Team recommended that the School of Medicine continue in full
              accreditation for a period of ten years and that a report be submitted to the Liaison
              committee on Medical Education (LCME) in five years to address issues of concern noted
              in the summary of this report.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle> Report University Self-Study Committee on Research and Externally-Funded
              Grants and Contracts for 1974-1984 with Recommendations for 1985-1995, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1985 March</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Medicine section was headed by Richard L. Guerrant.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia Self-Study Reports 1984-1986, Report of The
              Subcommittee on Professional Programs, Preliminary Draft, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1985 May</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Subcommittee member for the Medical School Benjamin C. Sturgill.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Report Self-Study Subcommittee on Graduate Programs, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">[1985?]</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The Subcommittee member for Basic Medical Sciences was Thomas W. Sturgill.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia Self-Study Reports, 1984-1986, Report of The Committee
              on the Faculty, Preliminary Draft, <unitdate type="inclusive">1985 June, 1986
              April</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The Committee member for the School of Medicine was John S. Davis, IV. The report
              was sent to Dean Norman J. Knorr, School of Medicine.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Inside UVA: “Self-study moves to review phase,” <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1985 August 1</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Report of the University Self-Study Committee on the Faculty, University of
              Virginia, <unitdate type="inclusive">1985 October, 1986 April</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The Committee member for the School of Medicine was John S. Davis, IV. The report
              was sent to Norman Knorr, School of Medicine.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia School of Medicine Draft Section of Self-Study Report
              on Minority Student Recruitment and Retention Efforts, <unitdate type="inclusive">1985
                December </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Norman J. Knorr from the School of Medicine is sent the report and asked to review
              the Draft. This report states that UVa as a “predominately white, southern institution
              has been trying for several years to achieve genuine heterogeneity by encouraging the
              admission of minority students, and particularly black students to every school of the
              University. Partly under the pressure of a 1978 court order, substantial steps have
              been taken towards meeting this goal and it is the purpose of this section of our
              report to evaluate our achievements to date.” There are two copies of the draft, one
              with changes written in.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia Self-Study Report, 1984-1986, the executive summary of
              Continuing Education, Institutes, and Other Outreach Activities, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">1986 March</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> A letter from Oscar A. Thorup to William H. Muller discusses the summary that is
              included.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Report of the Reaffirmation Committee Commission on Colleges, Southern
              Association of Colleges and Schools, University of Virginia, 20-23 April 1986,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">1986 April-May</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> The report is the draft report of the visit of the Southern Association of Colleges
              and Schools to the University. Also included in the folder is a memo from W. H.
              Muller, Vice-President for Health Affairs at the time, commenting on the draft
              primarily with the Medical Center in mind.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia School of Medicine, Summary of the Findings and
              Recommendations of the Institutional Self-Study Task Force, <unitdate type="inclusive"
                >1991 July 2</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Report of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, Charlottesville,
              Virginia, Prepared by an Ad Hoc Survey Team for the Liaison Committee on Medical
              Education (LCME) representing the Association of American Medical Colleges and the
              American Medical Association, <unitdate type="inclusive">1998 October 11-15</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The report is the final report for 1998, and includes a prior accreditation survey
              and progress reports.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>LCME guide to the Institutional Self-study, Liaison Committee on Medical
              Education, <unitdate type="inclusive">2004 July</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>For full accreditation surveys scheduled in 2005-2006. University of Virginia School
              of Medicine Institutional Self Study Re-accreditation 2006.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>LCME Functions and Structure of a Medical School, Standards for Accreditation
              of Medical Education Programs, <unitdate type="inclusive">2004 October
              11-15</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Survey Report Guide for 2005-2006 LCME Site Visits, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">2005 June</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:10</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Institutional Re-accreditation Project
              2005-2006. This document was reprinted with permission of the AAMC Secretariat of the
              LCME, 2005.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Guidelines for the Conduct of Accreditation Survey Visits, Liaison Committee
              on Medical Education 2005-2006,<unitdate type="inclusive">2005 July</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:11</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Re-accreditation Project 2005-2006. This
              document was reprinted with permission of the AAMC Secretariat of the LCME, 2005.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Rules of Procedure August 2005 edition (Revised February and June 2006),
                <unitdate type="inclusive">2006 June</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:12</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Re-accreditation Project 2005-2006. This
              document was reprinted with permission of the AAMC Secretariat of the LCME, 2005.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Background and Instructions for completing the LCME Medical Edcuation
              Database and Institutional Self-study Summary, <unitdate type="inclusive">[2006]
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:13</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>For LCME full accreditation surveys scheduled in the 2006-2007 academic year.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia School of Medicine LCME Institutional Self Study
              Summary Report, <unitdate type="inclusive">2006 October 8-11</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Medical Education Database Sections I-V, University of Virginia School of
              Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">2006 October 8-11 </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:15</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The sections are: I. Institutional Setting, II. Educational Program for the M.D.
              Degree, III. Medical Students, IV. Faculty, V. Educational Resources.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Appendix of Supporting Documents, University of Virginia School of Medicine,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">2006 October 8-11</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The sections are: I. Institutional Setting (Appendix), II. Educational Program for
              the M.D. Degree, (Appendix), III. Medical Students, (Appendix), IV. Faculty,
              (Appendix), V. Educational Resources, (Appendix).</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Required Course and Clerkship Forms (Years One through Four), University of
              Virginia School of Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">2006 October 8-11</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Medical Student Analysis and Graduation Questionnaire Results University of
              Virginia School of Medicine for the Liaison Committee on Medical Education, <unitdate
                type="inclusive">2006 October 8-11</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Role of Students in the Accreditation of Medical Education Programs in
              the U.S. and Canada, Liaison Committee on Medical Education Committee on the
              Accreditation of Canadian Medical Schools, <unitdate type="inclusive">2011
              July</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Downloaded from LCME website and reprinted, with permission, for use by the
              University of Virginia School of Medicine, November 2001.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>University of Virginia School of Medicine LCME Self-Study Summary Report,
                <unitdate type="inclusive">2014 October 19-22</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Required Course and Clerkship forms (Years One through Four) University of
              Virginia School of Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">2014 October 19-22</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:6 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Medical Student Analysis and Graduation Questionnaire Results for the Liaison
              Committee on Medical Education, <unitdate type="inclusive">2014 October
              19-22</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Medical Education Database Sections I-V University of Virginia School of
              Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive">2014 October 19-22</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>LCME Data Collection Instrument for Full Accreditation Academic Year 2014-2015;
              Section I. Institutional Setting, II. Educational Program for the M.D. Degree, III.
              Medical Students, IV. Faculty, V. Educational Resources.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
