<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viuh00037">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU-H">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Health
      System::Claude Moore Health Sciences Library::Historical Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViU-H::viuh00037:: University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection,
      1836-1943)//EN" "viuh00037.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook
          Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1943</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Student Notebook Collection <num type="collectionnumber">MS-37
          </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of
          the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Paper, created by Janet Pearson, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6/1//2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook
        Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1943</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
          <num type="Accession Number">MS-37 </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-hs-sm.png"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Historical Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Historical Collections, Claude Moore
        Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">University of Virginia School of Medicine
        Student Notebook Collection <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f"
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MS-37 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">17 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 7.2
        feet, 121 items </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Historical Collections </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>There are no restrictions. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection, Accession #MS-37,
          Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia,
          Charlottesville, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>The notebooks were donated by various people including Dr. Malcolm Foote Sher, Dr. Porter
          B. Echols, Jr., the Dr. Armistead P. Booker family, Dr. Weaver, Ms. Roberta Senechal,
          Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III, Mr. James Skalnik, and James D. Webb. Several notebooks were
          purchased. </p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information </head>
      <p>The student notebooks contain the notes that medical students took in their classes or
        laboratories at the University of Virginia. Some of the notebooks belonged to men who would
        become faculty members at UVa. Those include Armistead Page Booker who was Clinical
        Instructor in Pediatrics in 1947 and retired from his position of Associate Professor in
        1985; William Beverly Towles who became an instructor in anatomy in the 1872-73 session and
        became Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica, serving in that position until his death in
        1893; Charles Bruce Morton who is listed as the Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology
        in the "University of Virginia Record" for 1944-45 and was last listed in the "University of
        Virginia School of Medicine Record" for 1969-70; and Oscar Swineford was listed as an
        instructor in Medicine in the "University of Virginia Record" of March 15, 1928 and was last
        listed as a Professor of Internal Medicine in the 1966-67 "University of Virginia Record." </p>
      <p>Many of the students included the names of their professors and instructors and those
        include John Staige Davis, James L. Cabell, John P. Emmet, Henry Howard, Socrates Maupin,
        Albert H. Tuttle, Stephen Hurt Watts, John Henry Neff, William Hall Goodwin, Lawrence T.
        Royster, Allen F. Voshell, E. Wood, John Campbell Hortenstine, Henry Bearden Mulholland,
        Edwin Partridge Lehman, William Henry Parker, William Roland Hill, Charles Bruce Morton,
        William Edward Bray, Kenneth Boyd Grim, Samuel Alexander Vest, Edgar Wilson Kirby, Bruno
        Barelare, Tiffany Johns Williams, John McIntire Nokes, William Wirt Waddell, McLemore
        Birdsong, William Gayle Crutchfield, Everett Cato Drash, Edwin Webster Shearburn, Byrd
        Stuart Leavell, William Maryon Moir, David Cole Wilson, Thomas Shepherd Englar, Byrd Stuart
        Leavell, Oscar Swineford, Staige Davis Blackford, John Osborne McNeel, James Alexander
        Waddell, Dudley Crofford Smith, Fletcher Drummond Woodward, Vincent William Archer, George
        Cooper, Eugene Markley Landis, George McLean Lawson, Claude C. Coleman, Theodore Hough,
        William Douglas Macon, William Edward Brown, and Leroy Adelbert Calkins. </p>
      <p>In our rare book collection there are other items of interest related to the student
        notebooks. These include the <title render="italic">Syllabus of the Lectures on Medical
          Jurisprudence and on the Treatment of Poisoning and Suspended Animation, Delivered in the
          University of Virginia</title>, by Robley Dunglison and printed in 1827 as well as volumes
        related to anatomy by William Beverley Towles. Towles' works are <title render="italic"
          >Notes on Anatomy</title> printed in 1886, <title render="italic">Anatomy Notes</title>
        published in 1890, <title render="italic">Notes on Anatomy</title> published in 1893, and
          <title render="italic">Descriptive Anatomy</title> published in 1898 and 1904. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>The notebooks range from 1836-1943 and include notes taken in classes for anatomy, surgery,
        physiology, gynecology, midwifery, chemistry, materia medica, preventive medicine, practice
        of medicine, ENT, bacteriology, jurisprudence, pharmacy, organic chemistry, pathology,
        psychobiology, internal medicine, toxicology, clinical diagnosis, histology, biology,
        syphilology, embryology, heart disease, urology, physical diagnosis, dermatology,
        pediatrics, orthopedics, Roentgenology, edpidemiology, nervous system, case teaching, and
        insanity. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The first 13 boxes and Box 14 through folder 5 are arranged chronologically. From Box 14,
        folder 6 the arrangement is in the order received. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Notes on Midwifery <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1840-1841 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken at the University of Virginia by Alexander M. Campbell from Dr.
            Howards' lectures, Session of 1840 and 41. Included are directions for purifying gold,
            silver solder, gold solder, stannate, flux, and enamels. According to the "Catalogue of
            the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," A. M. Campbell, from Amherst,
            Va., attended UVA in 1840-41 in the schools of Anatomy and Surgery. </p>
          <p>Professor: Henry Howard (Professor of Physiology, Medicine, Obstetrics, and Medical
            Jurisprudence).</p>
          <p>Textbook: Alfred Velpeau, Translated from the French with notes by Charles D. Meigs.
              <title render="italic">An Elementary Treatise on Midwifery, or, Principles of Tokology
              and Embryology</title> (Philadelphia: Grigg &amp; Elliot, 1838). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures of Professors J[ames] L. Cabell, [Henry] Howard,
            [John S.] Davis and [Socrates] Maupin <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1854-1855 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by James Sandford, M.D. from Pattonsburg, Virginia. Accounts
            related to medical visits are also included. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers
            and Students of the University of Virginia," James Sandford attended UVA during the
            1854-55 session. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy. </p>
          <p>Professors: James L. Cabell (Professor of Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery),
            Henry Howard (Professor of Medicine), John S. Davis (Lecturer on Anatomy, Materia Medica
            and Therapeutics), and S. Maupin (Professor of Chemistry)</p>
          <p>Textbooks: Professor Cabell: James L. Cabell, <title render="italic">Syllabus of
              Lectures on Comparative Anatomy and Physiology</title> (Charlottesville, University of
            Virginia: McKennie &amp; Son, 1853) ; William Benjamin Carpenter, <title render="italic"
              >Elements of Physiology: Including Physiological Anatomy</title> (Philadelphia:
            Blanchard and Lea, 1851) ; William Senhouse Kirkes, assisted by James Paget, <title
              render="italic">Manual of Physiology</title> (Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1849) ;
            Robert Druitt, <title render="italic">The Principles and Practice of Modern
              Surgery</title> (Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1853). Professor Howard: Henry
            Howard, <title render="italic">Outlines of Medical Jurisprudence</title>
            (Charlottesville, Virginia: Noel, 1845) ; Theodoric Romeyn Beck and John B. Beck, <title
              render="italic">Elements of Medical Jurisprudence</title> (Philadelphia: Thomas,
            Cowperthwait, 1838) Or Alfred Swaine Taylor, <title render="italic">Medical
              Jurisprudence</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1853) ; Alfred Velpeau,
            Translated from the French with notes by Charles D. Meigs, <title render="italic">A
              Complete Treatise on Midwifery: or, the Theory and Practice of Tokology: including
              Diseases of Pregnancy, Labor, and the Puerperal State</title> (Philadelphia: Lindsay
            and Blakiston, 1852) ; George B. Wood, <title render="italic">A Treatise on the Practice
              of Medicine</title> (Philadelphia: Lippincott, Grambo, and Co., 1855). Professor
            Davis: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard), <title render="italic">A System of
              Human Anatomy, General and Special</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1852) ;
            Robley Dunglison, <title render="italic">General Therapeutics and Materia Medica:
              Adapted for a Medical Text-book</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea,
            1853).Professor Maupin: George Fownes, <title render="italic">Rudimentary Chemistry for
              the Use of Beginners</title> (London: 1854) ; Edward Turner, <title render="italic"
              >Elements of Chemistry: including the History of the Imponderables and the Inorganic
              Chemistry</title> (Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait &amp; Co., 1846) for reference ;
            Edward Graham, <title render="italic">Elements of Inorganic Chemistry : including the
              Applications of the Science in the Arts</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea,
            1858) for reference ; Victor Regnault, <title render="italic">Elements of Chemistry :
              for the Use of Colleges, Academies, and Schools</title> (translated from the French by
            T. Forrest Betton, and edited with notes by James C. Booth and William L. Faber)
            (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1856) for reference ; Frederick A. Abel and C. L.
            Bloxam, <title render="italic">Handbook of Chemistry, Theoretical, Practical and
              Technical</title> (London: J. Churchill, 1854) for reference. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Syllabuses on Chemistry by Dr. J. A. Templeton, M.D. <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854-1855 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of
            Virginia," James A. Templeton from Augusta, Virginia, attended UVA during the 1854-55
            session. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy. </p>
          <p>Professor: S. Maupin (Professor of Chemistry) </p>
          <p> Textbooks: George Fownes, <title render="italic">Rudimentary Chemistry for the Use of
              Beginners</title> (London: 1854) ; Edward Turner, <title render="italic">Elements of
              Chemistry: including the History of the Imponderables and the Inorganic
              Chemistry</title> (Philadelphia: Thomas, Cowperthwait &amp; Co., 1846) for reference ;
            Edward Graham, <title render="italic">Elements of Inorganic Chemistry : including the
              Applications of the Science in the Arts</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea,
            1858) for reference ; Victor Regnault, <title render="italic">Elements of Chemistry :
              for the Use of Colleges, Academies, and Schools</title> (translated from the French by
            T. Forrest Betton, and edited with notes by James C. Booth and William L. Faber)
            (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1856) for reference ; Frederick A. Abel and C. L.
            Bloxam, <title render="italic">Handbook of Chemistry, Theoretical, Practical and
              Technical</title> (London: J. Churchill, 1854) for reference. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1855-1856 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones, a resident of Amherst County, Virginia,
            born in Fluvanna County, Virginia. Jones, has made drawings of Jno. S. Davis, Jas. L.
            Cabell, Henry Howard, and S[ocrates] Maupin. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy. </p>
          <p>Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Physiology and Surgery).</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John C. Dalton, Jr., <title render="italic">A Treatise on Human Physiology;
              Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine</title> (Philadelphia:
            Blanchard and Lea, 1859) ; Druitt, <title render="italic">The Principles and Practice of
              Modern Surgery </title>(Philadelphia: Lea and Blanchard, 1853). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology lectures by Dr. J[ames] L. Cabbell [Cabell]
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 November 14 - 1868 April
              16 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by William B. Towles from Cumberland, Virginia. According to the
            "Catalogue of the University of Virginia, 1868-69," William Beverly Towles received his
            MD degree in 1869. Dr. Towles, was a distinguished anatomist. He entered the University
            of Virginia as a student of medicine in 1867. In 1872 he was elected Demonstrator of
            Anatomy, and, upon the death of Dr. John Staige Davis in 1885, succeeded him as
            Professor of Anatomy. He worked for the University of Virginia until he died on
            September 15, 1893.</p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry and Pharmacy, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy
            and Materia Medica.</p>
          <p> Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Physiology and Surgery). </p>
          <p> Textbook: John C. Dalton, Jr., <title render="italic">A Treatise on Human Physiology;
              Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine</title> (Philadelphia:
            Blanchard and Lea, 1867).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: University of Virginia Materia Medica lectures by Dr. [John
            Staige] Davis <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868-1869
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. M. Hill from Bastrop, Texas. Hill lists a roll of the
            medical class at UVa for the 1868-69 session, including Walter Reed. Hill has 44 names
            written down with an additional 3 who took only one medical course. According to the
            "Catalogue of the University of Virginia, 1968-69," Augustus Middleton Hill was a
            student during the 1968-69 session. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry and Pharmacy, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy
            and Materia Medica. </p>
          <p>Professor: John Staige Davis (Professor of Anatomy, Materia Medica and Botany).</p>
          <p> Textbook: George B. Wood, <title render="italic">A Treatise on Therapeutics, and
              Pharmacology, or Materia Medica</title> (Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott &amp; Co.,
            1868). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Notes on the Practice of Medicine by T. B. Pugh, Session
            1873-74, University of Virginia <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
              >1873-1874 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken at the University of Virginia by T. B. Pugh from Napoleonville,
            Louisiana, Woodlawn Plantation. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students
            of the University of Virginia," Thomas Bryan Pugh was a student during the 1973-74
            session. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry (General and Industrial) and Pharmacy, Medicine, Physiology
            and Surgery, and Anatomy and Materia Medica. </p>
          <p>Professor: James F. Harrison (Professor of Medical Jurisprudence, Obstetrics and
            Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p>Textbooks: Austin Flint, <title render="italic">A Treatise on the Principles and
              Practice of Medicine; Designed for the Use of Practitioners and Students of
              Medicine</title> (Philadelphia: H. C. Lea, 1873) ; Henry Hartshorne, <title
              render="italic">Essentials of the Principles and Practice of Medicine : a Handbook for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1874). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Physiology and Surgery by Professor Cabell.
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873 October - 1874 January
              15 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-008 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007.</p>
          <p>Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and
            Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John C. Dalton, Jr., <title render="italic">A Treatise on Human Physiology;
              Designed for the Use of Students and Practitioners of Medicine</title> (Philadelphia:
            Blanchard and Lea, 1871) ; Thomas Henry Huxley, "The Elements of Physiology," <title
              render="italic">The Galaxy</title> (Volume 5, Issue 5, May 1868), 656-657 ; John Z.
            Laurence assisted by Robert C. Moon, <title render="italic">A Handy-Book of Ophthalmic
              Surgery for the Use of Practitioners</title> (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1869) ; John
            Ashurst, The Principles and Practice of Surgery (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1871). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Materia Medica, Volume I <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873 October 1 - 1874
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007.</p>
          <p>Professor: John Staige Davis (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard),<title render="italic"> A System
              of Human Anatomy, General and Special</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1868)
            ; George B. Wood, <title render="italic">A Treatise on Therapeutics, and Pharmacology,
              or Materia Medica</title> (Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott &amp; Co., 1868). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Chemistry Lectures of Thomas Bryan Pugh <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873 October 3 - 1874
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007. </p>
          <p>Professor: J. W. Mallet (Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy)</p>
          <p> Textbook: George Fownes, <title render="italic">A Manual of Elementary Chemistry,
              Theoretical and Practical</title> (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1869) </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Jurisprudence and Obstetrics by Prof [James F.]
            Harrison <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873-1874
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook and unbound pages </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007. The unbound pages contain exercises in English and Greek. </p>
          <p>Professor: James F. Harrison (Professor of Medical Jurisprudence, Obstetrics and
            Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Alfred Swaine Taylor, <title render="italic">A Manual of Medical
              Jurisprudence: with Notes and References to American Decisions</title> by Clement B.
            Penrose (Philadelphia: Henry C. Lea, 1866) ; William Leishman, <title render="italic">A
              System of Midwifery, Including the Diseases of Pregnancy and the Puerperal
              State</title> (Philadelphia, H. C. Lea, 1875). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Pharmacy <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1873-1874 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007. </p>
          <p>Professor: J. W. Mallet (Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy)</p>
          <p> Textbook: Edward Parrish, <title render="italic">An Introduction to Practical
              Pharmacy: Designed as a Text-book for the Student, and as a Guide to the Physician and
              Pharmaceutist</title> (Philadelphia, Blanchard and Lea, 1856). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Organic Chemistry <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873-1874 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook bound with copied lecture notes. </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by T. B. Pugh. For more information on Pugh see Box-folder
            001-007. </p>
          <p>Professor: J. W. Mallet (Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1883 October 5 - 1884 April 18 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by O. Nalle. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and
            Students of the University of Virginia," Orville Nalle, from Culpeper, Virginia,
            graduated with an MD degree in 1884. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry, Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery, and Medicine</p>
          <p>Professor: John Staige Davis (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Erasmus Wilson (edited by Paul B. Goddard), <title render="italic">A System
              of Human Anatomy, General and Special</title> (Philadelphia: Blanchard and Lea, 1868)
            Or Henry Gray, <title render="italic">Anatomy, Descriptive and Surgical</title>
            (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea's Son &amp; Co., 1883) ; Robert Farquharson, <title
              render="italic">A Guide to Therapeutics and Materia Medica</title> (Philadelphia:
            Henry C. Lea's Son, 1882) Or William Biddle, The Therapeutics of Gynecology and
            Obstetrics, Comprising the Medical, Dietetic, and Hygienic Treatment of Diseases of
            Women (Philadelphia, Brinton, 1881) Or Roberts Bartholow, <title render="italic">A
              Practical Treatise on Materia Medica and Therapeutics</title> (New York : Appleton,
            1879). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Notes on Surgery and Material Medica, Book No. 2 <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1884 February 18 - 1884 May 30 and 1885
              January 13 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook and 16 unbound pages </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by O. Nalle. For more information on Nalle see Box-folder
            002-006. The surgery lectures were given by Professor [James L.] Cabell. The unbound
            pages contain information about nerves. </p>
          <p>Professor: James L. Cabell (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John Call Dalton, <title render="italic">A Treatise on Human
              Physiology</title> (Philadelphia: H. C. Lea's Son &amp; Co., 1882) Or Gerald F. Yeo, A
            Manual of Physiology : <title render="italic">A Text-book for Students of
              Medicine</title> (Philadelphia: Blakiston, 1883) ; George Wilson, <title
              render="italic">A Handbook of Hygiene and Sanitary Science</title> (Philadelphia, P.
            Blakiston, son &amp; co., 1884) ; Horace Green, "Pathology and Treatment of Croup,"
              <title render="italic">The United States Democratic Review</title>, vol. 23, issue 125
            (Nov 1848) ; John Ashurst, <title render="italic">The Principles and Practice of
              Surgery</title> (Philadelphia, H.C. Lea, 1882) ; Thomas Edward Satterthwaite, <title
              render="italic">A Manual of Histology</title> (New York, Wood, 1882) Or Edward E.
            Klein, <title render="italic">Elements of Histology</title> (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers,
            1898); A. L. Ranney, <title render="italic">A Practical Treatise on Surgical
              Diagnosis</title> (New York: Wood, 1884). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Obstetrics, etc. <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1889 October 24 - 1890 February 1 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and
            Students of the University of Virginia," R. Edmond Dixon, from Bristol, Tennessee,
            attended the 1889-90 and 1890-91 sessions and had an A.B. from King College,
            Tennessee.</p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry (General and Industrial), Anatomy and Materia Medica,
            Physiology and Surgery, and Medicine </p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: William S. Playfair, <title render="italic">A Treatise on the Science and
              Practice of Midwifery</title> (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers &amp; Co., 1893) ; Arthur H.
            N. Lewers, <title render="italic">A Practical Textbook of the Diseases of Women</title>
            (Philadelphia: P. Blakiston Son &amp; Co., 1890). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume I) <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890 February 4-April 10
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001. </p>
          <p>Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, <title render="italic">A Text-book of Medicine for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (New York : D. Appleton and Company, 1887) ; R. C.
            M. Page, <title render="italic">A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis : of Diseases of the
              Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism</title> (New York : Vail,
            1889). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume II) <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890 April 11-29
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-003 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, <title render="italic">A Text-book of Medicine for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (New York : D. Appleton and Company, 1887) ; R. C.
            M. Page, <title render="italic">A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis : of Diseases of the
              Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism</title> (New York : Vail,
            1889). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part I, volume III) <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890 April 29-May 8
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-004 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by [R. E. Dixon].For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, <title render="italic">A Text-book of Medicine for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (New York : D. Appleton and Company, 1887) ; R. C.
            M. Page, <title render="italic">A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis : of Diseases of the
              Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism</title> (New York : Vail,
            1889). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part II, volume I) <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 February 3-April 4
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon.For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, <title render="italic">A Text-book of Medicine for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (New York : D. Appleton and Company, 1887) ; R. C.
            M. Page, <title render="italic">A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis : of Diseases of the
              Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism</title> (New York : Vail,
            1889). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine (Part II, volume II) <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 April 16-June 11
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: Adolf von Strumpell, <title render="italic">A Text-book of Medicine for
              Students and Practitioners</title> (New York : D. Appleton and Company, 1887) ; R. C.
            M. Page, <title render="italic">A Handbook of Physical Diagnosis : of Diseases of the
              Organs of Respiration and Heart, and of Aortic Aneurism</title> (New York : Vail,
            1889). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica, Number I <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 January 2-May 5 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William B. Towles (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: J. Mitchell Bruce, <title render="italic">Materia Medica and Therapeutics:
              An Introduction to the Rational Treatment of Disease</title> (Philadelphia: Lea Bros,
            1891). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica, Number II <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 May 15-June 9 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William B. Towles (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: J. Mitchell Bruce, <title render="italic">Materia Medica and Therapeutics:
              An Introduction to the Rational Treatment of Disease</title> (Philadelphia: Lea Bros,
            1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica, [Number III] <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 June 9-19 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William B. Towles (Professor of Anatomy and Materia Medica)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: J. Mitchell Bruce, <title render="italic">Materia Medica and Therapeutics:
              An Introduction to the Rational Treatment of Disease</title> (Philadelphia: Lea Bros,
            1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pathology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1890 December 18-1891 March 11 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-004 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by [R. E. Dixon]. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: William C. Dabney (Professor of Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine)</p>
          <p> Textbook: Horace Green, "Pathology and Treatment of Croup," <title render="italic">The
              United States Democratic Review</title>, vol. 23, issue 125 (Nov 1848).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume I] <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 April 4-22 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-005 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John B. Roberts, <title render="italic">A Manual of Modern Surgery: An
              Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present
              Time</title> (Philadelphia, Lea brothers &amp; co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler,<title
              render="italic"> A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis</title>
            Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood,
            1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, <title render="italic">Principles of Surgery</title>
            (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume II] <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 April 22-May 7 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-006 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John B. Roberts, <title render="italic">A Manual of Modern Surgery: An
              Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present
              Time</title> (Philadelphia, Lea brothers &amp; co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler,<title
              render="italic"> A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis</title>
            Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood,
            1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, <title render="italic">Principles of Surgery</title>
            (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, [Volume III] <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 May 9-25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-007 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by [R. E. Dixon]. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John B. Roberts, <title render="italic">A Manual of Modern Surgery: An
              Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present
              Time</title> (Philadelphia, Lea brothers &amp; co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler,<title
              render="italic"> A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis</title>
            Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood,
            1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, <title render="italic">Principles of Surgery</title>
            (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, Volume IV <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 May 27-June 10 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-008 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John B. Roberts, <title render="italic">A Manual of Modern Surgery: An
              Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present
              Time</title> (Philadelphia, Lea brothers &amp; co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler,<title
              render="italic"> A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis</title>
            Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood,
            1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, <title render="italic">Principles of Surgery</title>
            (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, Volume VI <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1891 June 22-23 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-009` </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by R. E. Dixon. For more information about Dixon see Box-folder
            003-001.</p>
          <p> Professor: Paul B. Barringer (Professor of Physiology and Surgery)</p>
          <p> Textbooks: John B. Roberts, <title render="italic">A Manual of Modern Surgery: An
              Exposition of the Accepted Doctrines and Approved Operative Procedures of the Present
              Time</title> (Philadelphia, Lea brothers &amp; co., 1890); Ernst Ziegler,<title
              render="italic"> A Text-book of Pathological Anatomy and Pathogenesis</title>
            Translated and Edited for English Students by Donald MacAlister (New York: Wood,
            1883-1887); Nicholas Senn, <title render="italic">Principles of Surgery</title>
            (Philadelphia: F. A. Davis, 1891).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Histology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1892 September 19-December 5 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color, also bound with copied lecture notes.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by W. Levi Old from Bennett's Creek, Virginia. He had a B.A. from
            Randolph-Macon College, Virginia. He was a physician and surgeon in London Bridge,
            Virginia. He served in the Spanish-American War as a major in the Virginia Volunteer
            Unit Medical Corps. He was a charter member of the American College of Surgeons, and he
            worked for many years at St. Vincent's Hospital in Norfolk. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Physiology and Surgery, Anatomy and Materia Medica, Practice of
            Medicine, Chemistry, and Biology and Agriculture</p>
          <p>Professor: Albert H. Tuttle (Professor of Biology)</p>
          <p> Textbook: Edward E. Klein, <title render="italic">Elements of Histology</title>
            (Philadelphia: Lea Brothers, 1898). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Biology B, Botany, Volume I <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 September 25-1917 May 16 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color, also bound with copied lecture notes.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. According to the "University of Virginia
            Record Catalogue," Charles Bruce Morton received his MD degree on June 13, 1922. He also
            received the B.S. degree from the University of Virginia in 1920. In 1927 Dr. Morton was
            appointed Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology at the University of Virginia
            School of Medicine and promoted to full professorship in 1936. During the academic year
            1953-54, he served as Acting Chairman of the Department of Surgery. He received the
            University of Virginia's first award of the John Horsley Memorial Prize for Research in
            Surgery in 1927 and the President and Board of Visitors Sigma Xi Research Prize in 1928.
            Dr. Morton was a member of the Executive Committee of the University of Virginia
            Hospital from 1935 to 1954. He has been an Attending Surgeon and Gynecologist at the
            University of Virginia Hospital, and an Attending Surgeon on the courtesy staff of
            Martha Jefferson Hospital, 1927.</p>
          <p> In addition to his teaching and surgical practice, Dr. Morton has been active in a
            number of professional organizations, in which he has held important posts, and he has
            contributed over seventy articles to medical and surgical publications. His society
            membership include: International Society of Surgery, American Surgical Association,
            American College of Surgeons, American Medical Association, Southern Surgical
            Association (Vice President, 1946), Southeastern Surgical Congress, Eastern Surgical
            Society (President, 1957), Southern Society of Clinical Surgeons (President, 1946),
            Virginia Surgical Society (President, 1955), and Medical Society of Virginia. </p>
          <p>Professors: Ivey Forman Lewis (Miller Professor of Biology and Agriculture) William
            Allison Kepner (Associate Professor of Biology) </p>
          <p>Class: C. B. Morton took this class when he was an undergraduate student. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Histology, Embryology, Pathology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1920 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. See Box-folder 005-002 for additional
            information about Morton. </p>
          <p>Professor: Harvey Ernest Jordan (Professor of Histology and Embryology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lab Manual - Histology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1918-1919 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-004 </container>
          <physdesc>notebook with A notes </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. See Box-folder 005-002 for additional
            information about Morton. </p>
          <p>Professor: Harvey Ernest Jordan (Professor of Histology and Embryology)</p>
          <p> Textbook: Lab. Manual - Histology. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery and Urology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1920 September 20-1921 March 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. See Box-folder 005-002 for additional
            information about Morton. </p>
          <p>Professors: Stephen Hurt Watts (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology) and John Henry
            Neff (Associate Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery, Volume VI <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1920 Septmeber 22-1921 May 16 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Bruce Morton. See Box-folder 005-002 for additional
            information about Morton. </p>
          <p>Professor: William Hall Goodwin (Associate Professor of Surgery and Gynecology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Histology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1923 September 19 - 1924 May 29 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. According to the "University of Virginia
            Record," Albert Brown Dickey graduated with his MD degree June 1927. Dickey was from
            Louisiana and was a Medical Director and Superintendent of the State Tuberculosis
            Hospital in Madisonville, Kentucky. He also served on the consultant staff of Hopkins
            County Hospital in Madisonville. </p>
          <p>Professor: Harvey Ernest Jordan (Professor of Histology and Embryology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Chemistry <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1924 January-May 12 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Theodore Hough (Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), John Seward
            Lawrence (Associate Professor of Biochemistry), and Bert Barnet Hershenson (Instructor
            of Physiology and Biochemistry). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, I] Eye, Ear, Nose <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926 September 21 - 1927 March
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Unknown. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, II] Nervous Diseases and Legal
            Medicine <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926 September 21-1927
              May 3 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Unknown. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: [General Medical Studies, III] <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1926] October 5 - [1927] May 21 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p> Professors: Unknown. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis, Physiology, Pathology <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1924] January 12 - [1925] June 2
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Instructor of Medicine), and James Edwin Wood (Instructor of Medicine). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica and Pharmacology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1922] september 22 - [1925] June 3
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professor: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1924] September 24 - [1925] April 17 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Theodore Hough (Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), Bert Barnet
            Hershenson (Assistant Professor of Physiology and Biochemistry), and Robert Battaille
            Hiden (Instructor of Physiology and Biochemistry). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Gynecology and Surgical Pathology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1925] April 19 - [1926] March 9 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professor: Leroy Adelbert Calkins (Professor of Obstetrics and Genecology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Obstetrics <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1925] September 21 - [1926] April 1 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, 1 TD reprint, 1 booklet </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. Slipped in the notebook is a 1927 booklet entitled "Physicians' Pocket
            Reference to the International List of Causes of Death," as well as a 1954 reprint from
              <title render="italic">Current Researches in Anesthesia &amp; Analgesia</title>. </p>
          <p>Professor: Leroy Adelbert Calkins (Professor of Obstetrics and Genecology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Urology and Orthopedics <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1925] September 21 - [1926] May 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">008-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Allen Fiske Voshell (Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery) and John
            Henry Neff (Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1925] September 23 - [1926] May 18 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">008-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Stephen Hurt Watts (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), William Hall
            Goodwin (Associate Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Isaac Alexander Bigger
            (Assistant Professor of Surgery), Frank Helvestine (Instructor of Surgery), John Henry
            Neff (Professor of Genito-Urinary Surgery), and Dr. Page. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pediatrics <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1925] September 24 - [1926] March 7 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">008-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and James Alexander
            Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Internal Medicine [I] and Physiology quiz <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1925] September 21 - [1926] May 28
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">008-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, ADS, TD with AN </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. Included in the book is a 7 page physiology quiz as well as a Secretary's
            Guide for Phi Chi. </p>
          <p>Professor: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Internal Medicine [II] <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1926] September 27 - [1927] April 4 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">008-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professor: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Clinical Diagnosis <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">[1926] September 26 - [1927] May 27 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">009-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professor: William Edward Bray (Associate Professor of Clinical Diagnosis and Director
            of Clinical Laboratories). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Etiology of Heart Disease <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">N.D. </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">009-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, 1 AN </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by A. B. Dickey. See Box-folder 006-001 for more information
            about Dickey. </p>
          <p>Professors: Unknown. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Orthopedics <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1925 February 6-May 8 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">009-003 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Daniel O. Nichols from Hinton, West Virginia. The notebook is
            a gift from Dr. Weaver in Culpeper, Virginia dated April 17, 1975. According to the
            "University of Virginia Record," Daniel Oscar Nichols graduated with his MD degree June
            1926. After graduating from medical school, Dr. Daniel Oscar Nichols interned at Blue
            Ridge Sanatorium and the University of Virginia Hospital while also maintaining his
            practice in Charlottesville. He became a member of the Virginia Academy of General
            Practice in 1953. </p>
          <p>Professor: Allen Fiske Voshell (Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Notebook: Pathology notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1930 June 24-August 7 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">009-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notebook were taken by Oscar Swineford. This is not be a "student" notebook as
            Swineford graduated from UVa SOM in 1926. The notebook was written when he was teaching
            as Instructor in Clinical Pathology, 1928-1930. After receiving the B.S. degree in 1923
            and the M.D. degree in 1926 at the University of Virginia, Dr. Swineford joined the
            faculty of the University of Virginia School of Medicine. He became Professor of
            Internal Medicine and Head of the Allergy Division at the University of Virginia School
            of Medicine. Hi was important in encouraging medical schools all over the United States
            to develop the teaching of allergy. He was President of the American Academy of Allergy
            and the Southeastern Allergy Association. He was Chairman of the Allergy Section of the
            Southern Medical Association. He was a member of the Scientific and Educational Council
            of the Allergy Foundation of America, of the American Rheumatism Association, the
            Medical Society of Virginia, the American Medical Association, and a fellow of the
            American College of Physicians. Chiarri is written on the front of the notebook and on
            pages inside but it is not clear if this is a student or instructor name.</p>
          <p>Donor: Mrs. Blair, daughter of Dr. Swineford, Jr. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pathology notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1930 June 10-August 14 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">009-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notebook were taken by Oscar Swineford. This is not be a "student" notebook as
            Swineford graduated from UVa SOM in 1926. For additional information about Swineford see
            Box-folder 009-004. The notebook was written when he was teaching as Instructor in
            Clinical Pathology, 1928-1930.</p>
          <p>Donor: Mrs. Blair, daughter of Dr. Swineford, Jr. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Materia Medica notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1929-30 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. According to the the "University of Virginia
            Record," Delmar Franklin Weaver from Orange, Virginia, graduated with an MD degree on
            June, 14, 1932. After serving as Instructor of Surgery at the University of Virginia
            School of Medicine, Weaver did a Fellowship at the Rochester, Minnesota, Mayo Clinic in
            otolaryngology, bronschoscopy and plastic surgery from 1936 to 1939. Later he was
            associate surgeon in Otolaryngology at Henry Ford Hospital, Detroit. From 1950 to 1970,
            Weaver was in private practice in Detroit. He was appointed Clinical Professor of
            Otolaryngology, College of Medicine, Wayne State University in 1963. From 1970 until he
            retired Weaver was on the staff at Culpeper Memorial Hospital and was a visiting staff
            member at the UVa Medical Center. </p>
          <p>Professor: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and
            Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Obstetrics notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1930 September 22 - 1931 March 10 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see
            Box-folder 010-001. </p>
          <p>Professor: Francis Bayard Carter (Associate Professor of Obstetrics). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pediatric lecture notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1930 September 23 - 1931 March 14 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see
            Box-folder 010-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and William Wirt Waddell,
            Jr. (Assistant Professor of Pediatrics). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery lecture notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1930 September 24 - 1931 May 30 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see
            Box-folder 010-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), William Hall
            Goodwin (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Richard Hardaway Meade
            (Assistant Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce Morton (Assistant
            Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), and Caleb Smith Stone (Instructor of Surgery).
          </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Orthopedics Lecture notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1931 January 7-May 14 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by D. F. Weaver. For additional information about Weaver see
            Box-folder 010-001 </p>
          <p>The lecturer was Dr. [Allen F.] Voshell. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pediatrics <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1931 September 21-December 5 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by J. A. M. Thompson. According to the the "University of
            Virginia Record," John A. Moorman Thompson from Stevensburg, Virginia, graduated with an
            MD degree on June, 13, 1933. He was on the staff of Blue Ridge Sanatorium, and also
            served on the staff of the Veterans Hospital at Oteen, N.C. </p>
          <p>Professors: Lawrence Thomas Royster (Professor of Pediatrics) and William Wirt Waddell,
            Jr. (Assistant Professor of Pediatrics) </p>
          <p>Donors: Ms. Roberta Senechal and Mr. James Skalnik. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Syphilology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1932 January 5 - 1933 March 17 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">010-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by J. A. M. Thompson. For more information on Thompson see
            Box-folder 010-006. </p>
          <p>Professor: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology.) Also
            includes notes in public health taught by Dr. Kenneth F. Maxcy. </p>
          <p>Donors: Ms. Roberta Senechal and Mr. James Skalnik. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Calibration of Volumetric Apparatus <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937 August 3-September 28
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker when he was an undergraduate student.
            According to the "University of Virginia Record," Armistead Page Booker from New Castle,
            Delaware, graduated with an MD degree on June, 15, 1943. He earned a B.S. from Virginia
            Military Institute. He was Charlottesville's first full-time pediatrician, and cared for
            four generations of children. He was a founder of Pediatrics Associates and worked as an
            Associate Professor of Pediatrics at the University of Virginia where he became Chief of
            the Pediatric Clinic and Director of the blood bank. He also served as a physician at
            the Blue Ridge School in Dyke and at Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center in
            Fisherville. He was Chief of Pediatrics at the Martha Jefferson Hospital. He served in
            the military for 38 years, including active duty in the Army and Air Force. He was
            awarded the meritorious service medal and the Army commendation medal. He served in many
            community and professional posts, and was author of numerous publications.</p>
          <p> The inscription on the front cover of the notebook includes "Eastern Laboratory,
            Gibbstown, N.J." Eastern Laboratory was a research facility developed by DuPont. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Notebook: Embryology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
              >[1939]-40 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Bacteriology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1938 November 15-December 13 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-003 </container>
          <physdesc>AD notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker when he was an undergraduate student. For
            more information on Booker see Box-folder 011-001. This is a collection of data sheets.
          </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Laboratory Assignments for 2nd Term <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 January 3-March 4
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. The assignments were given by Drs. [Robert Bennett] Bean, [Carl]
            Speidel, and [Wiley Roy] Mason. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: General Medical Studies [I] <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 January 3-April 15 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: General Medical Studies [II] <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 February 13-May 30 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: General Medical Studies [III] <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 April 17-May 27 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: "Materia Medica, Drug Lists and Laboratory Exercises" Printed
            in Ann Arbor, Michigan by Edwards Brothers, Inc., 1939. Forward by J[ames] A[lexander]
            Waddell. <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 September 16-1941
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-008 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS booklet with A notes and drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica
            and Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: "Pharmacology; Laboratory Directions and Notes on
            Pharmacodynamics," Pharmacological Laboratory, University of Virginia, 1938, 7th
            revision, University Press. <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
              >1940 September 16-1941 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-009 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS booklet with A notes and drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica
            and Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Anatomy <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">19[39] September 21 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-010 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology Laboratory Experiments <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 September 26 - 1941 February 7
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">011-011 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey
            (Assistant Professor of Physiology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology 1 and Psychobiology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 September 19 - 1941 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Physiology: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward
            Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology) Psychobiology: Edward Lyman Corey
            (Assistant Professor of Physiology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pharmacology 1 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1940 September 16-December 2 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology), and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica,
            and Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: "University of Virginia Physiological Laboratory; An Outline
            of Experiments in Physiology," Third Edition <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1940 September 17 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-003 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS booklet with A notes and drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey
            (Assistant Professor of Physiology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology Laboratory Experiments <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 October 29-1941 February 28 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The experiments were done by J. D. Adams, A. P. Booker, R. Booth, R. Leigh, and F. A.
            McCue. According to the "University of Virginia Record," John Dean Adams, Armistead Page
            Booker, Richard Booth, Randolph Leigh, and Frank Armstrong McCue all graduated with an
            MD degree on March 15, 1943. </p>
          <p>Professors: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward Lyman Corey
            (Assistant Professor of Physiology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pharmacology 2 and Pathology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1941 January 3-May 12 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Pharmacology: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia
            Medica, and Toxicology), and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology,
            Materia Medica, and Toxicology); Pathology: James Robert Cash (Walter Reed Professor of
            Pathology), James Karl Scott (Assistant Professor of Pathology), John Ridley Seal
            (Instructor of Pathology), Walter Ansell Derrick (Instructor of Pathology), and Lyle
            Jamesson Hansbrough (Instructor of Pathology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis and Medicine 1 <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1941 January 3-February 18 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings, some in color </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice
            of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar
            Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine). The lectures are by [Staige Davis]
            Blackford. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology 2 and Medicine 2 <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1941 January 8-March 11 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Physiology: Sydney William Britton (Professor of Physiology) and Edward
            Lyman Corey (Assistant Professor of Physiology); Theory and Practice of Medicine: Eugene
            Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of
            Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige
            Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant
            Professor of Medicine). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: "Toxicology; Supplementary Notes on Toxicology, Chemical
            Identification, Clinical Symptoms and Signs, Antidotes and Antagonists," Pharmacological
            Laboratory, University of Virginia, 1941, University Press. <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1941 February 10 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-008 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS booklet with A notes </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica
            and Toxicology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Medicine 3 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 March 24-December 2 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-009 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice
            of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), and Oscar
            Swineford, Jr.(Assistant Professor of Medicine); The lecturers include Drs. Wood, E.
            Wood, and [John Campbell] Hortenstine. Dr. [Henry Bearden] Mulholland held clinic as did
            Dr. E. Wood. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery 1 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 March 24-October 22 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-010 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce
            Morton (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Claude C. Coleman (Clinical
            Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Everett Drash (Assistant Professor of Surgery and
            Gynecology), John Moyer Meredith (Assistant Professor of Neurological Surgery), William
            Henry Parker (Instructor of Surgery), William Roland Hill (Instructor of Surgery), and
            Arthur Morton Smith (Instructor of Surgery). The lecturers include Drs. [Edwin
            Partridge] Lehman, [William Henry] Parker, [William Roland] Hill, and [Charles Bruce]
            Morton. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Clinical Diagnosis <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 March 25-December 12 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">012-011 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: William Edward Bray (Professor of Clinical Pathology and Director of the
            Clinical Laboratories) and Kenneth Boyd Grim (Instructor of Clinical Pathology). </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Urology and Dermatology <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 September 22-December 13 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Urology: Samuel Alexander Vest, Jr. (Associate Professor of Urology), Edgar
            Wilson Kirby (Assistant Professor of Urology), Howard Harman Curd (Instructor of
            Urology), James Workman Culbertson (Instructor of Anatomy), and Bruno Barelare, Jr.
            (Research Fellow in Urology); Dermatology: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of
            Dermatology and Syphilology), Walter Croft Herold (Instructor of Dermatology and
            Syphilology), and Joseph Leigh Hundley (DuPont Service Fellow in Physiology). The
            lecturers include Drs.[Samuel Alexander] Vest, [Edgar Wilson] Kirby, and [Bruno]
            Barelare. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Obstetrics 1 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 September 22 - 1942 January 16 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Tiffany Johns Williams (Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology), John
            McIntire Nokes (Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology), and William Norman
            Thornton (Instructor of Obstetrics and Gynecology)The lecturers include Drs. [Tiffany
            Johns] Williams and [John McIntire] Nokes. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pediatrics 1 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 September 23- 1942 February 24 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Associate Professor of Pediatrics) and William
            Herndon Pearson (Instructor of Orthodontia). The lecturers include Drs. [Lawrence
            Thomas] Royster, [William Wirt] Waddell, and [McLemore] Birdsong. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery 2 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 October 27 - 1942 February 10 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Edwin Partridge Lehman (Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Charles Bruce
            Morton (Professor of Clinical Surgery and Gynecology), Claude C. Coleman (Clinical
            Professor of Surgery and Gynecology), Everett Drash (Assistant Professor of Surgery and
            Gynecology), John Moyer Meredith (Assistant Professor of Neurological Surgery), William
            Henry Parker (Instructor of Surgery), William Roland Hill (Instructor of Surgery), and
            Arthur Morton Smith (Instructor of Surgery). The lecturers include Drs. [Edwin
            Partridge] Lehman, [William Gayle] Crutchfield, [Everett Cato] Drash, [Edwin Webster]
            Shearburn, and [Charles Bruce] Morton. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Medicine 4 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1941 November 26 - 1942 February 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice
            of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford,
            Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical
            Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of
            Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine).
            The lecturers include Drs. E. Wood. [Byrd Stuart] Leavell, [William Maryon] Moir, and
            [Henry Bearden] Mulholland. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Orthopedics N. &amp; P. 1 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1942 January 5-November 3 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-006 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Orthopedics: Robert Vivian Funsten (Professor of Orthopedics), Charles Ames
            Frankel (Instructor of Orthopedic Surgery), Richard Taylor Ergenbright (Instructor of
            Orthopedics), Lloyd Delbert Fisher (Instructor of Orthopedic Surgery), and Dr. Harris;
            Neurology and Psychiatrics: David Cole Wilson (Professor of Psychiatry and Neurology).
            The lecturers include Dr. [David Cole] Wilson. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Obstetrics 2 and Sanitation, Statistics, and Epidemiology
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 January 16 - 1943
              February 26 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>The lecturers include Drs. [John McIntire] Nokes and [Thomas Shepherd] Englar. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Pediatrics 2 and Preventive Mediciine and Epidemiology
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 February 26-September 3
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-008 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Pediatrics: William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Associate Professor of Pediatrics)
            and William Herndon Pearson (Instructor of Orthodontia); Preventive Medicine and
            Epidemiology: George McLean Lawson (Professor of Preventive Medicine and Bacteriology)
            and Thomas Shepherd Englar (Professor of Public Health and Hygiene). The lecturers
            include Drs. [William Wirt] Waddell, [McLemore] Birdsong and [George McLean] Lawson.
          </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Medicine 5 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1942 February 27-August 11 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">013-009 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice
            of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford,
            Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical
            Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of
            Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine).
            The lecturers include Drs. [Byrd Stuart] Leavell, [Eugene Markley] Landis, [Oscar]
            Swineford, [William Gayle] Crutchfield. Drs. [Henry Bearden] Mulholland, [Staige Davis]
            Blackford, [Everett Cato] Drash, [John Osborne] McNeel, and Wood held clinic. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: E.N.T., Syphilology, and Medical Jurisprudence <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 March 29-November 24
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Diseases of Ear, Nose and Throat: Fletcher Drummond Woodward (Professor of
            Diseases of Ear, Nose and Throat), Edwin Weisman Burton (Professor of Diseases of the
            Eye), Cuthbert Tunstall (Assistant Professor of Diseases of Ear, Nose, and Throat),
            Glassell Slaughter Fitz-Hugh (Instructor of Otolaryngology), and Fielding Jason Crigler
            (Instructor of Ophthalmology); Syphilology: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of
            Dermatology and Syphilology), Walter Croft Herold (Instructor of Dermatology and
            Syphilology), and Joseph Leigh Hundley (DuPont Service Fellow in Physiology); Medical
            Jurisprudence: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and
            Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica
            and Toxicology). The lecturers include Drs. [James Alexander] Waddell, [Dudley Crofford]
            Smith, and [Fletcher Drummond] Woodward. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Roentgenology and N &amp; P 2 <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 July 7-December 1 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Roentgenology: Vincent William Archer (Professor of Roentgenology), George
            Cooper (Assistant Professor of Roentgenology), Ivor David Harris (Instructor of
            Roentgenology), Dr. Adams, and Dr. Pearce; Neurology and Psychiatry: David Cole Wilson
            (Professor of Neurology and Psychiatry). The lecturers include Drs. [Vincent William]
            Archer, [David Cole] Wilson, and [George] Cooper. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Medicine 6 <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1942 August 6 - 1943 February 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook with drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden
            Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice
            of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford,
            Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical
            Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of
            Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine).
            The lecturers include Drs. [Eugene Markley] Landis, [Henry Bearden] Mulholland, and Drs.
            Mulholland, Wood, and [Oscar] Swineford held clinics. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology 2 <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 September 28-December 5
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: George McLean Lawson (Professor of Preventive Medicine and Bacteriology),
            and Thomas Shepherd Englar (Professor of Public Health and Hygiene). The lecturers
            include Dr. [George McLean] Lawson. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: "Legal Medicine or Medical Jurisprudence, Outline of Course
            supplemented with Related Questions and Topics," Medical Department, University of
            Virginia, J. A. Waddell, University Press, 1942. <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1942 October 27 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-005 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS booklet with A marks </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The booklet belonged to Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see
            Box-folder 011-001. </p>
          <p>Professors: Medical Jurisprudence: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology,
            Materia Medica, and Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of
            Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology) </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Laboratory Notebook in Physiology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935 November 6 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-006 </container>
          <physdesc>TDS notebook with A notes, 1 TLS copy </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notebook was done by Malcolm Foote Sher and Charlotte Swaney. Sher donated it in
            1992. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Malcolm Foote Sher and Charlotte
            Ellen Swaney both received their MD degrees on June 13, 1938. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Surgery <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1936 January - 1937 June </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-007 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, 1 TLS copy </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Malcolm Foote Sher. According to the "University of Virginia
            Record," Malcolm Foote Sher received his MD degrees on June 13, 1938. The notebook is
            divided into sections: General Principles by Dr. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, Abdominal
            Surgery by Dr. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, General Surgery by Dr. [Charles Bruce] Morton,
            Thoracic Surgery by Dr. [Everett Cato] Drash, Sympath. Surgery by Dr. [Edwin Partridge]
            Lehman, Neuro Surgery by Dr. [Claude C.] Coleman, Urology by Dr. [John Henry] Neff and
            Gynecology by Dr. [Charles Bruce] Morton. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Medicine, Materia Medica and Chemistry <unitdate
              type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1836] </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">014-008 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, 1 TL </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken William H. Harding. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers
            and Students of the University of Virginia," Harding attended sessions in 1835-36 and
            1836-37. According to the accompanying letter from Palinurus Antiquarian Books, the
            lectures were given by John Patten Emmet. The letter also indicates that Harding was
            from a Virginia family in Northumberland County whose estate and plantation still stand,
            that he practiced medicine and served in the Virginia General Assembly before an
            untimely death. In the back of the notebook are fragments of letters to people including
            Ann H. George and his uncle. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology and Pharmacology <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922 September 20 - 1923 May 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">015-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, 1 TL </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Porter B. Echols. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers
            and Students of the University of Virginia," Porter Burks Echols graduated June
            1925.</p>
          <p> The lecturers include Drs. [Theodore] Hough and [James Alexander] Waddell. The
            notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1923 Jan 16 - 1925 February 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">015-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Porter B. Echols. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers
            and Students of the University of Virginia," Porter Burks Echols graduated June
            1925.</p>
          <p> The lecturers include Drs. [Allen F.] Voshell, [John Staige] Davis, [William Hall]
            Goodwin, [William Douglas] Macon, [William Edward] Brown, and [James Alexander] Waddell.
            The notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Practice of Medicine, Diseases of Nervous System, Case
            teaching, Insanity <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924 April
              28 - 1925 April 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">015-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Porter B. Echols. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers
            and Students of the University of Virginia," Porter Burks Echols graduated June
            1925.</p>
          <p> The lecturers included Drs. [Lawrence T.] Royster, [Leroy Adelbert] Calkins, and [John
            Staige] Davis. The notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Anatomy <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1873 October 4 - 1874 June 22 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">015-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Charles Shepherd Webb. According to his brief autobiography,
            when he attended the University of Virginia, he took a "thorough course in the
            theoretical branches and then went to the University of New York to get the benefit of
            the hospitals." He graduated with the degree of M.D. from the University of New
            York.</p>
          <p> The UVa lecturer was John Staige Davis in anatomy. The notebook also contains notes
            that were given by Professor Darling at the University of New York and another section
            on materia medica.</p>
          <p> The notebook was donated by Ann W. McDowell, Webb's granddaughter, in March 2010. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Notes on Chemistry and Medicine, <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 September 16 - 1840 March 30
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">016-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS with drawings notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Jethro Meriwether Hurt. Hurt attended the University of
            Virginia for the 1839-40 session and studied Chemistry, Medicine, and Anatomy and
            Surgery. He graduated from the University of Pennsylvania Medical School in 1841.</p>
          <p> (September 1839-1840 at the University of Virginia): Notes on chemistry (Dr. [John P.]
            Emmet) -- Chlorosis, page 23, (Dr. [Henry] Howard, March 1840) -- Muscles -- On the
            treatment of cholera (Dr. Howard) -- Series on the brain and spinal marrow -- Anatomy --
            Cholera asphyscia -- Medicine (Dr. Griffith) -- Of yellow fever -- Congestive fever
            (December 5, 1839) -- Treatment of gastritis -- Symptoms of chronic enteritis --
            Diarrhoea acute and chronic -- Causes of hepatitis -- Symptoms of meningitis -- General
            cerebritis -- Dr. [James L.] Cabell notes (1839) -- Dr. Howard notes. </p>
          <p>Gift of Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III. Fragile with brittle pages. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840
            </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">016-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Volume 2 (1840 continued ) -- Howard's lecture on midwifery -- Haemorrage -- Metritis
            on puerpera fever -- Signs of delivery -- Rape -- Latent diseases -- Survivorship --
            Wounds --- Persons found dead -- Adipocere -- Poisons -- Cough mixture [and other
            remedies and ointments]. </p>
          <p>Gift of Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III. Fragile with brittle pages and mold damage. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841
              January 16 - February 20 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">016-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS with drawings notebook </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Volume 3 Notes on materia medica (Dr. Emmet) January 16, 1841 - February 9, 1841 at
            the University of Pennsylvania): Midwifery -- Labor -- Presentations -- Causes --
            Treatment -- Mechanism of presentations -- Hodge (January 20, 1841) -- Wood (February
            20, 1841) -- Thraxacum -- Mineral acuscles -- Vegetable astringents -- Kino -- Nervous
            stimulants (Dr. Wood) -- Cerebral stimulants -- Alcohol -- Opium -- Hemorrhage --
            Hyoscyamus -- Camphor -- Belladonna -- Dr. Jackson -- Vascular repair -- Dr. Wood --
            Arterial sedatives -- Nux vomica -- Ansenic -- Emetics -- Cathartics. </p>
          <p>Gift of Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III. Fragile with brittle pages. </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919
              April 28 - June 7 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">016-004 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS with typed notes, drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notebook by Patton K. Pierce, UVA SOM class of 1921, includes Laboratory Exercises
            in Physiological Chemistry and Pharmacology. Experiments were done on animals including
            dog, cat, rabbit, turtle, rat, and frog, or various animal organs, with drugs such as
            alcohol, morphine, ether, caffeine, amyl nitrate, chloroform, opium, and strychnine.
            Also cocaine was applied to the student's tongue. There is no professor listed but James
            Alexander Waddell taught Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology in this time
            period. According to Southern Medical News, November 1925, "Dr. Patton Kimbrough Pierce,
            Eutaw [Alabama], aged 30, died August 16 at hospital in Harrisburg, Va. [probably
            incorrect, probably Alabama] of injuries received when the automobile in which he was
            driving overturned."</p>
          <p>Gift of James D. Webb who found the notebook at a flea market in Virginia. It arrived
            at the library March 4, 2013.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Lectures on Internal Medicine <unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1923 September 18 - 1924 May 5 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">016-005 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The notes were taken by Don Carlos Eskew, UVA SOM class of 1924. In the notebook is a
            slip of paper with Dr Don Carlos Eskew, Buffalo City Hospital, Buffalo, New York written
            on it. Some of the subjects covered are infectious diseases, heart disease, diseases of
            the blood, respiratory diseases, arthritis, diseases of the digestive tract, and
            diabetes mellitus. </p>
          <p>Professor: James Carroll Flippin (Professor of Clinical Medicine). </p>
          <p>The notebook was acquired from Palinurus Antiquarian Books on May 2, 2015.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Whiteley's General Chemistry Notes <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1885 November 30 </unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">017-001 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook, drawings </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> The title is "Whiteley's General Chemistry Notes" (Complete) Lithographed By
            Permission And for Sale Only by R. D. Anderson and Bro. University of Virginia. Calvin
            Whiteley Jr. states that the note of Physics are not full, but the Chemistry notes are
            full and contain almost everything said during the class. He was helped by the notes of
            others, especially an old set taken by Mr. Baker Thomas. These notes were then copied by
            a L.E. Flannagan, M.D. Major sections of the book are Physics, Chemistry Proper, The
            Atomic Theory, and Organic Chemistry. Five loose pages are about the brain.</p>
          <p> The verso of pages have contemporary notes taken by W.P. Miles Jr. who was a student
            at UVa in the sessions of 1885-86, 1886-87, and 1887-88. Miles signed his name and wrote
            18 East Range, University of Virginia, Nov. 30th 1885 in the book. He was from Burnside,
            Louisianna and studied Chemistry, Natural Philosophy, Modern Languages, and General and
            Industrial Chemistry. According to "Old Louisiana Plantation Homes And Family Trees" by
            Herman De Bachelle Seebold at the death of his father, Dr.William Porcher Miles Jr.
            abandoned the practice of medicine to attend to his large inheritance. He was not a
            graduate from the University of Virginia School of Medicine. </p>
          <p>The book was acquired from John Hellebrand of Palinurus Antiquarian Books in June
            2015.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Therapeutics and Materia Medica<unitdate type="inclusive"
              era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1866 [?]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">017-002 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones of Amherst County, Virginia, and Benjamin
            Hood. Jones graduated from the University of Virginia in 1865. Other authors may also
            have contributed; a note later in the book is dated June 18th [18]66. </p>
          <p>Schools Attended: Chemistry, Medicine, Physiology and Surgery, and Anatomy. </p>
          <p>Professor: John Staige Davis</p>
          <p>Fragile condition; loose and detached pages. Originally cataloged in Virgo as a rare book, together with the material in Box
            17: Folder 3. From the library of Dr. Peyton N. Rhodes (UVA Class of 1920), grandson of
            the author, Dr. William Joseph Jones (UVA Medical Class of 1865). The notebook was
            donated to the Health Sciences Library by Dr. Rhodes's brother-in-law, Dr. Harry L.
            Archer (UVA Medical Class of 1937). Original cataloging note describes Benjamin Hood as
            the “friend and amanuensis” of William Joseph Jones. Item moved to MS-37 in 2017.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Student notebook: Physiology and Surgery<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce"
              calendar="gregorian">1865-1870 [?]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">017-003 </container>
          <physdesc>ADS notebook</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones of Amherst County, Virginia. Benjamin
            Hood other authors may also have contributed; the name “John Amonett” of Harris Creek,
            Amherst, VA appears on the second page which is dated 1870. The notebook also includes
            several poems and a handwritten land agreement between William J. Jones and two other
            individuals. </p>
          <p>Professors: Henry Howard, John Staige Davis, J.L. Cabell</p>
          <p>Fragile condition; loose and detached pages. Originally cataloged in Virgo as a rare book, together with the material in Box
            17: Folder 2. From the library of Dr. Peyton N. Rhodes (UVA Class of 1920), grandson of
            the author, Dr. William Joseph Jones (UVA Medical Class of 1866). The notebook was
            donated to the Health Sciences Library by Dr. Rhodes's brother-in-law, Dr. Harry L.
            Archer (UVA Medical Class of 1937). Original cataloging note describes Benjamin Hood as
            the “friend and amanuensis” of William Joseph Jones. Item moved to MS-37 in 2017.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
