<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viuh00036">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU-H">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Health
      System::Claude Moore Health Sciences Library::Historical Collections//TEXT
      (US::ViU-H::viuh00036:: University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files,
      1849-)//EN" "viuh00036.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files,
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Biographical Files <num type="collectionnumber">MS-36 </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of
          the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Paper, created by Janet Pearson, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4/16/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2014-02-26">2014-02-26</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files,
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
          <num type="Accession Number">MS-36 </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Historical Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Historical Collections, Claude Moore
        Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">University of Virginia School of Medicine
        Biographical Files <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1849- </unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MS-36 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">7 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 3 feet,
        425 folders </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Historical Collections </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>There are no restrictions. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files, Accession #MS-36,
          Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia,
          Charlottesville, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>Most of the files have been acquired by the staff of Historical Collections by making
          photocopies of appropriate articles. </p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information </head>
      <p>This collection is a result of a decision to gather biographical information about
        University of Virginia School of Medicine faculty and friends. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>This collection contains biographical information about University of Virginia School of
        Medicine faculty and friends mainly collected from University of Virginia publications,
        including the "Bulletin of the University of Virginia Medical School and Hospital" from 1941
        to 1946, "University of Virginia Medical Alumni News Letter" from 1948-1973, "University of
        Virginia Medical Alumnews" from 1974-1991, and "UVa Medical AlumNews" beginning in 1992.
        Multiple articles from "The Daily Progress" as early as 1942 are also included as are single
        articles from other publications. Bibliographies of publications of faculty members are
        available for some of the entries. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>The files are arranged alphabetically according to the subjects' last names. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, A - Ci, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
            </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors and
            obituary notices, many from "The Daily Progress." </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Suresh Kumar Agarwal, E. Meredith Alrich, John F. Anderson, Patricia M. Andrews, W.
            Parker Anslow, Vincent W. Archer, Franklyn Nathaniel Arnhoff, John D. Arras, Ernst Otto
            Attinger, Nuzhet O. Atuk, Gerald D. Aurbach, Carlos R. Ayers, Evelyn C. Bacon, Franklin
            Bacon, Jerry W. Bains, Donald Granville Baker, Benjamin Lewis Barnett, Eugene J. Barrett, Anna Barringer, Paul
            Brandon Barringer, Jeffrey T. Barth, Robert Bennett Bean, William Bennett Bean, Roy C.
            Beazley, Daniel Becker, Julian Ruffin Beckwith, Ruth Beery, George A. Beller, Janssen
            Benno Jr., Robert M. Berne, Ruth Gaare Bernheim, Raymond C. Bice Jr., Isaac Alexander
            Bigger, McLemore Birdsong, Staige Davis Blackford, Leslie Blackhall, Robert Blizzard,
            James Ramsdell Bloss, Oliver Bierne Bobbitt, Leneas Bolling, Armistead Page Booker,
            William A. Booth, Edward Botchwey, Jamieson Bourque, Floyd Eugene Boys, Megan Bray,
            William Edward Bray, Sydney W. Britton, Stephen Brockmeier, Raymond K. Brown, William A.
            Brumfield, Carlo Bruni, John Buckman, Alice Huffman Bugel, Harrison Woods Burgess,
            Daniel J. Burke, Edwin W. Burton, Joshua Fry Camblos, Randolph J. Canterbury, Leigh
            Cantrell, Robert W. Cantrell, Robert M. Carey, Samuel Henley Carter, James R. Cash,
            David C. Cattell-Gordon, Edward P. Cawley, Alfred Chanutin, Robert L. Chevalier, A.
            Bobby Chhabra, Rose, Chioni, W. Randolph Chitwood, Anita H. Clayton</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, Co - F, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
            </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Diane Davis Cole, Edward L. Cole, Luke Combs, Brian P. Conway, Ray Costabile, George
            Cooper, Edward Lyman Corey, Charles G. Craddock, Kenneth R. Crispell, Marjorie R.
            Crispell, Alison Criss, Charles L. Crockett, Janet V. Cross, A. J. Crutchfield, William Gayle
            Crutchfield, Jesse Wesley Cumbia, William Cecil Dabney, Michael D. Dake, Claudette
            Dalton, John Francis Dammann, Frank D. Daniel, Thomas M. Daniel, Earl Clayton Davis,
            Frederick Carr Davis Jr., John Staige Davis, I (1824-1885), John Staige Davis, II
            (1866-1933), John Staige Davis, III (1900-1977), John Staige Davis, IV (1931-), Sara
            Ruth Dean, Steven T. DeKosky, Don E. Detmer, James Ellis Dill, Rebecca Dillingham, David
            B. Drake, E. Cato Drash, Elizabeth Frances Harlin Drash, Fritz E. Dreifuss, William R.
            Drucker, Percy Elisha Duggins, Brian Russell Duling, Robley Dunglison, Nancy Dunlap,
            John T. Dunn, Thelma B. Dunn, W. LeRoy Dunn, Linda Duska, Douglas William Eastwood,
            Milton T. Edgerton, Richard F. Edlich, Julia Langhorne Emmett Edmunds, Jeffrey Elias,
            Robert M. Epstein, Joseph H. Farrow, Robert Eugene Fechner, Alto E. Feller, John Miller
            Turpin Finney, C. A. Finnigan, G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, John C. Fletcher, Charles J.
            Flickinger, Dorrie K. Fontaine, Eugene Abram Foster, Charles James Frankel </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, G - H, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates, </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Sim S. Galazka, Thomas J. Gampper, W. Horsley Gantt, Richard Garnett Jr., Arthur
            Garson, Mac Roy Gasque, Chalmers L. Gemmill, Chris A. Ghaemmaghami, E. Gibson, Jay Y.
            Gillenwater, Alexander G. Gilliam, Lawrence W. Gimple, Dorothy Sandridge Gloor, Earl
            Atwell Glosser, Gerald Goldstein, Carlos F. Gomez, William Hall Goodwin, Carl W.
            Gottschalk, William Tate Graham, Kenneth E. Greer, William H. Grey, Dieter Hans Max Gröschel (Groschel),
            Charles W. Gross, John L. Guerrant, Richard L. Guerrant, DuPont Guerry, Barry M.
            Gumbiner, Jack M. Gwaltney, Peter Hairston, James T. Hamlin, Joyce L. Hamlin, Percy
            Gatling Hamlin, Marie-Louise Hammarskjold, Guy M. Harbert, John Frederick Harlan, Jr.,
            J. Hartwell Harrison, Andrew D. Hart, Fern R. Hauck, David R. Hawkins, Brad Haws,
            Frederick Hayden, Halstead S. Hedges, Lennart Heimer, J. Ronald Heller, Charles Henderson, J. Owen
            Hendley, John Herr, Charles Edwin Hess, Erik L. Hewlett, Scott K. Heysell, Barry T. Hinton, Joel
            Hockensmith, Vincent P. Hollander, Hubert B. Holsinger, Larry Honikman, Edward W. Hook,
            Jessie T. Hook, William E. Hopkins, J. Shelton Horsley, Bayard Taylor Horton, Charles E.
            Horton, Rick Horwitz, Sharon L. Hostler, Eric Houpt, R. Edward Howell, Yin-tang Hsu,
            Molly Hughes, William Bryce Hunt, Thomas H. Hunter, Jethro Meriwether Hurt</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, I -Ma, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates, </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>James Isbell, J. Michael Jaeger, Janine Jagger, Robert Jahrsdoerfer, John A. Jane, John Jane Jr., William
            Jefferies, Thomas Richards Johns, Bankole Johnson, Charles McCoy Johnson, Herbert
            Clairborne Jones, Rayford Scott Jones, Harvey Ernest Jordan, William S. Jordan, Robert
            J. Kadner, Neal Kassell, John Kattwinkel, Adam J. Katz, Jefferson Randolph Kean,
            Theodore E. Keats, Thaddeus Elliot Kelly, Edwin L. Kendig, Mark Kester, James E.
            Kindred, Robert G. Kindred, Joan Echtenkamp Klein,  Doug Lischke, Linda Kofeldt, Wallace Jones Kirtley, Jr., James D. Kitchin,
            Walter O. Klingman, Norman J. Knorr, Boris P. Kovatachev, Christopher M. Kramer, John
            Gregory Kroll, Calvin M. Kunin, Lucinda Bolling Robertson Lally, Thomas W. Lamb,
            Jeanette Lancaster, Eugene M. Landis, Jan Langman, James M. Larner, Joseph Larner, Cato
            Laurencin, Edward R. Laws, Byrd Stuart Leavell, Kerry Leavitt, Edwin Partridge Lehman,
            Norbert Leitinger, Kant Y.K. Lin, Vernon W. Lippard, Maurice Lipper, William Fontaine
            Lippitt, James B. Littlefield, Jacob Andrew Lohr, David Eugene Longnecker, Thomas P.
            Loughran Jr., James Richmond Low, Preston Brooks Lowrance, Frank L. Lowther, Stephan
            Ludewig, Randal C. Luscombe, David Russell Lyman, William Andrew MacIlwaine III, Tina Mammone, Gerald
            L. Mandell, John Rogers Mapp, Howard Marraro, John O "Rob" Marsh, Barry J. Marshall,
            Harry Taylor Marshall, John Crook Marshall, Otis Marshall, Sarah Josephine Marshall,
            Victor F. Marshall, Marcus Martin, Juan deD. Martinez-Galindo</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, Mc - O, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
            </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">005-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Joe Edwin McCary, John Houston McClung, Mary Jane McCone, Regina C. McCormack, Hulbert
            C. McCoy, Frank C. McCue, H. S. McGaughey, Francis Henry McGovern, Anne Kane McGuire,
            Lockhart B. McGuire, Robert E. McLaughlin, Walter Copley McLean, Josephine McLeod, Owen
            C. Meadows Jr., Robert J. Meyer, Charles W. Miller, James Quinter Miller, Stacey E.
            Mills, George Minor, Daniel N. Mohler, Wilhelm Moll, Cary N. Moon, Christopher C. Moore,
            Claude Moore, Michael Patrick Moore, Peter Van Cortlandt Moore, John J. Moran, Raymond F. Morgan, Gordon
            Morris, Judah Leon Morris, Mary Jane Morris, C. Bruce Morton, Christopher A. Moskaluk,
            Henry B. Mulholland, John Henry Mulholland, William Henry Muller, Ferid Murad, Richard
            Alan Murphy, Charles E. Myers, Mohan Nadkarni, Jerry Nadler, James P. Nataro, Richard D.
            Nauman, Eugene Ezra Neff, John Henry Neff, Nelson family, Frank Donald Nidiffer, John
            McIntyre Nokes, Ruth Marion Nolan, Stan Nolan, Wallace Clay Nunley, William O'Brien,
            Robert E. O'Connor, Robert B. Ooghe, John A. Owen</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, P - S, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates, </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">006-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Albert J. Paquin, William Parson, John Thomas Parsons, Robert C. Patton, Lillian
            Peake, Richard D. Pearson, Katherine L. Peck,
            Samuel Randolph Penn, William A. Petri, Vivian W. Pinn,
            Grover Cleveland Pitts Jr., Thomas Platts-Mills, William Bryan Pollard, Susan M.
            Pollart, Barbara Post, Richard Price, Edwin W. Pullen, Ruthann Mary Chambers Pullen,
            Peter J. Quesenberry, Theodore Rall, Kodi S. Ravichandran, Benjamin Watkins Rawles, Sean Reed, Walter Reed, Robert Allen Reid,
            David Rekosh; James C. Respess, Karen Schulder Rheuban, Laurel Wysong Rice,
            Frank Ripberger, John Risher, Robert J. Roberts, Mason Gordon Robertson, James K. Roche,
            Dudley F. Rochester, George T. Rodeheaver, Bradley M. Rodgers, John Alexander Rorer,
            Mitchell Rosner, Lawrence T. Royster, Leslie E. Rudolf, Edwin Louis Rushia, Catherine
            Marie Russell, Greg Saathoff, Ann Dawson Samuels, William Roberts Sandusky, Prewitt
            Semmes, Chris Shaffrey, Mark E. Shaffrey, Binit B. Shah, Alfred R. Shands, Mack I.
            Shanholtz, Richard P. Shannon, Henry K. Sharp, Milton A. Shlenker, John Richard Shrum, Richard Coffman
            Shrum, Joseph F. Siler, David Simmons, William H. Sipe, James R. Skinner, Craig L.
            Slingluff, Harvey D. Smallwood, Katherine Smallwood, David E. Smith, Dudley C. Smith,
            Emily Reese Smith, H. McKelden Smith, Diane Gail Snustad, Nicholas Sperelakis, Carl C.
            Speidel, Wilford W. Spradlin, Warren G. Stamp, William D. Steers, Ladislau Steiner, Ian Stevenson, David
            Deaderick Stone, Robert M. Strieter, Benjamin C. Sturgill, Grover Cleveland Sumpter,
            Oscar Swineford </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Biographical files, T - Z, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates, </unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">007-000 </container>
          <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its predecessors.
          </physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Peyton T. Taylor, Robert H. Thiele, Bernard Thisse, Christine Thisse, Thomas E.
            Thompson, Michael O. Thorner, John T. Thornton, William Norman Thornton, Oscar A.
            Thorup, William G. Thurman, Thomas W. Tillack, Gregory C. Townsend, Jonathon D. Truwit,
            Jim Tucker, James C. Turner, Jim Turner, Achilles L. Tynes, Paul B. Underwood, Robert Van de Castle,
            Charles Scott Venable, Samuel Alexander Vest, Walter Victor Vieweg, Vamik Volkan, James
            Alexander Waddell, W. W. Waddell, Mary Burke Wagner, Robert R. Wagner, George W. Ward,
            Hugh Shepherd Warren, W. Dean Warren, Stephen Hurt Watts, Peyton Edwin Weary, David
            Delmar Weaver, Delmar Franklin Weaver, Oswald M. Weaver, Michael J. Weber, Ruth
            Elizabeth Weeks, Bliss King Weems, Geoffrey Weiss, Munsey S. Wheby, Clayton E. Wheeler,
            Kerr L. White, M. Lawrence White, David K. Wiecking, Robert P. Wilder, Morton C.
            Wilhelm, Gaylord Stone Williams, Michael E. Williams, Tiffany Johns Williams, David C.
            Wilson, William J. Wilson, J. Edwin Wood, Jr., James Edwin Wood, III, George Frederick
            Wooten, Fletcher D. Woodward, Robert D. Wright, Arthur William Wyker, Harry Robert Yates, Hugh Hampton Young</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
