<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-hs_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="viuh00036">
    <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
        <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViU-H">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Health
            System::Claude Moore Health Sciences Library::Historical Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViU-H::viuh00036:: University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files,
            1849-)//EN" "viuh00036.xml" </eadid>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical
                    Files, <date>1849-</date>
                </titleproper>
                <subtitle id="sort">Biographical Files <num type="collectionnumber">MS-36 </num>
                </subtitle>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
                &address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of
                    the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
                <p id="usestatement">
                    <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
                </p>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc>
            <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Paper, created by Janet Pearson,
                    <date>4/16/2008</date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <frontmatter>
        <titlepage>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical
                Files, <date>1849-</date>
            </titleproper>
            <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences
                Library <num type="Accession Number">MS-36 </num>
            </subtitle>
            <p id="logostmt">
                <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
            </p>
            <publisher>Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </publisher>
            <date type="publication">2008 </date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
                <defitem>
                    <label>Processed by: </label>
                    <item>Historical Collections Staff </item>
                </defitem>
            </list>
        </titlepage>
    </frontmatter>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <runner placement="footer">Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library </runner>
        <did>
            <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
            <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Historical Collections, Claude
                Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia </repository>
            <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">University of Virginia School of
                Medicine Biographical Files <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date"
                    encodinganalog="245$f">1849- </unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">MS-36 </unitid>
            <physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5,"
                1.75 feet, 335 folders </physdesc>
            <langmaterial label="Language">
                <language langcode="eng">English </language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Historical Collections
            </origination>
        </did>
        <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Administrative Information </head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
                <head>Access Restrictions </head>
                <p>Collection is open to research. </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
                <head>Use Restrictions </head>
                <p>There are no restrictions. </p>
            </userestrict>
            <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
                <head>Preferred Citation </head>
                <p>University of Virginia School of Medicine Biographical Files, Accession #MS-36,
                    Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of
                    Virginia, Charlottesville, Va. </p>
            </prefercite>
            <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
                <head>Acquisition Information </head>
                <p>Most of the files have been acquired by the staff of Historical Collections by
                    making photocopies of appropriate articles. </p>
            </acqinfo>
        </descgrp>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
            <head>Historical Information </head>
            <p>This collection is a result of a decision to gather biographical information about
                University of Virginia School of Medicine faculty and friends. </p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
            <head>Scope and Content </head>
            <p>This collection contains biographical information about University of Virginia School
                of Medicine faculty and friends mainly collected from University of Virginia
                publications, including the "Bulletin of the University of Virginia Medical School
                and Hospital" from 1941 to 1946, "University of Virginia Medical Alumni News Letter"
                from 1948-1973, "University of Virginia Medical Alumnews" from 1974-1991, and "UVa
                Medical AlumNews" beginning in 1992. Multiple articles from "The Daily Progress" as
                early as 1942 are also included as are single articles from other publications.
                Bibliographies of publications of faculty members are available for some of the
                entries. </p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement </head>
            <p>The files are arranged alphabetically according to the subjects' last names. </p>
        </arrangement>
        <dsc type="combined">
            <head>Contents List </head>
            <c01 level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Biographical files, A-D, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
                        </unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">001-000 </container>
                    <physdesc>Photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its
                        predecessors and obituary notices, many from "The Daily Progress."
                    </physdesc>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p>Suresh Kumar Agarwal, E. Meredith Alrich, John F. Anderson, Patricia M.
                        Andrews, W. Parker Anslow, Vincent W. Archer, Ernst Otto Attinger, Nuzhet O.
                        Atuk, Gerald D. Aurbach, Carlos R. Ayers, Evelyn C. Bacon, Franklin Bacon,
                        Jerry W. Bains, Benjamin Lewis Barnett, Eugene J. Barrett, Paul Brandon
                        Barringer, Robert Bennett Bean, William Bennett Bean, Roy C. Beazley, Julian
                        Ruffin Beckwith, Ruth Beery, George A. Beller, Janssen Benno Jr., Robert M.
                        Berne, Ruth Gaare Bernheim, Raymond C. Bice Jr., Isaac Alexander Bigger,
                        McLemore Birdsong, Staige Davis Blackford, Robert Blizzard, James Ramsdell
                        Bloss, Oliver Bierne Bobbitt, Leneas Bolling, Armistead Page Booker, William
                        A. Booth, Edward Botchwey, Floyd Eugene Boys, William Edward Bray, Sydney W.
                        Britton, William A. Brumfield, Carlo Bruni, Harrison Woods Burgess, Edwin W.
                        Burton, Joshua Fry Camblos, Robert W. Cantrell, Robert M. Carey, Samuel
                        Henley Carter, James R. Cash, David C. Cattell-Gordon, Edward P. Cawley,
                        Alfred Chanutin, Robert L. Chevalier, W. Randolph Chitwood, Diane Davis
                        Cole, Edward L. Cole, Luke Combs, Ray Costabile, George Cooper, Edward Lyman
                        Corey, Charles G. Craddock, Kenneth R. Crispell, Marjorie R. Crispell,
                        Alison, Criss, Charles L. Crockett, A. J. Crutchfield, William Gayle
                        Crutchfield, Jesse Wesley Cumbia, William Cecil Dabney, Michael D. Dake,
                        Claudette Dalton, John Francis Dammann, Thomas M. Daniel, Earl Clayton
                        Davis, Frederick Carr Davis Jr., John Staige Davis, I (1824-1885), John
                        Staige Davis, II (1866-1933), John Staige Davis, III (1900-1977), John
                        Staige Davis, IV (1931-), Sara Ruth Dean, Steven T. DeKosky, Don E. Detmer,
                        James Ellis Dill, David B. Drake, E. Cato Drash, Elizabeth Frances Harlin
                        Drash, Fritz E. Dreifuss, William R. Drucker, Percy Elisha Duggins, Robley Dunglison, John T.
                        Dunn, Thelma B. Dunn</p>
                    <p>(Agarwal, Suresh Kumar; Alrich, E. Meredith; Anderson, John F.; Andrews,
                        Patricia M.; Anslow, W. Parker; Archer, Vincent W.; Attinger, Ernst Otto;
                        Atuk, Nuzhet O.; Aurbach, Gerald D.; Ayers, Carlos R.; Bacon, Evelyn C.;
                        Bacon, Franklin; Bains, Jerry W.; Barnett, Benjamin Lewis; Barrett, Eugene
                        J.; Barringer, Paul Brandon; Bean, Robert Bennett; Bean, William Bennett;
                        Beazley, Roy C.; Beckwith, Julian Ruffin; Beery, Ruth; Beller, George A.;
                        Benno Jr., Janssen; Berne, Robert M.; Bernheim, Ruth Gaare; Bice Jr.,
                        Raymond C.; Bigger, Isaac Alexander; Birdsong, McLemore; Blackford, Staige
                        Davis; Blizzard, Robert; Bloss, James Ramsdell; Bobbitt, Oliver Bierne;
                        Bolling, Leneas; Booker, Armistead Page; Booth, William A.; Botchwey,
                        Edward; Boys, Floyd Eugene; Bray, William Edward; Britton, Sydney W.;
                        Brumfield, William A.; Bruni, Carlo; Burgess, Harrison Woods; Burton, Edwin
                        W.; Camblos, Joshua Fry; Cantrell, Robert W.; Carey, Robert M.; Carter,
                        Samuel Henley; Cash, James R.; Cattell-Gordon, David C.; Cawley, Edward P.;
                        Chanutin, Alfred; Chevalier, Robert L.; Chitwood, W. Randolph; Cole, Diane
                        Davis; Cole, Edward L.; Combs, Luke; Cooper, George; Corey, Edward Lyman;
                        Costabile, Ray; Craddock, Charles G.; Crispell, Kenneth R.; Crispell,
                        Marjorie R.; Criss, Alison; Crockett, Charles L.; Crutchfield, A. J.;
                        Crutchfield, William Gayle; Cumbia, Jesse Wesley; Dabney, William Cecil;
                        Dake, Michael D.; Dalton, Claudette; Dammann, John Francis; Daniel, Thomas
                        M.; Davis, Earl Clayton; Davis Jr., Frederick Carr; Davis, John Staige, I
                        (1824-1885); Davis, John Staige, II (1866-1933); Davis, John Staige, III
                        (1900-1977); Davis, John Staige, IV (1931-); Dean, Sara Ruth; DeKosky,
                        Steven T.; Detmer, Don E.; Dill, James Ellis; Drake, David B.; Drash, E.
                        Cato; Drash, Elizabeth Frances Harlin; Dreifuss, Fritz E.; Drucker, William
                        R.; Duggins, Percy Elisha; Dunglison, Robley; Dunn, John T.; Dunn, Thelma B.) </p>
                </scopecontent>
            </c01>
            <c01 level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Biographical files, E-K, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
                        </unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">002-000 </container>
                    <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its
                        predecessors. </physdesc>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p> Douglas William Eastwood, Milton T. Edgerton, Richard F. Edlich, Julia
                        Langhorne Emmett Edmunds, Robert M. Epstein, Joseph H. Farrow, Alto E.
                        Feller, John Miller Turpin Finney, C. A. Finnigan, G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh,
                        John C. Fletcher, Dorrie K. Fontaine, Eugene Abram Foster, Charles James
                        Frankel, Sim S. Galazka, Thomas J. Gampper, W. Horsley Gantt, Arthur Garson,
                        Mac Roy Gasque, Chalmers L. Gemmill, Mary E. Gibson, Jay Y. Gillenwater,
                        Alexander G. Gilliam, Lawrence W. Gimple, Gerald Goldstein, Carlos F. Gomez,
                        William Hall Goodwin, Carl W. Gottschalk, William Tate Graham, Kenneth E.
                        Greer, Charles W. Gross, John L. Guerrant, Richard L. Guerrant, DuPont
                        Guerry, Jack M. Gwaltney, Peter Hairston, James T. Hamlin, Joyce L. Hamlin,
                        Guy M. Harbert, John Frederick Harlan, Jr., J. Hartwell Harrison, Andrew D.
                        Hart, Fern R. Hauck, David R. Hawkins, Frederick Hayden, Halstead S. Hedges,
                        Lennart Heimer, Charles Henderson, John Herr, Vincent P. Hollander, Hubert
                        B. Holsinger, Larry Honikman, Edward W. Hook, William E. Hopkins, J. Shelton
                        Horsley, Charles E. Horton, Sharon L. Hostler, Eric Houpt, Yin-tang Hsu,
                        Thomas H. Hunter, Jethro Meriwether Hurt, John A. Jane, William Jefferies,
                        Thomas Richards Johns, Bankole Johnson, Herbert Clairborne Jones, Rayford
                        Scott Jones, Harvey Ernest Jordan, William S. Jordan, Robert J. Kadner, John
                        Kattwinkel, Adam J. Katz, Jefferson Randolph Kean, Theodore E. Keats,
                        Thaddeus Elliot Kelly, Edwin L. Kendig, James E. Kindred, Robert G. Kindred,
                        Wallace Jones Kirtley, Jr., James D. Kitchin, Walter O. Klingman, Norman J.
                        Knorr, Boris P. Kovatachev, John Gregory Kroll, Calvin M. Kunin</p>
                    <p>(Eastwood, Douglas William; Edgerton, Milton T.; Edlich, Richard F.; Edmunds,
                        Julia Langhorne Emmett; Epstein, Robert M.; Farrow, Joseph H.; Feller, Alto
                        E.; Finney, John Miller Turpin; Finnigan, C. A.; Fitz-Hugh, G. Slaughter;
                        Fletcher, John C.; Fontaine, Dorrie K.; Foster, Eugene Abram; Frankel,
                        Charles James; Galazka, Sim S.; Gampper, Thomas J.; Gantt, W. Horsley;
                        Garson, Arthur; Gasque, Mac Roy; Gemmill, Chalmers L.; Gibson, Mary E.;
                        Gillenwater, Jay Y.; Gilliam, Alexander G.; Gimple, Lawrence W.; Goldstein,
                        Gerald; Gomez, Carlos F.; Goodwin, William Hall; Gottschalk, Carl W.;
                        Graham, William Tate; Greer, Kenneth E.; Gross, Charles W.; Guerrant, John
                        L.; Guerrant, Richard L.; Guerry, DuPont; Gwaltney, Jack M.; Hairston,
                        Peter; Hamlin, James T.; Hamlin, Joyce L.; Harbert, Guy M.; Harlan, Jr.,
                        John Frederick, Harrison, J. Hartwell; Hart, Andrew D.; Hauck, Fern R.;
                        Hawkins, David R.; Hayden, Frederick; Hedges, Halstead S.; Heimer, Lennart;
                        Henderson, Charles; Herr, John; Hollander, Vincent P.; Holsinger, Hubert B.;
                        Honikman, Larry; Hook, Edward W.; Hopkins, William E.; Horsley, J. Shelton;
                        Horton, Charles E.; Hostler, Sharon L.; Houpt, Eric; Hsu, Yin-tang; Hunter,
                        Thomas H.; Hurt, Jethro Meriwether; Jane, John A.; Jefferies, William;
                        Johns, Thomas Richards; Johnson, Bankole; Jones, Herbert Claiborne; Jones,
                        Rayford Scott; Jordan, Harvey Ernest; Jordan, William S.; Kadner, Robert J.;
                        Kattwinkel, John; Katz, Adam J.; Kean, Jefferson Randolph; Keats, Theodore
                        E.; Kelly, Thaddeus Elliott; Kendig, Edwin L.; Kindred, James E.; Kindred,
                        Robert G.; Kirtley, Jr., Wallace Jones; Kitchin, James D.; Klingman, Walter
                        O.; Knorr, Norman J.; Kovatachev, Boris P.; Kroll, John Gregory; Kunin,
                        Calvin M.) </p>
                </scopecontent>
            </c01>
            <c01 level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Biographical files, L-Q, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
                        </unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">003-000 </container>
                    <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its
                        predecessors. </physdesc>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p> Lucinda Bolling Robertson Lally, Thomas W. Lamb, Jeanette Lancaster, Eugene
                        M. Landis, Jan Langman, James M. Larner, Joseph Larner, Cato Laurencin,
                        Edward R. Laws, Byrd Stuart Leavell, Edwin Partridge Lehman, Kant Y.K. Lin,
                        Vernon W. Lippard, William Fontaine Lippitt, James B. Littlefield, James
                        Richmond Low, Preston Brooks Lowrance, Stephan Ludewig, David Russell Lyman,
                        William Andrew MacIlwaine III, Gerald L. Mandell, John Rogers Mapp, John O
                        "Rob" Marsh, Barry J. Marshall, Harry Taylor Marshall, John Crook Marshall,
                        Otis Marshall, Victor F. Marshall, Marcus Martin, Juan deD.
                        Martinez-Galindo, John Houston McClung, Regina C. McCormack, Hulbert C.
                        McCoy, Frank C. McCue, H. S. McGaughey, Francis Henry McGovern, Anne Kane
                        McGuire, Lockhart B. McGuire, Robert E. McLaughlin, Walter Copley McLean,
                        Josephine McLeod, Owen C. Meadows Jr., Charles W. Miller, James Quinter
                        Miller, Stacey E. Mills, George Minor, Daniel N. Mohler, Wilhelm Moll,
                        Claude Moore, Peter Van Cortlandt Moore, John J. Moran, Raymond F. Morgan,
                        Gordon Morris, Judah Leon Morris, Mary Jane Morris, C. Bruce Morton,
                        Christopher A. Moskaluk, Henry B. Mulholland, John Henry Mulholland, William
                        Henry Muller, Ferid Murad, Charles E. Myers, Jerry Nadler, James P. Nataro,
                        Richard D. Nauman, Eugene Ezra Neff, John Henry Neff, Nelson family, John
                        McIntyre Nokes, Ruth Marion Nolan, Stan Nolan, Robert E. O'Connor, John A.
                        Owen, Albert J. Paquin, William Parson, John Thomas Parsons, Robert C.
                        Patton, Lillian Peake, William A. Petri, Vivian W. Pinn, Grover Cleveland
                        Pitts Jr., Thomas Platts-Mills, William Bryan Pollard, Richard Price, Edwin
                        W. Pullen, Ruthann Mary Chambers Pullen, </p>
                    <p>(Lally, Lucinda Bolling Robertson; Lamb, Thomas W.; Lancaster, Jeanette;
                        Landis, Eugene M.; Langman, Jan; Larner, James M.; Larner, Joseph;
                        Laurencin, Cato; Laws, Edward R.; Leavell, Byrd Stuart; Lehman, Edwin
                        Partridge; Lin, Kant, Y. K.; Lippard, Vernon W.; Lippitt, William Fontaine;
                        Littlefield, James B.; Low, James Richmond; Lowrance, Preston Brooks;
                        Ludewig, Stephan; Lyman, David Russell; MacIlwaine III, William Andrew;
                        Mandell, Gerald L.; Mapp, John Rogers; Marsh, John O "Rob;" Marshall, Barry
                        J.; Marshall, Harry Taylor; Marshall, John Crook; Marshall, Otis; Marshall,
                        Victor F.; Martin, Marcus; Martinez-Galindo, Juan deD.; McClung, John
                        Houston; McCormack, Regina C.; McCoy, Hulbert C.; McCue, Frank C.;
                        McGaughey, H. S.; McGovern, Francis Henry; McGuire, Anne Kane; McGuire,
                        Lockhart B.; McLaughlin, Robert E.; McLean, Walter Copley; McLeod,
                        Josephine; Meadows Jr., Owen C.; Miller, Charles W.; Miller, James Quinter;
                        Mills, Stacey E.; Minor, George; Mohler, Daniel N.; Moll, Wilhelm; Moore,
                        Claude; Moore, Peter Van Cortlandt; Moran, John J.; Morgan, Raymond F.;
                        Morris, Gordon; Morris, Judah Leon; Morris, Mary Jane; Morton, C. Bruce;
                        Moskaluk, Christopher A.; Mulholland, Henry B.; Mulholland, John Henry;
                        Muller, William Henry; Murad, Ferid; Myers, Charles E.; Nadler, Jerry;
                        Nataro, James P.; Nauman, Richard D.; Neff, Eugene Ezra; Neff, John Henry;
                        Nelson family, Nokes, John McIntyre; Nolan, Ruth Marion; Nolan, Stan;
                        O'Connor, Robert E.; Owen, John A.; Paquin, Albert J.; Parson, William;
                        Parsons, John Thomas; Patton, Robert C.; Peake, Lillian; Petri, William A.;
                        Pinn, Vivian W.; Pitts Jr., Grover Cleveland; Platts-Mills, Thomas; Pollard,
                        William Bryan; Price, Richard; Pullen, Edwin W.; Pullen, Ruthann Mary
                        Chambers </p>
                </scopecontent>
            </c01>
            <c01 level="item">
                <did>
                    <unittitle>Biographical files, R-Z, <unitdate type="inclusive">varied dates,
                        </unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    <container label="Box-Folder" type="box-folder">004-000 </container>
                    <physdesc>Mainly photocopies of articles from "UVa Medical AlumNews" and its
                        predecessors. </physdesc>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p> Kodi S. Ravichandran, Benjamin Watkins Rawles, Walter Reed, James C.
                        Respess, Karen Schulder Rheuban, Laurel Wysong Rice, John Risher, Robert J.
                        Roberts, Mason Gordon Robertson, George T. Rodeheaver, Bradley M. Rodgers,
                        Mitchell Rosner, Lawrence T. Royster, Leslie E. Rudolf, Catherine Marie
                        Russell, Ann dawson Samuels, William Roberts Sandusky, Prewitt Semmens, Mark
                        E. Shaffrey, Alfred R. Shands, Mack I. Shanholtz, Henry K. Sharp, Milton A.
                        Shlenker, Richard Coffman Shrum, Joseph F. Siler, Prewitt Semmes, William H.
                        Sipe, James R. Skinner, Craig L. Slingluff, Harvey D. Smallwood, Katherine
                        Smallwood, David E. Smith, Dudley C. Smith, Emily Reese Smith, H. McKelden
                        Smith, Diane Gail Snustad, Carl C. Speidel, Warren G. Stamp, Ian Stevenson,
                        Robert M. Strieter, Benjamin C. Sturgill, Grover Cleveland Sumpter, Oscar
                        Swineford, Peyton T. Taylor, Bernard Thisse, Christine Thisse, Thomas E.
                        Thompson, Michael O. Thorner, William Norman Thornton, Oscar A. Thorup,
                        William G. Thurman, Thomas W. Tillack, Achilles L. Tynes, Paul B. Underwood,
                        Charles Scott Venable, Samuel Alexander Vest, Vamik Volkan, James Alexander
                        Waddell, W. W. Waddell, Robert R. Wagner, Hugh Shepherd Warren, W. Dean
                        Warren, Stephen Hurt Watts, Peyton Edwin Weary, David Delmar Weaver, Delmar
                        Franklin Weaver, Oswald M. Weaver, Michael J. Weber, Ruth Elizabeth Weeks,
                        Bliss King Weems, Geoffrey Weiss, Munsey S. Wheby, Clayton E. Wheeler, M.
                        Lawrence White, David K. Wiecking, Robert P. Wilder, Morton C. Wilhelm,
                        Michael E. Williams, Tiffany Johns Williams, David C. Wilson, William J.
                        Wilson, J. Edwin Wood, Jr., James Edwin Wood, III, Fletcher D. Woodward,
                        Robert D. Wright, Hugh Hampton Young</p>
                    <p>(Ravichandran, Kodi S.; Rawles, Benjamin Watkins; Reed, Walter; Respess,
                        James C.; Rheuban, Karen Schulder; Rice, Laurel Wysong; Risher, John;
                        Roberts, Robert J.; Robertson, Mason Gordon; Rodeheaver, George T.; Rodgers,
                        Bradley M.; Rosner, Mitchell; Royster, Lawrence T.; Rudolf, Leslie E.;
                        Russell, Catherine Marie; Samuels, Ann Dawson; Sandusky, William Roberts;
                        Semmes, Prewitt; Shaffrey, Mark E.; Shands, Alfred R.; Shanholtz, Mack I.;
                        Sharp, Henry K.; Shlenker, Milton A.; Shrum, Richard Coffman; Siler, Joseph
                        F.; Sipe, William H.; Skinner, James R.; Slingluff, Craig L.; Smallwood,
                        Harvey D.; Smallwood, Katherine; Smith, David E.; Smith, Dudley C.; Smith,
                        Emily Reese; Smith, H. McKelden; Snustad, Diane Gail; Speidel, Carl C.;
                        Stamp, Warren G.; Stevenson, Ian; Strieter, Robert M.; Sturgill, Benjamin
                        C.; Sumpter, Grover Cleveland; Swineford, Oscar; Taylor, Peyton T.; Thisse,
                        Bernard; Thisse, Christine; Thompson, Thomas E.; Thorner, Michael O.;
                        Thornton, William Norman; Thorup, Oscar A.; Thurman, William G.; Tillack,
                        Thomas W.; Tynes, Achilles L.; Underwood, Paul B.; Venable, Charles Scott;
                        Vest, Samuel Alexander; Volkan, Vamik; Waddell, James Alexander; Waddell, W.
                        W.; Wagner, Robert R.; Warren, Hugh Shepherd; Warren, W. Dean; Watts,
                        Stephen Hurt; Weary, Peyton Edwin; Weaver, David Delmar; Weaver, Delmar
                        Franklin; Weaver, Oswald M.; Weber, Michael J.; Weeks, Ruth Elizabeth;
                        Weems, Bliss King; Weiss, Geoffrey; Wheby, Munsey S.; Wheeler, Clayton E.;
                        White, M. Lawrence; Wiecking, David K.; Wilder, Robert P.; Wilhelm, Morton
                        C.; Williams, Michael E.; Williams, Tiffany Johns; Wilson, David C.; Wilson,
                        William J.; Wood, Jr., J. Edwin; Wood, III, James Edwin; Woodward, Fletcher
                        D.; Wright; Robert D.; Young, Hugh Hampton) </p>
                </scopecontent>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
