<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vipets00008">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia State University::Johnston Memorial Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViPetS::vipets00009::The Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church Papers, 1876-1974)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vipets00009.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViPets">PUBLIC
"-//Virginia State University::Johnston Memorial
Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT
(US::ViPetS::vipets00009::The Reformed Zion Union
Apostolic Church Papers, 1876- 1974)//EN"
"vipets00009.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the The Reformed Zion Union
Apostolic Church Papers 
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876-1974</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church,
Papers, 1876-1974 
<num type="collectionnumber">1980-36</num></subtitle>
        <author>Alicia McCloud and Lucious Edwards</author>
        <sponsor>Funded in part by a grant from the National
Endowment for the Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State
University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vsu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Board of
Visitors of Virginia State University.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">43 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
2000, and created by Robert Ingram. Date of source: 
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 April 2002</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
<language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia State University::Johnston
Memorial Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT
(US::ViPetS::vipets00009::The Reformed Zion Union Apostolic
Church Papers, 1876- 1974)//EN" "vipets00009.xml" converted
from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-26" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 26, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic
Church Papers, 
<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876-1974</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
<lb/>Special Collections and Archives 
<num type="Collection Number">1980-36</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vsu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial
Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vsu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: Alicia McCloud and Lucious
Edwards</label>
          <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Funded in part by a grant from the National
Endowment for the Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives,
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections and Archives, Johnston
Memorial Library, Virginia State University</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
1876-1974</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">1980-36</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
contains ca. 200 pieces.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The Reformed Zion Union Apostolic
Church papers contain minutes, reports and the church's
history projects during almost a hundred year span from the
church's organization. Included in these papers is an
unfinished history of the church's existence, minutes from a
conference dating back to 1876, and minutes from the Sabbath
schools that were formed.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church Papers, 1876-1974,
Accession # 1980-36, Special Collections and Archives,
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University,
Petersburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>James Oliver Allen gave these papers to the Virginia
State University Archives/Special Collections Department in
hopes of a publication of a book on this denomination. They
are to be preserved, administered, and used by the Virginia
State University Archives/Special Collections under
customary practices and guidelines of general archival
administration. Copyrights were transferred to Virginia
State University by Deed of Gift in February 1980.
Accession Number: 1980-36.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>History of the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic
Church</head>
      <p>James Richard Howell established the Reformed Zion Union
Apostolic Church in 1869, although the beginnings of its
foundation can be traced back to 1865. James Howell was a
native of New York City where he was an elder of the African
Methodist Episcopal Zion Church. Elder Howell, who was an abolitionist, envisioned a church to evangelize the
Southern "Negro." </p>
      <p>Elder Howell left his home in New York City and boarded a
train heading south. Several hours later he had arrived in the town of LaCrosse in Mechlenburg, Virginia. This is where he began to form
the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church. Howell began to talk
with individuals concerning the church he envisioned. These
individuals appeared to have been interested in his idea. On on April
1, 1869, a delegation including ministers from various
denominations, assembled in Boydton, Virginia to consider
Howell's plan of union.</p>
      <p>The plan of union was accepted by the delegation with
exception of some matters relating to the episcopate
government. Elder Howell won suggestion of his new
denomination, the Zion Union Apostolic Church. The name came
from many of the scriptures that Howell read. Zion was the stronghold
of ancient days, therefore, Zion would be the stronghold of
God's people in this age. As Christ taught oneness of himself
and the heavenly father and his oneness with his followers,
so, too, shall his church dwell as a union. </p>
      <p>During October 1869, a second meeting was held at the          Zion Society to complete the work of a Zion Union Society. At
this meeting guidelines for the general rules were adopted and
Elder Howell was elected to a four-year term as President of
the "Zion Union Apostolic Church of America."</p>
      <p>The denomination was divided into three major factions, the
liberals, who had withdrawn from the Episcopalian communion,
the conservatives, who had been in the white Methodist church,
and the fundamentalists who had come from the Baptist churches
or were new converts to Christianity. The three factions made
almost unceasing war on each other. The liberals were perhaps
a decade ahead of their time in plans and ideas. The
fundamentalists were determined to fight for local church
sovereignty and the immunity of the pastors from any authority
except local congregations. The conservatives hued strictly to
the Methodist line, in doctrines and in practices. Bishop
Howell was almost a faction within himself. He used his powers
of appointment, silencing and expulsion of ministers as a
sledgehammer to drive the stakes of Zion according to his own
designs.</p>
      <p>Controversy became rampant and even bitter. The
struggle the between the bishops and the elders became more divisive to the church when
a movement grew to merge the Zion Union Church with the
Episcopal Church. Bishop Howell fought with an abrasive
tenacity and the division was so sharpened that some Elders
and churches withdrew from Zion.</p>
      <p>Bishop James Howell released himself from his duties of
bishop from 1880-1881. Bishop William Howell was a man
considered agreeable to conservatives, liberals and the 
fundamentalist. Bishop Howell immediately approved ineffective
with the opening of the conference of 1880. His first order of
business was the merger of the Episcopalian government. After
four days of meetings on the matter, a motion prevailed that
the Common Book of Prayer would be adopted. The conference
ended with the Zion Union Apostolic Church being organized into   thirty-eight Episcopalian churches and missions.
and purposes.</p>
      <p>The merger, however, was as a yet one-sided affair. James
R. Howell came out of the Conference more determined than ever
to save his beloved Zion. When the Annual Conference of 1881
was called to order, Howell had done little on the merger
except the rather astringent efforts of opposition. Once
returned to office of Bishop, James R. Howell used his powers
to batter his opponents. The shock of his fury tore the church
asunder. The Conservatives found it necessary to go to the
Bishop and once again point out the grave situation. Howell
acceded. He set to work to hear the breach in Zion. He
successfully arranged a Conference in 1882 to put Zion Union
on one accord. The Conservative leadership took over once the
Conference was called to order and set in motion plans, which
would free Zion Union of discord. The Conference ended with
differences worked out, a return to presidential government
and complete rejection of the merger. From this conference,
the church was known as the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic
Church. However in the Conference of 1884, the Episcopacy
government was restored with the ruling that is shall never be
eliminated.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The Reformed Zion Union Church papers (1876-1974) are vital
papers about the formation of a denomination after the Civil
War. These papers give a detailed account about the beginnings
of this denomination and its founder James Richard Howell.</p>
      <p>Howell, a former member of the African Methodist Episcopal
Zion Church, envisioned a church where all could go to worship
regardless of race, creed, or color. Howell determined to see
his vision come true, set out to find a place for this church.
He boarded a train and found himself in LaCrosse, Virginia and
this is where the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic Church
denomination began.</p>
      <p>These papers document the origins, purposes and functions
of a uniquely African American Christian church. They
represent a church that was not in existence until 1869. These
papers have a distinct worth because it gives you an
understanding of how a church was established after the Civil
War.</p>
      <p>These papers include minutes from Annual Conferences,
Sunday School Conventions, Home Missions and Educational
Convention, Women's Home Mission and Educational Society, the
Reformed Zion Union Sabbath Schools, and Rising Zion Young
Peoples Society.</p>
      <p>The papers are useful not only to members of this
denomination but anybody who is interested in how black
churches were formed after the Civil War. These materials also
help to inform us of the structure of the African American
community after the Civil War. These materials document some
of the activities in Virginia's black belt. Also, these papers
may also be useful for genealogical work because quite a few
names are used.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Series Description</head>
      <p>In series one of the Reformed Zion Union Apostolic papers,
there are detailed records of the church's history. In these
records an unfinished publication of the church's history and
a brief history of the denominations formation and James
Richard Howell. Included are many projects that the church was
working on along with financial reports from these projects.
Some minutes from annual conferences are added in this
series.</p>
      <p>The second series contains minutes from annual conferences,
Sunday school conventions, Women's home Mission and
Educational Society, Home Mission and Educational Convention,
the Reformed Zion Union Sabbath Schools and Rising Zion Young
People's Society. These minutes are from the first and second
district. These records date from 1876-1970.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series I">Church History
Project</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manual Script Early Church History 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Church History 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Brief History 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>History 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Church Report 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 19, 1963</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial Report 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Committee Report 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Individual Church Report 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Report on school at LaCrosse 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Trustee Report 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Conference Rules and Regulations 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Historical Notes 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Notes 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Programs about Bishops 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Programs 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926, 1951, 1976</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Broadside 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925, 1964</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes 2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes Sunday School Convention 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annual Conference Minutes 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series II">Minutes and
Reports</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
1st district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
1st district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
1st district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:23</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
1st district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927, 1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:24</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:25</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:26</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:27</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:28</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:29</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:30</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:31</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:32</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:33</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:34</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:35</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1966</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:36</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Sunday School Convention
2nd district 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
1:37</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>22nd Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:38</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>29th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1909</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:39</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>36th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:40</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>40th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:41</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>General Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:42</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>15th Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1897</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:43</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>16th Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1898</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:44</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>18th Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:45</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>31st Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:46</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>32nd Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:47</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>33rd Annual Session 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:48</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 24th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:49</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 25th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:50</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 26th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:51</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 27th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:52</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 28th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:53</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 29th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:54</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 30th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:55</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 31st Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:56</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 33rd Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:57</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 41st Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:58</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 44th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:59</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 45th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:60</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 47th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:61</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2nd District 49th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
2:62</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of Women's Home Mission and
Educational Convention 2nd District 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943, 1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:63</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Women's Home Mission and
Education Society 2nd District 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951, 1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:64</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Reformed Zion Union Sabbath
Schools 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1906, 1909</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:65</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Home Mission and
Educational Convention 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919, 1949, 1952</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:66</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Home Mission and Education
Convention 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954, 1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:67</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of the Rising Zion Young People's
Society 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946, 1948</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:68</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of 5th and 9th Annual Meetings 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876, 1880</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:69</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of 10th and 11th Annual Meetings 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
1883-1884</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:70</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of 13th and 14th Annual Meetings 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
1886-1887</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:71</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of Annual Meetings 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905, 1921</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:72</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of Annual Meeting 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:73</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Minutes of General Conferences 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938, 1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:74</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 21st Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1903</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:75</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 26th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1907</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:76</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 27th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:77</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 34th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:78</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 38th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:79</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 66th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:80</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 67th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:81</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 68th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:82</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 69th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:83</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 70th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:84</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 71st Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:85</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 73rd Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:86</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 75th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:87</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1st District 79th Annual Conference 
<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
3:88</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
