<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vircu00156">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRCU">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::James Branch Cabell Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU::vircu00156::A Guide to the Emily Dickinson letter to Mrs. Henry Hills circa 1879, circa 1879)//EN" "vircu00156.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Emily Dickinson letter to Mrs. Henry Hills, <date>circa 1879</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Dickinson, Emily, letter to Mrs. Henry Hills, circa 1879, A guide to
<num type="collectionnumber">M 235
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Margaret T. Kidd
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-cab_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 2015 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All rights reserved <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Margaret T. Kidd, <date>7 August 2015</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Emily Dickinson letter to Mrs. Henry Hills, <date>circa 1879</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">M 235
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2015
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Alice Campbell and Margaret Kidd
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Emily Dickinson letter to Mrs. Henry Hills, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">circa 1879
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 235
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Description" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 item, handwritten letter</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Access to the original letter is restricted. Permission to view the original must be granted by the head of Special Collections and Archives. Inquire at the reading room desk or send an email to libjbcsca@vcu.edu for assistance.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Emily Dickinson letter to Mrs. Henry Hills, circa 1879, Collection # M 235, Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA.<!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The letter was donated to Special Collections and Archives by the Associates of the James Branch Cabell Library.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>The letter is available in <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://gallery.library.vcu.edu/items/show/79597">digital form</extref> via the VCU Libraries Gallery. A facsimile of the letter is available in Special Collections and Archives.
</p>
</altformavail>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>This letter was purchased by the Associates of the James Branch Cabell Library on 16 June 1972, from Seven Gables Bookshop located in New York City. Per notes written on the invoice for the transaction, the bookshop states it acquired the letter as follows: "It came to us, with one intermediary, from Mr. Hills Skillings, acting for the heirs of Mrs. Henry Hills." 
</p>
</custodhist>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Emily Elizabeth Dickinson, daughter of Edward and Emily Norcross Dickinson, was born 10 December 1830, in Amherst, Massachusetts. She attended Amherst Academy and Mount Holyoke Female Seminary. Dickinson lived most of her life in the family home on 280 Main Street in Amherst. After the death of her parents she remained in the home with her sister, Lavinia. Aside from a few trips to Washington, D.C., Philadelphia, and Boston, by her late 20s Dickinson rarely left home and was known for her reclusiveness. Despite this she maintained close relationships with family and friends via correspondence, in which she often included poems. Very few of Dickinson's poems were published in her lifetime. After Dickinson's death in 1886 at age 55, Lavinia discovered nearly 1,800 poems in Emily's room. Eventually all of Dickinson's poetry was published posthumously. 
</p>
<p> Mary Adelaide Spencer Hills was born in 1840, to Owen Spencer and Mary Pitkin in South Manchester, Connecticut. Adelaide, as she was known, married Henry Francis Hills of Amherst, Massachusetts in 1863. As a wedding gift, Hills built her a house on 360 Main Street (now renumbered as 38 Gray Street) in Amherst, making the couple neighbors with the Dickinsons. The Hills lived in New York and summered in the house in Amherst. The Hills were friendly with the Dickinsons and Adelaide was a frequent correspondent with Emily. Adelaide died in 1910.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This letter is from Emily Dickinson to her neighbor Mrs. Henry Hills (Adelaide Spencer Hills). The letter is unsigned and undated. It reads:</p>
 <p>Vocal, is but one</p> 
<p>form of remembrance,</p> 
<p>dear friend.</p> 
<p>the cherishing</p>
<p> that is speechless,</p>
<p>is equally</p>
<p> warm -  
</p>
<p>The letter was first published in 1894, in the two-volume <title render="italic">The Letters of Emily Dickinson</title> edited by Mabel Loomis Todd. After the death of Adelaide Hills in 1910, the letter passed into the hands of her children, specifically her daughter Susan Clapp Hills Skillings. According to Dickinson scholar, Thomas H. Johnson, a transcript of the text of this letter, and others in Mrs. Skillings possession, was made by George Frisbie Whicher. In Johnson's <title render="italic">The Letters of Emily Dickinson</title> (1958), this letter, listed as "letter 614," is given a possible date of 1879, and the original is listed as missing. The original letter remained with Mrs. Hills' heirs, until it was obtained by Seven Gables Bookshop from Mr. Hills Skillings.</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Visit the Emily Dickinson Museum site to find out more about her <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.emilydickinsonmuseum.org/letters">letters</extref> and a bibliography of major editions of her <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emilydickinsonmuseum.org/major_editions">writings</extref>.
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>For more information about the Hills family see the finding aid for the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/amherst/ma89.html">Hills Family Papers</extref>, Amherst College Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
