<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-cab_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-cab_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vircu00131"> 
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViRCUH">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::James Branch Cabell::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vircu00131::A Guide to the Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection, 1988-present)//EN" "vircu00131.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection, <date>1988-present</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">M 350
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cindy Jackson
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2010 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cindy Jackson, <date>06 August 2010</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection, <date>1988-present</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
<num type="Accession Number">M 350
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cindy Jackson
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cindy Jackson
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives,
      James Branch Cabell Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1988-Present
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 350
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Stacks
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">1.48 linear feet.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Will Eisner Comic Industry Awards Collection, Collection Number M 350, Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Received the original archives from the awards administrator, Jackie Estrada.  Yearly donations thereafter are given as part of the on-going repository designation.</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Will Eisner Comic Book Industry Awards, the "Oscars" of the industry as they are known, were not always the Eisner Awards.  They were once the Jack Kirby awards.</p>
<p>In 1984 Fantagraphics Books created the Jack Kirby Awards to honor the best works and creators in comics.  Dave Olbrich, a Fantagraphics employee, was the Awards Administrator.  The awards were given out beginning in 1985 at the San Diego Comic Convention with Jack Kirby on hand to congratulate winners.</p>
<p>Olbrich left Fantagraphics Books in 1987, leaving the fate of the awards uncertain.  In the end, two new awards programs were started:  Fantagraphics started the Harvey Kurtzman Awards (commonly known as the "Harveys"); and Olbrich started the Will Eisner Comic Book Industry Awards.</p>
<p>The Eisner Awards was originally set up as a non-profit organization with an advisory board which consisted of Will Eisner and representatives of various comic museums and libraries.  Funding was supplied by sponsors within the industry, including distributors, retailer associations, and printers.</p>
<p>The first Eisner Awards were conferred at the San Diego Comic Convention in 1988, for works published in 1987 with Will Eisner on stage to congratulate the lucky winners in eleven categories.</p>
<p>The awards for 1990 had to be cancelled due to errors included on the final ballot.  Olbrich opted to cancel that year's program rather than go forward since there was no time to correct the ballot. That year at the convention, Will Eisner, Dave Olbrich, Denis Kitchen, Fae Desmond, and Jackie Estrada met and proposed the idea that would change the awards from a one man operation into a collaborative effort, complete with a judging panel to handle the nominating process.</p>
<p>The Eisner Awards came under the auspices of the San Diego Comic Convention, Inc., a non-profit corporation, after the Comic-Con Board of Visitors approved the proposal presented to them by Fae Desmond.  Jackie Estrada was named Awards Administrator.  The program is funded by contributions from distributors, retailers, media companies, and other industry suppliers.</p>
<p>A call for entries is sent to all comic publishers at the beginning of each year with the opportunity to nominate works in more than twenty-five categories.  Each year a new judging panel gathers in San Diego for a weekend to determine what selections will make up the Eisner Awards ballot.  Then the finalized ballots go out to creators, publishers, editors, retailers, and distributors.  The results are tabulated by Mel Thompson and Associates, and the winners are announced during an annual gala ceremony in July at the San Diego Comic-Con.</p>
<p>Source: The Eisner Awards: A Brief History</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The materials in the collection consist of awards programs, ballots, calls for entries and comic books, graphic novels, journals, and comics-related books that were nominated for awards dating from 1988 to present.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Materials are arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.  Comic books, journals, graphic novels, etc. have been incorporated into other collections best suited to house them.  Comic books receive a donor label on their archival bag to identify them in the greater collection.  Books and graphic novels have been assigned a local note identifying the items as part of the Eisner Award Collection.</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Awards Programs
<unitdate type="inclusive">1992-1999
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Awards Programs
<unitdate type="inclusive">2000-2005, 2009
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Ballots
<unitdate type="inclusive">1992-1999
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Ballots
<unitdate type="inclusive">2000-2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Call for Entries
<unitdate type="inclusive">1988, 1990-1999
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Call for Entries
<unitdate type="inclusive">2000-2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive">2006
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Eisner Award Plaque [Hall of Fame - C. C. Beck]
<unitdate type="inclusive">1993
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Eisner Award Statue [Best Limited Series - DC: The New Frontier]
<unitdate type="inclusive">2005
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
