<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00019">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00019::A Guide to the Frank Repass Brown Papers, 2004.3)//EN" "viwyc00019.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Frank Repass Brown Papers, <date>2004.3</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Brown, Frank Repass, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">2004.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>12 August 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Frank Repass Brown Papers, <date>2004.3</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2004.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Frank Repass Brown Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1788-1975, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2004.3
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">3.5 linear feet..
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Frank Repass Brown Papers, Mss. Collection 2004.3, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by the estate of Martha Brown DeBord in September 2004.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Frank Repass Brown, son of Michael Dallas Brown and Emily Repass Brown, was born on 27 March 1887 in Rural Retreat, Virginia.  He attended school in Rural Retreat and business college in Kansas.  He returned to Virginia and graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
</p>
<p>Upon his graduation, he assumed management of the family farm in Rural Retreat and embarked upon a lifelong love and service in the field of agriculture.  He was a charter member of the Rural Retreat Community Fair as well as a member of Future Farmers of America.  He received an honorary degree from Future Farmers of America in recognition of his contributions to agriculture and farming in particular.</p>
<p>Brown shared his love of books and reading with many libraries in the region by making monetary and in-king donations of books and magazines.  Rural Retreat High School Library, Marion College Library, and Southwest Virginia Mental Health Institute (then Southwestern State Hospital) in Marion, Virginia benefitted from his generosity.</p>
<p>He was a lifelong member of St. Paul Lutheran Church in Rural Retreat and wrote a history of the church, <title render="italic">Historical Sketch of St. Paul's Lutheran Congregation, 1776-1941</title>.  He served on the board of trustees for Marion College, a junior college for women, from 1924 to 1964</p>
<p>Brown collected and compiled lists of cemeteries in Wythe County, especially in the western portion.  He also collected local history and kept several scrapbooks.  Brown also recorded local weather, keeping records noting daily temperature and rainfall for over forty years.  He also researched local history and genealogy of many area families.</p>
<p>Brown married Virginia Umberger in 1925; the couple had no children.  He died on 12 October 1973 and is buried in Black Lick Cemetery.  His collection was bequeathed to his niece, Martha Brown DeBord.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Papers are arranged into twelve series:  Series I, Books, Religious (1788, 1828, undated); Series II, Cemetery Records (1898-1973, undated); Series III, Diaries, Personal (1905-1973); Series IV, Diaries, Vital Statistics (1896-1975); Series V, Ephemera (1815-1973); Series VI, Ledgers, Personal (1873-1975); Series VII, Ledgers, Genealogy (undated); Series VIII, Scrapbooks, Genealogy (undated); Series IX, Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous (undated); Series X, Scrapbooks, Local History (1896, 1913, undated); Series XI, Memoirs (1887-1960, undated); and Series XII, Photographs (undated).</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series I.  Books, Religious.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1788, 1828, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Repass Family Bible.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1788.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>16"length x 11 3/4" width x 4 2/8" height.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Repass Family Bible; printed in Nurnberg, Germany by Johann Andrea Endterischen Company.  Introduction by Johann Michael Dillherns with acknowledgements to the German Kaiser, the King of Poland and the Crown Prince of Saxony.  Frank Repass Brown kept the Bible during his lifetime and willed it to his niece Martha Brown DeBord.  In German; conserved in 1963.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Little Catechism of Martin Luther.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1828.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4" width x 6" length x 1/2 depth.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>German, printed in Lancaster, Pa., cloth bound with leather spine.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  German Study Bible.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 1/4" width x 6 1/2" height x 1 1/8" depth.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>German study Bible with frontispiece and p. 1-14 missing; leather bound with metal clasps.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II.  Cemetery Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1898-1973
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Frank Repass Brown compiled a loose-leaf binder of notes and maps on various local cemeteries in Wythe and adjoining counties.  The original records are housed in acid-free folders in the Frank Repass Brown Papers, Series II.  The records consist of lists of veteran burials, burials in miscellaneous cemeteries, and the cemetery compilation by Brown in which he divided Wythe County into four quadrants, mapped cemeteries, and listed burials.
</p>
<p>Photocopies donated by Beverly Repass Hoch (who copied the records in 1997 with permission from Martha Brown DeBord) may be found in the vertical file collection, "Wythe County Cemeteries - Frank R. Brown Records." Photocopies include all cemetery records except letters and financial accounts for various cemetery associations.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Cemetery Records - Cemeteries - Bethany - Mountain View.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains lists of burials in Bethany Methodist Church Cemetery (west of Ceres), Cullop Family Cemetery in Smyth County (listed with Luther Chapel Cemetery), Kimberlin Cemetery, Lutheran Chapel Cemetery (Washington County, Va.), Mt. Mitchell Cemetery, Mt. Pleasant Methodist Church Cemetery, Mountain View Cemetery (Rural Retreat), and the Jefferson Neff Family Cemetery in Lee County, Va. (listed with Luther Chapel Cemetery).
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Cemetery Records - Cemeteries - St. John - Zion.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains lists of burials in St. John's Lutheran Church Cemetery, St. Paul Lutheran Church Cemetery, Sharon Lutheran Church Cemetery (Ceres), Steffey Family Cemetery (Groseclose), Derting and Bennington Cemetery (listed with Steffey Family Cemetery), Repass (west of Bland Court House; listed with Steffey Family), Davis Family Cemetery (Groseclose; listed with Steffey Family Cemetery), Thiel Creek Presbyterian Church Cemetery (Cleveland, Tenn.), Mt. Mitchell Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Mt. Pleasant Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Pleasant Hill Cemetery (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Fairview (listed with Thiel Creek Cemetery), Zion Cemetery (Crockett, Va.), and Zion Methodist Episcopal Church Cemetery (Marion).
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 1 (p.1-16).
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains part one of the cemetery compilation arranged and organized by Brown.  Using a Wythe County road map, he divided the county into four quadrants and plotted each cemetery on this map; a copy of this map is in each folder containing Cemetery Compilation records.  Brown also developed an alphabetical index to the cemeteries, linking each entry on individual cemeteries to quadrant letters and numbers corresponding to the map.  For example, the location of the Foglesong cemetery may be found on quadrant section A, cemetery number 1.</p>
<p>Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order):  Foglesong, Neff, Doak, Newland, Fry, Earhart Ward, Pruner, Wauker, Buchanan (3), Phillippi, Steffey, Keesling, Vaught, Phillippi, Horn, Etter, Vaught, Engledove, Peery, King, Shelton, Richardson, Pennington, Orr, Cassell, Litz, Aekers, Snavely, Kettering, Newland, Hillenburg, Umberger, Kegley, Wohlford-Grubb, Corvin, Harkrader, Brown, Cassell, Umberger, Walters, Grubb, Henley, Gose, Percival, Fry, Gannaway, Mathews, Painter, Arney, Sanders-Whitman, Davis, Crockett, McGavock, Keesling, Toncray, Huddle, Simmerman, Gregory, Pierce, Hudson, Allison, and Walters.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 2 (p. 17-30).
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains part one of the cemetery compilation arranged and organized by Brown.  Using a Wythe County road map, he divided the county into four quadrants and plotted each cemetery on this map; a copy of this map is in each folder containing Cemetery Compilation records.  Brown also developed an alphabetical index to the cemeteries, linking each entry on individual cemeteries to quadrant letters and numbers corresponding to the map.  For example, the location of the Foglesong cemetery may be found on quadrant section A, cemetery number 1.</p>
	<p>Cemeteries in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order):  Oglesby, Cooley, Warder, Montgomery, Crockett, Patterson, Halsey, McGavock, Seyhert, Jones, Shaffer, Thorn, Crockett, Danner, Pearman, Pine Grove, Vaughan, Ogle, Stevans, Gannaway, Kirk, Shupe, Morgan-Trigg, Huddle, Red Bluff, Spence, Byrd-Neese, Wisely, Baker, Sayers, Williams, Buntz, Watts, Blair, Ward, Hudson, Raper, Jackson (2), Hinz, Baker, Fry, Booth, Pine Grove, Simmerman, Davis, Graham, Monks Corner, Derian and Mabe.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 3 (p. 31-40, [41-42]).
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains part one of the cemetery compilation arranged and organized by Brown.  Using a Wythe County road map, he divided the county into four quadrants and plotted each cemetery on this map; a copy of this map is in each folder containing Cemetery Compilation records.  Brown also developed an alphabetical index to the cemeteries, linking each entry on individual cemeteries to quadrant letters and numbers corresponding to the map.  For example, the location of the Foglesong cemetery may be found on quadrant section A, cemetery number 1.</p>
<p>Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order):  Kent, Jackson, Walters, Painter, Huddle, Clark, Mundy, Trigg, Pierce-Umberger, Federal Troops, Jackson, Catron (2), Pope, Chadwell, Early, Earhart, Bell, Sayers-Bell, Ayers, Wright, Robinson, Porter, Jackson, Aker, Arnold, Earhart, Catron, Tompson, Suiter, Crockett, Poor Farm, Simmerman, Nye (Armbrister), Robinson, Ricky Porter, Blair, Hollandsworth, Davis, Groseclose, Six, Wetzell, and Federal Troops.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Cemetery Records - Cemetery Compilation, part 4 (n.p.)
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains part one of the cemetery compilation arranged and organized by Brown.  Using a Wythe County road map, he divided the county into four quadrants and plotted each cemetery on this map; a copy of this map is in each folder containing Cemetery Compilation records.  Brown also developed an alphabetical index to the cemeteries, linking each entry on individual cemeteries to quadrant letters and numbers corresponding to the map.  For example, the location of the Foglesong cemetery may be found on quadrant section A, cemetery number 1.</p>
<p>Cemeteries included in this folder include (following Brown's compilation order):  Peery, Wauker, Buchanan, Phillippi, and Sanders.  Also included is a handwritten article on cemeteries in the Black Lick section of Wythe County, note "Family Cemeteries in Wythe County to Look Up," and "Miscellaneous Cemetery Notes."  This last article contains information on the burial of Federal Troops, White Top Cemetery, and West End Cemetery.  Also included in this folder are notes on burials from notebooks of Mrs. Philip Spence that includes Counselman, Miller, Raper, Graham, Shaffer, Crockett (Newberry Farm), Elbert Simmerman Farm, and John Trigg.  Also included is article "Our Cemeteries in the West End of Wythe County."</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
		<c02 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 7.  Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1934-1968.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes regulations, financial reports, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1969-1970.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder includes financial reports, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 9.  Cemetery Records - Black Lick Cemetery Association.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1971-1973.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder includes financial records, letters, and other records of the Black Lick Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 10.  Cemetery Records - Kimberlin Cemetery Association.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1973.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder includes regulations, financial reports, letters, and other records of the Kimberlin Cemetery Association of which Frank Repass Brown was a member.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 11.  Cemetery Records - St. Paul Cemetery Association.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1942-1968, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains correspondence regarding state funding for maintenance of graves of Confederate veterans in St. Paul's Lutheran Church Cemetery, a list of Virginia cemeteries receiving state support for Confederate grave maintenance, and records of the St. Paul Association.  Also included are newspaper clippings (photocopies).
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 12.  Cemetery Records - Confederate Pensioners, Captain Blessing's Company, and Joseph Brown Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains "A List of Confederate Pensioners Who Have Drawn Pensions from Wythe County Since 1902," list of members in Captain Blessing's Company, and letter from Edward F. Witsell of the War Department to Mrs. N. Bruce Williams regarding Civil War records of Josiah Brown.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 13.  Cemetery Records - Confederate Veterans Burials.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a list of Confederate veterans who are buried in Asbury Cemetery, Fairview Cemetery, Lebanon Cemetery (on back of Fairview listing), Kimberlin Cemetery, King's Grove Cemetery, Marvin Cemetery, Rural Retreat (Mountain View), St. John's Lutheran Cemetery, St. Paul Lutheran Cemetery, and Zion Cemetery.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 14.  Cemetery Records - [Visit to Point Lookout Cemetery, Maryland].
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1950.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains Brown's "A Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place, August 17, 1950," regarding his visit to the Point Lookout Prison cemetery in Maryland to see the burial site of his grandfather, Gordon Repass.  Brown described the cemetery and included photographs in his typescript.  Also included is a letter from the War Department to Sally Maupin regarding service record of Gordon Repass.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 15.  Cemetery Records - War Veterans.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1898-1945.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains lists of veterans who served in the Spanish-American War, World War I, and World War II.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 16.  Cemetery Records - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1915-1953, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder includes miscellaneous records including a Wythe County Highway map (1950), letter regarding the Mt. View Cemetery Association (1951), map of Corinth Lutheran Church Cemetery, typescript of will of Emma Maria Doak (1951) and opinion regarding her legacy for maintenance of Marvin Cemetery (1953), and a poem entitled "Our Cemetery."  Also included is a poem entitled "The Memorial," article "Birthplace of Memorial Day," article "God's Acre," article "monuments to Those Dead," and newspaper clippings including "List of Surviving Confederate Veterans" by Lindamood [incomplete] and members of Co. H, 63rd Virginia Infantry Regiment C.S.A.  A newspaper clipping about Royal Oak Presbyterian Church Cemetery (Marion) and Rural Retreat High School are also in this folder.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Diaries-Personal.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1973.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">3
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Frank Repass Brown recorded weather data and brief notes on daily life in these diaries.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1916.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1905 to 31 December 1916.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1917-1927.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1917 to 31 December 1916.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1928-1939.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1928 to 31 December 1939.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 4.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1940-1953.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1940 to 31 December 1953.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 5.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1954-1964.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1954 to 31 December 1964.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 6
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1971.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains entries from 1 January 1965 to 31 December 1971.  Most entries record weather and brief comments on daily life.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 7.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1954-1963
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This envelope contains loose typed pages dating from 1954 to 1963.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Personal 8.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1900-1973
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This diary of loose-leaf pages consists of two parts.  The first part contains weather data recorded by Frank Repass Brown for Wythe County as well as newspaper clippings relating to his record-keeping.  This section has been photocopied and placed in Kegley Library Vertical File "Weather."  The second part "Miscellaneous Dates" contains local and national events chronicled by Brown from 1900 to 1973.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV. Diaries, Vital Statistics.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1975.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">3
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Frank Repass Brown recorded vital statistics for people in the Rural Retreat vicinity of Wythe County including births, marriages, and deaths.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Vital Statistics 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1975.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains records for births (1910-1957); marriages (1907-1973); and weather (1896-1975).
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Vital Statistics 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">early 1800s-mid 1900s.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary with "Birthdays and Anniversaries" stamped on its cover contains births from the early 1800s to the mid 1900s arranged in calendar style.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Vital Statistics 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800s-early 1900s.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains births from the 1800s to the early 1900s arranged alphabetically.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Vital Statistics 4.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800s-mid 1900s.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This leather bound diary contains births from the 1800s to the mid 1900s arranged calendar style.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Diaries, Vital Statistics 5.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1909.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This envelope contains loose-leaf typed pages that record births from 1887 to 1909.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series V.  Ephemera.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1815-1973.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Ephemera - Memorial Book for Ivan J. Brown.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1938, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a memorial book for Ivan J. Brown, brother of Frank Repass Brown, whose funeral was held on 11 July 1938 at Marvin Church in Wythe County, Virginia.  Also included are loose papers regarding the "Old Stone House" at the Rowan Museum in Salisbury, North Carolina, a "brown Family and Reunion" brochure, and various newspaper clippings on the Brown family.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2. Ephemera - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1815, 1956-1969, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains two programs (1957, 1969) for the Brown-Fisher reunion at Christiana Lutheran Church in Salisbury, North Carolina; Frank Repass Brown's "Notes on the Building of St. Paul Church;" historical sketch "St. Paul Lutheran Church;" sketch "Facts About the Rural Retreat Community;" a postcard of the home of Michael Brown in North Carolina; and a postcard of Grace Church in Rowan County, North Carolina.  Also included are two photocopies of 1815 tax tickets for Henry Lambert and Michael Lambert and a newspaper clipping and photocopy about Frank Repass Brown being honored at the Virginia Association of Future Farmers meeting.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Ephemera - Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1846, 1933, 1973.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains three letters, a birthday card, and a fragment from a fraktur or baptismal certificate.  A letter dated 7 March 1846 from Ephraim Brown and Elizabeth Brown of Hawkins County, Tennessee to Michael Brown of Wythe County discusses weather, health of neighbors, and their finances.  In a 19 March 1933 letter, Orvil C. Sharitz of Newton, Kansas shares Sharitz family data with Frank Repass Brown.  Another letter, from Margaret [unknown] of Pasadena, Texas to Frank Repass Brown, dated 8 August 1973, provides information on the Repass family.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VI.  Ledgers, Personal.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1975.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">4
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains four ledgers kept by Frank Repass Brown for his personal accounts including income and expenses (1918-1972) and livestock accounts (1922-1958). 
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ledger, Personal 1 - Marion College Alumnae.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1925.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This ledger contains a list of members of alumnae of Marion Junior College in Smyth County (1873-1925).  The ledger lists in alphabetical and then chronological order the name of student (maiden name) with married name in parentheses (p. 2-252).  A list in the back records members of the Wythe County Chapter, Marion College Alumnae (p. 197-200).  The ledger is cloth bound with "Day Book" printed on the cover.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ledger, Personal 2 - Income and Expenses.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1918-1972.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This ledger contains a list of income (1918-1972; p. 2-69) and expenses (1918-1966; p. 100-338) for Frank Repass Brown.  Each entry gives date, description, and to whom paid or from whom received, and amount.  The ledger is leather bound with book mending tape on the boards.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ledger, Personal 3 - Livestock Accounts.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1922-1958.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Accounts relating to farm and livestock income and expenses are recorded in this ledger; pages have been placed in an acid-free folder.  Accounts include livestock (1922-1958) and tax assessments on livestock (1931-1951).  Also contained in this ledger is a contract and account records between Frank Repass Brown and G. W. Jones (1944-1959).  Jones worked for Brown on his farm and received daily wages, one-third of the crop, house rental, and a cow.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Ledger, Personal 4 - Accounts.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1949-1975.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Personal accounts of Frank Repass Brown (1949-1975) are recorded in this ledger whose pages have been placed in an acid-free folder.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VIII.  Scrapbooks, Genealogy.
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series consists of three scrapbooks containing various genealogical information collected by Frank Repass Brown.  Scrapbooks consist of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Genealogy 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 folders, 185 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include the following families:  Dater/Tarter, Umberger, Etter, Yost, Phillippi, Shelton, Cline, Hounshell, and Catron.  Also included is information on Crockett Depot, Civil War battles in Wythe County, Mount Airy, German settlers, and Rural Retreat.  Folders are numbers 1 to 5.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Genealogy 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 folders, 22 p., loose clippings.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include the following families:  Brown, Cassell, Neff, Repass, huddle, Shannon, Wampler, Copenhaver, Sluss, Bedwell, Etter, Phillippi, Sharitz, Leedy, Stanger, Groseclose, Spangler, Miller, Dix, Litz, Catron, Staley, and Spence.  Folders are numbered 6 to 13.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Genealogy 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 folders, 194 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include the following families:  Repass, Groseclose, Brown, Sluss, Huddle, Brown, Cassell, and Steffey.  Folders are numbered 14 to 19.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IX.  Scrapbooks,  Miscellaneous
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series consists of three Scrapbooks containing various historical information collected by Frank Repass Brown.  Pages have been removed from the leather ring binders and re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on churches have been photocopies and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 folders, 158 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include:  St. John's Lutheran Church, St. Paul Lutheran Church, Hawkins Chapel, Zion Lutheran Church, St. John's Episcopal Church, Corinth Lutheran Church, Salem Camp Ground, Grace Lutheran Church, Kimberlin Lutheran Church, Marvin Methodist Church, Black Lick Church, Mt. Zion Church, Macedonia Church, Rural Retreat Methodist Church, Christ Lutheran Church (Roanoke, Virginia), and Ebenezer Lutheran Church.  Also included is information on Rev. Paul Henkel, Rev. George John Butler, Rev. John C. Repass, Rev. William P. Huddle, Rev. Elias Studebaker, Rev. William R. Brown, Rev. David Spangler Fox, Rev. Stephen Rhudy, Rev. William Carpenter, Rev. Henry Wetzel, Amos Copenhaver, Rev. Gideon Scherer, and baptismal certificates.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 folders; 199 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include:  Zion Lutheran Church, St. Paul Lutheran Church, Kimberlin Lutheran Church, St. John's Lutheran Church, Sharon Presbyterian Church, and Sharon Lutheran Church.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>10 folders; 276 p., loose clippings.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Topics include:  lists of books Frank Repass Brown donated to local libraries including Rural Retreat High School and Southwest Virginia State Hospital, bibliographies, and other information on books.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series X.  Scrapbooks, Local History
<unitdate type="inclusive">1896, 1913, 1943, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">6, 7
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1896, 1913, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">6
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This scrapbook with cloth spine and board covers contains newspaper clippings glued to scrapbook pages.  Topics covered include Lead Mines, Revolutionary War, Wythe County history, and colonial era Southwest Virginia history.  Several "The Southwest Corner," columns by Goodridge Wilson and "Wythe County History" columns (many excerpts from L. P. Summer's <title render="italic">History of Southwest Virginia</title>) are included.  An index is housed with the scrapbook.
	</p>
	<p>Several loose newspapers clippings, booklets and ephemera are housed in separate folders that are described below.  Photocopies of these loose clippings have been placed in the appropriate Kegley Library vertical file.</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 1.  Scrapbooks, Local History - Loose Clippings - Churches.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains seven loose newspapers clippings about St. Mary's Catholic Church, Fleming Methodist Church, Zion Lutheran Church, and  St. John's Lutheran Church.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 2.  Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Freemasons.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains three original loose newspaper clippings about Masonic Lodges in Alexandria, Virginia and Bristol, Tennessee.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 3.  Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - History.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains eleven loose newspapers clippings about Elliot Roosevelt in Abingdon, Virginia, Hedgefield (Mathews) house, Elizabeth Henry Campbell Russell (Madam Russell), Rev. Robert Sheffey, Revolutionary War leader Abram Penn, buffalo herd in Smyth County, capture of James Moore by Indians, Dunmore's Expedition, and Revolutionary War.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 4.  Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Miscellaneous.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains thirteen loose newspaper clippings about Jacksons Ferry bridge, White Top Music Festival, Wythe County World War II draftee list, Shannon &amp; Spangler Hardware Store and Tin Shop, hike by Southwest Virginia Trail Club, V.P.I. alumni in World War II, Wythe County schools, <title render="italic">Southwest Virginia Enterprise</title> editor James A. Williams, graduating class of Wytheville Training School, and auction of Laurel Glen Farm.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 5.  Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Clippings - Obituaries.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains five loose newspaper clippings about C. Bascom Slemp, Ella Repass Umberger, Bessie Noell Williams, and William N. Doak.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 6.  Scrapbooks, Local 1 - Loose Clippings - "Southwest Corner."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains fifteen loose newspaper clippings from Goodridge Wilson's column, "The Southwest Corner."  Topics discussed include early physicians, camp meetings, Crawford family, Robert Williams, C. Bascom Slemp, Callaway family, French and Indian War, Sheffey family, James Patton, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, and politics.  Original clippings are housed in an acid-free envelope; photocopies of these clippings on acid-free paper are also in this folder.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 7.  Scrapbooks, Local History 1 - Loose Booklets &amp; Ephemera.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1896, 1913, 1943 undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains seven booklets and ephemera items including notes on William Preston, notes on attendance at Burkes Garden Sunday School class (1913), 1943 bulletin from St. John's Lutheran Church, "A Historical Sketch of St. Paul's Lutheran Congregation," by Frank Repass Brown, program "An Evening of Music," at St. Paul Methodist Church, "Constitution of Rural Retreat Evangelical Lutheran Pastorate," and "Constitution of the Congregations of Mt. Airy Pastorate"(1896).</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Local History Scrapbook 2 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 8.  Scrapbooks, Local History 2 - p. 1-20.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on log cabins, Wythe Raceway, Jonas Huddle, Black Lick, Sluss family, Umberger family, Bedwell family, Steele family, Peery family, and Brown family.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 9.  Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 21-40.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Dutton family, Cline family, Cregger family, Sluss family, Groseclose family, Brown family, Repass family, Spangler family, and Repass Cave in Bland County.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 10.  Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 41-60b.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on magistrates, World War II veterans, Spangler family, Freemasons, Battle of Wytheville (1863), New River Valley, Ward family, Price family, and Buchanan family.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 11.  Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 61a-82.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Buchanan family, Patton family, Calhoun family, Evans family, Stalnaker family, Doak family, Hudson family, and Alexander Phillippi, John Greiner, Neff family, Copenhaver family, Kegley family, Leedy family, Capp family, and Cassell family.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 12.  Scrapbook, Local History 2 - p. 83-106.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on Dutton family, Battle of the Cove (1864) and Federal troops' burial site, Mary Draper Ingles, slavery in Wythe County, Laurel Glen farm, and Jacob Repass.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Local History Scrapbook 3 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 13.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 1-22.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes typescripts of articles written by F. B. Kegley on Southwest Virginia for <title render="italic">Mountain Empire</title> magazine.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 14.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 23-44.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes typescripts of articles written by F. B. Kegley on Southwest Virginia for <title render="italic">Mountain Empire</title> magazine.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 15.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 45-64.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes typescripts of articles written by F. B. Kegley on Southwest Virginia for <title render="italic">Mountain Empire</title> magazine.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 16.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 65-82.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes an excerpt from <title render="italic">German New River Settlement</title> by R. S. A. Heavener.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 17.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 65-102.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes an excerpt from <title render="italic">German New River Settlement</title> by R. S. A. Heavener.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 18.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 103-144.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on address by Sherwood Anderson at Ivanhoe High School, Fotheringay, Smithfield, Lead Mines, German settlers in New River Valley, postmasters in Rural Retreat, Michael Cregger, and marriage records from Wythe County.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 19.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 145-166.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Montgomery County marriage records, Wythe County wills, Lantz family, Revolutionary War in Southwest Virginia, Wythe County history, Esther Thompson Crockett, Samuel Crockett, David Doak, James Patton, Dr. Thomas Walker, and Bible records for the Hiral Miller family.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 20.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 167-192.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Hungry Mother State Park, Stalnaker family, Harmon family, log cabins, Rural Retreat, and Johnston Memorial Hospital (Abingdon, Virginia.)
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 21.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 193-216.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Johnston Memorial Hospital (Abingdon, Virginia), Greever family, Lancaster County, Pennsylvania, and Molly Tynes.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 22.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - p. 217-236.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on Franklin D. Roosevelt's visit to Shenandoah National Park, visit of Eleanor Roosevelt to the White Top Music Festival, Wilderness Road, Appalachian Power Company Claytor Dam project, Henry Grubb family, and early German settlers.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 23.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - unnumbered pages.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes information on James Hays Piper, Shot Tower, Seven Mile Ford, Wythe County formation, and Rural Retreat.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 24.  Scrapbooks, Local History 3 - loose newspaper clippings.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes both original newspaper clippings and acid-free photocopies.  Topics include Wythe Raceway, banks in Rural Retreat, Hungry Mother State Park, cabbage, William Nuckles Doak, Rural Retreat Lake, Rural Retreat post office and postmasters, Bertha Umberger, Marion College, and Confederate monument in East End cemetery.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 4.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Local History Scrapbook 4 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 25.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 1-38.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on the Battle of New Market, Tory Oaks (hanging of Tories in Black Lick during the Revolutionary War), William Gannaway Brownlow, Wythe County postmasters, James McCall home, Wythe Freemasons, Irish immigrants in Wythe, St. John's Lutheran Church, St. Mary's Catholic Church, Presbyterian churches, McCalls (town), and tax records.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 26.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 39-79.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on Fleming Church, Molly Tynes, McCalls (town), Mt. Airy, iron industry, slavery in Wythe County, muster roll of Col. Joseph Kent, camp meetings, William Richardson's militia company, Wytheville fire, Robert Sheffey, schools, Esther Thompson Crockett, ministers, mills, R. G. Williams' land grant, and newspapers.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 27.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 80-113.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on early settlers, notes from <title render="italic">Trans-Allegheny Pioneers</title> by John P. Hale, excerpts from Chalkley's <title render="italic">Chronicles of the Scotch-Irish</title>, excerpts from <title render="italic">Kegley's Virginia Frontier</title>, and early Wythe County history.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 28.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 114-149.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on Revolutionary War militia, Crockett family, roads, churches, and Fort Chiswell.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 29.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 150-179.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on Molly Tynes, postmasters, Dr. Thomas Walker, churches, Alexander Smyth, court records, racetrack in Wythe, roads, Newberry Farm, and Lead Mines.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 30.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - p. 180-203.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on Austinville, fish hatchery, Francis Mill Creek, Molly Tynes, and Shot Tower.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 31.  Scrapbooks, Local History 4 - loose newspaper clippings.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains both original newspaper clippings and photocopies on acid-free papers.  Topics include Fort Chiswell mansion (McGavock), cattle drive by Robert H. Crockett, E. Lee Trinkle, Sally Haller Wolfenden, Appalachian Power Company, John Neff (WCC faculty), John A. Whitman, Revolutionary War soldiers from Wythe, and Stephen Austin.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 5.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Local History Scrapbook 5 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 32. Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 1-29.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on lists of Revolutionary War soldiers from Southwest Virginia and those who swore allegiance to the United States.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 33.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 30-56.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on lists of Revolutionary War soldiers and lists of Confederate units and soldiers from Southwest Virginia.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 34.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 57-89.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on lists of Confederate veterans, list of servicemen and women in World War II, list of Wythe County militia members, and list of Revolutionary War veterans.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 35.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 90-113.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on lists of Confederate solders and list of guards at Charlestown, Virginia in 1859.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 36.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 114-137.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains a newsletter from the Virginia Grand Lodge of Freemasons and lists of Confederate soldiers.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 37.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 - p. 138-187.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains lists of Confederate soldiers, history of Smyth County, and history of the Civil War.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 38.  Scrapbooks, Local History 5 -<title render="italic">Christian Herald</title> Articles.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains articles clipped from the <title render="italic">Christian Herald</title>on religious history in various states.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Scrapbooks, Local History 6
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>2 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Local History Scrapbook 6 consists of pages removed from a leather ring binder; these pages have been re-housed in acid-free folders.  Pages have been numbered in pencil and titles and descriptions noted on an index included in each folder.  Some pages (those not excerpted from books, newspapers, and periodicals) with information on families and local history have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 39.  Scrapbooks, Local History 6 - p. 1-14.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains information on taverns, stage coaches, and early education in Wythe County.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 40.  Scrapbooks, Local History 6 - p. 15-59.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains a typescript of Louise DuBose's articles on the Allen family and the Hillsville Courthouse shootings.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series XI.  Memoirs.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1960, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">7
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memoirs.  Book 1 "Memoirs of Frank R. Brown:  Also Facts and Stories About Kin Folks and Friend."
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1903-1910, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Pages are not numbered.  Articles listed below are in the order in which Frank Repass Brown placed them.  The articles have been removed from the cloth and metal three ring binder and placed in acid-free folders.  Photographs have been removed from the memoirs and placed in Series XI; photocopies of these photographs have been placed in this collection.  The folder number is indicated below.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 1.  Memoirs - Book 1 - "Preface, Memoir, Flowers &amp; Garden."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Includes : "Preface," "Memoir," and "Flowers and Gardens."  Topics (listed in order) found in "Memoir" include young childhood; relationships with sisters and brothers including Matie, Ivan, Daisie, Carrie, Charley, and Gay; relationships with relatives including Aunt Ella Repass, Oden Neff, Aunt Jennie Neff, Frank Harkrader, Tom Dixon, Alice Wetzel, and Maria Woodward; house construction; trips with his father; springs; dogs; church and Sunday school; visits to relatives; memories of church services; Rev. W. R. Brown; Rev. D. S. Fox; Rev. Sieg; Rev. Arndt; Rev. Rhodes, Rev. Griener; Rev. Barringer; Rev. Shumate; Rev. Richard; communion services at church; annual church picnic; and wedding of Mr. and Mrs. T. F. Kidd.  "Flowers and Gardens" contains discussion of favorite plants and two photographs (photocopies) of his garden and plants.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 2. Memoirs - Book 1 - "My Pet Peeve, Nick Names, Jamestown Exposition, and Miscellaneous Experiences."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1907, undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Topics (listed in order) include music; cemeteries; and dolls.  "My Pet Peeve," discusses his dislike of fetching water.  Other topics include reading; <title render="italic">National Geographic</title>; books and libraries; donation of books to libraries; diaries and scrapbooks; "Nick Names" discusses nicknames given to himself and his brother.  Other topics include child labor; jobs; farming; molasses making; chestnut hunting; Wythe County fair.  "The Jamestowne Exposition" relates his trip to Jamestown in August 1907.  "Miscellaneous Experiences" discusses his grandfather's yard sale and his embarrassment at a church picnic.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Memoirs - Book 1 - "My School Days."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1903-1910.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>"My School Days" discusses Huddle School, Rural Retreat High School (RRHS) and teachers Prof. W. R. Bowers, Dorothy Stone, and Cynthia Phillippi.  Also included are <title render="italic">Annual Announcement of Rural Retreat High School</title> for 1903, 1904, 1907; postcard of RRHS; program for RRHS 1906 artistic exercises; program for RRHS primary and intermediate department artistic exercises for 1906; program for literary societies an class in expression presentation for 1906; program for contests in elocution at RRHS 1906; programs for 1906 and 1910 graduation at RRHS; reports cards for 1904 and 1905; and drawing of RRHS in 1910.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 4.  Memoirs - Book 1 - "My Trip to Kansas."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1908.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>"My Trip to Kansas" discusses his trip to visit his cousin T. B. Shannon in Iola, Kansas; his case of smallpox; his visit to Iola Carnegie Library; Oklahoma City; and White family.  "My Trip" also relates visit with uncle Reuben Repass in Graham, Texas.  Included is a smallpox quarantine certificate, five bulletins from First Presbyterian Church in Iola, Kansas; program for Altruistic Club banquet; and two sales slips for R. B. Shannon hardware store.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 5.  Memoirs - Books 1 - "Rat Decalogue and "Most Unusual Trip."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Topics include his experiences at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (V.P.I.); his roommates E. G. Goodwin and Karl Emil Edward Quantz; his work in the agriculture department; and "Rat Decalogue."  "A Most Unusual Trip" chronicles his trip on a V.P.I. Agricultural Department train excursion with professors and Virginia Railroad officials.  ALso included are six report cards; diploma for two year course in "Practical Agriculture and Farm Mechanics;" blueprint map of the V.P.I. campus, and a letter of recommendation from Prof. N. S. Mayo.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 6.  Memoirs - Book 1.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1908-1910.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes a booklet "Regulations for Virginia Polytechnic Institute 1908," place name card; program for "First Annual Banquet of the Agricultural Students," and graduation programs for 1909 and 1910.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memoirs Book 2.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>8 folders.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Pages are not numbered.  Articles listed below are in the order in which Frank Repass Brown placed them.  The articles have been removed from the cloth and metal three ring binder and placed in acid-free folders.  Photographs have been removed from the memoirs and placed in Series XI; photocopies of these photographs have been placed in this collection.  The folder number is indicated below.  Photocopies of Memoir Book 2 may be found in the Kegley Library vertical files under "Brown, Frank Repass."
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
				
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 7.  Memoirs - Books 2 - "My  Life and About My Parents."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Topics in "My Life" include the house of his grandfather Brown that was also the first home of his parents.  Photocopies of photograph of this farm are included.  "My Parents" discusses his father Michael Dallas Brown, and mother Emily Repass Brown and their families.  Writings about his father include his character, Civil War service, farming experiences, and his death from peritonitis.  He describes his mother's character, family, work, personal habits, cooking ability, and experiences during the Civil War.  He also discusses his parents' schooling and love of horses.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 8.  Memoirs - Book 2 - Grandparents, Michael Cassell, and Michael Brown.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder includes "My Grandparents and My Great Grandparents" which discusses the Civil War service of grandfather William Henry Brown, uncle Reuben Repass, and grandfather Gordon Repass.  He also writes about his grandmother Anna Sharitz Repass, great-grandfather Michael Brown, his great-grandfather Jacob Cassell Sr., and great-great-grandfather John Repass.  Articles are titled "Michael Cassell," "Michael Brown's Will," "Notes on the Life of Michael Brown, his Family, and Estate," and "Michael Brown's Grandchildren." 
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 9.  Memoirs - Book 2 - "My Kinfolk, Signs and Superstitions, and Sluss Family Massacre."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Brown discusses his relatives Newton Umberger, Mike Buchanan, Virginia Umberger Brown (his wife), Anna Marie Brown, Reuben Repass, Rufus Repass, Benjamin Brown, Ephraim Brown, Joseph Rufus Brown, and Sarah Shannon Repass.  Also included in this folder is an excerpt from <title render="italic">History of Augusta County, Virginia</title> by J. Lewis Peyton.  "Signs and Superstitions" examines beliefs of German settlers and "Sluss Family Massacre" discusses attack on Sluss family by native Americans in the 1770s.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 10.  Memoirs - Book 2 - "Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place, My Personal Expenses, and  Pets."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1905-1920.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>In "Visit to My Grandfather Repass' Last Resting Place," Brown discusses visit to Point Lookout, Maryland and Gordon Repass.  Other writings include transcripts of Civil War letters written by Brown relatives, walnuts candle stand, his farm pets and disdain of domestic pets, and rocking chairs.  Also included is a record of his personal expenses from 1905 to 1920.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 11.  Memoirs - Book 2 - New House and Moving.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1960
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>In "My Visit to the New House," "My Sale, January 21, 1960," "Moving," and "Winter 1960," Brown discusses his experiences in moving into his new house, and snowfall in February and March 1960.  Also included is certificate and award from Future Farmers of America.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 12.  Memoirs - Book 2 - New Year and Animals.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Includes articles "New Year Resolutions," "Game and Hunting," "Cranky Idea About Town Children," "The Old Pine Tree," "Pea Fowls," "Watches," and "Christmas.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 13.  Memoirs - Book 2 - Holidays, Slavery, and Jacob Cassell.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Articles include "Thanksgiving," "Cemeteries," "Slavery," "Hidden Treasures or Hidden Gold," and "Jacob Cassell Sr. House."  He also discusses name variation, higher education for women, Brown family tradition of equal inheritance for men and women, Marion College and Brown family involvement.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 14.  Memoirs - Book 2 - Biography and Family.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1915, undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains photocopies of photographs of Frank Repass Brown as a young child, teenager, college student, and adult.  Also included is the booklet, "Life Sketch of Rev. John C. Repass," typescript "The Repass Family by S. S. Cassell, 1915," program "Dramatic Recital of Olive Repass," notes on children of Emily Virginia Repass and Michael Dallas Brown, newspaper obituary of Ivan Josiah Brown, and newspaper clipping regarding election of Frank Repass Brown as honorary Lifetime Director of the Rural Retreat Fair Association.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Memoirs - Book 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1887, 1960, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">7
	</container>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Pages are not numbered.  Articles listed below are in the order in which Frank Repass Brown placed them.  The articles have been removed from the cloth and metal three ring binder and placed in acid-free folders.  Photographs have been removed from the memoirs and placed in Series XI; photocopies of these photographs have been placed in this collection.  The folder number is indicated below.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 15.  Memoirs - Book 3.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1887, 1960, undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This folder contains photocopies of photographs of Frank Repass Brown, Virginia Umberger Brown, Michael Dallas Brown, Emily Repass Brown, Josiah Brown, Elizabeth Groseclose Brown, and Anna Sharitz Repass.  Other items in this folder include notes on car trip and fuel consumption (November 1960), flyer regarding auction of his farm (1960), baptism card for Virginia Alpha Umberger (1887), and "Southwestern State Hospital," regarding donation of books and magazines.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series XII.  Photographs.
<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">8
</container>
<physdesc>8 envelopes.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 1 - Brown Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>19 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope includes 19 photographs of Emily Repass Brown, Florence E. Repass, Josie Brown Hudson, Carrie Brown, Mattie Brown, Charley Brown, Gay Brown, Elizabeth Groseclose Brown, Josiah Brown, Michael Dallas Brown, Isaac Brown, Hezakiah Brown, William Brown, Daisie Brown, Ivan J. Brown, and Frank Repass Brown.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 2.  Frank Repass Brown.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>20 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope includes 20 photograph of Frank Repass Brown and wife Virginia Umberger Brown.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 3.  Repass Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope contains 8 photographs of Seldon Repass, Mary E. Repass, Ellen M. Repass, Florence E. Repass, Anna M. Sharitz Repass, and tombstone of John Jacob Repass.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 4.  Shannon Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>9 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope contains 9 photographs of Dale Shannon, Brown Shannon, Marion Shannon, Jerome Shannon, Dallas Shannon, Thomas B. Shannon, George D. Shannon, George Shannon, and Carrie Brown Shannon.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 5.  Umberger Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>7 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope contains 7 photographs of Ella G. Repass Umberger, Chloe Umberger, Repass Umberger, Anna K. Umberger, Virginia A. Umberger, Lois E. Umberger, Stephen A. Umberger, and Margaret Repass Umberger.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 6.  Other Families.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 photographs, 8 greeting cards.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope includes 8 photographs of Joe Bill White, Jimmy White, Paul White, Mollie Neff, John Neff, Stephen Sharitz, Kate CasselL Schrock, Fletch Lloyd, Thomas Jonathan Jackson (Stonewall Jackson), Robert Edward Lee, and 8 greeting cards.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 7.  Places.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>10 photographs.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope contains 10 photographs of Brown farm, Quaker Church in Speedwell, Huddle School, and Frank Repass Brown house and garden.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Envelope 8.  Unidentified.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>20 photographs.	
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Envelope contains 20 unidentified photographs.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		</c02>
	</c01>
	</dsc>
	</archdesc>
	</ead>
		