<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00095">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00095::A Guide to the Repass-Umberger Family Papers, 1819-1968)//EN" "viwyc00095.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Repass-Umberger Family Papers, <date>1819-1968</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Repass-Umberger Family, Papers, 1819-1968
<num type="collectionnumber">2004.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>15 June 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Repass-Umberger Family Papers, <date>1819-1968</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2004.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Repass-Umberger Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1819-1968
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2004.5
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">25 folders; 124 photographs.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Repass-Umberger Family Papers, Mss. Collection 2004.5, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Margaret Cobb Wampler in 2004.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The son of William Repass and Barbara Harkrader, Gordon Repass was born on 12 January 1819 in Black Lick in the western portion of Wythe County, Virginia.  He married Anna Magdalena Sharitz, daughter of Daniel Sharitz and Mary Sluss Sharitz on 21 March 1839.  Anna Sharitz was born on 12 February 1819.  The couple had ten children as follows:  Elmira J. Repass (1839-1841), Reuben F. Repass (1841-1922), Richard T. Repass (1844-1858), Mary E. Repass (1846-1869), Emily V. Repass (1848-1924), Selden W. L. Repass (1850-1929), unnamed infant (1852), Clementina E. Repass (1854-1862), Margaret B. Repass (1857-1937), and Ella G. Repass (1864-1944).
</p>
<p>Like generations before him, Gordon Repass farmed the fertile soil of Black Lick.  When Civil War erupted, he was forty-two and did not expect to serve in the Confederate Army as did his son, Reuben, who enlisted in the 8th Virginia Cavalry Regiment in 1861.  Gordon joined the home guards (4th Regiment, Virginia Reserves) early in the conflict.  However, Confederate military authorities sent Repass to join the 1st Virginia Infantry Regiment in the trenches around Richmond late in 1864.  In his letters home to Anna, he writes about his futile attempts to be discharged from this regiment or to be reassigned to the home defense guard or reserve units.  Captured by Federal soldiers on 6 April 1865 near Farmville, Repass died of dysentery at Point Lookout Prison, Maryland, on 3 May 1865.  He is buried at the prison.  Anna Sharitz Repass never remarried, raising her children and managing the farm by herself.  She died on 7 March 1899.</p>
<p>His son, Reuben F. Repass, survived the war and married Ellen Missouri Brown on 25 April 1865.  In 1869, Reuben and Ellen, with their children Lee Gordon and Laura Edna, moved to Missouri where they lived until 1876 when they relocated to Texas.  His wife Ellen died on 14 August 1904 and he later married Lizzie Wright.  Reuben died in Graham, Texas on 1 August 1922.</p>
<p>Margaret B. Repass married Stephen A. Umberger on 5 November 1877.  They had the following children:  Chloe A. Umberger (1878-1939; married Walter Spence), Gordon Repass Umberger (1880-1945), Lois E. Umberger (1882-1974), Anna K. Umberger (1883-1933), Virginia A. Umberger (1885-1953; married Frank Repass Brown), infant son (1893), and Margaret Belle Umberger (b. 1894; married Edgar Cobb).  Margaret B. Repass Umberger died on 10 January 1937 and Stephen A. Umberger died on 15 December 1924.</p>
<p>Selden W. L. Repass married 1) Elizabeth Florence Earhart (1848-1893) by whom he had a daughter, Olive Anna Repass (married Walter B. Brown); 2) Lula Mae Umberger Repass (1868-1898); 3) Ella B. Patterson (1867-1938).  Selden Repass died on 3 June 1929.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Series I, Correspondence (1862-1920, undated), contains letters sent by Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass and their family during the Civil War.  Repass, conscripted into the 1st Virginia Infantry Regiment, C. S. A. in 1864, spent his service in the defenses around Richmond, Virginia.  Captured in April 1865, he died at Point Lookout prison in Maryland on 3 May 1865 from dysentery.  Photocopies of letters written by his son Reuben F. Repass, who moved to Texas after the Civil War, are also included in this series as is correspondence of other family members.
</p>
<p>Series II, Financial Records (1847-1925, undated), is comprised of two account books, promissory notes, receipts, and tax tickets.  One account book, dating 1847 to 1899, contains financial transactions by Gordon Repass, Anna Sharitz Repass, and Selden W. L. Repass and an inventory of Gordon Repass' estate.  A letter from Selden W. L. Repass to Reuben F. Repass is also in the book. The other account book, kept by Anna Sharitz Repass from 1858 to 1880, is comprised of financial transactions and a memoir by Reuben F. Repass <title render="doublequote">The Campaign of 1861.</title>  This account book also has various notes on family history and vital records.  Photocopies of many of these records have been placed in the Kegley Library files.</p>
<p>Series III, Legal Records (1849-1904), contains deeds between Gordon Repass, Selden W. L. Repass, Reuben F. Repass, Stephen A. Umberger and others.  Also included in this series are records pertaining to the estate of Anna Magdalena Sharitz Repass who died on 7 March 1899.</p>
<p>Series IV, Genealogical Records (1819-1968, undated), contains a wealth of family history information collected by Anna Sharitz Repass and her granddaughters, Lois Ella Umberger and Margaret Belle Umberger Cobb.  Specifically, this series contains four memorandum books kept by Anna Sharitz Repass in which she recorded daily events and weather.  Other material includes obituaries and research notes on the Repass, Umberger, Sharitz, Doak, Howe and Huddle families as well as photocopies of records from the Bible of Gordon Repass.  Correspondence and research notes of Lois E. Umberger and Margaret Bell Umberger Cobb (descendants of Gordon Repass and Stephen A. Umberger) regarding Umberger family history are also in this series.  A photograph of the 1819 fraktur (baptismal certificate) of Anna Sharitz Repass is also in this series.  Photocopies of many of these records have been placed in the Kegley Library vertical files.</p>
<p>Series V, Miscellaneous Records (1845-1908, undated), includes records of Marvin Methodist Church and the Black Lick Farmers Club as well as literary manuscripts by Maggie B. Repass Umberger and others.</p>
<p>Series VI, Photographs, contains 124 photographs (sepia, black and white, and ferrotypes) of members of the Brown, Cobb, Cox, King, Minter, Repass, Sharitz, Spence, Topham and Umberger families.</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>
<persname role="author">Gose, George B.</persname>
<title render="italic">Pioneers of the Virginia Bluegrass.</title>
<imprint>Radford, VA: Commonwealth Press, 
<date type="publication">1971.</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
<bibref>
<persname role="author">Hoch, Beverly Repass.</persname>
<title render="doublequote">The Civil War Journal and Letters of Reuben F. Repass.</title>
<title render="italic">Wythe County Historical Review. </title>58.
<imprint>
<date type="publication">July 2000: 1-12.</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
<bibref>
<persname role="author">Hoch, Beverly Repass.</persname>
<title render="italic">From Ziefen to Sally Run:  Swiss Pioneer Jacob Repass (1734-1814) on the American Frontier.</title>
<imprint>Albuquerque, NM: Jacob Repass Memorial Fund, <date type="publication">1993.</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
<bibref>
<persname role="author">Umberger, Arthur D.</persname>
<title render="italic">Umberger (Umbarger) Family Chart.</title>
<imprint>
Aldan, PA.: Umberger, <date type="publication">1981.</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series I.  Correspondence.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1862-1920, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence - Gordon Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1862, 1864.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">1
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">31 March 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pen.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He requests her prayers during his time of military service and asks her to guide their children's religious training.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Camp Lee, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 November 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>he writes about his new assignment to the 1st Virginia Infantry Regiment encamped near Richmond, Virginia.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 November 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his mess-mates J. P. Sharitz, Alfred Catron, John Thomas and Michael Thomas, picket duty, church services in camp, and instructions for hog butchering.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">20 November 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his camp meals and cooking, skirmish with enemy, and religious life.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">27 November 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes from Camp Duns, 4 miles southeast of Chester Station in the trenches, about illnesses of A. Hines, J. P. Sharitz, and William Kegley, his failed attempts to get reassigned, camp rations, and instructions for harvest.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">12 December 1864
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>he writes regarding his illness, picket duty, attempts to get him home, and hog butchering instructions.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">30 December 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He comments on her description of Yankee raid into Wythe County [Stoneman's raid], his picket duty, and her stolen horse.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - Gordon Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">January - February 1865.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">2
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 January 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his rheumatism, official denial of his request for discharge from Robert E. Lee, his desire to be reassigned to reserve forces, and his intention to seek counsel from an attorney and issue of writ of habeas corpus.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">7 January 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his illness (probably dysentery), picket duty, thrashing of grain, his hunger, prayer meeting in camp, his clothing and laundry chores, and wounding of their son Reuben Repass.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8, 9 January 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his lack of food and hunger and new position near the James River.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">3 February 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his failed efforts to get reassigned to the reserve forces because he was not forty-five when he was conscripted.  He also requests a box of provisions from home including meat, bread, cornmeal, flour, beans, fruit, and soap.  On reverse:  Reuben Repass, Wytheville, Virginia to Gordon Repass.  18 January 1865.  1 p.; pen.  He encloses certificate of his father's age from court records.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">12 February 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">2:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his rheumatism, his stomach and head pains, high cost of food, and his beliefs that the Confederacy will not last because of lack of grain.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">[12 February 1865].
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He wishes her a happy birthday and gives instructions and messages to his children.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">16 February 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his recovery from yellow jaundice an the again requests a box of provisions.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter. Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass and Reuben Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">20 February 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his rheumatism, low rations, and high prices for provisions.  He inquiries about payment of the tax-in-kind in grain, provides instructions for farming, and mentions deserters.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Camp Howlett, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass and Reuben Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">23 February 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:9
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; faded.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his bad health.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - Gordon Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">March - June 1865.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">3
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 March 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his regiment's relocation to Duns Farm and the possibility of movement to Petersburg, receipt of the box of provisions, and his continued strategy to get reassigned to the reserve forces.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia, in the trenches below Richmond, to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">20 March 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pencil; torn.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He describes the constant marching of the regiment and his failed efforts to get reassigned.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Henrico County, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">24 March 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about constant marching and his meeting with their son, Reuben F. Repass who adds a note, dated 25 March 1865.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Chesterfield County, Virginia, encamped 2 miles northeast of Petersburg, to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">29 March 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.; pencil; faded; torn.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his dashed hopes of ever getting reassigned to reserve forces.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass, Point Lookout Prison Camp, Maryland to Selden W. L. Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">9 April 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; faded.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He urges his children to obey their mother and not neglect their education. Transcription by Beverly Repass Hoch included.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>John P. Sharitz, Point Lookout, Maryland to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">10 May 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">3:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pen.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He informs her that Gordon Repass died from chronic dysentery.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  V. I. Heintz, Assistant Adjutant General, Office Commissary General of Prisoners, Washington, D. C. to R. F. Repass, Wytheville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">12 June 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">3:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He informs him that Gordon Repass died on 4 May 1865 at Point Lookout, Maryland from chronic dysentery.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - Gordon Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">4
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">4:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He complains that <title render="doublequote">there is no chance for a man to get justice in this part of the army.</title>
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder" type="folder">4:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pencil; fragment.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He requests peaches and thread.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; fragment.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He gives recommendations for farming.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">4:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; fragment.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He gives instructions for sending box of provisions.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pencil; fragment.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He discusses foods he misses eating with his family.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gordon Repass to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">4:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pen; fragment.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about box of provisions and attempts to be reassigned to reserve forces.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Envelope addressed to Mrs. A. M. Repass, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">4:7
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Envelope addressed to Mr. Gordon Repass, Co. K, 1st Virginia Infantry, Terry's Brigade, Pickett's Division, Army Northern Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:8
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Scrap of paper with address of Gordon Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:9
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence - Gordon Repass - Transcripts and Notes.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">5
	</container>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Typed transcripts of letters written by Gordon Repass and notes on a exhibit prepared for the Wythe County Historical Society.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - Reuben Repass - Photocopies.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1869-1920, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">6
	</container>
	<physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Photocopies of letters written by Reuben Repass, son of Gordon Repass and Anna Sharitz Repass.  The original letters are in a private collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Rose Hill, Missouri to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">17 October 1869.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about family illness and farming,  His wife, Ellen Missouri Brown Repass, writes to Mary Repass.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Rose Hill, Missouri to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 January 1870.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about death of Mary Repass.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Rose Hill, Missouri to Emily V. Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 May 1870.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about farming and the type of settlers wanted in Missouri.  His wife, Ellen Missouri Brown Repass adds a brief note.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, South Prairie, Texas to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 January 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about farming and plans to build a house.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Victor, Colorado to "Dear Sister."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 May 1905.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his visit to his son Lee Gordon Repass, mining, and describes the town of Victor.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Ivan, Texas to "Dear Sister."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">7 November 1917.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his health, World War I, and farming.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Ivan, Texas to "Dear Sister." 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">27 October 1918.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his grandchildren, Ellen Kennedy, Lee Repass, and Fred Kennedy, weather, oil exploration, and World War II.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Ivan, Texas to "Dear Sister."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 August 1920.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about his vertigo and deafness and farming.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, Graham, Texas to "Dear Sister."
		<unitdate type="inclusive">5 October 1920.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:9
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about leasing his land to oil companies and his family.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Poem.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">6:10
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; photocopy.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Poem written by Reuben F. Repass to his sisters during the Civil War, <title render="doublequote">An Answer to Do They Miss Me at Home.</title>
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1877.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder" type="folder">7
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Stephen A. Sharitz, McMinn County, Tennessee to Gordon Repass, Black Lick, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 October 1849.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pen.; transcription included.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about Gordon Repass' conversion to Christianity and farming.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Emma Repass, Wythe County, Virginia to [unknown] Harkrader.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">16 August 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pen.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>She refuses his attentions speaking <title render="doublequote">plainly and deliberately upon the subject.</title>
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Scott &amp; Bolling Company, Richmond, Virginia to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 November 1869.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pen; transcription included.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>They write regarding sales of butter.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  A. Marco Davis to Margaret Repass, Black Lick, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">28 December 1875.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pen; envelope.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He inquires if he could escort her to Macedonia Church next Sunday.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter. R. Sharitz, Neosha Falls, Woodson County, Kansas to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">26 December 1875.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.; pen; torn; transcription included.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about family of George Shannon, his family, cost of livestock, and his health.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Ella G. Repass to Margaret B. Repass Umberger, Wytheville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 December 1877.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">7:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; envelope; transcription included.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>She requests that she bring pieces from her navy blue dress so she can fix her basque.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1903, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Folder." type="folder.">8
	</container>
	<physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Anna Sharitz Repass, Black Lick, Virginia to Emily V. Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">15 January 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; pencil; transcription.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>She writes about her health, illness of various neighbors, and death of Mr. Crowgie.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, South Prairie, Texas to Stephen Umberger.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">23 December 1899.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>He writes about family and farming.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Reuben F. Repass, South Prairie, Texas to S. A. Umberger and Maggie Repass Umberger.  
		<unitdate type="inclusive">23 December 1899.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pen; envelope.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Receipt for $64.26 for settlement of estate of Anna Sharitz Repass.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Stephen Neel Umberger to Lois Umberger.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1903.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; typed.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Written when he was seven years old.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Ella Repass Umberger, Oakland, Maryland to Margaret Repass Umberger, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>8 p.; pen.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>She writes about weather, chickens, family, and church functions.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  [unknown] to Lois Umberger and Anna Umberger.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pencil.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Writer thanks them for Bible.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  F. Davis to Anna Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; pen.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Davis thanks her for apples.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Oath of Allegiance to United States by Anna M. Sharitz Repass.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 November 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:8
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Four envelopes.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item." type="folder-item.">8:9
		</container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II.  Financial Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1925, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Financial Records - Account Book.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1899.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 account book; 129 leaves, 260 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Account book used by Gordon Repass, Anna Sharitz Repass, and Selden W. L. Repass from 1847 to 1879 and 1898 to 1899.  The book records transactions between the Repass family and neighbors revolving around home work and farming.  Included also are notes on the funeral of Anna Sharitz Repass, inventory of the estate of Gordon Repass dated 27 November 1865, and copy of letter by Selden W. L. Repass to Reuben Repass.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Account Book of Anna Sharitz Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1858-1880.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">
	</container>
	<physdesc>1 account book; 59 leaves, 118 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This account book, used by Anna Sharitz Repass, Reuben Repass, and others, contains financial transactions from 1858 to 1899, family notes, and a Civil War memoir by Reuben Repass entitled, <title render="doublequote">The Campaign of 1861.</title></p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Financial Records - Promissory Notes and Receipts.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1847-1925, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">
	</container>
	<physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains 1847 promissory notes from William Repass and Jonathan Repass to Joseph Fisher; 1846-1847 promissory notes from Gordon Repass to William Repass; 1849 promissory note from Gordon Repass to W. B. Winton; 1849 promissory notes from Gordon Repass to William Repass; 1856 statement of Gordon Repass in account with William W. Hedrick; 1857-1858 statement of Gordon Repass in account with William Gibboney; 1857 statement to Gordon Repass in account with John Buchanan and Company; 1862 receipt from W. P. Haller to Gordon Repass; 1869 promissory notes of Anna M. repass, administrator of Gordon Repass' estate, to John P. Sharitz; 1879 account statement of William Repass; undated inventory of Maggie REpass Umberger and Emily Repass Brown; undated bill of work for Gordon Repass; and 1925 receipt from Lindsey &amp; Killinger funeral home for funeral of Stephen Umberger.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Financial Records - Tax Tickets.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1854-1882.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box" type="box">
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains tax tickets as follows:  Wythe County and Virginia state tax for Gordon Repass, 1854; Wythe County and Virginia state tax for Gordon Repass, 1860; Wythe County tax for A. M. Repass, 1882; Wythe County tax for Ella G. Repass, 1881, 1882;  Wythe COunty tax for Selden W. L. Repass, 1882; and Wythe County tax for Maggie B. Repass, Umberger, 1881.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Legal Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1904
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Legal Records - Deeds.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1877.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains deeds as follows:  16 November 1849 between Wiley B. Winton and Sophia Winton and Gordon Repass; 17 July 1877 between Reuben F. Repass and Ellen M. Repass of Texas and Selden W. L. Repass of Virginia; 4 December 1877 between F. S. Blair, Commissioner of the Circuit Court of Wythe County, in the chancery suit of M. D. Brown and wife vs. Reuben Repass and Maggie B. Repass re: real estate of Gordon Repass; 4 December 1877 between F. S. Blair, Commissioner of the Circuit Court of Wythe County, in the chancery suit of M. D. Brown and Reuben Repass and Selden W. L. Repass re: the real estate of Gordon Repass.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Legal Records - Deeds.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1904.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains deeds as follows:  29 August 1883 between Selden W. L. Repass and E. F. Repass and Stephen A. Umberger; 12 December 1883 between Reuben F. Repass and Ellen M. Repass of Texas and Stephen A. Umberger; 14 February 1885 between Edly Doak, John C. Brown, William F. Cloyd, and Canaro D. Doak of one part and Stephen A. Umberger of the other part re: old Macedonia Church property; 1 September 1904 between Ella G. Repass Umberger and J. B. Umberger of Ohio and Maggie B. Umberger.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Legal Records - Estate of Anna Sharitz Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1899.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains account statements regarding settlement of the estate of Anna Sharitz Repass, an inventory of property, and a bill from Lindsey &amp; Killinger Funeral Home of Rural Retreat, Virginia for her funeral expenses.  She died on 7 March 1899.</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV.  Genealogical Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1819-1968, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>7 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Genealogical Records - Memorandum Books of Anna Sharitz Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1898.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Anna Sharitz Repass recorded daily events and weather in these four <title render="doublequote">Pierce's Memorandum and Account Books.</title>  Book 1 includes entries from December 1882 to September 1883; Book 2 includes entries from December 1883 to 1891; Book 3 includes entries from October 1888 to 1893; Book 4 includes entries from April 1892 to 1898.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Genealogical Records - Repass, Sharitz and Umberger Families.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1899, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains the following items:  <title render="doublequote">In Memoriam, Mrs. Margaret Repass Umberger,</title> undated; obituaries of Stephen Sharitz (18960, Alpha Umbarger, Annie Magdalene Sharitz Repass (1899), and Guy Sharitz (1888); notes on Daniel Sharitz family; 2 copies of family ancestral chart of Margaret Umberger Cobb (Umberger family, Repass family, Sharitz family, and Kegley family); photocopy of land tracts from chancery suit, M. D. Brown vs. Gordon Repass heirs; and photocopy excerpts from various publications on the Repass family including <title render="doublequote">Repass Line</title> and <title render="doublequote">Ancestry Record of the Family of Rippas Von Ziefen.</title>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Genealogical Records - Clippings on the Doak, Howe and Huddle Families.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1930-1968, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>9 items
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains newspaper clippings and notes as follows:  notes on Doak family on back of envelope; <title render="doublequote">R. R. Union Counsel Named by Hoover to Succeed Davis,</title> re: William Nuckles Doak; <title render="doublequote">Vestiges of Frontier Era, </title>by Goodridge Wilson (April 1953) re: Huddle family; <title render="doublequote">Old Mills of Wythe County: Doaks Mill;</title> <title render="doublequote">A Log House and Its Family, </title>by Goodridge Wilson (1968) re: William Nuckles Doak; <title render="doublequote">Wythe County HOme Where Doak Spent Boyhood, </title>(1930); <title render="doublequote">BOok Traces Howe Family from 1730s;</title> and <title render="doublequote">An Augusta Farm Boy Who Made His Mark, </title>by Goodridge Wilson (1968) re: Rev. Samuel Doak.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Genealogical Records - Photocopies from the Family Bible of Gordon Repass.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains photocopies of family records from the Bible of Gordon Repass that remains in the possession of the family.  Included are birth, marriage, and death records for Repass family, Sharitz family, Brown family, Earhart family, Patterson family, and Umberger family.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Genealogical Records - Umberger Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1923-1957, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains family papers of Lois Ella Umberger and Margaret Belle Umberger Cobb, daughters of Margaret B. Repass Umberger and Stephen A. Umberger.  Included are letters: 1) Katrina Umberger to Lois Umberger, 1923 re: Umberger and Lampe families; 2) Maud Umberger to Lois Umberger, 1924, re: William Umberger and Mary Sharitz, Augusta Umberger and Robert Repass, John Umberger and Mary Repass; 3) Maud Umberger to Lois Umberger, 1957, re: family matters.  Also included are Umberger family Bible records, <title render="doublequote">Family of S. A. Umberger</title> and <title render="doublequote">Children, Grandchildren, and Great-Grandchildren of S. A. Umberger and Margaret R. Umberger.</title>  A typescript article, <title render="doublequote">The Umbergers of Southwest Virginia</title> completes the folder.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Genealogical Records - Umberger Family Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains family papers of Lois Ella Umberger and Margaret Belle Umberger Cobb, daughters of Margaret B. Repass Umberger and Stephen A. Umberger.  Included in this folder are notes on Henry Umberger of Rose Hill; notes on Leonard Umberger and family; several scraps of paper with notes about various Sluss family and Umberger family members. and typescript, <title render="doublequote">Umberger Family Tree.</title>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Genealogical Records - Anna Magdalena Sharitz - Fraktur Photograph.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1819.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 item.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a photograph of a fraktur (baptismal certificate) for Anna Magdalena Sharitz,
daughter of Daniel Sharitz and Maria Magdalena Sluss, dated 12 February 1819.  The original fraktur in a private collection.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series V.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1845-1908, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Miscellaneous Records - Marvin Methodist Church.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1845 - 1907.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains records from Marvin Methodist Church.  Included are: deed dated 26 June 1845 between Mary Newland,
Eli Davis and Margaret Davis of the one part and Solomon Harkrader, Robert N. Ward, Samuel W. Lloyd, James Doak, Edley Doak, Nicholas W. Winn, and Austin Miller, Trustees, for construction of Methodist church; subscription, 1880, for construction of new church building; 1905 account statement for church improvements; and 1906-1907 account statement for Marvin Church building fund.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Miscellaneous Records - Black Lick Farmers Club Programs.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1902-1908.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains programs from the Black Lick Farmers Club for 1902, 1904, 1905, 1906, 1907 and 1908.  The programs provide the topic, host, and speaker for monthly meetings.  The Club's mission was to <title render="doublequote">promote good fellowship an neighborly feeling, secure mutual improvement in mind and morals, and to seek the best methods in husbandry and housewifery.</title>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Miscellaneous Records - Literary Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1876 - 1878, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains various literary works including:  essay, <title render="doublequote">Our Friends,</title> dated 17 June 1876, probably by M. B. Repass; writings by Maggie B. Repass, 1877, 1878, regarding her marriage to Stephen A. Umberger with transcription; undated essay, <title render="doublequote">Spring,</title> by M. B. Repass; undated essay, <title render="doublequote">Loved Ones,</title> by Mr. Repass; and untitled and undated poem by <title render="doublequote">F.</title> of Black Lick, Virginia.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VI.  Photographs.
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>124 photographs.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Photographs of Carrie Emmenetta Brown; Charlie Cassell Brown; Effie Gay Love Brown King; Frank Repass Brown; Olive Anna Repass Brown; Virginia Umberger Brown; Gordon Brown; Michael Dallas Brown; Emily Repass Brown; Joe Cassell; Missionary meeting at Corinth Lutheran Church and Marvin Methodist Church at Stephen Sidney Cassell house; Margaret Belle Umberger Cobb; Louise Cox and William Lee Cox Jr.; Kay Cox; Ellen Kennedy Cox; Laura Repass Kennedy; M. O. Kennedy and family; Frank Cox; Claude Cox; Lon Cox; William Lee Cox Jr.; Campbell Crowain; E. M. Davis, Sullens Doak; Rev. T. K. Handy; S. K. Harkrader; Victor King; Daisy Newman; Michael Newman; Ray Newman; Josephine Umberger Minter; J. T. Minter; John Topham; Josephine Katherine Minter; Harry Minter; Lewis MInter; Alma E. Sharitz; Anna Magdalena Sharitz Repass; Elizabeth Florence Earhart Repass; Ivan E. Repass; Lee Gordon Repass home in Graham, Texas; Lula Mae Umberger Repass; Mary Repass, Reuben F. Repass home in Texas; Selden W. L. Repass; Roanoke College faculty; Elizabeth Johnston Ryan; Clyde Ryan; Alma E. Sharitz; Charlie Sharitz; Gleaves Sharitz; Guy Sharitz; Sally Sharitz; John A. Sharitz; Reuben Sharitz; Stephen Sharitz; Susan Sharitz; Sluss family home site; Chloe A. Umberger Spence; Rev. W. L. Thompson; Steven Topham; Anna K. Umberger; Lois E. Umberger; Virginia A. Umberger Brown; Daisy Marion Howe Umberger; Ella G. Repass Umberger; James B. Umberger; Ross E. Umberger; Gordon Repass Umberger; Lee Umberger; Margaret B. Repass Umberger; Paul Umberger. R. L. Umberger; Stephen Umberger; Stephen Neel Umberger; Tom Umberger; Laurel Glen farm.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
	