<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00045">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00045::A Guide to the Hurst Family Papers, [1900-2004])//EN" "viwyc00045.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hurst Family Papers, <date>[1900-2004]</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Hurst Family, Papers, [1900-2004]
<num type="collectionnumber">2004.8
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>31 October 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hurst Family Papers, <date>[1900-2004]</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2004.8
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Hurst Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">[1990-2004]
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2004.8
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">92 folders..
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Hurst Family Papers, Mss Collection 2004.8, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Pamela K. Lawrence Martinson, daughter of Gwendolyn Hurst, through William Hurst in 2005.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Gwendolyn Jane Hurst, a archaeologist and genealogist, was born on 3 February 1939 in Emporia, Kansas to William Floyd Hurst and Alma Lydia Renschler Hurst.  She graduated from Washington State University and worked as an archaeologist in Hawaii (Bishop Museum), Alaska, and Thunderbird Archaeology Association in Winchester, Virginia.  She also served in the Peace Corps in the 1980s.  Gwen Hurst published several articles on archaeology and also was the author of <title render="italic">U. S. Medals and Rolls of Honor, Civil War</title>.
</p>
<p>In the 1990s and early 2000s, Hurst did extensive research into the Hurst family and its allied family lines including the Adams, Breeding, Harrell, Nunn, Odell, and Southern families.  She visited repositories across the country and regularly corresponded with other researchers.  the culmination of this research may be found in the Hurst Family Papers.</p>
<p>Gwendolyn Hurst died on 6 October 2004 in Strasburg, Virginia and was buried in the Maplewood Memorial Lawn cemetery.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection has been maintained in its original order.  Folders are arranged in geographical order and then by various family members.  Contents of the <title render="italic">Hurst Family - Wythe County</title> folder have been photocopied and placed in the Kegley Library vertical file collection.
</p>
<p>Folders include research notes, photocopies, correspondence, and excerpts from primary and secondary sources for Hurst family members in England, colonial America, several Virginia counties, Indiana, Kansas, Kentucky, maryland, Missouri, NOrth Carolina, Ohio, South Carolina, Tennessee, and West Virginia,.  Counties in Virginia include Amelia, Augusta, Bedford, Botetourt, Brunswick, Carolina, Carroll, Culpeper, Elizabeth, Essex, Fairfax, Fauquier, Finacastle, Frederick, Gloucester, Halifax, Henrico, Isle of Wight, Jefferson, King and Queen, King George, King William, Lancaster, Lee, Loudoun, Mathews, Mercer, Montgomery, Nelson, New Kent, Norfolk, Northumberland, Orange, Page, Prince William, Pulaski, Rappahannock, Richmond, Roanoke, Russell, Shenandoah, Southampton, Spotsylvania, Stafford, Tazewell, Warren, Washington, Westmoreland, Wythe, and York </p>
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>
