<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viwyc00146">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00146::A Guide to the Pope Miscellaneous Collection, 1926-1957, Undated)//EN" "viwyc00146.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Pope Miscellaneous Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-1957, Undated</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Pope Miscellaneous Collection, 1926-1957, Undated
<num type="collectionnumber">2013.2
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2013 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">20 March 2013</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Pope Miscellaneous Collection, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-1957, Undated</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2013.2
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2013
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Pope Miscellaneous Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-1957, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2013.2
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">2 folders.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p> Pope Miscellaneous Collection, Mss. Collection 2013.2, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by Sabrina Alderman in 2013.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This contents of this miscellaneous collection were found in the house of Tom Pope and Mary Pope and donated by Sabrina Alderman in 2013.  Folder 1 contains an illustrated flyer for the 1926 silent movie <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Tin Gods</title> starring Thomas Meighan and Aileen Pringle; the flyer advertises its showing at the Wytheville Opera House.  Also included are two sample Virginia Democratic Party ballots for 3 November 1931; names on the ballot include A. E. Shumate, State Senate; M. L. Harrison and D. A. Smith, Delegate; E. M. Chitwood and John W. McGavock Jr., Wythe County Treasurer; H. M. Heuser and W. Paul Parsons, Wythe County Commonwealth Attorney; M. B. Lindamood and D. B. Swecker, Commissioner of the Revenue; George B. Crockett, Corbet C. Williams, and W. H. Slater, Wythe County Sheriff; J. T. Gleaves, J. R. Rowe, and A. L. Porter, Wythe County Supervisor, Speedwell District; J. W. Patton, Justice of the Peace, Speedwell District; and A. B. Spraker, Wythe County Overseer of the Poor, Speedwell District.
</p>
      <p>Folder 1 also contains two Virginia Democratic Party sample ballots for 5 November 1935.  Names include: A. E. Shumate and William Gibboney (marked out), State Senate; M. H. Jackson and S. R. Crockett (marked out), Delegate; C. C. Tate and John W. McGavock (marked out), Wythe County Treasurer; Frank Raflo and W. Paul Parsons (marked out), Wythe County Commonwealth Attorney; J. Elmo Davis and D. B. Swecker (marked out) and A. P. Thomas Jr. (marked out), Wythe County Commissioner of Revenue; Charles W. Dobyns and R. C. Patterson (marked out), Wythe County Clerk of the Court; and J. Muncy Sutherland, W. C. Kineer (marked out), and Corbet Williams (marked out), Wythe County Sheriff.  Finally included are two cardboard illustrated advertisements for concrete chicken houses by Old Dominion Cement; the advertisements were sponsored by John S. Dix and Company, Crockett, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Folder 2 contains three publications including a 1941 <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">De Laval Handy Reference Yearbook</title> with calendar, almanac and articles on the dairy industry and milkers and cream separators manufactured by the De Laval Separator Company of Chicago and New York.  An July 1949 issue of the periodical <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Virginia and the Virginia County</title> focuses on Wythe County.  It includes photographs and articles on Wythe County history, tourism, government, and agriculture and contains numerous advertisements of local businesses and organizations.  Finally, a program for the Wythe County Lions Club minstrel show, dated 1 March 1957, completes this folder.  The program contains a program and multiple pages of advertisements for local businesses and organizations.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
