<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00099">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00099::A Guide to the Huddle Family Papers, 1796-1953)//EN" "viwyc00099.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Huddle Family Papers, <date>1796-1953</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Huddle Family, Papers, 1796-1953
<num type="collectionnumber">1997.8
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>9 July 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Huddle Family Papers, <date>1796-1953</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1997.8
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Huddle Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1796-1953.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1997.8
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">96 folders..
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Huddle Family Papers, Mss. Collection 1997.8, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Beverly Repass Hoch in 1987 and 1997.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>The donor gave additional materials in 2000 (James Layfayette Buck letters)and 2006 (account ledgers and miscelleneous Black Lick Township papers).  The donor also gave additionalcorrespondence in 2008.
</p>
</accruals>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Born on 16 May 1768 in Shenandoah County, Virginia, Henry Huddle was the son of John Huddle and Elizabeth Piper Huddle.  After her first husband died, Elizabeth Huddle married Peter Spangler Jr. and moved to Wythe County.  At age twenty-eight, Henry Huddle purchased 200 acres in the Kimberling section of the young countty along a tributary of Reed Creek which eventually was named Huddle Branch.  Neighbors of Henry and his wife Magdalene Kimberling Huddle (1770-1845) included the Cassell family, Cook family, Dutton family, Kimberling family, Reusch family, and Snavely family.  As his neighbors, Huddle depended upon his farm for his livelihood.  According to local memory, Huddle also built pie safes.
</p>
<p>Henry and Magdalene Huddle raised eight daughters and three sons.  Henry Huddle died on 14 December 1846 and Magdalene died on 27 January 1845.  Both are buried in the Kimberling Church cemetery.</p>
<p>Their son Jonas, born on 17 July 1806, continued to farm and live at the family home.  On 23 May 1833, he married Elizabeth Brown (1806-1885).  Jonas not only farmed but also served as justice of the peace and as the Kimberling Church Sunday school superintendent.  Jonas Huddle also served as an Overseer of the Poor and often helped settle estates for various families.</p>
<p>Jonas Huddle and Elizabeth Huddle had five girls and three sons.  Jonas died on 24 May 1881 and Elizabeth died on 24 April 1885.  Both are buried in the Kimberling Church cemetery.</p>
<p>Their youngest son, Isaac Newton Huddle, was born on 7 May 1849.  Isaac was a farmer but also participated in local politics, serving on the Wythe County Board of Supervisors and on the Black Lick Township Board.  Isaac also served as clerk for the Black Lick Township Board from 1871 to 1875.  On 3 October 1872 he married Sarah Jane Steffey (1849-1936).  Isaac Huddle and Sarah Huddle raised two daughters, Minnie Elizabeth neff (married A. Oden Neff) and Emma Katharine Copenhaver (married Edgar P. Copenhaver).  Isaac Huddle died on 17 February 1924 and his wife Sarah Huddle dield on 24 Apr8il 1936; both are buried in Kimberling Church cemetery.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Huddle Family Papers are arranged in six series.  Series I, Correspondence (1872-1912) includes letters to Isaac Newton Huddle and John Huddle involving financial transactions.
</p>
<p>Valuable information regarding early financial transactions in Wythe County may be found in Series II, Financial Records (1807-1953).  Account books belonging to Henry Huddle, his son Jonas Huddle, and his grandson Isaac Newton Huddle combined with receipts and tax receipts provide researchers a glimpse into the personal and professional business of the Huddle family.  Also included in this series are financial records involving the estates of Adam Snaffle and David Musser.</p>
<p>Series III, Land Records (1796-1896), includes several early deeds transferring property purchased by the Huddle family.  The earliest deed recrods the purchase of Henry Huddle in 1796 of 200 acres along Huddle Branch from Jacob Tobler.  Other records in this series include portions of surveys.</p>
<p>Information regarding nineteenth century education practices may be found in Series IV, Education Records (1812-1882).  Several notesbooks used by James E. Poe and Jonas Huddle illustrate instructional methods in penmanship and arithmetic.  Two compositions by Isaac Newton Huddle and an arithmetic textbook, <title render="italic">Caldwell's Practical Arithmetic</title>, complete this series.</p>
<p>Series VI, Miscellaneous Records (1868-1871) include an article by Jonas Huddle on the Sluss family massacre, a poem, and a hand-drawn map of Virginia.  Brochures from the Pitts Agricultural Works, Richmond Hair Dye Company, Dickie's Poultry Powder Company, and the Golding Printing Press Company, and a flyer for the Louisville, St. Louis and Chicago railroad schedule complete this series.</p>
<p>Series VI, Black Lick Township Records (1870-1875) documents the formation and activities of Black Lick Township from 1870 to 1875.  Isaac Newton Huddle served as clerk for the Township from 1871 to 1875.  The Township records were found in the Huddle home in the 1980s.  Materails include claims, tax receipts, and lsits of delinquent taxpayers.  Also included are records of the Overseers of the Roads.  Appointed by the Township Board, each overseer was responsible for road construction and maintenance in his district.  Records of the Overseers of the Poor are also found in this series.  These citizens coordinated efforts to provide medical care, room and board for poorer residents of the Township.</p>
<p>An important component of this series is the official order book of the Township Board.  Here are recorded transactions of the Board including meetings, claims allowed, listings of Overseers of the Roads and the Poor, listings of road hands, and levying and collection of taxes.</p>
<p>Series VII contains correspondence of James Lafayette Buck, a Mt. Airy, Virginia, native to Isaac Newton Huddle.  Buck attended Roanoke College and the Salem Lutheran Seminary in Salem, Virginia.  The letters date from 1870 to 1878.  Beverly Repass Hoch transcribed and annotated the letters; a copy may be found in the Kegley Library.</p>
<p>Series VIII, 2006 Addendum, contains two account ledgers and several loose papers relating to Black Lick Township.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive">1866-1912.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>3 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
			<c03 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle>Letter.  Cousin Matilda [unknown], Walnut Grove, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
			<unitdate type="inclusive">10 October 1871.
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:1
			</container>
			<physdesc>1 p.
			</physdesc>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Re: her wedding to Mr. Charles.</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  James Buchanan, Rural Retreat, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 August 1892.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: watch he sold to pay Dr. Hobson Clark.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. W. B. Tilson, Chatham Hill, Virginia to John Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 March 1912.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: request that Huddle pay Ogden Neff for feed.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1876
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  A. C> M. Earhart, Dayton, Missouri to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">9 June 1867.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: He recounts his journey to Missouri from Bristol, Indiana and his farming endeavors with his brother.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  William Dunford, Wythe County, Virginia to Lew Guillion.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 June 1868.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: Mrs. Latz agrees to <title render="doublequote">take you now if you will come.</title>  Possibly Louisa Guillion, daughter of Major Guillion and ELizabeth H. Gordon Guillion.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Fannie Yonce to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 June 1868.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re:request that he send photographs of himself.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  James H. Matney, Spencer, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 July 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: farming in Indiana, timber, his work as a plasterer and brick-layer, and John Huddle of Burkes Garden now living in Attica, Indiana.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  James H. Matney, Spencer, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 August 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: weather, corn, and his job constructing a dry goods store in Indianapolis.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Francis Marion Huddle, Rotherwoood, Hawkins County, TEnnessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 December 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: Tennessee girls, Will Crigger, James A. Fisher, and David Jones.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Groseclose, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 February 1875.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: financial notes and mild winter.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Gibboney and Son, Wytheville, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 December 1876.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: account for blasting powder.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1884-1886.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. W. Yost, Wytheville, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">30 January 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: lawsuit for debt of Repass.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  John P. Sheffey, Marion, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 March 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: debt for horse named Rockingham.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  John P. Sheffey, Marion, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 April 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: claim of J. A. Repass vs. R. M. Williams.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. Y. Howe to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">28 June 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: payment for Mr. Leonard to buy cow from Mr. Hoofnagle.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Postcard.  W. W. Yonce, Fremont, Nebraska to Isaac Newton Huddle, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 March 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>postcard.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: his move to Nebraska.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. W. Yonce, Fremont, Nebraska to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 August 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: asks him for truth about rumor that <title render="doublequote">a man is at Johns and has a niger yongon.  I would ask some of my peopel about hit but I know that tay will knot tell me the truth about hit.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  N. B. Studebaker, Charleston, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">11 September 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: cabbage and his school.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. W. Studebaker, Charleston, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 September 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: crates of cabbage, illness of George Catron and Mrs. Catron.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. W. Yonce, Fremont, Nebraska to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">29 September 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:9
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: decision to stay in Nebraska, Charley Baumgardner, John Dutton, Solomon Crockett, his Congregational Church, and cabbage.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Postcard.  F. A. Yonce, Wytheville, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle, Rural Retreat, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 December 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:10
		</container>
		<physdesc>postcard.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: birthdate of Jacob Tobler and his teaching job.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  J. C> Pope, Groses, Smyth County, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">15 December 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:11
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: inability to pay debt until his leather is ready to be shipped.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  J. C. Pope, Groses, Smyth County, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">30 December 1885.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:12
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: selling corn.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  J. C. Pope, Gorses, Smyth County, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 January 1886.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:13
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: selling corn to Mr. Jones and bacon to Mrs. Phillippi.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum - Henry Huddle to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1872.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">24 December 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: fear of living near river, catching a fish as big as his son Jefferson Davis Huddle, Robert Harkrader,  the Pawlett account, Steffey School account, James Swacker and cattle, and the old Cassell family farm.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to ISaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">11 February 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: cold winter, planting corn, new variety of tomatoes from New York, wax bunch beans and pumpkin seeds.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate>10 March 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: illness of Polly Matilda Etter Huddle, busy time at Kingsport shipping flour and corn.  <title render="doublequote">I wish you could have been here for it was a rite smart show to see 4,000 bushels all sacked in 2 bushel sacks.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">31 March 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.; postscript by Polly Huddle.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: plans to purchase land, Thomas Creager whom he thinks is a liar and rascal, crop of wheat, oats, corn; weather, health of Ephraim Brown and Benjamin Brown.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">9 APril 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: sweet potatoes, lettuce, corn, peaches, grass, clover, and the Steffey account.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 May 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: shooting of Hugh Davis, crops of corn, oats, wheat, sweet potatoes, quitting pipe smoking, noise of locusts and frogs being as <title render="doublequote">Farow's Plagues.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Rotherwood, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">15 August 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: death of John Tobler, husband of Mary Magdalene Huddle, camp meeting held by black members, catfish weighing 45 pounds.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum - Henry Huddle to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1884
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 January 1873.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: his new home formerly owned by Rev. Samuel Patton, requests newspaper from David St. Clair, his interest in corn mill.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">16 March 1873.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: apple tree grafts, crop of lettuce, radishes and oats.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">4 June 1873.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: crops, Franklin Dutton; frost that killed peach crop, desire to sell his interest in corn mill jointly owned by David Litz and John Brown.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">17 October 1875.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: diptheria of Ellen Groseclose, fever of Dr. James Vance, death of his horse, and corn mill transaction with David Litz and John Brown.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">28 August 1876.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: crops, supposed insanity of David Staley, corn mill transaction with David Litz and John Brown.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Henry Huddle, Kingsport, Tennessee to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 January 1884.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: pneumonia of Alfred Cregar, his old age at 62, postscript by Jefferson Davis Huddle re: hunting and desire to meet girls.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum - JOseph Shannon to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1866-1868.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph N. Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 April 1866.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: move to Indiana and lost boxes, and abundant corn crop.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph N. Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 May 1866.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: sick horse, and his father quit teaching school because of illness.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph N. Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">16 December 1866.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re:corn harvest, apple crop, rabbit hunting, teaching career of his father who earns $35.00 monthly at the free school</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph N. Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 February 1867.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: cold weather and snow, price of sleighs, rabbit hunting, and local schools.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">23 June 1867.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: his corn crop, bad wheat crop, and opinion on freedom of former slaves.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">21 August 1867.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: threshing wheat, corn crp, and his failed attempt to make arrangements for Huddle to send him money through postal service.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 December 1867.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: good corn harvest, local schools, and missing postal money order that Huddle sent.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Hannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 February 1868.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: protracted church meetings at Presbyterian and Methodist gatherings, support for George H. Pendleton of Ohio for President.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 July 1868.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">6:9
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: corn crop, drought, wheat harvest, high temperatures, presidential political campaign, <title render="doublequote">Grant is no more worthy of the office than your dog in my view.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum - Joseph Shannon to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1872.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 February 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">7:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>6 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: winter weather, wheat and corn crops, construction of new railroad, engagements in Wythe County, visit of relative to Kansas who purchased land for family.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 April 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">7:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: his decision to quit school to farm, marriage of William Dunford, tells Huddle to move west to Kansas.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">16 July 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">7:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: Sunday School lessons, harvesting crops, news from Reuben Repass in Kansas, relocation of John Huddle and Alfred Repass to Attica, Indiana, construction of railroad between his house and barn.  <title render="doublequote">We find them very troublesome, six men and three teams are staying with us.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="subgrp">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 September 1871.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">7:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: prevalent illness of ague in Attica, planting of corn and clover, construction of railroad, John Huddle, and probability of Henry Have returning to Virginia.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Joseph Shannon, Attica, Indiana to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">21 January 1872.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">7:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: illness of Tommy Shannon, fear of smallpox in Attica, Indiana, and sleigh riding.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Correspondence - 2008 Addendum - Robert Snavely to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1874-1876.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Snavely, Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, Blacksburg, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">17 APril 1874.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">8:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: Kimberlin Luthern Church Sunday School, successor to Jonas Groseclose, address of Rev. David F. Bittle, and his opinions on area marriages.  <title render="doublequote">I should not be so very much surprised to hear of divorcements as I really think some of the marriages made last fall are rather shabby.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Snavely, Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, Blacksburg, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 September 1874.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">8:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: his Latin, Greek, German, chemistry, and mathematics classes; James Lafayette Buck, and new students known as <title render="doublequote">sick rats.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Snavely, Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, Blacksburg, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 October 1874.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">8:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re:Kimberlin Lutheran Church Sunday School, election of Jacob Snavely to convention, camp meeting, and his concentration on his studies.  <title render="doublequote">I never hunt or participate in any sport scarcely as I find the simplest amusement will hinder any one's progress in study.</title></p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Snavely, Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, Blacksburg, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">22 March 1875.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">8:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: compatibility with new roommate, new students Guy Brown and Marion Brown, monety stolen from Smyth County student William Davis, and Huddle's debating society.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Snavely, Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, Blacksburg, Virginia to Isaac Newton Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 April 1876.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">8:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>6 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: death of Franklin Dutton, participation in inter-collegiate Virginia oratory society, bad apple crop, and hope to get teaching job at Pleasant Hill School in Smyth County, Virginia.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Financial Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1807-1953, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>22 folders
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Financial Records - Jonas Huddle Account Book.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1842-1845.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>26 p.; written in German.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Financial Records - Jonas Huddle Account Book. 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1842-1845.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
		<physdesc>74 p.; 3 loose papers; pages numbered in pencil.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Financial Records - Isaac Newton Huddle Account Book.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1893-1894.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 p.; pencil.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Financial Records - Receipts - Henry Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1807.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 receipt.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		</c02>
		<c02 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 5.  Financial Records - Receipts - Jonas Huddle.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1844-1854.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<physdesc>20 receipts.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Financial Records - Receipts - Jonas Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1856-1878, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>11 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Financial Records - Receipts - Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1897.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>17 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Financial Records - Receipts - Copenbarger Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1821-1856.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 9.  Financial Records - Receipts - Snavely Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1871.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 10.  Financial Records - Receipts - Staley Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1848-1869, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>23 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 11.  Financial Records - Receipts - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1830-1953, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>15 receipts.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 12.  Financial Records - Tax Receipts - Henry Huddle and Jonas Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1845-1876.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 13.  Financial Records - Tax Receipts - Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1870-1898.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 14.  Financial Records - Tax Receipts - Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1900-1917.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>16 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 15.  Financial Records - Tax Receipts - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1845-1891.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 16.  Financial Records - Insurance - Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1904.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 item.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Policy for house and storage buildings in Black Lick, Virginia from Farmers Mutual Fire Insurance Company.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 16.  Financial Records - Promissory Note and Bonds.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1832-1857.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 18.  Financial Records - Estate of Adam Snavely, Henry Huddle, Administrator.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1826-1835, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		</c02>
		<c02 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Folder 19.  Financial Records - Estate of David Musser, Jonas Huddle, Guardian of Heirs - Receipts and Account Statements.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1833-1849, Undated.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<physdesc>16 items.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 20.  Financial Records - Estate of David Musser, Jonas Huddle, Guardian of Heirs - Receipts and Bonds.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1850-1852.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 21.  Financial Records - Estate of David Musser, Jonas Huddle, Guardian of Heirs - Receipts.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1853-1859, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>18 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 22.  Financial Records - 2008 Addendum.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1800-1918.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Land Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1796-1896, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Folder 1 contains 10 deeds dating from 1796 to 1896; Folder 2 contains surveys, 1826 and undated.  Folder 3 contains deeds from the 2008 Addendum, dating 1809 to 1912.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV.  Education Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1812-1882, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>6 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Folder 1 contains a writing notebook of James E. Poe ca. 1812; Folder 2 and Folder 3 contain  arithmetic notebooks dating 1819 of Jonas Huddle; Folder 4 contains an arithmetic notebook dating from 1824-1825 of JOnas Huddle.  Folder 5 contains a book of Isaac Newton Huddles on arithmetic entitled <title render="italic">Caldwell's Practical Arithmetic.</title>  Folder 6 contains compositions by Isaac Newton Huddle.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series V.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1871, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Folder 1 contains brochures for various products, a schedule for the Louisville, St. Louis and Chicago Railroad, a hand-drawn map of Virginia, an article by Jonas Huddle on the Sluss family massacre, and a poem.  Folder 2, from the 2008 Addendum, contains two poems and a summons to Daniel Fulkner dated 1802.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VI.  Black Lick Township Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1870-1875.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>41 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Folders 1 through Folder 10contain claims Black Lick residents filed for services rendered to the Township Board.  Although most claims involved payment due for road maintenance, residents who built coffins, provided room and board, and gave medical care also filed claims.  Boar dmembers reviewed and paid claims at most of their regular meetings.  Claims are arranged alphabetically and date from 1870 to 1874.
</p>
<p>Folder 11 through Folder 20 contain tax receipts dating 1871 to 1873 for Black Lick Township residents.  The Township levied an 11% tax on eery $100 value of real estate and personal property; receipts are alphabetical by surname.</p>
<p>Folder 21 and Folder 22 contain Overseer of the Poor account statements dating 1870-1875, Folder 23 through Folder 25 contain claims dating 1870 to 1875.  Folder 26 contains the bond of Dr. John D. Stuart for his services. Ephraim Buck served as Overseer of the Poor.  As such he reviewed various claims from residents and businesses who provided care to indigent citizens.  He also regularly supervised accounts established with businessed and individuals who provided regular services to paupers.  Businesses often provided clothing and physicians medical care.</p>
<p>Folder 27 through Folder 30 contains bonds for District One, District Two, District Three, and District Four for the Overseers of the Roads.  Folders 31 contains a list of road hands.  Folder 32 through Folder 33 contain account statement and reports from 1870 to 1875.  Folder 34 through Folder 36 contains claims for the Overseers of the Roads.  Folder 37 contains miscelleneous receipts; Folder 38 contains list of delinquent taxpayers.  Folder 39 contains an order book dated 1870-1875; Folder 40 a land book dated 1873; and Folder 41 contains receipts from the 2008 Addendum.</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VII.  Correspondence - James Layfayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1870-1878, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>11 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Please see Beverly Repass Hoch's <title render="italic">James Lafayette Buck Letters, 1870-1878, While a Student at Roanoke College, Salem, Virginia</title> for a complete analysis of letters.  Hoch annotated and transcribed letters written by James Lafayette Buck from Roanoke College to Isaac Newton Huddle in Rural Retreat, Virginia between 1870 and 1878.
</p>
<p>James Lafayette Buck was born in Wythe County, Virginia, on 19 September 1846.  The son of John Buck and Catherine Philippi Buck, he served in the Civil War and then entered Roanoke Collegte in 1870.  It was then that he started a long correspondence with Isaac Newton Huddle.  Buck graduated from Roanoke College in June 1875 and seminary in Salem, Virginia three years later.  He then served as an ordained Lutheran pastor at Zion Church in Roanoke County, Virginia.  Buck married Callie Louise Cobb in 1883.  Rev. Buck served churches in Virginia, North Carolina, Pennsylvania, South Carolina, and Florida.  He died in 1920 in Jacksonville, Florida.                                                                                                                       </p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1870.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">January - March 1871.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1870.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">April - December 1871.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1872.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1873.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Jamse Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1874.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1875.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1876.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 9.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1877.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 10.  James Lafayette Buck to Isaac Newton Huddle.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1878, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Flder 11.  Photographs of John Christian Buck House.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Financial Records, 2006 Addendum.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1852-1903.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Beverly Repass Hoch dontated two account books and several loose papers relating to the Black Lick Township in January 2006.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Account Book.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1881-1897.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 item; 97 p.; name index.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This account ledger records financial and barter transactions such as wheat, hay, potatoes, corn, cabbage, eggs, flax seed, bacon, mutton, and labor (drilling, hauling, and farming). Names include:  David C. Jones, Eli Huddle, James A Huddle, E. P. Dudley, D. S. Dudley, Jesse C. Pope, John D. Yonce, Henry Woods Fisher, Harrison BOlt, Amandus Crigger, Catherine Dutton, R. D. Candler, Reese Whitley, Rev. E Studebaker, W. B. Williams, and Isaac N. Huddle.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Account Book.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1894 - 1903.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 item; fragment; pages numbered 343 to 478; name index on p. 343.  
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This account book fragment records financial and barter transactions including cabbage, livestock, labor (farming, threshing), hay, and other crops.  Names include: Kellus R. Fisher, James Lambert, W. F> Whitley, F. G. Hudson, A. J. Weaver, George E. Rhudy, F. H. Camron, C. B. Davis, John Harrelton, H. H. Bridges Lindamood, J. L. Buck, J. J. Scherer, S. G. Howe, E. W. Jones, Harrison Mays, H. D. Lefler, and M. C. Lambert.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Black Lick Township Reords and Miscellaneous Financial Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1852, 1859, 1871-1874, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains several financial documents relating to the Black Lick Township of Which Isaac Huddle was a clerk.  Records include:  1852 statement of account between Terracy Musser and D. F. Martin; 1859 account statement of Martin S. Steffy for estate of John Staley.  Black Lick Township documents include:  1871 account statement between H. H. Holbrook and Black Lick Township; 1872 account statement of Black Lick Township with Gibboney &amp; Sons; 1872 list of delinquent taxpayers; 1872 account statement between J. G. Kegley and Black Lick Township; 1873 account statement between H. C. Earhart and Black Lick Township; 1873 settlement between James W. Repass and Isaac N. Huddle; 1873 promissory note between L. F. Cooper et al and Township; 1874 statement of collections recieved; 1874 list of claims allowed by the Black Lick Township; 1874 account statement between H. H. Holbrook and Black Lick Township Road District; 1874 statement between Black Lick Township and S. Y. Cooper, Overseer of Roads, 1874 list of claims allowed by the Black Lick Township; undated list of allowed claims; and undated list of road hands in District No. 4, Black Lick Township.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
	