<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00063">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00063::A Guide to the Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers, 1884-1964.)//EN" "viwyc00063.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers, <date>1884-1964.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">McGavock, Jacob Cloyd, Papers, 1884-1964.
<num type="collectionnumber">1983.1
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>5 January 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers, <date>1884-1964.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1983.1
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1884-1964
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1983.1
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">54 folders..
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers, Mss. Collection 1983.1, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Beverly Repass Hoch in 1983.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>A great-grandson of Irish emigrant James McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., was born to Randal and Cynthia Elizabeth McGavock of Max Meadows, Virginia in 1856.  Randal lived in his father's (Hugh McGavock) homestead and was a prosperous farmer.  Jacob Cloyd McGavock continued the family legacy of farming.  In 1883 he married Amanda Billups of Norfolk, Virginia.  Several years later the couple and their growing family moved into the family home in Max Meadows, Virginia.
</p>
<p>
Amanda Billups McGavock was the daughter of prominent Norfolk businessman Cealy Billups.  Upon his death in 1910, Amanda assumed ownership of several residential and commercial properties.  Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Randal McGavock essentially supervised the management of these valuable properties with assistance of several rental agencies in Norfolk.</p>
<p>Amanda suffered from what her doctors termed a nervous disorder.  Evidently she sought relief from her illness with morphine.  She continued this habit for some time amidst the advice of one of her doctors, Dr. W. S. Sayers of Roanoke, Virginia.  She spent much time in hospitals and clinics in Richmond, Virginia and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.  She died in 1915.</p>
<p>Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Amanda McGavock reared five children.  Their eldest, Eulalie Billups McGavock, tragically died in 1903.  Their eldest son, Randal, moved to Norfolk, Virginia where he worked in his grandfather's farming implement business.  He married Hazel Stone of Norfolk, Virginia.</p>
<p>Born in 1890, their son Cecil Billups McGavock assisted his father with farming after his education at Emory and Henry College and Virginia Polytechnic Institute.  In 1911 he married Mamie Claiborne of Montgomery, Alabama and in September 1912 became the father of Cecil Billups McGavock Jr.  Cecil and Mamie eventually separated; she lived in Charlottesville while Cecil worked for many years in South Hill, Virginia.  He died in 1960.</p>
<p>Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. was born in 1893 and attended school at Massanutten Academy, S. R. Crockett's school in Crockett, Virginia, and Fishburne Military Academy.  He settled in Max Meadows, Virginia after a stint of working in Detroit, Michigan.  He married Cynthia Painter of Alabama; he later remarried Byrd Pendleton in 1967 and remained in Wythe County, Virginia farming. He also served on the Board of Supervisors.  He died in 22 January 1989.</p>
<p>Ezra Summers McGavock, the youngest child of Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and Amanda Billups McGavock, was born in 1897.  He attended Hampden-Sidney College and Union Theological Seminary.  He served Presbyterian churches in rural Bland County before moving to larger areas in Virginia and West Virginia. He first married Mary Haynes in the early 1920s; she died in 1965.  He then married Marjory Deane Davis Cornett in 1969; she died in 1977.  Rev. Summers McGavock died 12 January 1984.</p>
<p>Ezra Summers McGavock and his brother Cecil Billups became embroiled in a bitter legal dispute over the settlement of their mother's land at Dutch Gap farm near Richmond, Virginia.  Correspondence of Randal McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Cecil Billups McGavock, Ezra Summers McGavock, and Mary Haynes McGavock shed light on this divisive argument.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Jacob Cloyd McGavock Papers are arranged in four series, comprising correspondence, financial and legal records, records pertaining to the settlement and management of the estate of Cealy Billups, and miscellaneous records.
</p>
<p>Series I, Correspondence (1884-1964), consists of letters sent and/or received by Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and his family.  Correspondence include Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr. and his wife Amanda Billups McGavock and their son Randal McGavock, Cecil Billups McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr., and Ezra Summers McGavock.  Also contains in this series are letters of Mamie Claiborne McGavock (Mrs. Cecil Billups McGavock) and Mary Haynes McGavock (Mrs. Ezra Summers McGavock).  Topics discussed include agriculture, animal husbandry, politics, and family life and illness.</p>
<p>Extensive correspondence concerning real estate investments in Norfolk, Virginia, Nashville, Tennessee, and Wythe County are also included.  Correspondence of Cecil Billups McGavock contains many letters discussing school life at Emory and Henry College and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.  Similarly, the correspondence of Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr. covers his student days at Massanutten Academy in Woodstock, Virginia, S. R. Crocketts school in Crockett, Virginia, and Fishburne Military Academy in Waynesboro, Virginia.</p>
<p>Series II, Financial and Legal Records (1899-1932), includes account statements and notices from the Bank of Max Meadows, the Bank of Wytheville, and the First National Bank of Wytheville.  Also included in this series are livestock market reports (1917-1929), bills and receipts (1899-1932, undated), and tax receipts (1901-1932).</p>
<p>Series III, Cealy Billups Estate Records (1910-1929), contains records pertaining to the settlement and management of the estate of Norfolk, Virginia businessman Cealy Billups.  His daughter, Amanda Billups McGavock, inherited several residential and commercial properties in Norfolk; these properties were directly managed by various real estate and rental agencies.  Records and statements of these agencies (1911-1929), bills and receipts (1911-1928, undated), Norfolk Water Department receipts (1911-1929), and tax receipts (1911-1912) comprise this series.  Also included is a copy of Cealy Billups' will and distribution of his estate.</p>
<p>Series IV, Miscellaneous Records (1909-1933, undated), includes a livestock insurance certificate dated 1929, report cards of Ezra Summers McGavock from Hampden-Sydney College dated 1919, and other items.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head><c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series I.  Correspondence.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1932.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box" type="box">
</container>
<physdesc>36 folders
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr..
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1905.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:1
	</container>
	<physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Edmund Pendleton, James A. Walker, Humphreys-Davidson Hardware Company, J. G. Brown of Bank of Wytheville, A. G. Crockett of Max Meadows Pharmacy, S. R. Crockett, J. V. Haller, R. H. Glendy, William W. Brauer, and W. G. Heuse.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1907.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:2
	</container>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include:  Alice M. Howard, Lee &amp; Company of Lynchburg, Virginia, D. D. Hull Jr. of Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company, T. A. Groseclose of Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company, J. Norment Powell, Princeton Banking Company, and Robert Blair.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1908-1910.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:3
	</container>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include:  J. A. Howard, C. W. Gleaves of First National Bank of Wytheville, L. D. Calfee, Robert Sayers Jr., and Tuttle and Clark Company.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1911.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:4
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include Clyde Smith, Ferdinand Powell, William J. Brown, H. C. Hoggard and Company, Williams, Hayes and Company, and W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Savings and Trusts.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr..
	<unitdate type="inclusive">January-February 1912..
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:5
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Norfolk National Bank, W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Savings and Trusts, Leland Jordan of Murfreesboro Bank and Trust Company, C. W. Coleman, Williams, Hayes and Company, and Jesse Beery.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">March-December 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="series-folder" type="series-folder">1:6
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: C. b. Welton, L. E. Harvie of Real Estate Loan Deposit Company, R. B. Chaffin and Company, Julien Gunn, Williams, Hayes and Company, B. E. Smith, and Harding A. Jackson.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">January-June 1913.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:7
	</container>
	<physdesc>11 item.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Harding A. Jackson, Julien Gunn, R. B. Chaffin and Company, L. E. Harvie of Real Estate Loan Deposit Company, and H. M. Hayes of Williams, Hayes and Company.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">July-December 1913.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:8
	</container>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: H. M. Hayes of Williams, Hayes, and Company, W. P. James, Colby N. Thomas, Douglas E. Taylor, and W. S. Sayers.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 9.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1914.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:9
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include:  L. E. Harvie of F. W. Dabney Realty Corporation, John S. Childrey, and R. B. Chaffin and Company, P. M. Berry of Middle Atlantic Immigration Company, A. M. Gwyn, and Annie Sayers.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 10.  Correspondence - Jacob  Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1915-1916.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:10
	</container>
	<physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include:  Randal McGavock, J. S. Crockett, S. F. Ewald Company, E. Crittendon, Charles Tunstall Real Estate, Trust and Insurance Company, Kirkpatrick and Howard Company, Williams, Hayes and
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 11.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1917.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:11
	</container>
	<physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Barrett and Hurd Inc., J. S. Crockett, L. E. Harvie of Broadway Realty Company, Randal McGavock, W. S. Poage, W. W. Dillon and Company, M. P. Barrett of Barrett and Hurd Company, and S. G. Hudson.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 12.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1918-1919.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:12
	</container>
	<physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: N. R. Patrick, T. K. Wolfe of Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Bennett Land and Company, Jno. A. Bolling of W. W. Dillon and Company, J. M. Corvair, L. D. Walder of W. S. Robinson and Company, Charles M. Langhorne of Fish Guano Company, and Henry Sweets of Presbyterian Church in the United States.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 13.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1920-1921.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:13
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: J. M. Corvair, James M. Graham of Bank of Max Meadows, Robert Sayers, C. A. Moomaw of Mountain Trust Bank, J. P. Wade of Kerns Commission Company, and B. E. Smith of Church Hill Bank.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 14.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1922-1925.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:14
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include Randal McGavock, L. A. Hull of National Carbide Sales Corporation, Stras, Stras and Persinger Realtors, and Barnett-Schenk drug Company Inc.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 15.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1926.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:15
	</container>
	<physdesc>15 items.		
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: James M. Graham of Bank of Max Meadows, John t. Howe, L. B. Davis of Mountain Trust Bank, Newton and Company, J. M. Wade of Kerns Commission Company, Edward J. Fox of Live Stock Commission Merchants, Mary McGavock, and W. G. Porter.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 16.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1927-1929.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:16
	</container>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Randal McGavock, John T. Howe and Company, Ezra Summers McGavock, Fannie Harvie, Florence B. Chandler, Harvie Realtors, L. B. Davis of Mountain Trust Bank, Mary McGavock, and Holcombe Robertson.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 17.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1930-1932.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:17
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: W. L. Clayton of Jelliffe, Wright and Company, Fannie Harvie, Ezra Summers McGavock, L. E. Harvie, and Cecil H. McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 18.  Correspondence - Amanda Billups McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1884-1910.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:18
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., S. F. Ewald, J. G. Brown of Bank of Wytheville, and Ezra Summers McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>


	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 19.  Correspondence - Amanda Billups McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1911-1914.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:19
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: W. W. Vicar of Norfolk Bank for Saving and Trusts and H. C. Hoggard and Company.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	



	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 20.  Correspondence - Cecil Billups McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1907.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:20
	</container>
	<physdesc>11 items.	
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Nancy Hanson, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Virginia D. Watkins, Annie F. Crockett, and Amanda Billups McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 21.  Correspondence - Cecil Billups McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1908-1924, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:21
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: M. H. Claiborne, Randal McGavock, C. Kent, J. C. Drewry and Company, Holcombe Robertson, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Harvie Realtors, and Amanda Billups McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 22.  Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1911 - February 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:22
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Cecil Billups McGavock, Nena C. Hager, M. H. Claiborne, Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne, and Royall R. Claiborne.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 23.  Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">March-April 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:23
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Blanche D. Ambler, M. H. Claiborne, Anne Bolling, Amanda Billups McGavock, M. H. Claiborne, and Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 24.  Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">July - October 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:24
	</container>
	<physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Mrs. Royall R. Claiborne, Cecil Billups McGavock, and Nena C. Hager.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 25.  Correspondence - Mamie Claiborne McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">November 1912 - 1926, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:25
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.	
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Cecil Billups McGavock, Nena C. Hager, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., Ernest Walton Browne, Czarina F. Pettit, Thomas H. Wilcox, and Edgar Cecil Andrew.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 26.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1911 - January 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:26
	</container>
	<physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, T. Graham Crockett, Randal McGavock, and Robert Blair.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 27.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">February - March 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:27
	</container>
	<physdesc>8 items.	
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock and Agnes Simmerman.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 28.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">September 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder.">1:28
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Randal McGavock, Mamie Claiborne McGavock, Amanda Billups McGavock, and Cecil Billups McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 29.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">October 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:29
	</container>
	<physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Agnes Simmerman, and Randal McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 30.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">November 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:30
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock, Randal McGavock, Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr., and Agnes Simmerman.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 31.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">December 1912.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:31
	</container>
	<physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Amanda Billups McGavock and Sallie Green.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 32.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1914-1917.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:32
	</container>
	<physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include:  Mamie Claiborne McGavock, Randal McGavock, and Jacob Cloyd McGavock Sr.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 33.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1918-1920.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:33
	</container>
	<physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Ellen Simmerman and Randal McGavock.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 34.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1921-1936.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:34
	</container>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Ellen Simmerman, Stuart B. Campbell, Cecil Billups McGavock, Rachel M. Ewing, Randal McGavock, W. A. Kegley, and Cecil Billups McGavock Jr.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 35.  Correspondence - Jacob Cloyd McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1937, 1964, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:35
	</container>
	<physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Cecil Billups McGavock, E. Lee Trinkle, W. C. Thomas of Wythe County National Farm Loan Association, W. E. Davidson, James W. Patton, Andrew G. McLeary of Dixieland Equipment Company, Randal D. McGavock, Herschel Gower, George Waller Crockett, Agnes Simmerman, and Ellen Simmerman.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 36.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1912-1937.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:36
	</container>
	<physdesc>3 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondents include: Royall R. Claiborne to Nena Hager, R. A. Lampton to James O'Conner, and E. Lee Trinkle to Cynthia Painter McGavock
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II.  Financial and Legal Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1899-1932.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>9 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Cealy Billups Estate Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1910-1929.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>

<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1909-1933.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 folder.
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>




