<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viwyc00044">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00044::A Guide to the Lilborn Walter Huddle Papers, 1875-1933)//EN" "viwyc00044.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Lilborn Walter Huddle Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1933</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Huddle, Lilborn Walter, Papers, 1875-1933
<num type="collectionnumber">1998.6
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 October 2011</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Lilborn Walter Huddle Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1933</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1998.6
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Lilborn Walter Huddle Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1933
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1998.6
</unitid>
      <physloc label="Location"/>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">20 folders.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract"/>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a"/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p> Lilborn Walter Huddle Papers, Mss. Collection 1998.6, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by Beverly Repass Hoch in 1998.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Lilborn Walters Huddle, the son of William Litz Huddle (1829-1902) and Caroline Virginia Copenhaver (1837-1901), was born on 21 February 1879.  He attended Roanoke College in Salem, Virginia and graduated from the University of Tennessee in Knoxville with a medical degree.  He married Delia Celestine Baughman on 23 October 1907.  They had three children including Della Virginia Huddle (b. 1910), Samuel Walter Huddle (1912-1975), and Frank William Huddle (1916-1979).  Huddle practiced general medicine in Rural Retreat, Virginia, in an office beside his house.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>Series I, Correspondence (1922-1933), contains both general and medical correspondence of Lilborn Walter Huddle and his family.  Letters from relatives and friends comprise Folder 1 while other folders contain letters regarding referral of Huddle's patients to other physicians for treatment.  Hugh H. Trout, V. M. Cox, F. h. Smith, George B. Lawson, P. S. Smith, and other physicians reported their treatment protocols, diagnosis and prognosis to Huddle of patients referred by him.
</p>
      <p>Series II, Financial Records (1912-1928) contains account books, bills and receipts from Huddle's professional transactions.  Bills from the S. E. Massengill Company, National Drug Company, Strother Drug Company, and Parke, Davis and Company list various pharmaceuticals, drugs, and medical supplies.  Also found are bills from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Southwest Virginia Enterprise</title>, the Lynn Commandery post of the Knights Templar of Virginia (stationed in Marion, Virginia), Rural Retreat Mutual Telephone Company and others.
</p>
      <p>Series III, Miscellaneous (1875, 1926, 1928) contains physician record forms for the Child Welfare Conference, Virginia State Board of Health.  Each form, filled out by Dr. Huddle, includes name of child, address, name of parent or guardian, occupation, name of family physician, date of birth, race, sex, and health status.  This series also includes pharmaceutical advertisements from Cole Chemical Company, Anedemin Chemical Company, S. E. Massengill Company, and Parke, Davis and Company.  By-laws of the Mt. Airy Masons Lodge, a Hotel DeSota (New Orleans) brochure, a broadsheet for public speaking by Benjamin Franklin Buchanan, and a pledge card for donations to the Luther A. Fox professorship at Roanoke College complete this series.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I.  Correspondence.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922-1933.
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence.
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-1933.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:1
		</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains correspondence from W. A. Plecker, State Registrar who admonishes Huddle to correctly identify color of father in illegitimate births and to accurately class "mixed families" as either Negro, colored, mixed issue, free issue, Melungeon, Cuban, Croatans, mixed Indians, etc. but not white.  Also included are letters from Anna Bailey, J. P. Davis, Virginia Oewel, Virginia O'Neal huddle, and S. D. Riddle.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - Referral Letters.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922, 1925.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains referral letters between Lilborn Walter Huddle and physicians Hugh H. Trout and George B. Lawson, Jefferson Hospital in Roanoke, Virginia and F. H. Smith and P. S. Smith, Abingdon, Virginia.  Patients include Mrs. Winn, Miss Hensley, Ralph Heldreth, G. R. Miller, Mr. Brown, Mrs. G. W. Blessing, Mrs. Umberger, and Mrs. James Dutton.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - Referral Letters.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains referral letters between Lilborn Walter Huddle and physicians V. M. Cox of Bristol, Virginia and F. H. Smith and P. S. Smith, Johnston Memorial Clinic, Abingdon, Virginia.  Patients referred include Mrs. Corvin, Mr. Etter, Florence Huffman, Mr. Fulton, and Mrs. Brown.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - Referral Letters.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January - March 1927.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:4
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains referral letters between Lilborn Walter Huddle and physicians Hugh H. Trout, Jefferson Hospital, Roanoke, Virginia; P. S. Smith, F. H. Smith, Dr. Sillaman and J. Coleman Motley, Johnston Memorial Clinic, Abingdon, Virginia.  Patients include Ralph Heldreth, Mrs. Miller, Mr. Kinder, Mrs. Frank Neff, Claude Testerman, Mrs. Hayton, Miss Fowler, Mr. Brown, Bess Goodpasture, Mrs. Staley, Fred E. Lindsey, and L. G. Steffey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence - Referral Letters.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April - May 1927.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:5
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains referral letters between Lilborn Walter Huddle and physicians Carleton B. McCulloch, State Life Insurance Company, Indianapolis, Ind.; F. H. Smith, Johnston Memorial Clinic, Abingdon, Virginia; H. C. Henry, Central State Hospital, Petersburg, Virginia; Hugh h. Trout, Jefferson Hospital, Roanoke, Virginia.  Patients include Ralph O. Heldreth, Mr. Brown, C. P. Killinger, Dean Neese, Miss Killinger, Mrs. Greever, and Mrs. S. G. Miller.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - Referral Letters.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June - August 1927.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:6
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains referral letters between Lilborn Walter Huddle and physicians Hugh H. Trout, Jefferson Hospital, Roanoke, Virginia and C. M. Scott, St. Luke's Hospital, Bluefield, West Virginia.  Patients include Lillie Jones Staley (Mrs. Joseph H. Staley)
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II.  Financial Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1928
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>11 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Series II, Financial Records (1912-1928) contains account books, bills and receipts from Huddle's professional transactions.  Bills from the S. E. Massengill Company, National Drug Company, Strother Drug Company, and Parke, Davis and Company list various pharmaceuticals, drugs, and medical supplies.  Also found are bills from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Southwest Virginia Enterprise</title>, the Lynn Commandery post of the Knights Templar of Virginia (stationed in Marion, Virginia), Rural Retreat Mutual Telephone Company and others.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III.  Miscellaneous.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922-1928.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 1.  Miscellaneous Records - Child Welfare Conference Physicians Records.
	<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 May 1922.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">3:1
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains physician records of the Child Welfare Conference for Infant and Pre-School Children Under Auspices of the Virginia State Board of Health and Wythe County.  Each record completed by Dr. Lilborn Walter Huddle provides name of child, name of parent, parent occupation, and birthdate, weight, height, and health status of child.  Children and parents include: Alma Baumgardner, daughter of L. W. Baumgardner; Richard Baumgardner, son of L. W. Baumgardner; Garland Buckley, son of Dallas Buckley; Nannie Helen Buckley, daughter of Dallas Buckley; Stuart L. Buckley, son of Mrs. T. S. Buckley; Charles Garland Hudson, son of Mrs. A. K. Hudson; Janet Miller, daughter of R. B. Miller; Warren Miller, son of R. B. Miller; Keifer Neff, son of H. K. Neff; Mary Margaret Neff, daughter of H. K. Neff; Mildred May Shealy, daughter of P. E. Shealy; Clarence Luther Slagle, son of W. W. Slagle; Ruby Lucille Steffey, daughter of C. C. Steffey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 2.  Miscellaneous Records - Pharmaceutical Advertisements.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927, undated.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="Series-folder">3:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items		
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains advertisements from:  Cole Chemical Company for Organ-O-Tones No. 19 for obesity; Anedemin Chemical Company for Anedemin for pregnancy symptoms; S. E. Massengill for Creo-Derma; and Parke, Davis, and Company for scarlet fever streptococcus toxin for immunization.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 3.  Miscellaneous Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875, 1926, 1928, undated.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">3:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This folder contains Mt. Airy Lodge by-laws, pledge card for Fox Memorial Professorship at Roanoke College; stock market brochure, descriptions of paintings by Zula Kenyon from the Gerlach-Barklow Company, and flyer for speech by B. F. Buchanan in Marion, Virginia.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
