<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00143">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00143::A Guide to the Doak Family Papers, 1710-1986)//EN" "viwyc00143.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Doak Family Papers, <date>1710-1986</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Doak Family, Papers, 1710-1986
<num type="collectionnumber">1991.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>20 December 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Doak Family Papers, <date>1710-1986</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1991.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Doak Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1710-1986
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1991.2
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">7 series..
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Doak Family Papers, Mss. Collection 1991.2,  Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Doris M. Hickox, widow of Dr. George Harold Hickox, in 1991.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Dr. George Harold Hickox was born on 1 March 1903 in Spokane, Washington.  He was the son of Ryall Michael Hickox and Mary A. Doak Hickox.  He graduated from State University of Iowa with a bachelor and masters degree in engineering.  He earned a doctorate in mechanical engineering from the University of California in 1939.  He held various teaching and professional positions throughout his career including the Tennessee Valley Authority, University of Tennessee, National Science FOundation, Corps of Engineers, and Boeing Aircraft Company.  Upon his retirement in 1970 he embarked upon a sixteen year project to collect and document his family history, concentrating on the Doak family.  Hickox died on 11 December 1986.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Doak Family Papers consist of card files, articles, correspondence, census data compilations, and family group sheets researched and compiled by George Harold Hickox.  The material, arranged into seven series, documents the Doak family and its allied lines.
</p>
<p>Series I, Document File Folders, include 3,000 documents arranged by Hickox in 120 file folders.  He gave each document an individual number, i.e. D1.  The original arrangement system has been maintained.  Access into this series is provided through a card file system.  Each document has been indexed for family name, personal name, and place names in the Wythe County.  Folders contain correspondence, family group sheets, census data, and other materials.</p>
<p>Series II, Card Files, have been kept in their original arrangement as devised by Dr. Hickox.  The files are arranged into four groups.  Group 1 consists of cards arranged alphabetically by first name of Doak family members in Generations 1-4.  Dr. Hickox counted the first generation as that of David Doak (1710-1787) and his siblings.  Group 2 consists of cards for Generation 5.  Group 3 consists of the Kirby family members.  Group 4 consists of miscellaneous Doak family and other family members.  Each card may give the birth, marriage, and death information of the family member.  Accuracy of this information has not been verified.</p>
<p>Series III.   Census Data Compilations.  Dr. Hickox compiled these sheets from information contained in the United States Census schedules for 1790 to 1900.  Sheets are arranged chronologically but have not been indexed.  Frequent names appearing include Hickox (Hickock) and Doak.</p>
<p>Series IV, Doak Descendants Association Records, include family group sheets and correspondence relating to the Doak family and allied families.  These records have not been indexed.</p>
<p>Series V, Edmund Doak Papers, is a sub-collection consisting of family group sheets, Daughters of the American Revolution lineage charts and applications, and correspondence collected by Dr. Edmund Doak.  Accuracy of this information has not been verified.  These records have not been indexed.</p>
<p>Series VI, Alexander Doak Family Group Sheets, were compiled by Hickox pertaining to the descendants of Alexander Doak, son of David Doak.  These records have not been indexed.</p>
<p>Series VII, Correspondence, contains correspondence between Dr. Hickox and the Wythe County Historical Society; it details the donation of David Doak's gravestone to the Society.  These records have not been indexed.</p>
</scopecontent>
</archdesc>
</ead>
