<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viwyc00064">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00064::A Guide to the McGavock Family Papers, 1751-1961)//EN" "viwyc00064.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the McGavock Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1751-1961</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">McGavock Family, Papers, 1751-1961
<num type="collectionnumber">1989.1
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 January 2012</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the McGavock Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1751-1961</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1989.1
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">McGavock Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1751-1961
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1989.1
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">178 folders.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p> McGavock Family Papers, Mss. Collection 1989.1, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by Shirley McGavock McConnell in 1989.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
      <p>The history of the McGavock Family in America begins with the migration of James McGavock (1728-1812).  Born in Antrim, Ireland in 1728, James sailed to Philadelphia around 1755.  He left his widowed mother and brother Randal living at the McGavock homestead called Carnton near Glenarm.  After venturing through the Great Valley of Virginia, James settled in Rockbridge County, Virginia where he prospered as an innkeeper in Fincastle.  In 1760 he married Mary Cloyd (1741-1827); Mary Cloyd McGavock and James McGavock had five sons and five daughters.
</p>
      <p>Searching for fertile land upon which to build his family estate, James McGavock purchased land in Fort Chiswell in present-day eastern Wythe County, Virginia in 1771.  Fort Chiswell prospered as a supply depot for military goods, particularly during the French and Indian War and Revolutionary War.  McGavock capitalized on this thriving market by stocking goodly quantities of lead, powder, and flint among other supplies.</p>
      <p>Concerned by the growing friction between Great Britain and the American colonies, James McGavock joined a local Committee of Safety in 1775. Committee members often met at the ordinary (tavern) which McGavock had constructed in 1772.  On 25 January 1775, he was among numerous Southwest Virginia men who signed the Fincastle Resolutions proclaiming their desire for independence from Great Britain.</p>
      <p>With the construction of the Montgomery County courthouse in 1779, McGavock hoped to achieve his dream of building a bustling town in Fort Chiswell.  Unfortunately, court officials deemed the location too inaccessible and hilly for town development.  As the migration of settlers to Kentucky and beyond increased during the 1780s, however, McGavock enjoyed a lucrative trade supplying the weary pioneers with food, lodging, and supplies.  By 1800, Fort Chiswell boasted an ordinary, mill, blacksmith shop, carpentry shop, and store.</p>
      <p>While his sons David and Randal settled in Nashville, Tennessee, James McGavock's sons Hugh McGavock (1761-1844), James McGavock (1764-1838), and Joseph McGavock (1780-1833) remained at Fort Chiswell.  Although he employed all three sons in his various businesses, James McGavock Sr. left his Fort Chiswell property to James McGavock Jr. after his death in 1812.</p>
      <p>James McGavock Jr. continued his father's lodging business while developing Fort Chiswell into a prosperous farm.  He married Mary Crockett (1778-1826) in 1799 and had twelve children.  James McGavock Jr.  passed his Fort Chiswell estate on to his sons Stephen Cloyd McGavock (1807-1880) and Joseph Cloyd McGavock (1812/1813-1886)(nicknamed Cloyd).  He died in 1838.  James McGavock Jr. was also known as James McGavock Sr. after his father's death.</p>
      <p>Stephen McGavock  and Joseph Cloyd McGavock successfully ran the Fort Chiswell estate for over four decades.  In 1839, they constructed an imposing mansion which features five stories and large Palladian windows.  The brothers not only supervised the plantation activities but engaged in land acquisition and development.  Stephen McGavock also served on the Board of Directors of the Farmers Bank of Virginia.</p>
      <p>Ephraim McGavock (1805-1876), son of James McGavock Jr., settled in Wytheville.  In 1840 he married Abigail Jouett Williamson (1812-1877) (nicknamed Abie), a native of New York.  Abie McGavock founded a private school for girls in Wytheville at which she served as both principal and teacher.  Ephraim McGavock and Abigail Jouett Williamson McGavock had eight children.</p>
      <p>Upon Joseph Cloyd McGavock's death in 1885, Ephraim's oldest son James Hampton McGavock (1842-1916)assumed responsibility for the family estate.  He maintained the Fort Chiswell plantation and developed a special talent for horse breeding.  James Hampton McGavock also served on the Board of Directors for the Farmers Bank of Southwest Virginia as well as the Wythe County Board of Supervisors.  He fought in the Confederate States Army in Company A of the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment.</p>
      <p>James Hampton McGavock wed Elizabeth Pointer (1843-1893)(nicknamed Bettie) of Williamson County, Tennessee in 1867.  Elizabeth Pointer was the daughter of William H. Pointer.  Her only brother Edward Pointer died during the Civil War.  Elizabeth Pointer McGavock and James Hampton McGavock had five sons, two of whom died as infants.  She died in 1893 following a long and painful illness.  James Hampton remarried in 1900 to Evilina Moore of Louisiana.  They had one son.</p>
      <p>The eldest son Edward Pointer McGavock (1868-1950)embarked upon a medical career after studying at Hampden-Sydney College.  He graduated medical school at the University of Virginia in 1893 and settled in Lynchburg and Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      <p>William Pointer McGavock married Flora McDonald Stokes in 1894 and moved to Fredericksburg, Virginia.  By 1907, William had traveled to New Mexico where his lifelong penchant for strong drink and gambling almost led him to the gallows.  While intoxicated he accidentally shot a man and faced lynching by local citizens and execution by local law enforcement.  With the aid of an adept lawyer, he escaped punishment.  Amazingly, the New Mexico courts released him upon the proviso that he never return.  He died in Santa Barbara, California in 1918.</p>
      <p>Cloyd McGavock remained in Wythe County and married Annie L. Jordan in 1902.  He was employed in various endeavors including a bake shop and the New River Ordnance Plant.  His brother Edward Pointer remained the patriarch of the family even while practicing medicine in Richmond and Lynchburg.  Edward evidently made most of the business decision regarding Fort Chiswell and the estate of his father, James Hampton McGavock, who died in 1916.</p>
      <p>In 1918, the Fort Chiswell Mansion exchanged hands.  Edward Pointer McGavock returned to Richmond and Cloyd McGavock settled in Wytheville, Virginia.  Cloyd McGavock later married Willie Wolf McGavock who conducted much family business for Edward Pointer McGavock.  Edward Pointer McGavock died in 1950 and Cloyd McGavock in 1951.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The McGavock Family Papers cover two hundred years of family history, ranging from a 1751 land plat of Fort Chiswell to a 1961 tax receipt.  A rich and varied collection, the Papers provide researchers with valuable information on the history of Wythe County, southwest Virginia, and Tennessee.  Subjects revealed through the collection include land acquisition and development, agriculture, horse breeding, domestic matters, slavery, education, salt manufacturing, and banking.  Information on the American Civil War, World War I, and World War II are also among items in the collection.
</p>
      <p>The collection includes Series I, Correspondence (1787-1950); Series II, Financial and Legal Records (1794-1961); Series III, Land Records (1751-1903); Series IV, Miscellaneous Records (1772-1951); Series V, Books (1826, 1890-1893); and Series VI, Photographs.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I.  Correspondence.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787 - 1950.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>61 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence - James McGavock Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787 - 1800.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:1
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Randal McGavock, James Wood, David McGavock, Thomas Preston, John Blunt, and Hugh McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - James McGavock Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799 - 1819.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: David McGavock, Randal McGavock, R. Crockett, John Mallory, James Toncray, Adam Wirt, William Preston, G. Henderson, Andrew Crockett, and Robert Sanders Jr.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - James McGavock Jr..
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 - 1838.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Isaac Stuart, Alexander Smyth, John Haller, Randal McGavock, Sarah H. Collins, Dr. Jacob Haller, Lysander McGavock, Benjamin Reichel, Isaac Lehew, Ferguson, Jones &amp; Campbell Company, George Kincannon, James Toncray, William Hill, and Jane L. Crockett.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 - 1838.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:4
	</container>
            <physdesc>3 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Lysander McGavock and Francis Bell.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 5. Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 - 1844.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:5
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: William H. McFarland, B. Moore Company, Ephraim McGavock, T. J. Morrison, Gordon L. Jordan, F. H. Lawson, John Scruggs, H. S. Mathews, and Sayers, Oglesby and Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 - 1849.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:6
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Morrison, Watkins and Company, Ephraim McGavock, Agnes L. McGavock, McDaniel and M. Corkle, H. W. and S. S. Fry Company, Joseph J. Ramsey, McDaniel and Son, Beverly A. Johnston, and Mary McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 7.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 - 1852.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:7
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Stuart McClung, McDaniel &amp; Son, J. A. Hopkins, Joseph Cloyd, Mary McGavock, Lee and Johnson Company, and George Watt and Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 8.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 - 1859.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:8
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 9.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 - 1864.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:9
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: T. J. Morrison, Captain R. G. Banks, Thomas P. Clapp, R. Patton, David Sexton, Joseph S. Venable, M. Aiken, W. H. Werth, Captain C. W. Venable, Charles H. Miller, Robert W. Haynes, M. Clark, and G. S. Williams.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 10.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865 - June 1866.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:10
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Isaac B. Dunn, Gordon Cloyd Kent, W. W. Ward, W. H. Crouch, R. H. Crockett, R. C. Crouch, Lee and Taylor Company, and Emma Terry.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 11.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 1866 - December 1866.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:11
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Lee and Taylor Company, W. H. Werth, Jacob Bonsack, Charles A. Haller, William Richardson, William Napier of Cincinnati, Cumberland Gap and Charleston Railroad, and T. J. Finne.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 12.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:12
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  John Williamson McGavock, William Napier, Jacob Harris, A. G. Mathews, Samuel Heninger, and Joseph L. Kent.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 13.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:13
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: A. J. Huffard, A. M. Jordan and Company, Moore and Scott Company, John W. Gibboney, Jacob Bonsack, John Williamson McGavock, E. S. Trinkle, and J. W. Finley.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 14.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 1869 - June 1869.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:14
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  J. B. Painter, Lee and Taylor Company, and John Williamson McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 14.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 1869 - December 1869.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:15
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock and Lee and Taylor Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 16.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1870 - May 1870.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:16
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Lee and Taylor Company, W. A. Stuart, V. C. Huff, John Clark, Clark and Tyree Company, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, Woodruff and Company, and H. Chaffin.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 17.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 1870 - December 1870.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:17
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: John Williamson McGavock, Woodruff and Company, and L. Norvell. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 18.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1871 - June 1871.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:18
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.				
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Michael Caprell, Woodruff and Martin Company, W. A. Stuart, Hahn Brown and Company, J. F. Kent, Daniel E. Wright, V. C. Huff, and Fudge and Gale Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 19.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1871 - December 1871.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:19
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Ambrose B. Rucker, William and Franklin Company, Howell and Orr Company, R. H. Crockett, Watson and Brown Company, W. R. Stewart, and J. F. Kent.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 20.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1872 - September 1872.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:20
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.	
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: L. Norvell, Barnes M. Rucker, F. H. McGavock, Pettyjohn and Rucker Company, and William B. Bryant.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 21.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1872 - December 1872
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:21
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Pettyjohn and Rucker Company, Lee, Taylor and Company, and L. Norvell.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 22.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:22
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Pettyjohn and Rucker Company, Joseph Cloyd, Hahn and Brown Company, G. A. Heuser, and Jesse M. Pettyjohn.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 23.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1874.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:23
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: G. A. Heuser, T. J. Finne, D. P. Watson, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, Mosler and Bahmann Company, Al Alston, Thomas Wood, Mathew Aiken, James Wilkinson, Agnes L. Richardson, Margaret McGavock, Charles A. Haller, and Jacob Bonsack.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 24.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:24
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  T. J. Finne, J. H. Caddall, Taliaferro and Company, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, C. W. Shortt, James B. Marshall, J. S. Crockett, Robert J. Glendy, and R. H. Crockett.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 25.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:25
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Mary Richardson, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, T. J. Finne, J. F. Kent, J. C. Allison, Thomas C. Basshor, E. L. Osborn, Robert J. Glendy, and H. D. Hatcher.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 27.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1878 - June 1878.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:26
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: F. S. Blair, James Kent, William Mathews, A. D. Hatcher, Graham Robinson and Company, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, Francis Bell, J. F. Kent, and W. S. Paulett.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 27.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1877.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:27
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: William Mathews, Mary C. Richardson, W. S. Paulett, A. D. Hatcher, R. P. terry, S. C. Hurt and Company, R. A. Alston, J. A. D. Myers, and Wood, Kasey and Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 28.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 1878 - November 1878.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:28
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: E. C. Deuel, A. D. Hatcher, R. P. Terry, R. C. Kent, W. S. Paulett, Madison Puckett, Francis Bell, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, William Raper, and John Raper.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 29.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1879 - March 1879.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:29
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: W. S. Paulett, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, Francis Hargrave McGavock, S. C. Hurt and Son, Robert Button, and Joseph Topham.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 30.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 1879 - December 1879.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:30
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie Company, W. C. Crockett, R. Sayers, J. F. Kent, and Francis Bell.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 31.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:31
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Allen W. Talley, H. M. Smith, Jno. T. Hawlett, 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 32.  Correspondence - Stephen McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:32
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: William D. Crockett, J. F. Kent, Lee, Taylor and Company, Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock, John Williamson McGavock, J. P. Mefe, D. H. Miller, A. Myers, William Napier, and G. C. M. Dondall.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 33.  Correspondence - Joseph Cloyd McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871 - 1885.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:33
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Jones and Brown Company, D. T. Jones, James Kent, Samuel Townsend and Son, Sherman and Culver Company, Karn and Hickson Company, Adam Brothers and Paynes Company, and J. W. Robinson.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 34.  Correspondence - Elizabeth Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857-1859.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:34
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Edward H. Pointer.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 35.  Correspondence - Elizabeth Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 - 1866.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:35
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Edward H. Pointer, B. N. Jenkins, and James Hampton McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 36.  Correspondence - Elizabeth Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867-1868.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:36
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: James Hampton McGavock, Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock, and William H. Pointer.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 37.  Correspondence - Elizabeth Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871 - 1878.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:37
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Nora Mayes, Sarah Jackson McGavock, James Hampton McGavock, Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock, S. A. Pointer, Thomas G. Pointer, and Margaret M. Genans.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 38.  Correspondence - Elizabeth Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885-1888.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:38
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: James Hampton McGavock and Peirce Sanders.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 39.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1869.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:39
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock, Lee and Taylor Company, C. P. Kent, John Williamson McGavock, Malvina Mathews, and William H. Pointer.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 40.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871-1879.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:40
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: E. H. Robinson, S. A. Pointer, Nowlin Brothers and Bigbie, John D. Stuart, and J. F. Kent.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 41.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880-1884.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:41
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Thomas G. Pointer, Frank H. Levering, F. S. Buchanan, H. S. Buchanan, Jno. T. Hawlett, Augustus Heuser, J. M. McFerrin, C. N. Hunter, R. R. Berkeley, Thomas E. Doswell, C. S. Kalfee, B. F. Counselman, L. C. Irving, D. S. Lewis, and Lee S. Allison.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 42.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 1885 - August 1885.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:42
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include; D. S. Lewis, W. I. Mann, George W. Dunford, and Ben W. Terry.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 43.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1885 - December 1885.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="Series-folder">1:43
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: N. Robinson, J. M. McFerrin, Samuel Gibbs, Jacob Harris, F. P. Fizer, John Sickels, and S. A. Clark.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 44.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1886.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:44
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: A. S. Williams, James T. Crockett, John Funk, James MacGill, R. M. Crockett, Charles K. Harrison, Sanders D. Bruce, Mrs. C. S. Adams, R. C. Shaffer, Thomas Lewis, Joseph W. Caldwell, William Steele, Isam Connelly Groome, and R. R. Henry.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 45.  Correspondence - James Hampton McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">188 - 1912.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:45
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: D. H. Porter, John S. Sanders, Joseph H. Sanders, Bennett Barnes, W. W. Woodson, F. J. T. Sayers, D. M. Hayes, Matthew H. Maury, Nora Mayes, W. A. Caldwell, William V. Wilson Jr., Robinson Brothers, G. H. Hartsell, and S. M. Thomas.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 46.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885 - March 1886.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:46
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Georgie Lindsley, Elizabeth Hayes, Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, and Maggie C. Pollock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 47.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1886 - December 1886.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:47
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Georgie Lindsley, Maggie C. Pollock, James L. Kent, Elizabeth Hayes, Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, W. L. McCraa, and William Pointer McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 48.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1887 - April 1887.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:48
	</container>
            <physdesc>21 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Elizabeth Hayes, Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, Mary Lejeune Wade, F. H. Terry, and J. Robert Walker.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 49.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1887 - December 1887.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:49
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, James L. Kent, W. L. McCraa, James S. Rhea, Georgie Lindsley, J. Robert Walker, and Henry Silverthorn.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 50.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1888.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:50
	</container>
            <physdesc>18 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:   Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, Georgie Lindsley, F. E. Robbins, Richard McIlwaine, Crittenden Joye, W. D. Shue, J. Robert Walker, Martha L. McIlwaine, James W. S. Rhea, James L. Kent, and C. T. Hall.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 51.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890 - 1892.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:51
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Peirce Sanders, Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, Crittenden Joye, J. F. McKinsky, and John D. Thomas.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 52.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1893 - April 1893.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:52
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, J. H. Fulton, James Hampton McGavock, and Sarah Jackson McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 53.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1893 - June 1893.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:53
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Annie Lee Bolling, Carrie H. Davis, Lizzie Kent, Mollie L. Logan, Bessy Carter Davis, Sarah Jackson McGavock, John D. Thomas, Lizzie R. Poage, L. N. Randolph, James Hampton McGavock, Millie N. Caldwell, and Sue M. Spiller.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 54.  Correspondence - Edward Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900-1929.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:54
	</container>
            <physdesc>22 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: James Hampton McGavock, Ed Hayes, Grace Hardee Lovelace, J. Norment Powell, R. L. Barnes, Clinchfield Fuel Company, G. A. Reese, J. R. Simmons, Cloyd McGavock, Willie Wolf McGavock, and Abie Jouett Williamson McGavock.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 55.  Correspondence - William Pointer McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890 - 1907.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:55
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, Sue Peyton Kent, Sue Spiller, Mrs. R. B. Merchant, William V. Wilson Jr., William Bernard, Charles Del Bondo, and Fannie Jouett Fulton.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 56.  Correspondence - Cloyd McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901 - 1950.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:56
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Clarence L. Painter, Evelyn Robbins McGavock, O. C. Dutton, Fred C. Main, Roanoke Seed and Supply Company, William V. Wilson, B. J. Owen, Stuart B. Campbell, and J. L. Runion.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 57.  Correspondence - Willie Wolf McGavock.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1943.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:57
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Joseph H. Anderson, R. T. Stephenson, W. W. S. Butler, Hugh Trout, William J. Lees, Nora Wolf, and Ruth Brichetto.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 58.  Correspondence - William H. Pointer.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863 - 1870.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:58
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 letters.	
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: William Barry and Thomas G. Pointer
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 59.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 - 1884.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:59
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Jacob Kinchlove, Charles Austin, Jacob McGavock, Joseph McGavock, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Mother,</title> slave of W. M. Cozart, Edmund Norris, Jacob A. Bevrle, Jacob Bonsack, F. Harris, Ephraim McGavock, Sallie B. Pointer, William Gibboney, John C. Graham, John L. Sayers, J. A. Moore, W. A. Moore, J. W. Alsbaugh, Frank. H. Levering, V. C. Huff, William B. Foster, C. K. Beecraft, William Terry, J. M. McFerrin, and John Clark.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 60.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885 - 1916.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:60
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 letters.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: D. S. Lewis, James Alexander Walker, Jno. L. Hawlett, C. E. Coffin, John H. Fulton, John R. Robinson, J. P. Cofer, Sarah Jackson McGavock, H. Douglas Fuller, John Williamson McGavock, C. W. Gleaves, and C. B. Moore.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II.  Financial and Legal Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1804-1942.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>53 folders
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Series includes wills of James McGavock Sr., Josiah Ramsey, James McGavock Jr., James McGavock III, Mary McGavock, Cynthia McGavock, Stephen McGavock, Joseph Cloyd McGavock, James Hampton McGavock, and Cloyd McGavock (Folders 1-10).  Folder 11 contains summons while Folder 12 has judgments.  Account books (Folders 13-18), insurance politics (Folders 19-21), stocks and securities (Folders 22-26), Confederate vouchers (Folder 27), cancelled checks (Folder 28), tax receipts and returns (Folders 29-22), and bills and receipts (Folders 34-53) complete the series.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III.  Land Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1751 - 1903.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>21 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Series includes deeds and indentures (Folders 1-13), plats and surveys (Folders 14-18), Maury and McGavock and Max Meadows Land and Improvement Company records (Folders 19-20), and land records of William H. Pointer (Folder 21).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1772-1951.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>17 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Series includes records on politics, American Red Cross, school compositions, advertisements, inventory of John Neely estate, petition of Botetourt County residents for new county (1772), bills - Thomas Jefferson to William Rutherford (1770) and James Madison to John Rutherford (undated).  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series V.  Books.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1893.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>18 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Includes medical notebooks of Edward Pointer McGavock, Bible of Elizabeth Pointer McGavock, and notebook of Randal McGavock.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VI.  Photographs.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>7 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Series includes photographs of Ephraim McGavock, Cloyd McGavock and other family members; many unidentified.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
