<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00109">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00109::A Guide to the Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection, 1749-2008.)//EN" "viwyc00109.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection, <date>1749-2008.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Woods, Pearle Ceary, Genealogical Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">2010.4
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>26 October 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection, <date>1749-2008.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2010.4
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1749-2008
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2010.4
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">6 albums.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection, Mss. Collection 2010.4, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Patricia Woods Botelle, daughter of Pearle Ceary Woods, in 2009.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The daughter of Joseph Patrick Ceary and Stella Moore Ceary, Pearle Ceary was born on 11 October 1924 near Cripple Creek, Wythe County, Virginia.  She graduated high school in 1942 and worked at Wytheville Knitting Mill.  In September 1943, she moved to Baltimore, Maryland to work at Bethlehem Steel Company.  She married Cecil Preston Woods on 23 May 1953; the couple stayed in the Baltimore area where they raised two daughters.  Cecil Woods managed a hardware store while Pearle Ceary Woods kept financial accounts for the store.</p>
<p>After the death of her husband in 1988, Pearle returned to Rural Retreat, Virginia to live with her sisters.  Until her death on 31 August 2008, she devoted herself to family and genealogical research.  She compiled six albums of research on her family and that of her husband.  Her cremains are buried in St. Peter's Cemetery in Wythe County, Virginia.  
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Pearle Ceary Woods Genealogical Collection consists of six albums of genealogical notes, family charts, census records, photographs and other documents relating to the Ceary family, Cary family, Cleaver family, Surratt family, Moore family, Collins family, Cooley family, Lee family, Welsh family, Leatherman family, Pearman family, Freeman family, Porter family, Ferguson family, Ewing family, and Sublette family. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 1.  Ceary Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1910 - 2008.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 141 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains photographs, family charts, pedigree charts, census records, and other documents relating to: Pearle Ceary Woods, Cecil Preston Woods, Cripple Creek, Virginia, Rural Retreat, Virginia, Joseph Patrick Ceary, Stella Campbell Moore, Willard Robinson Deskins, Willie Cleo Ceary Deskins, Harry Douglas Bratton, Edna Luttie Ceary Bratton, Arthur Woodrow West, Cecile Virginia Ceary West, Rivers DeLaittre Davidson, and Stella Ruth Ceary Davidson, among others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 2.  Ceary, Cary, Cleaver Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1880-2006.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 139 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains photographs, family charts, census records, abstracts from local history and genealogical books, transcripts of newspaper clippings, and other documents relating to: Thomas Franklin Cary, Susan Catherine Cleaver, Pearle Ceary Woods, Joseph Patrick Ceary, Dorcas N. Ceary Hines, Frank Cleaver Cary, shooting of Dan Carey by William Dalton in 1897, Ellis E. Rosenbaum, Alberta Rosenbaum Ceary, John Henry Cary, Susie Campbell Cary, William M. Ceary, Hugh Thompson, Emma L. Cary Thompson, Harvey Clyde Blevins, Dorcas Lenora Ceary, John Estell Carey, Della Frances Carey Blevins, Ethel Jones Carey, Gladys Ceary Rich, Rev. Fred Solomon Rich, Carlie Franklin Ceary, George Elwood Cary, Frances Paulette Waller Cary, and others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 3.  Cleaver Family, Surratt Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1787-2004.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 67 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains pedigree charts, family group sheets, abstracts from local history and genealogy books, census records, and other documents relating to:  David Leonard Cleaver, Mary Ann Surratt Cleaver, Frank Cary, Susan Cary, Sarah Lucinda Cleaver, John C. Richmond, Mary Ann Cleaver, Nancy Cleaver, Rebecca Cleaver Aker, George A. Aker, Thomas Franklin Cary, Susan Catherine Cleaver, Dorcas Ceary Hines, Johanna Ceary Mitchell, Joseph Patrick Ceary, Robert O. Richmond, Walter T. Richmond, Frederick Cleaver, Jacob Cleaver, and others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 4.  Moore Family, Collins Family, Welsh Family, Pearman Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1796 - 1999.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 123 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains family group sheets, pedigree chart, photographs, deed records, census records, marriage records, transcriptions of newspaper clippings, and abstracts from local history and genealogy books relating to:  John W. Moore, Elizabeth Collins Moore, James William Moore, Amelia J. Allison Moore, drowning of James William Moore, Julia V. Huffard Moore, John Harrison Moore, John Stewart Littreal, Evaline Virginia Moore Littreal, David Collins, Elizabeth Stephens Cooley Collins, Ann Lee Collins, John Welsh, Leah Leatherman Welsh, James Pearman, Jane Freeman Pearman, John Porter, Elanor Pearman Porter, and others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 5. Welsh Family, Pearman Family, Porter Family, Ferguson Family, Sublette Family, and Ewing Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1749 - 1991.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 112 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains family group sheets, census records, abstracts from local history and genealogy books, photographs, and other documents relating to: James Pearman, John Porter, Eleanor Pearman Porter, Samuel Ewing POrter, Susannah Welsh Porter, Samuel M. Porter, Ursula Sublett Ferguson Porter, Andrew Porter, Margaret Jane Ewing Porter, Alexander Ewing, Rebecca Ewing, Benjamin Sublette, Elizabeth Jordan Sublette, Pierre Louis Soblet, Marte Martin Soblet, Abraham Soblet, Susanna Brian Soblet, and others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Album 6.  Moore Family, Porter Family, Collins Family, Cooley Family.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1896 - 2007.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 album; 145 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This album contains family group sheets, photographs, marriage records, pedigree charts, family group sheets, abstracts from local history and genealogy books, newspaper clippings, and other documents relating to: David Andrew Moore, Lutie Houston Porter Moore, John W. Moore, Elizabeth H. Collins, David Collins, Elizabeth Stephens Cooley, Pearle Ceary Woods, Stella C. Moore, Eugene Moore, Andrew Porter, Joseph Patrick Ceary, Stella Campbell Moore Ceary, Weston family, James Claude Moore, Bertha Clyde Jordan Moore, Harry Reed Moore, Florence C. Shockley Moore, Owen W. Moore, Lois Hudson Moore, Eugene Walter Moore, Frank Loda Gentry, Lessie Agnes Moore, James Guy Dalton, Virginia Elizabeth Moore, Harry Reed Moore Jr., Rebecca Littreal Moore, and others.  A detailed table of contents may be found with the album and the in-house finding aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>

