<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viwyc00144">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00144::A Guide to the Withers Family Papers, 1855-1954, Undated)//EN" "viwyc00144.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Withers Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1954, Undated</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Withers Family, Papers, 1855-1954, Undated
<num type="collectionnumber">1997.1
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2013 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 January 2013</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Withers Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1954, Undated</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1997.1
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Withers Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1954, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1997.1
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">317 folders.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Withers Family Papers, Mss. Collection 1997.1, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by Gary Laing and Ann Laing in 1997.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Robert Enoch Withers</title>
      </p>
      <p>Robert Enoch Withers, son of Robert Walter Withers and Susan Dabney Alexander Withers, was born on 18 September 1821 at Rock Castle in Campbell County, Virginia.  Withers followed his father's footsteps by becoming a physician; he graduated from the University of Virginia with a medical degree and trained at the Baltimore Almshouse Hospital.
</p>
      <p>He married Mary Virginia Royall on 3 February 1846; she was the daughter of Joseph Edwin Royall and Mary Elizabeth Royall of Lynchburg, Virginia.  The young couple settled in Campbell County where he practiced medicine.  During their sojourn in that county, Mary Virginia Royall Withers gave birth to seven daughters including Elizabeth Royall Withers (1846-1927)(married Edwin Lewis Carter), Susan Dabney Withers (1848-1924)(married Henry S. Williams), Alice Chinn Withers (1850-1892)(married Edmund Pendleton Goggins), Jennett Ann Withers (1851-1945)(married 1) Henry Cook 2) Major Waller Boyd), Mary Virginia Withers (1853-1855), Josephine Withers (1854-1956)(married John T. Read), and Kate Massie Withers (1856-1911)(married G. Woodville Smith) at the Briery in Campbell County.</p>
      <p>Faced with limited educational opportunities for his growing family, Withers eagerly accepted the advice of his brother Dr. Edward D. Withers and moved to Danville in August 1858.  He joined the practice of his brother, sent his girls to school at the Danville Female Academy  headed by Rev. George Washington Dame, and purchased a house on Wilson Street.</p>
      <p>Children born in Danville include Betty Ellison Withers (1858-1918)(married Stephen Putney), Willie Clare Withers (1859-1939), Virginia Secessia Withers (1861-1939)(married John Young Terry), Robert Edwin Withers (1865-1952)(married Mary Cloyd Kent), and Mary Thornhill Withers (1867-1874).</p>
      <p>When the Civil War erupted in 1861, Robert Enoch Withers joined the Confederate Army as a major; he later became colonel of the 18th Virginia Infantry Regiment until he was wounded at the Battle of Gaines Mill.  He subsequently oversaw Confederate prisons and hospitals at Danville, Virginia until the war's end.</p>
      <p>Withers served as lieutenant-governor of Virginia in 1873.  In 1875 he served as a United States Senator for one term.  In 1885 President Grover Cleveland appointed him as Consul to Hong Kong.  Withers and some of his family members, including Robert Edwin Withers, journeyed to Hong Kong where they stayed for four years.</p>
      <p>Withers moved to Wytheville, Virginia in 1879 and eventually purchased the Ingleside home which his daughter Bettie Ellison Putney later purchased from family members.  Robert Edwin Withers Sr. later bought Ingleside from niece Josephine Putney Dame.</p>
      <p>After his retirement from politics, Withers remained active in the Episcopal Church and served as Examiner of Records from 1896 to 1907.  He died on 21 September 1907.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Robert Edwin Withers Sr.</title>
      </p>
      <p>The eleventh child and only son of Mary Virginia Royall Withers and Robert Enoch Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Sr. was born 13 March 1865 in Danville, Virginia.  He attended private schools and the Virginia Military Institute in 1882.  At V.M.I., Withers joined Sigmi Chi fraternity.  After his graduation in 1885, he served as secretary to his father who was U. S. Consul to Hong Kong.</p>
      <p>Withers moved to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1893 and began a long career at the Pittsburgh Reduction Company which later became the Aluminum Company of America.  He served as treasurer and assistant secretary, vice-president of finance, a director, and as senior vice-president.</p>
      <p>He married Mary Cloyd Kent on 2 June 1892.  The couple had two sons, Robert Edwin Withers Jr., who was born on 1 June 1894, and Kent Cloyd Withers who was born on 28 December 1910.</p>
      <p>As his father, Robert Edwin Withers was an active member of the Episcopal Church.  He served as a lay reader and vestry member of Calvary Episcopal Church in Pittsburgh for many years.</p>
      <p>Withers and his wife purchased Ingleside from Josephine Putney Dame and spent many summers with family members there.  Robert Edwin Withers died on 29 December 1952.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Robert Edwin Withers Jr.</title>
      </p>
      <p>Robert Edwin Withers Jr. was born on 1 June 1894.  Suffering from various physical and behavioral problems, he attended a sanitarium and school run by Dr. Mary Pogue at Lake Geneva, Wisconsin.  he graduated from Yeates Preparatory School in Lancaster, Pennsylvania in 1916 and attended the University of Virginia.  When the United States entered World War I, Withers enlisted as a private in the Marine Corps and served guard duty at Grieve, France as a sharpshooter.</p>
      <p>He graduated from the University of Pittsburgh in 1922 with a bachelors degree in economics.  He studied under Rev. W. A. R. Goodwin at the College of William and Mary in 1927 and the following year entered the Virginia Seminary at Alexandria, Virginia to study for the Episcopal ministry.  He was ordained at Emmanuel Church, Glenmore, Buckingham County, Virginia in July 1931.  He served parishes in Appomattox, Buckingham, and Cumberland counties and also in Ridgeland and Bluffton, South Carolina.</p>
      <p>Robert Edwin Withers Jr. married Frances Glover Haskins on 10 August 1933.  Haskins was a school teacher and a native of Buckingham County.  They had one daughter, Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, who was born on 28 October 1935.  Robert Edwin Withers died in February 1981 and Frances Withers died in October 1989.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Kent Cloyd Withers</title>
      </p>
      <p>Kent Cloyd Withers was born on 29 December 1910 in Parnassus, Pennsylvania.  He attended the Arnold School and Storm King School.  He graduated from the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, New York and began work at the Aluminum Company of America plant in Alcoa, Tennessee.  He married Martha Anne Rogers of Morristown, Tennessee on 24 November 1939.  They had two sons, Robert Edwin Withers III, born 20 October 1941) and Kent Cloyd Withers Jr. (born 27 August 1947).</p>
      <p>During World War II, Withers and his family moved to Spokane, Washington where he worked at the Trentwood Government aluminum plant.  After the end of the war they moved back to Knoxville, Tennessee.  Kent Cloyd Withers died in 2000.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Withers Family Papers chronicle the lives of several members of the Withers family and Kent family of Wythe County, Virginia, and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.  Documents of Robert Enoch Withers, his son Robert Edwin Withers, and his wife Mary Cloyd Kent Withers and their children dominate this rich collection.  Also included are documents of siblings of Robert Edwin Withers and his wife.  Family life, education, the Episcopal Church, the Aluminum Company of America, diplomatic service in Hong Kong, Guatemala, and Russia are among subjects found in these Papers.</p>
      <p>Series I, Correspondence (1855-1954, Undated), contains 158 folders of correspondence of the Withers family, Kent family, and their relatives, professional colleagues, and friends.  The series is arranged chronologically.  Understandably, correspondence between the Withers family and Kent family dominate letters in Series I.  Information on family activities, schooling, finances, illnesses, and deaths are recorded.  Other families mentioned include the Campbell family, Dame family, Darling family, Putney family, and Read family.</p>
      <p>Topics covered in this series include education with the following institutions represented: College of William and Mary, University of Virginia, and Virginia Military Institute.  Two college preparatory schools, Storm King Preparatory School (Cornwall-on-Hudson, New York) and Yeates Preparatory School (Lancaster, Pennsylvania) are also covered in this series.  Correspondence in this subject is mainly between Robert Edwin Withers Jr. and Kent Cloyd Withers and their parents and friends.  Both generations were members of Sigma Chi fraternity.</p>
      <p>Religious topics, especially those of the Episcopal Church in Pennsylvania and Virginia, are also included.  Other churches covered are Wytheville Presbyterian Church and the Seventh Day Adventist Church.</p>
      <p>The Withers and Kent families traveled widely to destinations such as Atlantic City, NJ, Florida, Hollywood, White Sulphur Springs, WV, and other United States cities.  Robert Edwin Withers Sr. made an annual pilgrimage to Florida to play golf and often stopped in other southern  locations including South Carolina and North Carolina.</p>
      <p>Health issues including typhoid fever, Oak Leigh Sanitarium in Lake Geneva, Wis., psychiatry, the 1919 influenza epidemic, and the Frontier Nursing Service founded by Mary Breckinridge in Kentucky are discussed in this series.</p>
      <p>Correspondence from foreign countries is also included in this series.  Robert Enoch Withers served as U. S. Consul to Hong Kong while William Patton Kent was Consul to Guatemala.  Kent's son, Tyler Gatewood Kent, served in U. S. embassies in the Soviet Union and England.  He was charged with espionage by British authorities and imprisoned throughout World War II.</p>
      <p>Other topics covered in this series include automobiles, horses, and railroads.  Business topics include labor disputes including coal mining in Pocahontas, West Virginia, Aluminum Company of America, stocks, and bonds.  Wytheville topics include Withers Field, McWane Pool, St. John Episcopal Church, Wytheville Presbyterian Church, photographer Susie Fox, Ingleside, and town Christmas decorations as well as town life and activities.</p>
      <p>Series II, Withers Genealogy Book Correspondence and Records (1939-1952, Undated), contains correspondence relating to research and publication of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Withers Family of the County Lancaster, England, and of Stafford County, Virginia Establishing the Ancestry of Robert Edwin Withers III</title>, presented by Robert Edwin Withers Sr. and prepared by genealogists Katherine Cox Gottschalk and A. May Osler.</p>
      <p>Series III, Genealogical Records (1892-1950, Undated), contains notes and drafts of articles written by Mary Cloyd Kent Withers for her publication <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Word Sketches of Some of Her Relatives,</title> as well as newspaper clippings on Joseph Gordon Kent, Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling, Kent Crosby Darling, and Dr. Anna P. Kent.  Also included are newspaper clippings, a flyer, and notes regarding arrest of Tyler Gatewood Kent for espionage in England during World War II.  Notes and newspapers clippings on the Withers family include obituaries for Alice Withers Goggin, Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Susan Catherine Withers Massie, Robert Enoch Withers, Waller Massie Boyd, Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter, and clippings on Willie Clare Withers, Martha Anne Rogers Withers, Kent Cloyd Withers, Frances Haskins Withers, Robert Enoch Withers' Civil War experience, and naming of Withers Field in Wytheville, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Also included in this series are photocopies of newspapers clipping of engagements and weddings including those of:  Capt. Rodney Snow Jr. and Mary McKinney Goodson [1945], Stanley F. Reed Jr. and Harriet Dyer [1948], Archibald A. Campbell and Eloise Richberg [1950], Thomas Van Kirk Douglass and Margaret Taylor, Edward C. Fuller and Dorothy Berger Edsall, Frank McCormick Painter Jr. and Constance Verde, Charles O'Ferrall Thompson and Mary Terry, Walter Allison Moore and Mary Helen England, Dr. William Sterry and Dr. N. Bowman Wise, Carlton S. Redmond Jr. and Elizabeth Wight, Samuel Stevens Sands and Elizabeth Dame, George Walton Felker III and Elizabeth Paxton Grant, Thomas Pinckney and Charlotte Miller Kent, Kent Crosby Darling and Nelle Powell Payne, Dr. Robert Lee Payne Jr. and Ruth Tunstall Graham, George Macgill Carter Jr. and Margaret Marshall Darsie.</p>
      <p>Photocopies of clippings of obituaries include: Peyton Green, Edmund Fontaine Broun, Edwin Stanton Fickes, George E. Gibbons, Flora Cooke Stuart, Samuel Moorehead Russell, Octavia Reed Parrish, Thyrsa Wealththeow Amos, Ogden M. Edwards Jr., George F. Whitman, William Page Dame, Harvey B. Gaul, and Mrs. Thornson Massie.  Photocopies of miscellaneous newspapers on the Aluminum Company of America, the Very Rev. Arthur Barksdale Kinsolving, Emily Kent, Henry Watkins Ellerson, Eugenia J. Ferguson Mada Winters, and Rev. Lauiston L. Scaife also comprise this series.</p>
      <p>Series IV, Examiner of Records to the Auditor of Public Accounts - Correspondence and Reports (1896-1907, Undated), contains records of Robert Enoch Withers who served as Examiner of Records for the 15th Judicial District t of Virginia from 1896 to 1907.  As such Withers reported and audited claims and debts against the Commonwealth of Virginia for Bland, Carroll, Giles, Grayson, Pulaski, Tazewell, and Wythe counties.  The series includes correspondence from guardians, executors, commissioners, and others managing estates or orphans as required by an 4 March 1896 act of the General Assembly to report income and personal property.</p>
      <p>The Examiner was required to report <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">money, bonds, notes, stock, capital, capital stock, choses in action, and other evidences of debt, and all other species of personal property and income under the control of receivers, commissioners, or fiduciaries or held subject to the order of the several courts in each county subject to tax by an act approved March 4, 1896 as amended by an act approved 3 March 1898, entitled an act to provide for a method for the better assessment of personal property under the control of fiduciaries and the several courts of the commonwealth.</title>   The Examiner of Record for each court district reported to the state Auditor of Public Accounts.</p>
      <p>Series V, Religious Records (1912-1943, Undated), contains various materials reflecting the Withers affiliation with the Episcopal Church of the United States.  Items included are bulletins (1924-1941, Undated) of the Calvary Episcopal Church at which Robert Edwin Withers Sr. and Mary Cloyd Kent Withers regularly worshipped in Pittsburgh, Pa.  Withers served several times as a member of the vestry.  Another folder contains three miscellaneous items pertaining to Calvary Episcopal Church including an 1894 newsletter, a booklet honoring World War I veterans, and a 1925 guide to the church buildings.  Other items in this series include prayer books, a 1933 bulletin from parishes for which Rev. Robert Edwin Withers Jr. served, and a bulletin for the 1944 ordination service of Rev. Charles O'Ferrall Thompson at St. John's Episcopal Church in Wytheville, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Series VI, Legal Records (1883-1938, Undated), contains legal records including wills and lists of assets for the estates of Anastasia Pleasants Kent and her mother Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent.  Also included is a copy of the will of Robert Enoch Withers, agreements between Robert Edwin Withers Jr., and the Arthur F. James company regarding car rental, and a trust deed of Mary Cloyd Kent Withers for support of Ellen Stuart.</p>
      <p>Series VII, Financial Records (1896-1953, Undated) contains 54 folders relating to financial records of Robert Enoch Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, and Robert Edwin Withers Jr..  Included are account books, checkbooks, Social Security documents, and records on charitable donations by the Withers family.  Tax records include personal property tax receipts, real estate tax receipts, and United State income tax forms.</p>
      <p>Also included in this series are bills and receipts from Pittsburgh, Pa. and Wytheville, Va. businesses.  Receipts for Wytheville businesses including Bolling and Owens Company, W. H. Bolling, Brown Electric Company, G. S. Bruce and Company, Cregger and Chapman, Kincer-Miller Hardware Company, Owens and Kent Company, Owens and Owens Drugstore, Rider Brothers Company, J. Garland Sexton, and the Wytheville Telephone Company.</p>
      <p>Series VIII, Photographs (1912-1943, Undated), contains images of Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Jr., Kent Cloyd Withers, and Robert Edwin Withers III.  Also included are images of Tyler Gatewood Kent, Mary Terry Thompson as a child, Peggy Dewhurst (friend of Kent Cloyd Withers), Grace Ann Ashman as baby, Brumfield Royall, Don Spiller, and Billy Spiller as children.Photographs of Ingleside, the house of Kent Cloyd Withers in Spokane, Washington, an unidentified woman at Heinz Pier, Atlantic City, N. J. are also included.  Several other unidentified photographs also comprise the collection.</p>
      <p>Series IX, Miscellaneous Records (1933-1945), contains newsletters of the Aluminum Company of America, booklets on Prohibition and Temperance, and the Waldensians, and school and summer camp records of Robert Edwin Withers Jr. and Kent Cloyd Withers.  Also included are lists, addresses, and recipes collected by Mary Cloyd Kent Withers.  Materials of Robert Edwin Withers Sr. in this series include a National Geographic membership certificate, a Sigma Chi alumni list for Pittsburgh, Pa., and a program for a dinner in honor of Dr. Wesley Clair Mitchell held by the Pittsburgh Athletic Association.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1954, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>158 folders
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1901.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="Series-folder">1:1
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Alice Chinn Withers Goggin, Susan Withers Massie, Robert W. Withers, John Young Terry, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Raleigh W. Chinn, Bettie Ellison Withers Putney, Jennett Withers Cook Boyd, and Flora Virginia Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902-1906
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Robert C. Read, Susan Withers Massie, Annie B. Holt Goggin, H. E. Wood, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Willie Clare Withers, Flora Withers, Lizzie F. Graham, and Gloria Davis.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1900
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Bud Topham, W. Y. Hayes and Sons, N. B. Rhuday of Wytheville Woolen and Knitting Mills, J. W. Wood and Brothers, T. Lacy, Robert E. Scott, Rev. Mercer P. Logan, Lorig R. Millen, and George S. Sexton.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1907
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:4
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Elbert Lee Trinkle, George S. Sexton, Charles B. Thomas, Simon Kelly, J. C. Wysor, Huff, Andrews, and Moyler Company, G. V. Litchfield, J. M. Spewelt, and H. E. Moore.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence - Mary Virginia Royall Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1884-1899
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:5
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include John L. Winchester, David S. Peirce, and Robert Edwin Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 6.  Correspondence - Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1928
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:6
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Mary Cloyd Kent Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 7.  Correspondence - Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1930, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:7
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include Mary Cloyd Kent Withers.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 8.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1912
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:8
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 9.  Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914-1929
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:9
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 10.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930-1937
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:10
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 11.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:11
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 12.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:12
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 13.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:13
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 14.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February - August 1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:14
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 15.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September - October 1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:15
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 16. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:16
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 17.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1948
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:17
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 18.  Correspondence -  Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921-1925
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:18
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 19.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Jennet Ann Withers Cook Boyd
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931-1934, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:19
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 20.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Virginia Secessia Withers Terry
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935-1938
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:20
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 21.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Josephine Putney Dame
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1952
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:21
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 22.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Virginia Withers Ast
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951-1952
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:22
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 23.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Cleaveland J. Campbell
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1952, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:23
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 24.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Clarence J. Kitner
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1950
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:24
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Re: maintenance of Ingleside, house in Wytheville, Virginia.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 25.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Mary Terry Thompson
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937-1952, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:25
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 26.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879-1927
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:26
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Carrie Royall Thomas, Betty Ellison Withers Putney, Faye Walter M. Pintard, B. B. Royall, Willie Clare Withers, Rt. Rev. Cortland whitehead, Mary Pogue, F. Gardiner, Kate Crosby Darling, and Kent Crosby Darling.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 27.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1936
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:27
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Alvah K. Lawrie, Seth G. Malby, Joseph Cloyd Kent, Alice W. Merryman, John Royall Read, Mrs. Harry Graham Robinson, W. M. Gifford, C. Chapman, Robert B. Hill, Robert L. Peirce, and John Royall Read Jr.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 28.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:28
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Katherine Smith Hancock, Bird Carter, Horace B. Horton, Susie Williams Poindexter, Flora Lee Smith, Sam J. Simmons, Joe Manly, Carrie Royall Thomas, Thomas Pinckney, Sallie B. Davis, John C. Hagan Jr., R. W. Massie, Roy A. Hunt, E. M. Payne, William Robinson Terry, and Vincent Matthews Jr.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 29.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1942
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:29
	</container>
            <physdesc>22 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Rose Carter, Flora Lee Smith, Samuel Graham, Henry S. Hohman, Claude A. Rogers, Don Spiller, Anne H. Patrick Kent regarding charge of espionage against her son Tyler Gatewood Kent, Cleaveland J. Campbell, Carrie Royall Thomas, James W. Rickey, Elizabeth Royall Carter Layman, Paul J. Urquhart, Safford K. Colby, Roy A. Hunt, Alice Kennon Williams Gravely, Mary Kent Withers, and Lowell Innes.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 30.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1945
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:30
	</container>
            <physdesc>27 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Lucy M. Rickey, Robert Sanger, Bessie Gordon Jones, Martha Massie, William Terry, Robert L. Peirce, Fred A. Thoughton, E. Blough, Sallie Read, W. Bedford Moore Jr., Don Spiller Jr., S. J. Simmons, W. M. Gifford, E. F. Snead, Penn L. Withers, George O. Morgan, G. L. Nicolson, Robert Read, Kent Crosby Darling, and Garnett Brooke Lawson.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 31.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946-1949
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:31
	</container>
            <physdesc>29 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Charles Holland Mortiz, Virginia  Terry, Howard A. Noble, Cleaveland J. Campbell, Robert Carter, Robert E. Read, H. Austill Pharr, Vivian H. Umberger, Emily Werkheiser, Dorothy W. DeLong, Bessie Gordon Jones, Mary Kent Withers, Kent Cloyd Withers II, Edwin Royall Carter, Arthur B. Kinsolving II, Ovid M. Johnson, Agnes R. Poage, Richard B. Miller, Virginia Spiller, Elizabeth S. Linthicum, Sue Rector Read, and Elizabeth Hamlett Williams Paxton.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 32.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1952
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:32
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Katherine Lord Briggs, Mary Maxwell Gulick, Ovid M. Johnson, Benjamin C. McFadden, Kent Crosby Darling, Elizabeth Hamlett, Helen Gibbons, Jane Radal Hardess, Rose Carter, Rev. Edwin Royall Carter, Janannie McAlpine, Charles O'Ferrall Thompson, Rt. Rev. Charles Clingman, Jim Rea, Elizabeth Otey Williams, William Coalter Paxton, and Ellis M. Frost.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 33.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:33
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Alice Kennon Williams Gravely, Wyatt Massie, Robin Dudley, Mary Turley Goodson Rogers, Emily Alter Werkheiser, Burks Withers Jr., J. M. Peck Jr., Elizabeth Hamlett Williams Paxton, Frederick Crabtree, and Edward Crosby Darling (re: life in pre-Revolution St. Petersburg, Russia).
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 34.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1928
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:34
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: J. B. Kingsley, Reginald Fitz Hugh Bigg-Wither, Reeve Chipman of Temple Tours, Fendall Marbury of Massie, Marbury &amp; Bernard Law Firm, and Everett Armstrong Damon of the Storm King School.   
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 35.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1934
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:35
	</container>
            <physdesc>24 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: William H. Robinson, Nannie Dean of Wytheville Seventh Day Adventist Church, Willard E. Mead, Joseph Cloyd Kent, Bettie A. Palmer, J. H. Kennon of Pittsburgh Water Bureau, Rt. Rev. Robert Carter Jett of the Episcopal Diocese of Southwest Virginia, Ella McKee, Morris C. Miller of Christiansburg Improvement Corporation, R. W. Massie of Lone Jack Limestone Company, L. M. Johnston, Howard H. McClintic, and Edward N. Lewis of the National Cathedral Association.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 36.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935-1937
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:36
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Don D'Ivernois, Rev. W. A. R. Goodwin of Bruton Parish Church, Rev. C. Garmey of Calvary Episcopal Church, F. T. Haigh of Kane Manufacturing Company, Charles M. Thomas of U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, John Royall Read of Canadian Westinghouse Company, Gouverneur P. Hance of Saint Barnabas' Free Home, William J. Donaldson of Donaldson and Montgomery, Rev. Clifton Macon of Calvary Episcopal Church, Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania, Carroll H. Fitzhugh of Trinity Cathedral, U. S. Senator Carter Glass, J. N. Camden of Kentucky River Coal Corporation, Willard E. Mead, T. A. Robinson of Calvary Episcopal Church, William S. Thompson Jr. of Calvary Episcopal Church, and Rolfe Sebastian Ewald of S. F. Ewald Insurance Agency.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 37.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:37
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: J. M. McLaughlin of the Aluminum Company of America, Chester W. Cleaveland of SIgma Chi, Mary Holton Labberton Kirk, Franklin F. Holbrook of the Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, Rev. Dewall L. Gwathmey of St. John's Episcopal Church, Rt. Rev. Henry St. George Tucker, Bishop of the Episcopal Church, Robert L. Peirce, Dr. Hugh H. Trout, J. A. Anderson of Virginia Military Institute, Rev. Edwin J. Van Etten of Calvary Episcopal Church, Charles E. Kilbourne of Virginia Military Institute, John C. Hagan Jr. of Mason-Hagan Inc., R. W. Massis of Long Jack Limestone Company, and James M. Graham of First National Farmers Bank.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 38.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:38
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Rev. Edwin J. Van Etten of Calvary Episcopal Church, James B. Lynch of the Great Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Company, Honorable J. N. Camden of Kentucky, Allen B. williams, Jno. Gibson Jr. and T. A. Robinson of Calvary Episcopal Church, Rev. W. G. Pendleton, Gladys Williams of the Joseph Horne Company, John C. Sheriff of Lindsay, Weis &amp; Hutchinson, Rev. Arthur B. Kinsolving II of Calvary Episcopal Church, Robert C. Jett, John Congrove, Dick M. Reeser, A. D. Christian of Christian, Barton &amp; Parker, D. Stewart Templeton, and Edward K. Davis.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 39.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1943
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:39
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Herbert A. Jacob of Virginia Military Institute, R. S. Marshall of Virginia Military Institute, Campbell Bascom Slemp of the Southwest Virginia Museum, Walter Mitchell, Charles E. Stuart of Stuart, James &amp; Cooke, Inc., S. A. Copp of Carolina Aluminum Company, H. Bartlett Gerrard, Sidney Briggs of North British and Mercantile Insurance Company, George L. Claypool, Rev. Arthur B. Kinsolving II of Calvary Episcopal Church, Rev. Donald E. Veale of Calvary Episcopal Church, N. R. High Moor of Trinity Cathedral, Ovid M. Johnson of R. P. Johnson General Machinery.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 40.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1945
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:40
	</container>
            <physdesc>29 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Fox Chapel Golf Club, Ovid M. Johnson of R. P. Johnson General Machinery, W. Bedford Moore Jr., W. M. Gifford, James M. Graham of First National Farmers Bank, George S. Topham of First National Farmers Bank, Clayton Torrence of the Virginia Historical Society, Joseph M. Crockett of Crockett and Tutwiler, Rueben A. Lewis Jr. of Finance Magazine, H. J. Derthick of Facing Forward Inc., Arthur M. Scully, John Pomfret of St. John's Episcopal Church, Hugh Thompson Kerr of Shadyside Presbyterian Church, Chester W. Cleaveland of Sigma Chi, and Emma H. Rodgers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 41.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:41
	</container>
            <physdesc>34 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  E. S. Ruffin Jr. of Calvary Episcopal Church, Margaret E. Rich of the Family Society of Allegheny County, Richard E. Phillippi, L. J. Smith of the Aluminum Cooking Utensil Company, Charles E. Kilbourne of Virginia Military Institute, Bishop Austin Pardue, Alexander C. Zabriskie of the Virginia Theological Seminary, Ovid M. Johnson of R. P. Johnson General Machinery, J. W. Cappeau of Richards and Company, Stuart B. Campbell, Robert L. Peirce, General Richard J. Marshall of Virginia Military Institute, Edwin Hodge Jr., A. C. Yorke of Pennsylvania Railroad Company, C. E. Hankla of Wytheville Hotel Company, and W. Coalter Paxton of James L. Miller Tobacco Company.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 42.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947-1948
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:42
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: H. L. Mitchell of West Penn Power Company, E. A. Jack of Aluminum Company of America, Richard J. Marshall of Virginia Military Institute, Franz Recum, James R. Gilliam Jr. of Lynchburg Trust and Savings, Marion F. Johnson, William Ellis Jones of Jackson Memorial High School in Austinville, Rt. Rev. Arthur B. Kinsolving II, Fendall R. Ellis of Wythe County Schools, Robert E. Johnson of Wythe County Chamber of Commerce, Calvary Episcopal Church, Gourveneur P. Hance of St. Barnabas' Free Home, and Austin Pardue of the Episcopal Diocese of Pittsburgh.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 43.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:42
	</container>
            <physdesc>26 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: W. F. Halsey of the University of Virginia Development Fund, Rev. Roddey Reid Jr. of St. John's Church in Knoxville, Tennessee, Ernest Garrett, Rev. Sherwood S. Clayton of Grace Episcopal Church of New Orleans, John Huffard, Thomas F. Walker, Charles E. Kilbourne, William S. Thomas of the Diocese of Pittsburgh, Augustus K. Oliver of the Chamber of Commerce of Pittsburgh, H. H. Donaldson of Mercy Hospital, Calvary Episcopal Church, Charles A. Tracy of Amherst Congregational Church in New Hampshire, Richard Milton Sieg, Ann Adams of Kaufman Department Store, Lucius W. Robinson Jr. of Calvary Episcopal Church, Harvey Havelock Smith, Merrill E. Prichard of Sigma Chi, and F. C. Schreiber of Electrical Engineering Consulting.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 44.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Professional
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951-1952
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:44
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Arthur M. Gates Jr. of Wythe County Broadcasting Company, Carleton Barnwell of the Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary in Virginia, Richard J. Marshall of Virginia Military Institute, Waller Poage, Ralph Munn of the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, Herbert A. Jacob of Virginia Military Institute, O. B. Crosser of Davey Tree Expert Company, A. D. Huddleston of the Aluminum Company of America, E. L. Garrett, H. A. Bryon of the Church Club of Pittsburgh, and George T. Harrell of Bowman Gray School of Medicine.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 45.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Virginia Withers Ast
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:45
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 46.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Stuart Bland Campbell
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1906 - 1952, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:46
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 47.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Bette Darling
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1934, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:47
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 48.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Nelle Powell Payne Darling
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:48
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 49.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Anne H. Patrick Kent
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911-1938, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:49
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 50.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Charlotte Miller Kent
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:50
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 51.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Charlotte Kent Pinckney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:51
	</container>
            <physdesc>18 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 52. Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Flora Stuart
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931-1942, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:52
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 53.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - from Mary Cloyd Kent Withers II
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:53
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 54.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1918
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:54
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Sue N. Graham, Weningham Lyons Spelman, May Walton Kent, Mary E. Pogue, Edward Crosby Darling, Florence A. Smith, Margaret B. Brown, and Jack Burress.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 55.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1929
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:55
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: M. W. Talbot, Emily W. Fleming, Elise Caake Ward, B. S. Miller, Helen T. Wiekman, and Tyler Gatewood Kent. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 56.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1929
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:56
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Campbell P. Waugh, Phoebe Kent, Mary Thornhill Williams, Tyler Gatewood Kent, Tom Richardson, Kate T. McClay, Melesse Kerr Alter, Paul Maye, Rhea Davis, Janet Carter Ambler, Nellie Watts Fleming, Robert C. Jett, Arthur C. Thomson, Sally S. Raedhthour, Elizabeth Hamlett Paxton, and Rev. Devall L. Gwathmey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 57.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1945
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:57
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Mary B. J. Rodman, Daisy B. Turner, Edwin Royall Carter, Rev. Arthur C. Thomson, S. B. Davis, Elizabeth Edson Butt, Marguerite Fickes, Agnes T. Davis, Kate T. McClay, Kittie Filler, Lucy M. Cloyd, Phoebe Kent Scholl, Mrs. W. T. Moore, Ellen M. Gayle, Carrie Royall Thomas, and Mrs. Kenneth McAlpine.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 58.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1936-1937
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:58
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Joseph Cloyd Kent, George J. Alcorn and Company, Lucile Donaldson, Phoebe Kent Scholl, Robert Craig Kent Jr., Ishie Halpin, Colonial Art Furniture Company, Emily K. Crockett, and Mary Agnes Repass.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 59.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1938-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:59
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: C. Thurman Scott, Fannie Hounshell, Sue R. Waugh, Emily T. Watterson, Ishie Halpin, Sara Kent Oswald, Kent Crosby Darling, Virginia P. Brown, Sue Peyton, May Kent Repass, Marguerite Webb Fickes, Louisa S. Sinclair, Annabell C. Secombe, Sue A. Rogers, Joseph E. Caldwell re: mental illness of Robert Craig Kent Jr., and Elizabeth Waller Wilkins.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 60.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:60
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Olin Rogers, Sue Nelson Rogers, Mete Goodson, Sue Peyton Broun, Mary Goodson Rogers, Louisa S. Sinclair, Jane Hardess, Agnes Poage, Eliza B. Haskins, Mada Winters, Margaret Scott Caroline Sanders, Percy Blair, Hughes Clark, Frances E. Lacy, and J. J. Demskie. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 61.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1943
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:61
	</container>
            <physdesc>18 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Ann Patrick Kent Jacobsen, Richard R. Beasley, Elizabeth J. Jaeger, Amy Caldwell, William Watson Smith, Genevieve B. Alexander, Kent Crosby Darling, Lillian M. Simmons, Octavia V. Morrow, Frani B. Muser, Marguerite Webb Fickes, Mary M. Restelli, Annabell C. Secombe, Mary Breckinridge of Frontier Nursing Service, Rev. Arthur B. Kinsolving, and Richard Sieg.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 62.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1946
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:62
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Sue Peyton Kent Broun, Ishie Halpin, Ida W. Pereney, Julian S. Gravely, Towns Bremer, Jacob McGavock Boyd, Mary Breckinridge of Frontier Nursing Service, Jane Hardess, Octavia V. Morrow, G. S. Topham, W. D. Pollard, and Phoebe Kent Scholl.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 63.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947-1949
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:63
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Helen H. Church, Mary Breckinridge of Frontier Nursing Service, Mary D. Rowles, Caroline Sanders, Rev. William Lumpkin, Alice Bravely, Josephine Putney Dame, Robert Edwin Withers III, and Jennie McAlpine.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 64.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1951
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:64
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Josephine Putney Dame, Sallie Read, Janet McGavock Boyd, Margaret Scott, Janet Anderson, Jane Hardess, Marguerite Webb Fickes, Genevieve B. Alexander, Mete Goodson, Elizabeth Otey Williams, Walter J. Rome, Jennie McAlpine, Sam R. Sayers, and Mary Agnes Repass, Morgan.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 65.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952-1953
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:65
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: J. Nelson, Jennie McAlpine, Kent Crosby Darling, Helen Becker, Laura M. Scoville, William T. Trevillian, and Genevieve B. Alexander.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 66.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - Undated B - M
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:66
	</container>
            <physdesc>37 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Mary MacLeod B., Elise Heatherington Beall, Jennet Ann Withers Cook Boyd, Mary Cameron, Mary M. Campbell, Maude Leeves Cooper, S. Curran, Jane Darling, Kenny Darling, Pete Darling, Marjorie Doeller, Jean Hay Ewing, Helen A. Graves, Katherine Hancock, Kitty Smith Hancock, Mary C. Johnson, Lucile Donaldson Kennerly, Mildred Laporte, Minnie McCarter, Katharine McCormick regarding her trip to Soviet Russia, Winifred S. Miller, Octavia Murrow, and Frani B. Muser.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 67.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers - Undated, N-W
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-foder">1:67
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Virginia Oswald, May O'Toole, Olive Repass Pope, Mary Goodson Rogers, Dorothy Chandler Rayburn, Margaret Scott, Mary Sumner, Mary Terry, Carrie Thomas, Mary Terry Thompson, Jane Gray Kent Titus, Richard B. Tucker, Sue R. Waugh, Emily Alter Werkheiser, Mary Phillips Whiting, and Rose H. Worthington.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 68.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1909-1912
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:68
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 69.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913-1927
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:69
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 70.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1952
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:70
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 71.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1909-1910
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:71
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 72.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911-1913
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:72
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 73.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Kent Cloyd Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914-1915
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:73
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 74.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:74
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 75.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1919
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:75
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 76.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922-1929
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:76
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 77.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931-1934
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:77
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 78.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935-1938
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:78
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 79.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1951
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:79
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 80.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1926
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:80
	</container>
            <physdesc>19 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Maj. Gen. George Barnett, Samuel J. Graham, Robert Edwin Withers R., Edward K. Price, Ralph D. Rinehart, Raymond Hoblitzell, B. B. Boss, William Page Dame, Fritz Grabner, and Rev. Arthur B. Kinsolving.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 81.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1933
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:81
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Eleanor S. Chapman, Charlie Alison Curry, William J. Newton, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Walter R. Nathan, Wallace Motor Company, Kent Cloyd Withers, Josephine Withers Read, and Georgia Proctor.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 82.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:82
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Katharine Hancock, Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling, Willie B. Grabner, Kent Crosby Darling, Kent Cloyd Withers, and Mary Cloyd Kent Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 83.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1951, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:83
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 84.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1944
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:84
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 85.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:85
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 86.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:86
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 87.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:87
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 88.  Correspondence - Frances Haskins Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:88
	</container>
            <physdesc>25 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 89.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928- 1929
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:89
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 90.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930-1934
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:90
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 91.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1949, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:91
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 92.  Correspondence - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers to Kent Cloyd Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:92
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 93.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:93
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 94.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="series-folder" type="series-folder">1:94
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 95.  Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers Jr. and Frances Haskins Withers to Kent Cloyd Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911-1933
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:95
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 96.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Peggy Dewhurst
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1929, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:96
	</container>
            <physdesc>22 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 97.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Betty Murdoch
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:97
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 98.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Oliver Scaife III
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1934, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:98
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 99.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers from Mary Terry Thompson
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:99
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 100.  Correspondence - Kent Cloyd Withers - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1934
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:100
	</container>
            <physdesc>24 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent, Harry F. Marks, Priscilla Guthrie, William H. Rapp, Hugh Rodman, Edwin Van Etten, Edwin Royall Carter, James M. Coleman, and Andy Kirkbacker.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 101.  Kent Cloyd Withers - Miscellaneous by Surname
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:101
	</container>
            <physdesc>24 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Nancy Allderdice, Virginia Bachman, Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling, Sallie Gibson, Dorothy Glover, Mary S. Gordon, Harriet Gere Jayne, Harriet Marie Jolley, Charlotte Miller Kent, William H. Rapp, Hugh Rodman, Gretchen Rose, and Alice R. Tucker.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 102.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous by First Name
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:102
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 103.  Correspondence - Martha Anne Rogers Withers to Robert Edwin Withers Sr. and Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939-1951, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:103
	</container>
            <physdesc>29 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 104.  Correspondence - Martha Anne Rogers Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939-1945
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:104
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 105.  Correspondence - Martha Anne Rogers Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:105
	</container>
            <physdesc>23 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 106.  Correspondence - Martha Anne Rogers Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:106
	</container>
            <physdesc>22 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 107.  Correspondence - Josephine Withers Read to/from Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1910-1948
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:107
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 108.  Correspondence - Josephine Withers Read to Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:108
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 109.  Correspondence - Josephine Withers Read to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1941, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:109
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 110.  Correspondence - Stephen Putney to Betty Ellison Withers Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:110
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 111. Correspondence - Stephen Putney to Betty Ellison Withers Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:111
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 112.  Correspondence - Stephen Putney to Betty Ellison Withers Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:112
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 113.  Correspondence - Stephen Putney to Betty Ellison Withers Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881-1882
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:113
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 114.  Correspondence - Stephen Putney to Betty Ellison Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:114
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 115.  Correspondence - Stephen Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:115
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Charles Duffman and Company, R. E. Hatcher, Josephine Putney Dame, and Mary Virginia Royall Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 116.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney to Stephen Putney
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878-1880
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:116
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 117.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney from Josephine Putney Dame
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902-1905
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:117
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 118.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney from Josephine Putney Dame
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:118
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 119.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney from Josephine Putney Dame
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:119
	</container>
            <physdesc>16 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 120.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878-1880
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:120
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Janet Anne Withers Cook, H. Coolidge, Susan Dabney Withers Massie, Josephine Withers REad, Kate Massie Smith, and J. D. Jeffries.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 121.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 - 29 October 1905
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:121
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Susan Dabney Williams, Janet Ann Withers Cook, Elizabeth Hamlett Williams, L. Coolidge, Robert Enoch Withers, William Page Dame, and Elizabeth Elb.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 122.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">23 November 1905 - 27 November 1905
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:122
	</container>
            <physdesc>20 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Janet Anne Withers Cook Boyd, Phoebe Holt, Elizabeth E. Coolidge, W. m&gt; Dame, Eliza G. Massey, Virginia Secessia Withers Terry, Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter, Elizabeth Hamlett Williams Paxton, Carrie Royall Thomas, Lucy Maupin, Josephine Withers Read, Sally D. Royall, Anna Clay Crenshaw, Sue M. Graham, Mrs. E. M. Langhorne, and Major and Mrs. Sanders.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 123.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 1905 - 1907
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:123
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Alma M. Cowardin, Ashley C. Dempsey, Ethel Gaines, Kathrynne Holt, Elizabeth Henry Lyons, N. V. Tudor, John H. Fowle, Mary Thornhill Williams, and Janet Ann Withers Cook Boyd.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 124.  Correspondence - Betty Ellison Withers Putney - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:124
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: A. L. Elliott Jr. and Willie Clare Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 125.  Correspondence - Willie Clare Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881-1893
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:125
	</container>
            <physdesc>17 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Josephine Withers Read, Geoff H. Zimmerman, Rosa Bemis, H. L. Taylor, George W. Arthur, J. G. Duncan, Withers Massie, Alilce Withers Goggins, and George H. Zimmerman.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 126.  Correspondence - Willie Clare Withers 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1909, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:126
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: George H. Zimmerman, a physician who practiced in the coal boom town of Pocahontas, Virginia; P. P. Carter, Lizzie R. Poage, May Walton Kent, M. I. Wilson, C. G. Alley, Maggie Whistle, Mrs. Hunt, and Tyler Claiborne.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 127.  Correspondence - William Patton Kent to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1906-1909
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:127
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items; photocopies.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Regarding life as consul in Guatemala City, Guatemala.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 128.  Correspondence - William Patton Kent to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1931
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:128
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Re: social and diplomatic life in Washington, D. C.; William Nuckles Doak; Tyler Gatewood Kent.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 129.  Correspondence - William Patton Kent
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1932-1935
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:129
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Re: Tyler Gatewood Kent in Moscow; murder of Mary C. Hastings by Robert C. Kent; Franklin Delano Roosevelt.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 130.  Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:130
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 131.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:131
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 132.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:132
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 133.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:133
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 134.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:134
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 135.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:135
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 136.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Darling Withers to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:136
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 138.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:137
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 139.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling to Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:139
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 140.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Darling - Various Correspondents
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1909-1910, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:140
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Mrs. J. K. Alter, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., and Flora McIvor Stuart.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 141.  Correspondence - Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling - Incoming 
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883-1942, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:141
	</container>
            <physdesc>13 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Elizabeth Needham re: bombing of London in World War II; William Patton Kent, Mrs. W. H. Fioller, Flora McIvor Stuart, Nelle Powell Payne Darling, Charlotte Miller Kent, Katharine DeFrees, and Elizabeth S. McAlpine.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 142.  Correspondence - Joseph Cloyd Kent to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1932
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:142
	</container>
            <physdesc>12 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 143.  Correspondence - Joseph Cloyd Kent to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933-1939
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:143
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 144.  Correspondence - Joseph Cloyd Kent to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1941-1951, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:144
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 145.  Correspondence - Ellen Douglas Stuart to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1932-1941
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:145
	</container>
            <physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 146.  Correspondence - Ellen Douglas Stuart to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1947
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:146
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 147.  Correspondence - Ellen Douglas Stuart to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:147
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 149.  Correspondence - Ellen Douglas Stuart to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:148
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 149.  Correspondence - Ellen Douglas Stuart to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:149
	</container>
            <physdesc>18 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 150.  Correspondence - Janet Ann Carter Ambler
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880-1889
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:150
	</container>
            <physdesc>8 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: E. Lewis Carter, F. G. Cross, Tyler Claiborne, and Harry Stinson.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 151.  Correspondence - Janet Ann Carter
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1898, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:151
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: E. Mair, Elizabeth Royal Withers Carter, and Willie Clare Withers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 152.  Janet Ann Withers Cook Boyd
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1898, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:152
	</container>
            <physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Henry Cook and Waller Massie Boyd.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 153.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879-1838
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:153
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include: Mary Virginia Royall Withers, E. P. Goggin, Peirce Sanders, Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter, and William Page Dame.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 154.  Correspondence - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:154
	</container>
            <physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  Charlotte Kent Pinckney, Katherine Taylor Reed, and Josephine Withers Read.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 155.  Correspondence - Putney - Watts Family
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1956, Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:155
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondents include:  S. Putney Brown and Eliza Putney Watts.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 156.  Correspondence - Wedding Invitations
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1954
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:156
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Wedding invitations for: Josephine Lillian Belden and Walter Beatty Jackson; Elizabeth Belden Kent and Edward Crosby Darling; Agnes Palmer Lewis and Harry Clinton Ford; Annie Hendren Patrick and William Patrick Kent; Dorothy Mosher O'Hara and Dion Keith Kerr; Eileen Allen and Charles Peirce Macgill; Frances Glover and Robert Edwin Withers Jr.; Elizabeth Lawson and Henry Andrew Jaeger; Portia Tatem and Benjamin Harold Hosler; Mary Terry and Charles O'Ferrall Thompson; Phoebe Kent and Herman Frederic Scholl; Nancy Jane Poage and Alfred Harris Evans; Anne Davidson Williams and Myles Russell Hutchinson; and Mary Dorothea Allen and Douglas West Poage Jr.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 157.  Correspondence - Wedding Invitations
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:157
	</container>
            <physdesc>11 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Wedding invitations for: Clarissa Halstead Stem and E. Fontaine Broun; Catharine Hardin and Robert Wilbur Curry; Marguerite Saunders and Eugene Davis; Harriet La Salle Dorrance and David Marshall Humphrey; Charlotte Johnston Miller and Joseph Cloyd Kent; Mary Spencer Gordon and John Frederick Kraft Jr.; Virginia Peyton Broun and Robert William Lawson Jr.; Frani Blough and Curt Muser; Ruth Tunstall Graham and Robert Lee Payne Jr.; Margaret Elizabeth Fleming and Kenneth Olney Rhodes; and Frances Randolph Howard and Robert Gilchrist Robb.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Folder 158.  Correspondence - Invitations - Miscellaneous
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1937
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">1:158
	</container>
            <physdesc>7 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II.  Withers Genealogy Book Correspondence and Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939-1946
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>30 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III.  Genealogical Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1892-1950, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>9 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV.  Examiner of Records to the Auditor of Public Accounts - Correspondence and Reports
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1896 - 1907, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>50 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series V.  Religious Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894 - 1944, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VI.  Legal Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883-1938, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VII.  Financial Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1896 - 1953, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>54 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VIII.  Photographs
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 - 1943, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IX.  Miscellaneous Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933 - 1945, Undated
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>5 folders.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
