<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00039">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00039::A Guide to the Henry M. Heuser Papers, 1810-1951)//EN" "viwyc00039.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry M. Heuser Papers, <date>1810-1951</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Heuser, Henry M., Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">2006.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>11 October 2011</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Henry M. Heuser Papers, <date>1810-1951</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2006.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Henry M. Heuser Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1810-1951
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2006.2
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">24 folders.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Henry M. Heuser Papers, Mss. Collection 2006.2, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by Ruth Ann Chitwood as part of the W. R. Chitwood Collection in 2001.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The son of Guido A. Heuser and Jennie Sehorn Heuser, Henry Massillon Heuser was born on 28 February 1867 in Wytheville, Virginia.  His father, a prominent merchant in Wytheville, was born in Rodenberg Germany; his mother was the daughter of Rockbridge County sheriff Massillon Sehorn and Sarah Jane Ruff Sehorn.  Her mother died after her birth and her father died a year later.  Jennie was raised by relatives in Wytheville and she named her son Henry after her father.
</p>
<p>Heuser attended schools in Wythe County, graduated from the law school at Washington and Lee University in 1891.  He embarked upon private practice in Ivanhoe, Virginia, and later moved his office to Wytheville.  He subsequently served as commonwealth attorney, member of town council, and judge.  He was a member of the Wytheville Presbyterian Church.</p>
<p>Married to Myra Emily Painter (1870-1925) on 23 February 1893, the couple raised two children, Paul Ernest (b. 1894) and Frederick Randolph (b. 1894).  Heuser died at the age of 90 on 7 June 1957 and is buried beside his wife in East End Cemetery in Wytheville, Virginia.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Papers consist of four series.  Series I, Legal Records (1887-1928, undated), contains documents relating to several cases in which Heuser was involved as a legal professional, deeds, legal publications, attorney licenses, and personal docket books from his service as Commonwealth Attorney for Wythe County.
</p>
<p>Series II, Education Records (1883-1887, undated) contains compositions and debate speeches written by Heuser as well as a notebook for his natural law course taught by Professor John Randolph Tucker of Washington &amp; Lee Law School.  Also included are two certificates from the Peabody Normal Teachers' Institute for Jennie Sehorn Heuser and Dora Heuser and a copy of <title render="italic">Centennial Poem for Washington and Lee University, 1995-1885</title> by Margaret Junkin Preston.</p>
<p>Series III, Genealogical Records (1810, 1951, undated) contains family trees, notes, and correspondence regarding the Heuser, Ruff, Woods, Sehorn and Wallace families.  A special component of this folder is an 1810 certification of character for Cathy Sehorn signed by several supporters residing in Dandridge, Jefferson County, Tennessee.</p>
<p>Series IV, Miscellaneous Records (1886-1949, undated) contains a Wytheville (East End) cemetery certificate, notary public certificate, and certificate for Heuser's role as a government appeal agent for the Selective Service System.  Also included is a copy of <title render="doublequote">Report of the Freedom Train Visit to Penns Grove, N. J.</title> dated 1949 by Paul D. Heuser as well as several political broadsheets relating to temperance.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head><c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Legal Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1928, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Legal Records - Coulter - Littreal Case.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1894.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
	</container>
	<physdesc>10 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains correspondence sent to Henry M. Heuser by his client, A. E. Coulter, regarding allegations made against him by Emmet Littreal of Ivanhoe.  Littreal claimed that Coulter had inappropriate relations with his wife; Coulter denied any wrongdoing and requested that Heuser settle the matter.  Also included are several letters to Coulter from Mattie Littreal, the wife of Emmett Littreal.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Legal Records - William G. St. Clair.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1895-1896.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains correspondence, draft affidavit, and receipts regarding debt of W. G. St. Clair and his wife rented property owned by Frances Hatcher McTeer, widow of John M. McTeer who died in November 1892.  Heuser served as collection agent.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Legal Records - W. P. Sizer.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1893-1896.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
	</container>
	<physdesc>18 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains documents relating to debts owed to W. P. Sizer by R. A. Porter and L. H. Odell. Included are promissory notes, account statements, summons, and correspondence.  
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Legal Records - W. C. Weaver
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1895.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
	</container>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains correspondence between W. C. Weaver, H. M. Heuser, and the Anglice Collecting Agency of Bristol, Tennessee regarding debt that Weaver claims Heuser owes him through J. McWilliams.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Legal Records - Commonwealth Attorney Docket Notebook.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1916 - January 1925.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
	</container>
	<physdesc>1 item.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a personal notebook used by Heuser to record and make note regarding his court docket while he served as commonwealth attorney.  Included are names of cases, name o person to be indicted, and crime committed.  Criminal and civil cases are recorded.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>

	<unittitle>Folder 6.  Legal Records - Commonwealth Attorney Docket Notebook.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1925 - 1928.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
	</container>
	<physdesc>1 item.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a personal notebook used by Heuser to record and make note regarding his court docket while he served as commonwealth attorney.  Included are names of cases, name of person to be indicted, and crime committed.  Criminal and civil cases are recorded.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 7.  Legal Records - Attorney Licenses.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1890-1895.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains attorney license issued to Henry M. Heuser from the Commonwealth of Virginia.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 8.  Legal Records - Felts vs. Commonwealth of Virginia.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1904.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
	</container>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains correspondence relating to the case of Felts vs. Commonwealth of Virginia.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 9.  Legal Records - Virginia State Bar Association Publications.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1887, 1891, 1892.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
	</container>
	<physdesc>3 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains <title render="italic">The History of the Federal Convention of 1787 and of Its Work</title> by John Randolph Tucker, <title render="italic">The Virginia State Bar Association President's Address by Edward C. Burks Delivered at the Third Annual Meeting,</title>   and <title render="doublequote">The Virginia State Bar Association Paper Read by John W. Riely at the Fourth Annual Meeting, 1892</title>.        
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 10.  Legal Records - Deeds.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1890-1905
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
	</container>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains the following deeds:  October 1890, William M. Painter and J. D. Barns; September 1895, H. M. Heuser and Mrs. Frances J. McTeer; October 1895, Mrs. Frances J. McTeer and H. M. Heuser; April 1896, Robert G. Hudson, M. K. Hudson, Edwin E. Hudson and H. M. Heuser; April 1905, Mrs. M. K. Hudson, Robert G. Hudson, Margaret D. Hudson Edwin E. Hudson and H. M. Heuser.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II.  Education Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1887, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>8 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Series II contains compositions, speeches written by Henry M. Heuser while a student in Wytheville schools.  Also included is a notebook used by Heuser while a student in a natural law class of Professor John Randolph Tucker at Washington and Lee University.  An 1885 poem by Margaret Junkin Preston celebrating the centennial of Washington and Lee University.  Two certificates from the Peabody Teachers' Institute, Wytheville, Virginia issued to Jennie S. Heuser and Dora Heuser signed by W. B. McGilvray, dated 12 August 1884, are also included in this series.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Genealogical Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1810-1951, undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Genealogical Records - H. M. Heuser Family Trees.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
	</container>
	<physdesc>6 items.				
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a letter from Charles Heuser of Hanover, Germany with a Heuser family tree.  Also included is a tree for Humphrey Montgomery Sehorn and Alice Cathy.  Another tree documents the Michael Woods and Catherine Campbell line (including the Wallace, Ruff, Anderson, and Sehorn families) as does a smaller tree.  Also included is an ancestor chart for Henry Massillon Heuser that documents his maternal Sehorn and Ruff lines.  
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Genealogical Records - Ruff Family.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
	</container>
	<physdesc>3 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains mimeographed typescript with notes from the family Bible of Jacob Ruff Sr. and William Ruff.  Also included are handwritten notes on the death of Jno. Ruff as well as data copied from notes of Jno. A. R. Varner on the descendants of Martha Wallace and Jno. Ruff.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Genealogical Records - Woods, Sehorn, Wallace Families.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1810, 1951, undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
	</container>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>This folder contains a handwritten article on the Michael Wood and Elizabeth Campbell line (including Wallace line), an obituary for William Anderson Wallace of Devine, Texas, and a letter to Henry M. Heuser from Kit Heuser regarding clipping about death of Massillon Sehorn in 1844.  An 1810 certification of character for Cathy Sehorn signed by several supporters residing in Dandridge, Jefferson County, Tennessee is also included.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1886-1949.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 folders.	
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains membership certificates of Henry M. Heuser East End Cemetery, Wytheville, Virginia; Selective Service System service certificate; and commission as notary public.  Also included is a copy of <title render="doublequote">Report of the Freedom Train Visit to Penns Grove, N. J.</title> by Paul D. Heuser and various political broadsheets by W. M. Martin, J. B. Harsh, C. N. Otey, J. W. McGavock, and John C. Brady.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
