<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00132">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00132::A Guide to the Spiller-Brown Family Letters, 1854-1859)//EN" "viwyc00132.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Spiller-Brown Family Letters, <date>1854-1859</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Spiller-Brown Family, Letters, 1854-1859
<num type="collectionnumber">2001.21
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>11 December 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Spiller-Brown Family Letters, <date>1854-1859</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2001.21
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Spiller-Brown Family Letters
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1854-1859
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2001.21
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">4 items.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Spiller-Brown Family Letters, Mss. Collection 2001.21, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Ruth Ann Chitwood donated the Spiller-Brown Family Letters in 2001 as part of the W. R. Chitwood Collection.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William Hickman Spiller, son of Hickman Spiller and Catherine M. Smith Spiller, was born on 8 October 1800.  He married Susanna Crockett in Wythe County on 22 December 1831.  A successful merchant, Spiller amassed great wealth through his real estate transactions and his various general merchandise stores (Auman and Spiller, Henderliter and Spiller, Bosse and Spiller); at his death in 1855 his estate was worth over $29,000 and included 49 slaves.
</p>
<p>Susanna Crockett Spiller and William Hickman Spiller raised eight children including: Catherine Markham Spiller (1833-1872)(married James Hammet); Jane Crockett Spiller (b. 1835) (married Robert G. Carrington); Elmira Spiller (b. 1838) (married 1) Alexander Stuart Brown (1858) 2) William Alexander Stuart (1863); Josephine Spiller (1840-1904) (married John Preston Sheffey); Lucy Ann Spiller (b. 1842) (married Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers); Frances Smith Spiller (b. 1844); William Hickman Spiller Jr. (b. 1847) (married Cynthia McComas Boyd); and Joseph Robert Spiller (1850-1882).</p>
<p>James Austin Graham, angered over an unsuccessful wooing of Catherine Spiller, shot William Hickman Spiller on 31 March 1855 at the Boyd Hotel in Wytheville, Virginia.  Spiller was in the bar room with Connally F. Trigg, William Terry, Charles Crockett, Oscar Cox, and Mr. Taliaferro.  Graham shot Trigg, who was wounded, before shooting Spiller, who died later in the office of Dr. Ewing.  Spiller is buried in St. John's Lutheran Church Cemetery in Wytheville, Virginia.</p>
<p>The son of Judge James Ewell Brown and Anne Dabney Stuart, Alexander Stuart Brown was born on 20 January 1831.  Brown and his sisters, Jane Brown (1819-1873) and Frances Peyton Brown (1821-1860) (married Joseph F. Kent) were first cousins of William Alexander Stuart and James Ewell Brown Stuart and their siblings who were children of Archibald Stuart (brother of Anne Dabney Stuart Brown)and Elizabeth Pannill Stuart.  Alexander Stuart Brown died on 8 April 1859 after a ten day illness of stomach inflammation.  He is buried at St. John's Lutheran Church Cemetery.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains four letters written to, from, and about the Spiller family and the Brown family of Wytheville, Virginia.  Correspondents include William Hickman Spiller, Elmira Spiller Brown Stuart, Jane S. Brown, Alexander Stuart Brown, M. T. Stuart and M. C. Carter.  Topics include the schooling of Elmira Spiller, murder of William Hickman Spiller, and death of Alexander Stuart Brown.  
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter.  William Hickman Spiller, Wytheville, Virginia to Elmira Spiller, Richmond, Virginia.
<unitdate type="inclusive">12 January 1854.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>3 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>He exhorts her to study well and inform him about her school life in Richmond, Virginia.  He mentions Mr. Hoge, her aunt Kitty Findlay, and Mr. Spotts of Richmond.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter.  William Hickman Spiller, Wytheville, Virginia to Elmira Spiller, Richmond, Virginia.
<unitdate type="inclusive">20 May 1854.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>He urges her to <title render="doublequote">make good use of the time while there and let the last part of your studies and musick be of such a character of advancement as to have the tutors who have had charge of you well satisfied.</title>  He also mentions her sister Jane Crockett Spiller and aunt Jenney Draper.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
	<c01 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Letter.  Jane S. Brown, Wytheville, Virginia to Alexander Brown Stuart.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2 April 1855.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>2 p.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>She writes about the murder of William Hickman Spiller by James Austin Graham, telling him that a large posse of men are tracking Graham who is still at large and that the wedding of Catherine Markham Spiller is postponed.  <title render="doublequote">It made me think of your escape with renewed thankfulness and the situation in which you were placed went far to reconcile me to your departure that you may be happy in your new home.</title>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Letter.  M. T. Stuart to [Elmira Spiller Brown].
<unitdate type="inclusive">17 April 1859.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 p.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>M. T. Stuart expresses sympathy for the death of her husband, Alexander Stuart Brown.  M. C. Carter adds lines of sympathy also in this letter.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
