<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viwyc00108">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00108::A Guide to the Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine Papers,, 1899-1953)//EN" "viwyc00108.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine Papers,, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1953</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Woolwine, Dr. Andrew Bane, Papers, 1899-1953
<num type="collectionnumber">2001.5
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 October 2012</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine Papers,, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1953</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">2001.5
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1953
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2001.5
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">20  books.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p> Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine Papers, Mss. Collection 2001.5, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by Ruth Ann Chitwood in 2001 as part of the W. R. Chitwood Collection.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>The son of Charles Carroll Woolwine and Josephine Woodrum, Andrew Bane Woolwine was born on 3 May 1874 in Pearisburg, Virginia.  He attended the private Pearisburg Academy before attending the Medical College of Virginia.  He graduated from that institution in June 1897.  The new doctor subsequently opened a medical practice in Ceres, Virginia in December 1899 where he practiced until his death in 1945.  Woolwine visited his patients on horseback and horse and buggy until 1914 when he purchased a Ford automobile.
</p>
      <p>Woolwine married Mary Ellen Groseclose of Ceres on 9 October 1902; the couple raised two children, Andrew Groseclose Woolwine, born 1903, and Dorothy Candler Woolwine, born 1913.  Their grandchild, Mary Woodrum Jones Strailman, was born in 1936.  Until his death on 3 November 1945, Woolwine was active in Sharon Presbyterian Church and the Democratic Party.  He was also a member of the Bland County School Board, Southwestern Virginia Medical Society, and the Medical Society of Virginia.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Papers consist of three series of birth records, death records, and account books recording medical transactions practiced by Dr. Woolwine during his tenure in Ceres, Bland County, Virginia.
</p>
      <p>Series I, Birth Records (1918-1942), contains certificates for births attended by Dr. Woolwine in the Sharon Magisterial District (Ceres) of Bland County, Virginia.  As regulated by Virginia law, these birth records are classified and therefore closed to researchers until one hundred years after the event (2018-2042).  Immediate family members may request copies of birth certificates directly from the Virginia Department of Health, Bureau of Vital Statistics.  Kegley Library researchers will not be allowed to view these records until they are declassified.</p>
      <p>Series II, Death Records (1917-1953), contains certificates for deaths recorded by Dr. Woolwine and his successors in the Sharon Magisterial District (Ceres) of Bland County, Virginia.  Each certificate provides name of deceased, sex, race, marital status, date of birth, date of death, age at death, occupation, birthplace, name of parents and birthplace of parents, cause of death, and burial information.  The records are in chronological order; however an alphabetical list has been prepared and is available for researchers in the Kegley Library reading room.</p>
      <p>Series III, Account Books (1899-1945), consists of seven account books that record medical transactions between Dr. Woolwine and patients living in and around Ceres, Bland County, Virginia.  Books include:  Account Book 1, (1899-1903); Account Book 2 (1903-1912); Account Book 3 (15 May 1911 - 15 February 1912); Account Book 4 (1912-1921); Account Book 5 (1921-1926); Account Book 6 (1935-1943); and Account Book 7 (1943-1945).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I.  Birth Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1942.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>9 books.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>These records are classified (closed to researchers) until 100 years after the date of birth as required by Virginia State regulations.  As required by the Bureau of Vital Statistics of the Virginia Board of Health, Dr. Andrew Bane Woolwine recorded births in these booklets that occurred in the Sharon Magisterial District of Bland County, Virginia.  Records are arranged in original order.  CLOSED TO RESEARCHERS until 2018 to 2042.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II.  Death Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1953.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>14 books.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>As required by the Bureau of Vital Statistics of the Virginia State Board of Health, Dr. Woolwine recorded deaths that occurred in the Sharon magisterial district of Bland County.  Each certificate provides name of deceased, sex, race, marital status, date birth, date of death, age at death, occupation, birthplace, name of parents and birthplace of parents, cause of death, and burial information.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 1.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 December 1917 - 19 September 1918.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="Series-folder">2:1
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 item.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for:  Jennie Shields McNutt, Cynthia Elizabeth Kirby, Kitts infant, David Benjamin Umbarger, Margaret E. Lambert, and John Kirby.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 2.  
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">22 January 1918 - 7 March 1919.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for:  Mary Jane Peery, Martha Anne Cox, Groseclose infant, Minerva A. Repass, Dillie Caroline Waddell, Henry T. Lampert, Harvy John Kitts, Lurena Wilkerson, William Stonewall Jackson Morris, Waddell infant, Peter G. M. Spangler, and Mary Jane Atkins.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 3.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11 April 1919 - 22 December 1921.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Edward Henry Creger, Virginia Date Williams, David Marcellas Baugh, Mary Lucinda Groseclose, Elizabeth Ann Umbarger, William Jesse Peery, William Roy Bernard Turley, Mary Jane Groseclose, Rosa May McFarlane, Bruner infant, Louisa Ann Hayton, Bogle infant, Maggie Brown, Kitts infant, Elsie Vivian Peak, Charity C. Waddell, Bales infant, Vietta Marie Houndashell, Laura Naomi Kitts, and Thomas Patton Umbarger.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 4.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10 February 1919 - 4 May 1920
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:4
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for:  Susan Babette Winesett, Ingram infant, Harry Randolph Scott, Leoni Jane Lampert, Christopher Foglesong, Mary Adline Scott, Minnie Gray Hounshell, Ossie May Ingram, Elvira Texas Davis, and Stuart M. Kitts.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 5.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 May 1920 - 21 August 1922
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:5
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Abraham Fry, Lawrence Lafayette Neel, Joseph McHenry Kinder, Ada Florence McClellan, Mary Magdalene Neel, Margaret Ann Havens, John Helory Harden, Josie Alice Wilson, Daniel Adams Crow, Foglesong infant, , Samuel Hillman Harden, Neel infant, James Henry Scott, Claude Swanson Foglesong, and Elbert Smith Stowers.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 6.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 January 1922 - 9 November 1925.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:6
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Sherrell Williams, Newman infant, Amasa A. Tibbs, George Washington Lampert, Gollehon infant, John Greever Peery, Frankie King, Lucinda Catharine Kitts, Newton Montgomery Kitts, Warren Hayton, George Clayborn Cox, Hectorine Ibbie repass, Lucilea Williams, Henry Thomas Tibbs, Nannie Adeline Gillespie, Tibbs infant, Sallie Kate Lambert, William Harrison Tilson, William James Spangler, Ethel Eliza Dillman, Pearl Catherine Dillman, infant Dillman, Catherine Waddle, Estel Peter Crabtree Jr., Beckie Geneva Jones, A. P. L. Wilson, and Etta Matilda Lambert.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 7.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 March 1923 - 1 September 1925
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:7
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Francis Victoria Harden, Stephen S. Kitts, James F. Hounshell, Emma Katherine Lindamood, Mary Jane Repass, Lucy Jane Lampert, Arnold A. Umbarger, Sarah E. Pauley, Kitts infant, Margaret Ann Hounshell, Nancy Ann Hounshell, Lampbert infant, John David Dillman, Sylvia Thompson, Morgan Rufus Umbarger, Neel infant, Effie Bane, Bane Infant, T. J. Randolph Peck, and Calvin Wagner Harden.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 8.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9 January 1926 - 6 December 1932.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="series-folder" type="series-folder">2:8
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Lillie Price Allen, Hezekiah Hampton Hanshew, Elizabeth Lampert, William Bascomb Allen, Harden infant, Lampert infant, Samuel Shelton Davies, Robert G. Kitts, Alice V. Thompson, Harris infant, Joseph H. Hounshell, Joseph Wesley Lambert, Bertha E. Scott, Rebecca Clementine Lampert, James David Umbarger, Polly Ann Kitts, Loudenna Stowers, Robinett J. Waddle, Hattie Catharine Davis, Nora Cleveland Harden, James A. Lambert, Florence Missouri Kitts, Alfred Vanse Thompson, Clarence M. Umbarger Jr., Thomas M. Cassell, Charlie W. Compton, Margie Calene Neel, Geneva Pocahontas Baugh, Mary Jane Umbarger, Sarah Jane Crabtree, Sarah Ellen Neel, and Flanadore Alexis Crabtree.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 9.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">27 March 1926 - 8 September 1928.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:9
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Rachel Jane Umberger, Eliza Jane Broyles, Ella May Harmon, Missouri Kitts Duncan, Gordon infant, Nellie Virginia King, Mabel C. Baugh, Matilda G. Gordon, Matild Louise Williams, Lee Monroe Cox, John Greever King, Louisa Caroline Duncan, Atwell infant, Mary J. Umberger, Williams infant, James Wesley Bridges, John Lewis Hayton, Richard Waddle, Cassell infant, and Boyd Shelton Bridges.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 10.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">19 October 1928 - 6 October 1933.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:10
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Andrew Jackson Williams, Martin Luther Baumgardner, Samuel Stephen Hanshew, Amanda Emeline Stowers, Lavinia Victoria Groseclose, Margaret Melissa Bane, Leonard F. Duncan, Henry H. Foglesong, Adam Dallas Groseclose, Frances Miller King, Hobart Nelson Kitts, Benjamin F. Carnahan Wilson, Ballard Preston McFarlane, Mahalia Victoria Atwell, Reese Samuel Gillespie, Jesraell Taylor Waddle, Mark K. Tilson, Robert Miller King Jr., Meek Lowden, May Ettie Emily Catron, John Wesley Boyles, Robert Lee Groseclose, Hanshew infant, Josephine Bogle, Lizzie Barnett, Sarah Josephine Groseclose, Eula Elvira Repass, Margaret Lockwood Meek, Mae T. Hearner, James Jones Umberger, Bertie Edith Sparks, Elender Lee Fields, James Martin Kitts, Walter Harvey Neel, Cox infant, James Crabtree, Margaret Victoria Groseclose, Hanshew infant, Cregger infant, and Mary Jane McCormick.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 11.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 October 1933 - 19 May 1939.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:11
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for:  Curtis Eugene Groseclose, Durham infant, Ellen Shewey, William G. Ferrell, George Washington Barger, Alice Virginia Tarter Crabtree, Loella Kitts, Victoria Kitts, Laura Agnes Dillow, Charles Martin Hanshew, Ettie Ingram, William Thomas Webb, William Frederick Shewey, Arthur Glen Kitts, Alexandria Price Thompson, Randles Johnson Ingram, ray Foglesong Scott, Ollie Mae Neal, Lettie Maude Hanshew, Garner Davis Peck, Eliza Jane Umberger, Victoria Markum Hanshew, Margaret Christina Foglesong, Alphus Matterson Cox, Wythe Grayson Waddle, William Saunders Bevill, Darthula Ann Spangler, McClellan infant, Willis Grant Lindamood, Matilda Florence Cox, Hattie Ruth Hayton, William P. King, Dicia A. Riley, Estel Monroe Thompson, Thomas J. Peck, Robert Carson Atkins, Isaac Taylor Gollehon, Sarah Elizabeth Kitts, Ellen Rose Wilson, Joe Blane Neel, Freddie Keith Bogle, Barbara Ellen Umberger, Connie May Stowers, Thurman Burke, James William Sparks, Crabtree infant, Lafayette Digsby Repass, Russell Layne Umbarger, Amanda Victoria Boling, Martha Bostonie Lindamood, Robert Lee Neal, John David Umbarger, Harmon Ingram, Cosby Jane Sparks, Polly Ann Pauley, Matilda Jane Kitts, Ransom Marion Catron, Virginia Bane, and Pauley infant.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 12.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1 June 1939 - 2 June 1942.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:12
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Alice W. Waddell, Foglesong infant, Alma Mozelle Bogle, Sarah L. Lambert, Sarah A. Catron, Gemima Ellen King, Everett Walters, Shirley Marie Pauley, Fred Fulton Foglesong, Ibbie Frances Thompson, Everett Kent Thompson, Charles Harlow Lindamood, Hanshew infant, Ellis Miller Brown, Burke infant, Sarah Ann Davis, Andrew Napoleon Bogle, Jonas Umberger, Martin E. Foglesong, John Shewey, Florence Shewey, William B. Hounshell, Cox infant, John Thompson, Hariston Morton Lambert, Harvey George Brewster, Cregger infant, Cregger infant, Charles Benton Hayton, Eliza Melvinia Perkey, Amanda D. Umberger, and Texis Mae Wilson.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 13.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">16 September 1942 - 1 December 1948.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:13
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Aubrey Arthur Harner, Ellen M. Epperson, Louisa Caroline Waddle, Wythe Green Kitts, Robert Bane Shewey, Leona Kitts Shewey, Rexie Kitts, Iria Guy Repass, Simon Kent Groseclose, Samuel V. Ingram, Dora Thorn Lindamood, Lillie K. Kirby, Blena Clyde Barnette, Julia Ann Gillespie, Ida Missouri Brewster, Edna Hester Groseclose, Hancock infant, Lambert infant, Clinton Artis Kinder, MIlton Groseclose, Andrew Jackson Hayton, Blanche M. Kimberling, Groseclose infant, Charles Henry Neel, James David Neel, James C. Burke, John White Pauley, Larry J. Blackburn, Josie Alberta Thompson, Robert Keith Umberger, Minnie Margaret Peery, Lillie Virginia Crabtree, Andrew Bane Woolwine, Martha Sophia Perkey, Frank Seldon Stowers, Laura Jane Kinder, Andrew Enoch Umbarger, Elbert Swanson Crabtree, Kent Williams, Amanda Elizabeth Kitts, Innis Helen Reeves, Jefferson Fletcher Dieter, Rodia Winesette, Susan M. Cox, John Henry Edwards, Nathan Easterly Winesette, Charles Abram Crabtree, Ira Otis Kitts, Lyda Mae Patrick, and Arthur Gale Repass.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book 14.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">17 January 1949 - 19 July 1953.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Series-folder" type="series-folder">2:14
	</container>
            <physdesc>1 book.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This book contains records for: Lula Kegley Compton, Ellie Frank Hayton, Ina B. Waddell, Charles M. Hounshell, Ashby Palmer Umbarger, Lillie Belle Cassell, John Herman Tibbs, William Henry Durham, Laura Virginia PEck, Henry Holly Harden, Margaret Irene Catron, Anna Belle Barger, Paul Everett Hounshell, John William Shaffer, Charles Hanshew, Carl Hayton, Sam B. Kirby, Virginia Albertine Edwards, Henry Arlington Umberger, Ada Grace Kitts, Mary Dell Hayton, Ollie Kate Hayton, Mary Ann harden, Rhoda Jane Brown, Joseph Graham Bogle, H. Perry Thomas, Joseph Blanton Kirby, and Minerva Ann Hubble.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III.  Account Books.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1945.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>7 books.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>This series contains account books that record medical transactions between Dr. Woolwine and patients living in and around Ceres, Bland County, Virginia.  Included are Account Book 1, (1899-1903); Account Book 2 (1903-1912); Account Book 3 (15 May 1911 - 15 February 1912); Account Book 4 (1912-1921); Account Book 5 (1921-1926); Account Book 6 (1935-1943); and Account Book 7 (1943-1945).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
