<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wcc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wcc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viwyc00124">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViWyC">PUBLIC "-//Wytheville Community College::Kegley Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViWyC::viwyc00124::A Guide to the Sayers Family Papers, 1779-1888)//EN" "viwyc00124.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sayers Family Papers, <date>1779-1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Sayers Family, Papers, 1779-1888
<num type="collectionnumber">1993.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&#169; 2011 By Wytheville Community College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Carlson Reynolds, <date>9 November 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Sayers Family Papers, <date>1779-1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections, Kegley Library
<num type="Collection Number">1993.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville
            Community College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2011
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Cathy Carlson Reynolds
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Kegley Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Sayers Family Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1779-1888
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1993.3
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">9 folders.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Sayers Family Papers, Mss. Collection 1993.3, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College, Wytheville, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by the estate of Samuel R. Sayers in 1993.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William Sayers and his wife Esther Thompson Crockett Sayers settled in Wythe County in the mid-eighteenth century and raised three sons, Robert Sayers, Alexander Sayers, and John Thompson Sayers.  The eldest son Robert Sayers (1754-1826) accumulated vast wealth during his lifetime including the profitable Anchor and Hope Plantation near Max Meadows.  A bachelor, he willed the Anchor and Hope land to his nephew Robert Sayers. 
</p>
<p>John Thompson Sayers (1758-1816) served as a major in the Continental Army during the Revolutionary War and fought under Colonel William Preston.  He was wounded severely at the battle of Cowpens, South Carolina on 17 January 1781.  Surviving his wound, he married Susanna Crockett  in 1784 and raised eight children including Robert Sayers I (1796-1876).</p>
<p>Their second son, Robert Sayers I inherited the Anchor and Hope Plantation.  He and his wife, Senah Ross Sayers, raised eight children.  Their sons, Robert Sayers Jr. (1826-1911), John Thompson Sayers II (b. 1831), and Samuel Rush Sayers (1833-1914) all served during the Civil War on the side of the Confederacy.  Robert Sayers Jr. was a colonel of local militia while John Thompson Sayers II enlisted in 1861 in the Wythe Grays (Company 1, 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment) and eventually rose to captain.  Federal troops captured him shortly after the battle of Gettysburg in July 1863 and imprisoned him at Johnson's Island near Sandusky, Ohio.  Military records indicate that he was released in March 1865.</p>
<p>Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers was educated at the University of Pennsylvania during the mid-1850s and practiced medicine in Wythe County.  During the Civil War he served as surgeon with the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment and the 27 Virginia Infantry Regiment.  For what he cited as personal reasons, Dr. Sayers unsuccessfully sought a resignation from the Army in May 1863.  Citing his valuable medical knowledge and experience, military authorities refused his request and he continued to serve as surgeon throughout the war.   Dr. Sayers married Lucy Ann Spiller; one his children was Robert Sayers III.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Sayers Family Papers are arranged in three series.  Series I, Correspondence (1849-1888, Undated) includes letters received and sent to Senah Ross Sayers and her family from 1849 to 1888.  Correspondents include Robert Sayers Jr., John Thompson Sayers II, Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers, Anne C. Sayers, and Robert Sayers III.  Topics discussed in this correspondence document daily life at Anchor and Hope Plantation and Wytheville, Virginia.  School life at Emory and Henry College (1849), Hampden-Sidney College (early spelling) (1888), United States Naval Academy (1888), and the University of Virginia (1888) is also covered in these letters.</p>
<p>The bulk of the correspondence, however, offers a fascinating glimpse at life during the Civil War from both a soldier's and civilian's perspective.  Robert Sayers Jr. served as a colonel in the local militia while John Thompson Sayers and Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers both served in the Army of Northern Virginia, Confederate States Army.  Samuel Rush Sayers worked as a regimental surgeon throughout the war with the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment and the 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment.  His letters reveal much of camp life and battles (Second Manassas, Winchester, Fredericksburg, Spotsylvania, Wilderness, and the siege of Petersburg). His brother served as a lieutenant and eventually captain of the Wythe Grays (Company A, Virginia Infantry Regiment).  John Thompson Sayers was captured at Gettysburg and sent to Johnson's Island, a prison camp near Sandusky, Ohio.  Several letters to and from the prisoner and family members are included.
</p>
<p>Series II, Military Records (1779-1865) includes records of John Thompson Sayers including an order from Colonel William Preston in 1779 during the Revolutionary War and 1797 and 1799 commission papers as captain and major of the 35th Regiment, Virginia Militia.</p>
<p>Series III, Miscellaneous Records (1854-1863, Undated) contains records including a library card and lecture pass for Dr. Samuel Rush Sayers from the University of Pennsylvania Medical School in 1854.  Also contained in this series is a Confederate States of America bond dated 1863 issued to Robert Sayers.  Genealogical notes, newspaper clippings, and photocopies of correspondence in Series I complete this series.  The photocopies contain a note in the upper left hand corner indicating in which folder the original will be found.</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head><c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series I.  Correspondence.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1888, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>5 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1849, 1859.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>2 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Sayers Jr., Emory and Henry College, Emory, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">15 October 1849.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to Ann C. Sayers, c/o Mrs. Susan Crockett Sayers Hoge, Giles County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">21 February 1859.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1861-1862.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>9 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Harpers Ferry, Virginia to Robert Sayers Jr., Wytheville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 June 1861.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp near Winchester, Virginia to Susan Crockett Sayers Hoge, Giles County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">21 November 1861.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  John Thompson Sayers, Camp near Winchester, Virginia to Dear Sister.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">24 November 1861.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to Dear Daughter.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">27 November 1861.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp in Highland County, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">9 April 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">11 August 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Prince William County, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.  
		<unitdate type="inclusive">31 August 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:7
		</container>
		<physdesc>4 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Richmond, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">10 December 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:8
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Yerby Hospital, Fredericksburg, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">14 December 1862.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">2:9
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; postscript, 2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 3.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1863-March 1864.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Surgeon, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, Camp Paxton, Virginia to James A. Seddon, Secretary of War, Richmond, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">20 May 1863.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.; fragment in 3 pieces.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Reverse has 1) note from Charles A. Haynes, Lieutenant Colonel Commanding, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20 May 1863; 2) note from Daniel M. Shriver, Lieutenant Colonel, 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment, 20 May 1863; 3) note from R. T. Coleman, Chief Surgeon, Johnson's Division, 21 May 1863; 4) note from Jubal A. Early, Major-General, 2nd Army Corps, 21 May 1863; 5) note from W. H. Taylor, Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia, 21 May 1863; 6) note from L. Guild, Medical Director, Army of Northern Virginia; 7) note from W. H. Taylor, Headquarters, Army of Northern Virginia, 24 May 1863; note from C. A. Lee, Assistant Adjutant General, 30 May 1863.  All concerning disapproval of Samuel Rush Sayers' request for resignation.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">13 October 1863.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter. Robert Sayers Jr., Wytheville, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 October 1863.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp near Orange Courthouse, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Block No. 10, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 January 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>



		</c03>


		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">7 March 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">3:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 4.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">April 1864-1865.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>6 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Camp Stonewall Brigade, [unknown] to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 March 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Ohio to Sister.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">9 April 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Field Hospital, [unknown] to Senah Ross Sayers.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">6 May 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Location perhaps near Spotsylvania Courthouse, Virginia.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Anne C. Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia to John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Sandusky, Ohio.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 August 1864.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  John Thompson Sayers, Johnson's Island, Ohio to Senah Ross Sayers and Robert Sayers Sr., Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 January 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Field Hospital, 2nd Corps, Army of Northern Virginia, near Petersburg, Virginia to Senah Ross Sayers, Anchor and Hope Plantation, Wythe County, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 March 1865.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">4:6
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 5.  Correspondence.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1888, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  R. Crockett, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 February 1888.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>3 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  W. Mc [illegible], Hampden-Sidney College, Farmville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">21 June 1888.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:2
		</container>
		<physdesc>7 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>early spelling of Hampden-Sydney College.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Samuel Rush Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia to Robert Sayers III, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">28 June 1888.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>

		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Robert Sayers III, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland to Samuel Rush Sayers and Lucy Ann Spiller Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">3 October 1888.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>On reverse: [unknown] Sayers to Will [unknown].
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Letter.  Lucy Sayers, Wytheville, Virginia to Ellen B. Stuart, Saltville, Virginia.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 January [unknown].
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">5:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>2 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II.  Military Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1779-1865.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Military Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1779-1799.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>5 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Order from Colonel William Preston, Montgomery County, Virginia for Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">3 June 1779.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:1
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: orders to impress provisions during march <title render="doublequote">of Continental Soldiers to the northward.</title>
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
			</c03>

			<c03 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle>Note from Jonathan Conger to Leader, Tory Expedition.
			<unitdate type="inclusive">13 January 1790.
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:2
			</container>
			<physdesc>1 p.
			</physdesc>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Re: letter to Leader of the Tory expedition up New River to allow Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers to receive his pay.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Order from Colonel William Preston to Lieutenant John Thompson Sayers.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">3 April 1780.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:3
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: recruitment of men near the Lead Mines.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Appointment of John Thompson Sayers as Captain.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">7 September 1797.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:4
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: 35th regiment, 19th Brigade, 3rd Division of Virginia Militia.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>

		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Appointment of John Thompson Sayers as Major.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2 October 1799.
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder-item" type="folder-item">1:5
		</container>
		<physdesc>1 p.
		</physdesc>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Re: 35th Regiment, 19th Brigade, 3rd Division of Virginia Militia.
		</p>
		</scopecontent>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III.  Miscellaneous Records.
<unitdate type="inclusive">1854-1863, Undated.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 folders.
</physdesc>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 1.  Miscellaneous Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1854-1863, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 items.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Folder contains lecture pass dated 11 October 1854 and library card issued 18 October 1854 for Samuel Rush Sayers for use at the Pennsylvania Hospital.  Lecture card was for lectures by Samuel Jackson, M. D. , University of Pennsylvania.  Also included is a Confederate States of America bond, issued to Robert Sayers, dated 1 September 1863 and undated genealogical notes on John Thompson Sayers and Susan Crockett Sayers.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>Folder 2.  Miscellaneous Records.
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1888, Undated.
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>Photocopies.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Photocopies of correspondence in Series I and newspaper clippings.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
