<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vachcbc00001">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed" scriptencoding="iso15924"
    dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-VaChcBC">PUBLIC "-//Charles City County Richard M.
      Bowman Center for Local History//TEXT (US::VaChcBC::VaChcBC00001::William Henry Harrison and
      John Tyler Rare Books Collections, 1773-1862)//EN" "VaChcBC00001.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the William Henry Harrison and John Tyler Rare Books Collections,
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1773-1862</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">William Henry Harrison and John Tyler Rare Books Collections<num
            type="collectionnumber">RB</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Charles City County Richard M. Bowman Center for Local History</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vachcbc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2024 (<emph><extref
              xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/" xlink:type="simple"
              >CC0 1.0</extref></emph>)</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using a form and manually entry <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">2024-07-26</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>William Henry Harrison and John Tyler Rare Books Collections, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1773-1862</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Charles City County Richard M. Bowman Center for Local
        History<num type="Collection Number">RB</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vachcbc_logo.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Charles City County Richard M. Bowman Center for Local History, Charles City,
        VA</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2024</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vachcbc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Charles City County Richard M. Bowman Center for Local History</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>

  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Charles City County Richard M. Bowman Center for Local
      History</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <!-- DACS 2.2 -->
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Charles City County Richard M. Bowman
        Center for Local History</repository>
      <!-- DACS 2.3 & 2.4 -->
      <unittitle label="Title">William Henry Harrison and John Tyler Rare Books Collections,
          <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1773-1862</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">RB</unitid>
      <!-- DACS 2.5 -->
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent>54 books</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <!-- DACS 4.5 -->
      <langmaterial label="Language">Materials in this collection are in
          <language>English</language>.</langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract"/>
      <!-- DACS 2.6 -->
      <origination label="Creator"/>
    </did>

    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <!-- DACS 4.1 -->
      <accessrestrict id="ref2">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>The collection is open for research use.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
    </descgrp>
    <!-- DACS 2.7 -->
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p/>
    </bioghist>
    <!-- DACS 3.1 -->
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection includes published books and booklets related to Presidents John Tyler and
        William Henry Harrison. Some of the titles are written by Presidents Harrison or President
        Tyler while others are written about them. The collection includes presidential addresses to
        Congress, public lectures, Whig documents, monument dedications, sermons and funeral
        eulogies.</p>
      <p>Interesting and unique examples include texts in favor of Harrison's presidency,
        those against the "Tyler dynasty" and a former Postmaster General who states that "The
        ferocity of the Harrison party is equal to their folly." Additional documents include an
        1841 census of the Eastern District of the United States with categories for free white
        persons, free "colored" persons, and enslaved individuals.</p>
    </scopecontent>

    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>1. Abell, Alexander Gordon. <title render="italic">Life of John Tyler, President of the United States</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>2. An Old Democrat. <title render="italic">The Contrast: or, Plain Reasons Why William Henry Harrison should be Elected President of the United States, and Why Martin Van Buren Should Not be Re-Elected</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>3. Angier, Joseph. <title render="italic">A Eulogy on the Occasion of the Death of William Henry Harrison, Late President of the United States</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>4. Bacon, Leonard. <title render="italic">A Discourse on the Death of William Henry Harrison, President of the United States, Delivered before the Citizens of New Haven, on the 17th of April, 1841</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>5. Beard, Reed. <title render="italic">The Battle of Tippecanoe.  Historical Sketches of the famous field upon which General William Henry Harrison won renown that aided him in reaching the presidency .  Lives of the Prophet and Tecumseh with many interesting incidents of their rise and overthrow. The campaign of 1888 and Election of General Benjamin Harrison </title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>6. Boston Harrison Club. <title render="italic">Harrison Melodies. Original and Selected. </title> Harrison Melodies. Original and Selected. 
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>7. Chitwood, Oliver Perry. <title render="italic">John Tyler, Champion of the Old South</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>8. Christian, George L. <title render="italic">John Tyler Address delivered before the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Virginia at Greenway, Charles City, Virginia on Monday October 17, 1913 at the unveiling of a memorial to mark the birthplace of President Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>9. Collins, T.K. &amp; P.G.  <title render="italic">The Life of Major-General William Henry Harrison</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>10. Crapol, Edward P. <title render="italic">John Tyler, the accidental president</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>11. Cumming, Hiram. <title render="italic">Secret history of the perfidies, intrigues and corruptions of the Tyler dynasty: with the mysteries of Washington City connected with that vile administration in a series of letters to the ex-acting President</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>12. Dow, F. J &amp; Co. <title render="italic">Pictorial History of Remarkable Events in America. In Four Parts.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>13. Eaton, George W. <title render="italic">Prof. Eaton's Address, in Hamilton, N.Y., On the Occasion of the Death of William Henry Harrison</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>14. Ellett, Katherine Tyler. <title render="italic">Young John Tyler.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>15. Freilinghuysen, Theodore. <title render="italic">Report of the Committee of Arrangements of the Common Council of the City of New York, for the Funeral Obsequies in Memory of William H. Harrision, Late President of the United States: with an Oration</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>16. Globe Office. <title render="italic">Comparison of Mr. Poinsetta plan for the re-organization of the Militia with that of General Harrison, and both with the old law.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>17. Gordon, Armistead C. <title render="italic">Monument to John Tyler. Address delivered in Hollywood Cemetery at Richmond, Virginia on October 12, 1915 at the dedication of the monument erected by the Government to John Tyler, tenth President of the United States.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>18. Gordon, Armistead C. <title render="italic">John Tyler. Tenth President of the United States. An Address by Armistead C. Gordon at the Dedication, October 12, 1915, of the Monument Erected by Congress in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, VA in Memory of President Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>19. Hadduck, Charles C. <title render="italic">A Discourse Delivered at Hanover, N.H. May 7, 1841, on the Occasion of the Death of William Henry Harrison, Late President of the United States</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>20. Hazard, Samuel. <title render="italic">United States Commercial and Statistical Register.</title> Volume 4 No. 23. June 9, 1841.
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>21. Hoffnagle, Warren Miles. <title render="italic">The Road to Fame: William Henry Harrison and national policy in the Northwest from Tippecanoe to River Raisin.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>22. Hooper, J. J. <title render="italic">Congress of the Confederate States. : Proceedings on the announcement of the death of Hon. John Tyler, January 20, 1862</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>23. House of Representatives. <title render="italic">House of Representatives Report no. 485 (27th Congress, 2nd Session). Claims of the State of Virginia</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>24. Kendall, Amos. <title render="italic">Mr. Kendall's Address to the People of the United States, May 1840</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>25. Kendall, Amos. <title render="italic">Kendall's Expositor for 1841: Containing an Epitome of the Proceedings of Congress of the Memorable Extra Session: also, Dissertations upon Currency, Exchanges, the Tariff, and Other Topics, with a summary of the Current News</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>26. Knight, Thomas A. <title render="italic">Tippecanoe, being the story of the Tippecanoe and Tyler Too! Campaign of 1840</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>27. Lambert, Oscar Doane. <title render="italic">Presidential Politics in the United States 1841-1844</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>28. Leahy, Christopher J. <title render="italic">President Without a Party, The Life of John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>29. Marshall, W. &amp; Co. <title render="italic">The Life of William Henry Harrison, the People's Candidate for the Presidency</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>30. May, Gary. <title render="italic">John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>31. McRae, A. S. <title render="italic">The Whig Log Cabin at the City of Richmond in 1840</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>32. Monroe, Dan. <title render="italic">The Republican Vision of John Tyler.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>33. Moser, Harold D. <title render="italic">John Tyler a Bibliography.</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>34. Peterson, Norma Lois. <title render="italic">The Presidencies of William Henry Harrison &amp; John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>35. Poinsett, Joel Roberts. <title render="italic">Plan of the Standing Army of 200,000 Men: submitted to Congress by the Secretary of War, and recommended by the President of the United States</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>36. Prescott, E. G. <title render="italic">A Sermon Delivered Before the Inhabitants of the Town and County of Salem, N.J., on Friday, April 23, 1841. In Commemoration of William Henry Harrison, Late President of the United States</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>37. Reed, John. <title render="italic">Speech of the Hon. John Reed, of Massachusets on the General Appropriation Bill</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>38. Rives, William C. <title render="italic">Letter from the Hon. William C. Rives, of Virginia</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>39. Sherman &amp; Co. <title render="italic">The Civil Services of William Henry Harrision, with Extracts from his Addresses, Speeches, and Letters, and a Sketch of his Life</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>40. Southern Historical Publication Society. <title render="italic">Charles City-William Byrd, John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>41. Tyler, Frances Payne Bouknight. <title render="italic">A Time of High Cotton. A Personal History of Three Interrelated Plantations. Mulberry Hill, Home of Lt. William Miller Bouknight. Pine House, Home of Capt. Benjamin Warren Bettis. Sherwood Forest, Home of America's Tenth President, John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>42. Tyler, John. <title render="italic">Message from the President of the United States John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>43. Tyler, John. <title render="italic">Lecture Delivered Before the Maryland Institute for the Promotion of Mechanic Arts, on Thursday evening March 20, 1855 by Hon. John Tyler of Va., ex-President of the United States. Subject: "The prominent characters and incidents of our history from 1812 to 1836</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>44. Tyler, John. <title render="italic">Message from the President of the United States. To the Two Houses of Congress, at the Commencement of the First Session of the 27th Congress, June 1, 1831</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>45. Tyler, John.<title render="italic">Message from the President of the United States, 28th Congress, 1st Session</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>46. Tyler, John.<title render="italic">An Address, Delivered Before the Literary Societies of the University of Virginia, on the Anniversary of the Declaration of Independence by the State of Virginia</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>47. Tyler, Lyon Gardiner. <title render="italic">John Tyler and Abraham Lincoln. Who was the Dwarf? A reply to a challenge by Lyon Gardiner Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>48. Unknown. <title render="italic">Proceedings on the Announcement of the Death of Hon. John Tyler, January 20th and 21st, 1862. Published by Order of the Congress by J. J. Hooper, Secretary</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>49. Unknown. <title render="italic">John Tyler: His History, Character, and Position with a Portrait</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle> <title render="italic"></title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>50. Weeks, Jordan, &amp; Co. <title render="italic">The People's Presidential Candidate; or The Life of William Henry Harrison of Ohio</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>51. Whig Central Committee of Maryland. <title render="italic">Address to the People of Maryland by the Whig Central Committee of the State</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>52. Whig Party in Virginia. <title render="italic">Address of the Whig Convention for the Nomination of  Electors, to the People of Virginia</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>53. Wise, Henry A. <title render="italic">Seven decades of the Union. The humanities and materialism illustrated by a memoir of John Tyler</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>54. Zullman, Daniel. <title render="italic">Address delivered in the Tabernacle before the Tippecanoe and other Harrison Associates</title>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
