<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viwn1">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-Viwn">PUBLIC "-//Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library//TEXT (US::Viwn::viwn1::A Guide to the Macky-Dunbar Records, 1796-1814)//EN" "viwn1.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Macky-Dunbar Records, <date>1796-1814</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Macky-Dunbar Records
<num type="collectionnumber">1752 THL
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Archives Staff
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library <!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/hrl_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 2018 By Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Lorna M. Loring, <date>22 August 2018</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Macky-Dunbar Records, <date>1796-1814</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library    <!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Accession number">1752 THL
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/handley.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library   <!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2018
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Archives Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer"> Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library  <!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a"> Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Macky-Dunbar Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1796-1814
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">1752 THL
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 volume ; 40 cm</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Dunbar, Robert; Macky, Robert
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to all researchers.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Restrictions may apply concerning the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult a member of the archives staff for information concerning these restrictions. The user assumes all responsibility for identifying and satisfying any claimants of copyright.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Macky-Dunbar Records, 1752 THL, Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library, Winchester, VA, USA.<!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information</head>
<p>Acquired as a gift.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Dr. Robert Macky (1737 - 1814) was a Scotsman by birth and is thought to have been a Quaker. He came to Virginia from Pennsylvania. He was the surgeon in the 11th VA Regiment of Foot during the Revolutionary War and at one point served with Colonel Daniel Morgan. He was also personal physician to Lord Fairfax.</p>
<p>Dr. Macky was active in business and politics and became both weathly and influential. On January 31, 1778, he received a land grant of 430 acres in Hampshire County from Lord Fairfax. In 1779, he purchased the James Dowdall Lot #60 on the north side of Piccadilly Street and the east side of Drury Lane (present day Braddock Street), where he built his home. Dr. Macky also purchased Lot #77 from the estate of George Washington in 1804. </p>
<p>Dr. Macky died March 10, 1814 at his residence on the corner of Braddock and Piccadilly Street (where the current Old Post Office building now stands). He and his wife Catherine were both buried in the garden of their home. When the home was razed the Post Office and adjacent parking lot were built over the garden. The graves were never moved.</p>
<p>There is less information about his partner, Robert Dunbar. Dunbar lived in a house at the intersection of Piccadilly and Loudoun streets, close to where Macky lived. He died in 1815 and is buried in Mt. Hebron cemetery. His daughter, Mary Louise Dunbar, was the second wife of Winchester lawyer Philip Williams.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection holds a ledger belonging to the medical practice of Doctors of Robert Macky and Robert Dunbar. The ledger contains records of treatment and sale of medicines to patients between the years 1796 t 1814, mainly in the Winchester-Frederick County area. The account book shows entries organized by individual account holders accompanied by the names of those whose treatment was billed to that account holder, often with details of treatment. Additionally, there are records of business transactions between the practice and individuals providing services of one kind or another, and names of other local doctors consulted by the practice.</p>
<p>Entries may show family members, guests, hired workers, and enslaved persons receiving treatment. The practice also provided medical care to people who, through infirmity or poverty, were under the care of the Overseers of the Poor of Frederick County. Consequently, the accounty book is a valuable source of information about people living in the Winchester-Frederick County area, as well as for the history of medicine in Virginia at the turn of the eighteenth century. An index of account holders and other names treated by or doing business with Macky and Dunbar is available and kept with the collection.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>
<persname role="author">Thomas, Ann Whitehead.</persname>
<title render="doublequote">Dr. Robert Macky: Surgeon, Revolutionary War, 1737[?]-1814.</title>
<imprint>
<date type="publication">1990.</date></imprint>
Located in MMF-Macky, Dr Robert, Ann Whitehead Thomas Collection, 938 THL;
<persname role="author">Dunn, Victor S.</persname>
<title render="doublequote">Frederick Parish Vestry Book, 1764-1818.</title>
<title render="italic">Magazine of Virginia Genealogy</title> 45, no. 1.
<imprint>
<date type="publication">February 2007: 32-38</date></imprint>
<persname role="author">Cartmell, Thomas.</persname>
<title render="italic">Shenandoah Valley Pioneers and their Descendants: A Hisotry of Frederick County, Virginia.</title>
Berryville, VA: Chesapeake Book Company, 1963.
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head><c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://cdm17303.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p17303coll4/id/840/rec/3">Account Book of Drs. Robert Dunbar and Robert Macky,</extref>
<unitdate type="inclusive">1796-1814
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container type="Box">1</container>
<physdesc><extent>1 volume ; 40cm</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01> 
</dsc>
</archdesc> 
</ead>
