<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead audience="internal" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00217.xml"
      >vihart00217</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Bertha Couchman Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence,
          1918-1927: <num>SC 0063</num></titleproper>
        <author>Tiffany Cole, February 2017 </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2017 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole
        on <date>2017-03-23 14:02:39 -0400</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the Bertha Couchman Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence,
          <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918-1927</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          0063</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Tiffany Cole, February 2017</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Bertha Couchman Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence, </unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Hess, Bertha Couchman, 1884-1980</persname>
      </origination>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Dunn, Ethel Virginia, 1903-2002</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0063</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.12 Cubic Feet; 2 letter folders</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1918/1927" type="inclusive">1918-1927</unitdate>
      <physloc audience="internal" id="aspace_c0550bbd6fcbff4ff569f8ac4f9ff411">Special Collections,
        Carrier Library, James Madison University </physloc>
      <abstract audience="internal" id="aspace_7d0d762f8e39e1bca49ad6e1af2a71b4">The Bertha Couchman
        Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence, 1918-1927, is comprised of four postcards and
        seven letters written by Hess and Dunn, her niece, to their family in Martinsburg, West
        Virginia. Couchman authored three postcards while visiting Harrisonburg in August 1918 and
        the remainder of the correspondence was written by Dunn while she was a student at the State
        Teachers College at Harrisonburg and while she was a teacher in Morgantown, West
        Virginia.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_870025f2fd036396b63a75e7e23f341d">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy
          laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting
          the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_763705dcbceeec60c0aeec1eeaa360ad">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite audience="internal" id="aspace_ff5499ac5e58a29a070e6f2aafdc3381">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[Identification of item], [box #, folder #], Bertha Couchman Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn
          Correspondence, 1918-1927, SC 0063, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison
          University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_7b01b2cdd9cb0a07431be5c58ceddc18">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The correspondence was donated to Special Collections by Maxine N. Evans in September
          2002. Evans' mother, Evelyn Staples Nuse was Ethel Virginia Dunn's first cousin. Evans'
          grandmother, Alice Couchman Staples, was Bertha Couchman Hess' sister.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist audience="internal" id="aspace_7eea1e0da9dffa48932b8c3189ef448e">
        <head>Provenance</head>
        <p>The donor came into possession of a "Xerox size box" of materials saved by Barbara
          Lucinda (Lucy) Gordon Couchman, Bertha Couchman Hess' mother and Ethel Virginia Dunn's
          grandmother, and Alice Couchman Staples, the donor's grandmother. The materials that make
          up this collection were contained within that box.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <processinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_d6a6918ea18b6aba3785380c7758f200">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>At some point during initial processing and for unknown reasons, the envelopes that
          accompanied the letters in this collection were photocopied and the originals discarded.
          The letters were dated based on the postmark on the envelopes and based on information
          provided by the donor. In order to streamline the process of applying collection numbers,
          Special Collections staff completed a large-scale renumbering campaign in the spring of
          2017. <emph render="bold">This collection was previously cataloged as SU
          2002-0910.</emph></p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist audience="internal" id="aspace_3170a454f9402fa72b202d7991b1311c">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>Bertha Couchman Hess was born April 20, 1884 to David Calvin Couchman and Lucy Gordon
        Couchman of West Virginia. She married Robert Newton Hess (1880-1854) on June 20 1917 in
        Martinsburg, West Virginia. She died in April 1980 and is buried at Darkesville Cemetery in
        Berkelely County, West Virginia.</p>
      <p>Ethel Virginia Dunn, Hess' niece, was born September 29, 1903 to William Nelson Dunn and
        Mary Catherine Couchman Dunn of Martinsburg, West Virginia. Dunn matriculated into the State
        Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg in 1923 and attended for two years. She was a member
        of the Choral Club, Racquet Tennis Club, Athletic Association, and Y. W. C. A. She went on
        to attend Rutgers University where she received a Bachelor of Science degree in education.
        Dunn was a school teacher Morgantown, West Virginia for four years before continuing her
        career in New Brunswick, New Jersey where she taught for 44 years. Dunn died February 9,
        2002 and is buried at Rosedale Cemetery in Martinsburg, West Virginia.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_3959c5ffe05096d5b7f4cdeb2a815d31">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The Bertha Couchman Hess and Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence, 1918-1927, is comprised of
        four postcards and seven letters written by Hess and her niece Dunn to their family in
        Martinsburg, West Virginia. Couchman authored three postcards while visiting Harrisonburg in
        August 1918 and the remainder of the correspondence was written by Dunn while she was a
        student at the State Teachers College at Harrisonburg and while she was a teacher in
        Morgantown, West Virginia.</p>
      <p>In Hess' three postcards to family she mentions that she is having a nice time (she
        attended the fair) and that Harrisonburg is a "beautiful little town" of about 6,000 people.
        The postcards feature scenic views of Harrisonburg and the State Normal School for
        Women.</p>
      <p>Dunn's correspondence dates primarily from her time as a student at the State Normal School
        for Women. In a postcard written to her grandmother, postmarked October 19, 1923, Dunn
        describes how she plans to spend her free time: "I am going on a hike Saturday. We are going
        up to the mountains for chestnuts. This certainly is a pretty little town and I like it real
        well." The postcard features a view of the court house. An additional five letters are
        included from Dunn's time as a student and are dated 1924-1925. She wrote to her
        grandmother, Lucy Gordon Couchman, and her Aunt Bert, presumably the aforementioned Bertha
        Couchman Hess. Dunn's letters include descriptions of Harrisonburg and campus: "This is a
        very pretty town and the view of the mountains are lovely. I never saw such lovely sunsets
        before. We have a beautiful school. There are eight large stone buildings with red tile
        roofs." She also provides detailed accounts of life as a student including descriptions of
        classes, roommates, social events, meals, weather, and receiving care packages. She makes
        frequent mention of her cousin Sadie and Aunt Laura who live in town. Dunn also describes a
        trip to Clifton Forge, Virginia in March 1925, during the holiday between quarters.</p>
      <p>Dunn's last letter is dated November 29, 1927 at which point she is teaching school in
        Morgantown, West Virginia. She describes the Thanksgiving holiday during which she threw a
        party for her students. Her class also put together a box of groceries for a needy
        family.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement audience="internal" id="aspace_7ce703bf9c6e5c2c79ea69bf4d24630d">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The correspondence is arranged by author in two letter folders and further arranged
        chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <bibliography audience="internal" id="aspace_adc68c5712d0e479bfe48b5bbddadda1">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Obituary for Ethel V. Dunn, <emph render="italic">The Herald-Mail</emph>, February 11,
        2002.</p>
      <p><emph render="italic">The Schoolma'am</emph>, 1924. Harrisonburg (Va.): State Normal School
        for Women.</p>
      <p><emph render="italic">The Schoolma'am</emph>, 1925. Harrisonburg (Va.): State Teachers
        College.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh">State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) --
          Students -- Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) --
          History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) --
          Students -- Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) --
          History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">James Madison University -- Students -- Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="local">James Madison University -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Education, Higher -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Universities and colleges -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg --
          History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Morgantown (W. Va.) -- History</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat">Letters (correspondence)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Postcards</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_8204aac3fe088cfa096cf189ffa338dc" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bertha Couchman Hess Postcards, <unitdate normal="1918/1918"
            >1918</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_a9d6f18c925fb30b639ebb2e67229fe4" label="Box:Folder"
            type="Box:Folder">1:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_42b5e96883a4e189f6e1ae36053479c3" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ethel Virginia Dunn Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1923/1927"
              type="inclusive">1923-1927</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_55935c357f49256f00d2f190709b9b43" label="Box:Folder"
            type="Box:Folder">1:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
