<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9"
     xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1"
              dateencoding="iso8601"
              langencoding="iso639-2b"
              repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid countrycode="US"
             mainagencycode="US-vihart"
             url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00352.xml">vihart00352</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories, 1978-1979:<num>SdArch 5</num>
            </titleproper>
            <author>JMU Cataloging, 1993
</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2019 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved. </date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       xlink:type="simple"
                       xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and transformed with ASpace2VaHeritage.xsl on <date>2020-02-17 14:49:27 -0500</date>.</creation>
         <langusage>English</langusage>
         <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1979 </date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SdArch 5</num>
         </subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad"
                    xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
         <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2019</date>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>JMU Cataloging, 1993
</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <repository>
            <corpname>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</corpname>
         </repository>
         <unittitle>African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories</unittitle>
         <origination audience="internal" label="source">
            <persname role="dnr" source="local">Ramsey, Inez Linn</persname>
         </origination>
         <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SdArch 5</unitid>
         <unitid label="Collection Number"
                 encodinganalog="099$a"
                 audience="internal"
                 identifier="246"
                 type="Archon Instance::ACCESSION">246</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.46 cubic feet; 7 folders, 15 audiocassettes, 15 cds</physdesc>
         <unitdate normal="1978/1979" type="inclusive">1978-1979</unitdate>
         <abstract id="aspace_5e4cc2762f8096ae5d44c5fcee1d2e32">African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories, 1978-1979, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts, photographs and background research of interviews with black residents of Harrisonburg, conducted by students under the supervision of Inez L. Ramsey, Professor of Library Science and Secondary Education at James Madison University.</abstract>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict id="aspace_a9e9762ebc18ae961f689795971cb083">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Access to the Oral Histories is governed by agreements with the narrators. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>  
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict id="aspace_4eb1171aa344e1f24b87ebc8cd07013e">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>  
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite id="aspace_bd91a3973c563a95db0a6c7f50324510">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories, 1978-1979, SdArch 5, Special Collections, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.</p>  
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo id="aspace_0b751e61fb74dd15ac6c4e195b09c3ab">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Collection was donated on June 4, 1991 by Dr. Inez Ramsey.</p>  
         </acqinfo>
         <processinfo id="aspace_ef8d8acbd46f3c9af3f16769a79a7bc5">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>Collection was cataloged at the item level in 1993; the descriptive metadata was compiled into a Finding Aid format in 2019. Cassette tapes were transferred to MAMA-R 700MB gold cd-r using Tascam cc-222 mkII; 618mb. Audio recordings were digitized by Kirsten Mlodynia, Digital Project Specialist at JMU Libraries in July 2018.</p>  
         </processinfo>
      </descgrp>
  
  
  
  
  
      <bioghist id="aspace_c9397e5987cc03419823ab9995d2f022">
         <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
         <p>Dr. Inez Ramsay was a librarian and professor of  JMU from 1975 until her retirement in 1998. In 1978, Ramsay served as the project director for the summer workshop, "Oral Tradition and Storytelling in the Black Community of Harrisonburg," in which she worked with six JMU students to conduct interviews that would "reconstruct the kind of lives black people in Harrisonburg have lived over the years." Legal releases from interviewees were obtained in 1991 and 1992.</p>  
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="aspace_225e1091ea6db8b7ca4178b14e384fad">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The African Americans in Harrisonburg Oral Histories, 1978-1979, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts, photographs and background research of interviews with black residents of Harrisonburg, conducted by students under the supervision of Inez L. Ramsey, Professor of Library Science and Secondary Education at James Madison University.</p>  
      </scopecontent>
      <bibliography id="aspace_ef22c57d438ea1218c98b4b46cc437bd">
         <head>Bibliography</head>
         <p>Reed, Gary. "Workshop seeks to preserve local black heritage." The Breeze, August 2, 1978.</p>
      </bibliography>
  
      <dsc>
         <c01 id="aspace_faab5a32433d546126fe10450be016eb" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-1: Documents and photographs, <unitdate normal="1978/1979" type="inclusive">1978-1979</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_e867727b88701626ec88e532b28f191e"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_82e49455082fe24dd814f91f8e6ea543"
                          parent="aspace_e867727b88701626ec88e532b28f191e"
                          type="Folder">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_307f36285897f51dcfb272f6043857cf">
               <head>Scope and Content</head>
               <p>Supplemental information includes list of persons buried in "Newtown Cemetery," the "colored cemetery" located on Kelly and Hill Streets, Harrisonburg, Va; "Roll of colored voters in Rockingham in the early 1900's," researched by Johnny Dove; 2 pages from the "History of the Augusta Street Methodist Church." Newspaper articles include: "Earl Johnson," from AFRO Magazine, Nov. 21, 1953, "R.E. Johnson dies; former Olympian" (Harrisonburg, Va. Daily News-Record (?), n.d.); "Mr. Harris has 93rd birthday," retired principal of Lucy Simms School (H'burg Daily News-Record (?), n.d.); "Simms School," (H'burg Daily News-Record, Aug. 22, 1978); "Despite segregation law, 'people were kind'," by Chris Simmons (H'burg Daily News-Record, Thurs., July 3, 1980); "Roberta Webb, a Valley treasure: black educator lived her religion," (H'burg Daily News-Record, Tues., Feb. 7, 1995).  Photographs and negatives of Miss Lucy Simms and school children.</p>
            </scopecontent>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_bf631147b16460cde3a67e4a66198317" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-2: Peggy Curry interviewed by Eugene "Ickey" Hollins, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 22, 1978</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_ed36050475f293877ab696a978e2d199">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Mrs. Peggy Curry of Harrisonburg, Va., wife of James Curry. Describes childhood including education (Effinger and Lucy Simms schools), busing of black children from surrounding areas including Elkton, McGaheysville, Grottoes to Harrisonburg), teachers, special days at school, black basketball team; Madison College (May Day); home remedies; segregation (swimming); and the free black community at Zenda. Recorded at the home of Mrs. Peggy Curry, Harrisonburg, Va. on July 22, 1978.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_c27f88fac9cdc0b491452595c9a76978">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_f83abaf32fd507eecf38176b819ad705">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_24c23e9b2e9731dca1ccaf4cb1ddab8c" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 22, 1978</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_c308a66a41f4f1dd3f414b75cccb2540"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_18406b49aebd8994ddb56e4171500c5e"
                             parent="aspace_c308a66a41f4f1dd3f414b75cccb2540"
                             type="Folder">2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_efb0d6a4400ac611838906e648f14934" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-3: Willie Nickens interviewed by Inez Ramsey and Vicki Lloyd, <unitdate normal="1978/1979" type="inclusive">July 17, 20, 24, 1978 and February 14, 1979</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_f743556fdebc3c9dec7f07fcac5085a3">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Virginia "Willie" Josephine Nickens (b. 1895) of Harrisonburg, Va., school teacher and maid for twenty years at Madison College. Describes childhood incl. experiences driving cattle thru town for Siebert family; "switching" (discipline); riding horses, downtown stable, local race track; roller skating, double decker sleds; bear and snake stories, fortune telling by Bob Rawls, the half-breed Indian blacksmith; heating with pot bellied stoves, lighting by kerosene lamps; early education (Effinger, Lucy Simms schools -- knew about Tin Cup Alley school, teachers Fannie Wilson, L. Simms and brother), training at Hampton Institute and meeting President Taft; cooking (quince honey, apple butter); gardening; home remedies; Madison College (Newman farms, first men on campus, soldiers, three sorority houses at Fine Arts bldg. where she was maid); stories of Indians in Bath County where her mother was born, also in Rockingham County (dug a tunnel from Hilltop to spring at Court Square in Harrisonburg); Red Hill and Zenda; churches (AME church and the missionary from Africa, John Wesley Methodist Church, Rev. Ronald Colley); Court days; various town personalities and black businesses (barber shops, black restaurant owner, first black policeman, Joseph Williams, the Olympian, R. Earl Johnson); her family (incl. story of her mother, born into slavery -- father the master, later escaped and caught), her children; mixed race families, voting privileges; and relations between blacks and whites over the years. Recorded at the home of Mrs. Willie Nickens, Harrisonburg, Va. on July 17, 20, 24, 1978 and Feb. 14, 1979. Tapes for four interviews. Note that some tapes contain blank sides: 5-3f (side 2 of tape 3); 5-3h (side 2 of tape 4); 5-3i (side 1 of tape 5)</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_43d4831da2748be36195bded995ded22">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_e6bcf8ffc19cd2da7b0e748d29fce588">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_ce82cd1a7ca1fcda89da509409a83147" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript and Supporting Documents, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 17, 20, 24, 1978 and February 14, 1979</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_d3969e03825452ea276dc30e40e368fc"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_7eb977f363845beca732800ee6c0571e"
                             parent="aspace_d3969e03825452ea276dc30e40e368fc"
                             type="Folder">3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_cfd9c461c96de4ca5f3e885a5df1a743" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-4: Minnie Stuart Bell interviewed by Inez Ramsey and Brenda McCormick, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 1978</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_99ba32c47f963ec779488f8fe7acbeae">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Mrs. Minnie Bell Stuart (b. 1894) of Harrisonburg, Va., known as Miss Minnie. Describes her childhood living in the black community of Depot Hill and Tin Cup Alley; importance of church in life as a preacher's kid, her grandmother teaching Sunday school to both black and white children from Effinger Street, founding of the AME Church (preacher from Africa, Rev. Marion Gioper, also Rev. Collings); daily life fetching water at the Spring House, using Black's Run as a community gathering place, picking wood from railroad tracks; black businesses (lady who owned a second-hand store, fishmonger who sold fish from Baltimore), other downtown buildings/businesses; courting practices; clothes people/boys wore; home remedies (dandelion wine); people and Asbury Methodist Church she worked for as a cleaning maid; and information about her family and children. Recorded at the home of Mrs. Minnie Bell Stuart, Harrisonburg, Va. in July of 1978.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_52178561faaace750ad9a1ad3bf04bea">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_055c2c2f00c089313e3c94906e0b40aa">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_e08902791147afec0082f85e13e26939" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript and Supporting Documents, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 1978</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_5910ae6a5d8b5e734ab74c9cea0c32d5"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_5a5bfbfcdf25d20307879a1d5d2e1eac"
                             parent="aspace_5910ae6a5d8b5e734ab74c9cea0c32d5"
                             type="Folder">4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_eae140b72569100cd6b14e34e088a21b" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-5: Helen Irvin Wells interviewed by Inez Ramsey and Carolyn Hobson, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 18, 1978</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_dbc163833fa32c976c6a2982e81415ad">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Mrs. Helen Irvin Wells (b. 1898) of Harrisonburg, Va., school teacher at Grottoes, Elkton and Bridgewater Elementary schools and cook at Madison College for fifteen years. Describes her childhood incl. holiday observances (Easter, Christmas); games, ghost stories told by the half-breed Indian, making dolls &amp; hats from corn husks, honeysuckle baskets; education (Effinger School, recollections of L. Simms, her brother, the poet U.G. Wilson, spelling contests, school schedule based on farming seasons), and later education at Va. State College); histories of local Methodist churches (circuit preachers John Wesley, Mr. Otterbein), gardening, canning, recipes (scripture cake); making quilts, hook rugs, and tatting (making lace). Recorded at the home of Mrs. Helen Irvin Wells, Harrisonburg, Va. on July 18, 1978 (?).  Includes 4-leaf paper contains recollections of the well known teacher, Lucy Simms, the names of local black Civil War veterans, and a list of prominent black leaders within the community. Note that the paper indicates three dates (July 18-20, 1978).</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_81fa8819d81cfe289262e35de31e1b1d">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open to research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_745405f349bd316361bedabe44dfe7b6">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_5545336a9a948832d59b6273cbff0c38" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript and Supporting Documents, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 18, 1978</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_376fa47d14e614d86cbab9e92f35f682"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_ec1950ccdf00b9f4db2b4eb462048e2f"
                             parent="aspace_376fa47d14e614d86cbab9e92f35f682"
                             type="Folder">5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_10c016c5ee94838d500ad71f847bb90a" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-6: Roberta Morgan Webb interviewed by Vicki Bemisderfer, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 20, 1978</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_99310e6766d022730930ddcb1f6e867d">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Mrs. Roberta Morgan Webb (b. 1889), a teacher for many years in the Harrisonburg, Va. area. Born in Raleigh, N.C., she spent her formative years with the Middleditches, a white family. Describes childhood (games, farming, holidays); education in integrated schools in Pa. and N.J. (ex. Ridley and Westfield, N.J.), graduation at Hampton College, teaching with L. Simms, Effinger School; home remedies; R. Earl Johnson; her family and children; and relations between blacks and whites. Recorded at the Va. Mennonite Nursing Home in Harrisonburg, Va. on July 20, 1978.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_9b5c672d4f7eb4f7547c8a52d6cf440b">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_91ddacf0dc0eec8c2d0ae12a7321a957">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_bcda5dcc00057f065a251ffc4ac68f8f" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript and Supporting Documents, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">July 20, 1978</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_81039fba8b8be4ba3d0c634b6033b7f9"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_bb3b0e4d70b20b0b3b0c507859fb642c"
                             parent="aspace_81039fba8b8be4ba3d0c634b6033b7f9"
                             type="Folder">6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_ea8722b5187f91983159b4c353a2f7a4" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>5-7: James Curry interviewed by Inez Ramsey, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">August 2, 1978</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_6010a28557246862acd655a2c8bce799">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Mr. James Curry of Harrisonburg, Va., custodian of Spotswood Elementary School and first black deacon of the Mennonite Church in Va. Describes childhood including life on the farm, discipline of children, education (Effinger and Lucy Simms schools), childhood games; his family; black churches including the Broad Street Mennonite Church, Pleasant Hill AME Church; black communities (Port Republic, Bridgewater, Red Hill in Harrisonburg); black businesses (carpenter shop, taxi business, the candy man/Dixie Williams' Store), professional teachers (Lucy Simms, Jeannie Francis) and doctors (Dr. Dickerson and the flu epidemic); home remedies; Madison College as a women's school; Harrisonburg as a small town (ex. watching horses being driven thru town, brick/cobblestone streets); reminiscences of WWI (changing of German St. to Liberty St.) and WW II (rationing, black soldiers); and general relations between blacks and whites. Recorded at the home of Mr. James Curry's son, Harrisonburg, Va. on Aug. 2, 1978.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_068abe1992d0e4ee566bdf3e2b58ad50">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_97eaab0294994bd8dc56afdca6aa9747">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_f368dbf892a82de6fdf4fd1af9314af4" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1978/1978" type="inclusive">August 2, 1978</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_fa8548da9d508960a78f3abc455b7da3"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_630b513d1fa3e0ca105614a13d0505fd"
                             parent="aspace_fa8548da9d508960a78f3abc455b7da3"
                             type="Folder">7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
