<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY Malone SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1575543~S0" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY Younger SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1184290~S0" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY OFerrall SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1307875~S0" NDATA html>
]><ead id="vihart00078">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::00078:: Margaret Reed Collection, 1902-1914)//EN" "vihart00078.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Margaret Reed Collection, <date>1902-1914</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Reed, Margaret, Collection, 1902-1914
<num type="collectionnumber">2041
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Heather Browne, <date>January 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper> A Guide to the Margaret Reed Collection, <date>1902-1914</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Accession Number"> SC# 2041
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Heather Browne, January 2008
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Margaret Reed Collection,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1902-1914
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC# 2041
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">One legal-sized folder containing three items
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The collection consists of three items: A letter from Charles T. O'Ferrall to Mayme Clarke Robinson concerning the family history, a transcript of the letter typed by Isabelle Robinson Reed, the daughter of Mayme Clarke Robinson, and a photocopy of Mayme Clarke Robinson's application to the Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR). 
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Charles Triplett O'Ferrall; Mary "Mayme" Clarke Robinson
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>None.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>None.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Margaret Reed Collection, 1902-1914, SC# 2041, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift of Margaret Reed, the great-granddaughter of Mayme Clarke Robinson, donated in 2007.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Charles Triplett O'Ferrall (Oct. 21-1840 - Sep. 22, 1905) was born in Frederick County, VA and spent much of his youth residing in Morgan County, VA (now WV). After his father's death when O'Ferrall was fifteen, he took over his father's position as clerk pro tempore of the circuit court in Morgan County. At the age of seventeen he was elected as the Clerk of the Court and held that position until the outbreak of the Civil War in 1861. Although O'Ferrall and Morgan County were supporters of the Union, he joined the Virginia Calvary in 1861 as a private. By 1865 O'Ferrall was an acting colonel, managing the forces in the Shenandoah Valley. During the War he sustained eight injuries and took a year-long recovery. During this period he met his future wife Annie McLain. The couple was married on Feb. 8, 1865. After the War O'Ferrall and his wife briefly ran an inn in Staunton, VA. In the fall of 1868 he enrolled in Washington College (now Washington and Lee) to study law. He graduated in August 1869 and settled in Harrisonburg, VA where he began his active political life. As a Democrat, he represented Rockingham County in the Virginia House of Delegates, 1871-1873; served as Judge for the Rockingham County Circuit Court, 1874-1880; was a member of the U.S. House of Representatives, 1884-1893; and served as governor of Virginia, 1894-1898. In 1898 he retired from public and political life. He wrote his autobiography <title render="italic">Forty Years of Service</title>, in 1904 and died a year later in Richmond.</p> 
<p>Mary "Mayme" Clarke Robinson was not as prominent a public figure as C.T. O'Ferrall, but she led an important and interesting life none the less. At the time of her application to the DAR in 1914 she was thirty-nine years old. She was married to Francis A. Robinson and they resided in Marshall, Illinois. She was born in Parker City in Armstrong County, Pennsylvania in 1875. Francis (Frank) Robinson worked for an oil company so they moved and traveled often. She and Frank had two daughters, Isabelle and Helen Jane. Isabelle is the grand-mother of the Donor, Margaret Reed. Frank passed away in the 1930's of heart disease; Mayme never remarried. As a widow Mayme (also known as "Dee Dee") lived in Westfield, NY, Chautauqua, NY, and Atlantic City. She would often visit and stay with friends in different places for a year or so. She spent the last years of her life in a nursing home in Erie, PA. She passed away in the middle to late 1960's when she was in her 90's.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection consists of three items, thirteen pages total, in one legal folder. The items included are a hand written letter from Charles T. O'Ferrall to Mayme Clarke Robinson, a typed transcript of this letter composed by Isabelle Robinson Reed, daughter of Mayme, and a photocopy of Mayme's application to the Walter Burdick chapter of the DAR. The letter provides a genealogical history of the O'Ferrall family and its extensions, it is seven pages in length on four sheets of paper; the original pages three and four are missing. A handwritten surrogate for page three is provided. The typed transcript is also missing page four. The application to the DAR is four pages in length and provides genealogical information about the applicant dating back to her great-grandfather James Clarke who served as a Quartermaster under Captain Fox in the American Revolution, and a branch of Charles T. O'Ferrall's family.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>One legal-sized folder arranged chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>
Malone, Dumas, editor. <extref entityref="Malone"><title render="italic">Dictionary of American Biography</title></extref>, New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1934, pp. 633-634. Ref. E176.D56
</bibref>
<bibref>
Younger, Edward, editor. <extref entityref="Younger"><title render="italic">The Governors of Virginia 1860-1978</title></extref>. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1982, pp. 135-141. F225.G77 1982
</bibref>
<bibref>
Biographical information about Mayme Clarke Robinson provided by the donor, Margaret Reed and her uncle, Truman P. Reed (Mrs. Clarke's grandson).
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Original DAR application and transcript of letter have been retained by donor. 
</p>
</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>See also the Charles Triplett O'Ferrall Collection, <extref entityref="OFerrall">SC# 2015 </extref>
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
