<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
      langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00094.xml"
         >vihart00094</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers,
                  1788-1967:<num>SC 0184</num>
            </titleproper>
            <author>Heather Browne, March 2008</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
               href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2018 By JMU Libraries. All
               rights reserved. </date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                  xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
                  Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and transformed with
            ASpace2VaHeritage.xsl on <date>2018-07-25 12:03:38 -0400</date>.</creation>
         <langusage>English</langusage>
         <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11-21</date>
            <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, <date era="ce"
               calendar="gregorian">1788-1967 </date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
               0184</num>
         </subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
               xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
               xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
         <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2018</date>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Heather Browne, March 2008</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <repository>
            <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
         </repository>
         <unittitle>The Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, </unittitle>
         <origination label="Creator">
            <famname rules="local" source="local">Leon and Judy Liskey</famname>
         </origination>
         <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0184</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.4 cubic feet; 1 box</physdesc>
         <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1788/1967" type="inclusive"
            >1788-1967</unitdate>
         <abstract id="aspace_31d822af7eb29cfa160a0bdcbd90866d">The Liskey Collection of Heavner
            Family Papers, 1788-1967, consists of one box (.4 cubic feet) of personal
            correspondence, business and personal financial records, and various other items
            pertaining to the William Heavner family, documented through the maternal side: William
            Heavner, Evaline Heavner Aubrey, Dorcas Aubrey Breneman (also spelled Brenneman), and
            Mae Breneman Liskey. Other names represented are Hughes, Brake, Dove, Hess, and Trumbo,
            among others. The collection is arranged chronologically in four series: Richard Hughes
            Estate Papers, Correspondence, Financial Papers, and General Miscellany.</abstract>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict id="aspace_d7521f78e115b8b0348937c88ee97823">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
               privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff
               before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
               collection.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict id="aspace_ab56ba095b3d64b458561bb1742f644b">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
               University Special Collection Library. For more information, contact the Special
               Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite id="aspace_e666ec3dea77d46c245037f4f4b074eb">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[Identification of Item], [box #, folder #], Liskey Collection of Heavner Family
               Papers, 1788-1967, SC 0184, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison
               University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo id="aspace_d3f903d4813531a7333f361418ff16b4">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Gift of Leon and Judy Liskey in November 2007.</p>
         </acqinfo>
         <custodhist id="aspace_d6e5d2264833eb8c2fa83dbcfa7a5338">
            <head>Provenance</head>
            <p>The collection was found in the eighteenth century home of the donors.</p>
         </custodhist>
         <processinfo id="aspace_cb36036859e20b04dc492c24221538a7">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>In order to streamline the process of applying collection numbers, Special
               Collections staff completed a large-scale renumbering campaign in 2017-2018. <emph
                  render="bold">This collection was previously cataloged as SC 5006</emph>.</p>
         </processinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist id="aspace_a7bb2347d349c1cc8b0bd94b333c4617">
         <head>Bio/Historical Information</head>
         <p>The Heavner family has a long and rich history in the Shenandoah Valley. William Heavner
            (1787-1866) was born in present day Pendleton County, West Virginia to Joseph and
            Elizabeth Hevinor. William married Joanna Custer (1792-1862) in 1814, and shortly
            thereafter purchased 650 acres in the area now known as Fulks Run. The couple raised
            seven children: Wells, Delilah, Elizabeth, William Jr., Harvey, Julian (Julie Anne), and
            Evaline. In addition to farming, William operated a blacksmith shop on the family
            property. Heavner also served as executor of the estate of Richard Hughes, of whom
            little is known. Why Heavner was acting as executor on behalf of Hughes is unclear.
            Nonetheless, papers relating to Richard Hughes' estate remained in the custody of
            Heavner after Hughes' death. </p>
         <p>Of the Heavner children, only three lived past the age of fifty: Wells (78), Julian (53)
            and Evaline (84). Wells (1815-1893) married Elizabeth Hess (1822-1875) around 1851, and
            with Elizabeth's mother Catherine, moved to Champaign County, Ohio, where Elizabeth's
            siblings had settled. They maintained contact with the Heavner family through
            correspondence, as over the years they moved further west. Julian (1824-1877) married
            Michael Brake in 1853 and settled in Hardy County. Evaline (1830-1914), the youngest
            daughter of William and Joanna, would become the matriarch of the Heavner estate. </p>
         <p>Evaline married George W. Aubrey of Luney's Creek in what is now Hardy County, West
            Virginia in 1859. During the Civil War, George Aubrey joined the Union Army. He was
            captured in September 1861 and was incarcerated at Libby Prison in Richmond, Virginia,
            where he died in 1862. During that time, Evaline and her infant son, William Casper,
            moved back to the family home in Brocks Gap, where she gave birth to their daughter
            Dorcas. Evaline suffered several other losses that year: her brother, William Jr., died
            serving in the Confederate Army; her son, William Casper, died shortly thereafter of
            complications from croup; and she then suffered the loss of her mother. With her father
            in his seventies, Evaline thus took charge of the family farm, where she spent the
            remainder of her life with Dorcas and her family. </p>
         <p>Dorcas Aubrey (1861-1946) married Jacob R. Breneman (1872-1953) in 1896. Following their
            honeymoon they moved into the Heavner family home to take over operations for Evaline.
            Breneman also was active in politics as a Democrat and served in the Virginia House of
            Delegates: 1926-1927, 1930-1931, and 1940-1945. Their daughter Mae (1903-1984)later
            married Robert D. Liskey (1903-1967). They were the parents of Mr. Leon Liskey, one of
            the donors of this collection, and are buried, as are the Brenemans, in Woodbine
            Cemetery in Harrisonburg, Virginia. </p>
         <p>For a more detailed genealogical account see Judy Ruleman Liskey's <emph render="italic"
               >When This You See, Think of Me!</emph> and <emph render="italic">With Pen in Hand:
               Buttons and Beaux.</emph> Both texts provide a history of the Heavner family,
            photographs, and correspondence that supplement this collection.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="aspace_be4e7d2d445a713c2e5e96fc6a8eeb50">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, 1788-1967, consists of one box (.4 cubic
            feet) of personal correspondence, business and personal financial records and various
            other items pertaining to the Heavner family. The documents were passed down through the
            matrilineal side of the Heavner family, much like the original Heavner home, where these
            documents were found. Documents were thus passed from William Heavner to his daughter
            Evaline (Heavner) Aubrey, to her daughter Dorcas (Aubrey) Breneman, to her daughter Mae
            (Breneman) Liskey, then to her son, Leon Liskey and his wife Judy. The collection
            remained in the possession of the Liskey family until the bulk of the papers were
            donated to Special Collections in November 2007. Family names of note that are seen
            throughout the collection are Brake, Dove, Hess, and Trumbo, among others. The
            collection is arranged chronologically in four series: Richard Hughes Estate Papers,
            Correspondence, Financial Papers, and General Miscellany. </p>
         <p>Series One, Richard Hughes Estate Papers, 1788-1837, consists of three folders of
            documents regarding Hughes' personal business matters and legal transactions involving
            his estate. William Heavner, acting as executor, retained these documents after the
            estate was settled. Personal papers include the appraisal and bill of sale of household
            possessions, powers of attorney, and court summonses. A folder of Hughes' receipts
            includes general and tax receipts directly related to Hughes' estate. A folder of
            miscellaneous material from Hughes' estate includes agreements and papers concerning
            land and property, as well as various promissory notes and receipts from other
            individuals such as George Dove, Conrad Custer, Solomon Jones, and Henry Overley. </p>
         <p>Series Two, Correspondence, 1852-1967, is arranged into four subseries, then
            chronologically. Letters to Evaline Aubrey, the Brenemans (also spelled Brenneman) and
            other members of the Heavner family figure most prominently; the remainder are
            miscellaneous letters, some with unknown senders and recipients. Hair clippings and hair
            art are present.</p>
         <p>Letters to Evaline Aubrey span from 1868 until 1913. In addition to correspondence from
            family and friends, many of the letters addressed to her are from M.P. Trumbo and
            concern family property in Illinois, where her brother Wells had settled. Legal and
            estate issues are also represented. </p>
         <p>Letters to and from J.R. Breneman, et al, date from 1904 until 1967, and primarily
            concern business interests; although family letters are also present. Several post cards
            are addressed to his daughter Mae from a trip Breneman took out West. Letters to his
            wife Dorcas are also filed here. </p>
         <p>Correspondence of the Heavner family, 1852-1896, includes letters to William Heavner
            Sr., as well as a small number to and from Wells Heavner. Correspondence relating to
            Well's mother in law Catherine Hess, brother in law Nathan Hess, and others are also
            filed here chronologically. </p>
         <p>Miscellaneous correspondence, 1861-1937, is a small series of letters from individuals
            who are either not directly related to the Heavners, or the letters are unsigned. </p>
         <p>Series Three, Financial Papers, 1820-1947, are arranged topically as promissory notes,
            property documents, general receipts, tax receipts, and other financial documents, then
            chronologically. Promissory notes are small sheets or slips of paper that clearly state
            "I Promise to Pay" or "I bind myself to" for a specific amount of money to a specific
            person. Property documents pertain to ownership, transfer, and inheritance of property.
            These include land agreements, notice of land for sale, and the estate division of
            William Heavner Sr., to the Brake and Aubrey families. General receipts cover a wide
            range of household purchases and expenditures. Tax receipts largely represent personal
            property taxes paid for the family property in Rockingham County, as well as property
            owned in La Salle County, Illinois, which had passed to Evaline from her brother Wells'
            family. Of particular interest are receipts for taxes paid during the Civil War.
            Miscellaneous financial documents range in content from a note regarding a young boy's
            indentured service in 1847, an 1852 toll road account, and a 1907 probate inventory of
            Michael S. Wine's estate, with Breneman acting as administrator. </p>
         <p>Series Four, General Miscellany, 1864-1925, consists of a wide array of items, such as
            greeting cards and ephemera, print material, recipes and home remedies, weaving patterns
            and fabric squares. Items of note are Mae Breneman's 1925 Shenandoah College graduation
            announcement, and undated obituaries for Lizzie E. Wittig and Ruby Heavner.</p>
         <p>An item-level description is available here: <extref xlink:type="simple"
               xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new"
               xlink:href="https://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/5006Liskey_Detail.pdf"
               >https://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/5006Liskey_Detail.pdf</extref>
         </p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement id="aspace_93220dba5d0bc7e85b8998a93cf687e0">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in four series:</p>
         <p>1. Richard Hughes Estate Papers, 1788-1837</p>
         <p>2. Correspondence, 1852-1967</p>
         <p>3. Financial Papers, 1820-1947</p>
         <p>4. General Miscellany, 1864-1925</p>
      </arrangement>
      <originalsloc id="aspace_dcfcd3a5692923c44b0d830a923077f3">
         <head>Location of Originals</head>
         <p>Documents cited in publications not extant in this collection may have been retained by
            the donor.</p>
      </originalsloc>
      <bibliography id="aspace_bf850b054a1b752e1e739ee7b12fe63d">
         <head>Bibliography</head>
         <p>Brock, Robert L. <emph render="italic">47 Pioneer Families of Rockingham County,
               Virginia.</emph> Baltimore: Gateway Press, 1997.</p>
         <p>"Harrisonburg Rockingham Historical Society, Rockingham County Tombstones by Cemetery,
            Woodbine Cemetery."
            http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~varockin/HRHS/cem/woodbine09_2.htm.</p>
         <p>Liskey, Judy Ruleman. <emph render="italic">Brocks Gap Missives: Personal Letters to a
               Young Lady in the Nineteenth Century, 1878 &amp; 1879, 1880.</emph> Fulks Run (Va.):
            Judy Ruleman Liskey, [19--?]</p>
         <p>Liskey, Judy Ruleman. <emph render="italic">Brocks Gap Missives: Personal Letters to a
               Young Lady in the Nineteenth Century, 1881, 1882.</emph> Fulks Run (Va.): Judy
            Ruleman Liskey, [19--?]</p>
         <p>Liskey, Judy Ruleman. <emph render="italic">My Sweet Valley Home: Rockingham County,
               Virginia, Personal Correspondence from October 16, 1876 to January 16, 1888.</emph>
            [Fulks Run Va.: J. R. Liskey], 1991.</p>
         <p>Liskey, Judy Ruleman. <emph render="italic">When This You See, Think of Me!</emph>
            [S.I.:s.n.], c1990.</p>
         <p>Liskey, Judy Ruleman. <emph render="italic">With Pen in Hand: Buttons and Beaux.</emph>
            [S.I.]:Judy Ruleman Liskey, c2006.</p>
         <p>"Virginia General Assembly." virginiageneralassembly.gov</p>
      </bibliography>
      <controlaccess>
         <head>Index Terms</head>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">Farmers -- Virginia -- Biography</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Indentured servants -- Virginia</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Agriculture -- Virginia -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Farm life -- Virginia -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Farm management -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Trust indentures -- Virginia</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Real property -- Virginia -- Rockingham County</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Estates (Law) -- Virginia -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Wills -- Virginia -- Rockingham County</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rockingham County (Va.) -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rockingham County (Va.) -- Social life and customs</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rockingham County (Va.) -- Genealogy</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Social life and
               customs</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh"> Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Genealogy</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Virginia -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Virginia -- Social life and customs</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Virginia -- Genealogy</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">Letters (correspondence)</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <dsc>
         <c01 id="aspace_5d8dcd7eb04e5ee661c40908d7594009" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series 1: Richard Hughes Estate Papers, <unitdate normal="1788/1837"
                     type="inclusive">1788-1837</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 id="aspace_20b4439d0dfaec969c0124e32ae49835" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Personal, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1788/1837"
                        type="inclusive">1788-1837</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_417b7963579b5f3609433bfafe30dd1d" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_1379e232caefe3700b32b70661f49e39" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Receipts of Richard Hughes, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1788/1831" type="inclusive">1788-1831</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_ee5e9e89816f8496187e08afd9100fc1" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_5a07ef8dfeb1144cd2f8155d4c7fa838" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1791/1830" type="inclusive">1791-1830</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_454f094c58a77c4a1764d1a27f671c26" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_f2b4bfc0b8d88fb7002c2831c5fee02c" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series 2: Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 id="aspace_be6cb2332cd9e9f539e56b65e0beda1e" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Evaline Aubrey, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1868/1913" type="inclusive">1868-1913</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_2f4e0d3a7034e1b1aa9be312323283c4" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_887d37af8c4433ea54252f883bd21f80" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>J.R. Breneman, et al, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1904/1967" type="inclusive">1904-1967</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_e52106e5fa8128c670c722635f87c3c9" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_270baa9ef1b875553fc68fd1e2ed27ee" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Heavner Family, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1852/1896" type="inclusive">1852-1896</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_094976796c20be18eb064a4c46577376" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_07dbd38b9f8365592bb68be6d5bc2539" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1861/1908" type="inclusive">1861-1908</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_213c93be6d5ba232ce2bcd56cfc04d39" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_4b76112ba500c668d636aedcbb89e972" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series 3: Financial Papers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 id="aspace_6c07dff565bb748f610cbd7dcb371209" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Promissory Notes, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1853/1906" type="inclusive">1853-1906</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_bfff402415483811b4d53837b9621849" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_69e0b30bbaa98b5476f1b28f69c943bc" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Property Documents, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1822/1911" type="inclusive">1822-1911</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_313293016dcc56d0684f41f82e93f38c" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">9</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_8d52bccadd42311256b36f4c1f998365" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>General Receipts, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1832/1930" type="inclusive">1832-1930</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_3a6d8353a6bd487b21bb4fbeb90c1a24" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">10</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_24230270feb9eb7b41ac833e6ab64300" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Tax Receipts, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                        normal="1854/1909" type="inclusive">1854-1909</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_528b186ca3f55c18734a1e57c0af9d46" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">11</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_7ca0dd03905f18b0ff9184cf1c914412" level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous Financial Documents, <unitdate calendar="gregorian"
                        era="ce" normal="1820/1947" type="inclusive">1820-1947</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_c149df43d77e8a36de855ae78dfd8819" label="Folder"
                     type="folder">12</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_d7934819c047874a26b1d178371258c0" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series 4: General Miscellany, <unitdate calendar="gregorian"
                     certainty="approximate" era="ce" normal="1864/1925" type="inclusive">1864-1925,
                     undated</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_f4d8567b2b341014d115aa59bb75c73d" label="Folder" type="folder"
                  >13</container>
            </did>
            <c02 id="aspace_0f4725c243adcaa324263bfd2b9cc0d2" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Insert 1: Cards and Ephemera</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_6db2d2ac584eff68b407954f95d31c44" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Insert 2: Print Materials</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_58de02b1a5fc45ce82c0a25ff3129dfa" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Insert 3: Recipes and Home Remedies</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_49998a9d573f3c1bd8ced009d9aeddd5" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Insert 4: Weaving Patterns</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="aspace_77c4b5307752e89b8d74147edfd89b00" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Insert 5: Fabric</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
