<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead audience="internal" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00224.xml"
      >vihart00224</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Barnhart Family Papers, 1836-1944: <num>SC
          0237</num></titleproper>
        <author>Tiffany Cole, April 2017</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2017 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole
        on <date>2017-05-02 08:36:18 -0400</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the Barnhart Family Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1836-1944</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          0237</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2016</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Tiffany Cole, April 2017</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Barnhart Family Papers, </unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <famname rules="local" source="local">Barnhart Family</famname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0237</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.1 Cubic Feet; 5 legal folders</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1836/1944" type="inclusive">1836-1944</unitdate>
      <abstract audience="internal" id="aspace_d276bcbc8c1113ce2aaca6b841892a60">The Barnhart Family
        Papers, 1836-1944, is comprised of assorted documents chiefly relating to the Barnhart
        family of New Hope, Virginia in Augusta County, particularly George Barnhart II and his son
        Gideon Barnhart. Materials include correspondence, bills, receipts and invoices, deeds, and
        envelopes. The collection also includes many documents concerning the estate of George
        Barnhart II. There are also materials within this collection pertaining to persons not
        directly related to the Barnharts.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_2d22d5d737b13a24e041ea30b32d84ec">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
          privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before
          visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
          collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_146a9dd270db0fe48a5488af221a205a">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite audience="internal" id="aspace_f6c35984cc5818e483f50b48cf4e1b3a">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Barnhart Family Papers, 1836-1944, SC 0237,
          Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_f55914feb083de8de4ca135c863a6d2c">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Acquired at Ebay auction in March 2017 from seller in Evington, Virginia.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist audience="internal" id="aspace_4e414a44cd604f6d31ba2de81243102c">
        <head>Provenance</head>
        <p>The materials within this collection originally comprised part of lot 177 of Jeffrey
          Evans &amp; Associates' November 12, 2016 Americana &amp; Fine Antiques sale. Jeffrey
          Evans' provenance note indicates that the materials originated from a private Shenandoah
          Valley of Virginia collection.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <processinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_1f856af3ae79f5380953d9dfcd9b7e08">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>This collection was originally housed in a photo album with most documents placed in
          Mylar sleeves. The materials were without a clear arrangement scheme. The archivist
          removed the documents from the album and imposed an artificial arrangement based on person
          or group of persons.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist audience="internal" id="aspace_e8ab7547e5274cfe8d8a245605263523">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>The Barnharts of Augusta County, Virginia descended from German immigrant John George
        Barnhart (1748-1832), also referred to as George Barnhart I. George I first arrived in
        Philadelphia in 1767 and migrated to Virginia in 1778 where he married Catherine Myers
        (1756-1826). They originally took up residence in Shenandoah County, but moved to Augusta
        County by the early spring of 1790. They had four children including an only son, George
        Barnhart II (1778-1857).</p>
      <p>George II married Polly Barnett (1785-1859) of Fairfield, Virginia. They went on to have
        four children including an eldest son, Gideon Barnhart (1814-1892) who married Martha Ann
        Weade (1825-1917) on March 13, 1845. Gideon was elected Captain of the 1st Battalion, 32nd.,
        Regiment of Virginia in 1843 and held that position for seven years. At the outset of the
        Civil War, Gideon would likely have been too old to report for active duty. However,
        evidence suggests that Gideon was a private in Company A, 3rd. Battalion Valley Reserves and
        mustered in April 23, 1864. Gideon and Martha Barnhart had five children, four of whom lived
        into adulthood. Their son Henry George Barnhart (1860-1915) married Fannie Ann Gentry
        (1859-1917) and the couple went on to have seven children.</p>
      <p>Materials relating to many of the aforementioned Barnharts and their children and
        grandchildren can be found in this collection.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_6b1c8d9fa3566aa0a3c2f1179d9fb45b">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The Barnhart Family Papers, 1836-1944, are comprised of assorted documents chiefly relating
        to the Barnhart family of New Hope, Virginia in Augusta County, particularly George Barnhart
        II and his son Gideon Barnhart. Materials include correspondence, bills, receipts and
        invoices, deeds, and envelopes. The collection also includes many documents concerning the
        estate of George Barnhart II. There are also materials within this collection pertaining to
        persons not directly related to the Barnharts.</p>
      <p>Papers relating to George Barnhart II chiefly comprise estate documents, specifically lists
        of property sold by the administrators of George II's estate in April 1857. Types of items
        sold from George II's estate include sundry household items, farm implements, and livestock.
        His widow Polly and son Gideon are listed as buyers of multiple items. There are several
        variations of the list of property sold, though they all appear to date to April 1857.
        Additional materials include receipts, financial accounts, and a deed between George II and
        Polly and their son Gideon for a tract of land on the south side of Round Hill.</p>
      <p>Papers specifically relating to Polly Barnhart include financial and estate documents. Of
        particular interest is a document dated April 25, 1857 in which Polly Barnhart grants power
        of attorney to her son Gideon. In this role, Gideon was to attend to his mother's interests
        in the estate of the recently deceased Lydia Barnett, likely Polly's sister. Two documents
        relate to George II's estate. One document, written on behalf of her children, allows Polly
        to take whatever property she wants from her husband's estate. The second document, written
        on behalf of Polly, surrenders all but one fourth share in the estate. She elects to divide
        the estate with her three living children.</p>
      <p>The Gideon Barnhart papers include financial documents and accounts, receipts, and
        correspondence. Included is an August 2, 1837 letter to Gideon from his cousin Nancy Cullen
        (1819-1910) in Holland Grove, Illinois. Earlier that year, Gideon spent time traveling back
        home from Illinois where he visited with his Uncle John P. Cullen and his family. Nancy's
        expresses pleasure that Gideon has arrived safely home. She provides updates on the
        happenings in Holland Grove. Of particular interest is a document that evidence suggests is
        a love letter from Gideon Barnhart to Martha Ann Weade. It is dated June 3, 1844 and was
        written less than one year before their marriage. The letter is only addressed "Dear Miss,"
        but within the body of the letter, the author, presumably Gideon, writes: "[I] am pleading
        my own cause Miss Marth when I think of the pleasant hours I have spent with you I must
        conclude there is yet thousand more yet unspent." He goes on: "I turn over one page and take
        the liberty of asking you whither my future visits will meet with your approbation not only
        as a parcial visitor but one who is trying to clime to the top of the top of the matrimonial
        chain. I do not wish to flatter you by saying to you your beautiful features and sparkling
        eyes rosey cheaks and prattling toung have left impressions uppon my mind." Several of
        Gideon's documents, including the love letter presumably penned by him to Martha Ann Weade,
        exhibit evidence of his signature having been clipped.</p>
      <p>One folder contains documents relating to other Barnhart family members excluding George
        II, Polly, and Gideon. Materials include correspondence, financial documents, and empty
        envelopes. Persons featured in these documents William F. Cullen, son-in-law of George
        Barnhart I, Henry George Barnhart, Walter W. Barnhart, George Gray Barnhart, and Laura Ruth
        Barnhart.</p>
      <p>Lastly, all other documents seemingly unrelated to the Barnhart Family are housed in one
        folder. These items include accounts between a Mr. Whitmore and Philadelphia merchants
        Schaffer &amp; Roberts and Inskeep, Molten &amp; Woodruff; a letter from W. H. Carrington to
        his uncle James Smallwood of South River in Augusta County; two letters penned by Francis
        Sigler of Indiana; a letter penned by Louisa D. Clagett; a family record outlining Clagett
        family marriages, births and deaths; and other miscellaneous papers and financial
        documents.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement audience="internal" id="aspace_97427583a6a2e9486214e3ad4e63ea80">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged by person or group of persons and further arranged
        chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <relatedmaterial audience="internal" id="aspace_00d8073bc46e8eb91217b6bf82e12228">
      <head>Related Material</head>
      <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=uva-sc/viu01311.xml">Barnhart
          family papers, 1832-1963, Accession #11264, Special Collections Dept., University of
          Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</extref></p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography audience="internal" id="aspace_f4d2a245f28e12b8308d23e765c6a4bc">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Barnhart, Nat G. <emph render="italic">Barnhart Family History: Augusta County, Virginia,
          1767-1967</emph>. Staunton, Va.: McClure Printing Co., 1967.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh">Augusta County (Va.) -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Augusta County (Va.) -- Genealogy</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Augusta County (Va.) -- Social life and customs</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Virginia -- History, Local -- Sources</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat">Letters (correspondence)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Estate inventories</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Estate records</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Estate administration records</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Deeds</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Financial Records</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Love letters</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Envelopes</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Receipts (financial records)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Invoices</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Family papers</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_da5b7726499f52963d31610307eed05c" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George Barnhart II Papers, <unitdate normal="1841/1857" type="inclusive"
              >1841-1857</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_90dff74abb3c16aab1f3105edb306eb3" label="Folder" type="Folder"
            >1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_5fb263184e39e1ffd6dde96b9d85a007" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Polly Barnhart Papers, <unitdate normal="1857/1859" type="inclusive"
              >1857-1859</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_4d249a226855bdf560c172a00590d70c" label="Folder" type="Folder"
            >2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_f7498c2d310dd785a9c47465a88a9518" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Gideon Barnhart Papers, <unitdate normal="1837/1872" type="inclusive"
              >1837-1872, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_7c6036bfd87222069884c31bcb817280" label="Folder" type="Folder"
            >3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_4f5a0e4ec7bb1eae3b3a6078e05bd366" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Assorted Barnhart Family Papers, <unitdate normal="1836/1944" type="inclusive"
              >1836-1944, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_2caee31ed69a0ead01cafd701fd14562" label="Folder" type="Folder"
            >4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_528b95eb28ab7b13d8c8f86e21380470" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Unidentified/Non-Barnhart Family Papers, <unitdate normal="1839/1898"
              type="inclusive">1839-1898, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_e99c9eb54c2059f52918c01a7c2cfd6d" label="Folder" type="Folder"
            >5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
