<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00179.xml"
      >vihart00179</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Confederate War Tax Form, 1863 <num>SC 0018</num></titleproper>
        <author>Dillon Thomas, October 2016</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2016 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole on <date>2016-12-13 12:03:29
          -0500</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the Confederate War Tax Form, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
        1863</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
        0018</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2016</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Dillon Thomas, October 2016</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc audience="internal" level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Confederate War Tax Form,</unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <corpname source="local">Confederate States of America</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0018</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.08 Cubic Feet; 1 legal folder</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1863/1863" type="inclusive">1863</unitdate>
      
      <abstract audience="internal" id="aspace_f42b6370ba00be83837e2751e18871b8">The Confederate War
        Tax Form, 1863, documents a series of guidelines for the taxation of unique goods and
        services by the Confederacy in Virginia. The two-sheet, partly printed form lays out all the
        materials which are to be taxed and includes a statement of the possession of liquor to be
        taxed. The forms were signed by James Gwyn of Richmond, Virginia and Confederate Assessor
        W.E. Johnson. </abstract>
    </did>
    <accessrestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_4debb01964449a024c7f52d35f0104bf">
      <head>Access Restrictions</head>
      <p>Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy
        laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting
        the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_ab8cfdc462942cf16ca25e8d6cb821ad">
      <head>Use Restrictions</head>
      <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
        University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
        Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite audience="internal" id="aspace_517b3c747850e27b9812bbedf1049a6e">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Confederate War Tax Form, 1863, SC 0018,
        Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_63bf8195f8dfab8bcd3b7a63e4331325">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>James Madison University Special Collections acquired this document at auction from
        Cohasco, Inc. in February 2015.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <bioghist audience="internal" id="aspace_31c58e6d4dba6359773773e0e6a2b9e5">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>When the Confederate States seceded from the Union in 1861, the Confederate government
        intended to be light on taxes in principle, resulting in almost exclusive dependence on
        private donations to sustain itself and the initial war effort against the Union. The
        American Civil War was initially funded entirely via private donations, yet the fortunes of
        many donors began dwindling and war-weariness set in as the war dragged on. As a result,
        private donations and minor taxes were no longer enough. At the height of the American Civil
        War in 1862 and 1863, the Confederate government was forced to begin a large scale taxation
        of citizens in order to maintain the war effort. The taxes were presented to increasingly
        disgruntled citizens as a means to continue the independence from the Union. This
        Confederate War Tax Form is one such taxation of Confederate citizens, specifically on
        luxury, service, and corporate holdings. The form taxes citizens in Confederate dollars.
        Later in the war, the Confederacy began taxation in kind, taxation paid in goods and
        services rather than currency.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_8344b3f3be50c20123ceea787266fa61">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The Confederate War Tax Form, 1863, consists a two-sheet, partly printed document. The form
        is completed for taxation of James Gwyn of Richmond, Virginia and signed and dated by the
        Confederate Assessor W. E. Johnson.</p> <p>The first page, titled “List No.1,” is the list form
        which corresponds with Section I: Naval stores, salt, wine, liquors, tobacco, cotton, flour,
        sugar, molasses, syrup, rice, and other agricultural products. The form lays out that the
        property of such items is to be taxed 8% of its total estimated value. John Gwyn provides
        only one piece of property to be taxed in this section, which is liquor. The liquor in
        Gwyn’s possession is valued at $250.00 and is to be taxed $20.00.</p> <p>The second page of the
        form begins by setting down the purpose of the tax that the form is levying, stating that it
        is to “lay taxes for the common defence and carry on the government of the Confederate
        States.” The form continues in laying down the fields of property in which it is collecting:
        Section I, Section V, and Section X. In each of the three sections, the form details the
        property types to be collected upon for each section. According to marginal notes, each of
        the sections also had a corresponding form in which the taxed citizen would list material
        they possessed that was liable for taxation. At the end of each section, the form requests a
        yes/no answer as to if the citizen was liable for taxation of any of the mentioned
        materials. John Gwyn provided a “yes” for Section I and Section V.</p> <p>It should be noted that
        Gwyn also provided a “yes” answer for Section V on the second page, yet there is no List No.
        2 included with the document.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement audience="internal" id="aspace_4f09d2da4dde60505caddd0f3748ebd5">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The Confederate War Tax Form, 1863, is comprised of two pages and is placed in one legal
        folder.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="lcsh">Taxation -- Confederate States of America</subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">Tax assessment -- Confederate States of America</subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">Tax administration and procedure -- Confederate States of
        America</subject>
      <subject source="lcsh">Tax collection -- Confederate States of America</subject>
      <genreform source="aat">Tax records</genreform>
      <persname source="local" rules="local">Johnson, W. E. </persname>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 audience="internal" id="aspace_78afbf6c4236b12e0511d3d4e9b261e9" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Confederate War Tax Form, <unitdate normal="1863" type="inclusive">
            1863</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_cd411445d4b60aa7aec8742f75276d61" label="Box:Folder"
            type="Box:Folder">1:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
