<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00232.xml"
      >vihart00232</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, 1939: <num>SC
          0069</num></titleproper>
        <author>Tiffany Cole, March 2017</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2017 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole
        on <date>2017-05-24 12:45:14 -0400</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1939</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          0069</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Tiffany Cole, March 2017</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, </unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Spitzer, Alpha Marie, 1917-2013</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0069</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.06 cubic feet; 1 letter folder</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1939/1939">1939</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_c9c8d048bbdc0e47886d41165a2110d2">The Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, 1939,
        is comprised of one 3 ¾ x 5 ¾ inch spiral notebook chronicling Spitzer's trip with her
        sister Margaret from Broadway, Virginia to Pueblo, Colorado and back during the summer of
        1939. Both Spitzer sisters were alumni of Broadway High School and the State Teachers
        College at Harrisonburg.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="aspace_1e8294114b6a8786757d6497ab6e016f">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
          privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before
          visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
          collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="aspace_b8c4db465812e38b4965b655afa9c843">
        <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="aspace_89f60babda9f972cbe0bfba4b32d71ae">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, 1939, SC 0069,
          Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="aspace_311330d125b7e6d942593194e37c061d">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Acquired from Ebay in March 2017 from a seller in Nellysford, Virginia.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="aspace_73208b1bf76a1761ea62f1eb4aa3d78f">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>Alpha Marie Spitzer was born May 2, 1917 in Broadway, Virginia to Grover Spitzer and Ethel
        Holsinger Spitzer. She graduated from Broadway High School in 1933 and from the State
        Teachers College at Harrisonburg in 1937 with a Bachelor of Science degree in High School
        Teaching and Administration. While at the State Teachers College, Spitzer was an active
        member of the Curie Science Club, Sesame Club, Alpha Literary Society, Hiking Club, Varsity
        Hockey, Varsity Basketball, numerous other class sports, and the Y. W. C. A. Her sister
        Margaret Lucile Spitzer (1915-2008) also graduated in 1937 with a Bachelor of Science degree
        in Home Economics.</p>
      <p>Spitzer began teaching math and French at Linville-Edom High School. She moved to Fairfax,
        Virginia in 1943 to teach business education and direct vocational office training. In 1955,
        Spitzer received her master's degree from Virginia Tech. She returned to the Shenandoah
        Valley in 1995 and was active in the Bridgewater Church of the Brethren and also volunteered
        at the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society. Spitzer died July 13, 2013.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_6cdfad4f4a7a8e297c6f334e04db8535">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, 1939, is comprised of one 3 ¾ x 5 ¾ inch spiral notebook
        chronicling Spitzer's trip with her sister Margaret from Broadway, Virginia to Pueblo,
        Colorado and back during the summer of 1939. Both Spitzer sisters were alumni of Broadway
        High School and the State Teachers College at Harrisonburg.</p>
      <p>The Spitzer sisters traveled by car, a 1935 Ford, from their hometown of Broadway, Virginia
        to Pueblo, Colorado where they visited friends and family. They left Broadway on the morning
        of July 23, 1939, arrived in Pueblo, Colorado on July 27, and returned home to Broadway the
        evening of August 10. They visited many sites along the way and Alpha chronicled their
        jaunts and funny findings in brief diary entries. Pit stops and corresponding diary entries
        of note include the Greenbrier resort at White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia ("Very well
        kept"); Hawk's Nest State Park, Ansted, West Virginia ("Took 3 pictures of New River
        Gorge"); Mt. Sterling, Kentucky ("Stopped for radiator repair on car"); Lexington, Kentucky
        ("Stopped for gas at Gulf. Worked penny slot machine…Took pictures of tobacco"); Shoals,
        Indiana ("Stopped to see Jug Rock and Pinnacle (adm 10¢). Took pictures"); Hutchinson,
        Kansas ("Scene of many large grain elevators. A city very nice. We went to hamburger stand
        &amp; got ice coffee. Crossed the Arkansas River"); and Dodge City, Kansas ("In dust storm
        this eve. Saw tumbleweed blowing across road. Saw jack rabbit a while back"). The sisters
        visited other cities of interest including Dodge City, Kansas; Denver, Colorado; Pikes Peak,
        Colorado; Lincoln, Nebraska; Moline, Illinois; Detroit, Michigan; Niagara Falls, New York;
        and Gettysburg, Pennsylvania.</p>
      <p>Included in the travel diary is a preliminary itinerary titled "Tripping thru the States."
        It is dated July 1, 1939, three weeks prior to the start of the trip. It is largely
        representative of the sisters' actual trip with the exception of a visit to the New York
        World's Fair which did not occur. Additionally, the trip was planned to begin July 27, four
        days later than the actual start date, and end August 20, when the sisters would return
        home. They arrived in Broadway on August 10. Lists of the sisters' respective expenditures –
        gas, food, lodging, Kodak film, etc. – are interspersed in the diary entries. A list of
        "motoring maps" used by the sisters to inform their travel routes is also included.</p>
      <p>The pages immediately following the conclusion of the travel entries are blank. Several
        pages at the very end of the notebook include calculations, lists of names and addresses,
        and a list of pictures taken on the trip equaling six rolls of film.</p>
      <p>Alpha Spitzer's address label, that post-dates the diary, is affixed to the front cover of
        the notebook.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_66bf80ecf19a172dba542e22b4124148">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The diary remains bound and is housed in one letter folder.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <bibliography id="aspace_b9b02eded019d4319bf41a6865673358">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Obituary for Alpha M. Spitzer, <emph render="italic">Daily News-Record</emph>, July 17,
        2013.</p>
      <p>Program for the Twenty-Eighth Annual Commencement Exercises, State Teachers College, June
        7, 1937.</p>
      <p><emph render="italic">The Schoolma'am</emph>, 1937. Harrisonburg (Va.): State Teachers
        College.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh">State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Alumni
          and alumnae</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Automobile travel -- United States -- History -- 20th
          century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Travel -- History -- 20th century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Travelers -- United States -- 20th century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Travelers' writings -- History -- 20th century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Voyages and travels -- History -- 20th century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Women travelers -- United States -- History -- 20th century</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United States -- Description and travel</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat">Diaries</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_76899884e814d6319353ab03e085dd33" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Alpha Spitzer Travel Diary, <unitdate normal="1939/1939"
            >1939</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_dccc0ef7d16ec0cd915e7a8d426fe441" label="Folder" type="folder"
            >1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
