<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xml">
<!NOTATION aspx SYSTEM "">
<!ENTITY Wampler SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1681051~S0" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Grandfather SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b2156760~S0" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Poultry SYSTEM "http://www.vapoultrygrowers.com/VPGC-Web/DesktopDefault.aspx?tabid=1" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Family SYSTEM "http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1681051~S0" NDATA aspx>
]><ead id="vihart00108">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::vihart00108:: Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection, c. 1930s-1997)//EN" "vihart00108.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection, <date>c. 1930s-1997</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Custer, Elizabeth "Libby"
<num type="collectionnumber">2002
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Victoria Edwards and Tracy Harter, <date>October 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>Guide to the Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection, <date>c. 1930s-1997</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="">SC# 2002
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2009
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Victoria Edwards and Tracy Harter
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">The Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">c. 1930s-1997
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number SC# " encodinganalog="099$a">2002
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1/2 Hollinger box, .209 linear feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Elizabeth <title render="doublequote">Libby</title> Custer Collection, c. 1930s-1997, consists of 1/2 Hollinger box (.209 linear feet) of business and personal records relating to the Custer family business, Virginia Valley Processors, Inc., of Hinton, Virginia.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Elizabeth <title render="doublequote">Libby</title> Custer (Hinton, Virginia)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>None.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Digital images are provided for educational and research purposes only and are not to be downloaded, reproduced, or otherwise distributed.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>The Elizabeth "Libby" Custer Collection, c. 1930s-1997, SC# 2002, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The collection was donated in April 2008 by Mrs. Libby Custer of Hinton, Virginia.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>Digital images of photographs and other material were made from a scrapbook retained by the donor. Images are available in Special Collections.
</p>
</altformavail>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p><title render="bold">Libby Custer</title>
</p>
<p>Elizabeth Libby Wampler Custer was born on March 27, 1913 in Dayton, Virginia to Charles Wampler, Sr. and Sadie Zigler Wampler. The Wampler family has been one of the most influential families in the Rockingham County, Va. area. Charles Wampler, a pioneer in poultry raising, is considered the founder of the modern turkey industry. He served as the first Rockingham County Extension Agent and in 1927, with two brothers, founded the Wampler Feed and Seed Company. One of nine children, Libby worked in the family business from a young age. As a young woman she attended Juniata College, a Church of the Brethren liberal arts college in Huntingdon, Pennsylvania. She married Harry Lawson Custer (November 17, 1909 to February 22, 1981), a Fulks Run native, on October 12, 1934, and continued working with him in their poultry processing business, Virginia Valley Processors, Inc. They had three children, Kay, Stephen and Judy.</p>
<p>Throughout her life Libby also expressed herself through painting. Between 1935 and 1959 Libby occasionally took classes at Bridgewater College taught by Olive Delp Graham. In 1964, at the age of 41, Libby participated in the first adult education class offered by Harrisonburg Public Schools under Mrs. Carrie K. Showalter. Over the years, Libby has painted various properties, homesteads, and scenic vistas at the request of friends and family, often on unconventional materials such as planks of wood, reflecting her pragmatism: <title render="doublequote">You can paint on anything.</title> An exhibit of her work and a reception in her honor was hosted in 2007 by the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society, where she continues to volunteer.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Harry Custer and Virginia Valley Processors, Inc.</title></p>
<p>The history of Virginia Valley Processors is part of a larger <title render="doublequote">family tree</title> of poultry and other business ventures. After starting a small business in 1928, Custer made a name for himself as a distributor of poultry and eggs in the Washington, D.C. area in the 1930s. In 1942, Custer bought property in Hinton, Virginia, where he had decided to settle. After serving in the Navy during World War II, Harry made a living hauling live poultry, establishing H.L. Custer Poultry in 1947 and originally operating from a barn on the property. The business flourished, with Custer distributing poultry to markets in Washington, D.C., Baltimore, and Philadelphia, as well as entering into business ventures in West Virginia. In 1956, he and two associates, Homer and Jim Long, organized as Virginia Valley Processors, Inc., which operated from a plant on the property in Hinton through the 1960s. By 1970 the company merged with his father-in-law's company, Wampler Feed and Seed, Inc., and other Wampler family operations which were reorganized as Wampler Foods, Inc. The Hinton plant thus became the processing division, with Custer serving as vice president and a member of the board of directors.</p>
<p>A 1984 merger with poultry processor Horace W. Longacre resulted in the formation of Wampler-Longacre, Inc. Shortly after another acquisition in 1988, the company reorganized as WLR Foods, Inc., and continued to acquire several other businesses in the decades that followed. In 2001, Pilgrim's Pride, Inc., acquired WLR Foods, Inc. In 2004, after a reported three year loss, Pilgrim's Pride, Inc., announced the pending closure of the Hinton plant. This prompted swift action by the newly formed Virginia Poultry Grower's Cooperative, Inc., in its successful efforts to purchase the plant. The Hinton plant continues to operate today under the Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative, Inc.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Elizabeth <title render="doublequote">Libby</title> Custer Collection, c. 1930s-1997, consists of 1/2 Hollinger box (.209 linear feet) of business and personal records relating to the Custer family business, Virginia Valley Processors, Inc., of Hinton, Virginia. The collection is arranged in three series: Account Books, Publications and Clippings, and Digitized Material.
</p>
<p><title render="bold">Account Books, 1951-1955,</title> includes payroll accounts, live poultry purchases, and refrigeration expenses during transport. The original covers were removed and the pages retained. One payroll account book records the names, hours worked, and rates of pay of female employees from February 18, 1955 until December 21, 1955, while a second account book documents the names, hours worked, and rates of pay of male employees from April 29, 1955 until December 30, 1955. Information regarding a possible temporary closing of the plant is also present. An account book regarding a possible temporary closure of the plant is also present. An account book regarding live poultry purchases between May 17, 1954 and December 21, 1955, documents the seller, type of poultry (i.e. toms, hens, culls, chicks) and amount paid. Pages from the account book of Cassco Ice consists of twenty pages that document expenses for transporting refrigerated dressed poultry to various named vendors, including dates, lot numbers, number of boxes, and cost. The last three pages contain entries from 1951-1952 recording stock purchases, listing stocks, shares purchased, cost, and dividends.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Publications and Clippings, 1939-1997,</title> consists of photocopies of articles and brochures relating to the local poultry industry and its history. One folder contains seven issues of the Wampler Foods, Inc., publication <title render="doublequote">Turkey Talk.</title> Another folder of material pertains to the takeover of one of the Virginia Valley Processors' New York customers, Murray Packing Company, in 1963 allegedly by an organized crime family under the auspices of Berkshire Foods. As a result, Virginia Valley Processors suffered an unrecoverable loss of $200,000. Also notable in this series are biographical information relating to Harry Custer's 1973 Virginia Poultry Federation awards and a typed memorial after his death in 1981, a news clipping regarding Charles W. Wampler Jr.'s 1997 Lifetime Achievement Award in Industry from the Science Museum of Virginia, and an undated article about a longtime employee of the Hinton plant, Sissy Obaugh.</p>
<p><title render="bold">Digitized Materials, c. 1930s-1960s,</title> consists of photocopies of digital images from a scrapbook Mrs. Custer loaned to Carrier Library Special Collections. Images pertain to the early days of Virginia Valley Processors, Inc., various employees, and a small number of family photographs. Digital images are available for viewing in Special Collections. See a descriptive list of these images. [http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/2002Custer_md_forpdf.pdf]</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged in three series: Account Books, 1951-1955; Publications and Clippings, 1939-1997; Digitized Materials, c. 1930s-1960s.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref><extref entityref="Wampler">The Charles W. Wampler Collection</extref>, SC# 3095, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
</bibref>
<bibref><title render="doublequote">Harry Custer Receives Award.</title> <title render="italic">Turkey Talk</title>, Vol 2:21 (May 31, 1973): 1.
</bibref>
<bibref><title render="doublequote">Libby Custer Art Exhibit On Display now at HRHS.</title> <title render="italic">Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society Newsletter </title>, Vol 29:2 (Spring 2007): 9.
</bibref>
<bibref>Wampler, Charles W. <extref entityref="Grandfather"><title render="italic">My grandfather, my grandchildren and me: an autobiography of Charles Wampler</title></extref>. Harrisonburg, Va.: Dayton, Va.: Shenandoah Press, 1968.
</bibref>
<bibref>Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative website. <extref entityref="Poultry">http://www.vapoultrygrowers.com/VPGC-Web/DesktopDefault.aspx?tabid=1</extref> (accessed November 5, 2009).
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
<head>Location of Originals
</head>
<p>Mrs. Custer retained the original scrapbook from which digital images were created.
</p>
</originalsloc>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p><extref entityref="Family">Charles W. Wampler, Jr. Collection of Wampler Family Papers</extref>, 1798-1962, SC# 3095
</p>
<p>Charles W. Wampler, Jr. Collection of Wampler Business Records, SC# (still in process)
</p>
<p>William D. Wampler Collection of Wampler Business Records, SC# 2003 (still in process)
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I">Account Books,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1951-1955:
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payroll, Women,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1955
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Payroll, Men,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1955
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Poultry Purchases,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1954-1955
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Cassco Freezer Account
	<unitdate type="inclusive">(undated, c. 1951)
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II">Publications and Clippings,
<unitdate type="inclusive">1939-1997:
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Turkey Talk,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1972-1973, 1985
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>Murray Packing Co.,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1964
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle>General, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1939-1997
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III">Digitized Material [available in Special Collections; see descriptive list here]
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>