<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00242.xml"
      >vihart0242</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk Letters, 1832, 1836: <num>SC
            0242</num></titleproper>
        <author>Tiffany Cole, August 2017</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2017 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole
        on <date>2017-08-16 14:20:12 -0400</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk Letters, <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1832, 1836</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          0242</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Tiffany Cole, August 2017</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk Letters, </unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Hollis, J. W.</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0242</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.08 cubic feet; 1 folder</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1832/1836" type="inclusive">1832, 1836</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_36c476f54e42312e54f7f261e2cf2d3b">The J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk
        Letters, 1832, 1836, are comprised of nine letters written to Funk by his publisher J. W.
        Hollis of Winchester, Virginia. The letters discuss in considerable detail various editorial
        changes to Funk's works <emph render="italic">A Compilation of Genuine Church Music</emph>
        and <emph render="italic">The Confession of Faith</emph>, which Hollis printed in 1832 and
        1837 respectively.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="aspace_c68911a9f8efd498a88744c6c7e64fe2">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
          privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before
          visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
          collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="aspace_02c4dbb3534342045644c70ace2cccf8">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="aspace_16abb633217935d7f0ea0d81f81b6f79">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk Letters, 1832,
          1836, SC 0242, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University,
          Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="aspace_30544bb489198440c5b32a3c0d7c8bba">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Purchased from Michael Brown Rare Books, LLC on August 1, 2017.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail id="aspace_20782882a4c338bc5faf82fe17c797f6">
        <head>Other Formats Available</head>
        <p>Due to minor text loss along the edges of the pages, Special Collections staff
          transcribed each letter. The letters are foldered with their corresponding
          transcription.</p>
      </altformavail>
      <processinfo id="aspace_e3033aeaa2489084cb3ee8cf3313e397">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>Physical evidence suggests that these letters were bound at some point – the edges have
          been trimmed resulting in uniformly shaped pages and there are holes with remnants of
          string along the letters' left edge suggesting they were previously stitched together in a
          bound folio or album. As a result, minor text loss is exhibited along the edges of the
          letters. As such, Special Collections staff completed full transcriptions to aid the
          researcher in reading the letters.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="aspace_0f7d05fb951e9affb56e3fb1a3de91cd">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>Several complete and thorough biographies have been written about Joseph Funk, his family,
        and his contribution to the American music, printing, and publishing industries. As such,
        this biographical note does not serve as an exhaustive rehashing of previous scholarship.
        Researchers are encouraged to review the bibliography for additional resources on Joseph
        Funk.</p>
      <p>Joseph Funk (1778-1862) was born the eleventh child of Henry Funk and Barbara Showalter
        Funk in Berks County, Pennsylvania. His family migrated to Rockingham County, Virginia
        around 1780 and settled several miles northwest of Harrisonburg, at the eastern foot of
        Little North Mountain, in the small hamlet of Mountain Valley. The Funks, for the most part,
        worshipped in the Mennonite faith. Funk was a staunch supporter of the religion and two of
        his brothers were leaders in the church. Funk was married twice, first to Elizabeth Rhodes
        (d. 1813) with whom he had five children, and second to Rachel Britton (d. 1833) with whom
        he had nine children. Funk was a land owner, farmer, school teacher, singing teacher, and
        most notably a composer and publisher. In 1832, J. W. Hollis of Winchester published Funk's
        first edition of religious hymns, A Compilation of Church Music (known as Harmonia Sacra
        beginning with the fourth edition). Joseph also developed a shape note system for use in
        Harmonia Sacra. In 1847, Funk founded Joseph Funk &amp; Sons under which name he began a
        print shop and bindery; it was the first Mennonite printing house in the United States.
        Joseph lived the remainder of his life a widower in Singers Glen, Virginia (formerly
        Mountain Valley). The name change occurred in 1860, just two years prior to Funks death, in
        homage to the community's celebrated musical trailblazer. The Joseph Funk home, located on
        Rt. 613 in Singers Glen, still stands and is listed on the National Register of Historic
        Places.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_740fb60c35ac38ab13468759f330cc47">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk Letters, 1832, 1836, are comprised of nine letters written
        to Funk by his publisher J. W. Hollis of Winchester, Virginia. Eight of the letters date to
        1832 and discuss in considerable detail various editorial changes to Funk's <emph
          render="italic">A Compilation of Genuine Church Music</emph>, which Hollis printed that
        same year. The last letter dates to 1836 and is co-written by J. W. Hollis and Robinson, his
        business partner. During this time, Funk was working on <emph render="italic">The Confession
          of Faith</emph>, which Hollis printed 1837.</p>
      <p>The letters primarily concern editorial suggestions to Funk's seminal work <emph
          render="italic">A Compilation of Genuine Church Music</emph> (later <emph render="italic"
          >Harmonia Sacra</emph>). Hollis and Funk are corresponding frequently to discuss editorial
        changes and suggestions, including numbering verses, shape notes, copyright, and layout.
        Hollis also address Funk's concern with the many errors he has found in the proof-sheets,
        writing on February 7, 1832 that "At least so far as your work is concerned, my anxiety to
        be correct has led me to 'consume the midnight oil' in revising and re-revising each
        successive proof-sheet."</p>
      <p>In addition to editorial suggestions and errors, the letters discuss Funk's payment to
        Hollis and future in-person meetings for which Funk would travel to Winchester. Outside of
        business matters, the letters are generally pleasant in nature as Hollis updates Funk on his
        health and sends his regards to Funk's family.</p>
      <p>The last letter, dated 1836, by Hollis and Robinson discusses payment and account
        settlement with Funk. It also includes elements of general news and gossip.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_94831e3c4d37516315fd6ac396b3f0e0">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged chronologically, with each letter foldered individually with its
        corresponding transcription.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <relatedmaterial id="aspace_a20e3996f0f7bf7d25efa6cf06a4b0e6">
      <head>Related Material</head>
      <p>Eastern Mennonite University's [Harrisonburg, Va.] Menno Simons Historical Library is home
        to original Joseph Funk correspondence, 1837-1848, to his daughter and son-in-law Mary and
        John Funk.</p>
      <p>Joseph Funk &amp; Sons Correspondence, Ms2008-074 - Special Collections, Virginia
        Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.</p>
      <p>Funk Family Correspondence, 1833-1860, Mss. Misc. Boxes F, Mss. Octavo Vols. F, American
        Antiquarian Society, Worchester, Ma.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_b72315fd9f52ba9e684b438ac1d18960">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>Fretz, A. J. A Brief History of Bishop Henry Funck and Other Funck Pioneers. Elkhart, In.:
        Mennonite Pub. Co., 1899.</p>
      <p>Funk, Frances. Joseph Funk: A Biography. Locust Grove, Va.: Frances Fulk, 1984.</p>
      <p>Horst, Irvin. Joseph Funk: Early Mennonite Printer and Publisher. Goshen, In.: Mennonite
        Historical Society, 1957.</p>
      <p>Two Notable Shaped-Note Leaders: Joseph Funk by John W. Wayland and Aldine S. Kieffer by
        Weldon T. Myers, William B. Blake, and B. C. Unseld. Wytheville, Va.: Bookworm &amp;
        Silverfish, 1995.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh">Funk, Joseph, 1778-1862</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Musicians -- Virginia -- Rockingham County</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Publishers and publishing -- Virginia</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Mennonites -- Hymns</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Singers Glen (Va.) -- History</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat">Letters (correspondence)</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>People:</head>
        <persname rules="local" source="local">Funk, Joseph, 1778-1862</persname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_8ad85ef10a5e3d700108b16ae30fe499" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>February 7, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_c8557522a690058f740f3232baf48dd6" label="Folder"
            type="folder">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_8c6e26e738cbc327ddd558e07bf70ad9" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>March 22, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_a0a1602dd45b6b15b70cd85887320d6d" label="Folder"
            type="folder">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_b6e36b816d37fcaf27e8dbc33b7ebf1b" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>July 8, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_37adae9159a9d39fefeafef0a63e4305" label="Folder"
            type="folder">3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_58215baffa384d796e044338c2db78d6" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>July 30, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_2f3f8e09ba365c933eec240325026606" label="Folder"
            type="folder">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_71b278609687dc3d8ea7b9a6734feb2a" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>August 16, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_75b4b2b273194ec3771a286113e0b831" label="Folder"
            type="folder">5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_75d0612020cea0a12ee007547b27448f" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>September 18,
            1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_5cfc87cff30fffce36cc2c714938a312" label="Folder"
            type="folder">6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_f168c8027e521c9471435e7543c51ec5" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>September 28,
            1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_102ef49dd14b0e088dcf3e8f288030cf" label="Folder"
            type="folder">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_67ea911aa0cb64c9dc8c2f8bce2205d2" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>October 3, 1832</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_107dfba27f434e41cf292cb2c06b3a1a" label="Folder"
            type="folder">8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_9178dbf93009590c348b4f360049c00f" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robinson and J. W. Hollis to Joseph Funk, <unitdate>March 17,
            1836</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container id="aspace_0ac7419fa96627c66efcf8e9734d5439" label="Folder"
            type="folder">9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
