<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vihart00126">
	<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
		<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier
			Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::vihart00126:: Warden Ledger collection,
			1806-1880)//EN" "vihart00126.xml" </eadid>
		<filedesc>
			<titlestmt>
				<titleproper>A Guide to the Warden Ledger collection, <date>1806-1880, bulk 1806
					</date>
				</titleproper>
				<subtitle id="sort">Warden Ledger collection<num type="collectionnumber">5023</num>
				</subtitle>
			</titlestmt>
			<publicationstmt>
				<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
				</publisher> &address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2011 By JMU Libraries. All
					rights reserved. </date>
				<p id="usestatement">
					<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
				</p>
			</publicationstmt>
		</filedesc>
		<profiledesc>
			<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Trevor Alvord,
					<date>5/2011</date>
			</creation>
			<langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
			</langusage>
		</profiledesc>
	</eadheader>
	<frontmatter>
		<titlepage>
			<titleproper>Guide to the Warden Ledger collection, <date>1806-1880, bulk 1806</date>
			</titleproper>
			<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number "> SC#
					5023 </num>
			</subtitle>
			<p id="logostmt">
				<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
			</p>
			<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
			<date type="publication">2011</date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
				<defitem>
					<label>Processed by: </label>
					<item>Trevor Alvord, Kathryn Barela, and Mark Purington</item>
				</defitem>
			</list>
		</titlepage>
	</frontmatter>
	<archdesc level="collection">
		<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University </runner>
		<did>
			<head>Descriptive Summary </head>
			<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison
				University </repository>
			<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Warden Ledger collection<unitdate
					type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1806-1880</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<unitid label="Collection Number SC# " encodinganalog="099$a">5023</unitid>
			<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">645 items</physdesc>
			<langmaterial label="Language">
				<language langcode="eng">English </language>
			</langmaterial>
			<abstract label="Abstract">This collection consists of three digital documents; one
				ledger and two estate appraisal documents from the antebellum and gilded periods of
				American history. The ledger documents significant commerce in early antebellum
				Hardy County, then Virginia (now West Virginia). The two estate documents are from
				homes of individuals who lived in Augusta County Virginia.</abstract>
			<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Warden Family </origination>
		</did>
		<descgrp type="admininfo">
			<head>Administrative Information </head>
			<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
				<head>Access Restrictions </head>
				<p>None. </p>
			</accessrestrict>
			<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
				<head>Use Restrictions </head>
				<p>Reproduction of this collection for publication, exhibition, web display or
					commercial use is only permissible with the consent of James Madison
					University's Libraries &amp; Educational Technologies' Special Collections (540)
					568-3612, library-special@jmu.edu</p>
			</userestrict>
			<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
				<head>Preferred Citation </head>
				<p>Warden Ledger Collection, SC# 5023, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James
					Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.</p>
			</prefercite>
			<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
				<head>Acquisition Information </head>
				<p>The digital rights to the material were anonymously donated in October 2010.</p>
			</acqinfo>
			<custodhist>
				<head>Provenance </head>
				<p>The two appraisal documents were contained in the ledger, all of which have been
					held in the donor family's possession until the time of donation to James
					Madison University. The originals were returned to the owner after a digital
					copy was made.</p>
			</custodhist>
			<processinfo>
				<head>Processing Information</head>
				<p>Digitization of the Nimord Warden buisness ledger was made with an EOS Canon
					Digital Rebel XT 8 megapixel w/ EX Sigma 50 mm F2.8 DG Macro lens, copystand
					illuminated w/ 4 GE 100watt Reveal incandescent bulbs, edited in AdobePhotoshop
					5.0, with archival copies saved to 72 ppi LZW tiff. Digitized by Julia Merkel,
					December 2010.</p>

				<p>The two appraisal documents: "A List of the Property Appraised of the Estate of
					Samuel Harnsberger December 26th, 1857" and "Mother’s Sale Bill 5th November
					1880", were scanned by an EPSON Expression 10000XL set at 600dpi. The images
					were edited using Adobe Photoshop Elements 8 and saved as high quality jpg's. A
					high-resolution tiff file was also created as the archival file. Digitized by
					Trevor Alvord, April 2011.</p>
			</processinfo>
		</descgrp>
		<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
			<head>Biographical Information </head>
			<p>The Warden family traces its history back to the earliest days of European settlement
				in the Shenandoah Valley. Records indicate a direct genealogical line to Jost Hite,
				believed to be one of the first European settlers. The family initially settled
				along the Lost River in Hardy County in the early 18th century when that county was
				still part of the commonwealth of Virginia. The family grew and prospered as farmers
				and merchants, as indicated by the 1806 ledger, which records regular trade
				transactions with ships bound for France, London, Dublin, Spain and the West Indies.
				Among the commodities purchased were French wines, sugar and rum from Barbados and
				Irish linens. Export items included finished leather, ox hides and tallow for making
				candles.</p>

			<p>The Nimrod Warden ledger accounts for business activities in Hardy County near
				Winchester, Virginia. This ledgers' historical significance directly correlates to
				the Shenandoah Valley and to the large industries that the Valley is known for
				today. The ledger describes the inventory for a business which appears to be that of
				a substantial wholesaler. The contents of this ledger illuminate national and
				international trade activities preceding the War of 1812, specifically the trade
				embargo. Even though the business accounted for in the Nimrod Warden ledger operated
				in harsh conditions of trade and was not located at a major port such as Boston it
				still thrived in commerce using the backdrop of the Shenandoah Valley. The monetary
				amounts in the ledger are in pounds sterling, demonstrating that even thirty years
				after the start of the revolutionary war the American trade industry still used
				pounds.</p>
		</bioghist>
		<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
			<head>Scope and Content </head>
			<p>The Warden Ledger Collection consists of three digital documents compiling 174
				images. The main ledger (Nimrod Warden) is 13.5 inches long and 8.5 inches wide. The
				name Nimrod Warden appears on the cover page of the ledger, it does not indicate if
				he was the owner or the bookkeeper. The words "Hardy County" appear at the top of
				almost every page and the dates covered are January 24 through December 24, 1806.
				This ledger gives a detailed accounting of the state of international trade between
				Jeffersonian America and Napoleonic Europe at the dawn of the 19th century.</p>



			<p>Included in the collection is an appraisal of the estate of Samuel Harnsberger of
				Augusta County, dated December 26, 1857. Handwritten notes (added in the 20th
				century) identify Samuel Harnsberger as the grandfather of Warden C. Parkins, Sr.,
				who was directly descended from the Warden family. The ledger is an accounting of
				Mr. Harnsberger's estate, which included livestock, furniture, farm equipment, and
				several pages of promissory notes for personal loans made by Mr. Harnsberger. One
				page of the ledger lists the names of twenty-five slaves of various ages. The 1850
				US census lists seventeen slaves owned by Samuel Harnsberger of Augusta County.
				Noted Shenandoah Valley historian John Wayland identifies a Samuel Harnsberger as a
				director of the Valley Turnpike Company, a public/private venture that developed a
				commercial route from Staunton to Winchester in the late 1830s which is still in
				service today as Virginia Route 11. The Harnsberger ledger includes a heading for
				"55 shares of Turnpike stock".</p>



			<p>The final ledger, dated November 5, 1880, also appears to be an accounting of an
				estate sale for the household goods of an unnamed woman. At the top of the first
				page is written "Mother's sale bill," and in a later note, possibly written with a
				felt-tipped pen, is the name "Susan Clagett Warden?" which has been crossed out.
				Genealogical records show that Susan Clagett Warden was a great-grandmother to
				Warden Parkins, mentioned in the Harnsberger ledger. Several of the items were
				purchased by Jacob and J.M. Warden, who are possibly Susan Warden's husband and
				brother-in-law, James McCoy Warden, respectively. Their mother, Lucinda Van Nort
				Warden passed away in April, 1880, and is very likely the "Mother" noted on the
				ledger. This accounting, like the Harnsberger sale, give a detailed look into the
				lives of Shenandoah Valley residents in the mid- to late-19th century.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
			<head>Arrangement </head>
			<p>The digital images of the collection are arranged in the same order as the original
				ledger.</p>
		</arrangement>
		<descgrp type="add">
			<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data </head>
			<originalsloc>
				<head>Location of Originals</head>
				<p>Original Ledger is retained by the donor, 2011.</p>
			</originalsloc>
		</descgrp>
		<dsc type="combined">
			<head>Contents List </head>
			<c01 level="file">
				<did>
					<unittitle><extref
							href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/megazine/11274/nimrod-warden-ledger-hardy-county-west-virginia-18/"
							actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">Nimrod Warden Daybook,
							</extref><unitdate type="inclusive">1806 January 24</unitdate>
					</unittitle>
					<physdesc>(86 pages)</physdesc>
					<note audience="external">
						<p><extref
								href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/view/11274/nimrod-warden-ledger-hardy-county-west-virginia-18/"
								actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">[Browse
								Images]</extref></p>
					</note>
				</did>
			</c01>
			<c01 level="file">
				<did>
					<unittitle><extref
							href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/megazine/11273/samuel-harnsburger-appraisal-document-1857/"
							actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">A List of the Property
							Appraised of the Estate of Samuel Harnsberger,</extref>
						<unitdate type="inclusive">1857 December 26</unitdate>
					</unittitle>
					<physdesc>(14 pages)</physdesc>
					<note audience="external">
						<p><extref
								href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/view/11273/samuel-harnsburger-appraisal-document-1857/"
								actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">[Browse
								Images]</extref></p>
					</note>
				</did>
			</c01>
			<c01 level="file">
				<did>
					<unittitle><extref
							href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/megazine/11272/mothers-sale-bill-1880/"
							actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">Mother’s Sale Bill,
							</extref><unitdate type="inclusive">1880 November 1880</unitdate>
					</unittitle>
					<physdesc>(12 pages)</physdesc>
					<note audience="external">
						<p><extref
								href="https://mdid.cit.jmu.edu/viewers/view/11272/mothers-sale-bill-1880/"
								actuate="onrequest" show="new" linktype="simple">[Browse
								Images]</extref></p>
					</note>
				</did>
			</c01>
		</dsc>
	</archdesc>
</ead>
