<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vihart00151">
	<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
		<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier
			Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::vihart00NUMBER::COLLECTION NAME AND
			DESCRIPTION [i.e. vihart00129::Wampler Business records, 1918-1972])//EN"
			"vihart00NUMBER.xml" </eadid>
		<filedesc>
			<titlestmt>
				<titleproper>A Guide to the Bethlehem Stone Church Records, <date>1844-1980s</date>
				</titleproper>
				<subtitle id="sort">Bethlehem Stone Church Records<num type="collectionnumber">SC
						5037</num>
				</subtitle>
			</titlestmt>
			<publicationstmt>
				<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
				</publisher> &address; <date type="publication">&copy; 2012 By JMU Libraries. All
					rights reserved. </date>
				<p id="usestatement">
					<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use </extref>
				</p>
			</publicationstmt>
		</filedesc>
		<profiledesc>
			<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Mark Peterson,
					<date>04/2013</date>
			</creation>
			<langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language>
			</langusage>
		</profiledesc>
	</eadheader>
	<frontmatter>
		<titlepage>
			<titleproper>A Guide to the Bethlehem Stone Church Records, <date>1844-1980s</date>
			</titleproper>
			<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections <num type="Collection Number "> SC
					5037</num>
			</subtitle>
			<p id="logostmt">
				<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
			</p>
			<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
			<date type="publication">2013</date> &contact; <list type="deflist">
				<defitem>
					<label>Processed by:</label>
					<item>Lauren Fleming</item>
				</defitem>
			</list>
		</titlepage>
	</frontmatter>
	<archdesc level="collection">
		<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University </runner>
		<did>
			<head>Descriptive Summary </head>
			<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison
				University </repository>
			<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Bethlehem Stone Church Records,
					<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f"
					>1844-1980s</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<unitid label="Collection Number SC# " encodinganalog="099$a">SC 5037</unitid>
			<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">5,430 digital images</physdesc>
			<langmaterial label="Language">
				<language langcode="eng">English </language>
			</langmaterial>
			<abstract label="Abstract">The Bethlehem Christian Church Records is a digital
				collection that contains scans of documents relating to the church from its
				inception in 1844 through the 1980s. There are minutes of business meetings and
				Sunday Schools, financial accounts, lists of members, and general historical
				information.</abstract>
			<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Bethlehem United Methodist Church of
				Christ, Tenth Legion, Virginia</origination>
		</did>
		<descgrp type="admininfo">
			<head>Administrative Information </head>
			<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
				<head>Access Restrictions </head>
				<p>None</p>
			</accessrestrict>
			<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
				<head>Use Restrictions </head>
				<p>None</p>
			</userestrict>
			<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
				<head>Preferred Citation </head>
				<p>[Identification of Item], The Bethlehem Stone Church Records, 1844-1980s, SC
					5037, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University,
					Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
			</prefercite>
			<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
				<head>Acquisition Information </head>
				<p>Documents lent to James Madison Special Collections for digitization in 2012.</p>
			</acqinfo>
			<custodhist>
				<head>Provenance </head>
				<p>Acquiring the collection was suggested to Mark Peterson, head of James Madison
					Special Collections, by Dr. Andrew Witmer. Dr. Witmer intended to include the
					collection in his History Harvest project but was unable to do so because of
					time constraints. Dr. Peterson contacted the church and, with the help of the
					church’s secretary, gathered the collection for digitization in 2012.</p>
			</custodhist>
			<processinfo>
				<head>Processing Information</head>
				<p>The pages in the documents were scanned front and back. In some instances pages
					were not scanned when there was an abundance of blank pages in a series at the
					end of ledgers. There are some duplicate images, particularly in Series IV which
					relate to church history. For instance, there are multiple copies of 5037.2.1998
					to reflect multiple hard copies of the document; 5037.2.1998 was not scanned
					more than once. Documents 5037.2.1101, 5037.2.1097, and 5037.2.1281 are
					duplicates. On file 5037.2.685 there are stamps stuck to the original page that
					cannot be removed to reveal the writing underneath. </p>
			</processinfo>
		</descgrp>
		<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
			<head>Biographical Information </head>
			<p>Bethlehem United Church of Christ, commonly called the Bethlehem Stone Church, sits
				in Tenth Legion, just south of New Market, Virginia in the Shenandoah Valley. Today
				the church campus consists of a small stone building and a larger brick building.
				The stone structure was the original house of worship for the Bethlehem congregation
				and was constructed in 1845, one year after its founding. Since that time Bethlehem
				United Church of Christ has had an active congregation that has held church dinners,
				homecomings, regular Sunday worship, and Sunday School. During the Civil War the Old
				Stone Church was used as a military hospital and during a restoration of the
				building in 2008 the names of many soldiers were found penciled on the walls. After
				the Civil War the church was used by several different denominations including the
				Christian Church, the United Brethren in Christ, and the German Baptist Church. The
				structure itself was in need of repair from neglect and damage done during the Civil
				War. In 1872 a committee was formed to reorganize the congregation and repair the
				Church’s structural damage. The congregation worshipped in the Stone Church until
				1952 when a larger brick church was built on the land beside it. Since that time the
				congregation has continued worship on the property and has shown interest in its
				rich history. In 1981 Bethlehem Stone Church was added to the Virginia Landmarks
				Register and in 2008 the congregation, with support from the community, restored the
				Stone Church. </p>
		</bioghist>
		<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
			<head>Scope and Content </head>
			<p>The Bethlehem Stone Church Records consist of 5,430 digital images. These images have
				been arranged according to theme into five series. The following is a breakdown of
				each series with a short description of the various documents:</p>
			<p>Series I: Business/Treasurer’s Minutes</p>
			<p>Church Begins 1844… (1844-1873) This book notes where church services were held and
				who was present. It includes a roll of all the male and female members and their
				standing within the church.</p>
			<p>Deed 1844 Two (1881-1886) The first page of the document labels this book as
				“Bethlehem, Va Christian Church Book.” It details the governing principles of the
				church in 1881, a roll of members, minutes of meetings, and the original deed for
				the church land.</p>
			<p>1892 E.T. Isley/1895 R.H. Peel (1881-1895) This notebook is filled with general notes
				as to the business of the church. It includes membership records as well as accounts
				of how much money each member contributed to the pastor’s salary. Lists of annual
				committee officers are listed as well as minutes of business meetings.</p>
			<p>1883 Three (1884-1894) Business and treasury minutes are noted here. There are
				listings of receipts and debts paid, and the organization of Sabbath School (Sunday
				School).</p>
			<p>1896 R.H. Peel-1910 Rev. W.T. Walters (1896-1910) Like many of the other business
				records, this notebook lists the officers of the church, a roll of the members, and
				business minutes of Conference meetings. </p>
			<p>Treasurer (1897-1898)-check date Records of church members and their payments to the
				pastor’s salary. </p>
			<p>Ledger (1906-1915) The ledger includes apportionment records and general treasury and
				accounting information. </p>
			<p>Va Valley Central Christian Conference Treasure Book (1912-1924) A treasurer’s
				account of various committees within the conference such as the Woman's Home and
				Foreign Mission Board.</p>
			<p>Tithing Record (1919-1926) This is a record of tithing for members of the church
				starting in 1919 running through 1926. </p>
			<p>Church Record (c. 1940s) Conference minutes, indexes of church members, and
				attendance records are included in this record.</p>
			<p>Annual Report to Conference (1944-1945) An accounting of the contemporary composition
				of the church such as who was pastor—Rev. G.H. Beazey—his history, the total
				membership, and the church’s finances.</p>
			<p>Proposed Budget for 1946-1947 (1946-1947) The details of this document spell out the
				proposed budget for 1946 and 1947. Some of the categories are the pastor’s salary,
				parsonage rent, pew payments, janitor services, etc. </p>
			<p>Payment of Parsonage Debt per Church (1948) This payment record lists the debts of
				various parsonages for things like plumbing, property repairs, and the building of
				garages. Bethlehem United Church of Christ is one of the churches listed on this
				report.</p>
			<p>A Decision From Bethlehem… (5 December 1950) A letter that details the reasons behind
				Reverend Clyde O’Koon's resignation.</p>
			<p>Church Business Meeting Minutes (1948-1952) These minutes relate details of the
				monthly business meetings. They were opened with prayer and discussed issues like
				salaries, building additions to the church and arrangements for Home Coming.</p>
			<p>On March 4, 1952 (1952) In 1952 Bethlehem United Church of Christ hosted the
				twenty-second mid-year session of the Virginia Valley Central Conference of
				Congregational-Christian Churches. This document relates the members elected to this
				particular conference.</p>
			<p>WriteRight (1952-1954) This book is filled with monthly business meeting notes for
				the church.</p>
			<p>Series II: Sunday School Minutes Each of these documents contains minutes of Sunday
				School meetings. They detail the people elected to committee positions, a roll of
				members in the classes, a list of classes, a weekly program of the meetings that
				includes songs, scriptures and a few business notes. Any exception to this has been
				noted. </p>
			<p>S.S. Records 1896-1903 (1896-1903) S.S. stands for Sunday School.</p>
			<p>Sunday School Records 1907-1912 (1907-1912) </p>
			<p>SE Ledger S. S. Treasurer 1913-1914 (1913-1914) This is a cash account of the
				Bethlehem Sunday School’s collection. There are a few business meeting minutes at
				the end.</p>
			<p>Sunday School Minutes 1938-1940 (1938-1940) Rosalie F. Sellers gave these minutes to
				Bethlehem United Church of Christ in 1988.</p>
			<p> S.S. Records 9/1/1940-7/25/1943 (1940-1943)</p>
			<p>Record 1943-1946 Pauline Brown Shope gave these records to Bethlehem Church on July
				7, 1986. </p>
			<p> Sunday School Minutes 1948-1952 (1948-1952)</p>
			<p>The 1950 Supernatural Notebook (1950-1951) Less formal in organization than all
				previous Sunday School records.</p>
			<p>100 pages composition (1931-1934) This composition notebook includes notes and
				accounts for expenses and profits of soup sales, election dinners, and
				Mid-Conference Dinners. Menus for these dinners are included. A woman’s group within
				the church organized these meals and fundraisers at the church. </p>
			<p>Ladies' Aid-Minutes of Meetings (1936-1942) The Ladies' Aid Committee met monthly at
				various members' homes and organized things such as raffles, and benevolent aid
				missions. They would buy oil cloth for tables, get the piano in the church tuned,
				write cards for convalescents, and send out fruit baskets. This document is the
				minutes of their meetings. </p>
			<p>History of Women’s Fellowship of Valley of Va (1938) This is a typed history report
				of the Valley Conference. There is one report of Bethlehem that mentions the
				Conference at Bethlehem. It mentions the work that they did in organizing the
				Conference Missionary Association. Most of the information is about the women’s
				missionary conference, but men are mentioned as well. </p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1965-1966) Program Booklet for Lay Life and Work of Bethlehem United
				Church of Christ. This annual booklet was created by and for the Women’s Fellowship
				Committee. It’s theme for 1965-1966 was “Mission: The Christian's Calling.” It
				includes an index of sections that consist of a lesson plans for a bible study.
				There is also a list of officers and leaders for the Committee. It is essentially a
				reference guide or a program for the upcoming year. </p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1966-1967) This is the same as the above booklet but it has no
				stated theme.</p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1967-1968) Theme: “Living our faith in Today’s Walk”</p>
			<p>Program Booklet ((1968-1969) Theme: "Facing the New Day</p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1969-1970) Theme: "Bring the Good News"</p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1970-1971) Theme: "Love is"</p>
			<p>Program Booklet Theme: "Do According to Your Faith"(1971-1972)</p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1972-1973) Theme: "As You Go"</p>
			<p>Program Booklet (1974-1975) No theme stated</p>
			<p>Women’s Fellowship Binder (1959-1968) This is a binder filled with minutes from the
				Ladies' Aid Meetings. They would gather together, have a devotional, and then hold a
				meeting. Their minutes reveal that their work included organizing church suppers,
				giving gifts to orphans they were sponsoring, and buying supplies for the church
				kitchen. </p>
			<p>Women’s Fellowship Binder (1969-1975) Like the previous Women’s Fellowship Binder,
				this binder holds minutes for the women’s committee at the church. Unlike the
				previous binder the name of this committee changed from the Ladies' Aid Meetings to
				the Women’s Fellowship of Bethlehem. The committee did the same sorts of charitable
				work and fund-raising as before. </p>
			<p>Series IV: Church History Many of the documents in these history collections are
				duplicates of one another. For example, files numbers 5037.2.1628, 1752, 1753, 1826,
				1998, and 2024 are each the same document referring to changes in the architectural
				structure of the church building. </p>
			<p>Newspaper Scrapbook- “Perfection” This scrapbook contains newspaper clippings that
				mention Bethlehem United Christian Church and its members. There is a focus on
				obituaries. An inscription on the interior of the document tells us that the
				scrapbook was made by Miss Ella (Ella Pickering) and given to the church upon her
				death.</p>
			<p>Memories Binder This is a collection of documents relating to the history of the
				church. There are typed histories of the church, images of members and activities on
				the grounds, details of changes to the church architecture, and lists of pastors. </p>
			<p>Church History Folder This folder also contains newspaper clippings and photographs
				related to the church. It also has several program bulletins for the 145th
				anniversary celebration of worship, a church directory, and the addresses of many
				members. </p>
			<p>Church Papers Folder Here are more miscellaneous items concerning church history. </p>
			<p>Church History Additional Folder Similar to the above history folders. This one
				contains a history of the parsonage for the church, and landscape plans for the back
				yard/parking lot of the church. </p>
			<p>History Info Folder This contains a brief history of Bethlehem Christian Church, more
				typed histories, and newspaper clippings. </p>
			<p>Miscellaneous Papers-Bethlehem Miscellaneous papers about the church that includes
				newspaper clippings, images, and more typed histories of the church. There are also
				images of soldiers names penciled on to the church wall from the Civil War.</p>
			<p>National Historic Marker Info Folder (1980s) During the 1980s the church put forth a
				nomination form for the Church’s addition to the National Register of Historic
				Places. The documents in this folder are the nomination forms and letters pertaining
				to this process which was successful.</p>

			<p>Series V: Miscellaneous</p>
			<p>Record Book-Book I Deaths Rena Foltz (1915-1979) An inscription on the back of the
				front cover tells us that Rena Foltz wrote this record book between 1915 and 1979,
				and it was donated to the church by her daughter at Rena’s death. It lists people
				who died, when, at what age, who their family was, and sometimes where they are
				buried. </p>
			<p> Record Book-Book II Deaths Rena Foltz Same information as the above Record Book of
				Deaths. </p>
			<p>Historic Garden Week (1984) In 1984 Bethlehem United Christian Church was included in
				the Historic Garden Week Tour. As such, it had an entry in the event’s book which
				was donated to the church. The entry for Bethlehem is on page 58, file 5037.2.1188. </p>
			<p>Geography Questions This document contains a hand written play, poems, and trivia
				about American geography. </p>

		</scopecontent>
		<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
			<head>Arrangement </head>
			<p>The collection is arranged in 5 series:</p>
			<blockquote>
				<p>I: Business/Treasurer's Minutes</p>
			</blockquote>
			<blockquote>
				<p>II: Sunday School Records</p>
			</blockquote>
			<blockquote>
				<p>III: Women's Business</p>
			</blockquote>
			<blockquote>
				<p>IV: Church History</p>
			</blockquote>
			<blockquote>
				<p>V: Miscellaneous</p>
			</blockquote>
		</arrangement>

		<dsc type="combined">
			<head>Contents List </head>

			<c01 level="series">
				<did>
					<unittitle label="Series I"> Business/Treasurer's Minutes<unitdate
							type="inclusive">1844-1954</unitdate></unittitle>

				</did>

				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Church Begins 1844<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1844-1873</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.001-5037.2.108</unitid>
					</did>

				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Deed 1844 Two<unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1881-1886</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.132-5037.2.304</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>1892 E.T. Isley/1895 R.H. Peel <unitdate type="inclusive">
								1881-1895</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.999-5037.3.1127</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>1883 Tree<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1884-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.305-5037.2.444</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>1896 R.H. Peel-1910 Rev. W.T. Walters<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1896-1910</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.1130-5037.3.1272</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Treasurer<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1897-1898</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.1357-5037.2.1468</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Ledger<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1906-1915</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.320-5037.3.627</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>VA Valley Central Christian Conference Treasure Book <unitdate
								type="inclusive">1912-1924</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.630-5037.3.697</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Tithing Record <unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1919-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Images 5037.3.2037-5037.3.319; 5037.3.061-5037.3.065</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Church Record<unitdate type="inclusive"> c.
							1940s</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.3.1410-5037.3.1664</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Annual Report to Conference <unitdate type="inclusive"
								>1944-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.115-5037.2.118</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Proposed Budget for 1946-1947 <unitdate type="inclusive"
							/></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.109-5037.2.110</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>

				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Payment of Parsonage Debt per Church<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1948</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.119-5037.2.122</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>A Decision from Bethlehem <unitdate type="inclusive">1950
								December 05</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.113-5037.2.114</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Church Business Meetings<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1948-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.003-5037.3.060</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>On March 5, 1952<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.111-5037.2.112</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>WriteRight<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1952-1954</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1042-5037.2.1095</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
			</c01>
			<c01 level="series">
				<did>
					<unittitle label="Series II"> Sunday School Records <unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1896-1951</unitdate></unittitle>

				</did>

				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>S.S. Records <unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1896-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.180-5037.3.996</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Sunday School Records <unitdate type="inclusive"
								>1907-1912</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.3.1280-5037.3.1402</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>SE Ledger S.S. Treasurer <unitdate type="inclusive"
								>1913-1914</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.3.700-5037.3.779</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Sunday School Minutes<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1938-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.445-5037.2.527</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>S.S. Records <unitdate type="inclusive"> 1940 September 09-1943
								July 25 </unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.773-5037.2.9914</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Record<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1943-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.573-5037.2.772</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Sunday School Minutes<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1948-1952</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.3.066-5037.3.200</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>The 1950 Supernatural Notebook<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1950-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.992-5037.2.1041</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>

			</c01>
			<c01 level="series">
				<did>
					<unittitle label="Series III"> Women's Business <unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1931-1975</unitdate></unittitle>

				</did>

				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>100 Page Composition <unitdate type="inclusive"
								>1931-1934</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.001-5037.1.072</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Ladies Aid-Minutes of Meetings<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1936-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.081-5037.1.192</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>History of VA Women's Fellowship of Valley of VA<unitdate
								type="inclusive"> 1938</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.1284-5037.2.1356</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1965-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.201-5037.1.217</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1966-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.228-5037.1.243</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1967-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.252-5037.1.272</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1968-1969</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.281-5037.1.302</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1969-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.311-5037.1.329</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1970-1971</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.341-5037.1.364</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1971-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.375-5037.1.397</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1972-1973</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.408-5037.1.427</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Program Booklet<unitdate type="inclusive">
							1974-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.438-5037.1.449</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Women's Fellowship Binder<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1959-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.553-5037.1.1017</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Women's Fellowship Binder <unitdate type="inclusive"
								>1969-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.1020-5037.1.1374</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
			</c01>
			<c01 level="series">
				<did>
					<unittitle label="Series IV"> Church History <unitdate type="inclusive"
						/></unittitle>

				</did>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Newspaper Scrapbook<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.1805-5037.1.1852</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Memories Binder<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1546-5037.2.1682</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Church History Folder<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1684-5037.2.1888</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Church Papers Folder<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1890-5037.2.1908</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Church History Additional Folder<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.1910-5037.2.1988</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>History Info Folder<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1990-5037.2.2030</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers- Bethlehem<unitdate type="inclusive"
								><!-- YYYY MONTH DD --></unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.2080-5037.2.2122</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle>National Historic Marker Info<unitdate type="inclusive">
								1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.2.2032-5037.2.2077</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
			</c01>
			<c01 level="series">
				<did>
					<unittitle label="Series V"> Miscellaneous <unitdate type="inclusive"
							>1915-1984</unitdate></unittitle>

				</did>

				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Record Book- Book I Deaths Rena Foltz <unitdate type="inclusive"
								> 1915-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.1.1380-5037.1.1589</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Record Book- Book II Deaths Rena Foltz <unitdate
								type="inclusive"> </unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid> Image 5037.1.1591-5037.1.803</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> History Garden Week <unitdate type="inclusive">
							1984</unitdate></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1096-5037.2.1283</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
				<c02 level="file">
					<did>
						<unittitle> Geography Questions <unitdate type="inclusive"/></unittitle>
						<unitid>Image 5037.2.1470-5037.2.1544</unitid>
					</did>
				</c02>
			</c01>
		</dsc>
	</archdesc>
</ead>
