<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9"
     xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     audience="internal"
     xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1"
              dateencoding="iso8601"
              langencoding="iso639-2b"
              repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid countrycode="US"
             mainagencycode="US-vihart"
             url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00357.xml">vihart00357</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia Oral Histories, 1992:<num>SdArch 12</num>
            </titleproper>
            <author>JMU Cataloging, 1999</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2019 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved. </date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       xlink:type="simple"
                       xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and transformed with ASpace2VaHeritage.xsl on <date>2020-02-18 09:59:57 -0500</date>.</creation>
         <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia Oral Histories, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992 </date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SdArch 12</num>
         </subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad"
                    xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
         <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2019</date>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>JMU Cataloging, 1999</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <repository>
            <corpname>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</corpname>
         </repository>
         <unittitle>Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia Oral Histories</unittitle>
         <origination audience="internal" label="source">
            <persname role="dnr" source="local">Smith, Andrea</persname>
         </origination>
         <origination audience="internal" label="Creator">
            <persname role="ivr" source="local">Smith, Andrea</persname>
         </origination>
         <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SdArch 12</unitid>
         <unitid label="Collection Number"
                 encodinganalog="099$a"
                 audience="internal"
                 identifier="219"
                 type="Archon Instance::ACCESSION">219</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.2 cubic feet; 3 folders, 3 audiocassettes, 3 cds</physdesc>
         <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">1992</unitdate>
         <abstract id="aspace_d4c8941b01ea5eb2818f77e7c7f90de6">The Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia, Oral Histories, 1992 is comprised of background paper, audio recordings and transcripts, associated with two interviews with individuals discussing their experiences with education in the Shenandoah Valley, from the 1920s-1970s.</abstract>
         <physloc id="aspace_cadb23211b7999ef7c60024ba39f63cb">Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</physloc>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict id="aspace_cdd3176de4e7c6daf52beff558dcfc9a">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Access to oral histories is governed by agreements with the narrators. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>  
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict id="aspace_50bff1f6782acdc28cf145c6e704c1a3">
            <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
            <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>  
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite id="aspace_e4f628ceb30d24d50352a6bda7022b2d">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia, Oral Histories, 1992, SdArch 12, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>  
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo id="aspace_985b4d052bb54330df36130873961abc">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Donated by Andrea Smith, December 12, 1992.</p>  
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
  
  
  
  
      <bioghist id="aspace_e9911b33d3cde443244d49abb2566d68">
         <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
         <p>Andrea Smith, an undergraduate student at James Madison University, conducted these interviews in fulfillment of a JMU student internship, during the Fall of 1992.</p>  
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="aspace_b767c9f0d2c06e4020b7f06d2937a63b">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>Comparison of Private versus Public Education in Rockingham County, Virginia, Oral Histories, 1992 is comprised of background paper, audio recordings and transcripts, associated with two interviews with individuals discussing their experiences with education in the Shenandoah Valley from the 1920s-1070s.</p>  
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement id="aspace_647d3d598d86a6f9f78114599ca7309a">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Items are arranged chronologically.</p>  
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess>
         <head>Index Terms</head>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">Schools -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rural schools -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Private schools -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Home schooling -- Virginia -- Rockingham County -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- 20th century</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Education, Elementary -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Education, Elementary -- Curricula -- History</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Education, Secondary -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Education -- Virginia -- Rockingham County (Va.) -- History</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">oral histories (literary works)</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <dsc>
         <c01 id="aspace_501d4f44715bebb498e44dad096e4811" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>12-1: Project Description and Background Paper, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">December 9, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_933076f56c6abacf2478e949d8b48a58"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_507f8530f4ef2c0962750fbeb931d3df"
                          parent="aspace_933076f56c6abacf2478e949d8b48a58"
                          type="Folder">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_1d40901724f893694638439b3dae3f3b">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This monograph provides a short history of education in the state of Virginia, the Shenandoah Valley, and in particular, Rockingham County, Va. Compares and contrasts the types of education available for affluent and less affluent families, in the form of private and public education. Reviews how private education began through tutoring and academies and quotes from the writings of Major R. Grattan (d. 1849), of Rockingham County. Briefly records the history of public education, beginning with Thomas Jefferson and including the efforts of Henry Ruffner who first proposed a state-wide public school system based on districts (1845; similar plan adopted in 1870). Mentions education of Afro-Americans and segregation. Records school figures (buildings, numbers of students), various rules of attendance and typical curricula for the five districts of Rockingham County beginning in the 1870s through the 1950s. Compares education in urban and rural settings with mention of types of school buildings (including the use of one-room schools), and changes towards consolidation. Accompanies interviews of two ladies and their reminiscences of educational opportunities growing up during the 1920s, one as a member of a prominent family and the other who later became a school teacher and supervisor in the Rockingham County school system. The project summary, based on the interviews, determined that while private education was viewed as being more favorable than public education, they were in many ways comparable.</p>
            </scopecontent>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_1570297c67af7b98c64f00e5d51f3e42" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>12-2: Margaret Grattan Weaver interviewed by Andrea Smith, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">October 23, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_e04369a1c227019cf64029fcb072884e"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-Materials">SdArch12-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_d6558d014549b7f15a70bb9ce9ed2405">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Grattan Weaver, member of a prominent Rockingham County, Va. family. Discusses education issues in general and the history of local private education in particular, especially in reference to her own family, beginning with her great grandfather, Major Robert Grattan (founder of Hood College, Md.). Mentions the old schoolhouse located behind the main house on the farm and the system of private tutoring. Talks about various local preparatory and finishing schools, military academies and colleges (Stribling Spring School, McGaheysville; one at Mossy Creek and Harrisonburg; West Central Academy, Mt. Clinton; Augusta Military Academy; Shenandoah Institute, Dayton; Woodberry Forest; Stuart Hall, Staunton; Hollins College; Harrisonburg High School and National Park College (where Mrs. Weaver went to school); Hampton Institute; Wellesley College (Mass.); VMI and the University of Va. Talks about school experiences and various curricula common to the day; compares and contrasts private and public education. Other references are made to family history (incl. the Roller family), various farms, the education of former slaves and the Civil War. Recorded at Mrs. Margaret Grattan Weaver's home, Inglewood Farm, Rockingham County, Va., on Oct. 23, 1992.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_03e76d6e33abd52697d0adc51ca0ba3e">
               <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
               <p>Audio and transcript are open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_b2642c28344b4e763a25fedf87e40aea">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_b17e42b6a1ec851af00189c0be76c20f" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">October 23, 1992</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_834e638eb6c5f2e25f826afa677d121a"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_967255cc88e5eddabd921d769494a204"
                             parent="aspace_834e638eb6c5f2e25f826afa677d121a"
                             type="Folder">2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_34bff53192dd4f68d92eec5f0c8b8a30" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>12-3: Dorothy Swank interviewed by Andrea Smith, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">October 28, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_025b65e457e3b54b1557c22e2eb23336"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-Materials">SdArch12-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_063a9f08936097cf4580acafae22f833">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the reminiscences of Dorothy Swank, retired elementary school teacher for the Rockingham County (Va.) school system. Talks about her educational background and experiences over a span of forty-four years of teaching including: teacher training (through the State Normal school now known as James Madison University); certification; experiences teaching in one-room schools such as Little North Mountain and Mt. Pleasant, teaching at a combined elementary-high school at Bridgewater, and Broadway elementary school; discipline problems; and experiences as an elementary school supervisor. Mentions conditions in one-room schools and their gradual phase out (last one in Rockingham County closed in 1962); recreation opportunities for students; teacher salaries and Depression-era problems; curricula; numbers of students in classrooms; compulsory attendance and consolidation of high schools (1951). Mentions contributions in the area of special education and providing education for learning disabled students; her interest in the Friendship Industries sheltered workshop in Harrisonburg; development of kindergarten programs; use of TV in schools; and art education. Remembers former students and their accomplishments to date. In general provides a perspective on public education in Rockingham County, Va. from the 1920s through early 1970s. Recorded at Ms. Dorothy Swank's home, Singers Glen, Rockingham County, Va., on Oct. 28, 1992</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_d541fad1fd320f28c833e6c2c5833cd6">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Audio and transcript are open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_424d3a0bd8aedff3b59e95b0f34aa8b3">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_16f246256e78fee88553b4e1b862c9ec" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">October 28, 1992</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_1f7cccb342c38ad78c87070d6d1cc5c7"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_087189ad3694d7fa5f76927324b3240c"
                             parent="aspace_1f7cccb342c38ad78c87070d6d1cc5c7"
                             type="Folder">3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
