<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
      langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-US-vihart"
         url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00126.xml"
         >vihart00126</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Warden and Harnsberger Family Papers, 1806-1880:<num>SC
                  0201</num>
            </titleproper>
            <author>Trevor Alvord, Kathryn Barela, and Mark Purington, 2011; Julia Merkel, 2011;
               Sarah Roth-Mullet, April 2019; Tiffany Cole, December 2019</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
               href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2019 By JMU Libraries. All
               rights reserved. </date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
                  xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
                  Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and transformed with
            ASpace2VaHeritage.xsl on <date>2019-12-12 10:53:36 -0500</date>.</creation>
         <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change audience="internal">
            <date>2013-11-21</date>
            <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
         </change>
         <change audience="internal">
            <date>April 2011</date>
            <item>Revised by Julia Merkel</item>
         </change>
         <change audience="internal">
            <date>April 2019</date>
            <item>Collection renumbered by Sarah Roth-Mullet</item>
         </change>
         <change audience="internal">
            <date>November 2019</date>
            <item>Updated to reflect acquisition of Harnsberger estate appraisal and mother's sale
               bill and information about Nimrod Warden ledger.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Warden and Harnsberger Family Papers, <date era="ce"
               calendar="gregorian">1806-1880 </date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
               0201</num>
         </subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
               xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
               xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
         <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2019</date>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Trevor Alvord, Kathryn Barela, and Mark Purington, 2011; Julia Merkel, 2011;
                  Sarah Roth-Mullet, April 2019; Tiffany Cole, December 2019</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <repository>
            <corpname>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</corpname>
         </repository>
         <unittitle>Warden and Harnsberger Family Papers, </unittitle>
              <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0201</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.12 gigabytes; 3 digital files</physdesc>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.08 cubic feet; 2 folders</physdesc>
         <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1806/1880" type="inclusive"
            >1806-1880</unitdate>
         <abstract audience="internal" id="aspace_b590b222a2ea762b0f201fb68fbc4fff">The Warden and
            Harnsberger Family Papers, 1806-1880, comprise Nimrod Warden's copybook (only available
            as a digital facsimile), a sale bill probably for the estate of Lucinda VanNort Warden,
            and appraisal of Samuel Harnsberger's estate.</abstract>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language> . </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_49b3696fe9aec69c9ddd59e01dfbb11f">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Collection is open for research. The Nimrod Warden copybook is only available in a
               digital format. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws
               before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting
               the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict audience="internal" id="aspace_8688b0d86647cc1b2e2d63535f85b442">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
               University Special Collection Library. For more information, contact the Special
               Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite audience="internal" id="aspace_53e1b9fcf9d91e1690207bd1478e1923">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Warden and Harnsberger Family Papers,
               1806-1880, SC 0201, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison
               University.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_27fda00abd1da40599d3369b8bc202ff">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>In September 2010, the owner of the Warden and Harnsberger manuscript material
               contacted JMU history professor Dr. Michael Galgano and loaned him the documents and
               copybook. The owner gave Dr. Galgano permission to scan the materials which Special
               Collections completed in December 2010 and April 2011. The digital rights to the
               material were donated in October 2010 by the owner who wished to remain anonymous.
               The physical material was returned to the owner.</p>
            <p>The Samuel Harnsberger property appraisal and mother's sale bill were acquired by
               Special Collections at Jeffrey Evans &amp; Associates' 37th Semi-Annual Americana
               &amp; Fine Antiques Auction featuring Virginia and the South on November 16, 2019.
               Per the auctioneer's catalog, the manuscripts descended directly in the Warden family
               to the current owner.</p>
         </acqinfo>
         <custodhist audience="internal" id="aspace_04bb7e11c26c23025e04bc4d888e6005">
            <head>Provenance</head>
            <p>The Harnsberger appraisal and mother's sale bill were contained in the Nimrod Warden
               copybook, all of which had been held in the owner's family's possession until the
               time of loaning to James Madison University for the purposes of digitization. The
               originals were returned to the owner after digital copies were made. All three items
               were then consigned by Jeffrey Evans &amp; Associates for his 37th Semi-Annual
               Americana &amp; Fine Antiques Auction featuring Virginia and the South on November
               16, 2019. Prior to the auction, Evans was alerted by a researcher that the Nimrod
               Warden ledger was not an authentic account of Warden's business dealings, but
               actually an exact transcription of William Jackson's 1801 manual <emph
                  render="italic">Book-Keeping in the True Italian Form of Debtor and Creditor by
                  Way of Double Entry;...</emph>, making it a copybook and not a daybook. As a
               result, the ledger was pulled from the auction and returned to the owner. Up until
               November 2019, the Nimrod Warden copybook was assumed by JMU Special Collections to
               be a legitimate account of Warden's Hardy County merchant house and farm. It was even
               cited as such in Steven Stoll's <emph render="italic">Ramp Hollow: The Ordeal of
                  Appalachia</emph> (2017). The description within this finding aid has been updated
               to reflect the actual provenance of the Warden copybook.</p>
         </custodhist>
         <processinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_63ebbe3e588595c1f65c3bdc1a2870b7">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>Digitization of the Nimord Warden copybook was made with an EOS Canon Digital Rebel
               XT 8 megapixel w/ EX Sigma 50 mm F2.8 DG Macro lens, copystand illuminated w/ 4 GE
               100watt Reveal incandescent bulbs, edited in AdobePhotoshop 5.0, with archival copies
               saved to 72 ppi LZW tiff. Digitized by Julia Merkel in December 2010.</p>
            <p>"A List of the Property Appraised of the Estate of Samuel Harnsberger December 26th,
               1857," and "Mother's Sale Bill 5th November 1880," were scanned by an EPSON
               Expression 10000XL set at 600dpi. The images were edited using Adobe Photoshop
               Elements 8 and saved as high quality jpg's. A high-resolution tiff file was also
               created as the archival file. Digitized by Trevor Alvord in April 2011. Image files
               were converted to pdfs for access.</p>
            <p>In order to streamline the process of applying collection numbers, Special
               Collections staff completed a large-scale renumbering campaign in 2017-2019. <emph
                  render="bold">This collection was previously cataloged as SC 5023 and formerly
                  titled Warden Ledger Collection</emph>. The collection was also renamed Warden and
               Harnsberger Family Papers to more accurately reflect its contents and creators. The
               biographical note and scope and content note were updated to reflect the fact that
               the Nimrod Warden copybook is not an authentic account of Warden's business dealings,
               but actually an exact transcription of William Jackson's 1801 manual <emph
                  render="italic">Book-Keeping in the True Italian Form of Debtor and Creditor by
                  Way of Double Entry;...</emph>. Previous versions of the collection's finding aids
               are available in the collection control file.</p>
         </processinfo>
      </descgrp>






      <bioghist audience="internal" id="aspace_dc885a006d0de2dcd89d9384eddffddd">
         <head>Biographical Information</head>
         <p>Nimrod Warden (b. 1786) was the son of William Wallace Warden (1749-1823) and Sarah
            Chrisman Warden (1757-1829) of Hardy County, Virginia (now West Virginia), likely near
            Lost River. Until November 2019, it was assumed that Nimrod Warden was a prosperous
            merchant, wholesaler, and international trader. This was likely not the case given that
            the 1806 account book that these assumptions were based on is, in actuality, a copybook
            of an 1801 bookkeeping manual. Additionally, genealogical evidence strongly suggests
            that Nimrod Warden was born ca. 1786. It seems highly unlikely that he would have been
            the proprietor of such a successful international trading company at the age of 20, when
            the copybook was created (1806). Nimrod Warden's brother, Benjamin Franklin Warden
            (1790-1844), married Lucinda VanNort (1807-1880) in 1829. It is assumed that the sale
            bill in this collection dated November 5, 1880 and titled "Mother's Sale Bill" is likely
            from the estate of Lucinda VanNort Warden. </p>
         <p>The Warden family of Hardy County is linked to the Harnsberger family of Augusta County,
            Virginia via Grace Gretchen Warden (1869-1941), granddaughter of Benjamin Franklin
            Warden and Lucinda VanNort Warden. Grace Gretchen Warden married Samuel Harnsberger
            Parkins (1863-1933), son of Isaac J. Parkins (1822-1872) and Christina V. Harnsberger
            Parkins (1828-1891). Isaac J. Parkins' name is at the top of Samuel Harnsberger's estate
            appraisal indicating he likely conducted the appraisal. Christina V. Harnsberger Parkins
            is the daughter of Samuel Harnsberger (1798-1851) and Anne G. Robinson Harnsberger
            (1797-1860), not their granddaughter as a note on the Harnsberger estate appraisal
            indicates.</p>
         <p>An even more detailed account of the Warden-Harnsberger genealogical line is available
            in the collection's control file. Researchers should note that the Harnsberger surname
            is spelled Harnsbarger and Hernsberger in additional to other spelling variations.</p>
         <p>Samuel Harnsberger resided in Augusta County, Virginia and was a farmer and enslaver by
            occupation. Harnsberger was also the second proprietor of a tavern and stagecoach stop
            located along the Valley Turnpike (Rt. 11) near Verona. According to the 1850 United
            States Census Slave Schedule, Samuel Harnsberger owned 20 enslaved persons ranging in
            age from 1 year old to 57 years old. There are 25 enslaved persons listed on the 1851
            appraisal of his estate. All but two are listed by name. </p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_718cc3a9fcffa9eddd31b210081347ca">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The Warden and Harnsberger Family Papers, 1806-1880, comprise Nimrod Warden's copybook
            (only available as a digital facsimile), a sale bill presumably for the estate of
            Lucinda VanNort Warden, and appraisal of Samuel Harnsberger's estate. </p>
         <p>The copybook, previously thought to be an authentic account of Nimrod Warden's
            international business dealings, is actually a transcription of William Jackson's 1801
            manual <emph render="italic">Book-Keeping in the True Italian Form of Debtor and
               Creditor by Way of Double Entry;...</emph>. Warden wrote "Hardy County" at the front
            of the ledger as well as at the top of each page. Otherwise, the copybook is a near
            exact transcription of Jackson's manual. It is possible that Warden's transcription of
            the text served as a tool to practice his bookkeeping and/or penmanship skills. </p>
         <p>The copybook's handwritten title page reads: "Day Book January 24th 1806 Nimrod Warden.
            Hardy, County Virginia. Lost River." An inscription on the front pastedown provides some
            clues as to the provenance of the copybook as well as genealogical information. It
            reads: "This book is for Warden C. Parkins Aug. 20th 1934. Given to Warden, Jr. in 1960s
            (1968 probably) by his father." Jacob D. Dietrick's bookseller label is affixed to the
            front pastedown. Dietrick had a patent medicine and bookstore on Main Street in
            Winchester, Virginia.</p>
         <p>The "Mother's Sale Bill," dated November 5, 1880, is likely a bill for the estate sale
            of Lucinda VanNort Warden who died in April 1880. The bill lists items sold, buyers'
            names, and the amount each item sold. Items sold include household goods (coffee pot,
            wash pan, jars, baskets, bedding), untitled books, farm implements, and livestock.
            Lucinda VanNort Warden's sons, Jacob/Jake Warden (1841-1927) and J[ames] M[cCoy] Warden
            (1839-1928) are listed as buyers on the sale bill. The notation "Susan Clagett Warden ?"
            was marked out, presumably by a previous owner of the document, as Clagett died in 1926
            making it unlikely that the sale bill corresponded to her estate. The notation is also
            in a different hand from the bill and post-dates the creation of the document. </p>
         <p>The Samuel Harnsberger estate appraisal, dated December 26, 1851, comprises an inventory
            and appraisal of Harnsberger's personal affects, household goods, livestock, and
            enslaved persons, taken two months after his October 1851 death. The items are listed
            according to their location in the house. Livestock, farm implements, and the enslaved
            persons are not associated with a specific room. All but two of the enslaved persons on
            the appraisal are listed by name. They include Easter, Eve, Joe, Bowley, Henderson,
            Frank, Henry, Andy, [Corse], Alexandra, Martha, unnamed girl listed with Bell, Amanda,
            Bill, Mountain Bill, Nancy, John, James, Big Jim, Stephen, unnamed girl, Angeline,
            George, and [Cap] Jane. Financial assets and liabilities are listed and include stock,
            cash on hand, and outstanding loans/bills/interest due. Notations at the top of the
            appraisal indicate that I[saac] J. Parkins was the estate appraiser. Additionally,
            notations post-dating the creation of the document indicate that Parkins was Warden C.
            Parkins Jr.'s great-grandfather. This information is correct based on documentary
            evidence. A note also suggests that I. J. Parkins was Samuel Harnsberger's grandson (by
            marriage). Given that Parkins was married to Samuel Harnsberger's daughter Christine,
            Parkins would have been Harnsberger's son-in-law.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement audience="internal" id="aspace_071eabfb9ca89281031eb3ff80ba056b">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>The collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <originalsloc audience="internal" id="aspace_4b1f4da1071a94190303e8895da6d022">
         <head>Location of Originals</head>
         <p>The Nimrod Warden copybook is retained by the owner, a Warden family descendant. The
            Harnsberger appraisal and sale bill were also retained by the owner at the time of
            digitization by Special Collections. All three items were then consigned by Jeffrey
            Evans &amp; Associates for his 37th Semi-Annual Americana &amp; Fine Antiques Auction
            featuring Virginia and the South (November 16, 2019). Once it was discovered that the
            Nimrod Warden ledger was not an authentic account of Warden's business dealings, but
            actually an exact transcription of William Jackson's 1801 <emph render="italic"
               >Book-Keeping in the True Italian Form of Debtor and Creditor by Way of Double
               Entry;...</emph>, the ledger was pulled from the auction and returned to the owner.
            JMU Special Collections acquired the Harnsberger appraisal and sale bill at the
            aforementioned auction and incorporated them into this collection.</p>
      </originalsloc>
      <relatedmaterial id="aspace_e4d4cdf6568c97fad9d031eb9f895053">
         <head>Related Materials</head>
         <p>Jackson, William. <emph render="italic">Book-Keeping, in the True Italian Form of Debtor
               and Creditor by Way of Double Entry: Or, Practical Book-Keeping, Exemplified From the
               Precepts of the Late Ingenious D. Dowling ... With the Addition of Computations in
               Exchange, and Tables Shewing the Proportion That the Weights and Measures of the
               Principal Cities in Europe Bear to Each Other</emph>. Philadephia: John Bioren,
            1801.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <bibliography id="aspace_1140d4d9512d2406ad970347f2b34b4b">
         <head>Bibliography</head>
         <p>"United States Census (Slave Schedule), 1850 ," database with images, FamilySearch
            (https://familysearch.org/ark:/61903/3:1:S3HY-6X3W-S9J?cc=1420440&amp;wc=MJC6-92Q%3A1042937501%2C1042951501%2C1042951502
            : 22 May 2014), Virginia &gt; Augusta &gt; Augusta county &gt; image 28-29 of 61; citing
            NARA microfilm publication M432 (Washington, D.C.: National Archives and Records
            Administration, n.d.).</p>
         <p>Department of Historic Resources. "Willow Spout," Marker A-99, 1992.</p>
      </bibliography>
      <controlaccess>
         <head>Index Terms</head>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">Copybooks -- West Virginia -- Hardy County -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Estate sales -- West Virginia -- Hardy County --
               Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Estate sales -- Virginia -- Augusta County -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Augusta County (Va.) -- Genealogy -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Virginia -- History, Local -- 19th century -- Sources</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">West Virginia -- History, Local -- 19th century --
               Sources</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">Copybooks</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Estate inventories</genreform>
            <genreform source="aat">Estate records</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <dsc>
         <c01 id="aspace_89cb547fd132696b91de9b0753336028" level="item">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Nimrod Warden Copybook, <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce"
                     normal="1806-01-24/1806-01-24" type="inclusive">January 24, 1806</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_aca1866ae87603032a53fa7a036ce612" label="Box:Folder"
                  type="Digital-materials">SC0201-SET-001</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_00fdfb67d580550781b1f64333cea3cb" level="item">
            <did>
               <unittitle>A List of the Property Appraised of the Estate of Samuel Harnsberger,
                     <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1857-12-26/1857-12-26"
                     type="inclusive">December 26, 1857</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_737cc3fc6731c96d2564309939188cfa" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
                  >1</container>
               <container id="aspace_6ea04d62bccda26d48d3985b175531ca"
                  parent="aspace_737cc3fc6731c96d2564309939188cfa" type="folder">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_018944b89f71c4ba76a43df2d29e1045" label="Box:Folder"
                  type="Digital-materials">SC0201-SET-001</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_f37d74cf4c1fdc170e860e4449eeab8c" level="item">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Mother's [Lucinda VanNort Warden] Sale Bill, <unitdate
                     calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1880-11-05/1880-11-05" type="inclusive"
                     >November 5, 1880</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_5d65350927beb87835b2481544a657fa" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
                  >1</container>
               <container id="aspace_8d9d87e199bb1b22d360ef3aab1ab379"
                  parent="aspace_5d65350927beb87835b2481544a657fa" type="folder">2</container>
               <container id="aspace_dc31d2a330beeb23205dd236d5dfdee6" label="Box:Folder"
                  type="Digital-materials">SC0201-SET-001</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
