<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xml">
<!NOTATION aspx SYSTEM "">
<!ENTITY Contents SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/manuscripts/4044contents.pdf" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Payroll SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_08_02_07111903.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image1 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_04_38_09191906.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image2 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_06_10_09201906.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image3 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_06_21_10011900.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image4 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_07_02_09201906.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image5 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_07_05_11041902.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image6 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_07_08_09221906.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image7 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_07_12_08251900.jpg" NDATA aspx>
<!ENTITY Image8 SYSTEM "http://www.lib.jmu.edu/special/images/4044McHoneHouck/M4044_07_17_04001906.jpg" NDATA aspx>
]><ead id="vihart00100">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::vihart00100:: McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records, 1870-1913)//EN" "vihart00100.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records, <date>1870-1913</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records
<num type="collectionnumber">4044
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Heather Browne, <date>8/27/2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>Guide to the McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records, <date>1870-1913</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="SC#">4044
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Chris Bolgiano, Katherine Carr, Tracy Harter, Andrea Hillebrenner, Maggie Keller, Julia Merkel, Erica Morrison, Jodie Tsou, and Sarah Vaughan
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1870-1913
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection Number SC# " encodinganalog="099$a">4044
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">6 record storage boxes, 1 Hollinger box, and 1 oversize flat box; 8.5 linear feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection consists of 8.5 linear feet of records documenting the operations of the Houck Tannery and the J.P. Houck Store in Harrisonburg, Virginia, from 1870-1913, chiefly from 1890 to 1913.  The collection contains:  account ledgers, registries, correspondence, and financial and transportation documents that record this turn of the century industry.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Houck Tannery, Harrisonburg, Va.
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>None.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>None.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>McHone Brothers (LLC) Collection of Houck Tannery Records, 1870-1913, SC# 4044, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Records were donated by the present building owner, McHone Brothers, LLC, in 2000.  The collection was discovered in the late 1990s during renovations to the Houck Building on Court Square (71 South Main) in downtown Harrisonburg, the former offices of the Houck Tannery and store.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Notes
</head>
<p>The collection was received on several long strands of heavy gauge wire totaling twenty linear feet which presented some difficulty due to their great weight and inherent instability.  Documents had been punched onto the wire in chronological order which facilitated their arrangement but left edges exposed to a century's accumulation of grime and damage by pests.  As a practical matter rather than an ideal conservation practice, each article was wiped with an untreated flannel dust cloth rather than vacuumed under mesh to encourage the exposed and embrittled corners of documents to crumble away from their much cleaner cores.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Joseph P. Houck was born on April 4, 1839, in Allentown, Pennsylvania. In the spring of 1866 he went to work for Shenandoah Iron Works in Page County, Virginia. He was successful in the business for fourteen years. Around 1880, Houck and his family moved to Harrisonburg, Virginia, as he has significant business interests there. He had bought a controlling share of the Harrisonburg Steam Tannery in 1878, which soon was renamed Houck Tannery. In 1879 he opened the Houck Store near Court Square which sold leather goods in addition to household goods and furnishings. Houck was a prominent member of the community, a member of the Rockingham Union Lodge, and secretary and treasurer of Valley Telephone. He died on June 16, 1908. Both the Tannery and the Store were passed on to his son, Joe (J.T.). The younger Houck sold the store to William B. Dutrow in 1913, but continued to own and operate the tannery until its close in the 1920s. 
</p>
<p>The tannery which came to be known as the Houck Tannery has a long history prior to its ownership by J.P. Houck. Local historian John Wayland noted in his 1949 book <title render="italic">Historic Harrisonburg</title> that sources indicate that as far back as 1826, Joseph Cline had <title render="doublequote">carried on the tanyard now owned by Lowenback,</title> and that George Conrad had later purchased Cline's <title render="doublequote">farm and tanyard in town,</title> although the date of that sale is not provided. Nonetheless, in 1871 J.A. Loewenbach owned and operated the tannery. That year, he constructed a new building for providing steam power, and in 1872 he had run a pipe from an unidentified spring in town to the tannery. 
</p>
<p>By 1858 ownership of the tannery was transferred to J.P. Houck. Although several tanneries operated in Rockingham County, Houck's was the largest. An 1880 census reports a capital investment of $75,000 and thirty employees in the tannery. The industry also supported significant numbers of workers who supplied and transported raw materials to the factory. A spur was laid from the Chesapeake and Western Railroad directly to the tannery warehouse to facilitate the tonnage of bark required for the manufacture of leather. In 1889 the tannery boasted a well that ran six hundred feet deep. In addition, the tannery's powerful steam plant is credited with being the first provider of electricity in Harrisonburg. The city contracted with Houck in 1890 to power its street lights prior to the formation of the Harrisonburg Electric Commission. The factory ceased operation in the 1920s, and its 120 foot smokestack was demolished in 1929. A municipal parking deck now stands on the site. The sole remaining structure housed Whitesel-Sinton farm equipment in the 1930s, the armory until the 1950s, and the police department until its demolition in the early 1970s. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection consists of 8.5 linear feet of records that document the daily purchases and sale of the Houck Tannery and the J.P. Houck Store in Harrisonburg, Virginia, from 1870-1913, chiefly from 1890-1913. The collection is arranged into five series: Account Ledgers and Registries, Communication, Financial Documents, Distribution/Transportation Documents, Images and J.P. Houck store. The first four series deal primarily with the Tannery; materials relating to the Store are housed in series five. References to the Tannery may be abbreviated with JPHTC, while the Houck Store may be abbreviated JPHS.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged in five series:
</p>
<p>I.	Account Ledgers and Registries, 1870-1895
</p>
<p>II.	Communication, 1900-1912
</p>
<p>III.	Financial Documents, 1891-1912
</p>
<p>IV.	Distribution/Transportation Documents, 1893-1913
</p>
<p>V.	J.P. Houck Store, 1898-1912
</p>
<p> Items within each series are arranged alphabetically by topic or locality, then chronologically. Original pagination retained. 
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Barb, Mia, comp. 1991. <title render="italic">Tanbark Industry in the Shenandoah Valley. </title>Oral History Interviews, SdArch 4. Carrier Library, Special Collections, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va. 
</bibref>
<bibref>Boligano, Chris. 1999. <title render="doublequote">Tanbark Harvesting as an Economic and Environmental Factor in Appalachia.</title> [S.I.:s.n.], 1999. Presented at [the] Shenandoah Valley Regional Studies Seminar, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va., January 22, 1999. 
</bibref>
<bibref>Coakley, Sherry L. 1991. <title render="doublequote">The Old Tannery.</title> Harrisonburg Rockingham Historical Society Newsletter, 13(1): 1-2.
</bibref>
<bibref><title render="doublequote">History of Rockingham County - Houck Tannery.</title> <title render="italic">Harrisonburg Daily News Record</title>, 28 February 1959.
</bibref>
<bibref>Lathrop, J.M. <title render="italic">An Atlas of Shenandoah and Page Counties, Virginia; from actual surveys by J.M. Lathrop and B.N. Griffing</title>. Strasburg, Va.: GP Hammond Pub., 1991. Originally published as: Philadelphia, Pa.: D.J. Lake and Co., 1885.
</bibref>
<bibref><title render="doublequote">Mr. Dutrow's 20th Anniversary.</title> <title render="italic">Harrisonburg Daily News</title>, 11 March 1908.
</bibref>
<bibref>Price, C.G. Sr. <title render="doublequote">My Recollections of Harrisonburg at the turn of the century</title>. <title render="italic">Rockingham Recorder</title> III:1, April 1979.
</bibref>
<bibref><title render="doublequote">Dutrow Buys Houck Store.</title>  <title render="italic">Daily News Record</title>, 11 July 1913. [original newspaper housed in Special Collections at Bridgewater College, Bridgewater, Va.]
</bibref>
<bibref>Suter, Scott Hamilton, and Cheryl Lyon. <title render="italic">Images of America: Harrisonburg</title>. Chicago: Arcadia Press, 2003. 
</bibref>
<bibref>Suter, Scott Hamilton, and Cheryl Lyon. <title render="italic">Places, Faces, and Traces: Historical Photographs of Harrisonburg and Rockingham County</title>. Dayton, Va.: Silver Lake Mill, 2005. 
</bibref>
<bibref>Wayland, John W. <title render="italic">Historic Harrisonburg</title>.  Staunton, Va.: McClure Print. Co., 1949 [esp. pages 11, 130, 243 and 239.]
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>West Virginia Pulp and Paper Company Logging Photographs, 1927-1931. SC# 3037, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle><extref entityref="Contents">Itemized Contents List</extref>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series I"><emph render="bold">Account Ledgers and Registries,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1870-1895</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>consists of a bound register (1870-1884), account ledger, and check stub registry. The register lists names alphabetically by race, date registered, and age. Initially presumed to have been an employee register, many of the names listed were prominent local citizens and/or businessmen who were not in the employ of the tannery; therefore it is likely that this was an unofficial voter register that somehow came to be housed in the same building as the tannery records, and may in fact have had nothing to do with the tannery itself. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series II"><emph render="bold">Communication,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1900-1912</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>includes business and payroll correspondence, telegrams and telegraphs, arranged alphabetically by topic, then chronologically. Several of the items in payroll correspondence are undated handwritten notes from employees or contract laborers, requesting that their pay be sent home with another individual. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series III"><emph render="bold">Financial Documents,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1891-1912</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>is largely composed of receipts and paperwork regrading transactions and regular operating expenses, arranged alphabetically by topic, then chronologically. Topics include cash accounts, expense accounts, and <extref entityref="Payroll">payroll information</extref> for Brandiwine [Brandywine], W.V., insurance and utility payments, tax and legal issues, cancelled checks, tannery receipts and vouchers, money orders (from Southern Express and Adams Express) and Houck Store receipts. Oversized materials that have been placed in an oversize box are noted in the <extref entityref="Contents">contents list.</extref>
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series IV"><emph render="bold">Distribution and Transportation Documents,</emph>
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1893-1913</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>constitutes the bulk of the collection and represents regular transactions that occurred during production at the Tannery. These are further divided into eight subseries, based on transaction type. These subseries are arranged alphabetically by location or railway, then chronologically. Descriptions of the subseries are as follows:
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Freight Bills and Receipts</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are 4.5" x 8.5" items arranged alphabetically by railroad [B and O, C and W, Southern Railway Co., and Valley Railroad] and then chronologically.  They record shipments of bark and other materials from various locations along the train lines to the Tannery.  The documents show the Tannery as consignee, car initials and/or number, item[s] shipped, weight and cost. <extref entityref="Image1">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Receipts for Hauling Chestnut Oak Bark by Train Load</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are 3" x 5.5" items arranged by locality, then chronologically. These were issued in Harrisonburg upon receipt of load, and show that the Tannery received a load of chestnut oak bark from a particular location, provide weight of the load and amount paid to a particular business. Broadway, Edinburg [Edenburg], Mount Jackson, and Stokesville are prominent, and are in separate folders. <extref entityref="Image2">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Receipts for Hauling Chestnut Oak Bark by Wagon Weight</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>were issued at Edinburg and Harrisonburg, respectively, and are chronologically arranged receipts paid to individuals for wagon loads of chestnut bark. Those issued at Edinburg at light blue 2.5" x 5.25" receipts paid by Jas. Bowman. <extref entityref="Image3">Image</extref> Those issued at Harrisonburg are 3.75" x 5.75" receipts paid by J.T. Tracy, R.P. Northrup, and others. <extref entityref="Image4">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Receipts for Hauling Chestnut Oak Extract</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are 2.75" x 5.75" receipts issued at Brandywine [Brandiwine], W.V., and are arranged chronologically. These were paid by the Tannery to individuals for hauling a certain number of barrels and poundage of chestnut oak extract. <extref entityref="Image5">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Receipts for Hauling Corn, Hay, etc.</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>were issued in Harrisonburg and are a small number of odd receipts similar to those used for hauling chestnut oak bark. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Reports of Bark Cars Unloaded</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are 8.5" x 7" sheets showing weekly totals for train cars unloaded, including initials of train car, car number, origin of the shipment, shippers name, and net weight. <extref entityref="Image6">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Reports of Wagon Bark Received</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are legal sized documents arranged by location received, then chronologically. These sheets record weight and amount paid for bark delivered by wagon per day over the course of several days. Broadway, Edinburg, and Stokesvile are prominent, and are in separate folders. <extref entityref="Image7">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries"> 
	<did>
	<unittitle><emph render="bold">Time Reports</emph>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>are legal sized document arranged by location, then chronologically. These pages record the number of teams sent from a location per day, the number of hours the team worked per day, subtotals per week, and totals per month, multiplied by cost per day. Locations primarily represented are Big River, Briery Branch, Little River, Loose Tract, and Stokesville. <extref entityref="Image8">Image</extref>
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series"> 
<did>
<unittitle label="Series V"><emph render="bold">J.P. Houck Store,</emph> 
<unitdate type="inclusive"><emph render="bold">1898-1912</emph>
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>consists of materials that can be attributed specifically to transactions pertaining to the J.P. Houck Store, such as bills of lading for wholesale goods, customer charges, and freight and shipping receipts.  These are arranged topically, then chronologically.  The bulk of this series contains bills of lading for goods shipped to the Store [non-Virginia bills of lading], and bills of lading for goods shipped from the Houck Store to other locations in Virginia [Virginia bills of lading].  These are arranged by railway/company.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
