<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vihart00094">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft"
    scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
    repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHarT">PUBLIC "-//James Madison University::Carrier
      Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViHarT::00094:: Liskey Collection of Heavner Family
      Papers, 1791-1967)//EN" "vihart00094.xml" </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, 1791-1967: <num>SC
            5006</num></titleproper>
        <author>Heather Browne, March 2008</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Heather Browne, <date
          era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>English</langusage>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers,
        1791-1967</titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          5006</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, James Madison University </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, James Madison
        University </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, </unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
        normal="1791/1967">1791-1967 </unitdate>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 5006 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.44 linear Feet; 1 Hollinger box</physdesc>

      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English </language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract"> The Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, 1791-1967,
        consists of one Hollinger box (.44 linear feet) of personal correspondence, business and
        personal financial records and various other items pertaining to the William Heavner family,
        documented through the maternal side: William Heavner, Evaline Heavner Aubrey, Dorcas Aubrey
        Breneman (also spelled Brenneman), and Mae Breneman Liskey. Other names represented are
        Hughes, Brake, Dove, Hess, and Trumbo, among others. The collection is arranged
        chronologically in four series: Richard Hughes Estate Papers, Correspondence, Financial
        Papers, and General Miscellany. </abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Multiple generations of the Heavner family
      </origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions </head>
        <p>Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
          privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before
          visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
          collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collection Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu). </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>[Identification of Item], The Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, 1791-1967, SC
          5006, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg,
          VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information </head>
        <p>Gift of Leon and Judy Liskey, 2007. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist>
        <head>Provenance </head>
        <p>The collection was found in the 18th Century home of the donors. </p>
      </custodhist>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information </head>
      <p>The Heavner family has a long and rich history in the Shenandoah Valley. William Heavner
        (1787-1866) was born in present day Pendleton County, West Virginia to Joseph and Elizabeth
        Hevinor. William married Joanna Custer (1792-1862) in 1814, and shortly thereafter purchased
        650 acres in the area now known as Fulks Run. The couple raised seven children: Wells,
        Delilah, Elizabeth, William Jr., Harvey, Julian (Julie Anne), and Evaline. In addition to
        farming, William operated a blacksmith shop on the family property. Heavner also served as
        executor of the estate of Richard Hughes, of whom little is known. Why Heavner was acting as
        executor on behalf of Hughes is unclear. Nonetheless, papers relating to Richard Hughes'
        estate remained in the custody of Heavner after Hughes' death. </p>
      <p>Of the Heavner children, only three lived past the age of fifty: Wells (78), Julian (53)
        and Evaline (84). Wells (1815-1893) married Elizabeth Hess (1822-1875) around 1851, and with
        Elizabeth's mother Catherine, moved to Champaign County, Ohio, where Elizabeth's siblings
        had settled. They maintained contact with the Heavner family through correspondence, as over
        the years they moved further west. Julian (1824-1877) married Michael Brake in 1853 and
        settled in Hardy County. Evaline (1830-1914), the youngest daughter of William and Joanna,
        would become the matriarch of the Heavner estate. </p>
      <p>Evaline married George W. Aubrey of Luney's Creek in what is now Hardy County, West
        Virginia in 1859. During the Civil War, George Aubrey joined the Union Army. He was captured
        in September 1861 and was incarcerated at Libby Prison in Richmond, Virginia, where he died
        in 1862. During that time, Evaline and her infant son, William Casper, moved back to the
        family home in Brocks Gap, where she gave birth to their daughter Dorcas. Evaline suffered
        several other losses that year: her brother, William Jr., died serving in the Confederate
        Army; her son, William Casper, died shortly thereafter of complications from croup; and she
        then suffered the loss of her mother. With her father in his seventies, Evaline thus took
        charge of the family farm, where she spent the remainder of her life with Dorcas and her
        family. </p>
      <p>Dorcas Aubrey (1861-1946) married Jacob R. Breneman (1872-1953) in 1896. Following their
        honeymoon they moved into the Heavner family home to take over operations for Evaline.
        Breneman also was active in politics as a Democrat and served in the Virginia House of
        Delegates: 1926-1927, 1930-1931, and 1940-1945. Their daughter Mae (1903-1984)later married
        Robert D. Liskey (1903-1967). They were the parents of Mr. Leon Liskey, one of the donors of
        this collection, and are buried, as are the Brenemans, in Woodbine Cemetery in Harrisonburg,
        Virginia. </p>
      <p>For a more detailed genealogical account see Judy Ruleman Liskey's <title
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic"
          xlink:href="">When This You See, Think of Me!</title> and <title
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic"
          xlink:href="">With Pen in Hand: Buttons and Beaux.</title> Both texts provide a history of
        the Heavner family, photographs, and correspondence that supplement this collection. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content </head>
      <p>The Liskey Collection of Heavner Family Papers, 1791-1967, consists of one Hollinger box
        (.44 linear feet) of personal correspondence, business and personal financial records and
        various other items pertaining to the Heavner family. The documents were passed down through
        the matrilineal side of the Heavner family, much like the original Heavner home, where these
        documents were found. Documents were thus passed from William Heavner to his daughter
        Evaline (Heavner) Aubrey, to her daughter Dorcas (Aubrey) Breneman, to her daughter Mae
        (Breneman) Liskey, then to her son, Leon Liskey and his wife Judy. The collection remained
        in the possession of the Liskey family until the bulk of the papers were donated to Special
        Collections in November 2007. Family names of note that are seen throughout the collection
        are Brake, Dove, Hess, and Trumbo, among others. The collection is arranged chronologically
        in four series: Richard Hughes Estate Papers, Correspondence, Financial Papers, and General
        Miscellany. </p>
      <p>Series One, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          render="bold" xlink:href="">the Richard Hughes Estate Papers, 1788-1837,</title> consists
        of three folders of documents regarding Hughes' personal business matters and legal
        transactions involving his estate. William Heavner, acting as executor, retained these
        documents after the estate was settled. Personal papers include the appraisal and bill of
        sale of household possessions, powers of attorney, and court summonses. A folder of Hughes'
        receipts includes general and tax receipts directly related to Hughes' estate. A folder of
        miscellaneous material from Hughes' estate includes agreements and papers concerning land
        and property, as well as various promissory notes and receipts from other individuals such
        as George Dove, Conrad Custer, Solomon Jones, and Henry Overley. </p>
      <p>Series Two, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          render="bold" xlink:href="">Correspondence, 1852-1967,</title> is arranged into four
        subseries, then chronologically. Letters to Evaline Aubrey, the Brenemans (also spelled
        Brenneman) and other members of the Heavner family figure most prominently; the remainder
        are miscellaneous letters, some with unknown senders and recipients. </p>
      <p>Letters to Evaline Aubrey span from 1868 until 1913. In addition to correspondence from
        family and friends, many of the letters addressed to her are from M.P. Trumbo and concern
        family property in Illinois, where her brother Wells had settled. Legal and estate issues
        are also represented. </p>
      <p>Letters to and from J.R. Breneman, et al, date from 1904 until 1967, and primarily concern
        business interests; although family letters are also present. Several post cards are
        addressed to his daughter Mae from a trip Breneman took out West. Letters to his wife Dorcas
        are also filed here. </p>
      <p>Correspondence of the Heavner family, 1852-1896, includes letters to William Heavner Sr.,
        as well as a small number to and from Wells Heavner. Correspondence relating to Well's
        mother in law Catherine Hess, brother in law Nathan Hess, and others are also filed here
        chronologically. </p>
      <p>Miscellaneous correspondence, 1861-1937, is a small series of letters from individuals who
        are either not directly related to the Heavners, or the letters are unsigned. </p>
      <p>Series Three, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          render="bold" xlink:href="">Financial Papers, 1820-1947,</title> are arranged topically as
        promissory notes, property documents, general receipts, tax receipts, and other financial
        documents, then chronologically. Promissory notes are small sheets or slips of paper that
        clearly state "I Promise to Pay" or "I bind myself to" for a specific amount of money to a
        specific person. Property documents pertain to ownership, transfer, and inheritance of
        property. These include land agreements, notice of land for sale, and the estate division of
        William Heavner Sr., to the Brake and Aubrey families. General receipts cover a wide range
        of household purchases and expenditures. Tax receipts largely represent personal property
        taxes paid for the family property in Rockingham County, as well as property owned in La
        Salle County, Illinois, which had passed to Evaline from her brother Wells' family. Of
        particular interest are receipts for taxes paid during the Civil War. Miscellaneous
        financial documents range in content from a note regarding a young boy's indentured service
        in 1847, an 1852 toll road account, and a 1907 probate inventory of Michael S. Wine's
        estate, with Breneman acting as administrator. </p>
      <p>Series Four, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          render="bold" xlink:href="">General Miscellany, 1864-1925, n.d.</title> consists of a wide
        array of items, such as greeting cards and ephemera, print material, recipes and home
        remedies, weaving patterns and fabric squares. Items of note are Mae Breneman's 1925
        Shenandoah College graduation announcement, and undated obituaries for Lizzie E. Wittig and
        Ruby Heavner. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement </head>
      <p>This collection is arranged in four series: I. Richard Hughes Estate Papers, 1788-1837 II.
        Correspondence, 1852-1967 III. Financial Papers, 1820-1947 IV. General Miscellany,
        1864-1925, n.d. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data </head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography </head>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Brock,
          Robert L. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1581532"
              ><title xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">47 Pioneer Families of
                Rockingham County, Virginia.</title></extref> Baltimore: Gateway Press, 1997. </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">
          <extref xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~varockin/HRHS/cem/woodbine09_2.htm">
            <title xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Harrisonburg Rockingham
              Historical Society, Rockingham County Tombstones by Cemetery, Woodbine
              Cemetery.</title>
          </extref>
        </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Liskey,
          Judy Ruleman. <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b2007302"
              ><title xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Brocks Gap Missives:
              Personal Letters to a Young Lady in the Nineteenth Century, 1878 &amp; 1879,
              1880.</title></extref> Fulks Run (Va.): Judy Ruleman Liskey, [19--?] </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">_____.
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b2007334"><title
              xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Brocks Gap Missives: Personal
              Letters to a Young Lady in the Nineteenth Century, 1881, 1882.</title></extref> Fulks
          Run (Va.): Judy Ruleman Liskey, [19--?] </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">_____.
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1317156"><title
              xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">My Sweet Valley Home: Rockingham
              County, Virginia, Personal Correspondence from October 16, 1876 to January 16,
              1888.</title></extref> [Fulks Run Va.: J. R. Liskey], 1991. </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">_____.
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b1273324"><title
              xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">When This You See, Think of
              Me!</title></extref> [S.I.:s.n.], c1990. </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">_____.
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://leo.jmu.edu/record=b2007296"><title
              xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">With Pen in Hand: Buttons and
              Beaux.</title></extref> [S.I.]:Judy Ruleman Liskey, c2006. </bibref></p>
        <p><bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">
          <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://virginiageneralassembly.gov">
            <title xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Virginia General
              Assembly.</title>
          </extref>
        </bibref></p>
      </bibliography>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unitid>Series 1</unitid>
          <unittitle>Richard Hughes Estate Papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Personal</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1788/1837">1788-1837 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">1 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Receipts of Richard Hughes</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1788/1831">1788-1831 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1791/1830">1791-1830 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">3 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unitid>Series 2</unitid>
          <unittitle label="Series II">Correspondence </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Evaline Aubrey</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1868/1913">1868-1913 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">4 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.R. Breneman, et al</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1904/1967">1904-1967 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">5 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Heavner Family</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1852/1896">1852-1896 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">6 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1861/1908">1861-1908 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">7 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unitid>Series 3</unitid>
          <unittitle label="Series III">Financial Papers </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Promissory Notes</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1853/1906">1853-1906 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">8 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Property Documents</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1822/1911">1822-1911 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">9 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Receipts: </unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>General</unittitle>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1832/1930">1832-1930 </unitdate>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">10 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Tax Receipts</unittitle>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1854/1909">1854-1909 </unitdate>
              <container label="Folder" type="folder">11 </container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Financial Documents</unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1820/1947">1820-1947 </unitdate>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">12 </container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unitid>Series 4</unitid>
          <unittitle label="Series IV">General Miscellany</unittitle>
          <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="1864/1925"
            certainty="approximate">1864-1925, n.d. </unitdate>
          <container label="Folder" type="folder">13 </container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insert 1: Cards and Ephemera </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insert 2: Print Materials </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insert 3: Recipes and Home Remedies </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insert 4: Weaving Patterns </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insert 5: Fabric </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
