<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
  <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="completed"
    langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00230.xml"
      >vihart00230</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Kathryn Eye Papers, 1920-1991: <num>SC 0231</num></titleproper>
        <author>Tiffany Cole, May 2017</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2017 By JMU Libraries. All rights
          reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
            Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and hand encoding by Tiffany Cole
        on <date>2017-05-30 15:10:16 -0400</date>.</creation>
      <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper> A Guide to the Kathryn Eye Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1920-1991</date>
      </titleproper>
      <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SC
          0231</num>
      </subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2017</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Tiffany Cole, May 2017</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <langmaterial>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <repository>
        <corpname>Special Collections, James Madison University</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle>Kathryn Eye Papers, </unittitle>
      <origination label="Creator">
        <persname source="local">Eye, Kathryn, 1909-1979</persname>
      </origination>
      <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0231</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1.14 cubic feet; 3 boxes</physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1920/1991" type="inclusive">1920-1991</unitdate>
      <abstract id="aspace_dc6abb5b677a2f6a7661dd6cba76e988">The Kathryn Eye Papers, 1920-1991,
        contain the papers of Kathryn Eye, local resident and missionary to the Belgian Congo.
        Materials document Eye's life, missionary work, and exhibit of her art collection at the
        Madison Art Collection and include correspondence, ephemera and stamps, and a
        scrapbook.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="aspace_9642e696f552b8d80a6bd2aab351a987">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and
          privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before
          visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this
          collection.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict id="aspace_70c29678ca1df133ecf27e21c037a1f0">
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>The copyright interests in this collection have been transferred to the James Madison
          University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special
          Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite id="aspace_8c4972ccf1307627a15d7ff62f68e680">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], Kathryn Eye Papers, 1920-1991, SC 0231,
          Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo id="aspace_9ff2d2256614c3bd87360423022027a8">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was transferred from Kate Stevens, Director of the Madison Art
          Collection, on October 3, 2013.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist id="aspace_6e26feab86b30c21726ed63aed9ba319">
        <head>Provenance</head>
        <p>The materials were first donated in 1990 by Marie Garnett, friend of Kathryn Eye, to Dr.
          Joanne Gabbin, then Director of the James Madison University Honors Program. After
          transfer to the Madison Art Collection, items from this collection were processed by
          Madison Art Collection staff. All materials were given an accession number (still present
          on the back of most documents) and delivered to Special Collections. It is likely the
          materials were labeled in original order; however, to increase their discoverability, the
          correspondence was rearranged in chronological order. The Madison Art Collection accession
          numbers allow the original order to be ascertained if necessary.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <processinfo id="aspace_82841d5264605d4619742ff9861ac3c4">
        <head>Processing Information</head>
        <p>The scrapbook was disbound and laid open with acid-free paper interleaved between the
          pages. Loose items were placed in envelopes and placed in their original location.</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="aspace_596999df0ac58f0f791f8c1ae957926f">
      <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
      <p>Kathryn Eye was born February 9, 1909 in West Virginia to William D. Eye, a Methodist
        reverend, and Leila Lupton Eye. She appears to have attended the Shenandoah Collegiate
        Institute in Dayton, Virginia and Blackstone College in Blackstone, Virginia; however, the
        exact dates of her attendance are unknown. Miss Eye received a Bachelor of Arts degree from
        Emory &amp; Henry College in 1931 and a Bachelor of Science and Registered Nurse degrees
        from Johns Hopkins University in 1936. She continued to work at Johns Hopkins Hospital as
        the superintendent of surgical and obstetrical nursing until receiving her missionary
        appointment to the Belgian Congo in 1938. She served as a medical, educational, and
        evangelistic missionary in Central Africa for more than two decades.</p>
      <p>Before her arrival in Africa, Eye spent several months training and traveling in Western
        Europe. During her furloughs from missionary work she continued to study medicine at various
        institutions including Vanderbilt University, the Florence Nightingale Hospital in London,
        and the Pasteur Institute in Paris. During Miss Eye's long service in Africa, she was head
        of educational work, director of the evangelistic program, and director of the Methodist
        Hospital. She served four missionary terms in the Congo and was partway through a fifth when
        the tumult of the Congo independence from Belgium led the United States Air Force to
        evacuate her in August 1960. Although Miss Eye anticipated returning to Africa, she never
        did.</p>
      <p>On her return to the United States, Miss Eye served as the Director of Religious Education
        at Asbury Methodist Church in Harrisonburg, Virginia before becoming the pastor at the
        Montague Avenue United Methodist Church in Winchester, Virginia. She spoke and preached in
        various locations from Virginia to Maryland, and even into Tennessee and Pennsylvania. In
        June 1964, Emory &amp; Henry College presented Eye with the Humanities Award for servicing
        the world. She was a life member of the Woman's Missionary Society and was an honrary life
        patron of the Women's Society of Christian Service of the United Methodist Church. Miss Eye
        retired and lived in Rawley Springs, Virginia until her death on November 16, 1979.</p>
      <p>Marie Garnett, the donor and collector of this collection, was a friend and frequent
        correspondent of Kathryn Eye. Garnett was the youngest daughter of Rev. and Mrs. James A.
        Johnson. In 1942, she married Hugh Garnett. She received a Bachelor of Science degree from
        Virginia Tech where she also did graduate work. During the Garnett's residence in New York,
        Marie was active in radio, newspaper, and magazine work. She served as the President of
        Republican Women. The Garnetts lived in Harrisonburg, Virginia and had one son, Stephen Lee
        Garnett.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="aspace_e4670f6dc5f2769a165019c260d03ad7">
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The Kathryn Eye Papers, 1920-1991, contain the papers of Kathryn Eye, local resident and
        missionary to the Belgian Congo. Materials document Eye's life, missionary work, and the
        exhibit of her art collection at the Madison Art Collection and include correspondence,
        ephemera and stamps, and a scrapbook. This collection is arranged into four series: 1.
        Correspondence, 1920-1975; Artifact Information, 1959-1991; Scrapbooks and Ephemera,
        1924-1988; and Series 4: Oversize, 1924-1959.</p>
      <p>Series 1: Correspondence, 1920-1975, contains letters primarily documenting Miss Eye's
        service in the Belgian Congo. Also included in this series are photographs attached to
        letters, Christmas cards, and envelopes. The letters are from Miss Eye to family and
        friends, letters received by Miss. Eye, and letters from Congolese people to friends of Miss
        Eye. The majority of the letters are written as a serialized newsletter describing the
        activities of Miss Eye in the Congo to her friends and family. She would send the letter to
        one individual with instructions detailing how the letter should progress. The letters are a
        mix of typed and handwritten correspondence with many including sketches. Subjects discussed
        include holiday celebrations, church services, interactions between natives and whites, food
        and customs, and political conflict. Eye describes the uncertainty that is facing the Congo
        in a letter dated January 23, 1960: "The future seems rather uncertain. As we contrast the
        past with the present confusion and conflict we wonder if we shall really be privileged to
        serve the Lord, much longer in this once favored colony….Our prayers would be especially
        toward the little children growing up in the midst of such disturbance and hatred as has
        been in evidence in the inter-tribal warfares."</p>
      <p>Of note is a Christmas card and photograph dated September 1959 of Kathryn Eye holding an
        African baby. The card claims that the photo is of Kathryn Eye and her nephew, shortly after
        her return from the Congo; however, Kathryn is clearly in the Congo and holding a baby of
        African descent. It is unclear if the wrong photo was included with the card or the note
        writer was mistaken.</p>
      <p>Several letters from American political dignitaries to Marie Garnett and Kathryn Eye are
        included. Correspondents include Pat Nixon, Dwight Eisenhower, and John F. Kennedy. Of note
        is a letter from President Dwight Eisenhower, dated October 28, 1960, thanking Kathryn Eye
        for an ivory elephant she gifted to Eisenhower during a recent visit to Staunton. Miss Eye
        presented the trinket to the President as a token of gratitude for the part the United
        States Air Force played in rescuing her from the unrest in the Congo.</p>
      <p>Series 2: Artifact Information, 1959-1991, contains information regarding the artifacts
        collected in the Belgian Congo by Miss Eye and the related exhibit at the Madison Art
        Collection. Notable items in this series include a document, written by Kathryn Eye, with
        photos and descriptions of various African artifacts. Also included is an art appraisal and
        an article on the Maryland Museum of African Art. The appraiser of the Kathryn Eye
        artifacts, Dr. Kwaku Ofori-Ansa, is mentioned in the aforementioned article.</p>
      <p>Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1924-1988, contains a scrapbook documenting Miss Eye's
        early life, her extensive stamp collection with a related 1959 issue of <emph
          render="italic">Life</emph> magazine, photographs of her friends and family, and various
        papers relating to her life and work for the Methodist Church. A single page from a
        scrapbook (not in the collection) is included and housed in an Oversize box with the <emph
          render="italic">Life</emph> magazine and Kathryn Eye's scrapbook.</p>
      <p>Kathryn Eye's stamp collection contains over 500 stamps from around the world. Many of
        these stamps were sorted by image in plastic bags when received by Special Collections.
        These stamps were removed from the plastic bags and placed in acid-free envelopes. Stamps
        and notes were kept separated in the same manner as received. Also in this series is a
        November 1959 issue of <emph render="italic">Life</emph> magazine featuring an article on
        international stamps. Many of the stamps mentioned in the article were collected by Kathryn
        Eye. Due to the disparate nature and sheer quantity of the stamps, no attempt has been made
        to assign a date range to those materials.</p>
      <p>The scrapbook is another notable item in this series. The scrapbook documents Kathryn Eye's
        life during her time at the Shenandoah College Institute in Dayton, Virginia and Blackstone
        College in Blackstone, Virginia. Included in the scrapbook are programs and souvenirs from
        various events she attended, cards from friends with holiday imagery, and photographs. Items
        of note are dried flowers and locks of hair.</p>
      <p>Other items include coins and paper currency from the Belgian Congo and photographs
        depicting Kathryn Eye, her friends and family, the Statue of Liberty, and the gardens of
        Versailles. Most of the photographs include handwritten descriptions of the subjects or
        scenes depicted. Photographs originally attached to correspondences were not removed; these
        can be found throughout Series 1: Correspondence.</p>
      <p>Series 4: Oversize, 1924-1959, consists of one box of oversize materials that do not fit
        within standard Hollinger boxes. Items include Kathryn Eye's scrapbook and one folder
        containing an issue of Life magazine and an oversize scrapbook page.Because the Oversize
        series consists of materials that have been physically removed from their intellectual
        arrangement within the existing series arrangement, the Oversize series functions only as a
        container list. The associated folder titles are each represented elsewhere in the
        collection.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement id="aspace_85a5a7189b9637359a9c6b417011fab3">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in 4 series:</p>
      <p>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>Series 1: Correspondence, 1920-1975</item>
          <item>Series 2: Artifact Information, 1959-1991</item>
          <item>Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1924-1988</item>
          <item>Series 4: Oversize, 1924-1959</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>All series are arranged chronologically. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <separatedmaterial id="aspace_620ee26f6139e23d62a92cb7d66075da">
      <head>Separated Material</head>
      <p>The Madison Art Collection retains all artifacts donated by Marie Garnett and collected by
        Kathryn Eye. Artifacts include weaponry, jewelry, sculpture, and paintings, and can be
        viewed at the Lisanby Museum at James Madison University. A copy of Richard K. MacMasters'
          <emph render="italic">Our Strong Heritage, 1778-1988: Asbury United Methodist Church,
          Harrisonburg Virginia</emph> (1988) was removed from the collection, cataloged, and placed
        in Special Collections' rare book collection. A small portion of the book related to Kathryn
        Eye is photocopied and contained within Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera.</p>
    </separatedmaterial>
    <bibliography id="aspace_142e832b8e452495bc96d89c860cf623">
      <head>Bibliography</head>
      <p>"Find A Grave Index," database, <emph render="italic">FamilySearch</emph>
        (https://familysearch.org/ark:/61903/1:1:QV2V-BGNZ : 13 December 2015), Kathryn Eye, 1979;
        Burial, Dayton, Rockingham, Virginia, United States of America, Clover Hill United Methodist
        Church Cemetery; citing record ID 67091406,Find a Grave, http://www.findagrave.com.</p>
      <p>Garnett, William E. and Emma Garnett McCoy. <emph render="italic">The Garnetts of Albemarle
          County, Virginia: James Muscoe and Cornelia Wingfield Garnett, Antecedents and
          Descendants</emph>. 1963.</p>
      <p>Obituary for Rev. Kathryn Eye, <emph render="italic">Daily News-Record</emph>, November 17,
        1979.</p>
    </bibliography>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh">Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 --
          Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.
          Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Nixon, Pat, 1912-1993 -- Correspondence</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">James Madison University. Madison Art Collection</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United Methodist Church (U.S.) -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">United Methodist Church (U.S.) -- Virginia -- Winchester</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Blackstone College for Girls</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Missionaries -- Congo (Democratic Republic)</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Art, African</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Stamp collections</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Postage stamps -- History</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Coins -- Congo (Democratic Republic)</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Money -- Congo (Democratic Republic)</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Congo (Democratic Republic) -- History -- 1908-1960</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh">Belgium -- Colonies -- Congo (Democratic Republic) --
          History</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat">Letters (correspondence)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Photographs</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Newspaper clippings</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Scrapbooks</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Appraisals (records)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Magazines (periodicals)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Postage stamps</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Money (objects)</genreform>
        <genreform source="aat">Envelopes</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <c01 id="aspace_961f7fcbf9c76fabd2c320bea118f1c5" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 1: Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1920/1975" type="inclusive"
              >1920-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_d3dee83e8dda71e732ef6935d86cef4c" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1920/1938" type="inclusive"
                >1920-1938</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_a487d86456f230d7b9810bbe8df18054" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_746f16b9bda1b31bc03c66708ea6013c"
              parent="aspace_a487d86456f230d7b9810bbe8df18054" type="folder">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_60feb37fa659d3964c0d6ed3195de368" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1939/1940" type="inclusive"
                >1939-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_84c153d0c3ed2fdbb5133195ee6172d2" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_3872f78e800f5fc83423ecf68a531143"
              parent="aspace_84c153d0c3ed2fdbb5133195ee6172d2" type="folder">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_d77bcee8c4c46ecfa48ee4efc8aaab2b" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1941/1941">1941</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_c01a5d7cf965811d1c337fa8eb5e3b98" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_3251f0c45a59fce3fb8b2fcabeedd5b5"
              parent="aspace_c01a5d7cf965811d1c337fa8eb5e3b98" type="folder">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_1da89ee198e74cec97822944b8dfa28a" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1946/1947" type="inclusive"
                >1946-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_05fbd0bf9162bc2a6e97b5ea293f6f9a" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_7c6c0e2d324ee780741bf10e6f1eca93"
              parent="aspace_05fbd0bf9162bc2a6e97b5ea293f6f9a" type="folder">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_c82bd2ad71faca129a9cdf8e8d47ee1f" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1954/1956" type="inclusive"
                >1954-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_8d7244e1234e4a7c3e2c87d3409dd4fa" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_7b6cebd217131fec54467e421236d36e"
              parent="aspace_8d7244e1234e4a7c3e2c87d3409dd4fa" type="folder">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_97578b4eec9bb413e7b4b75cbbef77bf" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1959/1959">1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_3f9e05a1eac931fd2acfd2cac54cfc76" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_ef6c6ed6cf5e4f7ef5c72b4f091d6b55"
              parent="aspace_3f9e05a1eac931fd2acfd2cac54cfc76" type="folder">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_b4e1551c43f2614655d35b55935fc17b" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1960/1960">1960</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_a44b89e5e667ca5fcfca25bcc15a5803" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_f76c7ac76446754ebdf5c627918a19a8"
              parent="aspace_a44b89e5e667ca5fcfca25bcc15a5803" type="folder">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_03eb8663dd1c2b698e3c2a7407ad3f28" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1960/1961" type="inclusive"
                >1960-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_76aeafe1e09e59df57766f0f0fc426d0" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_dec771f8f4e15bc55bc724e00d86618b"
              parent="aspace_76aeafe1e09e59df57766f0f0fc426d0" type="folder">8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_b78e7a075a6fe4e4303d9fa188f83a51" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1962/1975" type="inclusive"
                >1962-1975</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_3764adadbab64d67a0e198ebfb152c15" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_31dfcde6e9fe08e99a6f7a0f35da0c28"
              parent="aspace_3764adadbab64d67a0e198ebfb152c15" type="folder">9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_2fcd96131e421c7cee9f0cbbb648b8c1" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate normal="1920/1975" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_004d2fc8217b14b73cffedfa1fd7c246" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_c7576b18ae13c18702ffc5d1a24a0844"
              parent="aspace_004d2fc8217b14b73cffedfa1fd7c246" type="folder">10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_1864dfae71dda33fa0445c155f0455e1" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Envelopes, <unitdate normal="1939/1960" type="inclusive">1939-1960,
                undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_9258520f9d9614fbc758b4518125f5b8" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_022df879f4aabf43bbdbb43fb4f7a2ac"
              parent="aspace_9258520f9d9614fbc758b4518125f5b8" type="folder">11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_3bfa2a6115d9c36f3fcc248be042699d" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 2: Artifact Information, <unitdate normal="1959/1991" type="inclusive"
              >1959-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_51d9e99d7ea76b27b10e497cfd865802" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Artifact Description (original and photocopy), <unitdate normal="1959/1959"
                >1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_dbdcab8aa1c60fb34a4b1f0dbfa89f93" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_13718e1d6d172b34ddc32bdc90d93982"
              parent="aspace_dbdcab8aa1c60fb34a4b1f0dbfa89f93" type="folder">12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_c57a6672e7aa80d3be34bcc3555dd0c3" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate normal="1960/1991" type="inclusive">1960, 1991,
                undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_4b02c0940a45715de5d1505df730f34e" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_d8642b4033e4aaada70b4560b7a677d1"
              parent="aspace_4b02c0940a45715de5d1505df730f34e" type="folder">13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_d8e6e5dc17ea07d8d532dcc9355621aa" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Art Appraisal, <unitdate normal="1990/1990">1990</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_faaf0a1a4595aefb80da6c7a124569e0" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_55e9b968862c169084f603a0c2a978b5"
              parent="aspace_faaf0a1a4595aefb80da6c7a124569e0" type="folder">14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_c9c1d3d58898f56f17601a7635593fbd" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Kathryn Eye Art Collection Program, <unitdate normal="1959/1991"
                type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_ec6d08db87270c81e8578023a7e319c0" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_65cee426869d4d7bb50841e863584aa0"
              parent="aspace_ec6d08db87270c81e8578023a7e319c0" type="folder">15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d9d559b61564e36f22caf03cdade00a3" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, <unitdate normal="1924/1988"
              type="inclusive">1924-1988</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_4c6aec31c9bacfdac7be687acdbb0b8d" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook, <unitdate normal="1924/1926" type="inclusive"
              >1924-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_9c1424178348e45fcf14954d60723629" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >OV</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_5cebc0911b786924f60739229a637604" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate normal="1936/1938" type="inclusive">1936, 1938,
                undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_53be03a6e3d1e8aabaabf18ba4daa992" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_dda1dc9e4c8c8c95112584cac95bc97a"
              parent="aspace_53be03a6e3d1e8aabaabf18ba4daa992" type="folder">16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_f3be7e8224db3a1e99a4d87105d181e6" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><emph render="italic">Life</emph> magazine and scrapbook page, <unitdate
                normal="1959/1959">1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_db26101627108bdc7b04bcf4c60ef781" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >OV</container>
            <container id="aspace_1fc27a9073ef98982cea987d14f98a0b"
              parent="aspace_db26101627108bdc7b04bcf4c60ef781" type="folder">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_0364a9d86021f68f211f8eff4c6baa70" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Church Program and Songbook, <unitdate normal="1970/1970">1970,
                undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_f42548ce216f28d01ca16af54e07e9ed" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_7e74474cda9c56b8a1da777f7864213c"
              parent="aspace_f42548ce216f28d01ca16af54e07e9ed" type="folder">17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_6ecb5d216fe2faea33cec94f09cc949e" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Our Strong Heritage, 1778-1988: Asbury United Methodist Church, Harrisonburg
              Virginia (partial photocopy), <unitdate normal="1988/1988">1988</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_adc14d1072a7dca7991c0d2eb7dd9b71" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_fb5771357f442bf96febbfe7a4120e9d"
              parent="aspace_adc14d1072a7dca7991c0d2eb7dd9b71" type="folder">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_bcb0804ec2143976723afa762e3f3886" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Information on Africa, <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_104ae8a09b02d8ec9fb5d8a1b8cf99d6" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >1</container>
            <container id="aspace_52bfcfcba831082860ca6c40a8fd42b0"
              parent="aspace_104ae8a09b02d8ec9fb5d8a1b8cf99d6" type="folder">19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_8aad26974599b55a9b847a9549ee0eb3" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Currency, <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
              >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_5fa8f8b8a9b16922d73198520bac602b" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_a41f76506f17d41aee8de228dc26bea6"
              parent="aspace_5fa8f8b8a9b16922d73198520bac602b" type="folder">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_90a7db51e926cb6b1541ff99d06a9f0d" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Stamps (Folder 1 of 3), <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_630c0625eee75d3592b5ad4846537d06" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_69bea41c8c58903f71597b4cb2436cd3"
              parent="aspace_630c0625eee75d3592b5ad4846537d06" type="folder">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_0d2f86bec7393e278d70f063aff51f19" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Stamps (Folder 2 of 3), <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_ac5f02844ca0e7181bd4607e9c1fdb78" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_5d237c517c3f74949d679b9a53d79a77"
              parent="aspace_ac5f02844ca0e7181bd4607e9c1fdb78" type="folder">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_f642948ab946e67a29f1ac08ae5857fa" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Stamps (Folder 3 of 3), <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_5cb289e210bbe6af1d9735b0dde0a24e" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_4c97d599515a0c1f9ad5f36677a60f51"
              parent="aspace_5cb289e210bbe6af1d9735b0dde0a24e" type="folder">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_2afda7f7aff8c0a563a94cdfcbd1683b" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Great Books Project, <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_b867900f181af21a023d8757018859f5" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_324564207393fe8e6a8f3c35b9d86bb7"
              parent="aspace_b867900f181af21a023d8757018859f5" type="folder">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_f4aaa26c8fa027f876350ec35773e909" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper Articles, <unitdate normal="1924/1988" type="inclusive"
                >undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_d50e9a40b67eb4825d7c0e677564ad78" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >2</container>
            <container id="aspace_02f755fb1decf8fc00eeb7be1cdeb594"
              parent="aspace_d50e9a40b67eb4825d7c0e677564ad78" type="folder">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="aspace_d75f515b87ff8993a84d9904733afb0e" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 4: Oversize, <unitdate normal="1924/1959" type="inclusive"
              >1924-1959</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="aspace_c446afe3da9a733453787f5eeb268f7d" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook, <unitdate normal="1924/1926" type="inclusive"
              >1924-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_e230d186a3242fa415cf0f2e5e4ff1d1" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >OV</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="aspace_6fe7fa93d7c329aa22d8b09eab265bb8" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><emph render="italic">Life</emph> magazine and scrapbook page, <unitdate
                normal="1959/1959">1959, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container id="aspace_6984ea2b9e24ccf655320d2faa17f2bd" label="Box:Folder" type="box"
              >OV</container>
            <container id="aspace_90c44a319fd6ddf3aac393810b1b92ae"
              parent="aspace_6984ea2b9e24ccf655320d2faa17f2bd" type="folder">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
