<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9"
     xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd">
   <eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1"
              dateencoding="iso8601"
              langencoding="iso639-2b"
              repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid countrycode="US"
             mainagencycode="US-vihart"
             url="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=jmu/vihart00345.xml">vihart00345</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the New Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley Oral Histories, 1992-1993:<num>SdArch 8</num>
            </titleproper>
            <author>JMU Cataloging, 1997</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</publisher>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_address.xi.xml"/>
            <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> © 2019 By JMU Libraries. All rights reserved. </date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       xlink:type="simple"
                       xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace and transformed with ASpace2VaHeritage.xsl on <date>2020-02-17 15:57:15 -0500</date>.</creation>
         <descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
      </profiledesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the New Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley Oral Histories, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992-1993 </date>
         </titleproper>
         <subtitle> A Collection in <lb/> Special Collections <num type="Collection Number">SdArch 8</num>
         </subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:type="simple"
                    xlink:actuate="onLoad"
                    xlink:show="embed"
                    xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/jmu.jpg"/>
         </p>
         <publisher> Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University </publisher>
         <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2019</date>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/jmu_contact.xi.xml"/>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>JMU Cataloging, 1997</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <did>
         <repository>
            <corpname>Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University</corpname>
         </repository>
         <unittitle>New Cultural Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley Oral Histories</unittitle>
         <origination audience="internal" label="source">
            <persname role="dnr" source="local">Staropoli, Theresa</persname>
         </origination>
         <unitid label="Collection Number" encodinganalog="099$a">SdArch 8</unitid>
         <unitid label="Collection Number"
                 encodinganalog="099$a"
                 audience="internal"
                 identifier="249"
                 type="Archon Instance::ACCESSION">249</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.74 cubic feet; 13 folders; 8 audiocassettes</physdesc>
         <unitdate normal="1992/1993" type="inclusive">1992-1993</unitdate>
         <abstract id="aspace_1e664fe2a4f56c583f91c234d7b6b336">The New Cultural Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley Oral Histories, 1992-1993, is comprised of 8 audiorecordings and 12 transcripts or summaries of interviews by undergraduate history intern, Theresa Staropoli, with individuals from the Shenandoah Valley who provide services to refugees and immigrants, and individuals representative of groups new to the area.</abstract>
         <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict id="aspace_db6450850930b6fe92d95ef236dd3e00">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>Access to the Oral Histories is governed by agreements with the narrators. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.</p>  
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict id="aspace_b7b34b0b8f0b663a7e92e64b47f89740">
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>The copyright interests for select oral histories have been transferred to the James Madison University Special Collections Library. For more information, contact the Special Collections Library Reference Desk (library-special@jmu.edu).</p>  
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite id="aspace_b58a427f48981b534a6fadbcb9c44326">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[identification of item], [box #, folder #], New Cultural Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley Oral Histories, 1992-1993, SdArch 8, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.</p>  
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo id="aspace_c1c2221a7da4b7a414a946b9ab512546">
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Collection was donated by Theresa Staropoli on April 28, 1993.</p>  
         </acqinfo>
         <processinfo id="aspace_209f99cb0ac0c59ac13705435c56b823">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>Oral histories were cataloged at the item level in 1997; The descriptive metadata was compiled into a Finding Aid format in 2019. Audio recordings were transferred from audiocassette digital files by Kirsten Mlodynia, Digital Project Specialist at JMU Libraries in July 2018.</p>  
         </processinfo>
      </descgrp>
  
  
  
  
  
      <bioghist id="aspace_cfc2f488a70a3a909463684eb2b38921">
         <head>Bio/Historical Note</head>
         <p>Oral histories were created by Theresa Starapoli, an undergraduate student at JMU, who completed the project as an intern in Special Collections in 1992. The internship was funded by a Burruss Grant.</p>  
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="aspace_2523702d1436ba0bc47d26f9869de221">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>This oral history series studies the immigration of various ethnic groups into the Shenandoah Valley, starting with a review of past history (see background paper). Records interviews of individuals who provide services to refugees; also interviews of individuals representative of groups new to the area. Shows how these people are maintaining their cultural identities and how they are adapting to mainstream Valley culture. Studies reasons why they left their homeland; why they settled in the Valley; how their cultures differ; what troubles they have had maintaining their cultures; and how they perceive their reception by local residents. Interviews conducted with seven individuals providing services for immigrants include: Rev. Joseph S. Roberson, Alex Flores, Marlene Webb, Marta F. de Meza, Laura Draim, Sam Ritchie, and Sheryl K. Wyse. Interviews of new immigrants include: Willie Chavez, Ana Sanchez and Efraim Sanchez-Garcia, Tanya and Sasha Reut, and Thu Huynh. Series of five articles from Daily news-record (Harrisonburg, Va.), Dec. 28-29, 1995 include: Valley Hispanics fare well at orchards, poultry plants / Bettina Tilson; Mexican natives find good, bad in America / Bettina Tilson; Few Hispanics appear on welfare rolls / Chris Edwards; Tax laws require immigrants to pay / News-record staff; Hispanics working to adapt to life as Valley residents / Chris Edwards. Article from July 27, 1996: Hispanic census: Service group places count below estimates, refutes job/tax stereotype / Julie Collins.</p>  
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement id="aspace_1bc82f5c9a2a6a9fce64d95401e13d8d">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Content is arranged in no particular order.</p>  
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess>
         <head>Index Terms</head>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Subjects:</head>
            <subject source="lcsh">Multiculturalism -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.)</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Immigrants -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.)</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Hispanic Americans -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.)</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Russian Americans -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.)</subject>
            <subject authfilenumber="sh85008793" source="lcsh">Assimilation (Sociology)</subject>
            <subject authfilenumber="sh85000442" source="lcsh">Acculturation</subject>
            <subject authfilenumber="sh85043710" source="lcsh">English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers</subject>
            <subject authfilenumber="sh85023553" source="lcsh">Children of immigrants -- Education</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Literacy programs -- Virginia</subject>
            <subject source="lcsh">Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- 20th century</subject>
         </controlaccess>
         <controlaccess>
            <head>Genre and Form Terms:</head>
            <genreform source="aat">oral histories (literary works)</genreform>
         </controlaccess>
      </controlaccess>
      <dsc>
         <c01 id="aspace_b6c4fb0d41b2b46253aba6d15bd2b33c" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-1: Background Paper: New Cultural Pluralism in the Shenandoah Valley, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 24, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_590fb7103d0df1255ba7fb8f4dfb9e51"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_af70cf868470d5843f38b886827c6eef"
                          parent="aspace_590fb7103d0df1255ba7fb8f4dfb9e51"
                          type="Folder">1</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_3cc66c3818253188b90615a10ccaf4d8" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-2: Joseph Roberson, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_daf937fe3bb733938ebb7b8b16bae23b"
                          label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_c6abb5259dbe21539ba1ad7ab3f8fd9d">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Rev. Joseph S. Roberson, Program Coordinator, Virginia Council of Churches Refugee Resettlement Program. Explains purpose of the Refugee Resettlement Office, relations with other relief organizations (Church World Service, World Relief) and the Va. Dept. of Social Services. Mentions special emphasis placed on trying to place individuals persecuted for Christian beliefs. Comments on the refugee-immigration application and selection process from the standpoint of the refugee, the immigrating country, the U.S. government (incl. mention of the U.S. immigration law) and church organizations (such as his organization and its relation with sponsoring congregations in the area). Mentions numbers and variety of immigrants and their backgrounds (ex. Soviet Union, Hispanics and Ethiopia), including education and other related factors. Explains how the Resettlement Program tries to help support the refugees by providing interpreters, ESL (English as a second language) education opportunities, and other related services including providing entry-level job opportunities (ex. the poultry industry)</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_69a8721d6d9ef2e2c18b0bf545e0181b">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_dd7161b702fafbd9b79e3c95e89edd33">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_d875e9e6c421f13d90386afea2418aec" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 1992</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_9badbf19672f4ed905766f995f59ac20"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_3c853fd17db5e2c6f7b95dd53f68823b"
                             parent="aspace_9badbf19672f4ed905766f995f59ac20"
                             type="Folder">2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_820d1e89df8cf72a7867e456dc387764" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-3: Alejandro Flores, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 30, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_08e82f55882e6eae5f792ebdb33d396e"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_1c833b87fb51a1ba366fcbe7159c3c25">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Alex Flores, Human Resources Coordinator, Rocco Turkeys Inc., Dayton, Va. Talks about the plant and its relations with various groups of immigrant employees. Mentions hiring and management practices (ex. the high turn-over rate for production jobs, starting pay, application numbers and other related figures; low absenteeism and work ethic). Gives information on numbers of immigrants and their nationality (Hispanic, from Mexicio and Central America; Ukrainians; Pakistanians; and Laotians). Explains efforts to help support the refugees by providing interpreters, ESL (English as a second language) education opportunities (ex. JMU/federal grant literacy van), and other related services; also Spanish classes for managers. Mentions the typical day for a worker. Refers to different cultural backgrounds, family structure, assimilation (or lack of it) among varying groups, both within the plant and outside of it. Mentions need for further expansion of services within the community. Recorded at Rocco Turkeys Inc., Dayton, Va. on November 30, 1992</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_d92fd9b49e70c213f66923a3a3a9a51a">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral History is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_1318d5b00e235a7238337a9cd886caa2">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_ce5ebb7bc3340afc6eb165064b16960b" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 30, 1992</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_4c8142b70fb522a385b7ff21fb5d2154"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_b689bb7ce6b0dc31ddf05edd2d657625"
                             parent="aspace_4c8142b70fb522a385b7ff21fb5d2154"
                             type="Folder">3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_92847de7ffea6fe970d48e97778fc499" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-4: Marlene Webb, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">January 15, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_1fe49ec39084ec8d756243b83d3677fc"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_6866d69ef33f36649415dee4a6ea5b31">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Marlene Webb, an ESL (English as second language) teacher. Talks about her experiences with immigrants at the Dayton Learning Center; also as a tutor. Mentions nationalities of students and how/when they came to the area (beginning with the Vietnamese; then Laotians and Cambodians; Hispanics, mostly from Mexico; and more recently, Russians.) Explains the purpose of ESL teaching; publishers and training materials; bilingualism; and the language barrier encountered by many. Refers to different cultural and educational backgrounds of various groups and changes in economic and social status. Also mentions the family structure, assimilation (or lack of it) and related adaptabilities of age levels (differences between children and adults). Mentions stereotyping; attitudes among the community at large and differences in cultural values and the general need for greater understanding by the community. Recorded at the home of Marlene Webb at 1372 Sparrow Court, Harrisonburg, Va., Jan. 15, 1993.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_63c0dd901755e3f4fe0e29ddffc249dd">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_06398fbcd177f37b119915b0f3577d44">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_a5fa18fec0eb89ed5c4ce1a4342a3ee2" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">January 15, 1993</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_e97ec6da22887ad55f9d8081c96dbba6"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_e48453f62a37cfcff835542beea6b065"
                             parent="aspace_e97ec6da22887ad55f9d8081c96dbba6"
                             type="Folder">4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_fdb3cbff9c4216044f0043dd87239772" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-5: Willie Chavez (Guillermo O. Chavez), <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">February 10, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_9eafbdecbb8f0a99920cfee8ad8a580f"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_f4340ffd728d6311eecc128a9bd18587">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Willie Chavez (and his wife) about life as recent immigrants in America. Talks briefly about his experiences in the U.S. before coming to the Valley; illegal alien/visa status and recent citizenship as a result of the 1987 amnesty. Mentions reasons for coming to this country; separation from his family. Talks about different jobs he's had (ranch hand in Texas and Oklahoma); more recently in Bridgewater, Va. at the Perdue Processing Poultry Plant. Mentions the language barrier and attempts to learn English (through general association with friends and co-workers). Compares his economic and work situation in Mexico and the U.S. Talks about the traditional structure of the Mexican family and cultural and educational assimilation of and changes in his two children. Briefly mentions discrimination; stereotyping and attitudes among the general community. His wife mentions the differences in the place of the woman in Mexican and American society. Recorded at the apartment of Willie Chavez and family (wife, two children and brother), in Bridgewater, Va., Feb. 10, 1993.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_5c0b0d5e3c201ebc09860ba9df35baaa">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_78867e2b21b0148f52178b69c53ebd6c">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_bde6e63df394dbb6be4e0adaf19864ee" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">February 10, 1993</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_ae61cb5afa5bcad5930c30acf54dcbe5"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_291fbb6de01c7eeb1a860afd0dc8436d"
                             parent="aspace_ae61cb5afa5bcad5930c30acf54dcbe5"
                             type="Folder">5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_30b86e1155f5f714115df894a36aeaa7" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-6: Ana Sanchez, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">February 23, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_f4a72525be4b4e0aeef286aa8a540814"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_9dbbd986b63ee6efe694454471d01243">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Mrs. Ana Sanchez and Mr. Efraim Sanchez-Garcia about life as immigrants/Mexican-Americans in the U.S. Ana talks about her first experience in this country at the age of thirteen, about going back and forth between the two countries, separation from family, attempts to stay in school, and about various jobs she has had across the country (Utah, Wisconsin, Virginia), among them as a migrant worker. Efraim mentions his job at the local Wampler poultry plant. Ana talks about the language barrier, the value of and attempts to learn English (through classes and general association with others); also mentions her experiences as a translator for others. She and her husband Efraim compare and contrast life in California and Virginia and why they prefer the latter (because of crime in Cal. and the fact that they want to develop English skills, which they are better able to do because there are fewer Spanish-speaking people in Va.). They mention the amnesty program which Efraim took part in; illegal alien status, and attempts to get a visa/resident alien card; also about Mexican passports and the border between Juarez, Mexico and El Paso, Texas. They also talk about the value of the traditional Mexican family and mention the cultural and educational assimilation of Mexican American children. Recorded at the trailer home of Mr. and Mrs. Sanchez and their two children, south of Harrisonburg, Va., Feb. 23, 1993.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_d651d122f79641a745388fae75c324d6">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_709ba47c0a52b12ab77b949cd688e14d">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_1d23bcd9699ba7eeabf7b74a6014841e" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">February 23, 1993</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_9e3fb4d95348518058ca76e65ba24892"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_57cc2629204537b59475aecd57af5938"
                             parent="aspace_9e3fb4d95348518058ca76e65ba24892"
                             type="Folder">6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_395d94428ca32e61223e0d2b565504e7" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-7: Sasha and Tanya Reut, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">February 24, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_1705a4e5fe5fb19fc64e9295ae04af1f"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_6594a99117f88f1403885069a46fea6b">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Tanya and Sasha Reut about life as immigrants/Ukrainian-Americans in the U.S. Both were University-trained building engineers in the Ukraine, with little English; Sasha now works as a maintenance man at the Wampler poultry plant and Tanya works at Massanutten Ski Resort. They mention the language barrier and attempts to learn English (through classes and general association with others, etc). Compare and contrast life in the Ukraine and the United States and explain why they left the Ukraine (which ended up being a week before the 1991 independence coup); and talk about the process they went through to emigrate (American embassy in Moscow; Church World Services sponsorship). Also mention the current influence of crime/KGB/mafia in the Ukraine. Compare and contrast big cities in the U.S. with the Shenandoah Valley and Hinton, Va., with its Mennonite influence, etc. Talk about starting a business; freedom and educational opportunities for their two children. Mention the blending of Ukrainian traditions (ex. Christmas traditions, customs) and values with the American way of life. Recorded at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Reut and their two children, Hinton, Va., Feb. 24, 1993</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_a23985989ad7502ee60ffdb7dd454153">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_5a7d750b3d30e7df638d078549cdb04c">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_968961022abc66f3530ab99efd5c493d" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">February 24, 1993</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_b1cb591b4ab734eb99b8ad1b632b8ae5"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_066e3cb80f98ffb241ffa7202a823c95"
                             parent="aspace_b1cb591b4ab734eb99b8ad1b632b8ae5"
                             type="Folder">7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_926dacf915034f6fd1444a9f72a8204a" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-8: Thu Huynh (Am Thu Kieru Huynh), interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">March 17, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_83cec32b58e2a5f097944ab47ff6b772">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>This interview records the viewpoints of Ms. Thu Huynh about life as an immigrant/Vietnamese-American. Talks about the long process it took for her family to emigrate, starting with her brother (boat refugee). Explains reasons for leaving: economic situation and lack of freedom (government took over her father's business). Talks about the language barrier and attempts to learn English (through classes at the Dayton Learning Center and general association with others; also from her work at High's in Broadway, Va.) Mentions differences between cultures in Vietnam and U.S.: multi-ethnic language background (Chinese: Cantonese, Manchurian; Thai; Vietnamese); the place of women in Vietnamese/Chinese society and increased independence in the U.S. (ex. learning how to drive in this country); the food, cooking from scratch; and other customs). Comments on differences in family structure between two cultures; and the reluctance of some children to learn the old language, etc. Recorded at the home of Ms. Thu Huynh, Harrisonburg, Va., March 17, 1993</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_c8a5a8038b99a62129ae442de55a77cc">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open to research.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_923fc740fa3458ebe5733d5a8324fec0">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
            <c02 id="aspace_48472ca2a6ba607f3699be681b19cdd1" level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Transcript, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">March 17, 1993</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container id="aspace_cd9a517caa4c39e3544d6ca11b947f0e"
                             label="Box:Folder"
                             type="Box">1</container>
                  <container id="aspace_2dd86ac0939076071ec60d268ce934d6"
                             parent="aspace_cd9a517caa4c39e3544d6ca11b947f0e"
                             type="Folder">8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_5b3f88c2a10b1cf33bee463a756a1c4f" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-9: Marta F. de Meza, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1993/1993" type="inclusive">January 25, 1993</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_cc20b60f62478837a9d6821b62e2767b"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_e8124650af5e5fddab23be7dc6129907"
                          parent="aspace_cc20b60f62478837a9d6821b62e2767b"
                          type="Folder">9</container>
               <container id="aspace_56ed98eb9eb062b5b89dd6298c15d0c1"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_03aeff6bcbbe57110c5566f530f9716e">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the viewpoints of Marta F. de Meza, Coordinator of Spanish Ministry, Blessed Sacrament Catholic Church, Harrisonburg, Va. Explains purpose of the ministry: to provide religious and social support services for the Spanish speaking community which consists of a sizable Hispanic population, mostly from Mexico. Mentions assimilation and changes in lifestyle that occur in families as they try to adjust to American society. Explains economic reasons for leaving their country; separation of families, and changes in travel/settlement patterns over the years (crossing the border). Mentions discrimination; level of acceptance by local population and comparison of this acceptance to other immigrant groups such as the Russians. Interview setting: 154 N. Main Street, Harrisonburg, Va., Jan. 25, 1993.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_cc66b012885f8cc99e5aca30c6d36cc5">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Oral history is open for research. There is no audio for this interview.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict id="aspace_f091ebf8653c03c4db784e05d977a6bc">
               <head>Use Restrictions</head>
               <p>Copyright interests have been transferred to Carrier Library.</p>
            </userestrict>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_2a4722d4bcb24fdc22033ccd32aefe70" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-10: Laura Draim, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 11, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_d0f57485599482c62b25ff3b0a055d23"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_349e534f4f2da6366db0086cdee940a8"
                          parent="aspace_d0f57485599482c62b25ff3b0a055d23"
                          type="Folder">10</container>
               <container id="aspace_5e10286019897c0e3ed0bc9e8a8d0044"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_d01f5909843fade7b213d2025c6c7c08">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the viewpoints of Laura Draim, English as a Second Language Program Coordinator, Dayton Learning Center, Dayton, Va. Talks about the purpose of the Center: to provide general adult education, literacy, family-learning/training and development programs, and child care to those in need of such services. Mentions the purpose and history of the ESL program (first begun in 1972 by the Massanutten Technical Center); who is eligible to attend; and funding and statistical information on numbers of teachers and students and their nationality, many of whom are Mexican. Talks about the make-up of classes; changes and growth of program and the need for additional support to expand services. Briefly mentions assimilation and changes in lifestyle that occur in families as they try to adjust to American society. Comments on nationalities of immigrants and how this has changed over the years, dependent upon world events. Interview setting: Dayton Learning Center, Dayton, Va. (?), Nov. 11, 1992.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_ecb83d0f1accf668dccd9f21bf0ba2a0">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Interview notes are open for research. There is no audio or transcript for this interview.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_4177b1ad9befc2d2506d506393d94394" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-11: Sam Ritchie, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 11, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_6a860483f5d06c62d254ed6d1a2101b5"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_69b68221b8229c35cf29254e6c9b2e32"
                          parent="aspace_6a860483f5d06c62d254ed6d1a2101b5"
                          type="Folder">11</container>
               <container id="aspace_af76c229cf4321d4ac8e6dd1be34188c"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_2b4dadf50d8abef132921e3808a4d89e">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the viewpoints of Sam Ritchie, Superintendent of the Rockingham County (Va.) English as a Second Language program. Briefly reviews the history of the program, beginning in 1990 (?); also earlier efforts. Mentions problems associated with the program: student enrollment numbers, etc. Talks about differences in approach to ESL, depending upon level of school; the use of tutoring; and the state-mandated Literary Passport test. Briefly mentions assimilation and difficulties/changes in lifestyle that occur especially with older students; problems faced by migrant children. Interview setting: place (?); Nov. 11, 1992.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_394b312bee7bc5ea48951df360e02619">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Interview notes are open for research. There is no audio or transcript for this interview.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="aspace_8c99435af95fe236473896c6afa0efe0" level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>8-12: Sheryl Wise, interviewed by Theresa Staropoli, <unitdate normal="1992/1992" type="inclusive">November 18, 1992</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container id="aspace_55adcef5c14a0061c76e4b2c944966e7"
                          label="Box:Folder"
                          type="Box">1</container>
               <container id="aspace_3fc972d539269365888e655e283ba63b"
                          parent="aspace_55adcef5c14a0061c76e4b2c944966e7"
                          type="Folder">12</container>
               <container id="aspace_47476ff0a35d9fec2569b71b8f738e70"
                  label="Digital-Materials"
                          type="Digital-materials">SdArch8-SET-001</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent id="aspace_49111c32d5553202bbc3f448d5ab76ab">
               <head>Scope and Contents</head>
               <p>Records the viewpoints of Sheryl K. Wyse, a teacher for the Harrisonburg City public schools ESL program. Reviews the history of the program, beginning in 1984; also earlier efforts. Gives statistical figures on the number and nationality of ESL students (total figure as of Oct. 1992: 101 students), the rapid growth of the program (in 1988-89 there were only 16); also numbers of teachers, with plans for more hiring. Mentions organization of classes; how students are divided (by fluency levels); credits needed for graduation; and the Va. English Language Literary Passport Test. Talks about new approaches to ESL teaching (ex. use of native language/English language textbooks, other innovations). Briefly mentions assimilation and difficulties/changes that occur especially with older students, and the influence that ESL teachers have on students trying to adjust to a new culture. Interview setting: Harrisonburg City School Board Building, Harrisonburg, Va., Nov. 18, 1992.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <accessrestrict id="aspace_5e13999dfad28b6ddd60ded640e11aaa">
               <head>Access Restrictions</head>
               <p>Interview notes are open for research. There is no audio or transcript for this interview.</p>
            </accessrestrict>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
