<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01533">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu05133::R.L. Brown Letters, 1856-1861)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01533.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu05133::R.L. Brown Letters,
             1856-1861)//EN" "viu01533.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the R.L. Brown Letters 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1861</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Brown, R.L. letters, 1856-1861 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11021</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">23 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 1, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu05133::R.L. Brown
            Letters, 1856-1861)//EN" "viu01533.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the R.L. Brown Letters 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1861</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11021</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>R.L. Brown Letters 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1856-1861</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11021</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">There are 2 items
         in this collection.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>R.L. Brown Letters, 1856-1861, Accession #11021, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the Library from Timothy
            Bakken of Halvor Americana, Claredon Hills, Illinois, on
            October 7, 1991.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Hempfield Rail Road connected Wheeling with Greensburg
         by way of the Pennsylvania Rail Road and at one point was the
         only railroad to hold a charter from Virginia for passage
         through her territory to Pennsylvania and Ohio. 
         <emph render="super">1</emph></p>
      <p>R. L. Brown was a one-term member of the Virginia General
         Assembly in 1857-58 representing Upshur County (it and
         Clarksburg, now West Virginia, are mentioned in his letter). 
         <emph render="super">2</emph>National tension on the eve of
         the Civil War is reflected in his 1861 letter to an
         acquaintance, an unidentified circuit court judge.</p>
      <p><emph render="super">1</emph>See 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Hempfield Rail Road and the Bonds
         of Ohio County, Virginia and Washington County,
         Pennsylvania</title>(Philadelphia, 1852) in the Rare Book
         Division, Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library.</p>
      <p><emph render="super">2</emph>Cynthia Miller Leonard, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The General Assembly of Virginia July
         30, 1619-January 11, 1978</title>(Richmond, 1978), 467.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of two letters: M. B. Poitiaux,
         Wheeling, Virginia, to James C. Clarke, Greensburg,
         Pennsylvania, October 1856, concerning a upcoming meeting of
         the Board of Directors of the Hempfield Rail Road, and, R. L.
         Brown, Washington, D. C., to "Dear Judge," February 4, 1861,
         concerning the 1861 Peace Congress, the border states, General
         Winfield Scott, business prospects, and his family.</p>
      <p>Poitiaux's letter mentions James Kennedy Moorhead
         (1806-1884), a politician and businessman associated with
         railroad, telegraph, and canal enterprises for most of his
         career, and a member of Congress representing Pennsylvania
         from 1859 to 1869. [For another of Poitiaux's letters, see
         accession number 9110-C.]</p>
      <p>Brown, a pro-Southern advocate, predicts the creation of a
         Southern Confederacy but maintains that Virginia and four
         other border slave states will be held in the Union and forced
         to abolish slavery. He denounces General Scott as a dictator,
         says Washington is under martial rule, and anticipates the
         failure of the Washington Peace Conference (February 4-27,
         1861). Brown also discusses his willingness to engage in any
         type of profitable business with the judge, mentions the
         pending graduation of his son from medical school and asks the
         judge's assistance in helping him to establish a practice.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e207">
        <did>
          <unittitle>JAMES C. CLARKE TO M.B. POITIAUX 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856 Oct 4</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p><lb/><lb/>Wheeling Va Oct 4th 1856 
               <lb/><lb/>James C. Clarke Esq. 
               <lb/>Greensburgh Pa 
               <lb/><lb/>Dear Sir 
               <lb/><lb/>At request of J. C. Acheson Esq. I notify you that
               a meeting of the Board of Directors of the Hempfield
               Rail Road will be held in Philadelphia on Friday next
               Oct: 10th, to meet and confer with Gen. J. K. Moorhead
               President of ? Valley R. R. and Noah L. Wilson Esq.
               President of Cin[cinnati] &amp; Marietta R. R. Co. in
               relations to an agreement for a through line in
               connection with the Penna. Central R. R. 
               <lb/><lb/>Yours respectfully 
               <lb/>M. B. Poitiaux 
               <lb/>Clerk, H. R. R. Co.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e244">
        <did>
          <unittitle>R.L. BROWN TO "DEAR JUDGE" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 Feb 4</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p><lb/><lb/>Washington City Feby 4th 1861 
               <lb/><lb/>Dear Judge 
               <lb/><lb/>Your last kind favor has just been received--by
               some strange [fortuity] the letter was sent to the dead
               letter office and I accidently saw it among the list of
               dead letters advertised! This accounts for my not having
               answered it sooner. Since I last saw you, the political
               revolution has advanced a pace. This poor city is now a
               fortified camp--United States Soldiers are arriving by
               every Northern train and the prospect now is that by the
               4th of March we will be taken care of 
               <emph render="underline">in a horn</emph>. 
               <emph render="super">1</emph>At every turn you are
               saluted by trains of flying artillery, and Genl Scott 
               <emph render="super">2</emph>has now no less that three
               heavy trains of that arm of the service, to say nothing
               of the Mounted Dragoons and Infantry--in all some 1000
               regular troops. Six thousand of the Militia are being
               daily drilled by U. S. Officers and supplied with U.
               States Rifles 
               <emph render="super">3</emph>and other improved
               firearms. We are fast drifting to a military despotism,
               and this City--the neutral soil of the Republic, is to
               be the scene of the initiation of such a damnable
               dynasty. The Peace Congress meets here today--Their
               action will result in evil and that only, in inducing
               the border slave states to temporize and delay until
               Lincoln obtains the reins of government and binds them
               hand and foot so completely, as to shut out all hope of
               their extrication, except it be through oceans of blood.
               Rather than take such an alternative I believe Virginia,
               Maryland, Kentucky, Missouri and Delaware will
               ignominiously succumb, and agree to sacrifice the
               institution of Slavery. The Cotton States with North
               Carolina and Tennessee will form a Southern Confederacy
               and maintain it at all hazards and to the last
               extremity, and I trust in God that success may crown
               their efforts. They are the last hope for a
               constitutional Republic on this Continent--the Northern
               States have no proper idea of such a government, and can
               only appreciate the government of brute numbers and
               force. Genl. Scott is now virtually President and
               Commander in Chief, and is carrying things with a high
               hand. It requires no Prophet to foresee the end. I
               despair of my Country.</p>
          <p>Now a word about myself. My Wife's health is very
               delicate, and but for that I should have removed my
               family to Upshur 
               <emph render="super">4</emph>before this--I am afraid to
               turn my family out in such bad weather; but as soon as
               the Spring opens cleverly[?] I will give them the
               western shute. In your letter you say you have great
               prospects of realizing handsomely from the Coal oil
               business and add, "Why can't you join us and make a
               fortune"--In answer I will say that I am up for any
               thing by which I can make an honest living; and if your
               can suggest to me any situation likely to secure that
               result, just count me in. This is no idle offer on my
               part and I want you to consider it seriously. Again--My
               oldest son Dandridge will graduate at the Medical
               College here on the 1st of March, and I am gratified to
               be able to state that the Professors speak highly of his
               proficiency. 
               <emph render="super">5</emph>You traverse a large
               Circuit; and perhaps know of some location where he
               could commence with the prospect of making his bread for
               the first year or so. If you know of any such location,
               please inform me as soon as you can. I want to get out
               to see you all before long, but you are so much away
               from home on your Circuit that I hardly expect to catch
               you in Clarksburg. 
               <emph render="super">6</emph>Please therefore write me.
               Can't you come and take a peep at things here--if you
               want to get an idea of a military despotism you ought to
               look in upon us here.</p>
          <p>I expect nothing from Virginia but truculent
               submission and any other action on her part, will but
               agreeably disappoint me.</p>
          <p>Let me hear from you at your earliest convenience. If
               you know of any business I can engage in that will
               likely pay, call on me, and you will find me "yours to
               serve." My family desire to be kindly remembered to you.
               <lb/><lb/>Your friend truly 
               <lb/><lb/>R. L. Brown 
               <lb/><lb/></p>
          <p><emph render="super">1</emph>The capitol had been
               fortified against a supposed plot by secessionists to
               prevent the March 4 inauguration of Abraham Lincoln. On
               the day of this letter was written a peace convention of
               states called by Virginia, in a last national effort to
               prevent civil war, convened in the city. None of the
               seceded states (at this time, South Carolina,
               Mississippi, Florida, Alabama, Georgia, Louisiana,
               Texas) sent delegates. 
               <lb/><lb/><emph render="super">2</emph>Winfield Scott (1786-1866)
               of Virginia, general in chief of the army. 
               <lb/><lb/><emph render="super">3</emph>This refers to the U. S.
               Rifle-Musket, Springfield Model 1861, caliber .58. These
               rifles cost $14.93 in 1861. 
               <lb/><lb/><emph render="super">4</emph>Upshur County, Virginia
               (now West Virginia). 
               <lb/><lb/><emph render="super">5</emph>Columbian College or
               Georgetown College? 
               <lb/><lb/><emph render="super">6</emph>Now West Virginia.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
