<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03987">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03987::A Guide to the Abraham Berglund Papers, )//EN" "viu03987.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Abraham Berglund Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Berglund, Abraham, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">1984-c
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2007 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Stephanie Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12/06/2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Abraham Berglund Papers, 
</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">1984-c
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2007
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Abraham Berglund Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">1984-c
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Abraham Berglund Papers, Accession #1984-c, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection is an archival transfer from the Papers of the Bursar Office to the Albert and Shirley Special Collections Library at the University of Virginia in 1994.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Abraham Berglund, a professor of commerce and business administration at the University of Virginia, (1922-) was born in San Francisco, California on December 10, 1875 to Hans Berglund and Anna Christina Berglund and died on May 28, 1942. His parents were natives of Sweden. His father, who engaged in the shipping industry in San Francisco, was a noted world traveler, and his mother also had traveled extensively. 
</p>
      <p>
Professor Berglund received his B. A. degree in 1904 from the University of Chicago and was a student of [Dr. Laughlin], Dr. Thorstein Veblen, and H. J. Davenport. He developed a lifelong passion for economic inquiry. He became a graduate student in economics at Columbia University and was awarded the degree of doctor of philosophy in 1907. At Columbia he was a student of Professor John Bates Clark who greatly influenced Professor Berglund with his teaching and research. 
</p>
      <p>
Also in 1907 he married Miss Edna Margery Glass of Winfield, Kansas. Professor Berglund taught at the Cathedral School (St. John the Divine) and at the New York Military School in Manlius. His thesis was a notable investigation of the United States Steel Corporation. It was noted for its high merit and industrial analysis. In 1922 he began his career of research, writing and teaching economics at the James Wilson School of Economics and the McIntire School of Commerce, at the University of Virginia.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains 106 items, 0.5 linear feet, and is chiefly concerned with the correspondence of University of Virginia Professor Abraham Berglund from the Economics Department in the James Wilson School of Economics and the McIntire School of Commerce from 1917 to 1931 in Charlottesville, Virginia.  
</p>
      <p>
There are five letters from Professor Berglund to the President of the University of Virginia, Edwin Anderson Alderman, notifying the President (as requested) about the publication of Professor Berglund's article in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Quarterly Journal of Economics</title> and mentioning the difficulties in the department due to the resignation of [Professor Hawkins]. Berglund writes that he would like to meet with the President to discuss "certain matters of a departmental character." (December 1, 1923) Other letters to President Alderman from Professor Berglund concern the future needs of the Economics Department (February 21, 1924); requests for building costs of an Ocean Freight Carrier and Passenger Steamer from a colleague of President Alderman (November 11, 1924), mention of a questionnaire from [Professor Marshall] (December 11,1925) (questionnaire not included); a rough draft of a letter answering a request for feedback on the subject of freshman residences (n.d.), and a letter of support for University Librarian Harry Clemons to remain at the University of Virginia instead of accepting a position at his Alma Mater, Wesleyan College (December 7, 1928).
</p>
      <p>
There are also letters in the collection asking Professor Berglund for references and letters of introduction for several students and colleagues including George Talmage Starnes (October 11, 1924), Herman P. Thomas (April 19, 1924, October 3, 1924, November 2, 1924, 1925), Raymond B. Pinchbeck (February 20,1925, February 25, 1925, March 19, 1925) E. C. Crowell (March 1, 1924, May 2, 1926), and W. Edwards Beach (February 28,1925).
</p>
      <p>
There are letters from Professor Berglund to leaders in the Steel Corporation, Railroad Industry (December 6, 1928), Ship Building Industry and United States Commerce Department, requesting statistical information and data for articles and books that he is writing on various aspects of the economic industry.  Some of these correspondents are Senator Claude A. Swanson for copies of the Merchant Marine Acts passed by Congress in 1920 (December 5, 1928), Judge E. H. Gary, United States Steel Corporation (December 31, 1923, January 2, 1924), Mr. W. J. Filbert, Comptroller, United States Steel Corporation (March 25, 1924), Waller R. Staples, Counsel Norfolk &amp; Western Railway (April 4, 1924), L. Van Middlesworth, Vice President of the Operating Department, United States Shipping Board (May 24,1924, July 11, 1925), and the Bureau of Labor Statistics (December 1, 1923). 
</p>
      <p>
There is correspondence regarding faculty and teaching at the University of Virginia including a list of students whose thesis Professor Berglund has approved (May 15, 1925), and academic forms including forms for absences. Topics in these letters include advice on dissertations (October 2, 1924, January 20, 1925, February 3, 1925), advice on helping a particular student with low grades (January 29, 1924), extension classes (July 27,1925), salaries (July 22, 1925), a schedule of examinations (September 6, 1924), controversies about faculty reporting income tax (February 17, 1932), a review of E. D. McCallum's book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">The Iron and Steel Industry in the United States</title> by Abraham Berglund (March 8, 1932), suggestions for textbooks (July 4, 1924, September 27, 1924, December 30, 1924, September 5, 1925, September 19, 1925), invitations to esteemed members of society to lecture in Professor Berglund's classes including William S. Battle and Judge E. E. Cassell (July 1, 1924), as well as Francis Edward Steele (April 14, 1924), a list of Professor Berglund's publications that has to be turned in to Professor Ivey Forman Lewis (May 5,1924, June 30, 1926). Other academic faculty correspondents include George B. Zehmer (July 22, 27, 1925), Charles G. Maphis (November 14, 1924, November 27, 1924), John C. Metcalf (May 15, 1925), Davis R. Dewey (December 6, 1928), Albert G. A. Balz (May 28, 1929), and James S. Wilson, Acting Assistant to Dean (September 12, 1924).
</p>
      <p>
There are also letters among colleagues giving praise and criticisms to Professor Berglund or requesting copies of Professor Berglund's articles. Correspondents include Paul M. Tyler (December 18, 1923), Meredith B. Givens (September 11, 1924, February 8, 1925, February 25, 1925), Albion W. Small (October 1, 1924), E. L. Bogart (April 8, 1930), William S. Ripley (October 20, 1923), Vanderveer Custis (August 24, 1924), Julius Klein (March 7, 1928), and William Frank Taussig from Harvard (October 4, 1923, April 2, 1924, April 9, 1924, October 8, 1924).
</p>
      <p>
There is friendly correspondence from colleagues of Professor Berglund, including one letter from Tipton Snavely in which Snavely describes his trip to the University of Texas for a conference. He writes that he met some students from Washington and Lee on the train who had just finished a heavy night of drinking and "they left all of their fire water behind them or drank it all perhaps." (June 13, 1924)
</p>
      <p>
Another friendly correspondence is from Hugh E. Agnew (August 26, 1917) in which he describes that he is encountering businessman who accuse the University of Virginia of teaching socialism and that it is difficult for the University to receive funding with this being a prominent perception outside the community.  Agnew writes, "I'm glad to hear that you have something that is likely to improve conditions there, for it is certainly a close approximation to hades for many members of the faculty the way it is now. Besides the University is getting a bad name with other institutions."
</p>
      <p>
There are also letters about Berglund's support for certain legislation including the National Child Labor Amendment which gives Congress the power to restrict persons under eighteen years of age from working (January 3, 1925); the work of Senator Claude A. Swanson for America to become a member nation of the World Court (April 6, 1928); and a petition and request for support of Thorstein Veblen to become President of the American Economics Association (May 23, 1925). 
</p>
      <p>
Under Miscellaneous, there is a Certification of Membership for Professor Berglund to Alpha Kappa Psi Fraternity. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e153">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1923 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
          <physdesc>9 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letter from Hugh G. Agnew about socialism at the University of Virginia; correspondence with Professor Frank W. Taussig at Harvard University; letter to William S. Ripley defending criticism about the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Pittsburgh Plus</title> plan in his book <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Ocean Transportation</title>; letter from Paul M. Tyler, a mining engineer, about Berglund's article on the "U.S. Steel Corporation and Price Stabilization."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e173">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924 January-August 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
          <physdesc>25 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Invitation to the fourth session of the Institute of Politics; letter to Edwin Anderson Alderman from Berglund on behalf of the James Wilson School of Economics and the McIntire School of Commerce regarding the future needs and development of the department; letter to Professor Ivey Forman Lewis from Berglund with a list of articles Berglund has published since 1922; an outline of F. A. Chase and H. F. Clark's textbook on Building and Loan Associations (1924 January-August).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e187">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924 September-December 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
          <physdesc>21 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Schedule of examinations; letter requesting a copy of Berglund's article on the "Steel Corporation and Price Stabilization" in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Quarterly Journal</title>; a letter from the National Education Association asking for a donation of $2.00; a letter from G. &amp; C. Merriam Company advertising their <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Webster's New International Dictionary</title>; a letter to Edwin Anderson Alderman from Professor Berglund regarding the building costs of an Ocean Freight Carrier and a Passenger Steamer; letters to professors at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard regarding George Talmage Starnes, a graduate student at Harvard.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e207">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
          <physdesc>24 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>A tentative schedule of supplementary salaries that will be offered to teachers with extension classes; correspondence with the National Child Labor Committee about the proposed Child Labor Amendment; a job recommendation from Professor Berglund for Raymond B. Pinchbeck, a former student; a letter from Paul H. Douglas with a petition supporting Thorstein Veblen for the Presidency of the American Economic Association.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e221">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926-1931 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
          <physdesc>16 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letter from E. Crowell asking Professor Berglund for a recommendation to work at Ohio State University; correspondence with various universities regarding recommendations for former students; a letter from Professor Berglund to Senator Claude A. Swanson in regards to support for America becoming a member nation of the World Court; a letter from Professor Berglund to Edwin Anderson Alderman concerning support for University Librarian, Harry Clemons to remain at the University; a letter from Professor Berglund to Professor E. L. Bogart in response to Bogart's critique of Berglund's book on <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Ocean Transportation</title>; Berglund's review of  E. D. McCallum's book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Iron and Steel Industry in the United States</title> (1932).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d. 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
          <physdesc>10 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Essay on the procedures at the McIntire School of Commerce; Absence from Examination forms; miscellaneous notes; a rough draft of a letter to Edwin Anderson Alderman regarding the freshman residences.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d. 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Certification of Membership to Alpha Kappa Psi fraternity  May 17, 1924.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
