<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01260">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01260::A Guide to the Papers of the Davis Family, 1852-1937)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01260&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01260::A Guide to the Papers of
             the Davis Family, 1852-1937)//EN" "viu01260"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Davis Family 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1937</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Davis Family 1852-1937 Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11386</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2000 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">32 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word.
         Date of source: 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 22, 1999</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01260::A Guide to the
            Papers of the Davis Family, 1852-1937)//EN" "viu01260"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Davis Family 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1937</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession number">11386</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Davis Family 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1852-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11386</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">ca. 450
         items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">There are ca. 450 items, 1852-1937,
         pertaining to the Davis Family, founders of the Southern
         Female College in Petersburg, Virginia. There is
         correspondence of the Davis family; and, there are
         correspondence, papers, photographs, and printed relating to
         the Southern Female College and Petersburg Female
         College.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>The collection is without restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Davis Family Papers, 1852-1937, Accession #11386,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased by the Library from
            Heartwood Books, Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 24,
            1998.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Arthur Kyle Davis (1867-1953) was the son of Williams
         Thomas and Caroline Virginia (Robinson) Davis. He received
         degrees from Randolph-Macon College and Hampden-Sydney
         College. He married Lucy Pryor McIlwaine on November 12, 1890,
         and had issue: Lucy McIlwaine (Mrs. Jones), Caroline Robinson
         (Mrs. John B. Young), and, Arthur Kyle, Jr., President of
         Southern College (Junior), 1889-1942. Davis was president of
         the Virginia Association of Colleges and Schools for Girls and
         member of various associations, including the Virginia
         Historical Society and the Southern Association of Colleges.
         He was also the author of several educational and historical
         pamphlets.</p>
      <p>Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. (1897-1972) was the son of Arthur
         Kyle and Lucy Pryor (McIlwaine) Davis. He received a bachelor
         degree from the University of Virginia and diplomas in
         economics and political science from Balliol College, Oxford.
         He was an instructor in English at the University of Virginia,
         1923-1924, assistant professor, 1924-1927, associate
         professor, 1927-1940, and professor, beginning 1940. He was
         also a visiting professor at Harvard University, 1926, and
         Sweet Briar College, 1926-1927. Memberships included Modern
         Language Association of America, College English Association,
         American Folklore Society, Southeastern Folklore Society, and
         Phi Beta Kappa. Awards and honors included Rhodes scholar,
         1920-1923; Sterling Research Fellow, Yale University,
         1928-1929; and, American Council of Learned Societies grant to
         study Virginia folk songs, 1932. During 1918-1919, Davis
         served as second lieutenant in the United States Army; and,
         became lieutenant commander in the United States Naval
         Reserve, 1943-1945. Writings include: 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Traditional Ballads of
         Virginia</title>, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Folk-Songs of Virginia</title>, and 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">More Traditional Ballads of
         Virginia</title>.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Papers of Arthur Kyle Davis include correspondence of
         Joseph Dupuy Eggleston (1867-1953) and Reaumur Coleman
         Stearnes (1866-1953) relating to the State Department of
         Public Instruction. There is also a letter, October 16, 1913,
         from "Will" Davis, Atlanta Coast Line Railroad Company,
         Savannah, Georgia, concerning his territory and settling in a
         boarding place. On September 12, n.y., architect John Kevan
         Peebles (1876- 1934) writes that he will arrive on the
         Cannonball train and will proceed directly to the church.
         Other items of interest include a 1912 pamphlet, "Three
         Centuries of an Old Virginia Town..." by Davis, President of
         Southern Female College; vehicle permit and registration,
         1913; and, two State Real Estate trust deed notes, 1920.</p>
      <p>Papers of Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. include report cards,
         1913, from the Tome School for Boys, Port Deposit, Maryland,
         and a letter, September 12, 1913, from Robert W[illiamson]
         Tunstall (1851-1917), Classical Department, Tome School, to
         Davis' father, discussing his credits and examination grades.
         There is a letter, September 30, 1920, from Davis, Jr. at
         Balliol College, Oxford, to his mother, Lucy Pryor (McIlwaine)
         Davis, discussing his experiences upon arrival in Oxford;
         visiting Balliol; meeting the master; the atmosphere at the
         college; Rhodes scholars from Oregon, Tennessee, and Nebraska;
         arranging a tennis game on the Balliol courts; descriptions of
         Balliol and the college at Oxford; a diagram and discription
         of his rooms at the college; a visit to Christ Church; and,
         his planned studies in English. Another letter, November 5,
         1922, from Balliol, refers to having tea with Mr. and Mrs.
         (Catherine Scott) Ridley near Boar's Hill; an anecdote about
         the consequences of walking a Miss Northrop back to Lady
         Margaret Hall in the rain; Fitzgerald Flournoy, the new
         Virginia Rhodes scholar; a debate on the study of literature
         and philosophy with [Robert Kent] Gooch (1893- ); a meeting of
         the International Assembly, where the near-Eastern question
         was discussed; Theodore Marberg, once Minister to Belgium,
         speaking on the League of Nations at the American Club;
         hearing Ruth Draper (1884-1956) in a series of character
         sketches; and, social activities. Another letter, December 16,
         1922, from Shakespeare Hotel, Stratford-on-Avon, mentions the
         engagement of Marjorie Hillyer to Arthur Patterson Marshall; a
         concert given by the Hillyers in the music room of Hall's
         Croft; being taken with Miss Betty Melhirst, a beautiful
         soprano and dancer; plans to be in London, staying at a house
         occupied entirely by literary and artistic people; receiving a
         letter from the Vice-Chancellor of Oxford about his
         communication on the difficulties of post-graduate work at
         Oxford; a visit to Shakespeare's birthplace; and, Baconian
         theory not existing for Stratfordians.</p>
      <p>Papers of Williams Thomas and Caroline Virginia (Robinson)
         Davis include letters from their daughter, E. T. C., and son,
         R. B., among others. During July - August 1866, E. T. C.
         writes from various places, including Silva Sonora,
         Mecklenburg, and Pilgrim's Rest, concerning her vacation;
         attending a protracted meeting conducted by Mr. Blincoe;
         attending the Baptist Association; girls attending the next
         session of [Petersburg Female College]; a tournament given in
         honor of the Petersburg girls and the disapproval of the
         preachers; the "Kissing Club"; sending catalogues to certain
         prospective students; and, trying to recruit students for
         Petersburg Female College but having difficulty because of
         hard times for farmers. There is a letter, July 23, 1866, from
         R. B. Davis in Cabin Ford, concerning his trip by boat;
         visiting family; negative opinion of a New England school
         marm, Miss Harwood; crops of wheat, oats and corn; and, his
         father's activities in Charlottesville and Norfolk.</p>
      <p>Other letters to Williams Thomas and Caroline Virginia
         (Robinson) Davis include a letter, October 27, 1867, from
         Agnes I. Duval in Floral Bank, British Honduras, describing
         her new life and the plans for same. She mentions Mr. Duval
         and R. F. Ledbetter having plans to have a steamboat on the
         river; wishing that Miss Lacy could come and be a teacher to
         her children climate permitting; and, having her guitar sent
         as she sold her piano in Mexico. A January 7, 1874 letter to
         "Carrie" concerns financial matters; the return of James
         Carroll from New Orleans; taking time to love and enjoy her
         children; worry over "Tom" who has been exhibiting the same
         symptoms of coughing and bronchitis as when at Randolph-Macon
         College; family news; and, the death of sister "Eliza." A
         February 4, 1875 letter to "Carrie" concerns a financial
         matter involving articles bought for Mary and Jennie; the
         practicality of getting a set of lower teeth; James [Carroll]
         not returning to his family; the improvement in Tom's health;
         hard times in Louisiana; and, the death of "Rebecca" due to
         heart disease.</p>
      <p>There is an interesting letter, January 22, 1877, from S.
         O. Harris, Royal Oak, Talbot County, Maryland, to Caroline
         Davis, concerning an extract from 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Godey's Lady Book</title>on the
         schooling of children and giving a discourse on female
         education. The correspondent writes that "the education of men
         and women should have some reference to their intellectual
         organization and capacities..."; advises "a harmonious
         development of the moral, physical and intellectual being" as
         the kind of education required for women; warns against
         "overtasking the youthful intellect of American girls"; asks
         that his motive not be taken unkindly; and, praises the course
         of study at the Southern Female College.</p>
      <p>On August 6, 1879, "Carrie" Davis, Southern Female College,
         writes to her mother, Caroline Davis, mentioning attending
         protracted meetings, news of "Kittie" and George Drew, and
         life at Southern Female College. On August 25, 1880, Williams
         Thomas Davis writes his wife, "Carrie" [Caroline Virginia
         (Robinson) Davis], about the activities of the family; hearing
         excellent sermons by [John Cowper] Granberry (1829- 1907) at
         Market Street Church; and, imploring her to use her influence
         to find some students for their school. On August 28, 1880,
         Davis writes his children in Brunswick County an interesting
         letter giving his opinions on "the system of labor and
         arrangements of society," "masters &amp; servants," and the
         mental energy of white people in contrast to the physical
         energy of "colored" people. He also advises them on how to be
         useful and happy and encourages the love of family and God. A
         touching letter, July 15, 1886, from Alice Clark expresses
         sympathy over the death of young "Carrie" Davis, empathizes
         with the loss of a loved one, expresses her own sorrow over
         losing her husband Emery, and gives religious encouragement.
         There is also a letter, February 8, 1904, from Robert Good
         Southall (1852-1924), House of Representatives, sending a copy
         of the Lincoln, Garfield and McKinley, eulogies. There is a
         carte-de-visite of Williams Thomas Davis as a mature
         gentleman.</p>
      <p>Papers of the Davis family pertain to financial matters
         during 1854-1857. There is a letter, February 5, 1860,
         concerning the hire of one of the best overseers in Warren and
         discussing his character, work skills, and recent endeavors
         and advising the recipient on how to treat him. An August 6
         letter, from James A. Davis in Pilgrim's Rest concerns a trip
         near Petersburg to Suffolk and Norfolk. A copy of a 1912
         letter pertains to Seacrist Gold Mining Company, Petersburg,
         and contains a report of an examination of the property.</p>
      <p>Papers of the Robinson family include letters, January 13
         and March 28, 1852, from John B. Robinson, "Lebanon," Norfolk,
         to Mrs. [Ann] Clark Robinson, Brunswick County, concerning
         studying and wearing the uniform at the academy; being
         examined in February by many of the citizens of Norfolk; news
         of the marriage of Nelly Moseley; the suicide during a state
         of intoxication of David Kyle; snow killing many peaches,
         apricots, strawberries and other fruits; a young
         African-American being burnt by drinking hot grease and being
         treated by linseed oil; Aunt Martha having land cleared; and,
         his sisters Rowena, Lucy and Caroline. He comments on suicide,
         saying "these worldly minded men have nothing to support them
         in times of trouble give way to despair and plunge into
         eternal ruin." There are also two letters, January 6 and June
         3, 1877, from Allen Y. and John B. Robinson in Orcus Island,
         Washington, stating their reasons for staying in such an
         outlandish country as the healthiness of the country and
         waiting to secure titles to their claims and the funds to pay
         for them. They write that they are providing assistance to
         needy families and selling eggs. They reveal that their plans
         to return to Virginia in 1862 were thwarted by the Civil War,
         and that they instead went to Caribou, British Columbia and
         built a large brick building in Victoria, British Columbia,
         which has deteriorated in value. They state that in 1864 they
         started trading on Puget Sound, Washington and afterwards took
         up two government land claims on Orcas Island. They admit that
         they cannot return to Virginia until receiving the title from
         the United States Government. The marriage of [Caroline
         Virginia (Robinson)] to [Williams Thomas] Davis is also
         mentioned.</p>
      <p>Papers of William A. Shepard and Martha (Davis) Shepard
         include four letters. On August 5, 1866, there is a letter
         from Millville, Brunswick County, about a quarterly meeting
         conducted in Lawrenceville; personal and family news; travel
         plans and other activities; the damage caused by a
         thunderstorm; the meager wheat crops, splendid oat crops, and
         promising corn and tobacco crops; the difficulties in sending
         the daughters of local families back to school; and, news of
         the Price family and the Ashton Lewises. Letters of September
         1866 mention travel in Virginia, interviewing a scholar, the
         visiting Davis children in Pilgrim's Rest, and Riddick having
         130 pupils with daily arrivals, and request that catalogues be
         sent. An October 8, [1889] letter reveals that they helped fix
         up a little church in the country and attended a dedication
         with Dr. Kern and mentions "Charlie," a bright young man and
         good football player.</p>
      <p>Papers relating to Educational Associations include:
         program for the Conference for Education in the South (1903);
         program for the Department of Public Instruction (1906);
         Constitution of the Virginia Association of Colleges and
         Schools for Girls (1906); program for the first annual meeting
         of VACSG (1907); Interstate Teachers' Agency (1907-1909);
         Department of Public Instruction circular concerning
         certification of teachers (1910); circular letter re the
         Educational Association of Virginia meeting, inviting teachers
         of Latin or Greek to join (1911); Nathaniel C. Starke,
         principal of Petersburg Military Academy (1911) enclosing
         circular; pamphlet, "Education in Virginia..." (1912) by
         Arthur Kyle Davis; and, pamphlet, "The Southern Seminary"
         (n.d.).</p>
      <p>Business papers of the Petersburg Female College consist
         chiefly of receipts, ca. 1860-1863, for teachers' salaries.
         There are also bills for advertising, music and tuning the
         college's pianos.</p>
      <p>Papers relating to Southern College (Junior) include a
         brochure, "Commencement Snap-Shots" depicting members of the
         graduating class (1934); program of finals (June 1936);
         letter, December 21, 1937, from Raleigh C. Powell Building
         Construction concerning an inspection of the Southern College
         buildings and property and replacement estimates; and, a "Book
         of Views" containing photographs of the college buildings and
         student groups and activities.</p>
      <p>Business papers of the Southern Female College include
         accounts for advertising (1910-1913); a building addition to
         Davis' house at the college (January 1872); medical care
         (January 1872); clothing and food (1872); tuning pianos (June
         1872); ink and composition books (July 1872); children's oak
         chairs (January 1873); and, a list of furniture and other
         items in the dining room and other rooms. There are catalogues
         and printed material of the Southern Female College, including
         a broadside (September 1879), catalogues (1887-1888 and
         1892-1893), and a program of a Christmas concert (1913). Among
         the correspondence for the Southern Female College are a
         letter, September 2, 1905, from Marie Crosby concerning a
         position of teacher of music, and including testimonies; and,
         a letter, May 27, 1908, containing recommendations for Isabel
         K. Emerson. Insurance papers include an inspection and survey
         report of the buildings of the Southern Female College
         (December 1935).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e222">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Arthur Kyle Davis 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1905-1929</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e230">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1913-1932</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e238">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Thomas Davis and Caroline Virginia
               (Robinson) Davis 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1866-1907</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e246">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Davis Family 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1854-1927</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e254">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John B. Robinson 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852,
               1877</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e262">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William A. Shepard and Martha (Davis) Shepard
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866,
               1889</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e270">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Educational Associations 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1903-1912</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e278">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Petersburg Femal College: Business Papers 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1860-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e288">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern College (Junior) 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1934-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e296">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Advertisements 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1910-1913</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e305">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Business Papers 
               <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871-1873,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e315">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Catalogues and
               Printed 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879-1893,
               1913</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e323">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1905-1914</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e331">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Insurance 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1910,
               1935-1936</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e339">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Photographs 
               <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e347">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Requests for
               Catalogues 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1905-1914</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e355">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Southern Female College: Telegrams 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1898-1913</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
