<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01370">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01370::A Guide to the William Bolling War of 1812 Orderly Book)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01370.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01370::A Guide to the William
             Bolling War of 1812 Orderly Book)//EN"
             "viu01370.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the William Bolling War of 1812
            Orderly Book, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Bolling, William, War of 1812 Orderly
            Book 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11138</num></subtitle><author>Special Collections Staff</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">47kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Leonard Sadosky, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 April 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01370::A Guide to the
            William Bolling War of 1812 Orderly Book)//EN"
            "viu01370.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the William Bolling War of 1812
         Orderly Book, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11138</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>William Bolling War of 1812 Orderly Book 
         <unitdate label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11138</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">The collection is a
         single volume orderly book.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This is an orderly book, August 10
         - October 18, 1813, for Captain William Bolling's Cavalry,
         with army units assigned to the defense of the Hampton Roads
         and Norfolk, Virginia areas during the War of 1812. The orders
         concern court-martials, troop movements, artillery, hospitals,
         commissaries, etc.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>William Bolling Orderly Book, 1813, Accession #11138,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This orderly book was purchased by the Library from Mr.
            Franklin Gilliam of Franklin Gilliam Rare Books, of
            Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 18, 1994.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>William Bolling was the commandant of cavalry under
         Brigadier General Robert B. Taylor.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This is an orderly book, August 10 - October 18, 1813, for
         Captain William Bolling's Cavalry, with army units assigned to
         the defense of the Hampton Roads and Norfolk, Virginia areas
         during the War of 1812. The orders concern court-martials,
         troop movements, artillery, hospitals, commissaries, etc.</p>
      <p>William Bolling was commandant of cavalry in Brigadier
         General Robert B. Taylor's (1774-1834) brigade, assigned to
         the defense of Norfolk. The book covers the period following
         the battle at Craney Island in June, during which the British
         Navy continued a blockade of Hampton Roads and made periodic
         forays into the Elizabeth River and Lynnhaven Bay.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Overview</head>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 10-11 Adjutant Office,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Proceedings of a garrison court martial. Court consisting
         of Capt. Anderson, Lt. Craven, Cornet Harris, and Adj. William
         McCandlish, judge advocate. Trial of John Campbell, a private
         in Capt. Joseph Atkinson's troop of cavalry on the charge of
         contemptious and abusive language toward a sargeant of the
         corps to which he belongs, brought against him by Sarg.
         Lightfoot of the same company. Confined to the guard house; no
         communication for two days and nights.</p>
      <p>Court with D. Sanford, judge advocate. Trial of Nathaniel
         Sebrun, a private in Capt. Saunders' troop of cavalry on the
         charge of disorderly conduct brought against him by Corp.
         Turner. Acquitted and discharged. Trial of Isaac Avery, a
         private in Capt. Carr's troop of cavalry for not attending
         parade on the 5th and 8th instant. Acquitted first charge.
         Sentenced to stable guard four days and nights.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 12 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Calling attention to Brigade Orders of
         March 7 and April 1 concerning applications for furloughs.</p>
      <p>Proceedings of a court martial, with Lt. Col. Pegram,
         president. Trial of George Garris, a private in Capt. Sharp's
         company of the 35th U. S. Infantry on the charges of leaving
         his post and leaving his gun sticking in the ground. Sentenced
         to eight days hard labor. Trial of William Proctor, a private
         in Sharp's company on the charge of desertion. Sentenced to
         wear the ball and chain 30 days, to pay reduction in amount of
         ten dollars to make good the amount of the apprehension fee,
         and to sweep out the encampment during that 30 days. Trial of
         William King, a private in Sharp's company on the charges of
         disobedience of orders and desertion twice. Sentenced to wear
         the ball and chain thirty days, to be confined to the
         encampment for six months, to stoppage of pay in the amount of
         ten dollars to make good the amount of the apprehension fee.
         Trial of James Barkham and others on the charges of failing
         inspection due to stolen or damaged firearms.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 13 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The captains or commandants of companies,
         the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd regiments, will inform the adjutants of
         their respective distances from Norfolk to their respective
         regimental or battalion places of rendezvous who will report
         to the Brigade Inspection in order to ascertain the mileage
         the men are entitled to...</p>
      <p>Trial of Capt. Spencer Gunn of the 2nd Regiment, Virginia
         militia on the charges of drunkenness and neglect of duty.
         Sentenced him to be cashiered, but court showed mercy.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 14 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning the general court martial of
         which Col. Beatty is president, for the trial of Lt. Col.
         Thomas Lee of the 95th Virginia Regiment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 14 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Concerning the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd regiments
         in regard to the distanced certified from Norfolk to their
         places of rendezvous.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 15 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning application for discharge.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 16 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning copies of the [ ] handbook for
         the field officers, the captains of each regiment, and one for
         the subalterns of each company, which are to be considered as
         public property.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 17 Adjutant and Inspector
            General Office, Washington</emph>
      </p>
      <p>As of August 5, 1813, all officers of the army of the U. S.
         commanding districts, posts, or fortresses are commanded to
         turn back and in case of any attempts to evade this order to
         detail all sea vessels, or river or bay crafts, which may be
         suspected of proceeding to, or of communicating with, any
         station, vessel, squadron, or fleet of the enemy within or
         near the waters of the United States.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 18 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Lt. Col. Henry Beatty to assume command of
         the Brigade of State Troops.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 19 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Ensign Archibald Atkinson
         (1792-1872) of Capt. Shields' company of riflemen on charges,
         brought against him by Capt. James M. Smith, of disobedience
         of orders, quitting his platoon, contempt and disrespect for a
         superior officer, and disorderly and unofficer-like conduct.
         Acquitted of 1st and 2nd charges. Sentenced to suspension of
         all command in the militia for ten days for the 3rd and 4th
         charges.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 19 Brigade Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Appointing Capt. Julian Magagnos of the 2nd
         Regiment as Acting Brigade Inspector.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 20 Brigade Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Brigade quarters will be Capt. Julian
         Magagnos' dwelling house; morning reports of the troops are to
         be handed in by 9:00 each morning.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 21 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. General court martial of President Col.
         Sharpe dissolved. General court martial of seven members and
         two supernumeraries will convene the following day.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 21 Brigade Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Commandants of the 4th and 98th Regiments
         will appoint the officers to compose the court martial.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 22 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning officer of the day.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 23 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Arrival of Quartermaster Col. Swann;
         special duty discharge of George Newton as judge advocate.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 23 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Capt. Roberts of the 4th Regiment shall
         augment his company to one hundred men by selecting the best
         sharp shooters from that regiment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 24 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Lt. Col. William Sharpe will assume command
         of the regiment now commanded by Lt. Col. Green, officer of
         the day for tomorrow.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 25 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Some of the state troops have been formed
         into a regiment to be called No. 6 consisting of the following
         companies of Capt. Coles, Wingfield, Townes, Clays, Daniels,
         Poole, and Neblett.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 26 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Reports of the field officers of the day
         indicate "that the deciplin [sic] of the army has become
         greatly relaxed and that the duty of guards and centinals in
         particular is so negligent..." [Discusses neglects of other
         general orders in some detail.]</p>
      <p>Trial of Heartwell Long, a private in Capt. Shorts' company
         on the charges of disobedience of orders, reproachful and
         disrespectful language to Sarg. Shelton. Sentenced to hard
         labor for thirty days, to wear the ball and chain at night for
         thirty days, and to be ducked four times. Trial of John
         Thucatt, a private in Capt. Jones' company on the charges of
         stealing. Sentenced to hard labor for ten days, to be marched
         up and down the line on two separate days..., and to have his
         rations of whiskey stopped for twenty days. Trial of James
         Mitchell, a private in Capt. Preston's company on the charges
         of disobedience of orders, mutinous conduct, challenging
         Ensign Scott to a duel. Sentenced to three months constant
         duty, confinement in the guard house at night, to wear the
         ball and chain, that his rations of whiskey be stopped, that
         he be carried around the encampment..., and that one half of
         his head be shaved at the end of the term of punishment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 28 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Carry out orders of monthly returns. Trial
         of Antoine Sorby, a private of Lt. Smith's detachment on the
         charges of disorderly and mutinous behavior. Sentenced to wear
         the ball and chain for five days, to have his rations of
         whiskey stopped for ten days. Trial of Isaac Willson for the
         charge of desertion, from the company of Capt. Coupland of the
         10th Infantry. Sentenced to twenty days hard labor and payment
         of $8.00 be taken out of his next pay; prisoner's feeble state
         of health seems to render him unable to sustain any service
         corporal punishment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 29 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Officer of the day for tomorrow is Maj.
         Waggoner.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 29 Brigade Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Concerning the palpable neglect of the
         officers of guards and sentinels in the performance of their
         respective duties; the health of the army and the medical
         attention given to those sick in the hospitals vs. in the
         camps.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 30 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Arthur Cherry of Capt. Pollard's
         Company of 20th U. S. Infantry on the charge of desertion.
         Sentenced to serve 43 days after the team of his enlistment
         shall expire to be put to hard labor thirty days and
         afterwards to wear the ball and chain for ten days. Trial of
         John Harney of Capt. Wilkinson's company of militia on the
         charge of neglect of duty.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">August 31 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. No furloughs for anyone able to do duty.
         The manner of procuring supplies; the departments which are to
         supply the army consists of the contractors, the quartermaster
         general, the commissary of purchases, and the company of
         ordinance.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 1 Cavalry Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. Adj. McCandlish having resigned his
         commission, Lt. D. Sanford is appointed to the office of
         Adjutant of Cavalry.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 2 Cavalry Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. Due to the closeness of the enemy, no
         neglect of duty will be overlooked.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 2 Cavalry Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. Police officers will be appointed daily,
         whose duty it will be to visit the relays to make sure orders
         are carried out, particularly in reference to health.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 4 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The superintendent of the General Hospital
         will report to Dr. Pendegrast, hospital surgeon, on the first
         day of each month, the state of the sick of the troops.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 5 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Regulations concerning the allowance of
         quarters, forage, fuel, straw for bedding, stationary, and the
         transportation of the baggage of officers.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 6 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning the allowance of fuel from the
         last day of April to the first day of November of each
         year.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 7 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Of Forage. For all horses in service there shall be allowed
         fourteen pounds of hay and twelve quarts of oats, or, in lieu,
         eight quarts of corn per day.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 7 Brigade Quarters,
            Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Quarters. The Commandant of the 4th Regiment will
         transfer over to Capt. Pitt.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 8 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Of Straw. One truss of straw weighing thirty pounds allowed
         for every two men at the end of every sixteen days, and being
         refreshed with eight pounds at the expiration of thirty two
         days. At the end of the period of sixteen and thirty two days,
         a fresh bedding will be received.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 9 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of John Thompson, a private in Capt.
         Pollard's company on the charge of neglect of duty. Acquitted.
         Trial of Henry Hill, lieutenant of Capt. Isaac Mitchel's
         company of riflemen on the charge of leaving camp eight days
         without permission. Suspended from command for one week and
         privately reprimanded. Trial of Sherwood Kidd, a private in
         Capt. Taliaferro's company on the charge of disobedience of
         orders. Found not guilty.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 10 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Major Parham, president of court martial.
         Trial of John Jarvis, a private in Capt. Richard Kilsuks'
         Portsmouth Riflement on the charges of neglect of duty,
         disorderly conduct, and mutinous conduct. Sentenced to be
         publicly reprimanded by his captain and to have his rations of
         whiskey stopped for ten days. Trial of Corp. Bennett
         Stephenson's company of the 65th Regiment on the charges of
         desertion. Sentenced to continue in service seven days after
         his company shall have been discharged, and to be reduced
         because of the prisoner's ill state of health and voluntary
         return. Trial of William Hart, a private of Capt. Clayton's
         company of the 65th Regiment on the charge of desertion.
         Sentenced to remain in service eleven days after his company
         shall have been discharged, to be put to ten days hard labor,
         and at the end of that time to wear the ball and chain five
         days. The court being lenient because of voluntary return.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 12 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning arrangements for the supplies of
         the medical department.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 13 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning supplies for the Army. Necessary
         to ascertain what supplies are on hand in the various
         departments.</p>
      <p>Of Transportation. To each company or detachment of one
         hundred men shall be allowed one four-horse wagon and team or
         two two-horse wagons and teams, for the conveyance of their
         baggages and camp equipage.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 15 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning morning revelry, change in
         grounds of encampment once in every ten days.</p>
      <p>Of Stationary. To officers commanding a district so much
         stationary as may be necessary for the discharge of his public
         duties. To other officers a certain number of quires of
         paper.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 16 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Annual Estimates. Duty to make out and transmit to the war
         department by the first day of December in each year the
         annual estimates of the forage, fuel, straw for bedding,
         articles of stationary, dragoon and artillery horses, oxen,
         wagons and carts for the transportation of baggage and all
         other articles, the furnishing of which ascertains to the [ ]
         department.</p>
      <p>Of Laboratories. Authorize hire of women and children and
         low wagers in all work which can be performed by them as well
         as by men.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 17 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Inspection of Powder. Duty of Commanding General of
         Ordinance to call upon the Commissary General of Purchases for
         the names and places of residence of all persons engaged in
         making powder, cannon-shot or other ordinance stores.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 18 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning Capt. Richard Pollard of the
         20th Regiment of the United States Infantry and the court
         martial of Sgt. Carney and Corp. Popejoy.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 18 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of John Casey, private in Capt.
         Wingfield's company of the 6th Regiment Virginia Militia on
         the charge, made by Lt. Col. Green, of sleeping while posted
         as a sentinal. Sentenced to ride a wooden horse from the left
         to the right of the regiment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 21 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Henry Hill for the charges of
         leaving his confinement before being set at liberty by his
         commanding officer and absenting himself from his company
         without leave. Sentenced to be cashiered and that all pay and
         emoluments accruing to him since the day of his first
         absenting without leave be stopped.</p>
      <p>Trial of Zachariah Glasscock on the charge of sleeping on
         his port while standing as a sentinel. Testimony proved
         prisoner to be disqualified for duty as a sentinel. Trial of
         Lt. Barnes on the charge of neglect of duty. Found guilty but
         received no punishment in consideration of his zeal and good
         conduct upon all occasions. Trial of Richard Philips, a
         private in Capt. Poole's company of the 6th Regiment on the
         charge of sleeping on his post when posted as a sentinel.
         Found guilty of charge but testimony proved him to be
         incapable of performing the duties of a sentinel, therefore no
         punishment was given.</p>
      <p>Capt. Kelrick's company of riflemen will prepare for muster
         and inspection the next day.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 23 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The commandants of the 4th, 5th, and 6th
         Regiments will cause their quartermasters to deliver to Lt. L.
         G. A. Armstead, keeper of ordinance and military stores all
         their cartridges over and above 20 rounds to a man.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 24 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Ensign Hallaman on the charge of
         absenteeing himself without leave permission. Sentenced him to
         be cashiered. Trial of Fred Pleasant Acarn, a private in Capt.
         Cole's company of the 6th Regiment on the charge of sleeping
         on his post as a sentinel. Sentenced to wear a chain for five
         days, to sweep out the camp and other cleaning, and to be
         confined in a guard tent. Trial of Archibald Haley, a private
         in Capt. Daniel's company of the 6th Regiment on the charges
         of sleeping on his post while serving as sentinel. Sentenced
         to be chained with P. Acarn, to sweep out the camp and other
         cleaning, and to be confined in a guard tent and to be fed on
         bread and water during the confinement.</p>
      <p>Col. Goodwin, commander at Craney Island will discharge
         such of the detachment of the state troops attached to his
         command which arrived here under Maj. Blow of the 65th
         Regiment. Prior to the discharge Maj. Blow will cause all
         arms, ammunition, accoutrements, tents, camp equipage and
         every other article of public property which has been received
         by the troops since they have been in service to be returned
         to the proper departments.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 25 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Capt. Kelsick's company from the 7th
         Regiment is discharged from the present service of the
         States.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 27 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. The Commandant of the 6th Regiment will
         detail three soldiers from the line to act as wagoneers.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 28 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The 6th Regiment commanded by Lt. Col.
         Sharpe will prepare for muster and inspection on the 30th
         instant. Two inspection returns and three muster rolls will be
         required.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">September 29 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The Quartermaster General, having made
         complaint that when boats or wagons are detailed, for the
         conveyance or transportation of detachments, they are not
         always regularly returned when done with; that by such
         detention, much inconvenience is experienced...</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 2 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The surgeons of the state troops are
         directed to make reports to the Assistant Adjutant General of
         the names of all persons who have been and are now employed in
         the hospital or attending the sick.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 3 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Sgt. Owen and Private Wilkinson S.
         Woodson of the Powhatan Cavalry, Sgt. Chisholm of the
         Albemarle Troop, Corps. Dandridge and Payne, Private Turman of
         the Goochland Troop, and Private Jordan of the Isle of Wight
         Troop on the charges of disobedience of orders in connection
         with an expedition determined by the commanding general. All
         acquitted except for Sgt. Chisholm who was reduced to the rank
         of a private soldier.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 3 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. The troops detailed to the Bay Shore shall
         perform ten days duty at a time, besides on day to go and one
         day to return, for those stationed on the west side of
         Lynnhaven, and three days for going and returning for those on
         the east.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 4 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Concerning the erection of the huts on
         Craney Island and the detail of the number of men requisite
         for that duty.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 5 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Sgt. Watson of Capt. Osborn's
         company on the charge of neglect of duty. Declared honorably
         acquitted.</p>
      <p>Capt. Richardson of the Virginia [Artillerist] in
         requisition at Craney Island will be mustered and inspected
         today and discharged from the service of the United States.
         Prior to discharge they are to deliver over to the Commandant
         of the Artillery all the public ordinance, arms,
         accoutrements, ammunition, camp equipage, and every other
         article drawn by the company since they have been in
         service.</p>
      <p>The commandant of the brigade will detail a fatigue party
         of one sergeant, one corporal, and 18 privates, subject to the
         orders of Maj. Faulkner to repair to Lambert's Point.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 7 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The Commandant of the Brigade will cause
         the detachment from the 4th Regiment now at Craney Island to
         be relieved tomorrow, by an equal number.</p>
      <p>A general court martial of nine members and two
         supernumaries of which Lt. Col. Lindsay is appointed
         president, will convene at Fort Norfolk for the trial of such
         persons as may be brought before it. The general court martial
         of which Col. Sharp is president is dissolved.</p>
      <p>The court of inquiry convened under general orders of the
         18th to set at Fort Norfolk on the 20th at the instance of
         Capt. Richard Pollard, Maj. McConnico, president. Adduced that
         no censure can be attached to Capt. Pollard for the removal or
         disposition of the sentinels on the night of Mark Arrington's
         escape.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 7 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. The Commandant of the 5th Regiment will
         detail 250 men with a suitable number of officers with orders
         to go to Craney Island tomorrow morning, for the purpose of
         relieving the detachment from the 4th Regiment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 8 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Lt. Col. Francis Preston will assume the
         command of the Brigade of State Troops. Lt. Col. Koonts will
         take command in the 4th Regiment.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 9 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Lt. Barnes on the charge of
         unofficer-like conduct. Acquitted. Trial of Private Bolling
         Barnes on the charge of desertion. Sentenced to labor twenty
         days, to be confined in the black hole every night during that
         term, and to be fed bread and water for that term. General
         court martial information.</p>
      <p>The Commandant of the Brigade will order a fatigue party of
         45 privates under the direction of one commissioned officer
         and three noncommissioned officers, who will be provided with
         spades, axes, and handbarrows; they will repair to Fort
         Barbour with their tents.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 10 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Companies of the State Artillerists will
         prepare for inspection. The troops about to be discharged will
         immediately after inspection deliver the public arms and
         accoutraments to their former Captain who will grant each man
         a receipt for the same. Arms, ammunition, and accoutrements to
         then be distributed to the relieving troops. Capt. Maron's
         Rifle Company at the east side of Lynnhaven River will be
         relieved.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 10 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. The Commandant of the 6th Regiment will
         detail twenty-five riflemen and others to relieve the
         detachment from the 5th Regiment stationed on the east side of
         the mouth of Lynnhaven River.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 11 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The Commandant of the Brigade of State
         Troops will cause the fatigue party form the 4th Regiment at
         Lambert's Point to be relieved.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 12 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. The troops on command or detachment from
         the 5th and 4th Regiments with the exception of 250 men lately
         ordered to Craney Island will be ordered to rejoin their
         regiments immediately.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 12 Cavalry Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. The different companies will meet at the
         usual parade ground the following morning.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 14 Cavalry Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. Reprimand of an officer who left his post
         of observation before he was regularly relieved. A garrison
         court martial will convene at the Adjutant General Office
         tomorrow.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 14 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of Lt. Daniel, a private in Lt.
         Smith's detachment 2nd Artillery on the charges of
         disobedience of orders and disorderly conduct preferred
         against him by Lt. Garland of the 35th Regiment U. S.
         Infantry. Sentenced to be confined to the garrison for three
         months, to perform fatigue and police duty, to have his
         rations of whiskey stopped, and to publicly asked pardon.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 16 Assistant Adjutant General
            Office, Norfolk</emph>
      </p>
      <p>General Orders. Trial of William Kingry, a private of Capt.
         Jones' Company 35th Regiment U. S. Infantry on the charge of
         desertion from Fort Nelson. Found guilty of absence without
         leave, and sentenced to be confined to the garrison for three
         months, to perform police and fatigue duty, and to have his
         rations of whiskey stopped. Trial of William King of Capt.
         Hart's Company 35th Regiment on the charge of desertion.
         Sentenced to hard labor, to public work with a ball and chain,
         to be confined in the guardhouse at night, to have his rations
         of whiskey stopped, and to have the word "deserter" written in
         red letters on the back of his coat. Trial of William Cane of
         late Capt. Allen's Company of 1st Artillery on the charge of
         desertion from Craney Island. Sentenced to public work with
         the ball and chain, to be confined in the guardhouse for
         twelve months, to have his rations of whiskey stopped, to have
         the word "deserter" written in red letters on the back of his
         coat, and to make restitution for the expenses of his
         apprehension. Trial of Nathaniel Emmery and Peyton Hobbs of
         Capt. Cocke's Company 35th U. S. Infantry on the charges of
         desertion. Sentenced Emmery to four months confinement to the
         garrison, to perform police and fatigue duties, and to have
         his rations of whiskey stopped. Sentenced Hobbs to be confined
         to the garrison fifteen days.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 16 Brigade Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Brigade Orders. Commandants of regiments and companies will
         provide a list of all the artificers under their respective
         commands designating their professions.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">October 16 Cavalry Quarters</emph>
      </p>
      <p>Cavalry Orders. Concerning list of artificers.</p>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
