<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu00102">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu00102::Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families)//EN" "viu00102.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families</titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Stuart-Baldwin Families, Papers <num type="collectionnumber">228-a</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved. </date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. 175 Kilobytes] </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from WordPerfect. [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1997.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>
        <item/>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-16" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 16, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::00102::Stuart-Baldwin Papers)//EN" "ViU00102.sgm" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Special Collections Department <num type="Accession number">228-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008 </date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff </item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1921</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number">228-a</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Extent">ca. 800 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions </head>
        <p>See the <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials"> University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation </head>
        <p>Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families, Accession #228-a, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottevsille, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1994 March 3</date></p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information </head>
      <p>For biographical information concerning Archibald Stuart and Alexander H.H. Stuart, please consult <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dictionary of American Biography,</title> Volume
        XVIII, pages 160-162.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection consists of the additional papers of the Stuart and Baldwin families, chiefly Archibald Stuart (1757-1832) and Alexander H.H. Stuart (1807-1891), of Staunton, Virginia, ca. 1754-1921, ca. 800 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet),
        including correspondence; financial and legal papers; printed items; microfilm; an architectural drawing; Civil War military papers of Captain George M. Cochran, Jr.; nineteenth century newsclippings; drafts of speeches by Alexander H.H. Stuart; land
        grants signed by Virginia governors, including Beverley Randolph, Robert Brooke, John Floyd, and James Monroe; two engravings of Alexander H.H. Stuart; and papers regarding the settlement of the estate of Archibald Stuart . Since Alexander H.H. Stuart
        was a prominent member of the Virginia Whig Party, there is considerable material in this collection concerning the Whig Party and Virginia politics.</p>
      <p>CORRESPONDENCE OF THE STUART-BALDWIN FAMILY -SUMMARIES (BOX 1)</p>
      <p> Martha S. Baldwin forwards a letter to her husband General Briscoe Gerard Baldwin (d. 1852) from their daughter Mary Baldwin regarding her health (n.d.)</p>
      <p> James Barbour (1775-1842), Secretary of War, mentions an interview with [Henry] Clay concerning the participation of members of the administration in the political convention [of the National Republican Party ] and discusses his knowledge of the true
        charges leveled against Andrew Jackson while in control of Louisiana during the War of 1812, Jackson's conflict with Louisiana Governor William Charles Claiborne and the Governor of Georgia, his refusal to obey the orders of President Monroe, his
        denunciation of Madison, and his behavior as acting Governor of Florida (1827 Dec 16); Barbour also mentions his involvement in "a controversy of mixed vexation," his retirement, " and says, " [John C.] Calhoun 's pamphlet is the final act in the drama
        -and I apprehend the breach will become wider and wider" (1831 Feb 19)</p>
      <p> G.A. Baxter, member of the Board of Visitors of Washington Academy, informs Archibald Stuart of his election to the Board, and explains why his resignation was errantly reported in their minutes (1807 Sep 29)</p>
      <p> Robert Beverley discusses a possible land sale (1791 May 5); asks Archibald Stuart to attend to his properties near Staunton and make sure all back taxes are paid (1791 Nov 24); discusses land business and court matters (1791-1797); makes reference
        to the slave revolt in the French colony of Haiti in the West Indies and the declaration of independence by Toussaint L'Ouverture (1743-1803), criticizing George Washington for his early acknowledgement of the French Republic, believing he acted
        unconstitutionally, and expresses great confidence in the talents, integrity, and firmness of Mr. [John] Adams (1798 Dec 17)</p>
      <p> John Breckinridge writes business letters (1788 &amp; 1790), his son, J.C. Breckinridge, asks for information from Archibald Stuart for a biographical essay about his father (1815 Apr 30)</p>
      <p> Gerald Briscoe, [Jr.?] writes about a land dispute in "Caintucke" (all three letters, 1794-1796, n.d.)</p>
      <p> Cuthbert Bullitt to Archibald Stuart and General John Brown discusses a suit involving Colonel Clendenning for lack of payment on a bond (1790 Jan 2); and the death of his brother, Thomas Bullitt, asking for a petition in the Legislature of Virginia
        for their financial relief (1823 Dec 16)</p>
      <p> Joseph C. Cabell refers to a pamphlet containing Mr. Madison's letter and an appendix establishing the point that the Tariff Policy is the true Republican doctrine; Cabell paid T.W. White, Richmond printer, for 3,000 copies and will have more printed
        if necessary; claims that the opposition party is exerting every effort to destroy Madison's influence in the state (1829 Feb 24)</p>
      <p> Arthur Campbell requests an investigation into the circumstances surrounding the sickness and death of the boy Charles H. Campbell; speaks of the opposition to the federal constitution and the value of the controversy over the amendments to point out
        the real motives of those trying to keep Virginia and North Carolina from approving the Constitution (1789 Sep 2); discusses difficulties in obtaining land warrants due to the boundary dispute with Kentucky and refers to the petition to revise the
        Virginia State Constitution opposed by the friends of [Patrick ?] Henry (1795 Sep 30); refers to Thomas Jefferson and the success of the "friends of monarchy" who won the late election for President, and the French Revolution (1797 Feb 20); and
        mentions his desire that the land law in the Act of 1795 would be repealed or amended (1798 Dec 22)</p>
      <p> John Coalter discusses a debt against Mrs. Reid, and declares "I have no hopes of the republic since New Jersey has proved recreant" (1812 Nov 6)</p>
      <p> George Davis discusses legal and business matters (1792 Aug 17)</p>
      <p> R. Gamble discusses legal and business matters (1791-1800)</p>
      <p> Hugh Holmes writes concerning the competition between Winchester and Staunton to be the branch of the Virginia Bank which he believes must be kept exclusively under a Republican direction; asks for Archibald Stuart to secure a loan for five hundred
        dollars; discusses the rumor that merchants believe that the Eastern and Northern Tories have devised a stratagem to defeat the loan requested by the government to conduct the War of 1812 with Great Britain (1814 Mar 9); speaks of his pain from
        numerous operations; the raids of the Tunisian corsairs upon British ships in the English Channel (1817 Jul 12); and the death of Mary, the daughter of Archibald's brother Alexander (1823 May 6)</p>
      <p> [Chapman ?] Johnson (1779-1849) sends a copy of a decree from the court of appeals in the case of [Doneghe ?] and Campbell to Archibald Stuart; sent a copy of Archibald Stuart 's letter about the seat of government to the Editor of <title
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Enquirer</title> for publication; refers to the failure of their efforts to establish the University of Virginia and his belief that nothing will be done
        for it this winter; the non-effect of political essays upon the public mind, and mention of "the great James River project" (1822 Mar 2)</p>
      <p> John Lewis to Dabney Carr notes "my seeing Mr. Jefferson" is very uncertain, and writes about the Mayo v Lewis lawsuit (1768 Jan 23)</p>
      <p> John Lewis to Thomas Jefferson writes regarding his lawsuit Mayo v Lewis, docketed in Thomas Jefferson 's hand (1772 Oct 4)</p>
      <p> J. Marshall speaks of the fickleness of political parties in reference to "Zach." and refers to a business matter (n.d.)</p>
      <p> George Mathews (1739-1812) writes of his safe arrival in Georgia where he was asked to sit for election to political office (1791 Oct 10); and details concerning his dispute over a land sale in Virginia and his motive in accepting the office of
        [Governor of Georgia?] (1794 Apr 4)</p>
      <p> James D. McCutchen to Joseph Janney writes concerning his inability to make his payment for land due to the drought, high feed costs and poor crops and his proposal to work out an alternative method of payment (1839 Mar 25)</p>
      <p> Andrew Moore (1752-1821), elected to the first four Congresses, March 4, 1789-March 3, 1797, writes from New York and Philadelphia, sends copies of all laws passed, wages established at six dollars per day, set the budget for the staff of the
        President and Vice-President, discusses office seekers, mentions that the amendments to the constitution are being conducted with a great deal of warmth, believes the amendments "will quiet the public mind and remove in a great measure the opposition
        to government" (1789 Aug 12); asks for help in securing compensation for a slave who escaped into Pennsylvania and proved that he was a free black unjustly sold to Moore who was unaware of his status by a previous owner (1791 Nov 5); the preoccupation
        of Congress with a bill fixing the rates of representation in Congress and the disputed election between General Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) and General James Jackson (1757-1806) before Congress (1792 Mar 15); his disappointment in the bill fixing the
        ratio of representation and the decision made in the House concerning the contested election which declared the seat vacant (1792 Mar 26); discusses the resignation of Thomas Jefferson as Secretary of State who appeared determined never to enter public
        life again, with the former Attorney General Edmund Randolph succeeding Jefferson as Secretary of State; mentions the great loss suffered by the country by Jefferson's resignation at this critical time and praises Jefferson highly; encloses a number of
        resolutions introduced by Mr. Madison, the conflict over the payment of interest on the debt of the United States; cites Jefferson's opinion on the same subject; forwards copies of the correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and Citizen Edmond Charles
        Genet and Jefferson's report on United States trade with Europe (1793 Jan 4); the attempt by Washington and Congress to have Citizen Genet recalled to France due to his insolent and insulting conduct (1793 Dec 8); the situation of the United States
        becoming more and more critical due to the increase of British spoliation on American shipping, detaining our vessels, and alleging that an old law precluded the United States from Britain's West Indian ports; the purchase of flour and beef and the
        chartering of United States vessels to transport it because the United States was bound by treaty to guarantee the French West Indies; Madison's resolutions; the empowerment of the President to impose an embargo on all shipping coming into American
        ports; the arming of small vessels to use against the Algerians; a bill providing for the defence of our ports and harbors; the establishment of arsenals, and a resolution for the enlistment of 15,000 troops, with training during 24 days a year, and
        the need for a direct tax to fund national defence (1794 Mar 14)</p>
      <p> Garrett Peterson asks [Charles Anderson] Wickliffe for help in locating Archibald Stuart and buying a piece of land belonging to Archibald Stuart to make his title to his plantation more secure (1826 Jan 24, see Wickliffe's letter, 1826 Feb 26)</p>
      <p> William Preston to William Anderson seeking advice in a land claim controversy (1783 Jan 1)</p>
      <p> [Andrew Reid, Jr.] to Thomas J. Stuart writes a social letter to a friend (1807 Sep 5)</p>
      <p> Alexander Farish Robertson Correspondence, chiefly with Philip Alexander Bruce concerning his history of the University of Virginia and especially the Honor System (1921)</p>
      <p> John Steele writes that the Governor [Henry Lee] has written Mr. White asking him to help Archibald Stuart investigate the High Sheriff for embezzlement (1792 Mar 5)</p>
      <p> Robert Sterritt notifies Joseph Janney that he has secured a purchaser for Archibald Stuart 's plantation in Rockbridge County, James D. McCutchen, (1837 Jul 14, see also McCutchen 1839 Mar 25)</p>
      <p> Eleanor Briscoe Stuart to Thomas J. Stuart concerning his studies and vacation while at Washington Academy (1806 Jan 24 &amp; Mar 2) and to her mother, Mrs. Margaret Briscoe (1808 Feb 19)</p>
      <p> Martha M. Stuart writes to her mother-in-law, Mrs. Eleanor (Briscoe) Stuart concerning family news (n.y. Apr 8)</p>
      <p> [Charles Anderson] Wickliffe (1788-1869) forwards a letter from Garrett Peterson to Archibald Stuart concerning a land sale (1826 Feb 26)</p>
      <p> William Wirt (1772-1834) asks Archibald Stuart to send his anecdote about Patrick Henry for his biography and to furnish the details just as it was originally told (1816 Aug 10)</p>
      <p>MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS OF THE STUART FAMILY (BOXES 1-2)</p>
      <p>This series contains an architectural drawing; an engraving of Alexander H.H. Stuart by Danforth, Baldwin &amp; Company; financial and legal papers, including notification of Archibald Stuart 's appointment as a Presidential elector (1792 Nov 12);
        insurance policies for Archibald Stuart 's barn, grist mill, saw mill, dwelling and kitchen (1811, 1812); Archibald Stuart 's appointment as a commissioner to collect money for a monument to George Washington (1817 Apr 4); stock certificates; accounts
        and receipts; indentures; land plats; legal cases of both Archibald Stuart and Alexander H.H. Stuart; copies of wills of Alexander Stuart, Robert Stuart, Chapman J. Stuart, and Alexander H.H. Stuart; the military papers of Captain George M. Cochran,
        Jr., Quartermaster, 52nd Virginian Infantry, Pegram's Brigade, Early's Division; the settlement of Archibald Stuart 's estate, and drafts of several speeches by Alexander H.H. Stuart, one protesting the increase in salary of the superintendent of the
        Western Asylum because it would be disproportionate to all other salaries allowed by the state of Virginia, another declining the office of President of the branch of the Bank of the Valley and resigning his post as a member of the board, and a third
        delivered at the fiftieth alumni reunion at the University of Virginia .</p>
      <p>CORRESPONDENCE OF ALEXANDER H.H. STUART -SUMMARIES (BOXES 2-4)</p>
      <p>Abolitionist (Unidentified) writes a vitriolic letter denouncing slavery and slaveholders and promising his willing participation in the coming revolution to bring about complete democracy (1841 Jun 20)</p>
      <p> William H. Allen writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart while he was member of the House of Representatives (1841-1843) seeking his help in establishing a post office at Green Valley, Virginia; the closest one is at Cloverdale (n.y. May 13)</p>
      <p> Appomattox County, Virginia, Rough &amp; Ready Club requests Alexander H. H. Stuart to represent the Whig position on the upcoming Presidential election at their next political discussion (1848 Sep 7)</p>
      <p> Henry Carey Baird requests a copy of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's recent address to use in his pamphlet concerning the farmers of the United States (1859 Nov 1)</p>
      <p> C[ornelius ?] C. Baldwin discusses his biographical sketch of his brother [Gerard ?] Baldwin which he hopes will appear in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Richmond Whig</title>
        and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart for any comments or additions; he mentions his son, Briscoe G. Baldwin III, a year old and his oldest son, Charles Cornelius (1867 Jan 14)</p>
      <p> John B. Baldwin writes concerning business opportunities in Philadelphia ([1843? Jan 30]); Alexander H. H. Stuart 's appointment as Secretary of the Interior and the care of his former legal clients while he is in Washington, D.C. (1850 Sep 24); his
        disappointment that Millard Fillmore was defeated for the presidential nomination as the Whig candidate; and as Winfield Scott supports the Whig platform without reserve his only objections to Scott as the Whig candidate lies in his great vanity and
        his associations (1852 Jun 23); Brigadier General Robert Seldon Garnett (1819-1861), who served under General Taylor in the Mexican War, was proceeding to the region with 2500 men according to Alexander H. H. Stuart 's suggestions; and Baldwin believes
        that the Convention will hardly be well attended (1861 Jun 8); reports that he is within musket range of the enemy who is building winter quarters and mentions the presence of Early's army coming towards [Richmond ?] (1864 Nov 18); writes about his
        concern over the asylum releasing Briscoe as "incurable but harmless" (1869 Dec 5); and writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning the sale of the "gum tree lot," payment of taxes and an accident of Mayo Cabell; and believes his father may soon be
        elected Judge ([ca. 1841-1843] Dec 6)</p>
      <p> Joseph G. Baldwin writes his cousin concerning his plan to move to California for the opportunities there (1849 Mar 2); a long jesting letter congratulating Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to be Secretary of the Interior and including
        family news (1850 Sep 27); and describes San Francisco where he has just opened his law practice (1854 Sep 15)</p>
      <p> I.L. Barbour, President of the Orange and Alexandria Rail Road Company, writes that he is unable to comply with his financial request (1866 Dec 11)</p>
      <p> A.W. Barton urges Alexander H. H. Stuart to help defeat the [ Virginia Reform ?] Convention, "The tremendous opposition to the mixed basis beyond the Alleghany -the indifference upon the whole subject in the valley counties and some division east of
        the Blue Ridge will enable us to do it" (1850 Apr 22)</p>
      <p> S.S. Baxter recommends William D. Delany as Inspector of the Custom House in Norfolk (1851 Nov 24)</p>
      <p> Thomas Hart Benton (1782-1838) writes concerning the Brazeau claimants attempts to get Alexander H. H. Stuart to re-open the case he decided last summer and asks him to leave questions about the decision up to the judiciary ([ca. 1851-1853])</p>
      <p> Berford &amp; Company, California Express Office, reports a great dissatisfaction of their customers and fellow California Whigs with the appointment of Mr. Beall as Superintendent of Indian Affairs (1852 Apr 12)</p>
      <p> Dr. Edmund Berkeley voices his concern over the increase in smallpox cases and attributes the cause to the lack of a vaccine agent in western and central Virginia and suggests Staunton as a likely location for such an agent and offering himself as a
        candidate (1837 Jan 20)</p>
      <p> James B. Bingham, editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Intelligencer,</title> discusses politics in Wheeling, [West] Virginia, and his concern that both the Democrats and
        Republicans are pulling votes away from the Whig Party (1859 Sep 28)</p>
      <p> David Alexander Bokee (1805-1860) discusses national politics and urges Alexander H. H. Stuart and other conservatives not to make any arrangements with the Republicans preliminary to the organization of the House; refers to the <title
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Times</title> article quoting a correspondent from Ohio who believes "the South is beginning to prepare the way for union with the Republicans as
        such in 1860"; and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to support the efforts of conservatives of the North "to induce the Republican Party to abandon `its distinct organization' founded as it is `on foolish abstractions" (1859 Oct 24)</p>
      <p> Patrick Brady 's letters, from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, all discuss various aspects of his suit against Daniel Brady, including his stolen ledger which later appears to have been altered, his demand for the deed to the Bath Iron Works, and
        questions about ultimate settlement (1857, 1867-1869)</p>
      <p> Mary Louisa Brooks writes whimsically about how much she misses Washington, D.C., and how unattractive she finds New York City "this huge temple of Mammon" (n.y. Mar 18)</p>
      <p> Alexander S. Brown writes his cousin Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning business and family matters (1857-1858)</p>
      <p> Joseph Rodes Buchanan asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to attend the National Democratic Convention to be held on May 7, 1867, in Louisville, Kentucky, discussed in an enclosed editorial from The Louisville Journal which was recently identified with the
        Democratic Party; the Convention to be composed of the leading men of the Northern Democracy and leading men of the South to secure cooperation between the two groups, "which is now our only hope" (1867 Feb 28)</p>
      <p> John C. Bullitt, Patrick Brady 's council in Philadelphia, asks when the first remittance of the Brady v. Brady settlement will arrive (1871 Oct 28)</p>
      <p> William M. Burwell draws Alexander H. H. Stuart 's attention to the political aspects of the negotiations over the Isthmus of Tehuantepec as a quicker route to the western states (1852 Jul 23)</p>
      <p> J.S. Calvert furnishes a financial summary for Alexander H. H. Stuart (1868 Jan 21)</p>
      <p> Samuel D. Campbell asks for help in getting payment for his brother William Campbell who worked to get depositions for Catherine Crider in Wardlaw v. Crider (1830 Nov 30)</p>
      <p> Lewis Cass (1782-1866) discusses two appointments with Alexander H. H. Stuart acceptable to the Whig Party (1852 Jul 20)</p>
      <p> John H. Cassin asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to visit their county and address them concerning the political questions of the day (1859 Apr 13)</p>
      <p> Katherine Chase discusses the circumstances surrounding her divorce from Mr. William Sprague (1883 Mar 18)</p>
      <p> H. Chrisman offers to purchase real estate or other goods for Alexander H. H. Stuart on his trips west if he wishes (Dec 7, 1855)</p>
      <p> Bolivar Christian sends a copy of the Confederate Acts and discusses the problems of setting up the new Confederate Congress (1862 Jan 18)</p>
      <p> C.M. Conrad writes concerning Alexander H. H. Stuart 's order for a cask of table claret wine from New Orleans (1855 Apr 3)</p>
      <p> William Wilson Corcoran says he will be happy to have a copy of the proceedings of the Peabody Board and hopes to see him soon (1855 Oct 23)</p>
      <p> Thomas Corwin (1794-1865) a letter of introduction for [Calhoun Benham], U.S. Attorney for California (1853 Jul 10)</p>
      <p> J.A. Cowardin, Editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Daily Dispatch,</title> letter of introduction from L.A. Trigg, and a discussion of the Readjuster controversy, and
        William Mahone, and says "I do not think Mr. Hunter will suit these times. We want an aggressive man, one who is bold and sagacious too. I think General [James Lawson] Kemper is that man" (1873 Feb 14)</p>
      <p> John Jordan Crittenden (1786-1863) writes a letter of introduction for his friend Samuel Casey (1851 Sep 26)</p>
      <p> Claudius Crozet writes concerning the Northwest Turnpike and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart feels that Mr. Eskridge is capable of opening the road himself (1838 Jun 1)</p>
      <p>Rector E.A. Dalrymple 's recommendation of Thomas B. Edelin (1852 Jul 15)</p>
      <p> John W. Daniel (1842-1910) does not approve of the Readjuster policies, "I am firm against repudatum alias enforced readjustment alias stealing. I believe in the Decalogue, and of course in repressing thieves, by whatsoever name they are called"
        (1877 Jul 18)</p>
      <p> J.D. Davidson sends the election results for Rockbridge County (1851 Dec 10) and encloses a check for a claim against Seaforth (1852 Jan 2)</p>
      <p> Garrett Davis (1801-1872) discusses a power shift in the House of Representatives away from [John C.] Calhoun toward [Thomas Hart?] Benton who "will be the dictator this winter &amp; will wield more power than all others together"; mentions the
        numerous job seekers wandering the halls of Congress like unclean birds; discusses the hopes of the Whig Party to gain the Presidency next election and mentions possible opponents and weighs their respective threat to the chances of the Whig candidate;
        and the need for much organization and work to succeed in the next election (1843 Dec 13); a long and detailed description of the difficulty during the extra session of the 27th Congress in organizing the House caused by the opposition of the Democrats
        and the division in the Whig Party (1845 Dec 16); the third letter discusses business questions; congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to be Secretary of the Interior; expresses his appreciation for Millard Fillmore; and comments
        about South Carolina, " South Carolina is a little beside herself, but I believe it is the insanity of ambition pride &amp; arrogance thwarted, and that a good sound drubbing would be an infallible cure." (1851 Jan 28)</p>
      <p> George M. Davis thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for giving his son Carey Davis a job as a clerk in the Pension Office (1851 Jul 27)</p>
      <p> William Wallace Davis, editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The District Whig</title> discusses politics in Norfolk and the loss of the election to the Democrats despite his own
        efforts to visit various Whigs and get them to the polls on Election Day (1851 Oct 2)</p>
      <p> William Crosby Dawson (1798-1856), Georgia Senator, asks Alexander H. H. Stuart not to fill a vacancy in the General Land Office until he could speak with him (1852 Jul 28)</p>
      <p> Horace H. Day discusses the charges brought against the Commissioner of Patents, Mr. Thomas Ewbanks (1792-1870) saying his official conduct has been one-sided, partial, and not in accordance with the rules and laws of the Patent Office (1851 Feb 7)
        and asking if the New York papers have correctly reported Alexander H. H. Stuart 's comments about the charges (1851 Mar 12)</p>
      <p> Wills De Hass (1818?-1910) sends a copy of his <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">History of Western Virginia</title> (1851 Jul 24); wants Alexander H. H. Stuart to be a candidate for
        Vice-President (1851 Oct 6); voices concerns over his application for a consulship or another office (1852 Jun 1 &amp; Oct 18); two letters furnish private details of the Baltimore Convention (1852 Jun 20); and hopes for a position in the Maryland
        Historical Society (1853 Feb 16)</p>
      <p> William D. Delany tries to enlist Stuart's aid in securing the office of Inspector of the Custom House at Norfolk (1851 Nov 25) or the Postmaster office at Norfolk (1852 Sep 29)</p>
      <p> Charles Devens, Jr., U.S. Marshal, Boston, letter introducing General John S. Tyler (1852 May 24)</p>
      <p> Samuel Dickson writes concerning the Patrick Brady v Daniel C.E. Brady suit for $ 50,000 growing out of the dissolving of a partnership in 1857; and describes the Bath Iron Works and Buffalo Forge property (1867 Apr 24)</p>
      <p> D[orothea] L[ynde] Dix (1802-1887) writes six letters to Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning the establishment of a first class hospital in Washington, D.C. and seeks the aid of Captain Randolph in the Legislature of [Virginia ?] ([ca. 1851-1853])</p>
      <p> James B. Dorman writes that the Whigs of Rockbridge unanimously desire the nomination of Millard Fillmore as President; believes the hostility to Fillmore stems from his approval of the Compromise of 1850 and his "fidelity to the Constitutional
        rights of the South"; and many Whigs object strongly to General Winfield Scott 's Roman Catholic affinities (1852 Jun 7)</p>
      <p> John Doyle writes that he has recommended Alexander H. H. Stuart to the prominent Whigs in Pennsylvania as the best choice for nomination to the Vice-Presidency while he favors Fillmore for the Presidency over Scott (1851 Sep 20); his concern over
        the imminent split in the Whig Party of Lexington, Virginia (1852 Dec 4); his son, R.L. Doyle, writes concerning their Alum Springs property containing iron deposits and several mineral springs and asks the aid of Alexander H. H. Stuart in securing a
        loan to convert their property into a viable health resort (1853 Jan 7)</p>
      <p> G.G. Dyer defends his change of political parties from Whig to Democratic based on his open support of the Tariff and the United States Bank and extols the virtue of the new state of Iowa which he describes as a land of beauty and opportunity (1851
        Sep 27)</p>
      <p> J.L. Edwards, Pension Office, discusses the claims of the descendants of Colonel Alexander McClanahan to land based on his Revolutionary War service, with the Committee of Safety for the Colony of Virginia form appointing Alexander McClanahan to Lt.
        Col. of the 7th Regiment of Regular Forces attached (1776 Feb 29 &amp; 1843 May 19)</p>
      <p> Vespasian Ellis discusses the plan of organization adopted at the National Council where a Committee of 13 was appointed to take the general charge of the interests of the American Party which was presented to the Council by himself; the plan was
        adopted unanimously but the Chairman E. Brooks received the credit for the plan; he suggested that Alexander H. H. Stuart would be a good person from Virginia to be on the Central Committee of 13; mentions the efforts of Baldwin of Connecticut and
        others to "free soilize" the party platform and the fact that he opposed and defeated the plan was suppressed in the report on the proceedings in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href=""
          >Louisville Journal</title> (1857 Jun 10)</p>
      <p> Erie Railroad Company Board of Directors offers to Alexander H. H. Stuart free use of the railroad as member of the Cabinet (1851 Jul 12)</p>
      <p> Edward Everett (1794-1865), Secretary of State, regrets he will not be able to dine with Alexander H. H. Stuart due to personal illness (1852 Dec 20); and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that General Franklin Pierce wishes for him to continue to act
        as Secretary of the Interior until his successor is appointed (1853 Feb 26)</p>
      <p> Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884) thanks him for his interest in James E. Stewart (1852 Aug 25)</p>
      <p> Millard Fillmore letters to Alexander H. H. Stuart -address the question of his feelings toward the South, "I disclaim most unequivocally now and forever any desire on my part to interfere with the rights on what is termed the property of citizens of
        other states" and encloses a copy of the leading [Lewis] Cass paper in the state showing that Fillmore was denounced at the recent anti-slavery convention at Worcester along with Cass and Taylor (1848 Jul 5); excuses Alexander H. H. Stuart from the
        Cabinet meeting due to the death of Judge Baldwin (1852 May 19); authorizes Alexander H. H. Stuart to take on the duties of the Secretary of the Navy until his return (1852 Sep 25); thanks him for his letter of condolence upon the death of his wife,
        Abigail Powers on March 30, 1853 (1853 Jul 11); attempts to make arrangements for a Southern tour in the spring, and says, "This Nebraska matter presents a new phase to things in Washington . But is it wise for the South to set the example repealing
        the Compromise of 1820 ? If one compromise be disregarded will not another be, and will not the South in the end be left to the tender mercy of Northern fanaticism with an overwhelming numerical majority ?" (1854 Feb 9); observes that with the latest
        election it appears that the Whig Party has split into two factions, with the abolitionists joining the [Republicans ?] and the rest joining the American Party of Know Nothings and refers to the nomination of Henry Alexander Wise for Governor and his
        denunciation of the Know Nothings (1854 Dec 14); and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that Granger will try to meet him in Washington this winter and mentions the efforts of his friends to unite the national elements opposed to the present federal
        administration into an American Union Party (1854 Dec 22)</p>
      <p> Millard Fillmore to Daniel Webster sends John P. Scott over to see Webster concerning a position in the State Department in Londonderry, Ireland, now held by an appointee of President Tyler and says he will go along with whatever Webster wants (1851
        Apr 2)</p>
      <p> Edward H. Fitzhugh refers to the Bridge case in the Wheeling court (1850 Mar 25) *see newsclippings in Box 2*</p>
      <p> E[dmund] Fontaine, Virginia Central Railroad Company, concerning his barley which has been at Waynesboro for some time prior to his letter (1859 Mar 25)</p>
      <p> John S. Gallagher discusses the bestowal of advertising patronage by the federal government (1851 Jul 19); the suitability of Shannondale for a military asylum (1851 Aug 4); encloses a letter from William P. Buford, soliciting Alexander H. H. Stuart
        's influence to get Mr. Buford's son appointed to a cadetship at West Point (1851 Nov 13); his examination of the controversy about the post office in Winchester and his advice not to remove Milton (1852 Jan 9); encloses letters (not present) from
        friends desiring positions with the government (1852 Jan 16); introduces Colonel Joseph K. Hartwell (1852 Mar 10); recommends General [James] Singleton for the government position in New Mexico (1852 May 7); and asks for a copy of a letter from the
        Commissioner of Patents to Dr. James Blake of California (1852 Jul 2).</p>
      <p> Robert H. Gallagher, Bank of the Union, Washington asks that part of the Census Fund and the Pension Fund be deposited with him (1851 Dec 9; 1852 Sep 2)</p>
      <p> Alexander Galt concerning his position as Postmaster at Norfolk (1851 Jul 31)</p>
      <p> J. Garland 's letter of introduction for his relative, Alexander B. Garland (1853 Feb 2)</p>
      <p> William H. Garland requests the position of treasurer of the mint at New Orleans (1850 Oct 29) and writes concerning the outrage committed by the authorities of Cuba on the Crescent City [New Orleans ?] (1852 Oct 7)</p>
      <p> William Garnett, Collector Custom House, Norfolk, Virginia, concerning the effort being made to remove him from the Custom House (1851 Nov 18 &amp; 1852 Aug 11)</p>
      <p> George Washington's Birthday Celebration Committee, Rome, Georgia, requesting Alexander H. H. Stuart 's presence at their celebration and commenting, "The Southern people are terribly oppressed, but are disposed to preserve their manhood untarnished
        preferring to submit for a while to military despotism rather than to the ruin and degradation of radical rule and negro supremacy" (1868 Feb 11)</p>
      <p> R.T. Gibson 's letters are all concerning his futile attempts to secure the position of naval officer at the port of Savannah (1851-1852)</p>
      <p> W.M. Gilliam sends Alexander H. H. Stuart 's horse to Washington by Mr. Brent (1852 Mar 15)</p>
      <p> T.H. Gilmer seeks more appointments for people from Virginia from the Whig administration (1850 Sep 27)</p>
      <p> Thomas W. Gilmer writes that he is sorry that Alexander H. H. Stuart has been involved in controversy, mentions "old [James Iver ?] McKay " as chairman of the Ways &amp; Means Committee, and believes that Texas will come into the Union as fast as it
        can (1843 Dec 13)</p>
      <p> W.W. Gilmer approves Alexander H. H. Stuart 's stand on the National Bank but is not so fond of the election of [Walter ?] Coles (1841 Apr 15)</p>
      <p> William L. Goggin (1807-1870) his disappointment over his brother's failure to secure a position, the possibility of getting the postmastership at Sacramento City, and his declaration, "I am a Union man and I have long thought this should be the
        great issue (irrespective of old party associations) the Union or its Dissolution -God grant it may be perpetual -I repudiate utter fanaticism North or South" (1850 Nov 3); and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to remove his letter from the files of the War
        Department requesting an appointment as Visitor to West Point (1852 Mar 10)</p>
      <p> G. Goldenberg sends two printed pamphlets (present) entitled <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Observations Sur La Maladie Des Pommes De Terre</title> in French and a copy in German,
        presenting his treatise on the Potato Disease (1849 Feb 2)</p>
      <p> J.T. Gordon explains being detained in the lieu d'aisance while reading Senator [William McKendree] Gwin 's attack on the Administration (1852 Jul 9)</p>
      <p> Willis Arnold Gorman (1816-1876) agrees to a resolution to supply the heads of Departments with copies of the [Presidential Message ?] and accompanying documents (1852 Dec 14)</p>
      <p> J. Thompson Graham solicits money for the American Emigrant's Friend Society whose object is to "afford protection from fraud, imposition &amp; extortion to all foreign immigrants of whatever class, nation or creed, and procure for them situations
        free of charge." (1852 Oct 24)</p>
      <p> William A. Graham (1804-1875), Secretary of the Navy, concerning the applications of various persons for assistance or for government positions such as the Virginian Mr. Chapman for purser in the Navy, a term of shore duty for Purser Forrest of the
        U.S.S. Ohio, David Taylor of North Carolina prosecuting a claim in the Indian Bureau, the application of William E. Hopkins for a commission upon the frigate Cumberland, the appointment of Tobias Wolfe as Naval Storekeeper at Memphis, the application
        of Commander John Rudd for a command in the Mediterranean Squadron, and inquires about the circumstances surrounding the death of James H. Norwood, Indian Agent, who was killed at Sergeants Bluff on the Missouri River (1850-1852)</p>
      <p> Horace Greeley (1811-1872) discusses the advantages of his new <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Whig Almanac</title> which he sends to Alexander H. H. Stuart, "I have endeavored in
        this Almanac to condense into a single view the essential characteristics of the two great antagonist parties which now so evenly divide the country. I think this view, if generally circulated, will exert a salutary influence on the formation of
        political sentiment in our country and that this may be felt, even in the approaching Presidential contest." (1852 Jan 25)</p>
      <p> F. Gremger asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to visit the State Agricultural Fair of New York (1851 Sep 3)</p>
      <p> William Grever asks Stuart to loan him enough money to pay off James J. Trotter in return for a deed of trust upon all his property (1850 Oct 3)</p>
      <p> Benjamin Edwards Grey supplies a testimonial for John B. Temple and explains why he is willing to recommend Colonel Irwin to a clerkship (1852 Mar 17)</p>
      <p> George G. Grove asking for his distributive share of the funds of the B. Buler estate (1851 Oct 12)</p>
      <p> Francis Grund asks for copies of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Report for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The New York Herald</title> and other newspapers (1851)</p>
      <p> Hiland Hall (1795-1885) suggests that Judge Thornton's name should precede Mr. W[?]'s in the Secretary's instructions (1851 Sep 20)</p>
      <p> Nathan Kelsey Hall (1810-1874) invites Alexander H. H. Stuart to Buffalo for a little reception for President Fillmore at the conclusion of his term and asks him to convince William A. Graham to attend as well (1853 Jan 5); and writes about Fillmore
        wondering if the remaining Fillmore Cabinet members would attend a reunion at Buffalo (1871 Jan 5)</p>
      <p> J.K. Hanson encloses a letter from Hugh W. Sheffey referring to the bounty land warrant of his cousin Celly (1852 Apr 3)</p>
      <p> J. Hardesty, President of the Rough and Ready Club of Rockingham County, which procured a silver pitcher to be presented to Alexander H. H. Stuart as a tribute (1848 Oct 25)</p>
      <p> Kenton Harper writes enclosing the wills of Alex Grove and Lewis K Terrill and their effects from Camp Buena Vista following the Mexican War (1847 Dec 13); congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment as Secretary of the Interior (1850 Sep
        14); mentions his service as commandant of the Port of Parras in the Mexican War (1850 Sep 30); discusses his appointment to the Chickasaw Indian Agency (1851 Mar 18); his report concerning affairs at the Chickasaw Agency and his concern that there are
        many white persons living in the Agency without regular permission (1851 Sep 15); concern over the run-down condition of the Agency farm and house, cost of hiring "a negro woman who belongs to an Indian," and the probability that he will only stay for
        one year (1851 Sep 15); encloses a copy of his letter to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, L. Lea, about purchasing farming implements for "the Caddos" and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence to have his son, George K. Harper, appointed agent
        for the purchase (1851 Sep 22); the complaints from the Chickasaws about the wild tribes trespassing upon their territory, a recent visit from the chief of the Caddos, George Washington, who said that his tribe had been driven out of Texas, and brought
        up to this country by his father, Chief Chonena, who asked for and received a strip of land on the Washita from the General Council of the Choctaws, producing a certificate signed by George Folsom, one of the Choctaw District Chiefs, to prove what he
        said. The Chief also said that General Armstrong had promised them farming implements and other tools so they could settle down on the land allotted to them by the Choctaws, in a group of about 300 to 400. An eleven year old Mexican girl rescued from
        Indian captivity was left in his care by his predecessor, Colonel Long and he asks what is to be done with her (1851 Sep 22); and his investigation of charges of a wagonload of liquor being brought into the Indian Territory for sale (1851 Oct 5).</p>
      <p> J. Morrison Harris, Maryland Historical Society, informs Alexander H. H. Stuart of his honorary membership (1850 May 20)</p>
      <p> Judge N. Harrison, Salt Sulphur Springs, Monroe County, West Virginia, writes concerning several suits in his court and business matters involving Alexander H. H. Stuart ([1869] Sep 3)</p>
      <p> Solomon George Haven (1810-1861) hopes that Alexander H. H. Stuart will make a great impact in politics in the Old Dominion, and remarks about his own area, "I cannot tell you much of politics in this section [of New York ], there is almost a torpor.
        I have no choice between the democrats and the Republicans. The former is made up of the foreign votes here &amp; the latter partly in the same way and partly of the very dishonest men amongst our native born citizens. The Americans have a most worthy
        state ticket in this State... Today the chances are in favor of the Republicans carrying the state but the battle has yet got to be set in array before results can be foretold. Perhaps the result of the struggle in Kansas and a full opening of Congress
        is necessary to give any form whatever, to the future" (1857 Oct 8).</p>
      <p> A.M. Hay, his cousin, discusses the loss of her husband and the death of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's father, her plans to join her sister Mary in Athens, Greece, to help her run a boarding house for the upper class Greek girls attending the mission
        school, and requests Alexander H. H. Stuart 's aid in securing letters of introduction from Mr. Webster to the various consuls at ports of call along the way (1852 Aug 25)</p>
      <p> T.S. Haymond explains the causes of the defeat of the Whig candidate for Governor of Virginia, George William Summers (1804-1868) in the recent election, in his area of Virginia, the northwestern section of the state [ Monongalia County, West
        Virginia ?] (1851 Dec 20)</p>
      <p> Isaac Hazlehurst asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart send him copies of his articles signed "Madison" in reference to the American question (1857 Jun 24)</p>
      <p> Richard H. Henderson, Virginia Colonization Society, refers to the "true policy of Virginia to keep down the free colored population of the state: that her legislature originated the scheme for colonizing this population beyond the borders of the
        United States; that appropriations have been well received by the people" and recommends extending the act to those slaves set free by wills; and "The prohibitions as to the admission of free blacks in the non- slaveholding states are well known; and,
        should the other southwestern states follow the example set them by Mississippi as they soon will, either a channel must be opened through which this population may flow off to Africa, or it will increase amongst us to a most mischievous extent." (1837
        Oct 28)</p>
      <p>Professor Joseph Henry, Smithsonian Institute, letter of introduction for Mr. F. [Bonynge] the author of a work on the culture of tea and indigo in the United States (1852 Aug 4)</p>
      <p> Britton A. Hill writes enclosing his newspaper articles defending Alexander H. H. Stuart 's decision in the Labeaume land grant case which was attacked in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic"
          xlink:href="">The St. Louis Republican</title> by the claimant Maguire (1852 Feb 6 &amp; 9)</p>
      <p> William L. Hodge encloses a newsclipping about the decision of Millard Fillmore not to be a candidate for the Presidency and how much such a declaration will injure Fillmore and the party (1852 Jan 20)</p>
      <p> J.E. Holmes asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to recommend to the President that he increase the salary of District Judge Hoffman in San Francisco, California, lest he leave and an inferior officer replace him (1851 Oct 25)</p>
      <p>Rev. Samuel Rutherford Houston to Dr. John J. Moorman seeking Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence to have him appointed Principal of the Institution for the Deaf and Dumb in Staunton, Virginia (1852 Feb 24)</p>
      <p> M.U. Houston both letters discuss the Wheeling Bridge case in which a suit was brought alleging that the Wheeling Bridge was not suitable for railroad purposes and Alexander H. H. Stuart 's role in the matter (1850 Mar 16 &amp; Jun 8)</p>
      <p> Benjamin Chew Howard refers to the Wheeling Bridge case and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart wishes his brief to be inserted in his argument (1852 Jul 30)</p>
      <p> Robert Hull acknowledges the receipt of a check which makes them even and encloses a graphic and highly complimentary sketch of Mr. Alexander H. H. Stuart from a Boston paper (1851 Oct 3)</p>
      <p> Andrew Hunter writes about the "Beeler Case" and wishes to receive his administration fee now in Alexander H. H. Stuart 's hands (1851 Nov 27); and comments on his grief that Jefferson County has elected two Democrats to the Legislature, mentions
        other items about local Virginia politics, and the dissatisfaction of the voters at Harpers Ferry due to certain army regulations (1851 Nov 27 &amp; Dec 9)</p>
      <p> R.M.T. Hunter (1809-1887) asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to send an estimate of the expense of the wings of the Capitol to be included in the Civil and Diplomatic Bill (1852 Feb 3)</p>
      <p> John Daniel Imboden (1823-1895) writes concerning the suit of Daniel Mosby against Thomas Johnson and Thomas Turk over possession of a tract of land and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart has made any arrangements for someone to take over his legal cases
        (1850 Sep 23); his introduction of a series of land resolutions concerning the distribution of the proceeds from the sale of public lands approved by an act of Congress on September 4, 1841, and the possible use of such funds for the purpose of
        education, and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to get a clerk to make a brief statement as to what appropriations of land have been made for educational and internal improvements, to what states, when, and for what specific objects, has hopes of carrying
        the Central Railroad this session along with other internal improvements, the great excitement over the next Presidential election with Millard Fillmore being the choice of the Virginia Whigs with Alexander H. H. Stuart being mentioned as the
        Vice-Presidential candidate (1852 Jan 31); writes again concerning the great Central line of improvement through Virginia, especially a proposition to construct a railroad from Covington to the Ohio River on state account and asks if he can negotiate
        the sale of stock in London or New York (1853 Jan 22)</p>
      <p> Joseph K. Irving, San Francisco, writes through W.D. Fair, praising the fidelity of James M. Crane, editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The California Courier,</title> to Whig
        principles and doctrines, discusses "the gross frauds and outrageous wrongs inflicted and committed by the [Locofocos], in the matter of the contested seats" (1851 Mar 4); and introduces Dr. Wozencraft, California Indian agent (1852 Nov 30)</p>
      <p> G.W. Israel asks for a donation for a seminary to train teachers of moderate circumstances to educate the lower classes (1853 Feb 8)</p>
      <p> S.D. Jacobs refers to changes of mail routes proposed by R.G. Harmon (1851 Nov 13)</p>
      <p> John Janney (1798-1872) writes concerning the necessity of resigning his position, as the Commissioner to West Virginia, due to his poor eyesight, unless the Legislature decides to settle the state debt question by agreeing to pay two-thirds of the
        debt and repudiating the balance, leaving the creditors of the state of Virginia to look to West Virginia for the residue (1866-1867)</p>
      <p> G.N. Johnson concerning the legal case of the Bank of the United States vs Samuel Leake (1840 May 14)</p>
      <p> R.[G.] Johnson writes about postponing the argument in a legal case, "the only question to be argued in the brief case, is, whether the act of Congress does not legalize the Brief" (1850-1853 all about this case)</p>
      <p> William B. Kayser notifies Alexander H. H. Stuart that Dr. Hall has received payment through the Finley estate and has remitted five hundred dollars to Alexander H. H. Stuart drawn on the Bank of Winchester (1852 Sep 24)</p>
      <p> John P. Kennedy (1795-1870) tries to secure a clerkship for a friend, Mr. Ridgate (1850 Sep 18); regards "every man now who places the Compromise [of 1850 ?] in the front of his creed a good and true Whig -and every convert to the Administration on
        that ground a new recruit to the standard of Whig principles" (1851 Apr 17); arrangements made for the ceremony connected with the committee on the Inauguration of the Statue (1853 Jan 7); attempts to persuade Alexander H. H. Stuart to accompany
        himself and Mr. Millard Fillmore on a trip south to Richmond, Charleston, Savannah, and then on to Cuba, West Indies, New Orleans and thence to Kentucky and home (1854 Feb 13)</p>
      <p> Joseph C.G. Kennedy, Census Office, writes about various properties (1847 Jun 17); recommends that Mr. Hall be sent to Richmond to retake the census for that city (1851 Apr 2); mentions Alexander H. H. Stuart 's election to the National Institute
        (1851 Apr 8); beginning in May of 1851, he writes six letters during his trip to Europe to study the European use of statistics and their use in legislation, the census, and agricultural production; visits the Statistical Society of London and
        discusses the ratio of representation, fractions, and population (1851 Jun 3); visits the President of the Board of Trade to get information on the true basis of statistical knowledge (1851 Jun 10); urged to stay and address the British Association for
        the Promotion of Science of which Prince Albert was President, his visits to some of the foremost statistical men connected to British government offices and other nations such as Prussia, France, and Belgium (1851 Jun 23); his description of Berlin
        and Wittenberg, recommendation that a Bureau of Agriculture &amp; Statistics be created along the lines of those in France and Belgium, prediction that America will march to a degree of honor and prosperity that will far exceed any of the old world
        (1851 Aug 7); on recommendation of Baron Humboldt he plans to visit Vienna (1851 Aug 17); at home, the mania for rail and plank roads, political news of Pennsylvania, and his expectation that the Scott Whigs will carry the Presidency (1852 Oct 16);
        discusses the political race between Scott and Harrison in the region of Pittsburgh ([?] Oct 12)</p>
      <p> Kent Lumber Company concerning the payment of drafts incurred by federal agencies (1852 Oct 27)</p>
      <p> Andrew W. Kercheval with a genealogical inquiry about James Wood, a Revolutionary General and Virginia Governor (1867 Feb 14)</p>
      <p> William Kerr seeking whiskey patronage (1851 Nov 14)</p>
      <p> Samuel D. King about California affairs, blames the Whig government for neglecting the state and predicts bad consequences for the upcoming election (1851 Jul 14)</p>
      <p> Jefferson Kinney all three letters deal with business matters such as the sale of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's lots in Staunton for a railroad passenger depot and possible benefits to the town from the railroad (1852)</p>
      <p> Nicholas Kinney refers to the speech of [Mr. Nathaniel Pitcher Tallmadge ?] concerning the Bankruptcy Bill, the Locofocos, his disappointment with his friend [ Thomas Walker?] Gilmer, the conversion of David W. Patteson, who is a possible candidate
        for Congress, to Methodism (1841 Sep 3); sends a copy of letter from the Rev. B.M. Smith concerning a rumor that Alexander H. H. Stuart contradicted his statement about Dr. Ticknor's qualifications as assistant physician at the Asylum (1851 Feb 18
        &amp; 26); the strong position of the Whig party at present (1851 Feb 26)</p>
      <p> R.H. Kinney asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to pursue the military claim of the heirs of Dr. Roberts (1841 Jun 25)</p>
      <p> William Kinney reports on several court cases and discusses political appointments, especially Mr. Hagarty for the Liverpool consulate, and Alexander H. H. Stuart 's vote to rescind the 21 rule (1841 Jun 13); complains about the behavior of the Whig
        Congress so far, discusses Alexander H. H. Stuart 's outline of his plan of operations for this session and not fixing the ratio of representation under the new census for the next Congress, his fear that the Locofocos will gain influence in the
        Virginia State Legislature, the resignation of "Extra Billy" [Governor William Smith ] from his seat in the Senate and his hopes that the House of Representatives would give the seat to Extra "for really I consider him a great nuisance in the Senate,"
        believes that Webster's objections to the appointment of Hagarty to the consulate of Liverpool not valid as he [wrongly !] thinks Nicholas Trist was born in Louisiana and is not a Virginian, and discusses his [Kentz?] suit at length (1841 Jun 23);
        argues that the success of the suit of Porterfield vs Clark hinges on proving that the country in question belonged to the Cherokees in 1779, found out that Silas E. Burrows is the favorite of Webster for the Liverpool consulate, while the leading
        merchants of New York favor Hagarty, and says Tucker will accept the professorship of law on condition that they will let him reside out of the precincts of the University [of Virginia] (1841 Jul 22); reports that they have just finished the battle for
        Speaker of the Virginia Legislature with the election of [Valentine Wood] Southall considered a Whig victory, "we had a long, I cannot say very able or palatable message from the accidental Gov. of Virginia -coming into office as he did, he ought to
        have been modest" (1841 Dec 6); notes that the introduction of a batch of Federal resolutions into the House have alarmed the Locofocos, especially the one urging the repeal of the Distribution Act, which is popular in the Western part of the state,
        and discusses the prospects of several men for the Governorship of Virginia (1841 Dec 24); reports on election results in Augusta County, urges Alexander H. H. Stuart to write some articles on the Tariff to attract the support of the young farmers and
        mechanics which are being courted by the Democrats as new voters under the new state constitution (1851 Oct 24); discusses the legal case of Woods vs Brooks and expresses his confidence in the election of General Scott (1852 Jul 13); discusses the
        election of cashier at the Bank and the appointment of a marshall for the western district of Virginia (1852 Nov 12 &amp; 30); and discusses the affairs of the Staunton Bank, of which he is President, and the Central Railroad (1852 Dec 23)</p>
      <p> O.B. Knode asks Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence be used to have Colonel Tiernan appointed to a judgeship in Utah (1852 Jan 22)</p>
      <p> F.A. Kownslar writes concerning a debt (1833 Jun 24)</p>
      <p> Daniel Kraber concerning the will of George Lightner with a copy of the will attached (1831 Nov 15)</p>
      <p> J.D. Kurtz concerning cadet appointments (1853 Jan 17)</p>
      <p> John H.B. Latrobe appreciates Alexander H. H. Stuart 's speech and the exposition of the operation of the partnership principle by Alexander H. H. Stuart (1838 Sep 1)</p>
      <p> Joseph S. Leake inquires about the price of one of Mr. Alexander H. H. Stuart 's houses (1831 Nov 3)</p>
      <p> Adam Lee about taking up a land agency in the Transalleghany country (1831 Mar 11)</p>
      <p> John Letcher (1813-1884) hopes Alexander H. H. Stuart has received the seeds sent by his friend Whiting (1856 May 2)</p>
      <p> [Will H. Lewis ?], State Department, sends invitation to dine (n.d.)</p>
      <p> John Tayloe Lomax asks which states are a good market for legal books, expresses his opinion of the need for a protective tariff, his hope that Henry Clay will run as the Whig candidate for President, and the appearance that John C. Calhoun was the
        most prominent of the Locofocos (1842 Jul 8)</p>
      <p> L. Luckett describes his family's trip to Memphis, [Tennessee] (1859 Aug 1); mentions seeing the manufacture of weapons in Richmond and his trip to New Orleans during the Civil War, the condition of the cotton crop, benefits of the war in uniting the
        South, the vast difference between the Southerners and the Yankees, the ironclad [Thunderbolt ?] expected to leave New Orleans this week to go against Fort St. Phillip and Jackson (1861 Sep 2); refers to negotiations with England by the South and
        refers to slavery "our peculiar institution that they hoped was our weakness, is a tower of strength." (1861 Dec 23)</p>
      <p> James Lyons appreciates Alexander H. H. Stuart 's speech upon the subject of a national Bank and recommends the establishment of an Exchange Bank with branches in all of the states and regrets the division that the Bank issue has brought between the
        executive and legislative branches (1841 Aug 20)</p>
      <p> Joseph S. Machie both letters discuss getting the deposition of James M.H. Beale for a trial (1851-1852)</p>
      <p> James MacDonald wants his younger brother appointed a surgeon either in the Navy or Army (1851 Oct 8)</p>
      <p> Redick McKee reports on the progress of the Commission sent to California to visit the hundreds of small Indian tribes and families, his plans to soon visit the tribes along the Mercede River, Mariposa County, the condition of the Whig Party in
        California, the upcoming Senatorial contest, and his desire for the San Francisco Custom House position if it comes open (1851 Jan 28); reports signing the first treaty between the United States and the California Indians at Camp Fremont on March 19th
        with six tribes and the possibility of a treaty with two more tribes near Fresno River, the poor quality of the soil, and his poor opinion of Dr. Wozencraft, California Indian agent (1851 Mar 21); recommends pacifying the Indians with a liberal supply
        of beef and flour, his disagreement with Wozencraft who entered into a contract with Fremont, a political opponent, to supply beef to the Indians before the treaties were ratified by Congress and signed by the President, mentions other scandals and
        improprieties in the Indian agency of California, and feels that reorganization of the whole governmental system in California is necessary (1851 Jun 30); desires the newly created position of "Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Pacific Coast"
        and criticizes the appointment of Lt. Beall as Indian Commissioner for California because he is known as a Democrat (1852 Mar 17 &amp; May 5)</p>
      <p> Thomas M.S. McKennan letter of introduction for William Mills (1851 Oct 29)</p>
      <p> Lewis McKenzie asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to speak before the Bell &amp; Everett Club as a friend of the Union (1860 Aug 31)</p>
      <p> William McLaughlin asks if Staunton will support the invitation by the Franklin Club, Washington College, and the Virginia Military Institute, to Edward Everett to speak in Lexington in order to raise money to purchase Mount Vernon (1857 Nov 23)</p>
      <p> Theodorick B. McRobert thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for the clerkship in the Department of the Interior (1850 Oct 3); includes a letter from Archibald B. Walker concerning a possible pension based on the Revolutionary War service of Alexander Walker
        (1850 Nov 26 &amp; 1851 Jan 8); includes a letter from the Rev. Luther Emerson, of Cob Bottom, Highland County, who promises to write a series of essays on the Scriptural view of slavery if McRobert will help him get some Northern Whig newspapers to
        print them (1851 Dec 18 &amp; 26)</p>
      <p> F. Madera requests a promotion in the Pension Office (1851 Dec 30)</p>
      <p> Allan B. Magruder writes to secure a cadetship for his son, John T. Magruder, at West Point, and asks for a letter of introduction to the Secretary of the Navy on behalf of his brother, Captain Magruder (1851-1853); he also expresses his
        disappointment that Millard Fillmore did not receive the nomination at the Baltimore Convention (1852 Jun 24)</p>
      <p> James Maguire accuses Mr. Bartlett, the Mexican Boundary Survey Commissioner, of embezzling (1851 Mar 29)</p>
      <p> Francis Mallory (1807-1860) congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment to the Cabinet (1851 Jun 13); discusses the case of Mr. Kyle of Norfolk and criticizes Mr. Eubank and his staff over his handling of Kyle's case (1852); and informs
        Alexander H. H. Stuart that the Whigs of Norfolk want the postmaster position to go to John P. Leigh when Mr. Cohen dies (1852 Sep 29)</p>
      <p> N. Marmion to Messrs. Baldwin &amp; Stuart, Attorneys-at-Law, concerning the debt of George Nicholson (1834 Mar 6 &amp; Aug 21)</p>
      <p> Timothy Marmion writes concerning business matters (n.y. Dec 21)</p>
      <p> J.K. Marshall writes concerning a debt owed by Messrs. Harman &amp; Garber (1852 Jan 30)</p>
      <p> Thomas A. Marshall inquires if Alexander H. H. Stuart can help him determine if James M. Moffit is deceased, Moffit was a plaintiff in the legal case of Miller heirs vs Boatman (1833)</p>
      <p> Thomas Martin notifies Alexander H. H. Stuart that his father, Pleasant Martin, has moved to Tennessee (1830 Jul 27)</p>
      <p> William Martin discusses the upcoming Virginia election for governor and the need for Governor Francis Harrison Pierpont to convince the Legislature to fix the question of the payment of the interest on the public debt (1867 Feb 10)</p>
      <p> Maryland Institute Officers &amp; Managers ask Alexander H. H. Stuart to deliver their "Annual Address" at the opening of the Annual Exhibition of Manufacturers &amp; Machinery (1851 Oct 6)</p>
      <p> James Murray Mason (1798-1871) regrets that he does not have any of the published documents concerning the Wheeling Bridge case, excepting the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href=""
          >Congressional Globe</title> at home (1853 Oct 22)</p>
      <p> [John Young] Mason (1799-1859) recommending John Dabney for some Federal government position (1851 Dec 30)</p>
      <p>Colonel James W. Massie writes concerning a debt owed to Hugh McClure (1871 Apr 17)</p>
      <p> Thomas E. Massie, Santa Fe, New Mexico, introduces D.V. Whiting, as knowledgeable of modern languages (1852 May 5)</p>
      <p> Joel E. Matthews writes concerning the legal case of Matthews vs Minzes (1851-1852)</p>
      <p> Tyre Maupin informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that the Rough and Ready Club of Rockingham County plan to present him with a silver pitcher for his services to the Whig Party (1848 Sep 3); asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart knows whether James Madison ever
        offered a Cabinet position to General Scott and informs him that he plans to vote for Scott now that he has the Whig nomination (1852 Jul 17)</p>
      <p> R. Mayo asks for a favorable review of his book now before the Pension Committee of the Senate (1852)</p>
      <p> Thompson G. Martin writes concerning his efforts to sell some Alexander H. H. Stuart land for them in Scott County, Virginia, and Tennessee (1831, 1834)</p>
      <p>Members of the Virginia Legislature names Whig candidates favored by themselves for several positions (n.d.)</p>
      <p>Memoranda of A.H.H. Stuart while Secretary of the Interior, chiefly concerning appointments and removals for positions in the government under his jurisdiction (ca. 1851-1853)</p>
      <p> C.F. Mercer, President of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company, writes to Alexander H. H. Stuart as their representative (1832 May 28)</p>
      <p> Hugh Mercer asks Daniel Webster to transfer his son, George Weedon Mercer, from the Second Auditor's Office, to the State Department (1851 Feb 22 &amp; Jul 4)</p>
      <p> [S.]C.M. Merillat asks Alexander H. H. Stuart if he knows if Congress plans on raising the duties on foreign iron in the near future as he has interests in an iron rolling mill and they need to decide what to do with it now that it has suspended
        operations (1852 Jun 1)</p>
      <p> C.H. Merritt sends Alexander H. H. Stuart a ring made out of native gold of New Mexico (1851 Sep 30) and introduces Judge Houghton of New Mexico (1851 Oct 20)</p>
      <p> Thomas J. Michie (1795-1873) writes concerning various legal cases (1845 Aug 1; 1850 Dec 19; 1852 Jan 18 &amp; 29 and Oct 15); congratulates him on his appointment to the Cabinet and expresses his hopes that the Administration will benefit from any
        good will generated by the Compromise of 1850, his regret at being without Alexander H. H. Stuart 's companionship during his stay in Washington, and offers to help with any of his legal cases when he is not on the other side (1850 Sep 15); thanks
        Alexander H. H. Stuart for his gift, comments on the recent election, "for I could not but believe that a majority of the new made vote would be Democratic, &amp; I knew the power of the party which, to make men forget every excellence, &amp; carry out
        the behests of the party...nor are the Whigs less the slaves of such machinery than the Democrats," discusses the plight of Hungarian patriot and statesman, Lajos Kossuth (1802-1894), and mentions "the young Napoleon" [ Napoleon III ] (1851 Dec 29);
        sends a printed copy of his points of law, made in the appeal case of Points, assignee of Hottle vs Crawford, and discusses the case (1852 Jan 14)</p>
      <p> William C. Micou asks for his assistance in a case now before the Supreme Court (1852 Oct 20)</p>
      <p> Daniel F. Miller to Thomas Corwin -asks for Isaac Leffler (1788-1866), a former Whig member of Congress from Virginia, to be appointed to one of the land districts in Iowa; President Millard Fillmore appointed him receiver of public moneys for the
        Chariton land district of Iowa on August 30th (1852 Aug 17)</p>
      <p> Jacob Welsh Miller (1800-1862) introduces George P. [?], of New Jersey, a member of the U.S. &amp; Mexican Boundary Commission (1852 May 5)</p>
      <p> James Miller asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to intervene with John P. Kennedy on his brother's behalf for an appointment in the Navy Department (1852 Dec 1)</p>
      <p> Zophar Mills, Chairman of the Seventh Ward Democratic Whig Association of the City of New York, encloses a copy of the Preamble and Constitution of the Association (1851 Jul 8)</p>
      <p> Joseph L. Mitchell acknowledges the receipt of the agricultural book (1852 Feb 7)</p>
      <p> John Moebus requests Alexander H. H. Stuart to furnish him with the money to reach New York (1852 Jun 22)</p>
      <p> John Moffett writes concerning his unhappiness over the nomination of General Winfield Scott and his fears of a military candidate and Roman Catholics in the election (1852 Jun 27)</p>
      <p> Thomas S. Moffett, cousin of Alexander H. H. Stuart, requests he send one hundred dollars to Richmond (1834 Jan 27)</p>
      <p> Henry W. Moncure asks for a letter of introduction to Abbott Lawrence, the United States Minister to Great Britain, to facilitate his tour of Europe (1852 Jun 9)</p>
      <p> Charles P. Montague volunteers to carry dispatches abroad for the Federal government (1852 Jun 8)</p>
      <p> D.E. Moore expresses dismay at the election of John Tyler as President (1841 Aug 26)</p>
      <p> John K. Moore asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart remember his son, John B. Moore, who was unable to continue his plan of working in the mines due to dysentery caught while waiting in Panama for a ship, if any appointments open up in California (1850
        Nov 27); and expresses his disgust at the nomination of General Scott (1852 Jul 6)</p>
      <p> L.T. Moore writes concerning the Beeler family estate (1851 Oct 10,18, 21)</p>
      <p> Samuel McDowell Moore writes letters concerning political events in Virginia and the Virginia Legislature, including: the "Senatorial Lottery," his own possible candidacy for office in the Virginia Senate to oppose the "unworthy" David W. Patteson, a
        bill for a Railroad from Staunton to Harpers Ferry to Baltimore, the reorganization of the courts, and his opposition to amalgamating the Common Law and Chancery Court (1830 Jan 24); his busy schedule with the Committee on Elections which sent Barbour
        and Davis back to try again, returning the elections to the people for a revote, with no information about Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Senator (1830 Dec 25); passage of the Railway Bill from Staunton to the Potomac, and tells about the nephew of Chief
        Justice John Marshall shooting and killing William Gott after he refused to duel with him (1831 Feb 23-24); news that Jefferson [Kinney?] plans to run as a candidate for the Senate against Patteson and his own indecision about whether to run as well
        (1831 Mar 2); thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for his opinions about Moore running for the Virginia Senate in order to unseat David W. Patteson, speaks about his opposition to the odious amendment to Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Railroad Bill introduced
        into the House of Delegates which prohibited the government from subscribing to any part of the stock, the 29th section of the bill was stricken out, discusses all of his work to secure the passage of the bill as Alexander H. H. Stuart submitted it,
        and mentions the Judiciary Bill (1831 Mar 17); discusses the bill affecting court clerk fees, his decision not to run for the Virginia Senate seat, and the Railroad Bill (1831 Apr 10); furnishes his opinion of the elections at Rockbridge and Augusta,
        Mr. Dorman's efforts for David W. Patteson and against his own candidate (1831 Jun 30, Jul 4 &amp; 5); discusses the bill for internal improvements, the work of the Special Committee regarding the subject of removing free Negroes and Mulattoes, the
        emancipation of slaves, the majority of the Committee refused to pay for the Negroes killed in Southampton, and other propositions concerning slaves and their removal from western Virginia (1832 Jan 5); following Moore's election to the House of
        Representatives, he believes the followers of Martin Van Buren have the political advantage, the President seems anxious to get Daniel Webster into the Democratic Party in order to carry the Senate in their favor, Nullifiers also want Webster to switch
        parties to alienate Southerners, destroy the Union, and establish a Southern Confederacy, the inadvisability of Henry Clay running for President, and mention of Richard M. Johnson of Kentucky as a probable candidate for Vice-President with Van Buren
        (1833 Dec 24); discusses the election of [Littleton Waller] Tazewell (1774-1860) as evidence that the "Old Dominion" is dead set against Martin Van Buren for President and other political matters, and includes an amusing story of his social life (1834
        Jan 11); his concern over the Banking Bill and false accusations against Moore printed by the editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Fincastle Patriot</title> 1834 Apr 7);
        encouraged by the results of the Virginia elections and other political gossip (1834 May 20); discusses the resolutions regarding the Sub-Treasury scheme, Calhoun's speech supporting the scheme, and Clay's speech against it and Calhoun, and mention of
        the Locofoco Party (1838 Feb 22); some of the Whigs uneasy over Alexander H. H. Stuart 's vote on the 21st Rule which vote Moore approved, "I consider the true ground on which to meet the abolitionists is that they are prohibited by the Constitution
        from interfering with our domestic concerns, and we should meet them on the ramparts of the Constitution. And not in endeavoring to defend a rule of order of at least doubtful justice and propriety," and furnishes his version of the history of the
        "abolition humbug" beginning with General Jackson kicking Calhoun out of the "Kitchen Cabinet" and continuing with Calhoun's attempt to fan the flames of sectional division for his own political purposes; and his belief that the Whigs should pass Mr.
        Ewing's Bank Bill with as little alteration as possible, and mentions Extra Billy Smith 's letter expressing his opinion that Tyler will veto any bill chartering a U.S. Bank (1841 June 22); the defeat of the Bank Bill in Congress, Tyler's attack on the
        Whig Party as the enemy of States' Rights, the controversy over the nature of the proposed National Bank and his own solution to the problem, and his contention that the Bankruptcy Bill should not be passed at present (1841 Aug 22); complains about
        [John Minor] Botts giving Whigs a bad name, discusses flaws in the Bank Bill, notes that Whigs are dissatisfied with [William Cabell ?] Rives course in countering the Whig Party, and complains about [Henry Alexander ?] Wise (1841 Aug 27); and discusses
        the Firebaugh Will legal case (1850 Oct 18; 1852 Jan 5 &amp; Mar 16)</p>
      <p> John Moorman recommends the Rev. Samuel R. Houston as Superintendent of the Deaf and Dumb Asylum at Staunton, Virginia (1852 Mar 4)</p>
      <p> [W.?] Morris seeks a position in the State Department (1852 Dec 1)</p>
      <p> C.L. Mosby writes concerning claims against the Thomas Wells estate (1831 May 18); and asks if he knows of a purser position in the Navy for his brother, William W. Mosby (1851 Dec 15)</p>
      <p> [Alexander] Moseley expresses his concern with President Tyler and Edward Everett 's reply to the abolitionists (1841 Jul-Aug); discusses the idea of acquiring Cuba from Spain and the widespread aversion to Spanish rule in Cuba and his hopes that
        [John Minor ?] Botts would not be elected (1851 Jun 13 &amp; Oct 20); believes that Millard Fillmore will be nominated at the Baltimore Convention (1852 Mar 20); the need for a full Whig vote in Virginia to defeat Franklin Pierce (1852 Oct 5 &amp;
        7)</p>
      <p> J.W. Myers questions Stuart about the meaning of President Millard Fillmore 's latest message in regard to military intervention on behalf of the Hungarian Lajos Kossuth or in any European conflict (1851 Dec 11)</p>
      <p> Thomas Nairu writes concerning federal appointments in Iowa (1850 Oct 23)</p>
      <p> C.W. Newton, one of the Commissioners chosen to select a site for the Norfolk Custom House, discusses the matter, and recommends that the other commissioners be retained as superintendents to continue with the construction of the Custom House (1851
        May 1); asks why the delay in the appointment of his friend, Walter H. Taylor (1852 Aug 20); recommends John P. Leigh for the Postmaster position at Norfolk (1852 Sep 29)</p>
      <p> Isaac C. Newton regrets his defence of Bryant who was removed from office by his own misconduct and not through prejudice as he claimed (1853 Jan 15)</p>
      <p> Dr. C.N. Nichols concerning the purchase of " Woodstock, " the farm of Mrs. Brent and a note from John Carroll Brent (1852 Nov 23)</p>
      <p> William Ogden Niles writes concerning the prosecution of parties arrested for frauds upon the Departments of the Interior and the Treasury (1850 Nov 12)</p>
      <p> John A. North furnishes information in several cases in which Alexander H. H. Stuart is listed as Counsel in Judge Thompson's Circuit (1852 Aug 14)</p>
      <p> John A. [Parker ?] thanks Alexander H. H. Stuart for his recent speech on the slavery question and Mr. Lincoln's plan to purchase land to colonize the freed Negroes (1873 Oct 27)</p>
      <p> William Elisha Peters (1829-1906) urges Alexander H. H. Stuart through another faculty member not to use the revenue from the Corcoran fund for the general purposes of the University of Virginia or to any other than the benefit of the Professors
        which will assure the future of the institution (1876 Nov 23)</p>
      <p>[Sir Flinders ?] Petrie, Secretary of the Victoria Institute or Philosophical Society of Great Britain, invites Alexander H. H. Stuart to join the society (1878 Aug 12)</p>
      <p> Eb Phlegar furnishes a table of voting in the precincts of Montgomery County and Pulaski County (1841 Apr 24)</p>
      <p> L.M. Powell expresses his concern over Alexander H. H. Stuart 's fall into the water and tells about the loss of his trunk (1860 Oct 23)</p>
      <p> W.A. Powell statement of interest due (1868 Dec 16)</p>
      <p> William Ballard Preston (1805-1862) discusses the Whig Convention in Philadelphia, the nomination of Zachary Taylor, the vulnerability of Lewis Cass, and mentions [John Minor] Botts (1848 Jun 15)</p>
      <p> Charles Radziminski asks for a leave of absence to be arranged so he can travel to Europe and check on his family whom he has not heard from since his exile from Poland for revolutionary activity in 1834 (1852 Aug 1)</p>
      <p> Robert Ridgway (1823-1870) asks Alexander H. H. Stuart if he would accept the opposition nomination for Governor and discusses others who might accept a position on the ticket (1859 Jan 9)</p>
      <p> Lawrence Riggs writes about the desire of Rev. F.W. Hatch for the Chaplaincy to the U.S. Marine Hospital at St. Louis (1851 Jan 8)</p>
      <p> Alexander Rives discusses the idea of secession, "A vague fear distresses us, lest our people should be maddened by occurrences at the South and dragged after the seceding states. I am clean for keeping the state out of that vortex." He also suggests
        that the Southern representatives meet with their Stephen Douglass allies and agree to serve in Lincoln's Cabinet if asked (1860 Nov 20) and "You can well conceive that I am not favorably inclined to our unceremonious &amp; unexpected transfer to Jeff.
        Davis &amp; Co. I did not like the Convention's adoption of Judge Allen's sophism in the preamble to the Act of Secession; -it is a false gloss and unworthy of the state;" (1861 May 13)</p>
      <p> William Cabell Rives expresses hopes that they can create a great National Conservative Party to preserve the Union and avoid the extremism proclaimed by Mr. Seward in recent speeches in New York (1859 Jan 5); and fears his health will not permit him
        to give the speech on behalf of the Committee to the people of the United States; he died on April 25 (1868 Jan 7)</p>
      <p> William Barton Rogers hesitates to endorse any mining and economical surveys, and mentions that he enjoyed the address of his friend Judge Bradley at the public exercises at the University of Virginia (1881 Jul 7)</p>
      <p> W.H. Ruffner wishes that Alexander H. H. Stuart would receive the nomination for the Vice-Presidency and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to come to Philadelphia to make a speech before the Convention, "A little glorification of Hungary -some leanings
        toward our `Manifest Destiny' -a few digs at `European despotisms' -a compliment to the Sultan -a javelin at Nicholas -in short `much ado about nothing' is all that is needed." (1851 Dec 5)</p>
      <p> Benjamin Rush expresses his admiration for Alexander H. H. Stuart and his efforts to avoid the dissolution of the Union before the Civil War and hopes to further reconciliation between the North and South should he be elected to Congress (1874 Aug
        4)</p>
      <p> John C. Rusmisell discusses the popular election of Joseph Johnson for Governor in Virginia under the new state constitution (1851 Dec 25)</p>
      <p> N[athan] Sargent (1794-1875), author of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Public Men and Events,</title> in several letters that reveal the turbulent condition of American politics
        during the period immediately preceding the Civil War, Sargent urges that articles be published in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Whig</title> supporting his and
        Alexander H. H. Stuart 's positions in the upcoming elections, mentions the controversy over the Crittenden Amendment, violent feelings on both sides of the slavery issue, and urges a meeting of representatives of various Conservative groups who wish
        to work to preserve the Union, hopes for the defeat of John Letcher (1858-1859); and deplores the course of Goggin and Bell of Kentucky, "I can never subscribe to the doctrine that Congress must protect slavery in the Territories; never. We must
        repudiate that vagary." (1859 Aug 12); and discusses the effect of the outbreak at Harpers Ferry (1859 Oct 24)</p>
      <p> R.E. Scott furnishes his views as to the nomination to be made at the Baltimore Convention (1852 May 22)</p>
      <p> Joseph Segar writes concerning the Presidential nomination; his support for Millard Fillmore and his distaste for Scott (1852 Mar 11)</p>
      <p> Hugh W. Sheffey compares the advantages of investing in state bonds and U.S. stock, asks his opinion of "Thompson's Revolution" before the General Assembly which means to reduce the number of circuit courts and increase the pay of judges, the House
        of Delegates will soon begin examining the criminal code, expects passage of the Covington and Ohio Railroad Bill, anxious that all the state internal improvements be completed so that Virginia can tap the great Western wealth, and the bill enlarging
        the limits of Staunton has passed (1848 Feb 12); discusses his recent attempt to pass a bill to reapportion the delegates and senators throughout the Commonwealth and Mr. Scott of Fauquier County 's proposed bill re reapportionment, failure of the bill
        to extend the Louisa Railroad towards Harrisonburg, his concern over the Whig nomination, "Stuart, I am satisfied that the nomination of Mr. Clay will prostrate the Whig party in the South -no young man in the South can for twenty years to come expect
        to rise to any post of honour or distinction if Clay should ever be elected by the Wilmot proviso vote of the North" (1848 Feb 16); the Virginia Whig Convention voted to support Zachary Taylor for the Presidential candidate (1848 Feb 25); notifies
        Alexander H. H. Stuart that an appropriation of six thousand dollars was made by the General Assembly to the Deaf &amp; Dumb &amp; Blind Institution to square its debts and warns him as its President not to come to the General Assembly for more
        assistance (1850 Mar 14); and writes concerning the bounty land warrant of his cousin Celly (1852 Apr 2)</p>
      <p> W.G. [Snethen ?] asks that the Department of the Interior award land sale advertisements to the newspaper <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Virginian</title> edited by Terry and
        Shields (1852 Oct 9)</p>
      <p> Lord Stirling sends a copy of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Democratic Review </title>containing the first of a series of articles concerning his legally established rights in
        British North America (1852 Sep 11)</p>
      <p> Samuel Strong writes concerning the bids for the extension of the marble work of the Capitol (1851 Nov 5)</p>
      <p> James French Strother (1811-1860) asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to write to Mr. Hall and tell him that he believes the bill authorizing the appointment of an assistant agent will pass (1852 Jun 8)</p>
      <p> Alexander H.H. Stuart Letters writes in great detail to Thomas Michie concerning the subjects of internal improvements, especially the James River Company, &amp; the increase of Banking capital and the opposition of Joseph C. Cabell to their plans,
        and the Democratic Party being forced to accept David Campbell as Governor (1837 Jan 29); to an unknown correspondent, tries to correct the allegation by John Minor Botts that the resolution offered by Alexander H. H. Stuart at the extra session of
        Congress in June 1841 was copied by Alexander H. H. Stuart from Botts' resolution and presented as his own and asks for his correspondent to be a witness to what actually transpired (1845 Dec 12); furnishes a testimonial to the worthy service W.D.C.
        Goddard has performed in the Department of the Interior (1852 Jun 30); to his brother, Gerald B. Stuart, writes that William H. Clarke wants a barrel of his best whiskey sent, William Stuart needs a good horse, predicts big battles soon, probably at
        Yorktown, Harpers Ferry, or Manassas Gap, and says of the Convention, "We have a most miserable spirit prevailing in the Convention -a spirit of carping &amp; bitter hostility to Letcher -such men as Harris, Ambler, Garnett seem disposed to assail him
        on every frivolous pretext" (1861 Jun 15); writes to his daughter, Maggie B. Stuart, concerning her schooling (1873 Feb 7); from the University of Virginia, to his mother, Eleanor Stuart, about his brother Archibald Stuart 's engagement (Oct 7); and to
        his wife, informing her that he hoped to be home from Washington soon, neither the Whig nor Democratic Parties can command the full loyalty of their followers in the present debate, and describes his anxiety about his children (n.d.)</p>
      <p> Archibald P. Stuart assures him of his best wishes and support as he leaves for Washington and thanks him for the frock coat and the beautiful wheat (1850 Sep 29)</p>
      <p> Eleanor Briscoe Stuart writes concerning the settling of an estate (n.d.)</p>
      <p> J.E.B. Stuart while at West Point, answers Alexander H. H. Stuart 's questions about the annuity left him by Uncle Chapman (1851 Dec 25); and writes concerning the opportunities in real estate in Kansas where he is now serving at Fort Leavenworth
        (1857 Jan 28)</p>
      <p> Oscar J.C. Stuart writes concerning Alexander H. H. Stuart 's bereavement, the genealogy of his father's family, particularly his grandfather, John Stockton, and comments on the state of Virginia politics (1859 August 8)</p>
      <p> Isaac H. Sturgeon encloses newsclippings concerning the Labaume case (1852 Feb 4)</p>
      <p> George William Summers (1804-1868) describes the death of their friend, Secretary of the Navy Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844), who was killed by the bursting of a gun called "the Peacemaker" on board the U.S.S. Princeton on the Potomac River, near
        Washington, D.C. and what the loss of Secretary of State Abel P. Upshur would mean in the negotiations over the Oregon Territory with the new minister from Great Britain; feels that the quality of this Congress is decidedly inferior to the last, and
        his approval of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's articles in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Richmond Whig</title> (1844 Feb 28); and comments extensively on the "farce" of the
        Democratic-Locofoco nomination of James Polk for President (1844 May 30)</p>
      <p> William T. Sutherlin regrets the error of the people of Virginia at not returning Alexander H. H. Stuart to office, although he was instrumental in restoring Virginia to the Union, Alexander H. H. Stuart was not elected to public office in 1870 (1870
        Nov 9); refers to the speech by William Mahone as a "campaign document" in favor of his Virginia policy and against the free Railroad Law, his desire to get rid of the obligation to build the Cumberland Gap Road and to make several other changes in the
        Act of Consolidation, and expresses his low opinion of Mahone and his "Radicals" (1873 Apr 4)</p>
      <p> [J.H. Tagart ?] insists that Alexander H. H. Stuart accept his invitation to "eat a little Virginia venison with some Maryland canvass back ducks with an old friend" (1852 Nov 28)</p>
      <p> William H. Terrill asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart exchange autographs and photographs with him (1871 Nov 17)</p>
      <p> Lucas P. Thompson writes that various persons have urged him to suggest to Alexander H. H. Stuart that his best chance of election is to join the Know Nothing Party and run as one of their candidates but hesitates because "I entertain a prejudice not
        so much against the principles or what are said to be the principles of the new party as the secrecy of their organization and action" (1855 Jan 21)</p>
      <p> Nicholas K. Trout, Senate of Virginia, addresses the re-adjustment of the public debt question with West Virginia and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart of the fate of several bills in the Legislature (1867 Jan 20)</p>
      <p>Unidentified Letters include the following subjects: the failure to revive interest in an Act promoting a railroad from Staunton to Scottsville or the James River, the need to pursue the James River improvements, especially with the Louisa Railroad,
        but has little hopes of resolution until the settlement of the Bank Bill which he discusses and discusses the selection of a site for the Deaf &amp; Dumb Asylum (1839 Mar 1); the terrible disaster on the lower Mississippi claiming the life of B.B.
        Stuart (1859 May 2); the editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Sandy Valley Advocate</title> writes concerning the development of the great coal field in the Great Sandy Valley
        of Kentucky and asks what the Kentucky Whigs should do in the present political crisis (1859 Aug 27); and a Civil War letter from Bristoe Station, Virginia, where a Confederate soldier sends home fifty dollars in care of Alexander H. H. Stuart ([1861
        ?] Sep 12)</p>
      <p> Upshur County Citizens asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart come and speak to them on the issues of the day and express their support for William Leftwich Goggin (1807-1870) for Governor of Virginia (1859 Apr 6)</p>
      <p> Thomas Walter, Architect for the Extension of the U.S. Capitol, furnishes a report on the cost of the work during the residue of fiscal year (1851 Nov 6)</p>
      <p> Washington College Literary Society requests Alexander H. H. Stuart to give a speech before the Society on July 2nd (1857 Apr 28)</p>
      <p> John Watt asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart will send him a copy of the appendix published in connection with his report on John Brown 's raid on Harpers Ferry, containing extracts from the personal liberty bills passed by several of the Northern states
        (1861 Dec 3)</p>
      <p> Daniel Webster regrets that the information obtained in the Census Records is not particularly useful in answering Alexander H. H. Stuart 's questions about blind persons in the state of Virginia for the Virginia Institute for the Education of the
        Blind but suggests that an agent of the Institute might be given access to the records to compile the necessary information (1842 Aug 2); introduces Fitzhenry Warren of the General Post Office (1850 Oct 2); and regrets that the President has decided he
        cannot appoint Virginians to offices other than local offices (1851 Feb 8)</p>
      <p> William J. Willey warns that "Since the action of the Convention, handing the state of Virginia over to the Confederate states, without the knowledge or consent of the people, like a lot of horses or slaves, the excitement in N.W. Virginia, is
        becoming most intense, and indeed, in some quarters, terrible...The clamor here for a division of the state is becoming loud and universal -I fear it will become uncontrollable" (1861 May 7)</p>
      <p> Robert Winthrop encloses a seal, with a mistaken superscription to "Cha" Winthrop by Dr. Stuart, belonging to his great-grandfather, John Winthrop, who was a Fellow of the Royal Society, discusses family genealogy and the motto on the seal and asks
        him to take care of the seal while it is in his possession (1851 Apr 21); encloses a letter from Judge Thomas C. Manning (present) concerning the Mississippi Bonds question, and mentions Slater's Fund for educating the Freedmen (1882 Apr 28); regrets
        not seeing Alexander H. H. Stuart at the meeting of the Peabody Education Fund of which both he and Alexander H. H. Stuart were Trustees, describes the meeting and discusses politics (1884 Oct 8); discusses the death of Jefferson Davis and his opinion
        of the man (1889 Dec 16)</p>
      <p> Henry Wise (1806-1876) offended at personal references in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Valley Virginian</title> which gave a report on Alexander H. H. Stuart 's speech to the
        Citizens of Augusta County, at Staunton, "On the New Movement" which claimed Governor Wise had opposed the work of Alexander H. H. Stuart and had worked closely with carpet-baggers, Wise asks Alexander H. H. Stuart if he had approved the report and was
        it correct (1869 Feb 3); a copy of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's reply to Wise, in his speech he referred to, "parties holding the most antagonistic opinions, and having the most diverse objects in view -one party desiring the adoption of the Underwood
        Constitution, while the other was unalterably opposed to it -This while Governor Wells &amp; his committee were assailing our proposition in Washington, Governor Wise &amp; others, were attacking it at home -Thus extremes seem to meet, &amp; the
        singular spectacle was presented of Gov. Wells &amp; Gov. Wise, who probably held no other opinion in common, pulling together as it were in the same team, in opposition to the scheme" (1869 Feb 5); Wise reiterates his opposition to the "New Movement"
        and opposes both Governor Wells and "Negro Suffrage" (1869 Feb 8)</p>
      <p> R.N. Wood discusses members of the American Party recently elected to Congress and fears that unless they can unify the old Whigs with the "American Organization" Millard Fillmore will not be re-elected (1856 Apr 13)</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List </head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e778">
        <did>
          <unittitle>SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE OF THE STUART-BALDWIN FAMILY</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e782">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Martha S. Baldwin to Briscoe Gerard Baldwin, with his reply</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e790">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Barbour to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 &amp; 1831</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e798">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G.A. Baxter to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1807 Sep 29</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e806">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Beverley to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1791-1803</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e814">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.C. Breckinridge to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1788-1815</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e822">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Gerald Briscoe to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1794-1796, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e830">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cuthbert Bullitt to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790 &amp; 1823</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e838">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph C. Cabell to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 Feb 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e846">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Arthur Campbell to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1798</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e854">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Coalter to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812 Nov 6</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e863">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George Davis to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1792 Aug 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e871">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. Gamble to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1791-1800</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e879">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hugh Holmes to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814-1823</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e887">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Chapman] Johnson to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e895">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Lewis to [Dabney Carr ?]</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1768 Jan 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e903">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Lewis to Thomas Jefferson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1772 Oct 4</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e911">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. Marshall to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e919">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George Mathews to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1791 &amp; 1794</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e927">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James D. McCutchen to Joseph Janney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 Mar 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e935">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Andrew Moore to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1794, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e943">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Garrett Peterson to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 Jan 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e952">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Preston to William Anderson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1783 Jan 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e960">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Andrew] Reid to Thomas J. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1807 Sep 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e968">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander Farish Robertson Correspondence</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 &amp; 1921</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e976">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Steele to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1792 Mar 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e984">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Sterritt to Joseph Janney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">837 Jul 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e992">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Eleanor (Briscoe) Stuart to Thomas J. Stuart and Margaret Briscoe</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806-1808</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1000">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Martha M. Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor (Briscoe) Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[n.y.] Apr 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1008">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Charles Anderson] Wickliffe to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 Feb 26</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1016">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Wirt to Archibald Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 Aug 10</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e1024">
        <did>
          <unittitle>SERIES II: MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS OF THE STUART FAMILY</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1028">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Architectural Drawing</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1036">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Engraving of Alexander H.H. Stuart by Danforth, Baldwin &amp; Company</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1044">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1792-1888</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1052">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers - Accounts &amp; Receipts</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1797-1857, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1060">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers - Indentures (Some Copies)</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1836</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1068">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers - Land Plats</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1770-1896, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1076">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers - Legal Cases</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">789-1879, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1084">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial &amp; Legal Papers - Wills of Alexander Stuart, Robert Stuart, Chapman J. Stuart, &amp; Alexander H.H. Stuart (Copies)</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1890</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1092">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Military Papers of Captain George M. Cochran, Jr., Quartermaster, 52nd Virginia Infantry, Pegram's Brigade, Early's Division</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857, 1862-1864</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1100">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Material</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1852, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1109">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852, 1867, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1117">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers re the Settlement of Archibald Stuart's Estate</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805-1849</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1125">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Speeches (Drafts) by Alexander H.H. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e1133">
        <did>
          <unittitle>SERIES III: CORRESPONDENCE OF ALEXANDER H.H. STUART</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>*Unless otherwise noted the recipient of the letter is Alexander H.H. Stuart*</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1140">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Abolitionist (Unidentified)</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Jun 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1148">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William H. Allen</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.y. May 13</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1156">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Appomattox County, Virginia, Rough &amp; Ready Club</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Sep 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1164">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Carey Baird</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Nov 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1172">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.C. Baldwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Jan 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1180">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John B. Baldwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1843?]-1869</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1188">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph Baldwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1850</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1196">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph G. Baldwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 Sep 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1204">
          <did>
            <unittitle>I.L. Barbour</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866 Dec 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1213">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A.W. Barton</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Apr 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1221">
          <did>
            <unittitle>S.S. Baxter</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1229">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas H. Benton</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[ca. 1851-1853]</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1237">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Berford &amp; Company</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Apr 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1245">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dr. Edmund Berkeley</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Jan 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1253">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James B. Bingham</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Sep 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1261">
          <did>
            <unittitle>David Alexander Bokee</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Oct 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1269">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Patrick Brady</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857, 1867-1869</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1277">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Louisa Brooks</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.y. Mar 18</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1285">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander S. Brown</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857-1858</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1293">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph Rodes Buchanan</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Feb 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1302">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John C. Bullitt</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871 Oct 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1310">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William M. Burwell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1318">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.S. Calvert</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868 Jan 21</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1326">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel D. Campbell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 Nov 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1334">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lewis Cass</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1342">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Cassin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Apr 13</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1350">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Katherine Chase</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883 Mar 18</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1358">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H. Chrisman</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Dec 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1366">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Bolivar Christian</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 Jan 18</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1374">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.M. Conrad</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Apr 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1382">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Wilson Corcoran</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885 Oct 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1391">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Corwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Jul 10</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1399">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.A. Cowardin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850, 1873</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1407">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Jordan Crittenden</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Sep 26</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1415">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Claudius Crozet</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Jun 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1423">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Rector E.A. Dalrymple Recommendation of Thomas B. Edelin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1431">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John W. Daniel</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1877 Jul 18</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1439">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.D. Davidson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1447">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Garrett Davis</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843-1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1455">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George M. Davis</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1463">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Wallace Davis</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 2</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1471">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Crosby Dawson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1480">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Horace H. Day</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Feb 7 &amp; Mar 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1488">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Wills DeHass</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1496">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William D. Delany</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1504">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Devens, Jr.</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 May 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1512">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Dickson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Apr 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1520">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dorothea Lynde Dix</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1851-1853]</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1528">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James B. Dorman</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1536">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.L. &amp; John Doyle</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1544">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G.G. Dyer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Sep 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1552">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.L. Edwards</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 May 19 (&amp; 1776 Feb 29)</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1560">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Vespasian Ellis</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Jun 10</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1569">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Erie Railroad Company Board of Directors</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1577">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edward Everett</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1585">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles James Faulkner</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1593">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Millard Fillmore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1854</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1601">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Millard Fillmore to Daniel Webster</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Apr 2</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1609">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edward H. Fitzhugh</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Mar 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1617">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Edward] Fontaine</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Mar 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1625">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John S. Gallaher</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1633">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert H. Gallaher</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1641">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander Galt</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 31</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1649">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. Garland</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Feb 2</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1658">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William H. Garland</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850, 1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1666">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Garnett</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1674">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George Washington's Birthday Celebration Committee, Rome, Georgia</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">868 Feb 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1682">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.T. Gibson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1690">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.M. Gilliam</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Mar 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1698">
          <did>
            <unittitle>T.H. Gilmer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Sep 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1706">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Gilmer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 Dec 13</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1714">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.W. Gilmer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Apr 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1722">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William I. Goggin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850, 1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1730">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G. Goldenberg</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Feb 2</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1738">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.T. Gordon</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1747">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.A. Gorman</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Dec 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1755">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. Thompson Graham</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Oct 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1763">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William A. Graham</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1771">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Horace Greeley</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jan 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1779">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F. Gremger</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Sep 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1787">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Grever</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Oct 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1795">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Benjamin Edwards Grey</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Mar 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1803">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George G. Grove</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1811">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Francis Grund</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1819">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hiland Hall</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Sep 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1827">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nathan Kelsey Hall</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853, 1871</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1836">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.K Hanson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Apr 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1844">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. Hardesty</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Oct 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1852">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Kenton Harper</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847, 1850-1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1860">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. Morrison Harris</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 May 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1868">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Judge N. Harrison</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[?] Sep 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1876">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Solomon George Haven</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Oct 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1884">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A.M. Hay</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1892">
          <did>
            <unittitle>T.S. Haymond</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1900">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac Hazlehurst</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Jun 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1908">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Richard H. Henderson, Virginia Colonization Society</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Oct 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1916">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Professor Joseph Henry</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 4</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1925">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Britton A. Hill</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 6 &amp; 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1933">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William L. Hodge</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jan 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1941">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.E. Holmes</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1949">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Rev. Samuel R. Houston</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1957">
          <did>
            <unittitle>M.U. Houston</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1965">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Benjamin C. Howard</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jul 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1973">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Hull</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1981">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Andrew Hunter</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 27 &amp; Dec 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1989">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.M.T. Hunter</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1997">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Daniel Imboden</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2005">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.K Irving</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2014">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G.W. Israel to Alexander H.H. Stuart through President Millard Fillmore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Feb 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2022">
          <did>
            <unittitle>S.D. Jacobs</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 13</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2030">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Janney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866-1867</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2038">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G.N. Johnson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 May 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2046">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. Johnson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2054">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William B. Kayser</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Sep 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2062">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John P. Kennedy</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1854</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2070">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph C.G. Kennedy</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1847]-1870</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2078">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Kent Lumber Company</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Oct 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2086">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Andrew W. Kercheval</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Feb 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2094">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Kerr</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2103">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Samuel] D. King</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2111">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jeffers Kinney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2119">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nicholas Kinney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 &amp; 1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2127">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.H. Kinney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Jun 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2135">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Kinney</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2143">
          <did>
            <unittitle>O.B. Knode</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jan 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2151">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F.A. Kownslar</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 Jun 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2159">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Daniel Kraber</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2167">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.D. Kurtz</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Jan 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2175">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H.B. Latrobe</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Sep 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2183">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph S. Leake</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 Nov 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2192">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Adam Lee</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 Mar 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2200">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Letcher</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856 May 2</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2208">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Will H. Lewis ?]</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2216">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Tayloe Lomax</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 Jul 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2224">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L. Luckett</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859-1861</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2232">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Lyons</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Aug 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2240">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph S. Machie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2248">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James McDonald</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2256">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Redick McKee</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2264">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas M.S. McKennan</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 29</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2272">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Louis McKenzie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 Aug 31</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2281">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William McLaughlin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Nov 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2289">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Theodorick B. McRobert</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2297">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F. Madera</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2305">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Allan B. &amp; John T. Magruder</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1853</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2313">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Maguire</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Mar 29</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2321">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Francis Mallory</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2329">
          <did>
            <unittitle>N. Marmion to Messrs. Baldwin &amp; Stuart, Attorneys-at-Law</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2337">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Timothy Marmion</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.y. Dec 21</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2345">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.K. Marshall</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jan 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2353">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas A. Marshall</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2361">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Martin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 Jul 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2370">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Martin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Jan 16 &amp; Feb 10</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2378">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Maryland Institute, Officers &amp; Managers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 6</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2386">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Murray Mason</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Oct 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2394">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[John Young] Mason</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2402">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James W. Massie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871 Apr 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2410">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas E. Massie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 May 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2418">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joel E. Mathews</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2426">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Tyre Maupin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848, 1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2434">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. Mayo</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2442">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thompson G. Martin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831, 1834</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2450">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Members of the Virginia Legislature to the President and Members of the Cabinet</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2459">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memoranda of Alexander H.H. Stuart while Secretary of the Interior</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2467">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.F. Mercer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">832 May 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2475">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hugh Mercer</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 4 &amp; Feb 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2483">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[S.] C.M. Merillat</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2491">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.H. Merritt</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Sep 30, Oct 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2499">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas J. Michie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2507">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William C. Micou</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Oct 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2515">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Daniel F. Miller to Thomas Corwin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2523">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jacob Welsh Miller</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 May 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2531">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Miller</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Dec 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2539">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Zophar Mills</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jul 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2548">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph L. Mitchell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2556">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Moebus</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2564">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Moffett</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2572">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas S. Moffett</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 Jan 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2580">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry W. Moncure</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2588">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles P. Montague</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2596">
          <did>
            <unittitle>D.E. Moore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 &amp; 1841</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2604">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John K. Moore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 &amp; 1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2612">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L.T. Moore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Oct 10, 18, 21</unitdate>
            <container type="box">box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2620">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel M.D. Moore</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2628">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Moorman</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Mar 4</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2637">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[W.?] Morris</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Dec 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2645">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.L. Mosby</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 &amp; 1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2653">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Alexander] Moseley</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2661">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.W. Myers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2669">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Nairu</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Oct 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2677">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C.W. Newton</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2685">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac C. Newton</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Jan 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2693">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dr. C.N. Nichols</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Nov 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2701">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Ogden Niles</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Nov 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2709">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John A. North</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 14</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2717">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John A. [Parker?]</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873 Oct 27</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2726">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Elisha Peters</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1876 Nov 23</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2734">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F. Petrie</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878 Aug 12</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2742">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Eb Phlegar</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Apr 24</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2750">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L.M. Powell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 Oct</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2758">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.A. Powell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868 Dec 16</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2766">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Ballard Preston</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Jun 15</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2774">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Radziminski</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Aug 1</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2782">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Ridgway</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Jan 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2790">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lawrence Riggs</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2798">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander Rives</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">860-1861</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2806">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Cabell Rives</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 &amp; 1868</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2815">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Barton Rogers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 Jul 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2823">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.H. Ruffner</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2831">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Benjamin Rush</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1874 Aug 4</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2839">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John C. Rusmisell</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Dec 25</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2847">
          <did>
            <unittitle>N. Sargeant</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858-1859</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2855">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.E. Scott</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 May 22</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2863">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Joseph Segar</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Mar 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2871">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hugh W. Sheffey</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848-1852</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2879">
          <did>
            <unittitle>W.G. [Snethen ?]</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Oct 9</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2887">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lord Stirling</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Sep 11</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2895">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Strong</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 5</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2904">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James French Strother</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Jun 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2912">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander H.H. Stuart Letters</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837-1873</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2920">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Archibald P. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Sep 29</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2928">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Eleanor Briscoe Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2936">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J.E.B. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 &amp; 1857</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2944">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Oscar J.C. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Aug 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2952">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac H. Sturgeon</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 4</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2960">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G.W. Summers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 Feb 28, May 30</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2968">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William T. Sutherlin</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1870, 1873</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2976">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[J.H. Tagart?]</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Nov 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2984">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William H. Terrill</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871 Nov 17</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2993">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lucas P. Thompson</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Jan 21</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3001">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nicholas K. Trout</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Jan 20</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3009">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Unidentified Letters to Alexander H.H. Stuart</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839-[1861?]</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3017">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Upshur County Citizens</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Apr 6</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3025">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Walter</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Nov 6</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3033">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Washington College Literary Society</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Apr 28</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3041">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Watt</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 Dec 3</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3049">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Daniel Webster</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842-1851</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3057">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William J. Willey</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 May 7</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3065">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Winthrop</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851, 1882-1889</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3073">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry A. Wise</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1869 Feb 3, 5, 8</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3082">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R.N. Wood</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856 Apr 13</unitdate>
            <container type="box">Box 4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e3090">
        <did>
          <unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3094">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Engraving of Alexander H.H. Stuart by J.C. Buttre</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3100">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Land Grant to Thomas Turk signed by Beverley Randolph</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789 Aug 31</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3106">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Land Grant to [Monticu ?] Allen signed by Robert Brooke</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1796 Mar 30</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3112">
          <did>
            <unittitle>9 Land Grants to Archibald Stuart, agent of the Greenbrier Company, signed by James Monroe</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800 May 12-15</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3118">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Land Grant to Joseph Boyers signed by John Floyd</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 Sep 1</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e3124">
        <did>
          <unittitle>MICROFILM</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Positive copies of microfilms produced by The Library of Virginia</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3131">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Archibald Stuart Papers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1768-1831, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="Reel">M-260 REEL 1</container>
            <physdesc>
              <extent>(75 items)</extent>
            </physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3144">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander H.H. Stuart Correspondence</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830-1844</unitdate>
            <container type="Reel">M-260 (continued)REEL 2</container>
            <physdesc>
              <extent>(40 items)</extent>
            </physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3157">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexander H.H. Stuart Papers</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845-1850</unitdate>
            <container type="Reel">M-261 REEL 3</container>
            <physdesc>
              <extent>(15 items)</extent>
            </physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3170">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Letters, Deeds, Grants, etc. of the Stuart Family</unittitle>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1770-1896, n.d.</unitdate>
            <container type="Reel">M-262 REEL 4</container>
            <physdesc>
              <extent>(45 items)</extent>
            </physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
