<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01376">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01376::A Guide to Letters of the Hardgrove Family)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01376.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01376::A Guide to Letters of the
             Hardgrove Family)//EN" "viu01376.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to Letters of the Hardgrove Family 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1863</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Hardgrove Family, Letters, 1862-1863. 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11106</num></subtitle><author>Special Collections Staff</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">19 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Sue Cuthbertson, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/1/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01376::A Guide to
            Letters of the Hardgrove Family)//EN" "viu01376.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to Letters of the Hardgrove Family 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1863</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11106</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Letters of the Hardgrove Family 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1862-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11106</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">4 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection consists of
         electrostatic copies of four letters, 1862-1863, three from
         Union soldier Lieutenant N.H. Hardgrove to his brother,
         William Hardgrove, and one from Benjamin down to his sister,
         Judith A. Hardgrove.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Hardgrove Family Civil War Letters, 1862-1863, Accession
            #11106, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These copies of Civil War letters were given to the
            Library by Mr. C.L. Redus, Houston, Texas, through Robert
            Rutland, Charlottesville, Virginia, on September 7,
            1993.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Hardgrove Family, from Ohio, had several members in the
         Union Army during the Civil War.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>In the first letter, N.H. Hardgrove, Camp Shiloh,
         Tennessee, to William Hardgrove, Democracy, Ohio, April 26,
         1862, Hardgrove describes his first time on Mississippi soil
         during a reconnaissance near Corinth, Mississippi, on April
         25, joining four other divisions of Pope's and Rosecrans
         (Union) Army of the Mississippi, 1500 cavalry troops and two
         pieces of artillery on a twenty mile march there and back,
         driving the rebels out of their advance camp, and burning all
         of their tents and possessions in retaliation for the rebel
         attack on their camp on Sunday, April 6, during the Battle of
         Shiloh. The federal troops sent seventy- five to eighty shells
         into the Confederate camp before returning with eleven
         prisoners. He also mentions that another division went to
         Purdy, Tennessee, a small place on the Memphis &amp;
         Charleston Railroad, where Union troops captured hundreds of
         prisoners.</p>
      <p>In a second letter, Monterey, Tennessee, May 26, 1862,
         Hardgrove thanks his brother for sending him three dollars
         since he has not been paid yet, mentions his bout with yellow
         jaundice, refers to a hearty meal of hard crackers, salt pork,
         and beans, describes an incident in which a rebel citizen
         tried to steal some commissary stores, and complains about the
         distance from fresh drinking water, "The further south we go
         the worse the water gets." He mentions that General John
         Pope's (1822-1892) division engaged in very hard fighting over
         control of a spring that he guarded with siege guns. Hardgrove
         belonged to the Reserve Corps, which consisted of the First
         Division, commanded by General John Alexander McClernand
         (1812-1900) and the Third Division, commanded by General Lewis
         Wallace (1827-1905). Hardgrove's individual brigade, which was
         located to the extreme right of the Reserve Corps, was busy
         constructing over three miles of breastworks about four miles
         to the rear of the advance. The armies of General William
         Starke Rosecrans (1819- 1898) and General Franz Sigel
         (1824-1902) joined his division. He also talks about the loss
         of men in his regiment through sickness, death, furloughs, and
         other causes, "Six months active service in this wooden
         country uses up men mighty fast. We left Camp Sherman with
         over nine hundred men fit for duty - we now muster five
         hundred for duty." He intends to remain in service as long as
         the conflict lasts, "We are mighty independent with the Staff
         Boys and they know it and are afraid of us. We do just about
         as we please. We ask no favors from them nor do we expect to
         receive any. We have no respect for them and they have none
         for us; we pass them by as we would a dog and they do the
         same."</p>
      <p>Hardgrove's third letter, camp near Helena, Arkansas, July
         27, 1862, mentions his journey after leaving Memphis,
         Tennessee, down the Mississippi River about ninety miles to
         Helena, where General Samuel Ryan Curtis (1817-1866) had his
         headquarters in the residence of Confederate General Thomas
         Carmichael Hindman. Wallace has five thousand men and Curtis
         has about twenty-five thousand on hand and supposes they will
         soon leave for either Little Rock or Vicksburg, where P.G.T.
         Beauregard (1818-1893) has a considerable force. He describes
         their camp routine along the Mississippi River and the
         regiment's use of five hundred pounds of ice a day to keep
         their water fresh. Captain Briggs had gone home on furlough
         the day before they left Memphis and Charles D. Miller of
         Mount Vernon became acting adjutant: "There will be over two
         months pay due us. We have to come down to army rations hard
         crackers and salt pork. Wherever an army encamps it almost
         lays waste to the country. There are large cornfields here
         with a hundred acres or more in them which have been destroyed
         since the army has been here. And in fact everything else.
         There are too many of us here to live well off of the
         country."</p>
      <p>The fourth letter is from Benjamin Downs, Hardenburgh,
         [Ohio?], January 7, 1863, to his sister, Judith A. Hardgrove,
         and refers to the participation of his son, Edward Downs, a
         member of the [26th Regiment 2nd Volunteers?] in the Battle of
         Prairie Grove, Arkansas. His son, who was now in the hospital
         at Fayetteville, Arkansas, believed that a knife and looking
         glass in his pocket saved his life. His wife's brother, Joseph
         Waldorff, was not in the fight because he was guarding the
         provision train four miles back from the front lines. A
         neighbor, William Fineher, was killed in the battle. News had
         just been received about the Battle of Murfeesboro, involving
         a great many of the local men. Downs also mentions that two of
         his brother-in-laws were in the fight at Murfeesboro being in
         the 82nd Regiment Indiana Volunteers commanded by Colonel
         Morton Craig Hunter (1825-1896). His letter discusses news
         about other family members including his brother George's
         children, Leonard, William, and Kate (Hulse) Edminster.
         Apparently Benjamin and Judith's sister Margaret had died
         after childbirth; but their brothers, Curtis and William were
         all well.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
