<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04028">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04028::A Guide to the George F. Brasfield, Jr. Letters to His Parents, 1930-1931, 1947-1953)//EN" "viu04028.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the George F. Brasfield, Jr., Letters to His Parents, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930-1931, 1947-1953</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Brasfield, George F., Jr., Letters to His Parents, 
<num type="collectionnumber">7480-e
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Stephanie Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7/30/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the George F. Brasfield, Jr., Letters to His Parents, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930-1931, 1947-1953</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">7480-e
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">George F. Brasfield, Jr. letters to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">7480-e
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>George F. Brasfield, Jr., Letters to His Parents, 1930-1931, 1947-1953, Accession #7480-e, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The collection was purchased from Beltrone Co., by the University of Virginia Library on July 19, 2007.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>George F. Brasfield was a Second Lieutenant in the First Division of the United States Marine Corps from Petersburg, Virginia and attended Woodberry Forest School in Orange, Virginia and the University of Virginia in Charlottesville, Virginia.  
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of thirty-five letters from George F. Brasfield to his parents and family members describing his tour of duty in Korea from April to August of 1953. His letters refer to his service with a mortar platoon, opinions about the war and his passion for track and pole vaulting. He also mentions a prisoner exchange, the peace treaty with Synghman Rhee, his friendship with Lieutenant General Lewis "Chesty" Burwell Puller and "Easters" celebrations at the University of Virginia. He also briefly mentions Mel Roach, a University of Virginia alumnus who played for the Milwaukee Braves.
</p>
      <p>
With the collection are 22 track and field medals, 1930-1931, 1947-1951, chiefly for pole vaulting, awarded to the Brasfields, Sr. and Jr. at prep school meets.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The letters are arranged in chronological order.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e134">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 1, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>George describes that there is not much fighting due to the peace talks. He also mentions that the decrease in fighting may be a result of the discussion of atomic weapons. He writes that he wishes that they could work out an exchange of prisoners.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e144">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 10, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they have to stay up all night in reserves and that at least when they are on line, there is time to sleep. He describes how they nickname their outposts after beautiful movie stars like Marilyn Monroe so they can feel protective of them. Some of the other outposts are named "Vegas," and "Reno."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e154">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 12, 1953  
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He mentions that a prisoner exchange has been arranged even though it is only for 120 men for 5600 prisoners. He has transferred to a mortar platoon with Able Company which is in reserve. He describes their standing and waiting and their conditions in which they don't shower for weeks. He explains that they would much rather receive mail than food. He wants to get a position in marine aviation.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e164">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 19, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that he should be an expert on mortars by now and that he gets more sleep than the platoon leaders who have to stay up 20 hours a day. He mentions that the Chinese are fighting at the "Reno," "Vegas," and "Carson" outposts.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e174">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 20, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that their platoon is quiet and he is sleeping a lot. He also describes the tunnel mortar bushes where they live. He mentions his desire to vault on the Marines' track team. He is also reading newspapers, books and trying to learn the Russian alphabet.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e184">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 21, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that it is quiet in his platoon and on the front. They have moved out of the tunnel into a bunker. He wishes he were an aviator because they can fire at targets from a distance. He is watching the aviators shoot at the Chinese supply trucks. He describes the c-rations that come with jam and oleo, and no bread.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e194">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 22, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that the war is at a stalemate with both sides being scared of each other. He describes his feelings about his contemporaries getting married and thinks about the spring parties "Easters" that are underway at the University of Virginia. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e204">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 28, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that his platoon is inactive and there are rumors that they will be relieved. He enjoys watching the planes dive and listening to their bombs fall. He also writes that the "goonies" have an amazing amount of small arms that they throw at them.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e214">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they are relocating to practice amphibious landings and their living conditions will improve. He describes the Army, who will be relieving them, as being incompetent. He mentions that they hear celebrations from the Chinese and there is currently no fighting.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e224">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 8, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they are in camp about 26 miles from Seoul, near Korean rice farms. They are having rain showers and great food like fried chicken and ice cream. He mentions the local people and writes that he can't blame the people for stealing when they are starving. He makes disparaging remarks about the Army and how they are singing Marine songs to make the Chinese think that the Marines are still there.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e235">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 13, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes more about the misery of the poor people who are starving in Korea and is very sympathetic to them. He describes his busy schedule of preparing and giving lectures on map reading and small unit tactics.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e245">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 16, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about teaching courses on supply discipline and anti-aircraft defense. He mentions his dislike for teaching and his decision to pass on a military career because of all the standing and waiting that is required in peacetime. He also mentions the difficulty in remembering names because men are so frequently rotated to other sectors. He writes about their enjoyment in playing volleyball and an upcoming trip to Seoul. He describes his men as looking forward to it with great intensity while he dreads it because they can "drink a case of whiskey per man" and he has to get them all back in one piece. He also mentions that [Evan] joins the Raven Society at the University of Virginia.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 23, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about his impressions of Seoul and how there are thousands of little children trying to sell things that they have stolen from other Americans. It is also very commercialized and run down but the people don't want to repair it until the tourists leave.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e265">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 27, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about a regimental track race and winning first place in the 100 yard dash. He mentions that he has had no success with the high jump since he left his prep school, Woodberry Forest School.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e275">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 30, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about their performance of training problems and maneuvers all day. He also mentions that the Army is having a hard time at the "Vegas" outpost.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e285">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 6, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that their Colonel is "a real louse." He mentions that they are supposed to hear something about the peace talks. He also mentions that the University of Virginia does not have a good track coach.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e295">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[Wed] June n. d., 1953,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about his family friendship with General "Chesty" Burwell Puller and how during an inspection from General Puller, the general asks Brasfield why he hasn't won any medals yet. He also mentions that there is no news about Synghman Rhee and the truce.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e305">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 15, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that the South Koreans are angry and demonstrating about the truce. There is an air raid on Seoul and Brasfield wonders why they don't have more of them because they would be very effective. He also writes that after having a lot of diverse entertainers, he would "like to see a good looking white woman for a change."
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e315">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 19, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that Synghman Rhee is not cooperating in the peace talks. [Synghman Rhee postponed a cease-fire by setting free 27,000 North Korean war prisoners that the U. N. had promised to turn over to a neutral commission.] Brasfield also writes about the death of his dog at home and a job offer from his uncle. He also mentions that he is playing the ukulele to pass the time away.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e325">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 22, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that he had the highest score for the battalion rifle team which indicates to him that the "Marines are miserable shots."  He also mentions that the Colonel is displeased at their inspection and as a consequence they will have to work very hard. He also writes that it is very difficult to even get a pair of shoes.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e335">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 30, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they are going to Japan for four days if their flights are not cancelled due to the evacuation of flood refugees in [Kyushu]. He thanks his family for the piece of wedding cake and wedding photographs.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e346">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 5, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes from Camp Fisher, Japan that it has been raining but that they are having a good time, including dancing with Japanese girls. He describes the Japanese as being very gracious even though he does not trust them. He writes that the servants, in particular, will do anything possible to please foreigners.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 12, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they may have an armistice shortly. He is very tired of infantry and being in reserve. He also writes that his wallet is stolen.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e366">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 16, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that he is busy training a new draft. He mentions there is fighting on the Eastern Front but it is far away from him. He is very tired of being in reserve and would prefer to be on line. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e376">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 22, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that peace talks are close to being signed. There are not many air raids, and he wonders why they don't have more during the day. He also writes that he is looking forward to shooting pheasants in October. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e386">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 23, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes a letter to Aunt Bessie about the effects of nuclear weapons as a deterrent for wars.  He doesn't believe that "the fear of atomic [weapons] exceeds [the] nationalistic ambitions of most countries." He also describes the beauty of the countryside with the rice paddies and the green hills.  He mentions that Synghman Rhee won't sign the truce until all of the communists are out of North Korea.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e396">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 26, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>
He writes that the Fifth and Seventh Marines have been "shot up" at the "Berlin,"  "East Berlin," "Vegas," and "Carson" outposts. He is glad that he signed up for the First Marines because they are safely in the rear, miles from the shooting. He believes that the news about a truce is getting better every day and that the Chinese are trying to save face by causing an increase in the fighting.  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e406">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 28, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that the cease-fire was signed last night. Each side has to move back 2000 meters from their present position. He also writes that his remaining time of one year will be very boring.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e416">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 3, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they have changed camps and will probably remain in the new camp for the rest of the time. They are in an undeveloped camp and are using bulldozers to build it. He thinks they will need "a week of sun" to clean up from all of the mud. He also mentions that the Third Division Marines are flying out to relieve them. He wants to get an assignment as an air observer and learn to fly. He also writes about the people that were killed in the last hours before the truce was signed.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e426">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 9, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes about the hard work of building the camp and the complaints from the men. There are arguments among the men due to the strain.  He starts training a new draft and thinks that his tour will receive an additional two months on the remaining time.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e436">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 13, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He describes his Colonel and the new Colonel replacing him. They refer to the new Colonel as Colonel Queeg [from the character Phillip Francis Queeg in the movie, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">The Caine Mutiny</title>]. He writes that many officers are asking for a transfer to escape this Colonel who he says is "hopeless."  He writes that the Colonel is drunk often and unpopular with everyone. He also mentions that they will return through Pendleton. He still hopes to be an air observer. He also writes that [Wilbur] is getting married.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e449">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 20, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that they have been digging for two weeks to prepare their position. They are living in tents with only six other people and electric lights. The food is excellent. He mentions that his battalion was the only one that didn't see action and that they were scheduled to go on line the next day before the truce was signed. He also writes that [Evans] doesn't seem to like being in the service.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e460">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 26, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that there are rumors that they will be coming home in January. He does not think there is anything to keep them over there for another year. He mentions that some of his good friends were in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Life</title> magazine from August 10. He still has not heard any news about being an air observer.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e473">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 30, 1953 
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>He writes that he will be in Korea for a total of fourteen months and he is still waiting to hear about being an air observer. He is going to Seoul for rest and he thinks that it is a boring place. He also writes about Mel [Earl] Roach who attended the University of Virginia and played baseball for the Milwaukee Braves (1953-1954; 1957-1961), the Chicago Cub (1961), and the Philadelphia Phillies (1962).  
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
