<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01489">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01489::Lybrook Family Letters, 1834-1867)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01489.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01489::Lybrook Family Letters,
             1834-1867)//EN" "viu01489.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Lybrook Family Letters 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834-1867</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Lybrook Family Letters, 1834-1867 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11087-a</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">19 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 18, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01489::Lybrook Family
            Letters, 1834-1867)//EN" "viu01489.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-03-01" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Mar 01, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Lybrook Family Letters 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834-1867</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11087-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Lybrook Family Letters 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1834-1867</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11087-a</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">There are 6 items
         in this collection.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Lybrook Family Letters, 1834-1867, Accession #11087-a,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the University of
            Virginia Library from Timothy H. Bakken, Clarendon Hills,
            Illinois, on August 9, 1994.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of six letters, 1834-1843, and
         1867, all written to Henley C. Lybrook, Cassopolis, Cass
         County, Michigan Territory, by his sister Nancy, his father
         John, and his brother Philip Lybrook, of Giles County,
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>Nancy Lybrook, January 16, 1834, refers to Henley's
         mercantile business; their brother John, who lives in Carroll
         County, Indiana, about four miles from the Wabash River; the
         meteoric phenomenon on November 12, 1833; the death of the
         [county ?] clerk, David French; and the rumor of the
         engagement of the daughter of James White of Doe Creek to John
         Dukes, Jr.</p>
      <p>John Lybrook, his father, writes on May 15, 1836, an
         account of the trial (and trials) of Mr. Sleeth who was
         accused of putting in a false claim by Mr. Singleton
         representing the War Department; his acquittal and the
         continued harassment by Singleton who has been preventing the
         war veterans from drawing their back pay; Nancy has a fourteen
         month old daughter to Mr. Sleeth, named Ann Elizabeth; Colonel
         Snidow received his back pay but the applications of himself,
         Jacob Snidow, and Isaac Chapman were rejected; mentions old
         Henry Lybrook (1755-1837) a soldier during the Revolutionary
         War; and mentions two slaves by name, Rachel and Jim.</p>
      <p>Four of the letters were from his brother Philip Lybrook,
         also of Giles County, and discuss family affairs and local
         happenings. The earliest letter from Philip, November 8, 1839,
         mentions a visit from their brother John for two weeks;
         discusses details about their father's estate which the
         executors are eager to finish up, asking Henley what he and
         Catharine wants done with their share of the money, and
         offering to lend it out for them at interest for nine months;
         complains that Mr. Sleeth has not answered his letters
         concerning the estate; his brother John thinking of moving to
         the Iowa country and buying a new tract of land; and refers to
         the death of Uncle Henry Lybrook.</p>
      <p>The next letter, April 22, 1842, refers to the announcement
         of Henley's marriage in the newspapers; supplies many details
         concerning the trial and acquittal of Dave Lucas for the
         murder of Peter in Philip's yard last fall; Philip's concern
         for his own safety and his property while Lucas was living at
         Jacob Snidow's and passed by his house three or four times a
         week; the murder of a peddler from Floyd County, Virginia,
         last March 19, [1842], who was last seen in the company of
         Dave Lucas; the upcoming trial of Lucas for the murder of the
         peddler; the actions of Bill B. Hutchenson, who tried to
         prevent the discovery of the body of the peddler during the
         search; and his suspicions concerning William H. Snidow,
         formerly of Christiansburg, who benefited from the death of
         old John Chapman (in one of Snidow's fields) to the tune of
         $30,000.</p>
      <p>In his next letter, October 31, 1843, Philip expresses hope
         that the times will be better since the Whigs managed to get a
         tariff law through the House last session and apologizes for
         getting into a "political strain"; cannot assist Beltzer
         because he has the care of a household of twenty people plus
         Sally as well, the interest on her money pays only about half
         of her board; discusses other business affairs; relates the
         story of "our spurious wealth," consisting of the trial of
         Elijah Summerfield, son-in-law to old Gasper Link, who was
         indicted for passing two counterfeit five dollar gold pieces
         in Pearisburg; the gold pieces were apparently created by
         Gasper Harless, the son-in-law of old Jacob Snidow, who went
         to see a Mr. Mullins on the Sandy River for advice on making
         his coins complete and secure from detection while they were
         being used by Summerfield.</p>
      <p>The last letter from Philip, March 7, 1867, was written
         upon the news of the death of his brother John and he notes
         that only three of the family remains, Henley, himself, and
         their sister Betsy [Atkins ?] in Boone County, West Virginia;
         lists several of their acquaintances who have apparently died
         since communication was interrupted by the Civil War,
         including old George Snidow and his son George, Christian
         Snidow, Guy D. French, William H. Snidow, Frederick Williams,
         William Porterfield, John Albert, P.N. Snidow (killed in the
         Valley of Virginia campaigns), and Uncle Henry Chapman
         (1779-1865); two young men had amputations during the war but
         their lives were spared, youngest son of James Albert and
         James P. Snidow; furnishes the movements of William since the
         war; and begs his brother to come and see him one more
         time.</p>
      <p>Philip also writes about the conditions in the South
         following the Civil War, "We are in a bad condition here in
         the South. I suppose it will not be long until we will be
         placed under military control. I believe the bill has passed
         both houses of Congress to that effect the amendment of the
         Constitution will follow which will make universal suffrage
         legal with exception of our best and most accomplished men, we
         will if this arrangement is carried out as they intend, our
         legislators and officers of all descriptions will have to be
         of the Negro race or deserters who they call loyal men, if we
         have any. ...... I could not take what they call the test
         oath. I was opposed to the war but was compelled to furnish
         meat, bread, and hay, to the Southern army. I had to do it or
         have my property pressed and now I have to stand in ranks with
         the sufferers."</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
