<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02113">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu02113 :: A Guide to the George G. Young Civil War Letters )//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34; viu02113.xml &amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu02113 :: A Guide to the George
             G. Young Civil War Letters )//EN" " viu02113.xml "</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the George G. Young Civil War
            Letters, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1865</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Young, George G., Civil War Letters of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3676</num></subtitle><author>Mitzi Clark</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 24.5 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Sharon Defibaugh, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 20, 2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-19" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 19, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu02113 :: A Guide to
            the George G. Young Civil War Letters )//EN" " viu02113.xml
            " converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the George G. Young Civil War Letters,
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3676</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Mitzi Clark</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>George G. Young Civil War Letters, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1861-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3676</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of twenty-one items, primarily letters.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>George G. Young Civil War Letters, Accession #3676 ,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the University of
            Virginia Library from Mrs. Sterling Graydon on March 6,
            1951.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of twenty-one items, primarily
         letters from George G. Young, Company A, Second Regiment,
         South Carolina Cavalry, written between 1861 and 1865. Three
         letters were written by his brother, I.A. Young of Camden,
         South Carolina.</p>
      <p>Two letters in 1861 are written, apparently to family in
         Camden, by I.A. Young from Fairfax County Court House,
         Virginia. On September 18, 1861, he draws a map of the town,
         including the location and description of George's office. He
         writes that he is caring for George, who was wounded at Bull
         Run and mentions he has gone there to retrieve George's horse.
         He speaks of a souvenir he brought from the battlefield from
         the house of a Mrs. Henry, who was killed in her bed by a
         Federal cannon ball.</p>
      <p>On September 19, 1861, he says that George is better and
         that the two intend to go by "the cars" to Richmond and from
         there on to Camden--a trip of about thirty-six hours. He
         includes a detailed drawing of skirmishes near Vienna. Also in
         1861 is a permission slip given to G.G. Towny to go to
         Manassas to get some boxes, signed by John Chesnut and dated
         November 27, 1861.</p>
      <p>There is one letter in 1862, February 9, 1862 in which
         George writes I.A. Young a description explaining how horses
         can drown in mud holes if not rescued. He says Colonel Joseph
         Brevard Kershaw is acting Brigadier of the regiment, and that
         Colonel [Radfort] had nine of his pickets captured by the
         enemy, with efforts to recover them fruitless.</p>
      <p>Eleven letters by George in 1863 detail actions in and near
         Culpeper County and troop movements up the Valley. On February
         9, 1863, he tells I.A. Young of preparations for movement by
         his regiment (loading of supplies, etc., ) in anticipation of
         a raid by the Yankees, who are intending to burn the bridge
         across the Rappahannock River. (The raid did not materialize.)
         He adds that goods and clothes are now plentiful in the
         camp.</p>
      <p>On February 28, 1863, he writes from Page County, Virginia,
         now in the mountains, having come from Sperryville and Luray.
         He describes how men obtain furloughs by giving up their
         horses, and writes glowingly of the character and habits of
         General Wade Hampton.</p>
      <p>Continuing up the Shenandoah Valley, he writes April 3,
         1863, of passing General Stonewall Jackson's "battleground"
         and vividly describes a visit to Weyers Cave and the wonders
         he encountered therein. On Aug 2, 1863, from a camp near
         Culpeper, Virginia, George tells I.A. Young he has been in his
         heaviest fighting thus far, around Culpeper with a retreat to
         Brandy Station, where the Yankees had six brigades of
         cavalry.</p>
      <p>From Stevensburg, Culpeper County, George writes I.A. Young
         on Aug 22, 1863, to muse about his horrors of dying and being
         left for dead on a battlefield to be trampled on. He wants, he
         says, to be buried at home if possible. Still encamped near
         Brandy Station, on October 21, 1863, he tells I.A. Young that
         dead horses are scattered about for considerable distance
         because of cavalry fighting. His troops have passed through a
         number of deserted Yankee camps which have handsome
         appearances.</p>
      <p>Still in camp near Stevensburg, he tells his sister on
         November 3, 1863, that the neighborhood has been laid to
         waste, with Yankees pulling fine homes apart to obtain
         material for their own shanties. The homes of foreigners and
         Yankee sympathizers were spared. On November 29, 1863, he
         writes from [Roseland?], Nelson County, that he fears the
         Yankees might get below the Confederates and "it would not
         surprise me if the army fell back upon Richmond."</p>
      <p>In December of 1863, the regiment has moved near
         [Fincastle?] in Botetourt County, and George writes his sister
         on December 11, 1863, a description of Natural Bridge as they
         passed over it and mentions that he would like a copy of
         Miller's Almanac as he is becoming interested in
         astrology.</p>
      <p>December 15, 1863, he tells I.A. Young from Big Lick Depot
         near Roanoke, Virginia, that he arrived there the previous day
         and was able to visit friends within a mile of the depot. In
         his last letter of 1863, he writes his sister from Craig
         County, Virginia, on December 28, 1863, that he has been ill
         and is thus staying under the care of a Widow Givens about one
         half mile from camp on the top of the Allegheny Mountains. He
         tells an amusing story of a Confederate soldier who was aided
         in escape from the Yankees by hiding in a chicken coop.</p>
      <p>There are three letters in 1864. From Rockfish Valley,
         Nelson County, Virginia, February 1, 1864, George tells I.A.
         Young they are suffering from severe cold, with some Negroes
         captured in a raid so badly frost bitten they could not walk.
         Still from Nelson County, on February 2, 1864, George tells
         his sister he has passed near Lexington, Virginia, and the
         burial ground of General Stonewall Jackson on the outskirts of
         town. He writes that he thinks the young ladies of Craig
         County the most unrefined he has ever seen as they smoke
         pipes, chew tobacco, drink liquor and ride horses like
         men.</p>
      <p>In 1865, George has been taken prisoner and is in Newport
         News, Virginia. He writes I. A. Young on May 15, 1865, that he
         has been captured, is sick and "very feeble." All of his
         clothing, money and blankets were taken from him by a portion
         of the 12th New York Cavalry. There are two undated letters,
         one very faded, talking of some action around Chickahominy,
         Virginia.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged in chronological order.</p>
    </arrangement>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
