<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04057">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04057::A Guide to the Richard Harding Davis Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War)//EN" "viu04057.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Richard Harding Davis Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Davis, Richard Harding, Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War 
                    <num type="collectionnumber">6109-y</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Richard Harding Davis Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>The Clifton Waller Barrett Library<lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">6109-y</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Richard Harding Davis Collection, Clifton Waller Barrett
                Library
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">6109-y</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">The collection consists of ca. 40 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Richard Harding Davis Collection, Clifton Waller Barrett Library, Accession #6109-y, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were given to the University of Virginia Special Collections
                    Library by E. Anthony Newton, on July 7, 2009.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Davis was born on April 18, 1864, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Lemuel Clarke
                Davis, a newspaper editor, and prominent novelist, Rebecca Harding Davis. He made
                his reputation as a newspaper reporter in May to June 1889, by reporting on the
                devastation of Johnstown, Pennsylvania, following the disaster of the flood. Davis
                became a managing editor of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Harper's Weekly</title>, and was
                one of the world's leading war correspondents at the time of the Second Boer War in
                South Africa. As an American, he had the unique opportunity to see the war
                first-hand from both the British and Boer sides. Davis also worked as a reporter for
                the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Herald, The Times</title>, and 
                <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scribner's Magazine</title>. He was married twice, first to
                Cecil Clark Lewis, an artist, in Marion, Massachusetts, on May 4, 1899, and then to
                Bessie McCoy, a Vaudeville star. He and Bessie had a daughter, Hope. Davis died of a
                heart attack at home on April 11, 1916 at fifty-one years of age. Several books were
                consulted for information concerning Davis and his trip to South Africa, including
                    <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Richard Harding David Years</title> by Gerald
                Langford, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Reporter Who Would Be King</title> by Arthur
                Lubow and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">With Both Armies</title> by Richard Harding
                Davis.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>This collection contains Richard Harding Davis Letters concerning South Africa and
                the Boer War. Letters and documents by Richard Harding Davis and his wife Cecil
                describe their voyages to and from South Africa, the cities of Cape Town and
                Pretoria, and his coverage of the Boer War from both the British and the Boer sides.
                There are references to General Buller, Winston Churchill, Lady Randolph Churchill,
                Christiaan de Wet, Rudyard Kipling, Paul Kruger, Sir Alfred Milner, Lord Frederick
                Roberts, Allen Sangree, President M. T. Steyn, and Sir George Stuart White. Of great
                interest are letters describing the relief of Ladysmith, March 3-4, 1900, and the
                fall of Pretoria, May 18, 1900. A photograph of Cecil in a rickshaw in Durban is
                included as is a magazine of their return ship the R. P. D. 
                <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">König</title> of the Deutsche Ost-Afrika-Linie.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <p>These letters were formerly mounted into a scrapbook and numbered consecutively with
                a penciled notation at the top of the letter. The letters have been removed from the
                scrapbook for preservation purposes. The collection is now arranged by the date of
                the letter, or if undated, by the contents of the letter, and not the original order
                as arranged in the scrapbook, presumably that of the date of receipt.</p>
      <p>Item number 10 is actually two separate letters on two consecutive days, so it has
                been foldered separately. Several numbers, 25, 28, 30, and 32, are missing and those
                items are presumed lost or mis-numbered by the recipient or the creator of the
                scrapbook. There are also two items numbered 33. When it can be determined, the
                entire name of the correspondent is used in the listing, even if the letter has only
                the first name or a nickname. This is indicated by the use of brackets.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="d1e153">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 10?]</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to
                            Dear Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, note on <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">
                            U.S.M.S. St. Louis</title> stationery, saying goodbye to the Davis
                            family, including Mr. Davis and Nora Davis, as they are sailing to
                            London to secure authorization for Richard to cover the Boer War with
                            the British forces in the Transvaal,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          <physdesc>1 page on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e165">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January] 10-13</unitdate> Richard Harding Davis
                            ("Dick") to Dear Mother [Rebecca Harding Davis], written on 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">U.S.M.S. St. Louis</title> stationery, states he and
                            his wife, Cecil, have the most comfortable staterooms, they have met
                            many people who claim to have met them before, everyone is very
                            interested in their trip, and travel was very smooth until
                            Saturday,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e178">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 13]</unitdate> [Richard Harding Davis] to
                            [Rebecca Harding Davis?], written on <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">U.S.M.S. St.
                                Louis</title> stationery, Saturday, sea continues to be stormy,
                            tells a story about a man at his table who put up a freight trolley line
                            over the Chilkoot Pass to the Klondike district in the Yukon Territory,
                            Canada, and used it to ferry sixty frozen bodies over it in buckets at
                            one time; their ship is halfway across to Great Britain; they also had
                            tea with the Cass Canfield couple and talked politics at dinnertime. The
                            Klondike man claims he is a great leader in the Democratic party and
                            predicts they will toss out Bryan at the Convention at the last minute
                            and nominate Dewey or Olney with Wheeler as vice president. He assures
                            them that this is the strategy of Whitney and Josiah Quincy.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e196">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 20?]</unitdate> [Richard Harding Davis]
                            to Dear Nora [Davis], Bath Hotel, arrived on Wednesday at two in the
                            morning at the hotel and the porter brought them food and drink as they
                            sat in front of the fire; could not leave on Saturday because the War
                            Office refused him credentials; if they still refuse to issue them,
                            Davis plans on going without them, using instead letters of introduction
                            from [Herbert?] Asquith and others, to [Frederick] Roberts, Lord
                            [Alfred?] Milner, and [Herbert] Kitchener. They missed traveling down
                            [to the Transvaal] with [Rudyard] Kipling but on next Saturday plan to
                            go with [Henry Somers] Somerset, who cannot get a job as a
                            correspondent. Cecil has letters from Mrs. Asquith to Lady Edward Cecil
                            and Lady Charles Benedict, both of whom are at Mafeking.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e214">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 22?]</unitdate> Richard [Harding Davis]
                            to Dear Nora [Davis], on Bath Hotel, Piccadilly, stationery, tries to
                            relate all the exciting things that have happened since they have
                            arrived in [London?] because their situation seems to change by the
                            hour, trying to decide whether to go with the British or the Boers, to
                            stay in London or return home, to work for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The
                                Herald</title> or <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Mail;</title> The
                            British refused to give Davis a correspondent pass and he had decided to
                            go with the Boers, when [George W.] Steevens died and Lord Alfred
                            Harmsworth asked him if he could break with <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The
                                Herald</title> and take Steevens place. He offered to write for both
                            papers, which [James Gordon] Bennett, Jr. finally agreed to. Richard and
                            Cecil also have had dinner with Mrs. [Herbert?] Asquith; at another
                            dinner, Cecil sat next to [Alfred] Beit, who gave them letters to "all
                            the millionaire Hebrews at the Cape, wives and all. He is the man who
                            subscribed $250,000 for the volunteers and who is described as the man
                            who paid for the Jameson Raid. He paid [John Hays] Hammond's fine which
                            was in itself $175,000."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          <physdesc>7 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e238">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 23?]</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to
                            Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, Tuesday, writes "We are leading such a
                            busy life these days &amp; meeting <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">so</title>
                            many new &amp; exciting people that my brain reels - At last 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">things</title> are <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">
                            fixed</title> about the credentials. Dick is to take the place of
                            Steevens &amp; write for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Daily Mail</title>."
                            Taking over Steevens credentials were arranged with the help of Sir
                            Evelyn Wood. Cecil also mentions the help given them by Alfred Beit who
                            furnished letters of introduction and arranged rooms for them in South
                            Africa through his partners. Davis's play was well received by Cyril
                            Maude who wanted to show it to Wyndham. Richard's sciatica has also
                            improved. Cecil mentioned needing a maid to go to South Africa and the
                            rumors about the food shortages there.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e258">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 January 27?]</unitdate> [Richard Harding Davis]
                            to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Scot</title> stationery, Davis is on board and
                            leaving port, has bribed the company agent to get Cecil and himself
                            better staterooms, with Cecil's large enough to give teas and dances,
                            also rescuing their maid with a room of her own and saving himself a
                            considerable amount of money by dealing with the agent instead of the
                            company. Many friends came to see them off and they are accompanied by
                            [Henry Somers] Somerset and Butler Duncan of New York. He asks his
                            mother to tell Louise Clark what he has written and give his love to
                            Nora and Dad.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e275">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] January 31</unitdate> [Richard Harding Davis] to
                            Nora [Davis], on Steamship <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Scot</title>
                            stationery, reports that the trip has been rough so far, making them
                            glad to see land, even if it is only a slice of Portugal; Davis plans to
                            try to go with Kitchener, the main column, and will not try to pick up
                            the ends of the other campaigns; feels that since Kitchener cannot start
                            for several weeks, he will have plenty of time to settle Cecil in Cape
                            Town, South Africa, with friends and her maid, "I think her chance of
                            getting to the front is extremely small - extremely so - what we both
                            want is a quick campaign lots of things to write about and a quick
                            return - with <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Mail</title> and 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Herald</title> I now have a great chance and an
                            immense audience, and nothing is read in England except war letters."
                            Both Richard and Cecil were very happy at the Bath [Hotel] in London,
                            and Cecil now loves the city as much as he does. Notes that they did not
                            receive any of his mother's letters while in London.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
          <physdesc>7 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e297">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] January 31</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to
                            Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, on Steamship <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S.
                                Scot</title> stationery, off Madeira, complains that "Dick tells you
                            everything &amp; leaves me nothing; which is perhaps as well as he is
                            certainly a good describer"; mentions the rough seas, the possibility of
                            a casino and roulette table night to relieve the monotony on board,
                            hearing much of Transvaal matters, especially inside stories from
                            [Alfred] Beit; she writes "am in the painful state of being half
                            convinced that the English have <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">rights</title>
                            - However I think I can escape all troubles by turning Kaffir &amp; Red
                            American Indians &amp; [Filipino] &amp; from this high moral stand no
                            one can move me"; she also notes that she is supposed to "sustain the
                            wounded" when she arrives in Cape Town.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e316">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 4</unitdate> "Dick" Richard [Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], describes in great
                            detail the adventures they had on the trip by Portuguese rowboat to
                            Madeira taken by himself, Cecil, and Somers, in very rough and high
                            seas, his success at the roulette table the brief while they were in the
                            casino, the order of champagne for everyone out of his winnings, leaving
                            him seventy-five dollars to the good, his meal of fried eggs, and the
                            negotiation for payment on the return trip.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
          <physdesc>5 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e330">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 February 9</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Scot</title> stationery, describes their
                            participation in the "sports" contests on board ship through Cecil's
                            maid, Hubert, who won the threading a needle contest; the reassurance by
                            people who have lived in Cape Town for awhile that they have
                            introductory letters to the most important people there, including
                            almost every multimillionaire out of Kimberly, [Lord Alfred] Milner, and
                            the ladies nursing the wounded, so Richard has no uneasiness about
                            leaving Cecil in their care while he hopes to make his way to the front
                            with either Roberts or Kitchener. He believes the war an immense
                            opportunity, "as all the officers say, it is like taking a degree in war
                            there will not be such a chance again, and there has never been one like
                            it - I mean the use of modern weapons has been developed in the campaign
                            for the first time."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e351">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 February [10]</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Scot</title> stationery, describes the very
                            English manner of awarding the prizes for the sports contest held
                            yesterday involving a great deal of pomp and circumstance. Their maid,
                            Hubert, gave her prize money to the two youngest cabin boys.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e363">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 14</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Mount Nelson Hotel,
                            Cape Town, stationery, writes that they are settled in a very smart
                            hotel with many gardens and facing the mountains "owing to the crowding
                            Somerset has to room with me - Cecil has a very good room by herself";
                            [H.J.] Whigham has quarreled with [Paul Sanford Baron] Methuen and lost
                            his press pass to the front; and Richard mentions Rudyard Kipling,
                            "Kipling is at the hotel and walks around with his arm around his wife's
                            waist - He is very friendly, she is a middle class cat."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e378">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 February 17</unitdate> Telegram from [Richard
                            Harding Davis] notifying his [family ?] that Cecil was settled and that
                            he was going to Chieveley with General Sir Redvers Buller</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e386">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 18-19</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard
                            Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scot</title>, Richard left [Cape Town] yesterday and
                            hopes to reach Buller before Ladysmith is relieved and possibly join
                            Roberts with Buller later; plans to do a lot of cabling for the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Mail</title> every day; describes Cape Town as a
                            "dusty wind-ridden western town with a mountain back of it which one man
                            said was a badly painted back drop"; Cecil is settled in a hotel
                            situated at the base of the mountain with a sitting room and a big
                            bedroom; they have met [Sir Alfred] Milner, who volunteered to write an
                            unsolicited and flattering personal letter of introduction to the
                            Governor of Natal for Richard; describes his discussion with Milner
                            about his doubts of the loyalty of the Cape Towners to the Queen; Cecil
                            has become friends with the Waldrons and Mrs. Anderson, but dislikes the
                            Kiplings, "She hates the Kiplings as everyone does, a more offensive
                            little bounder it is difficult to imagine - He goes around in khaki 800
                            miles from the front and contradicts every general on every military
                            question - He ought either to go the front or go home"; Richard has
                            boarded ship [<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Scot</title>] and parted from
                            Cecil, describes their preparations for his voyage to join Buller and
                            his arrangements to cable his stories to the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">
                            Mail</title>, and plans to post this letter at Port
                            Elizabeth,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15</container>
          <physdesc>8 pages on 4 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e415">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 19</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Bunton's Grand
                            Hotel, Port Elizabeth, stationery, Richard is currently on shore at Port
                            Elizabeth, describes the local scene with rickshaws drawn by Kaffir
                            boys, the town looking like a western mining town, strange looking ducks
                            that turned out to be baby ostriches, and the vast distances of Africa
                            where it will still take him ten days to reach Buller's
                            location,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e429">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 20</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Deal's Central
                            Hotel stationery, East London, South Africa, writes that the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scot</title> is stopping at every port as if it were
                            a ferry boat; has met an American who got a commission in Brabant's
                            Horse and who had the hotel proprietor bring out two books to sign
                            marked "Autographs of Celebrities of the Boer War" for Davis to
                            autograph; and notes that many of the correspondents are now abandoning
                            Buller for Roberts,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e444">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 20</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to
                            Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, mistaken dated "1899" by Cecil, on Mount
                            Nelson Hotel, Cape Town, stationery, writes that Richard left yesterday
                            on the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scot</title> to go to Durban and then on
                            to Pietermaritzsburg for his horses and cart to join Buller at the
                            Tugela [River], a journey of a week by sea and then three to four more
                            days by land; seems like the war is much further away than when she was
                            in England with less news about it; she is not impressed with Cape Town
                            which she thinks is something between a frontier town and Cairo and
                            Algiers; Somerset and Whigham sit at her table at the hotel and she sees
                            the Kiplings in the dining room to her dismay,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18</container>
          <physdesc>6 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e461">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] February 23</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Imperial Hotel,
                            Maritzburg, Natal, stationery, writes that he reached Durban yesterday
                            and describes it as picturesque with many different nationalities; plans
                            to overtake Buller before he reaches Ladysmith; and describes the native
                            peoples he has seen, 3 pages on 2 leaves, with a broadside dated
                            February 21, 1900, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Supplement to the Cape
                                Times</title> "Good News From Buller" enclosed,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e475">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 1</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Kid" [Charles Belmont Davis], mistakenly dated 1899,
                            sends notification of his arrival in Ladysmith with postmarked envelope
                            [dated March 1, 1900] as proof, "This is just a line to say I got in
                            here with the first after a gallop of twelve miles. Keep this for me and
                            the envelope, with my love and best wishes - Dick"</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:20</container>
          <physdesc>1 page</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e487">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 1</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to Mrs.
                            [Rebecca Harding] Davis, Mount Nelson Hotel, Cape Town, stationery, has
                            received a telegram from Richard at Colenso and has also heard that Piet
                            Cronje has surrendered [at Paardeberg?]; she has made some drawings but
                            found far fewer subjects than expected, an entire Kaffir family watched
                            as she drew the grandmother in her room; Kipling has returned from
                            Kimberley; and she expects to meet Cecil Rhodes soon,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:21</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e500">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 March 2?]</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], boasts that on his
                            second day "I beat all these men who have been here three months in
                            getting my news on the wire. For I am a news man now and have to collect
                            horrid facts and lists of casualties and to find out whether it was the
                            Dublins or the Durbans that did it and what it was they did." The
                            geography of the area around the Tugela River is confusing; Richard
                            claims that he is as comfortable in his tent as can be, which he
                            describes as well as his three ponies; and he speaks of heavy losses,
                            "it is sheer straight waste of life through dogged
                            stupidity"</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:22</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e517">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 3-4</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Ladysmith, March 3,
                            Davis describes the relief of Ladysmith by Sir Redvers Buller's
                            soldiers, who form quite a contrast with the poor conditions of health
                            of the garrison, "They are yellow with fever, their teeth protruding and
                            the skin drawn tight over their skeletons - the incoming army had had
                            fourteen days hard fighting at the end of three months campaigning and
                            were robust and tanned ragged and caked with mud. As they came in they
                            cheered and the garrison tried to cheer back but it was like a whisper -
                            Winston Churchill and I stood in front of General [Sir George] White and
                            cried for an hour." Davis also mentions the heavy losses among the men
                            trying to break the siege, the scarcity of food, his ration of four
                            biscuits, an ounce of coffee and of tea, along with something called
                            mealies.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:23</container>
          <physdesc>5 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ladysmith, March 4, has received the first letter from her since they
                            left home, complains about how the British have fought the war, "It is a
                            beastly dull war - the whole thing is so 'class', and full of 'form' and
                            tradition and worrying over 'putties' and etiquette and rank - It is the
                            most wonderful organization I ever imagined but it is like a beautiful
                            locomotive without an engineer - the Boers out play them in intelligence
                            every day - the whole army is officered by one class and that the dull
                            one - It is like the House of Peers - You would not believe the mistakes
                            they make, the awful way in which they sacrifice the lives of officers
                            and men." Both portions,</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e549">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 5</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Outside Ladysmith,
                            Davis complains about the filth, smell, and dirt of the town and his
                            hotel and the attitude of the familiarity of the "colonials"; tells a
                            story of several very hungry troopers who came into the dining room to
                            purchase some tea who were refused rudely; he followed them out and
                            begged them to take tea with him on his verandah and served them the
                            scarce commodities of sugar, marmalade, whiskey, and cigars that he had
                            purchased; also saved a small puppy which he fed on beef tablets and
                            named Ladysmith; describes his beautiful tent with tape window panes,
                            ventilators, pockets inside, doors, two tables, two chairs, a bath tub,
                            two lanterns, folding bed, and a cape cart; and tells a sad story about
                            the men of Ladysmith driving away well-trained cavalry horses because
                            they could not be fed.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:24</container>
          <physdesc>6 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e569">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 15</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Royal Hotel, Durban,
                            Natal, stationery, returning to Cape Town, Davis plans to go to Roberts
                            if there is fighting or return to London if there is not; takes issue
                            with the British fighting against women "even if they are good shots";
                            has not seen enough to make a book out of his trip and both he and Cecil
                            have been bored with all the talk about the war; traveled to the
                            hospital ship <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Maine</title> and asked Lady
                            Randolph [Spencer Churchill] to give him a lift down to Cape Town and
                            plans on writing an article for her <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Anglo-Saxon
                                Review</title> on the "Passing of the War
                            Correspondent."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:25</container>
          <physdesc>7 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e587">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 March 24</unitdate> Telegram from L. Clarke Davis
                            to Mrs. L. Clarke Davis, received a message from Richard Harding Davis,
                            "seen enough war returning next week east coast very
                            leisurely"</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:26</container>
          <physdesc>1 page</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e597">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 25</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to [the Clark and Davis families?], Cape Town, writes explaining
                            his decision to return home, both Roberts and Buller planned on no
                            campaigning for about three weeks and he had already sold his outfit at
                            a loss; since the English irritated him he could not write about their
                            work with any pleasure, "My sporting blood refused to boil at the
                            spectacle of such a monster empire getting the worst of it from an
                            untrained band of farmers - I found I admired the farmers - so we
                            decided to chuck it and go to London." Davis had seen two battles and
                            the relief of Ladysmith, having gotten the "pick of the fighting and the
                            best 'story' according to every officer and correspondent; they intend
                            on returning home via the east coast [of Africa?] so Cecil can enjoy
                            some of the "real Africa not the shoddy 'colonial', shopkeeper's
                            paradise" as in Cape Town; Richard and Cecil Davis plan on stopping off
                            at Zanzibar, Port Said, Cairo, Constantinople, and then on to Paris by
                            way of the Orient Express, perhaps writing a book about the entire
                            experience with photographs and Cecil's drawings; he encloses a printed
                            itinerary that they will follow when they board the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Konig</title>, at Durban, leaving April 7
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title>; and explains why he thinks Cecil's maid,
                            Hubert, is a priceless treasure.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:27</container>
          <physdesc>5 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e624">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] March 31</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], off East Africa, his
                            joy at turning towards home together with Cecil and his appreciation of
                            her letters and enclosures about events at home,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:28</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e634">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] April 4</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to [Rebecca Harding Davis?], East London, South Africa, on 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">R.M.S. Moor</title> stationery, sent a request to
                            Secretary of State John M. Hay to get them into Pretoria, who said he
                            would be glad to see them there; they arrive at Durban tomorrow where
                            they will stay a day and two nights, and then go on board the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Konig</title> for Delagoa Bay [off the coast of
                            Mozambique]; while in Pretoria, Davis hopes "to write a book from both
                            sides giving my ideas of the English in the field and the Boer at home.
                            With the exception of Churchill who 'had to' I shall be the only
                            correspondent who has been permitted to go on both sides."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:29</container>
          <physdesc>10 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e651">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] April 5</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Royal Hotel, Durban,
                            Natal, stationery, enjoyed a rickshaw ride with Cecil and took a
                            photograph of her and her "attendants"; Commandant objected to their
                            going to Pretoria and was inclined to refuse them passes to leave Durban
                            for Delagoa Bay but after Davis wired many of his friends in South
                            Africa they were eventually vouched for by the High Commissioner; and
                            Davis includes details of their shopping in Durban; 5 pages on 2 leaves,
                            and black and white photograph of Cecil Davis in rickshaw</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:30</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e665">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900 April 22?]</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Grand Hotel, Pretoria,
                            S.A.R., stationery, writes that he and Cecil are settling down in
                            Pretoria and are going to keep house in the home of a refugee, moving in
                            today; the Chicago contingent [Irish-Americans who came out as an
                            ambulance corps] are going down to President Kruger's to bid him
                            farewell; Richard hopes to have some fine stories soon, see the
                            President, and get a cart to drive down to [Kroonstad?] and see the Boer
                            army in the field,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:31</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e680">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] April 23</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Pretoria Club
                            stationery, Pretoria, describes the house, that belonged to an English
                            refugee, given to him and Cecil to use for two pounds a month, which
                            includes two horses, a carriage and driver; describes Cecil's cooking
                            experiences; and the purchase by the Irish brigade of a plain gold
                            bracelet for Cecil with the engraving "From the Irish American Ambulance
                            Corps to Mrs. R.H. Davis" and the motto of Chicago "I will,"</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:32</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e694">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] April 25</unitdate> Cecil [Clark Davis] to Nora
                            [Davis], Pretoria, writes about their settling in as householders,
                            lacking only a cook to be complete; their current plans are to stay in
                            Pretoria until June 5<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> and then sail in
                            easy stages to Zanzibar, Mozambique, etc. to Naples and then go by rail
                            until they reach Aix, reaching America in August; they both plan to go
                            to the front in a day or two; they see much of [General "Koos"] De la
                            Rey and Coolidge; and Richard is busy reporting on all the interesting
                            things that are happening,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:33</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e709">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] May 4</unitdate> [Richard Harding Davis] to
                            "Dear Families," plans on going to the front with Cecil tonight, had
                            planned on accompanying the Boer artillery to Brandfort, but it was just
                            taken by the British,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:34</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e719">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] May 8</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis]
                            to [Davis and Clark families ?], Grand Hotel, Ventersberg, describes
                            their adventures in the Free State from the time they left Pretoria on
                            May 4<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> to attempt to go to Brandsfort,
                            then Winburg, and finally Smaaldel, all of which were taken by the
                            British before they could reach the area; yesterday they rode out with
                            [Otto von Lossberg] and camped at a Boer farm, just behind the Boer
                            trenches on the Sand River, with the British six miles away; Cecil
                            created a sensation among the Boers since all the women had fled; they
                            met President [Marthinus] Steyn, who gave Cecil a flower from his coat
                            and talked with her for some time; they decided to spend the night at
                            [Jones's Hotel], Ventersberg and Cecil woke him to say the British were
                            at the railway station, two hour's ride away but they have not arrived
                            yet; and they are now free to travel wherever they want through the loan
                            of [Otto von Lossberg]'s cart with two seats and five mules,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:35</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 l.</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e740">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] May 18</unitdate> Richard [Harding Davis] to
                            "Dear Dad [Lemuel Clark Davis] and others of the Clark and Davis
                            families," Pretoria, work on his <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Ledger</title>
                            and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scribner</title> stories has prevented his
                            writing a long letter before now; begins an account of Cecil and his
                            adventures with the Boers from May 4<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title>
                            until the present; writes about Captain [Otto von Lossberg], "a German
                            baron who married in New Orleans and became an American citizen and who
                            is now in command of Lossberg's Artillery in the Free State"; describes
                            in greater detail their meeting with President Steyn and the letter he
                            gave them to Dr. Reid, who ran an ambulance base on [Piet] Cronje's
                            farm, instructing him to give Cecil something to sleep on; they returned
                            to Ventersberg that night only to overhear an alarm about the closeness
                            of the British given to the landlady, "a grand low comedy character from
                            Brooklyn … sitting up in bed in curl papers, and with a Webley
                            revolver"; having decided to go back to sleep, they were able to use
                            Lossberg's cape cart and five mules to pack their things and head to the
                            Sand River, spending the night at Cronje's farm where Dr. Reid gave
                            Cecil his field mattress; they then used Lossberg's cart to pursue their
                            next objective - to reach the railroad bridge over the Sand River; they
                            found themselves between the Boer and British lines and stopped for
                            lunch; about three o'clock they were captured by three Boers, "I was
                            riding behind the cart and threw up my hands 'that quick,' but Cecil
                            could not hear me yelling at her to stop on account of the noise of the
                            cart - I knew if I rode after her they would shoot at me, and that if
                            she did not stop, as they were shouting at her to do, they would shoot
                            her. Under these trying circumstances I sat still - It caused quite a
                            coolness on Cecil's part."; they were finally released by the three
                            Boers and next met General Christiaan De Wet (1854–1922), who
                            directed them to a farmhouse about five miles off where they could
                            safely see the fighting the next day, although they decided to camp out
                            on the veldt near a stream; they were awakened by the sound of
                            bombardment and hurriedly tried to get out of the danger area, Cecil
                            showing much self-possession and calm and even urging the Boers to make
                            a stand; when the British were within five hundred yards of the Boer
                            artillery and [Louis?] Botha's men made a break for it, Richard finally
                            convinced Cecil to get on her pony and race for Ventersberg; when they
                            arrived there, they found everyone harnessing up [their carts and
                            wagons] and abandoning everything; Cecil determined to loot the cook
                            from Jones Hotel to work for them in Pretoria; while helping her pack
                            her things and anything else useful, the message came that the British
                            were only fifteen minutes away, so Richard loaded the cook, Cecil,
                            supplies, a dog and a kitten, in the cart, mounted his horse and left
                            hurriedly for Kroonstad racing for thirty miles in five hours without
                            one stop; at Kroonstad, President Steyn ordered a special car for
                            Richard and Cecil and sent them off at once; they plan to return as soon
                            as Davis reaches the Vaal where there must be a stand; the cook proves
                            to be a treasure and Cecil is busy doing portraits in oil,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:36</container>
          <physdesc>11 pages on 6 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e794">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] June 8</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis]
                            to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Kanzler</title>, having decided to leave
                            Pretoria when the British neared the capital, to avoid living under
                            British martial law subject to the censor and not having anything they
                            could do; writes about the Boers, "I know no class of men I admire as
                            much or who today preserve the best and oldest ideas of charity,
                            fairness, and goodwill to men"; <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Sun</title>
                            correspondent, Allen Sangree joined them at Delagoa and was robbed of
                            his notes on the Irish Brigade and other papers the night he arrived,
                            apparently by British agents willing to return them for a consideration;
                            describes how he and Sangree tried to get his papers back from the
                            British consul in the port [of Lourenço Marques?]; many wives and
                            children of the men of Pretoria and Johannesburg also on board the
                            ship,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:37</container>
          <physdesc>6 pages on 3 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e815">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] June 12</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board the 
                            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Kanzler</title>, admits to a sincere longing to
                            see family and home; describes the people and land of [Beira],
                            Mozambique where he also mentions the presence of slaves; has run out of
                            film and cannot get any more; Cecil is drawing and Richard writing for
                                <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Scribners,</title></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:38</container>
          <physdesc>4 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e828">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] June 21</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], have made their last
                            stop at Tanga, north of Zanzibar and just south of Mombasa, where they
                            have seen jungle; Cecil was carried about on a sedan chair by four
                            Somali boys; declares that this area is what people think of as the real
                            Africa; and shared a story of a lion attack on a man in a [stopped?]
                            railway car,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:39</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e841">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] June 25</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to Nora [Davis], off the coast of Suakin, [Sudan], currently in
                            the Red Sea and will arrive at Suez tomorrow; ship is very crowded with
                            women and children and it is very hot; describes the practices of the
                            second class passengers; and Richard shares his favorable impression of
                            Zanzibar and mentions slavery again; 3 pages on 2 leaves, with a picture
                            of their ship <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Konig</title></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:40</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e853">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] June 29</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding
                            Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], off the coast of Crete,
                            enjoying his return to civilization, although he mentions some of the
                            interesting friends they have made during this trip to South Africa,
                            "the Boer farmers, Dutch station masters who gave us a corner under the
                            telegraph table in which to sleep, with Nelson who kept the Transvaal
                            Steam Laundry, Colonel Lynch of the steerage who comes to the dividing
                            line to beg French books from Cecil" and interesting experiences in the
                            Transvaal; they were unable to cable home before Naples, due to the
                            presence of the plague at Aden, Suez, and Port Said; and shares how ill
                            Cecil had been recently,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:41</container>
          <physdesc>3 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e870">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 July 3</unitdate> Telegram [from Richard and Cecil
                            Davis] to L. Clark Davis, Napoli, message reads "Both well"</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:42</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e877">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] July 6</unitdate> Richard [Harding Davis] to
                            "Dear Family," Aix [Aix-en-Provence?], rejoiced at arriving after being
                            on board ship for a month; everyone was so welcoming and kind; and
                            Richard mentions his need to buy appropriate clothing for
                            Europe,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:43</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 2 leaves</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e888">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1900] July 7</unitdate> "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis]
                            to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], both are settling in and
                            getting rest and exercise; so far July is the coldest month they have
                            had on their trip; will spend about a week in Paris; and is looking
                            forward to home and real ragtime music,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:44</container>
          <physdesc>2 pages on 1 leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e899">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900 July 10</unitdate> Telegram from C. Anderson to L.
                            Clark Davis, message reads "sailing <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">St.
                                Louis</title> fourteenth home - sick to see you all at Marion - both
                            well."</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:45</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
