<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04007">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04007::A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, )//EN" "viu04007.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, 
</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Chaloner, John Armstrong, Papers of
<num type="collectionnumber">38-394-e
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2008 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Stephanie Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/20/2008</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, 
</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">38-394-e
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">38-394-e
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, Accession #38-394-e, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The papers were a gift to the Library from George Worthington, Charlottesville, Va., on May 24, 2005.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>John Armstrong Chaloner [Chanler] of Merrie Mills, Charlottesville, Virginia (1862-1935) was the great-great grandson of John Jacob Astor and for a short time was married to Amélie Rives (1863-1945) who was an American novelist who lived at Castle Hill, Charlottesville, Virginia. They were married in 1888 and divorced in 1895. It has been written that "Amélie was a master manipulator and morphine addict who refused her besotted husband sex and affection while spending his inheritance to refurbish her family plantation." Amélie is described as very flirtatious but her real passion seems to have been for Castle Hill and she desperately needed money to maintain her beloved home.  
</p>
      <p>
Chaloner's parents died when he was young leaving him to be the head of his family. He ran a business called the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Roanoke Rapids Machine Shops</title> but as his ideas for its expansion grew, his siblings feared they were going to lose money on it. This coupled with his neglect for his siblings (due to tensions between them and Amélie Rives) motivated the sibling to have Chaloner committed to an insane asylum. The couple's divorce after seven years was fodder for the media as were Chaloner's commitment to the asylum, his escape four years later and his lawsuits to prove his sanity and reclaim his fortune. Following their divorce Amélie Rives married Pierre Troubetsky and Chaloner still sent her money. After his escape from Bloomingdale and following the success of his trial, he returned to his home, Merrie Mills. In addition to being an author of several books, he wrote long passages about experiencing trance like states where he could see other realms of existence. He discussed these trances and his interest in psychology with important authors such as Henry James. 
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The papers consist of 147 letters and documents (1894-1920) by and to John Armstrong Chaloner (1862-1935), great-great grandson of John Jacob Astor of New York. Chaloner was an attorney, novelist, and entrepreneur who was often described as an eccentric. He lived at Castle Hill, and Merrie Mills Farm in Albemarle County, Virginia and owned a mill in Roanoke Rapids in North Carolina. 
</p>
      <p>The collection includes letters from various friends and business associates regarding financial help and business matters about his mill. There are also letters about Chaloner's escape from an insane asylum; letters to Judge Thomas N. Hill about his legal insanity case; letters to his friend, Rose Wilmer Page, asking for help with his lawsuit; a petition for a temporary injunction in Chaloner v. Dunn before the Supreme Court; and a certificate indicating a transfer of ownership of four cattle. There is also a document written by Chaloner stating that in the event of his death, he did not want his siblings on his property except for the viewing.</p>
      <p>There are letters from J. Marion Lee, who had been involuntarily committed to the Manhattan State Hospital, and was writing to her acquaintances asking for help in proving her sanity and receiving authorization for her release. She mentioned that she had a relationship in 1894 with Dr. James Albert "Al" Meara who allegedly drugged her, robbed her and had her committed because she had found out information about him that he wanted kept secret. There are love letters from Dr. Meara written to Miss Lee included in the collection. Her letters give a horrifying glimpse into incarceration in an insane asylum from 1894 to 1901. </p>
      <p>There are also letters from Albert and Abbie Legg asking Chaloner for money. Albert Legg was a former employee of Mr. Chaloner who wrote complaining about his wife and needing money. There are also letters from Abbie Legg who claimed that her husband mistreated her and left her penniless. Included with their correspondence is a letter from a policeman in Knoxville, Tennessee about Legg's drunkenness and womanizing. Chaloner wrote to Abbie Legg offering money to her husband on the condition that Legg would give some of it to her.</p>
      <p>There is correspondence between Mary Stacha Young and John Armstrong Chaloner that reveal that she was a singer who was in and out of work and had to support herself and her mother. She wrote to Mr. Chaloner telling him about her despair and requesting financial assistance. Chaloner responded that he would help them once he regained his rights to his property from his legal case. There is also correspondence about Chaloner's book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The X-Faculty</title> and his experiences with psychic phenomena. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically for correspondence and within each folder. 
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e144">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Certificate of Record for the American Jersey Cattle Club 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 April 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e153">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: Letters of J. Marion Lee at the Manhattan Mental Hospital
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1894-1901
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
          <physdesc>20 items
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Love letters from Dr. James Albert "Al" Meara to Marion Lee; and letters from Marion Lee to Mrs. Adaline E. Jackson, Mrs. Addie Eldridge, George Gordon Battle, Mrs. W. A. Hersey, Dr. H. B. Brice, and John Armstrong Chaloner
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e167">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: Albert Legg, Abbie Legg and John Armstrong Chaloner 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902-1903
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1;3
</container>
          <physdesc>10 items
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>June 25, n. y. Albert Legg: "The devil has taken hold of Mrs. Legg again and she is keeping me in hot water all of the time."
</p>
          <p>December 28, 1903 John Armstrong Chaloner writes to Abbie Legg that when his case is settled he will pay Mr. Legg one hundred dollars a month on the condition that Albert would give her thirty dollars a month.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e183">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: Letters to John Armstrong Chaloner 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
          <physdesc>7 items
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include Effie Ruth Varney (requests his autograph), Mary Elizabeth Breen (wishes him congratulations on his escape from Bloomingdale and success with his new book), George F. Fitzgerald, G. W. Vincent, John Penn Morris, and Laura Powers from the Methodist Church (requesting an organ for the church.)
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e197">
        <did>
          <unittitle>5 Correspondence: Mary Stacha Young and John Armstrong Chaloner 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1903-1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
          <physdesc>5 items
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e208">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence John Armstrong Chaloner to Thomas N. Hill 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1905
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
          <physdesc>3 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are letters asking Judge Hill to write a letter in support of Chaloner to Judge James U. Osborne regarding Chaloner's insanity case.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e222">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: John Armstrong Chaloner to "Whom it may concern"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1909
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In the event of his death Chaloner does not want his siblings on his property.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e236">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: John Armstrong Chaloner to Mr. G. B. Rives 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
</container>
          <physdesc>2 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters from John Armstrong Chaloner about using the pathway located on the property of Mr. Rives and regarding typhoid and the condition of Mrs. Douglas [wife of the groundskeeper.]
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e250">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: Rose Wilmer Page and John Armstrong Chaloner
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904, 1910
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
</container>
          <physdesc>12 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e261">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence: Rose Wilmer Page and John Armstrong Chaloner
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
</container>
          <physdesc>15 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e273">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Business Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1905; 1911
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
</container>
          <physdesc>27 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are letters between F. H. Treacy and John Armstrong Chaloner about the leasing or sale of the Roanoke Rapids Machinery Shop. Other correspondents mentioned are H. V. N. Philip, Winthrop Astor Chanler, Stanford White, and James Lindsay Gordon. Other business correspondence includes information about selling puppies, the Keswick Country Club, membership in the Alliance Francaise and a letter from the United States Patent Office regarding Chaloner's "Quarterly Newspaper." Correspondents in these matters were Emma K. Griffith, Richard H. Wilson, and H. E. Magruder.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e287">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Psychical Correspondence 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1911
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
</container>
          <physdesc>6 items
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence includes a letter from J. H. Hyslop to Chaloner asking for twenty five thousand to start the American Society for Psychical Research. Correspondents who admired Chaloner's writings on psychic phenomenon included Joseph Jalrow, Mrs. Joel W. Giles and Annie de Beers.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e301">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Publisher Correspondence 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901; 1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13
</container>
          <physdesc>3 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>October 1901 letter regarding advice on the paper and binding for Chaloner's book. Includes an untitled manuscript fragment/story about[Seraphine and Malatesta?]
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e315">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Invitations 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1903-1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14
</container>
          <physdesc>5 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>November 29, 1904 invitation from Edwin A. Alderman  to meet the French ambassador.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e329">
        <did>
          <unittitle>News clippings
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15
</container>
          <physdesc>15 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are newspaper clippings about a District Attorney arraigning public officials and the "newspaper government;" a clipping about the murder of McAuliffe; news about the Boer War; and various news clippings mentioning members of the Astor family.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e343">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Petition for temporary injunction in Chaloner v. Dunn 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1921
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item, printed.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Supreme Court Case; notice of motion about the citizenship (Virginia or North Carolina) of John Armstrong Chaloner.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e357">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed materials
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17
</container>
          <physdesc>5 items,
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e368">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Receipts
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18
</container>
          <physdesc>9 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
