<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03983">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03983::A Guide to the Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., )//EN" "viu03983.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.,
</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Byrd, Senator Harry F. Jr., Papers of 
<num type="collectionnumber">10320-k 
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2007 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Stephanie Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/12/2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 
</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">10320-k 
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2007
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">10320-k
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>Access to the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers is controlled by the Honorable Harry F. Byrd, Jr. An applicant for access who is not associated with the University of Virginia must furnish to the Director of Special Collections a brief description of his academic or other qualifications, a summary of his research project, and a description of any projected publication that might make use of material from, or material derived from, the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers. The Director of Special Collections will contact Senator Byrd and will notify the applicant of the Senator's decision.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>No part of the Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Papers, nor any material from them, or derived from them, may be published without the express permission of the Honorable Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Please see Access Restrictions above for the procedure to be followed to obtain Senator Byrd's permission.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Accession #10320-k, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Winchester, Virginia, on May 26, 2005.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Harry Flood Byrd, Jr., a former member of the Virginia Senate (1947-1965), United States Senator for Virginia (1965-1983), and newspaper executive, was born in Winchester, Virginia, on December 20, 1914, son of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and Anne Douglas (Beverley) Byrd. He was a student at the Virginia Military Institute, 1931-1933, and the University of Virginia, 1933-1935. Byrd married Gretchen B. Thomson of New Orleans, on August 9, 1941, and they had three children, Harry, Thomas Thomson, and Beverley. 
</p>
      <p>
Appointed to the United States Senate in 1965, Senator Byrd was elected to the Senate in 1966 as a Democrat and was reelected in 1970 and 1976 as an Independent. He was the first person in the history of the Senate to be elected twice as an Independent. Byrd was active on both the Armed Services Committee and the Finance Committee. He was also a member of the Virginia Democratic Central Committee (1940-1966). 
</p>
      <p>
Byrd was the editor of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winchester Evening Star</title> from 1935-, publisher of the Harrisonburg, Virginia, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Daily News Record</title>, 1937-; President and Director of the Rockingham Publishing Company, from 1946; director of the Associated Press, 1950-1966. 
</p>
      <p>
During World War II, he served as an executive officer of a patrol bombing squadron in the Central and Western Pacific as a Lieutenant Commander in the United States Naval Reserve. Byrd was a recipient of the Honor Medal, and a member of the Veterans of Foreign Wars, the American Legion, Rotarian Club, National Press Club, and the Army-Navy Club.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This addition to the papers of Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. consists of 370 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot), ca. 1960, 1966, 1982-2005. The papers contain manuscripts (electrostatic copies), typescripts and page proofs for <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds:  An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign</title> by Harry F. Byrd, Jr.; correspondence concerning the publication of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds</title> and responses from recipients and other readers to the book, many of whom wrote about their own involvement in or reminiscences about the 1970 campaign. Many of the responses were from U.S. Senators, members of the Virginia legislature, members of the media, and close friends of Byrd.
</p>
      <p>
Also present are news clippings concerning Defying the Odds, the burial of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and miscellaneous honors awarded to Harry F. Byrd, Jr., including the New Market Medal awarded to Harry F. Byrd, Jr. by VMI (2005 May 16); awards and honors, including resolutions and statues; and photographs. The collection also contains a letter from Richard E. Byrd to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Dear Rixey</title> [Smith], January 29, 1948.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e146">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Award - National Associated Businessmen Watchdog of the Treasury Award,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971-1972 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e157">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Award- <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Man-Boy Americanism Award</title> to Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">In Recognition of Distinguished and Unselfish Service to our Nation, State and Northern Virginia Communities.</title>
          </p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e176">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Award- 94th Congress National Federation of Independent Business Guardian of Small Business Award,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1975
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e187">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Award- Boy Scouts of America Great Salt Lake Council Appreciation Award,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1981 February 27 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e198">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning the publication of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 April-July
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include several persons who sent editing suggestions: J. Edward Grimsley, Charles L. Bartlett, Nelson Hyde, and James J. Kilpatrick; Larry J. Sabato, who wrote the preface; and several persons who wrote blurb statements for the book: Senator Sam Nunn (fax), Senator Russell B. Long (fax), and Charles McDowell. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e213">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning the publication of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/>1998 August-October
</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e225">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning responses to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 October-November
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include: George F. Allen, Lewis Allen, Hunter B. Andrews, William L. Armstrong, John Ashcroft, Charles L. Bartlett, Frank Batten, Fitzgerald Bemiss, David S. Broder, David Tennant Bryan, J. Stewart Bryan III, Judge James L. Buckley, Robert C. Byrd, George M. Cochran, Thad Cochran, John Warren Cooke, Paul D. Coverdell, Pete V. Domenici, Thomas N. Downing, Mark L. Earley, Gerald Ford, James S. Gilmore, III, Mills E. Godwin, Jr. (2 letters), Virgil H. Goode, Bob Goodlatte, Alan Greenspan, Ed Grimsley, Orrin G. Hatch, Jesse Helms, Nelson Hyde, J.J. Jewett, Paul Laxalt, Joseph I. Lieberman, Bob Livingston, Russell B. Long, Richard G. Lugar, Connie Mack, Mike Mansfield, John F. McNair, III, Patrick Munroe, W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr., Don Nickles, Herman J. Obermayer, Cokie Roberts, Sandra Mims Rowe, George Warren Shanks, Richard T. Short, Arlen Specter, William C. Stuart III, Fred Thompson, and Strom Thurmond.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e240">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning responses to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 December-1999 January
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include: Robert F. Bennett, Lloyd Bentsen, George Bush, Robert C. Fitzgerald, Judge Robert E. Gibson, Judge William H. Hodges, Ernest F. Hollings, Walter Dee Huddleston, Daniel K. Inouye, Patrick J. Leahy, Henry Luce III, Paul Saunier, Jr. (relates two anecdotes about Bill Tuck), Paul Simon, Howard K. Smith, Ted Stevens, Paul A. Volcker, Frank R. Wolf, and T. Eugene Worrell.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning responses to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999 February-2003
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include: Maryon Allen (anecdote about George Wallace), William Cohen, Mark O. Hatfield, Fred G. Pollard, William Rehnquist, Harrison H. Schmitt, John B. Updike (former staffer), Jesse Ventura, and Malcolm Wallop.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e270">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence concerning responses to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds:  An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1998-2000
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Correspondents include: Leslie D. Campbell, Jr., John T. Casteen, III, Clifford P. Hansen, Bill Mims, and Charles Wampler, Jr. (2 letters).
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e285">
        <did>
          <unittitle><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign</title>- Manuscript Chapters 1, 3, 6,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 April 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Copies. 
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e298">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 May 31
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Typescript Revision, 84 pages (Copy).
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e311">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign,</title>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998 July 21
</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
          <physdesc>Page Proofs and Dust Jacket Designs.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e324">
        <did>
          <unittitle>News clippings concerning Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and his book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Defying the Odds: An Independent Senator's Historic Campaign</title>, the burial of his father, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and miscellaneous honors awarded to Byrd,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1966, 1998-2005
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e336">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photographs of President Dwight Eisenhower and Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1960 Oct 27), including a letter of explanation dated October 21, 2003; and  photograph of Virginia Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. giving a speech on the floor of the Virginia Senate (n.d.),
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e345">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photographs of Cadets at Shenandoah Valley Military Academy, Winchester, Virginia,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920's
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photograph of the Associated Press Board of Directors,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize. 
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e367">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photograph of a <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Time Magazine</title> quote concerning the 1970 Virginia Senate election and an actual newspaper heading from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winchester Evening Star</title> about the Byrd victory,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e384">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proofs and Correspondence for a series of articles by Douglas B. O' Connell and Adrian O'Connor concerning the history of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Winchester Star</title> which was later made into a book,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1996-1997
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e396">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Resolutions concerning Harry F. Byrd, Jr. and the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Winchester Star</title> Leadership Awards and other Honors,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982-2004
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e408">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Senate Joint Resolution 179 honoring Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>Oversize.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
