<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01372">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01372::A Guide to the Papers of Margaret Lynn Templeton//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01372.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01372::A Guide to the Papers of
             Margaret Lynn Templeton//EN" "viu01372.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Margaret Lynn
            Templeton 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915-1934</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Templeton, Margaret Lynn Papers
            1915-1934 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11125</num></subtitle><author>Special Collections Staff</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">39 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Sue Cuthbertson, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4/30/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01372::A Guide to the
            Papers of Margaret Lynn Templeton//EN" "viu01372.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Margaret Lynn Templeton 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915-1934</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11125</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Margaret Lynn Templeton 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1915-1934</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11125</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">Five volumes of
         diaries.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The diaries of Margaret Lynn
         Templeton, (1895-1978), of Staunton, Va., contain personal
         entries documenting her social, academic, and business
         life.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Margaret Lynn Templeton, Accession #11125 ,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These diaries were made a gift to the Library by Joan
            Jacobs Brumberg of Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, on
            November 10, 1993.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are five volumes of diaries, December 1915 through
         March 18, 1934, kept by Margaret Lynn Templeton (1895-1978) of
         Staunton, Virginia. There are personal entries documenting her
         social, academic and business life. There are frequent
         references to military and social activities; officers,
         cadets, and students; and school buildings at Staunton
         Military Academy, Virginia Military Institute, and Washington
         and Lee University. References to Virginia Military Institute
         include drilling and marching, dress parades, graduation,
         balls and dances, patriotic pageants, and the library. Also
         mentioned are the Ambulance Unit and Society Celebration at
         Washington and Lee University. There is a mention of Helen
         Keller being at the New Theatre (May 1916).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Organization</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume I:</emph>7 pages 1-56, December 31,
         1915 - January 6, 1917, written on recto; pages 57-112,
         January 13, 1917 - November 3, 1917, written on verso.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume II:</emph>pages 113-270 (271
         blank), November 4, 1917 - October 13, 1919; list of
         "1919-1920 Dances"; [index] of 1918-1920; "Cadets I knew in
         1918-1919"; and, "Dore House Bunch 1918- 1919" following last
         page of diary.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume III:</emph>pages unnumbered,
         October 18, 1919 - September 9, 1921; "Dances 1919- 1920" and
         "Dances 1920-1921" on front cover; [index] of 1920-1921
         following last page of diary.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume IV:</emph>pages unnumbered,
         September 11, 1921 - May 13, 1928.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume V:</emph>pages unnumbered, June 8,
         1928 - March 18, 1934.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Select Diary Entries</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Jan:</emph>[at Curry's playing and
         dancing; tea at Mrs. J. A. Alexander; [Warren] Giles; Mr.
         Pine; Mr. and Mrs. Vernon Castle in the "Whirl of Life"; Mrs.
         Terry; mother; Harold Lockwood and May Allison in "End of the
         Road"; Miss Evie and Miss Moss; Mary Pickford in "Madam
         Butterfly"; dance at Staunton Military Academy; Mr. McKelvey;
         [dansant] at Mrs. S. D. Timberlake, Jr's; Junior meeting;
         dancing class; Starke; Eleanor; Eleanor Curry; Harold Lockwood
         at the New Theatre; to sally port; to M. S. B. to Anton
         Kaspar's recital; Francis Bell's sister; "Armstrong's
         wife"]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Feb:</emph>[Kenyon Smith; T. B. S.;
         dancing class; Edmund Starke; tea at Stuart Hall; mother; Joe
         Collins; Edwin Wayland; "Strife Eternal" at New Theatre;
         Argyle's; Willie Hann; Clifton Collier; basketball game
         between Staunton Military Academy and Washington and Lee
         University scrubs; Miss Baugh's and Mr. Thomas' recital; Miss
         Angy Manning Taylor's Bible lecture at First Presbyterian
         Church; Alumnae Board meeting; "Gentleman from Indiana"; Page;
         Eleanor; Margery Brelsford Pilson and her son Billy Brelsford;
         reception at Stuart Hall; type writing; Marguerite Clark in
         "The Prince and the Pauper"; Fullerton; Harold Lockwood in
         "The Buzzard's Shadow"; "Reveries of a Bachelor" at the New
         Theatre for the King's Daughters' Union; Dad; lecture at high
         school; Margaret Hawkes; Margaret Enslow; Evangeline Harman;
         Charlotte Spotts; Hogshead's; Catherine Holt; Episcopal
         reception for Staunton Military Academy cadets in church
         squad; McKelvey; Newbury; James; William Sale; Gates; Norman;
         movies; Belgian Benefit at New Theatre; double quartet from
         Staunton Military Academy; Schaubs; Lybarger; Frazier;
         McAllister; Laws; Kibbe]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Mar:</emph>[dancing class; Hann;
         Fullerton; Marsh; Kolstad; movies with Dad; downtown; Eleanor;
         Edwin Wayland; special dancing class; Virginia Eddy; Edith
         Bayles; millinery openings; Katherine Paul; Harriet Tynes;
         Carrie Sublett; tea at Mrs. Cassell's; Mary Pickford in "The
         Foundling"; recital at M. B. S.; Henghan; Leap Year Dance;
         Starke; Frances Churchman; James to Kentucky; Evangeline
         Harman; dance at Wilbur Stevens; Hogshead's; "Gaymont" country
         club; Juliet Kyle; Elsie; "Rabbit"; Low; Mr. Carter;
         Reifsneider; Laws; Westgate; Dot Curry; Webb Adams; Nannie
         Adams; Frances Churchman; Eliza Holt; played the Victrola;
         Morton [Logan]; Slater Logan]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Apr:</emph>[Eleanor; Carrie Sublett;
         downtown; Virginia Military Institute Easter dances; movies;
         Waynesboro; Mrs. Cassell; Mary Ella Webb; Barksdale cottage;
         Mrs. Gassman; Mrs. Kinnear; Mrs. J. E. Irvine; Mrs. Bush; Mrs.
         Culton; Mr. Leonard; meeting at Star Theatre with delegates;
         Mrs. Merchant, chairman of Shiloh Monument Fund for Virginia;
         Mrs. Coiner; Mrs. Myers; Mrs. Wayland; historical meeting;
         Captain Carson; Virginia Military Institute '15 in the Lyric
         Orchestra; on train; Mrs. Guy; meeting in camp room with talks
         by Miss Preston, Mrs. Irvine and Mrs. Ellyson; Mrs. Alexander;
         Julian Johnson; Edmund Starke; church; Katherine Paul; Edith
         and Mrs. Bayles; Virginia; First Dress Parade; Miss Marian
         Fuller; Webb Adams; M. B. A.; Virginia Military Institute
         Library; "Pat" Lafferty; Colonel Hodges; Mr. Amory; Mr.
         Durant; Benny Bowering; Aunt Mary; Lawrence Williams; "Wisdom"
         Boykin; baseball game; Janet Hughes; Mr. Zea; Mr. Steele;
         "Mutt" Loth; Mrs. Sansberry; Mr. and Mrs. McGiffert; John
         Bradford; Aunt "N" Nellie; movies at Virginia Military
         Institute; C. B. Thomas; Campbell Brown; Joe Collins; Billy
         Thomas; played piano; Mr. Sitwell; Mr. Parker; Miss Sitwell;
         Miss Cary; Stevenson; Major Anderson; Dress Parade; "Son"
         Read; circus and parade; Dutch Inn; Benny Bowering; Aunt "M";
         Neal Chapin; Mr. Mettinheimer; Mr. Thornton; Ashton Sale; Mr.
         Driscoll; S. L. Bagby; Mr. Porter; Mr. Alverson; Mr. Massie;
         Winfred Kidd; dance cards in white leather card cases stamped
         in gold; Janet; Interscholastic Track Meet; Staunton Military
         Academy boys; Ed Scriven; Howe; Mr. Blow; sang in choir; Mr.
         Grossman]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 May:</emph>[Lawrence Williams; on
         train with Virginia Military Institute baseball team and
         Staunton Military Academy track team; Helen Keller at the New
         Theatre; Edwin Wayland; Stuart Hall; work on the Bessie Hunton
         essays; Mr. Church; Mr. Hann; Neal Chapin; Collier; Billy
         Thomas; Anne Willard; Mary Pickford in "Poor Little Peppina";
         party for the Spanish boys at Staunton Military Academy given
         by Miss Houston; tea at the McDowell's; Eleanor; Staunton
         Military Academy boys left for camp; "Wisdom" Boykin; Church
         left for Annapolis; McDonnell; Mary and Carrie Walke; Miss
         Baugh; Miss Gammon; Dad; Mother; Deborah and Lewis; tea at
         Mrs. Swimley's for Ruth Guyer; Page; Mr. Mantor; Mr. Driscoll;
         Major Anderson; Mr. McGiffert; Mr. Lafferty; Virginia Military
         Institute final invitation; Mr. Stevenson; downtown; McKelvey;
         cadets return from camp; Dress Parade; Starke; Carter;
         Katherine Paul; Hanson; final drills; Martha Hancher; Edith
         Bayles; commencement exercises at the New Theatre; Guy C.
         Jackson]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 June:</emph>[Willis Hann; Starke;
         Wright; graduate recital at Stuart Hall; party for choir at
         Mr. McDowell's; Miss Mattie Shreckhise; Alumnae meeting at
         Stuart Hall; movies; Alumnae Banquet at Virginia Hotel; final
         recital at Stuart Hall; final exercises at Stuart Hall;
         Virginia Eddy received the Bessie Hunton Essay prize; to
         Lexington; meeting of the Federation of Women's Club; Mary
         Walke; Major Anderson; Virginia Military Institute Library;
         Mr. McGiffert; Benny Bowering; Mr. Scriven; Mr. Harrison;
         Janet Hughes; Captain Snidow; Mother; Dad; Society Celebration
         at Washington and Lewis University; dedication of Doremus
         Gymnasium; Dress Parade; Joe Collins; reception at Dr. Smith's
         house; Mr. Smithson; Mr. Houston; Mr. Houston Showell; Mr.
         Masinter; Washington and Lewis University final exercises; Mr.
         Driscoll; card for the dances; Opening Hop; Neal Chapin; Mr.
         Porter; Billy Thomas; Horace L. Smith '15 ; track meet; Maury
         "Wisdom" Boykin; Mr. Ingram; Mr. Porcher; Will Chapin; Mrs.
         Pratt; Janet; Miss Bauers; W. B. Bradford; Mr. Campbell; Mr.
         Lafferty; service at Virginia Military Institute; "Son" Read;
         Guard Mounting; Mr. Ingram; Ida May Digges; Dress Parade; the
         Archers; the Meade's; Mayhew Mantor; the German, Douglas
         Fraser; alumni had a figure; Francis Bell; combat exercises;
         on Hill for Graduation Parade; alumni drill; John C. Parker
         '14; Captain Snidow; dances; Alumni Banquet; Joe Collins
         received the Garnett Andrews prize for best essay on a
         military subject; "Little Thomas"; graduation exercises; Mr.
         Harrison]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 July:</emph>[entertainment for the
         church at the "Pines"; describes the ski-da-mer-rinks with
         Nancy Pendleton, Bessie Paul Gassman, Gretchen Bell, and
         Margaret Lynn Templeton as the creatures; Miss Edna Gretchen
         Hazard; "Pat" Lafferty; movies; Websters; Evan Sidebottom
         McCord, president of Washington and Lee University students;
         to Fairfield; Malvin Watkins; Janet; cousin Berta; Joe Sale;
         Francis and Louise Houston; "spin" in the car; William Sale;
         Dr. and Mrs. Vaden; Kenneth [Watkins]; Noel Shelton and his
         bride; William Taylor; Mr. Akers sang; Jimmy Martin; Mary
         Irvin Watkins; "Children's Day Services" at the school
         building; cousin Jennie Wheat; Noel and Bess; Estaline Sale;
         activities include dancing to organ and violin music; playing
         dominoes and croquet, taking pictures, and telling fortunes;
         listened to Mr. Akers play; cousin Will Templeton; sewing;
         telling ghost stories; [base]ball game between Fairfield and
         Walker's Creek; Bill Martin; Mr. Monteith, Estaline Sale's
         fianc&amp;#40672;dancing to the Victrola; Jack Lee; several
         car breakdowns to the from the dance; watching shooting stars;
         New Providence to church; cousin Berta and Mr. McFadden; Mrs.
         Elderton; Frances Sale; Phil Hanger; Mr. Turk; Henry Turk; the
         Houstons; cousin Anna; Wilson Springs; "Fats" Patterson; Bill
         Taylor; the Miley's Jack Lee]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Sep:</emph>[trip from Staunton to
         Lexington; Aunt "M"; Aunt "N" [Nellie]; the Edwards; the
         Bruces; Janet Hughes; Major Anderson; Mr. Sitwell; the Moores
         at the Blue Hotel; Mr. Miles, a student; Mr. Yen Chu Lee, the
         Chinaman; McCrum's; Mr. Tinsley; Mr. Colburn; Mr. Goodman;
         Adair's; Benny [Bowering] sent autographed copy of his song,
         "V. M. I. Spirit"; Major Murray Edwards' dance; dance in
         Virginia Military Institute Library; Major Millner; Captain
         Hepner; Mr. Durham; Mr. White; Aunt Virginia; movies; Virginia
         Military Institute [church] services; S. U. McGiffert; Dress
         Parade; E. S. McCord; "Son" [Read]; Phil Hanger; James;
         Lawrence Williams; Mrs. Brooke; Inspection; Ida May Digges;
         Mr. Durham; Mr. Eva; Mr. McCabe; Mr. Handley; cadets drilling;
         Douglas Fraser; Dress Parade; Jennie Wheat; D. P. Lawrence;
         Mr. Grubb]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Oct:</emph>[dancing classes; Ferris;
         Twitchell; Tannenbaum; O'Connor; Gundry; movies; Page; Mary
         Pickford in "Hulda from Holland"; Y. M. C. A.; Glenn Williams;
         Joseph; Mr. Nicholson; Paul Jones' figures at dancing class;
         Roderick; Munn.; Mackenzie; Mr. Kay; Whittaker; James; Lummus;
         Sloan Stevens Orr; Teddy Clark; Elizabeth Kerr; Frances
         Churchman; Mother; Mrs. Logan and Barnes; circles at dancing
         classes; Hogshead's Heughan; Stevens' Saunderson; Driskell;
         Jenkins]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Nov:</emph>[dancing classes; Frances;
         Billy Ferris; Mr. Williams; Mr. Armitage; Teddy Clark; Merrill
         Yost; Glenn Williams; Gibbs' bungalow; taking pictures;
         movies; Whorley; invitation to informal dance; Y. M. C. A. for
         election returns; James; Jenkins; Jim Roderick; Kay; Streit;
         Boxley; Watters; Wilkinson; Montgomery; Mahs; Lesczynski; Mrs.
         Logan; O'Connor; R. Barnes; Whittaker; G. Smith; Armitage
         Williams; Mother; Dad; Major [Ferris]; Mr. Pons gave her a
         "huge rush"; heard Elizabeth de Barrie Gille; Junior meeting;
         kitchen shower at Mary Stuart Robertson's for Kinney;
         Hogshead's; Broach; Sloane Stevens; Young; boys "rushing"
         her]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1916 Dec:</emph>[Frances; Reddy Laws;
         Hogshead's' Billy [Ferris]; Clough; Dixie Pons; Nicholson;
         Jenkins; Montgomery; dancing to the Victrola; Teddy [Clark];
         Twitchell; Young; date for the Washington Hop; Pritchard;
         dancing classes; Munn; Langley; Ford; "Pat" Watters; sold
         Christmas Red Cross seals; Helen Mooers; Dorothy Mercereau;
         Broach; O'Connor; Barnes; Armitage [Williams]; Christy; Mr.
         Armstrong; movies; cadets; Major [Ferris]; Roderick;
         Stevenson; McGiffert; Virginia Military Institute Library;
         Major Edwards; Captain Mayo; Major Anderson; Jackson Arch; Mr.
         Durham; Mr. Cole; Mr. Davis; "Son" Read; Janet; Mr. Massie;
         visit to hospital; Aunt Mary; Francis Bell; Aunt Nellie;
         Weinberg's; Bill Harrison; Mr. Adelstein; Marvin Driscoll; Mr.
         Mettenheimer; Sunday School tree; Lawrence Williams; church;
         Josiah Porter Green or "P Green"; Mr. Yen Chu Lee, the
         Chinaman; McCrum's; Mr. Tinsley; Benny Bowering; Mr. Abell,
         the coach; Major Stuart Wise Anderson; Captain Snidow; Mr.
         Rothert, a cadet; Miss Neale; Churchill Robertson; dansant at
         Virginia Military Institute; Mr. Lacy; Mr. Ruffin; H. B.
         Barton; Washington and Lee University; Will Chapin; taking
         pictures]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1917 Jan:</emph>[Yen Chu] Lee; Bessie and
         Paul Gassman; movies; Aunt "N" [Nellie]; Dixie [Pons]; Mr.
         Armstrong; Elizabeth Kerr; Billy [Ferris]; invitation to
         dance; James; boys "rushing" her; went to Intolerance; Mr.
         Roderick; Frances; fight in the gym; Teddy Clark; Young;
         Lidgemeyer; went to the New Theatre to see "Seventeen";
         Colonel Kable; saw soldiers come from the border; Pritchard;
         faculty party at Miss Foster's; Lee-Jackson Celebration at
         Stuart Hall; Mr. Taylor from Staunton Military Academy; Y. M.
         C. A.; "Tools" Lybarger responsible for a court-martial of Dr.
         Kable; dancing class; Andrews; O'Connor' Mother; Taylor;
         [basket]ball game; Frances; Hogshead's; dancing classes; date
         for Washington Hop; Billy [Ferris] in the Guard Room for
         several weeks; Major [Ferris]; reception at Stuart Hall;
         dance; Mr. Hutchings; Mr. Hogshead; Merrill taking pictures;
         Mr. Graham; banquet at the Y. M. C. A.; Christy]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1917 Feb:</emph>[Dixie [Pons]; dancing
         classes; church reception at First Presbyterian Church; Philip
         Enslow, Desmond Chandler, Schloss, Brooks, Fielding Lewis;
         "Mr. Bill" Coumerilk; "Johnny" Ayers; tea at the Bickles;
         Mother; downtown; Roderick; Frances; Emmert; McIlheny's; Teddy
         Clark; Andrews; Young; Johnson; invitation to the formal;
         basketball game of Staunton Military Academy; Mr. White; Fancy
         Dress Ball at Washington and Lee University; Al. G. Fields
         Minstrels; Mr. Wehrly; Forrester; Lesure; concert at the Y. M.
         C. A.; Yen Chu Lee; started work in Mr. Stickley's office; to
         Lexington; Aunt "M"; went to Dutch Inn; Mr. Hansel; Mrs.
         Nichols; Ring Turn Phi; Benny Bowering; Lawrence Williams;
         Major Anderson; Janet Hughes; Miss Neal; Captain Millner;
         Captain Snidow; John Porter Green; Mr. McCabe; Marvin
         Driscoll; Mr. Chapin; Mr. Blow; "Wisdom" Boykin; Mr. Mallard;
         Shull; Campbell; Sterling; Dr. Smith's son; in the senior
         figure with Roger White; left Lexington for Staunton; Alfred
         Young; Staunton Military Academy dance, in opening figure with
         Young; choir rehearsal]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1917 Mar:</emph>[played Grafonola; left
         for Washington; Mother; Aunt "N" [Nellie] and Mrs. Austin on
         train; at Winchester, party of boys from the Shenandoah
         Military Academy got on the train; Mr. Lovell; Inauguration
         guests; St. Andrews; Miss Hazard; presidential parade; Woodrow
         Wilson passed; to Hibbs Building to see fireworks; visited the
         Monument, the Capitol and the White House; White House closed
         to visitors due to explosion that wrecked the East Room;
         trouble with suffragettes the previous day; Huyler's; a Victor
         store; Cumberland Apartments; saw Great Expectations with Jack
         Pickford and Louise Huff; left Washington for Staunton; Mr.
         Downing, Virginia Military Institute cadet; Harpers Ferry; Mr.
         Waters; dancing classes; Frank O'Connor; Teddy [Clark]; Billy
         [Ferris]; Forrester; Wehrly; Dennett; Saturday night dance;
         Hutchings; Walker; Ortez; Captain Lykes; Major [Ferris]; David
         Bell; "Retreat"; Mr. "Andy" Grose; Mr. Oliver; James; Dixie
         [Pons]; received bid to Washington and Lee Easter dances from
         Roger White; Worline; Coumerilk; Romeo and Juliet at the
         movies; Betty Sommerville; took pictures]</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1917 Apr:</emph>[Worline; Mr. Coumerilk;
         Frances; Billy [Ferris]; Teddy [Clark]; took pictures;
         "Retreat"; Mother; Major [Ferris]; Major [Ferris]; Elinor
         Surber; Elizabeth Kerr; Taylor; Roderick; Fred Stock; dancing
         classes; Ortez; Mrs. Terry; Ellinor; Dress Parade; Inspection
         for the Government Inspector; Robert McGuffin; Mary Pickford
         movie; Young; choir practice; "C" company scouting; Hutchings;
         King; Matthews; Dennett; in Patriotic Parade in car devoted to
         the Staunton Juniors; Billy Ferris returned ring; Worline;
         Clifford Matthews; hair washed at Reba's; Miss Louis McChuy;
         Betty Somerville; left Staunton for Lexington; Roger White;
         Aunt Mary; Monday night dance; Shull, Hansel, Owens; Benny
         Bowering; "Son" Read; Francis Bell; Mr. Durham; Mr. Blow;
         "Wisdom" Boykin; Hansel; Gen. Nichols; Capt. McKay; Miss
         Nettie Smith; Capt. Derbyshire; Mr. Tinsley; Mr. Chapman;
         Church Robertson; Janet Hughes; Mr. Black; invitations to
         finals; Doremus Gymnasium for the dansant; Knighton; Richards;
         Kicklighter; "Inky" Peters; McCrum's; Mr. Mallard; movies;
         "Boots" Walker from Covington; Mr. Jeter; Mr. Richards;
         Sperner; Stiles; Shepperson; Knighton; Harnsberger, formerly
         S. M. A.; O'Connor; "Retreat"; concert at Y.M.C.A.; Wehrly;
         return to Staunton; Saturday night dance; Saunderson, the
         adjutant; Snyder}</p>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
