<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03861">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03861::Papers of William Hartwell Perry, Jr.)//EN" "viu03861.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of William Hartwell Perry, Jr. <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1865</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Perry, William Hartwell Jr., Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">7786-d
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/27/2005 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of William Hartwell Perry, Jr. <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">7786-d
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of William Hartwell Perry, Jr.
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1865
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">7786-d
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of William Hartwell Perry, Jr., Accession #7786-d, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Bruce Engstler, Charlottesville, Virginia, on May 8, 1967.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of eighty-nine letters, 1861-1863, from William H. Perry, Jr. (1836-?), a lawyer practicing in the courts of Lunenburg County, Nottoway County, and Prince Edward County, to his family
while serving in the Confederate army. William H. Perry, Jr., who attended the University of Virginia from 1856 to 1858, served with the Virginia Artillery, First Richmond Howitzer Company, 3rd Brigade, 2nd
Division. He saw action in the Orange County and Richmond, Virginia areas and participated in the Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville and Gettysburg campaigns, and the battle of Williamsburg.
</p>
      <p>Also present in the collection is one memoranda and medical fee account book, 1860-1865, with an name index, containing some references to events during the Civil War belonging to William H. Perry, Sr., a
physician of Lunenburg County, Virginia.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">1861</title><lb/>All four letters are written from Camp Shields, Virginia, about four miles south of Strasburg, Virginia. January 9, 1861 he writes his mother of his forays to Point of
Rocks and describes building his "house"--a 15 by 14 1/2 foot shelter covered with plank scavenged from the area. January 19, 1861 he tells his mother that he has moved into winter quarters and has a case of
mumps. January 23, 1861 the mumps worsen. February 2, 1861 to father, from Mr. McPherson's, reports he is staying with McPherson family while recovering from illness, is reading McCauley's England, muses that the
war will be long and wonders if General George Bibb Crittenden's "continued intoxication" could possibly be caused by division in his family as his brother, Thomas L. Crittenden, is a Union General; thinks
Confederate soldiers are tired of the war but would rather fight for their lifetime than reenter the old Union.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">January-July, 1862</title><lb/>January 11, 1862 from Camp Shields, describes camp life to father; likens his company to a fine bunch of southern gentlemen--"not FFV's, but clerks and
representatives of the commercial class." There is good eating, not much drinking because liquor costs are high; his brigade composed mostly of Mississippians, except for the cavalry and the artillery. February
10, 1862 comments on father's pleasant visit to Camp Shields, hears England has acknowledged the Confederacy; hears enemy firing nearby, presumably to celebrate the fall of Fort Henry. February 16, 1862 discusses
furloughs and the means of obtaining them and possibilities of a protracted war but says "That we will succeed I do not doubt."
</p>
      <p>February 18, 1862 gives mother a recipe for making coffee out of wheat. February 23, 1862 (still from Camp Shields) reports arrival of two big guns--a 32-pounder and a 24-pounder and describes their range;
talks of the arrest of Union General Charles Pomeroy Stone and speculates why; discusses the Henry &amp; Donelson campaign and its effect on the morale of troops. March 2, 1862 tells father of an expedition to
fire on Yankee boats if they passed on the Potomac; under enemy fire which they could not return because of possessing only a 6-pounder with a range of 1600 yards; discusses firing at Balls Bluff when enemy landed
and how Confederate soldiers cut bullets from the trees for souvenirs; further remarks on "Fort Donelson disaster" with suggestion that surrender of twelve thousand men "was unpardonable."
</p>
      <p>March 10, 1862 1/2 mile from Warrenton, describes to father his part in retreat of the Confederates as the whole Potomac army fell back, says Yankees are said to be in Leesburg "arresting secession citizens."
March [ ], 1862 tells father of marching one week and 79 miles over country roads en route to near Gordonsville. March 23, 1862 from Orange County, writes little brother and exhorts him to study and to write and
continues with a description of his camp. April 16,17, 18, 1862 to father, in the trenches on the James River seven miles from Yorktown, describes positioning of the artillery and details of fighting and wounded.
May 19, 1862 four miles from Richmond, tells mother of falling back to present position after battle of Williamsburg; his brigade has marched around Richmond and now is on the Mechanicsville Turnpike running out
toward Old Church in Hanover County. May 20 (continued in previous letter) doesn't see how General McClellan (George Brinton) can "claim a victory at Williamsburg."
</p>
      <p>May 25, 1862 five miles from Richmond, tells father he thinks Jefferson Davis has proved a "mean executive" and comments on the character of South Carolinians who "have shown their chivalry since the war began
by running whenever they had an occasion to fight." June 1, 1862 to father from 4 1/2 miles from Richmond on Garnett's farm, describes "battle of considerable dimension" near James River (Seven Pines) and his part
in it, with his company being engaged only an hour or two; speaks of the death of General Robert Hatton and the severe wounding of Brig. General Johnston Pettigrew.
</p>
      <p>June 2, 1862 largely illegible letter describes "terrible battle--one killed, eight or ten wounded in my company." June 20, 1862 to father, 4 1/2 miles from Richmond, speculates on various rumors concerning
movements of Confederate army and how little the average soldier knows; speaks of horrific losses on both sides in the five battles of Richmond (which he describes in some detail); tells of walking over the
battlefield and counting the dead on both sides, many of whom were buried where they lay; bemoans the loss of fine horses on both sides, and worries about lack of discipline in the infantry. June 22, 1862 to
father, 4 1/2 miles from Richmond, hears General Stonewall Jackson is coming with his army to assist; describes an incident involving the wounding of General Joseph E. Johnston and pictures him as the "finest
looking man I ever saw;" says General J. E. B. Stuart is gallant. June 26, 1862 to father, 100 yards from the front, artillery signifies start of battle; describes the sound of musketry--June 27 (cont'd from June
26) describes details of raging battle, and at 11:15 continues to write as shells fall on the camp. June 30, 1862 to father nine miles from Richmond, writes from Yankee breastworks after pursuing General George
McClellan's retreating force, with his brigade third from front rank; writes that prisoners "seem delighted at being captured;" says quantity of plunder left is immense, including coats, oil cloths and knapsacks
of splendid quality.
</p>
      <p>July 5, 1862 to father nine miles from Richmond, talks of McClellan's further retreat; thinks General John Bankhead Magruder showed horrible management skills or enemy would have been routed early in day; says
"Magruder said by all to have been drunk" adding that the general had come to camp late that night very much intoxicated. Undated partial letter concerning battle of Richmond noting violent opposition of people of
that city to Jefferson Davis because of "his neglect of its defense."
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">August-December, 1862</title><lb/>August 19, 1862 to mother 1/2 miles N.E. of Camp Lee, Virginia, unit is awaiting guns--one or two 6-pounders. August 26, 1862 still near Richmond, to
mother, describes monotonous life, but gives vivid description of attending meetings of Confederate Congress in Richmond with critiques of William Porcher Miles, South Carolina; Henry Stuart Foote, Mississippi;
Thomas S. Bocock, Virginia, and Francis Strother Lyon, Richmond; relates passage of Virginia's "motion to inquire" as to whether Confederate Commission should be withdrawn from Europe. September 16, 1862 near Camp
Lee, to mother, speaks of clothing costs and how he has obtained some. September 23, 1862 near Richmond, to father, awaiting orders to march; describes mood of people of Richmond; discusses Yankees use of
"parolees" in fighting Indians--cont'd, September 24, 1862 more discussion of parole system; September 30, 1862 near Camp Lee, Virginia, to father, getting ready to leave for Culpeper Courthouse.
</p>
      <p>[October 9, 1862] to father, tells of marching 18 miles a day to Culpeper Court House and passing Slaughter Mountain, where he observed the advantage to General Jackson's army afforded by the topography; says
people in the vicinity are all quite down on the Yankees because of the destruction they caused and "their treatment of women." October 22, 1862 to mother, says moved about ten days ago to nearer Warrenton;
countryside deserted; laments despondency of Southern people; says much of Lee's army is suffering from want of clothes and says commissary is fraudulently administered. October 31, 1862 Brandy Station, Culpeper,
to father, hears General Robert E. Lee arrived at Culpeper Court House the previous day; and Perry says he is encamped in a handsome brick house. November 10, 1862 (largely faded and illegible letter) apparently
describing more troop movements. November 23, 1862 to father two miles from Fredericksburg, Virginia, writes he left Culpeper three days previously and came to this location with General Lee and General
Longstreet's divisions; women and children have all left Fredericksburg, mostly walking; anticipates a battle soon. November 29, 1862 two miles from Fredericksburg, to father, Fredericksburg has a few citizens
returning; laments lack of shoes (and even socks); a Colonel in a Mississippi regiment reported two hundred men without shoes.
</p>
      <p>December 9, 1862 Fredericksburg area, to father, still quiet, doesn't think General Ambrose Everett Burnside will attack for at least a week; army is in "good fighting order." December 15, 1862 to father near
Fredericksburg, describes in exquisite detail the battle of Fredericksburg, particularly the artillery's part in it; lauds especially the heroics of Captain Braxton's battery. December 15, 1862 (partial letter)
claims prisoners taken say it was, "fighting Joe Hooker who was so badly whipped on our right," more details about positions. December 18, 1862 to a friend (presumably Perry's father) from Dr. G. Stiles of
Richmond informing him of the safety of his son and of the strong and valuable participation of the howitzers in the battle. December 25, 1862 to mother, has received orders to go into winter quarters fifteen
miles from Fredericksburg.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">January-June, 1863</title><lb/> January 5, 1863 to mother 2 1/2 miles from Chester Depot on Fredericksburg Railroad in Caroline County, thinks they are in present location to forage for [
], not to go into winter quarters; mentions he has vaccinated himself and one other with virus father sent him. January 23, 1863 to mother in camp six miles from Fredericksburg Road, moved to camp near [Luneas
Station] because of fear of attack. February 1, 1863 to mother from two miles from Fredericksburg at Hamilton's Crossing, describes log living quarters with chimney and its problems and attempted solutions,
different techniques of making firebacks, and other modes of living, including huts with dirt tops. February 8, 1863 camp near Fredericksburg, tells father of his use of vaccine for smallpox on himself and several
others; discusses activities in camp, including making pipes out of ivy root; discusses tastes in reading, opinions of Union leaders and shortage of rations. February 15, 1863 camp near Fredericksburg, describes
provisions (which are increasing) and tells how to make corn coffee. February 25, 1863 to father from camp near Fredericksburg, urges father to grow vegetables because of food shortage; thinks great impediments in
war effort come from dishonesty of quartermasters, commissaries and other sub officers; says he never thinks of battle of Fredericksburg without recalling Sir Walter Scott's description of the Slothful Knight in
"Ivanhoe." March 2, 1863 and continued March 3, 1863 to a friend from camp near Fredericksburg, discusses his decision not to think too much about the Confederacy and his part in the war because "not thinking
makes me a better soldier," talks of Confederates keeping up "constant intercourse with Yankees on the other side of the Potomac by going over in boats to trade for tobacco, papers and coffee; relates amusing
incident of boat propelled across the river by "works of a clock"; speaks of two divisions which have left the vicinity, one of which had twelve soldiers frozen to death and the other six. March 8, 1863 to father,
camp near Fredericksburg, talks of troop realignments and promotions in camp. March 15, 1863 to father, camp near Fredericksburg, gives specifics involved in soldiers drawing of clothing allotments; notes that
cavalry appears to draw three or four times as many furloughs as other branches.
</p>
      <p>April 2, 1863 to father, camp near Fredericksburg, reports health of the army seems best since war began. April [7], 1863 to father, camp near Fredericksburg, bad weather, several inches of snow, dull camp
routine. April 25, 1863 to mother, camp near Fredericksburg, reports Yankees crossed over about fifteen miles below his camp a few days previously. May 2, 1863 to father, 8 miles above Fredericksburg, details
enemy crossings of Potomac, skirmishing and artillery use, Jackson's flank movement and arrival of General James Longstreet. May 5, 1863 to father, camp near Fredericksburg, writes of the battle of
Chancellorsville describing the fighting and telling of running out of ammunition three times; two men in his company killed--one a Thom (sic) Barksdale, who he was busy interring until one a.m.; calls General
Joseph Hooker a "big fool" for dividing his armies. May 10, 1863 to father, from old camp near Fredericksburg, in a review of battle of Chancellorsville, gives a day-by-day account of action and the artillery's
part in it, including mention of the wounding of General A.P. Hill and General Stonewall Jackson. May 24, 1863 continued May 25, 1863 to mother, in camp 12 miles from Fredericksburg, artillery all organized into
battalions, each with four to six companies, with his company [First Regiment Virginia Artillery?] under the command of Colonel H.C. Cabell of Richmond. May 28, 1863 to father, Chambersburg, Pa., from the 23rd to
the 28th, starting at Ashby's Gap, Virginia, and proceeding through Millwood, Berryville, Summit Station, Martinsburg, West Virginia, crossing the Potomac at Williamsport, through Hagerstown, Md., and on to five
miles from Chambersburg, Pennsylvania; describes a "fine country with no signs of war."
</p>
      <p>June 14, 1863 to father, two miles from Culpeper Court House, gives the various positions of the Confederate army of which he is aware; thinks reputation of the cavalry has declined greatly since the battle of
Brandy Station and quotes taunting phrases infantry use in scorn when cavalry ride by. June 21, 1863 to father, Clarke County, Virginia, details travels to Clarke County from Culpeper Courthouse, passing the
cavalry in a disorganized state and thinks "they may have been whupped again."
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">July-December, 1863</title><lb/> July 5, 1863 in a brief note to father while retreating from battle of Gettysburg, says "results of the battles were rather unfavorable- - we had two killed
and ten wounded in our company." July 8, 1863 to father, camp one mile from Hagerstown, in a long letter details his involvement at Gettysburg; says lack of support from seasoned troops helped cause failure of
General George Pickett's charge; writes "one reason for falling back (during Pickett's charge) is said to be want of ammunition--our ammunitions for the artillery certainly are nearly gone." July 18, 1863 to
mother, camp near Bunker Hill twelve miles from Martinsburg, reports the entire Confederate army is in the vicinity but despite discussion, thinks another foray into Pennsylvania unlikely; thinks depletion of
forces not only due to killed wounded and those taken prisoner, but also perhaps by a good many "skulking in the rear." July 26-27, 1863 to father from hospital in Lynchburg, is suffering from diarrhea and was
sent to Lynchburg after marching with his company to Culpeper Court House.
</p>
      <p>August 11, 1863, this letter is to Perry in the hospital from a fellow soldier describing the company's current position in Orange County. August 16, 1863 to father, from camp in Orange County after his return
to the company from furlough in which he details location of various divisions. August 28, 1863 to mother from camp 23 miles from Northanna River and 13 miles from Frederick Hall, a station 65 miles from Richmond
on the Central Railroad, mentions his brigade of 800 has now increased to 1600 since the retreat from Gettysburg, though this does not appear to be the case with the army in general.
</p>
      <p>September 5, 1863 to father from howitzer camp, discusses the current location of Confederate Generals and predicts possible fall of Charleston, which he thinks would be great morale builder for Confederate
troops; thinks capital punishment the only way to prevent desertion among Confederates; lengthy comments on character of Jefferson Davis. September 9 continued to September 11, 1863 to father, reports he is in new
camp at Hanover Junction but is proceeding south-southwest to 1/2 miles from Taylorsville on the Fredericksburg Railroad. September 14, 1863 to mother, from howitzer camp near Taylorsville, thinks he may stay in
present location because of difficulty transporting artillery by train. September 22, 1863 to mother from howitzer camp three miles south of Gordonsville, has heard artillery firing all day on left from Madison
County where Confederate cavalry was driven out the previous day.
</p>
      <p>October 7, 1863 to mother, howitzer camp, notes that a large seminary for young women is nearby; address now is 1st Howitzer Company, Cabell's Battalion, Army of Northern Virginia October 17, 1863 to father,
howitzer camp, hears army has made an advance but knows nothing else; reports 600 to 800 prisoners have passed through; fears Confederates about to lose possession of valuable salt works. October 25, 1863 to
father, howitzer camp, want of shoes a big problem. November 2, 1863 to father, howitzer camp, discusses camp routine; quotes dialogue between A.P. Hill and General R. E. Lee after fall of Bristoe Station in which
Lee reportedly said to Hill--"Your line of battle was too short, sir, and too weak." November 11, 1863 to father, near Gordonsville, reports letter received from Major [ ] Hamilton, in command of his battalion, in
which a Captain Lamar, one of General Lafayette McLaws' aides, says Confederates must be prepared for gloomy news, that General Braxton Bragg is "most able" but ambition of his lieutenants creates difficulties.
November 21, 1863 to father, howitzer camp 2 1/2 miles east of Orange Court House, details current position of Confederate armies; mentions there are three stages in a soldier's life-enthusiasm, disgust and
indifference, and says he is descending into the latter; says camp life monotony is relieved by going hare hunting with sticks.
</p>
      <p>December 2, 1863 to mother, howitzer camp ten miles from Orange Court House, says line of battle is three miles away and intermediate firing is occurring. December 9, 1863 to father, camp near Orange Court
House, says anticipated battle did not materialize; thinks military blunders in the southwest cost dearly; discusses soldier substitutes, payment procedures and their worth. December 19, 1863 to father, Moreton's
Ford on the Rapid Ann, on picket duty, can hear enemy fire about a mile away; reports most of artillery has gone into winter camp near the Central railroad.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
