<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03980">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::03980::A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., 1853-1908)//EN" "viu03980.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853-1908</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">13407
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Ellen Welch, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6-9-06</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853-1908</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">13407
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853-1908
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">13407
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">This collection consists of ca. 154 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., Accession #13407, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>These letters were a gift from Mrs. Benjamin F. Harmon, 9300 University Blvd., Richmond, Va. on September 14, 2005.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Most of the collection consists of letters from three brothers who fought in the "Louisa Blues" 13th Regiment of Virginia in the Confederate Army (1861 to 1863) to their family in Louisa Court House, Virginia. The brothers were the Reverend John William Jones (1836-1909), Phillip Edloe Jones (n.y.-1863) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1840-1863).  They saw action in the Shenandoah Valley Campaign of Stonewall Jackson.  Phillip Edloe Jones was wounded in battle (shot in the lungs) and died at home in Louisa Courthouse in February of 1863. His mother, Ann Pendleton Ashby Jones, died on September 23,1862 while caring for her son, Edloe. Francis Pendleton Jones was wounded in the Battle of Gettysburg and died on September 2, 1863 in Winchester, Virginia. Their letters reveal their distinct personalities as well as details of the Civil War. Edloe loved soldier life and reveled in the comraderie, discipline and strenuous physical demands of camp.  Pendleton was a free spirit who became a first- rate cook, adapted well to camp life and enjoyed being a part of his regiment.  John (the Reverend John William Jones) graduated from the University of Virginia and as the oldest of the brothers gave them advice on their studies and career paths. During the war he took comfort in his religion and service to others. Edloe Jones was the leader among his brothers in soldier life. 
</p>
      <p>Prior to the war, two of the brothers, John William Jones (1855-1858) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1859-1860) attended the University of Virginia. The collection is particularly interesting because one of the brothers was the Reverend John William Jones (1836-1909) who became a chaplain during the war, befriended General Robert E. Lee after the war and later wrote a famous civil war book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Christ in the Camp</title>.  The brothers often wrote to their mother, Ann Pendleton Ashby Jones (?- 1862 ), father, Francis William Jones (1811-1889) who was a store owner, their sisters, Helen Jones Sumner (n.d.), Page Jones Tucker (Willie Page) (n.d.) and Lute Jones (n.d.) and younger siblings at home. There are also letters from Reverend John William Jones to his wife, Julia Page Helm. (n.d.).  The Jones family may be a relation of Brigadier General William Nelson Pendleton [1808-1883] and his son Colonel "Sandie" Pendleton. </p>
      <p>The Reverend John William Jones was born in Louisa Court House, Virginia in 1836.  He was ordained to the gospel ministry in 1860.  He enlisted as a private in the Confederate Army after Virginia seceded in 1861.  He was appointed regimental and then corps chaplain, earning the title of "The Fighting Parson".  Jones witnessed hundreds of men profess faith in Christ in camps and hospitals throughout the war.  After the war, while pastor of a church in Lexington, Virginia, he developed a close friendship with Robert E. Lee.  The Reverend Jones edited the Southern Historical Society Papers for fourteen years, wrote several books on General Lee, and published <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Christ in the Camp</title> in 1887.  His express purpose for the book was that it 'would be useful in leading men to Christ and strengthen the faith and brighten the hope of true children of God'. Four of his five sons followed their father into the ministry.  He died in 1909, greatly loved and respected as the 'most influential and well-known clergyman'... of the Lost Cause.  </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 154 letters of the Jones family from 1853-1908 in which 50 are original Civil War letters written by three brothers, John William Jones (1836-1909), Philip Edloe Jones (n.y.-1863) and Francis Pendleton Jones (1840 -1863) to their friends and family in Louisa Court House, Virginia. There are also ca.104 letters written before and after the war.  One of the brothers is the famous Reverend John William Jones, author of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Christ in the Camp</title>. He corresponded with his family, his wife (Julia Page Helm) and other close friends (including Thomas Hume, Jr. and theologian scholar, Crawford Howell Toy).  
</p>
      <p>From April to May of 1861, there are fourteen Civil War letters from Edloe Jones to his family where he described the details of camp life and his "perfect reconciliation" with it. He wrote that even though there is poor fare, little sleep and miles of marching he believes he could become really fond of this sort of life. </p>
      <p>From June to July of 1861, there are eighteen Civil War letters from the Jones brothers to their family showing the closeness of the brothers as well as some friendly competition between them.  There are also descriptions of fighting in Romney, and Martinsburg, Virginia with Stonewall Jackson.  There is a letter from the Reverend John William Jones to his wife Julia Page Helm offering encouragement to be strong in bearing their separation.  Another letter from Pendleton Jones to his sister, Lute, reveals some of the rumors going around camp suggesting a defeat of General Winfield Scott which he strongly believed to be untrue.</p>
      <p>From August through December of 1861, there are fifteen Civil War letters from the Jones brothers that describe Civil War Generals, details of skirmishes, and glimpses of their harsh living conditions including a letter about a skirmish after the Battle of 1st Manassas and before Munson Hill.</p>
      <p>In 1862, there are six Civil War letters from the brothers that convey a change in attitude toward the war. The brothers seem weary and disheartened at the prospects of anything good coming out of it. Edloe Jones is seriously injured and sent home where he dies after several months. </p>
      <p>There are four Civil War letters from the Jones brothers in 1863, including a letter from the Reverend John William Jones to his wife about religion and the war.  It reveals his strong will to minister to officers and soldiers so that their souls will be saved.    There are also letters from Pendleton Jones that discuss politics in the campaign of the Governor of Virginia specifically regarding candidate William (Extra-Billy) Smith. The letters also contain a discussion of politics within the camp.  The 13th regiment was re-organized and there were elections for captaincy and lieutenant and other positions.  Pendleton wrote that he would probably be named Orderly Sargearnt</p>
      <p>There are many officers generally mentioned throughout these letters including generals: Pierre Gustave Toutant Beauregard, Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall) Jackson, Robert E. Lee, Braxton Bragg , James Ewell Brown, (J.E.B.) Stuart, Joseph E. Johnston , James A. ['Old Pete'] Longstreet, Ambrose Powell (A.P.) Hill, James Alexander Walker, James Lawson Kemper, Richard Stoddert Ewell, Jubal Anderson Early, Nathaniel G. (Shanks) Evans, Robert Patterson, George Edward Pickett, Winfield Scott, Arnold Elzy (Jones), Earl Van Dorn, William (Extra Billy) Smith, George B. McLellan, Nathaniel Prentiss Banks, and John Charles "Pathfinder" Fremont. Other officers include Major James B. Terrill, Colonel Edward "Allegheny" Johnson, Captain H. W. Murray, Captain R. H. Anderson, Capt. Courtney, Colonel Gathes, Lieutenant Bird, Lieutenant Winston, and Seargeant John Hibbs.  </p>
      <p>The brothers fought and set up camp in some of the following places in Virginia: Harper's Ferry, Bolivar, Romney, Hanging Rock, Winchester, Martinsburg, Danville, Strasburg, Centreville, Rappahanock, Munson Hill, and Bull Run.</p>
      <p>In Series II Other Jones family papers, there are 104 letters of the Jones family that were written before and after the war. </p>
      <p>There are twenty-one letters from Francis William Jones to his son the Reverend John William Jones (1855-1859) while he was studying theology at the University of Virginia. Included is a letter that expresses his support for his son's chosen career.</p>
      <p>There are also twenty-seven letters from Ann Pendleton Jones to her son, the Reverend John William Jones (1856-1859).  She mostly wrote to him about local news regarding family and neighbors. </p>
      <p>There are eighteen letters from Helen Jones to her brother the Reverend John William Jones (1853-1860).  Among these is a letter from 1856 revealing that there were thirty cases of small pox in Charlottesville. Helen also wrote about students [drinking] making a fuss in town and being afraid of them.  According to a letter titled Social Hall Monday morning she wrote, "There is to be a Temperance meeting in the hall tonight.  I believe we are going but I am almost afraid to go there anymore.  Dr. Broadus and Dr. McGuffey &amp; several others are to speak this evening."   </p>
      <p>There is also correspondence between the brothers while they are at home and the Reverend John William Jones is at the University of Virginia and while he is visiting Greenville, South Carolina. Edloe Jones wrote to John on January 14,1860 about his studies. Pendleton Jones wrote three letters to John in 1859-1860. </p>
      <p>There are two letters showing that Pendleton Jones was [temporarily] expelled from school before going to the University of Virginia. </p>
      <p>Miscellaneous items include a photograph of Lieutenant Joe Berret- former Mayor of Washington and an original shoe shine cloth.  There is also a clipping from the newspaper Atlanta Journal and The Atlanta Constitution on the former Washington Mayor and his appraisement and payment regarding emancipated slaves (Oversize folder).</p>
      <p>There are also three letters from C. H. Toy (Crawford Howell Toy, 1836-1919) to the Reverend John William Jones.  Toy was a close friend of John William Jones and was the famous Reverend and biblical scholar, who attended the University of Virginia with John. He spent time in Charlottesville teaching at the Albemarle Female Institute. He wrote to John in 1860 offering advice on difficulties with a certain deacon and how to direct his career.  There are also six letters from another friend in theologian studies, Thomas Hume, Jr.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in two series: Series I.: Civil War letters from the Jones brothers; and, Series II.: Other Jones family papers. Series I is arranged chronologically and Series II is arranged by the last name of the sender and chronologically within each folder.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e178">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Civil War letters from the Jones brothers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1863
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e185">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 April 5-May 31
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
	</container>
            <physdesc>14 items.
	</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Edloe Jones wrote letters to his mother, father, sisters Helen and Lute, including a letter dated June 6, 1861 where he wrote to his father after he first arrived in camp at Harper's Ferry, "There was a great rejoicing here tonight amongst the soldiers, at the success of the Baltimoreans over the Lincolnists... We have between 1,500 and 2,000 soldiers here and a good many more expected. It really looks like war about here now. Soldiers marching every which way, a cannon planted on the top of every neigboring hill."
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e199">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 June 5-July 30
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
	</container>
            <physdesc>18 items.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Letters from the three brothers to their family including a letter dated June 6, 1861 where Edloe wrote to his sister about his brother, Pendleton, "Pen could bare more at camp than at University." (Harper's Ferry) In the same letter he also wrote "I saw an account of the fight at Fairfax C.H. in a dispatch sent to Billy Con. They speak of sending the Eastern Companies to Culpepper C.H. under Gen.(James Lawson) Kemper's command, but we are all violently opposed to it &amp; do not think we will go..." </p>
            <p>On June 9, 1861 in another letter, Edloe wrote to his mother that the Captain is trying to get John the position of Chaplain. Sometimes his characterizations of camp life were humorous such as when he wrote about his brother's marching skills: "I pity the man's heels behind John".  He also wrote about the Yankees, "If we do [fight] I will try to do my duty to kill one of the rascals at least if no more." </p>
            <p>On June 17, 1861 Edloe wrote a letter from Romney, Virginia showing that the brothers were very close and there was friendly competition between them.  He wrote,"I was right amused at Pen, he disliked so much to give up before me, he was walking right by me, and he would ask me if I was not most broke down. I wd tell him not to wait for me, for I had no idea of giving up (and ride in the wagon)". </p>
            <p>On June 19, 1861 Pendleton wrote home to his father about fighting in Romney, Virginia, "There was a skirmish last night between our forces sent out on guard and some 150 federal troops. We took 2 pieces of cannon from them... Killed two of their men and took possession of and burnt the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Bridge at New Creek."  He also wrote about his brother, "Ed is really in fare health and spirits.  His merry peals of laughter daily echo throughout the campground.  All our regiment is eager for an open fight with the enemy and sanguine that we can whip twice our number."  John added a note at the bottom of the letter, "The Yankees ran like troopers and our men had to shoot them running."</p>
            <p>On June 27, 1861 John William Jones wrote to his wife Page (Julia Page Helm) from Camp Gibbons-near Winchester, with encouragement to be strong.  He wrote, "Now, please, Dearest, for my sake as well as your own try and bear the separation better. It is indeed a sore trial for us thus to be separated from each other, and especially as our letters go so irregularly, but is our duty and you know that when we resolved to go 'far hence to the heathren' we made up our minds not to count trials when they beset the path of duty." </p>
            <p>On July 5, 1861 John also revealed in a letter to his sister that they were fighting with Colonel [Stonewall] Jackson near Martinsburg, "We soon hear tht Col. Jackson was engaging the enemy near Martinsburg and that we were wanted to support him.  We expected to have made a forced march to Martinsburg that night but were marched into a field some six miles from Winchester where we camped for the night and made a leisurely march of ten miles to this place on the next day where we found Col. Jackson's command quietly awaiting us.  On Monday we had a pretty smart skirmish with the enemy in wh, with greatly inferior forces, he repulsed them three times, took about 80 prisoners, killed upwards of a hundred, and then fell back to this place in good order, losing only one man killed, one missing, and five wounded.  We (I mean the forces brought from Winchester 10,000 strong) immediately joined Jackson and our whole army was drawn up in line of battle expecting every hour an attack from the Yankees who were at Martinsburg in strong force. And thus we have been ever since- our men are not allowed to go far from their guns, we are ready and anxious for them to come, we have a very strong position-our artillery sweeps the approaches for two miles and if the Yankees wd only come we wd give them a threshing to which the fight at Bethel was mere child's play. But I don't believe the cowardly thieves are coming.  They will content themselves with fortifying Martinsburg. We will have today a reinforcement of 3,000 or more (among them the N.O. artillery) and then we will be fully able to cope with them either here or at Martinsburg. But I doubt exceedingly whether we will have a fight- as soon as we move towards them I believe they will take their heels and recross the Potomac.  Don't be uneasy about us.  We are in the hands of a kind heavenly father who can preserve us..." </p>
            <p>On July 11, 1861, (Martinsburg) Edloe wrote a teasing remark about his brother Pendleton to his father, "I never saw a fellow eat as Pen does in my life.  I can't begin to keep up to him."</p>
            <p>On July 26, 1861  Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute from Winchester about rumors circulating around camp.  One rumor was that "Old fuss &amp; feathers [General Winfield Scott] has been decapitated. How glad I'd be if now... having lost his first (only) grand battle he wd be dishonored by the federalists. Alexandria has been evacuated; that great consternation was caused in the Federal Capital by the defeat of Manassas;  that old Abe has resigned, and that there is a general fight going on in the Metropolis.  But these are mere fictions I imagine and resistance will be offered our invincible soldiers." </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e227">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 August 9-November 29
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
	</container>
            <physdesc>15 items.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>On August 31, 1861 Edloe wrote to his father from Camp Fairfax: (Skirmish after the Battle of 1st Manassas and before Munson Hill) 
"My dear Pa,I do not reckon Pen left me anything at all to tell about our march &amp; fight the other day but I will write something about it even if I have to repeat what he has written... Well, about an hour before day on Sunday orders were given for one day's rations to be drawn, cooked &amp; put in haversacks &amp; to be ready to march with our blankets all day. Our Co. with the Montpelier Guard, The Baltimore Co. the Culpepper Minute Men &amp; two pieces of the Newtown artillery under command of Major Terrel [James Barbour Terrill), commenced marching about half after six, we didn't know where we were going; after a march of nine or ten miles we came to Anondale, a little village, where we rested several hours. We started again at one, went two miles farther when we came to Chessnut [Chestnut] hill on Cap. Mason's farm, where we halted. We could see Washington &amp; the Yankee pickets very distinctly. Col. [James Ewell Brown] Stuart with a part of his cavalry came to Chessnut hill soon after we arrived. Col Stuart took command of everything. Breastworks were laid off by Adjutant Blackford of Stewarts' [Stuarts'] cavalry, in front of Mason's house, &amp; we commenced work about four oclock. I worked harder on that hill than I ever done in my life."</p>
            <p>"The Baltimore Co. were sent out to scout &amp; they were fired upon by some of the Yankees in half a mile of us, they returned the fire &amp; soon drove them off, took one prisoner up a tree.  We stoped work abut eight oclock &amp; went to sleep on the ground, but were aroused several times during the night by the firing of the pickets, their balls come very near us once &amp; we all laid down on the ground to avoid them. We were at work again early the next day. We cd still see the yankee pickets on Munson's Hill &amp; their scouting parties, some of which ventured very near to us, but a few shots at them from our men wd soon send them off in double quick time." </p>
            <p>"There was a school house, not over five hundred yards from Chessnut Hill, in the woods, wh the Yankees wd get behind &amp; fire at our men, that house was burnt by our men. Not [a] single one of our men were hurt near Mason's hill, a horse belonging to one of the cavalrymen was shot through the leg; the loss of the enemy is unknown, but it is certain some were wounded if not killed."</p>
            <p>"We finished the fortifications late Monday evening.  We were reinforced Monday night by a part of the Mayeland [Maryland] line &amp; a part of a Georgia Regiment. Our blankets, overcoats &amp; _____ were not back here Tuesday morning &amp; our Co with the other three companies of the 13th, two pieces of artillery &amp; two Mayaland Companies started for Munson's hill about eight oclock, we marched cautiously through the woods &amp; got there in about an hour &amp; a half, just before we got there we saw a yankee riding as hard as he cd down the road &amp; we were ordered to shoot him; I didn't get a shot at him myself but some of our Co. did, his horse was shot &amp; I think he was wounded.  When we got on top of the hill we saw a body of Yankees drawn up at Bailey's Xroad, a mile off, we expected an attack.  Four prisoners were taken in a peach orchard at the bottom of the hill. Our Co. with the Montpelier Guard commanded by Major Terrel went to Upton's house to search it, we found no Yankees but they had just left, they had not finished their breakfast, they left a bowl of soup &amp; hot corn on the table.  C.H. Upton is the rascal who pretends to represent Virginia in the Federal Congress &amp; he is now in Washington."</p>
            <p>"Reinforcements arrived soon after the hill was taken.  Our Co. was stationed at Upton's, a Baltimore Co. was sent up the road toward Loudon &amp; Hampshire R.R., but were soon driven back, tow being wounded, they said the enemy were advancing upon us very rapidly. Major Terrel then ordered all of us to retreat to Munson's hill, we had not gone over a hundred yards before we met Col. Stuart who turned us back he said it wd never do for us to run.  Our detachment (excepting the Culpepper M. M.) with two Mayaland Companies, making five Cos. in all, were led on, right after the Yankees, by Col. Stuart. We soon got in the woods &amp; very near to the enemy, the skirmishes were put out to bring the battle on, the firing soon commenced, but it was some time before anyone but the skirmishes cd see a single yankee, not until we got to the Loudon &amp; Hampshire RR., Then all of us commenced shouting, &amp; the Yankees too sent up a shout, but their shouts didn't last long, for we charged across the R.R. upon them &amp; you never saw such scampering in yr life, but they rallied again &amp; for a few minutes their calls fell thick &amp;  heavy, They ran again across an open field &amp; it was there that I got two fair shots at the rascals.  We did not follow them anymore, but returned.  I got three shots, don't know that I did them a great deal of harm, but think I struck one, for I had rest on the fence at him."</p>
            <p>"I was right near poor Robinson when he fell mortally wounded. The loss of the enemy is unknown, three were seen dead, I saw one fall; our loss in all the skirmishes were five wounded &amp; one killed, we were certainly very fortunate. We were within two miles &amp; a half of the chainbridge. When we got back to Munson's hill I was very much exhausted. I was not as much excited as I expected I wd be in my first fight, though I was right much excited until after the first fire. Col. Stuart as well as the men behaved very bravely, Col. S is as brave as he can be &amp; is a splendid officer. Lieutenant Winston also conducted himself first rate, he kept as cool as a cucumber the whole time &amp;  gave his commands in a clear &amp; distinct tone as if he was on the parade ground. Our Major showed a great deal of bravery &amp; he raised himself in our estimation very much. I think he is most too rash." </p>
            <p>"We had the reinforcements Tuesday night &amp; Wednesday morning, part of the Washington artillery was there. There was right much of a skirmish Wednes [Wednesday] morning between Munsons Hill &amp; Bailey's Xroads, a rifled cannon was fired at them at the xroads several times, we cd see them running in every direction when the ball struck.  Our Co. was on picket Wednes night, we had a very hard time of it, it rained nearly the all time, we were very near the Federal pickets, cd hear them coughing on their post. We started back here Thursday morning &amp; had a very hard time in the rain. Bro. Jno was a little complaining &amp; Pen &amp; I staid behind with him, we walked on slowly &amp; didn't get to camp until late in the evening- all of us were the mudiest looking fellows you ever saw when we got in camp- Harry had us a nice supper ready when we arrived &amp; you may depend upon it that all hands done ample justice to it. After Sunday we had nothing to eat but peaches &amp; corn. I used to eat as many as seven ears of corn for a meal &amp; peaches in ______, I wd not like to say how many Pen [had]. We had a terrible time after our blankets were sent back, we slept like hogs, piled up together on the ground about four deep. It is the greatest wonder in the world that some of us were not made sick, I don't believe a single one even took cold, &amp; all of us are ready for another bush fight, though we wd prefer to have it in open field. My sheet is filled so I must quit. My best love to all of the dear ones at home, Aunt Cynthia's &amp; all of my friends &amp; accept a large share for yrself. We will write again soon. Yr devoted &amp; most aff son P.E. Jones"</p>
            <p>Edloe also wrote to his mother about the fight, "My dear Ma, As I c'd not get my letter off yesterday I will write a little more to you this morning just to let you know what I've been doing since my return to camp. We were excused from all drills Friday as we were so much fatigued. We were reviewed Friday evening by Gen. [James A.] Longstreet &amp; staff &amp; Gen Elzy [Arnold Elzy Jones]."</p>
            <p>"Perhaps I ought not to tell tales out of school, but can hardly help speaking of old Elzy, he was so drunk on review that he c'd hardly sit on his horse &amp; just before he got to the ground I saw him have a tremendous fall from his horse; he gets drunk nearly every day now, I wish we c'd get rid of him. We had inspection yesterday &amp; Battalion drill &amp; dress parade in the evening; a letter to Col. Hill, was read on dress parade from Col. Stuart complimenting us very much for our conduct at Munson''s Hill. We heard yesterday that they had been skirmishing near Munson's ever since we left. There seems to be a general movement with the troops now, they've moved up higher from about Centreville, Fairfax CH &amp; all around here. I wdn't be surprised at our moving at any time, but we w'd not move very far I know..." </p>
            <p>Edloe wrote again to his mother "My dear Ma, I don't feel very much like writing this evening but will try to write a short letter at least. Pen gave all of you a full account of our last trip to Munson's Hill in his letter to Lute, so I will not have much news to give. We had a right rough time of it the first few days &amp; night, but had a pleasant time the balance of the week. We had to whip the yankees out of Sewensville the first day &amp; then go right on picket that night in the rain; you never saw such a mad set of fellows in your life as we were the night we went on picket in the rain; we could have almost skined old Major. He certainly treated us very badly &amp; I hope we may never go under his command again. We were all delighted when Col. [James] Walker took charge of us. He has gotten well though looks right badly yet." </p>
            <p>"It is really amusing to hear our pickets talking with the yankee pickets. Our nearest pickets would say Bull Run to the Yankees, which made them very mad &amp; they would always shoot at our boys whenever they would say Bull Run or cheer for Davis. The yankee pickets are in sight of our line, but not near enough to be damaged much by our balls, &amp; they have breastworks at every post &amp; don't show themselves much. The evening we left, David Magruder was badly wounded; he with some others were trying to creep upon some Yankees who were on post when he was shot; it was a very foolish &amp; dangerous thing &amp; it is a wonder, more of them were not shot. I am afraid Davy's wound will prove fatal. His father came here last night. He went to Falls Church this morning to see him. I never intend to creep upon a yankee on his post, (unless I am ordered) because nothing can be gained by it &amp; it is very dangerous &amp; then I don't think it is exactly right..." </p>
            <p>"I don't think we will have to go to Munson's anymore directly, for Uncle Phil Ashby told me that his (Longstreet's) Brigade w'd move near Munson's to remain permanently. Gen.[Joseph] Johnston has his headquarters right near us, he is only a mile on the road to Fairfax CH. Two or three regts. have moved near us in the last week. Fairfax Station has become a very busy place, another depot &amp; two bakeries have been put recently.  I don't think they have commenced using the latter yet... We expect to be reviewed this evening, if the weather don't prevent by Gen. Johnston. Generals J. Johnston &amp; Longstreet have both complimented our Regiment very highly for the service rendered at Sewinsville, Their compliments to us will be published &amp; I reckon Bro. John has written a piece for the Dispatch, giving an account of our trip, it will be out in a few days. I suppose you have seen the Federal account of the fight. We've heard something about a fight between Floyd &amp; Rosencrantz, but do not know whether it is true or not...Our compliments were read out yesterday on dress parade, we are all getting proud of our Regt., call it the 'Bloody 13th'..." (Camp Blair) </p>
            <p>John also wrote to his mother on Sept. 20, 1861 about the fight, "As Pen and Ed have both written long accounts of our last trip down there (Munson Hill) I will refer you to yesterday's Dispatch to what 'Justice' has to say.  Our Regt. was certainly most providentially preserved in the face of a greatly superior force of the enemy and having heavy skirmishes nearly all of the time we had not a man touched until just before we left when David Magruder was wounded by a very rash attempt to cut off some of the yankee picquets."  He also mentioned that he is used to discomforts and advised her to not worry.  He wrote that he has been hoping to receive his commission as Chaplain of the Regt. "I have been expecting every mail to bring me my commission as chaplain of the Regt. but have thus far been disappointed.  I suppose that the Sec. of War has been very much pressed for time but [I] have no doubt of eventually getting the place." (Fairfax Station)</p>
            <p>On September 29, 1861, from Camp Blair, Edloe wrote to his father that Colonel Stuart has been made Brigadier General.  He added, "I think he ought to thank the 13th for his promotion."</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e268">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 Mar.16-October 23
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Letters include a letter from Pendleton to his mother on June 12, 1862. 
He wrote in detail about the war, "Jackson is the greatest General of the Age &amp; his brilliant achievements with a hand full of men badly equipped and poorly fed and clothed carry us back to the chivalric days of yore when men fought for Liberty and Home and remind us forcibly of the warrior Napoleon. But I must resume my sketch of our maneuvers &amp; transactions which must be meager &amp; imperfect.  On Monday the 26th, [May 1862] we followed up the enemy hotly &amp; our cavalry chased them from Martinsburg. This was their General Receiving Depot for this Dept. of their Army and the stores captured were of innumerable variety and of exceeding great value to the needy Rebels- such as salt, leather, coffee, [ordinance], clothing &amp; _____."</p>
            <p>"Next day our Brigade moved to this side of Winchester and the weary worn soldiers congratulated themselves upon the apparent prospects of rest and quiet; we remained here however only one night and next evening we were pitching tents while the rain pound down as marching orders were received. 'Twas with no reluctance, however, that the men prepared to follow the gallant 'Stonewall' and marched through the hardest rain &amp; deep mud fifteen miles after dark in the direction of Charlestown."</p>
            <p>"Wednesday the 28th [May 1862] we reached Charlestown early in the day and met with unbounded &amp; enthusiastic welcome from the citizens. The Federals fled before us and stores fell into our hands and many prisoners.  We had camped in a lovely spot and somewhat rested when there was an alarm and our regiment went off at 'doublequick' in direction of Harper's Ferry, eight miles distant.  Our regiment was delighted at the idea of once more visiting the spot where they spent their military childhood; we got in sight of the surrounding hills, and a few cannon shots were exchanged between the belligerents and nothing more; no damage to either party, I suppose.  We occupied our same encampment and early next morning were again called out &amp; our cavalry pursued the enemy into poor [Maryland].  But all at once orders were received to march back; the rain poured down in timult. The roads were already heavy with mud, our Brigade marched twenty six miles through all this &amp; camped near Winchester- it rained hard all night long and the men were poorly fed if indeed they had anything that night."</p>
            <p>"I can remember nothing of special interest to you from that day until Sunday (1st June), [1862 Battle of Seven Pines] the great battle day of ancient &amp; modern days; yet the hardships, heavy rains and fast days made a lasting impression upon me and if we mounted individuals suffered you can imagine how men on foot fared. The cause of the retreat as you are doubtless aware was the design of the Federals to entrap and overwhelm Jackson with numbers; [General James] Shields with a large column advanced towards Swift Run Gap from Manassas and [General John Charles "Pathfinder"] Freemont came down on the left from Romney while [General Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks reinforcements were to meet him in front. But Jackson can never be caught &amp; with his usual skill he has extricated himself from this trap while the enemy has been completely baffled. Sunday 1st inst.[June 1862] he engaged Fremont near Strasburg routed him with a small force; he continued his retreat while the men were worn out completely &amp; his army showed great signs of demoralization."</p>
            <p>"For one week more, we moved back slowly while the cavalry kept up daily engagements with the cautiously pursuing enemy.  Saturday 7th inst. [June 1862] in the afternoon we had a considerable cavalry engagement near Harrisonburg killing and capturing  many of the enemy &amp; putting them to flights; yet in this victory when he was about to commence a carier of fame unequalled by anything heretofore recorded on [historic page fill the brave chivalric], daring, generous Ashby [Turner Ashby]- a man who has beside all others been able to [inlain] most confidence in his own troops &amp; greatest [tremor] among the enemy he so much hated; his splendid horse had just been shot from under him &amp; he was gallantly leading on foot a brave band of infantry where a bullet pierced his heart and horse and rider lay breathless upon the same bloody battle fields." </p>
            <p>" Sunday (8th) [June 1862] early Jackson engaged Shields who had possession of Port Republic &amp; the bridge and dislodged him and about midday (General Richard Stoddert) Ewell's Divisions met and successfully routed Fremont's column; this was across the river from Port Republic which you see would make Shields in Ewell's rear while Jackson was upon road D of my rough map. The thirteenth was in the [thickest] of the fight and suffered some; it behaved most gallantly- the Blues were not with the regiment but detailed to support Capt. Courtney's Battery which guarded another position of the field and was not in action.  On Monday next day (9th) [June 1862 Battle of Port Republic] we crossed the river early and burnt the bridge (F) then attacked Shields on road E and routed him; captured many prisoners; killed many and took a battery; the casualties on our side were heavy but I do not know to which extent.  In the evening as we pursued Shields on E toward Gap A and were capturing many prisoners, Fremont leaving again [rallied approached] from Harrisonburg &amp; appeared with large forces in front of Port Republic; he could not cross and busied himself with shilling our Hospitals &amp; Ambulance train of which I was an eyewitness. We retreat[ed] to the mountain hollow by road G and remained there from Monday night until Wednesday when we started back by road H. </p>
            <p>On September 23, 1862 Edloe wrote a letter from Winchester about his mother's death. She had been caring for Edloe who was seriously injured in battle [shot in the lungs] and bedridden at home in Louisa. He does not recover from this wound and dies in February 1863. His mother passed away while caring for him. He wrote, "And our dear mother is no more! Absent from the loved scenes of home and mingling constantly with the rough society and wicked association of the camp I could scarcely realize the sad and mournful occurrence [that] my mother, she who had raised me, and protected &amp; defended me through life's most trying and dangerous hours, had been taken away from us! I can only realize now how fortunate I have been through life in having such a tender adviser &amp; counselor, one contains such characteristics as we can only express in  three words- a tender, virtuous, Christian mother!..."
</p>
            <p>On September 29, 1862 Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute, "Our division is encamped near Bunker's Hill fourteen miles from Winchester and everything seems to indicate quiet and rest after the stormy scenes through which we have passed since we left the Rapid Ann. [Rapidan River] The army is completely demoralized and worn out...  Uncle John [William Jones] is with Early [General Jubal Anderson Early] now who commands our division and I see him quite frequently- he looks well but is tired of this duty &amp; told me he was going to apply to General [Robert E.] Lee for some other duty.  It is reported by rumors that General (George ) Pickett is to be assigned to the command of Ewell's Division.  There has been great talk this week of peace and many firmly believed that ninety day armistice was about to be again between the National authorities.  All hands are getting sick and tired of this wicked and unhallowed war.  The Yankees themselves not withstanding their boasted preparations and abilities to conquer us speedily are also wearied with war and if we could only carry the war into their own territory they would soon be in favor of amicable adjustments." (Folder 4, Sept. 29, 1862 Pendleton to his sister, Lute. (Near Bunker's Hill) </p>
            <p>On October 23, 1862 Pendleton wrote to his sister Helen from Bunker's Hill near Martinsburg that "Jackson's corps has since been engaged in destroying the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in this vicinity; today they are at work between Martinsburg and Harper's Ferry and there are some prospects of a fight with the enemy as we draw nearer Harper's Ferry; but most of [General George B.] McClellan's Army seems to have disappeared since the news from Kentucky save some forces at the Ferry to marauding parties of cavalry here &amp; there. The news from [General Braxton] Bragg's army is encouraging if true and the fact of a brilliant success seems well established &amp; credible although we have exaggerated details.  Stuart's raid into Pennsylvania has eclipsed any dash or daring since the war begun; he brought away valuable property but the destruction of so many arms &amp; so much ordnance &amp; the moral effect are the greatest objects gained. Every one thought it a precursor of some grand move of the whole army but I believe that opinion has exploded and all believe that the army will fall back [soon dishonor] in a few days; in fact Longstreet corps has already moved &amp; encamped near Winchester.  Soldiers all wish the war to close &amp; of consequence there are thousands of rumors afloat about peace. But I see no signs of peace while both parties are endeavoring to put forth all their strength &amp; are making renewed effort to annihilate each other.   If whipped the North is no longer the nation it once was- poverty will reign where wealth was universal; if subjugated, the prosperity, happiness and being of the South forever perish, so that it is a question of life or death with both parties; of course there we must expect a protracted struggle when such momentous consequences are involved in the issue, when the resources of each party are so great, to when the combatants are stubborn Americans! Something may end the war sooner than I expect but I see no sign of speedy termination now."</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e298">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863 January 2-April 5
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
	</container>
            <physdesc>4 items.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>On January 2, 1863 the Reverend John William Jones (from camp near Fort Royal) wrote to his wife on  about religion and the war, "Just returned from preaching for my namesake [Uncle John William Jones] at 25th Virginia.  I tried to make ___ practical talk on the blessing wh. the Lord has given us during the past year as a Nation, a brigade, and as individuals and to draw thence lessons of thankfulness for the past and trustfulness and obedience for the future.  I tried to preach to myself as well as to others for truly the Lord has been good to me during the past years- far more than I have in any way deserved.  I enter the New Year with deep humiliation in view of my shortcomings in the past (both in what I have done and what I have failed to do) and with many resolves for the future- God help me to keep them.  Let us begin the New Year with determination to help each other make progress in personal holiness and labor together for the good of others.  If our hearts are only kept right it is always easy and pleasant to do good e.g. I have generally found it very hard to talk with officers (especially complete strangers) on the subject of religion and yet when an occasion offered this evening I found it easy and very pleasant to talk to Col. Higinbottom (of the 25th) about his soul, and urge him to seek after a personal interest in the savior's blood." John also mentioned that he is glad to hear that General Lee has somewhat relaxed the rigor of his orders about furloughs. </p>
            <p>On January 4, 1863 (Early's Brigade) Pendleton wrote to his sister Lute, "Politics visit the haunts of the camp and field and now there are lively discussions as to who will be the nest Governor [of Virginia] and who is to succeed the lamented Preston? in Congress.  William (Extra-Billy) Smith who is Colonel of the 49th Va. (in our Brigade) is highly commended for the Post of Governor and could our boys decide the elections his chances would be favorable." </p>
            <p>On February 26, 1863 (near Fredericksburg) Pendleton wrote to his father about the death of his brother Edloe and elaborates about his great character and how sadly he will be missed. </p>
            <p>On April 5, 1863 (near Rappahanock) Pendleton wrote to his father about his strong feelings toward General [Extra Billy William] Smith and Colonel [James] Walker. "General Early announced his permanent staff to the Division yesterday...We expect General Smith to assume command of the Brigade one day this week and the entire command are regretting deeply that the Services of Col. Walker will be lost.  That veteran soldier and gallant officer is now absent on three weeks leave of absence and in the meanwhile speaks confidently of resigning his commission; he bade us all farewell and said he did not expect to return again. This appointment of Gen. Smith is the most outrageous political trick that any times ever afforded. Col. Walker has the highest recommendation for promotion ever given by Ewell, Jackson and Lee, and every officer- save two or three Smith's in Col. Smith's old regiment- 49th Va.- petitioned for Col. W. to be assigned to this Brigade which he has commanded for seven months.  I hope old Bill will be defeated for Governor."</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e318">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
	</container>
            <physdesc>6 items.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included with several undated letters is one that Edloe wrote to his mother, "... I like this place first rate, would not care how long we would remain here. I had become right much attached to Harper's Ferry and hated to leave right bad.  I reckon Pen wrote the particulars about the fight, so I won't say anything about it. I am afraid we won't get in shooting distance of the Yankees at all. They are such cowards. You must excuse this short note. Don't be uneasy about us, we are very well &amp; ready to take another march if necessary. My best love to all. yr devoted &amp; most aff son." This letter was probably written in 1861 and showed that Edloe loved soldier life and reveled in the comraderie, discipline and strenuous physical demands of camp. </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e332">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Other Jones family papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853-1860; 1865-1907
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e339">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogy
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Letter and notes describing the Jones family genealogy
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e351">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. T. Hanks to sister Page Tucker
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Jones relatives (descendants)
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e363">
          <did>
            <unittitle>E.M. Harris to the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Mother of a soldier wrote to the Reverend John William Jones asking him if he knew anything about her son's dying moments
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e375">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Hume, Jr. to the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.; 1859-1860
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes six letters about his church related activities; invitations to visit each other; status of his health; and words of friendship.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>One of the letters from Thomas Hume, Jr. to the Reverend John William Jones was written August 2, 1860 and described an outing with some of his lady friends.  He was taken with one of the ladies and wrote about her and the art of flirtation that she exhibited.	</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e390">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ann Pendleton Jones to her son the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856-1859
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes twenty-seven letters about family and neighborhood news.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e402">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edloe Jones to his brother the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>On January 14, 1860 Edloe wrote to his brother John about his studies. He wrote that Latin doesn't agree with him, and he described an adventure catching an opossum that was a good size to eat.  He also inquired about John's love life. He wrote, "Do you intend on getting a wife out there?"... "I think Miss. Daisy would suit you very well, don't know whether you could get her or not."  He also wrote, "Pa got a letter from Pen a few days before he went to University, whenever he wants a little money he writes Pa a nice letter."
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e414">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Francis William Jones to his son the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Oct. 16-Sept.10; 1859; 1865 Nov.1-13
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Twenty one letters including one dated June 3,1859 when his father,Francis William Jones wrote to his son John about a position being offered by Dr. McGuffey. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>Another letter from his father was written on October 16, 1855 where he wrote to John expressing his support of his chosen career in theology: "I have no objection to the place you have marked out for yourself. I need not assure you that I have given the subject my most prayerful consideration &amp; I do not know what better you can do.  You can fully appreciate the feelings I have when I think of the many loved ones I have to provide for with no means to do so as I desire but is all right.  God will take care of those who trust in him as they ought to." </p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e429">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Helen Jones Sumner to her brother the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854-1856; n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Eighteen letters describing her activities and events in Louisa Court House as well as events in Charlottesville such as small pox and a temperance meeting with Dr. Broaddus and Dr. McGuffey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e441">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Helen Jones Sumner to her mother Ann Pendleton Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Three letters describing her visits with friends.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e453">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John R. Jones to Gilley Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e463">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Reverend John William Jones to his sister Page (Willie Page Tucker)
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883-1907
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e472">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John William Jones (Uncle) to his niece Mary Helen Jones Sumner
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858 May 11
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e481">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lute Jones to her borther the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858 October 6
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e490">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. Meade Jones to his brother
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:20
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e499">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Pendleton Jones to his brother the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:21
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes three letters from Pendleton while studying at Mr. Thompson's school to John at the University of Virginia.  John is helping him to get an appointment as a state student from the district.  He wrote to him about studying at the University of Virginia and obtaining a situation as a teacher after one year.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e511">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Pendleton (temporarily) expelled from school
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858 June
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:22
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>According to a letter from Helen Jones (n.d.) to her brother the Reverend John William Jones, Pendleton was expelled from a school prior to attending the University and the family was mortified.  He appears to have had a disagreement with his sponsor/teacher [John Thompson] which may have caused his dismissal. Helen wrote to her brother John about her concern for Pendleton and urges him to write him.  There is also a letter from Pendleton to John thanking him for his good advice but refusing to apologize.  He wrote that he felt very badly about it and wished he could just go away somewhere. He continued to live at home and Helen's letter reveals that Pendleton was trying to make a living by coming up with a new business idea but his father forbade it as he did not consider it to be a sound business venture. She wrote, "He and [Albin] have taken up a foolish idea that they could make a good deal, by buying a patent right for a washing tub &amp; without consulting anybody, wrote to the men about it, had not entered into any contract before Pa found it out &amp; forbid Pennie from going any farther with it."
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>Excerpts from Helen's letter to her brother John are: "We are all very much distressed about Pen at this time.  He has not been getting on well at school &amp; Tuesday he and John [Thompson] had some difficulty &amp; he was expelled from school.  I never saw Ma &amp; Pa more mortified about anything in my life... Pa does not know what in the world to do with him. I have tried my best to get Pennie to make some apology to John &amp; ask him to take him back to school, but he will not agree to it- I wish John you would write him an affectionate letter &amp; give him some advice- may be you might influence him, Pen's always had more obstinacy than any of the children but I would not have believed he would ever had allowed as to act so impudently." John must have written Pendleton because on June 5, 1858, Pendleton wrote to John thanking him for his advice but still refuses to apologize to Mr. Thompson.</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e526">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous correspondence: (letter from Ann Pendleton Jones's sister Georgie)
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:23
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e535">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous items: shoeshine cloth and photograph of Lieutenant Joe Berret-former mayor of Washington.
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:24
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e544">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L.R. Page to (Judy)
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:25
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e553">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Shomeaker to Edloe Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:26
	</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e562">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Crawford Howell Toy to the Reverend John William Jones
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:27
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes three letters from Crawford Toy to John where he offers advice and discusses his religious activities and their friendship.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Anson Tucker to his aunt
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:28
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Relatives (descendants) of Jones family
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e587">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Anson W. Tucker obituary
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:29
	</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Relative of Jones family
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="collection" id="d1e599">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Atlanta Journal and the Atlanta Constitution newspaper clipping on J.G. Berret and the appraisement of slaves
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 April 20
	</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="oversize"/>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
