<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01268">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01268::A Guide to the Memoirs of Mary Victoria Wesson Craw entitled What Every Little Girl Said to Her Mother &amp;#34;What Was It Like When You Were Growing Up?&amp;#34;: Scrapbook of a Lady of the Twentieth Century, 1983-1992)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01268.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01268::A Guide to the Memoirs of
             Mary Victoria Wesson Craw entitled What Every Little Girl
             Said to Her Mother "What Was It Like When You Were Growing
             Up?": Scrapbook of a Lady of the Twentieth Century,
             1983-1992)//EN" "viu01268.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Memoirs of Mary Victoria Craw
            entitled What Every Little Girl Said to Her Mother "What
            Was It Like When You Were Growing Up?": Scrapbook of a Lady
            of the Twentieth Century, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1992</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Craw, Mary Victoria--Memoirs 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11326</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2000 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">32.5 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word.
         Date of source: 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01268::A Guide to the
            Memoirs of Mary Victoria Wesson Craw entitled What Every
            Little Girl Said to Her Mother "What Was It Like When You
            Were Growing Up?": Scrapbook of a Lady of the Twentieth
            Century, 1983-1992)//EN" "viu01268.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Memoirs of Mary Victoria Wesson
         Craw entitled What Every Little Girl Said to Her Mother "What
         Was It Like When You Were Growing Up?": Scrapbook of a Lady of
         the Twentieth Century 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1992</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11326</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Memoirs of Mary Victoria Wesson Craw: What Every
         Little Girl Said to Her Mother "What Was It Like When You Were
         Growing Up?": Memoirs of a Lady of the Twentieth Century 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1983-1992</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11326</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">11-volume set of
         scrapbooks</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This is a 11-volume set of
         scrapbooks containing the autobiographical memoirs of Mary
         Victoria (Wesson) Craw (1908- ) of Charlottesville, Virginia,
         compiled during 1983-1992.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>The collection is without restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Mary Victoria Wesson Craw Scrapbooks, 1910-1992,
            Accession #11326, Special Collections Dept., University of
            Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This multi-volume autobiographical memoir of Mary
            Victoria Wesson Craw was given to the Library by the author
            and compiler, Mrs. Demas Thurlow Craw, of Martha Jefferson
            House, Charlottesville, Virginia, on August 29, 1997.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This is a 11-volume set of scrapbooks containing the
         autobiographical memoirs of Mary Victoria (Wesson) Craw (1908-
         ) of Charlottesville, Virginia, compiled during 1983-1992.
         Mrs. Craw was born in Springfield, Massachusetts and was
         educated at Bryn Mawr College. Victoria Wesson married
         Lieutenant Demas Thurlow "Nick" Craw (1900-1942) of the Army
         Air Corps on October 31, 1931. The two shared an interest in
         aviation and horses. The Craws were stationed at Schofield
         Barracks and Wheeler Field, Hawaii for three years, followed
         by Mitchel Field, Long Island, Montgomery, Alabama, and
         Langley Field, Virginia. During World War II, Major Craw was
         sent as an observer to the Royal Air Force in the desert
         stations of Egypt. His overseas assignment extended to duties
         in Greece and Turkey. Colonel Craw returned home for a few
         weeks prior to the North African invasion. Craw was killed
         while trying to reach the French commander in Port Lyautey,
         French Morocco on November 8, 1942. He was awarded the
         Congressional Medal of Honor posthumously.</p>
      <p>"Nick" and Victoria Craw had become acquainted with
         Charlottesville by a renewed acquaintance with Craw's West
         Point classmate Hardy Cross Dillard (1902-1982). He had
         introduced them to the University of Virginia's Institute of
         Public Affairs at which Major Craw gave the military point of
         view during the week that France fell. Following the death of
         Colonel Craw, Victoria felt so at home in Charlottesville that
         she decided to make her home there permanently. She went to
         work at the School of Military Government, housing the
         officers and making sure their medical needs were met. This
         was followed by a position as executive secretary for the
         McIntire Tumor Clinic. In the mid 1940s, Victoria and her son,
         Nicholas Wesson Craw, lived in Geneva, Switzerland, where he
         was exposed to and excellent education and foreign languages.
         She worked at the World's Alliance of the Y. M. C. A. doing
         odd jobs including the writing and recording of short wave
         broadcasts to English-speaking countries. Upon her return to
         Charlottesville, Victoria Craw became involved in civic
         affairs. She worked with the League of Women Voters, the first
         Blood Recruitment Program for the Red Cross, Planned
         Parenthood of Central Virginia, the Civic League of
         Charlottesville and Albemarle, the Board of Martha Jefferson
         Hospital, the University of Virginia Health Sciences Center,
         and others.</p>
      <p>This multi-volume autobiographical memoir consists
         throughout of a typewritten reminiscence by Mary Victoria
         Wesson Craw interspersed with correspondence, photographs,
         magazine and newspaper articles, invitations, essays,
         brochures, reports, certificates, and other memorabilia
         pertaining to the lives of Mary Victoria Wesson Craw, Demas
         Thurlow "Nick" Craw, Nicholas Wesson Craw and family and
         friends. Mrs. Craw's work shows a skillful mingling of
         personal and global history, often relating personal affairs
         against the background of historical events.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 1, ca. 1910-1930,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings and records.
         There are numerous photographs of Victoria Wesson. Included
         are the birth and baptismal records and school records and
         programs from Bryn Mawr for Victoria Wesson.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 2, ca. 1928-1931,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and
         memorabilia. Included are photographs of Victoria Craw and
         "Nick" Craw, including a wedding picture on October 31, 1931.
         Memorabilia includes a Cunard Line list of passengers, a
         Junior League program, their wedding invitation, steeplechase
         programs, and aeronautics memorabilia. Personal events covered
         include the Cunard Line cruise, European travel, and Victoria
         Craw's business career with Taylor's Little Shop in Cleveland,
         Ohio.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 3, ca. 1931-1937,</emph>contains
         photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia. There are
         photographs of Victoria Craw, "Nick" Craw, Nicholas Craw, the
         Nineteenth Pursuit Squad, Schofield Barracks, polo, [David]
         Stewart Iglehart (1863-1946), Secretary of War [Harry H.
         Woodring (1890-1967)], and Walter H. Frank. Memorabilia
         includes the "Official Insignia United States Army Units
         Stationed in Hawaiian Islands," Nineteenth Pursuit Squadron
         rosters, Ninth Bombardment Group certificate, and a
         hand-painted Valentine's Day greeting. There are recollections
         of living in Hawaii and on Long Island.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 4, ca. 1937-1941,</emph>contains
         photographs, essays, and memorabilia. There are photographs of
         Victoria Craw, Nicholas Craw, Victoria Wilson Craw, Frank Lee
         Wesson and Mathilde Overton Wesson, and Frank Herbert Wesson.
         A passport for "Nick" Craw is included. There is a discussion
         of Charlottesville boarding houses in the late 1930s and early
         1940s. There are recollections of European travel Langley
         Field, Charlottesville, and the University of Virginia.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 5, ca. 1940-1942,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, and writings. There is a letter,
         June 15, 1941, from Lincoln MacVeigh (1890-1972) of the United
         States Embassy. There are photographs of Victoria Craw, "Nick"
         Craw, Nicholas Craw, and their home, "Dunlora." There are also
         photographs of Athens, Greece; Cairo, Egypt; Ankara, Turkey;
         Palestine; Jerusalem, Israel; Damascus, Syria; and Iran during
         the time that "Nick" Craw was stationed in those areas. Items
         of interest are "Nick" Craw's impressions of Egypt and
         Victoria Craw's "Dunlora Diary 1941." There is data relating
         to "Nick" Craw while stationed in China, Egypt, Greece, and
         Turkey and his brief rest period in Washington, D. C. and at
         "Dunlora."</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 6, ca. 1942-1948,</emph>contains
         correspondence, magazine article, and photographs. There is a
         copy of a letter, November 23, 1942, from Major Peter M.
         Hamilton, French Morocco, including a narrative of his and
         "Nick" Craw's activities prior to the death of Colonel Craw at
         Port Lyautey, French Morocco. Related to the award of the
         Congressional Medal of Honor to Colonel Demas Thurlow Craw is
         a copy of the presidential citation, a magazine article, and a
         photograph of Franklin Delano Roosevelt presenting the Medal
         of Honor to Mary Victoria Wesson Craw and Nicholas Wesson
         Craw. There is correspondence and material relating to
         Victoria Craw's work in Charlottesville, particularly at the
         School of Military Government. There is an essay by Victoria
         Craw. There are reminiscences relating to Nicholas Craw's
         schooling in Geneva, Switzerland and travel from Switzerland
         to Holland and to Algeria and French Morocco, including
         Casablanca. There is a letter, April 28, 1948, from Edwin P.
         Lehman at the University of Virginia Hospital. Also included
         is a passport for Victoria Craw.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 7, ca.
         (1948-1954)1989,</emph>contains correspondence, photographs,
         newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and brochures. There are
         letters and photographs relating to a ceremony at Port
         Lyautey, French Morocco to dedicate a monument to Demas
         Thurlow Craw. There are photographs of Victoria Craw, Nicholas
         Craw, and their Pekingese, "Tiger v. Sonnenland." Other
         photographs include Colorado, the Craw family, and Gerhart
         Zuhling and Mary Stamps White Zuhling. Other items include a
         journal "Europe 1948," papers relating to "Tiger," and
         material concerning the purchase of "Oakwood." There are
         pamphlets and brochures: "Chatsworth" and "Dedication of
         Memorial Plaques Honoring the Graduates of West Point Who Gave
         Their Lives in Battle During World War II." There is a letter,
         November 17, 1954, from Kathryn H. Stone, House of Delegates,
         concerning ACTION. Materials relating to the League of Women
         Voters include a pamphlet, "The League of Women Voters of
         Albemarle/Twenty Years of History 1946-1966"and a manuscript,
         "Recollections of the League of Women Voters: A Modified
         Transcript of an Interview with Mrs. Demas T. Craw, August
         1988." There is a discourse, 1989, on the life of Cynthia M.
         Wesson along with photographs, Bryn Mawr memorabilia, and her
         last will and testament. Also included are annual reports,
         1961-1964, of Smith and Wesson Incorporated. There are
         recollections on travel in London, England.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 8, ca. 1951-1963,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and
         memorabilia. There are photographs of Victoria Craw, Nicholas
         Craw, Kristin Norstad, Isabel Norstad, Lydia C. duPont, and a
         trip on the S. S. 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Argentina</title>to the British West
         Indies, Brazil, Uruguay, and Argentina. Memorabilia includes
         the Moore-McCormick Lines list of passengers, wedding
         photographs and related items for Nicholas Craw and Kristin
         Norstad, a passport for Victoria Craw, and memorabilia on
         Paris including a 1960 typescript. There is material on the
         death of Lydia C. duPont and Frank H. Wesson. There are
         recollections on activities at the University of Virginia and
         life in Charlottesville and at "Dunlora."</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 9, ca. 1964-1978,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and
         memorabilia. There are photographs of Nicholas Wesson Craw II,
         Hot Springs, Barbados, and London. Other items include
         passports for Victoria Craw, an Arnold Air Society
         certificate, and a biographical sketch, November 1973, of Mary
         Victoria Wesson Craw. There is correspondence, 1976-1977, of
         the Embassy of the United States of America, Rabat, Morocco,
         concerning the bronze memorial plaque for Demas Thurlow Craw.
         Letters of May 1972 from William B. Spong, Jr., United States
         Senate; J. Harry Michael, Jr., Virginia Senate; and J. Kenneth
         Robinson, United States Congress relate to the Public Health
         Service Act and the proposed Hill-Burton regulations. There is
         discussion, correspondence, and newspaper clippings relating
         to James N. Fleming's proposed development near the Rivanna
         Reservoir (now the Ivy Creek Natural Area). There is also
         material relating to Mary Frazier Cash and the design of the
         park fronting the Albemarle County Office Building. There are
         recollections of Victoria Craw's work with civic
         organizations, including Planned Parenthood, the Board of
         Martha Jefferson Hospital, City Council, the County Board of
         Supervisors, and the Civic League of Charlottesville and
         Albemarle.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 10, ca. 1972-1978,</emph>contains
         photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia. There are
         photographs of Victoria Craw and Nicholas Craw. Items include
         invitations, a passport for Victoria Craw, and wedding
         memorabilia of Nicholas Wesson Craw and Page Farland Ross.
         There are recollections on the National Trust trip to England
         as well as memorabilia and brochures, "Stonehenge and
         Avebury," Burghley House Stamford," and "Blenheim Palace."
         There is memorabilia including postcards, a travel journal,
         and a brochure, "Tour to France including the Chateaux of the
         Dordogne." Pamphlets include "Thomas Jefferson" by Dumas
         Malone and "Sculpture by Cathe Wallendahl 1977."</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Volume 11, ca. 1979-1992,</emph>contains
         correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, and
         memorabilia. There are photographs of Victoria Craw, Mayor
         Laurence A. Brunton, Dorothy C. "Sunny" Knickerbocker, and the
         Martha Jefferson House. Memorabilia for the Paul Goodloe
         McIntire Citizenship Award given to Mary Victoria Wesson Craw
         in 1979 includes photographs, correspondence and newspaper
         clippings. There is a group of greeting cards and photographs
         of godchild Joan McIntosh Jessiman, Andrew Jessiman, and
         family. There are materials relating to the deaths of Nancy
         Hale Bowers, Frank Hawes Wesson, Dorothy C. Knickerbocker, and
         Fredson Bowers. An article on Nicholas Craw as director of the
         Peace Corps is included in a 1991 issue of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Leadership Perspective</title>. Other
         articles relate to the truce mission to French Morocco of
         Demas T. Craw and Pete Hamilton (1988) and to these memoirs,
         "Craw's Memoirs Bring Older Era Back to Life." There are
         correspondence and papers and recollections relating to
         Victoria Craw's involvement with SAFE, the Piedmont
         Environmental Council, the White Burkett Miller Center of
         Public Affairs, the University of Virginia Health Sciences
         Center, Martha Jefferson House and Infirmary, and the
         Charlottesville- Albemarle Community Foundation.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
