<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03018">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03018::Papers of Charles Elisha Taylor)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03018.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03018::Papers of Charles Elisha
             Taylor)//EN" "viu03018.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Charles Elisha
            Taylor, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1874</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Taylor, Charles Elisha, Papers of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3091,-a,-b,-c</num></subtitle><author>Mitzi Clark 1999 August</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ##132 Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by niyi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8/2/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03018::Papers of
            Charles Elisha Taylor)//EN" "viu03018.xml" converted from
            EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-03-02" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Mar 02, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Charles Elisha Taylor, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1874</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3091, -a, -b, -c</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Charles Elisha Taylor 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1849-1874</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3091, -a, -b, -c</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 550 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Charles Elisha Taylor, Accession #3091, -a,
            -b, -c, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Accession #3091 was given to the Library by Miss Mary
            Prichard Taylor of Hartsville, South Carolina on February
            23, 1966. Accession #3091-a was given to the Library by
            Mrs. Ethel T. Crittendon, Miss Mary Prichard Taylor, and
            Mrs. Aubrey Hawkins of Wake Forest, North Carolina on
            February 28, 1966. Accession # #3901-b was given to the
            Library by Mrs. Aubrey Hawkins of Wake Forest, North
            Carolina on November 15, 1967. Accession #3091-c was given
            to the Library by Mrs. Ethel T. Crittendon of Wake Forest,
            North Carolina on July 1, 1968.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 550 items from 1849-1874,
         chiefly concerning the Civil War service of Charles Elisha
         Taylor and his later experience as a student at the University
         of Virginia. There are 463 letters in all, primarily letters
         of Taylor with his family in Richmond and numerous friends
         from around the country.</p>
      <p>During the Civil War, Taylor was a member of Company F of
         Richmond and served under General Lee in the West Virginia
         campaign and with General Stonewall Jackson until the Battle
         of Kernstown, where he was wounded. In 1863, he was
         transferred to the Signal Service Corps under General J. E. B.
         Stuart and remained in this branch until the end of the war.
         He then entered the University of Virginia, graduating with
         the degree of Bachelor of Letters in 1870. He was ordained to
         the ministry in 1871 at Wake Forest College.</p>
      <p>Taylor was born in Richmond, Virginia, Oct. 28, 1842, the
         third son and sixth child of James Barnett Taylor, the first
         corresponding secretary of the Foreign Mission Board of the
         Southern Baptist Convention. Before entering the Confederate
         Army, he had been a student at Richmond College, having
         entered there at the age of fifteen. In his years at Wake
         Forest College, he was a professor of Latin and German; in
         1884- 1885, he was professor of Latin and Moral Philosophy,
         and from 1884-1905, Wake Forest College President. From 1885
         to 1915, he also was a professor of moral philosophy. He died
         on November 5, 1915.</p>
      <p>The collection of letters from family and friends while
         Taylor was a student at the University of Virginia deal with
         his student activities, membership in Sigma Alpha Epsilon
         fraternity and ministerial leanings.</p>
      <p>Also included in the collection is the diary of Charles
         Elisha Taylor during his Confederate service from April 21 to
         November 19, 1861; the diary of his wife, Mary Hinton
         (Prichard) Taylor, 1847 (1865) 1875 (also used for minutes of
         Young Ladies' Missionary Serving Circle); a narrative C AA
         Boy's Story,@ by Robert Samuel Prichard; newspaper clippings
         from the diary of Mary Hinton (Prichard); Taylor's school
         reports; University of Virginia certificates and essays by
         Charles Elisha Taylor; and an S A E fraternity pin.</p>
      <p>At the Z. Smith Reynolds Library at Wake Forest University
         there are 464 items in 30 volumes of Charles Elisha
         Taylor.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Civil War Correspondence of Charles
            Elisha Taylor-</title>
      </p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Letters from 
            <emph render="bold">1861-1862</emph>include twenty- two
            letters, primarily to family, describing Taylor's first
            days as a soldier in Company F, 21st Virginia Infantry, at
            Game Point Camp near Aquia Creek, Virginia, through his
            injury at the Battle of Kernstown to his transfer from
            Company F to the 10th Virginia Cavalry.</title>
      </p>
      <p>At Game Point, Aquia Creek, 
         <emph render="bold">(Spring, 1861)</emph>, Taylor describes
         his mess group, its members, a discussion of the food and how
         it is acquired, an excursion of ladies and "gents" to a nearby
         location for speeches, raising of the Confederate flag amid
         band music, and his learning of the voting taking place on
         ratification of the Ordinance of Secession. In August 
         <emph render="bold">(Aug. 27, 1861)</emph>, from a camp on
         [Valley Mt.}, he recounts the problems of mailing letters, his
         work on road making and bridge building, and his proposed move
         to winter quarters. Near Berryville, Va., 
         <emph render="bold">Sept. 15, 1861</emph>, he describes troop
         movements. 
         <emph render="bold">(Jan. 21, 1862,)</emph>.he writes from
         Winchester that his brigade expects to go into winter quarters
         at Romney. From Winchester, Virginia, 
         <emph render="bold">(Jan. 29, 1862)</emph>, he analyzes the
         need for colporteurs (those who distribute religious tracts to
         various divisions of the army) and mentions specific brigades
         that he feels have most need for missionary labor-- the
         Stonewall, Col. Anderson's, Col. Talliaferro's, his own
         brigade; Col. Ashby's Cavalry, and "six or eight companies of
         artillery." "All of these men", he writes, "have been ordered
         to winter quarters and need religious help." From Winchester 
         <emph render="bold">(Feb. 8, 1862)</emph>, he talks of the
         possibility of getting a furlough if he reenlists, of
         improvement in camp life and of taking a walk to an old
         Revolutionary Fort nearby which was built by George Washington
         .Still from Winchester 
         <emph render="bold">(Feb. 22, 1862)</emph>, he describes the
         movement of two regiments from Winchester -- the 3rd Arkansas
         and the 7th Tennessee, the former to the West and the latter
         to Manassas, adding that he expects movement of his own
         regiment "in a few days." "Things look blue in Tennessee," he
         adds, "but I am still convinced of the invulnerability of the
         Southern cause." In a long, descriptive letter from camp near
         Winchester 
         <emph render="bold">(March 9, 1862)</emph>, he tells of
         witnessing an attack by the Federa[?]y near Winchester where
         the Martinsburg and Charles Town railroads join about five
         miles from the camp. "Retreating Federals did an about face
         when met by four more companies led by Col. Turner Ashby and
         drove the Federals back to Bunker Hill several miles away."
         Taylor writes that General Stonewall Jackson moved all forces
         into a line of battle on the Martinsburg Road and ordered
         everything leveled in front of the fortifications for some
         distance preparing for attack. In the same letter, Taylor
         remarks on General Jackson's annoyance at horses being sent to
         a quartermaster outfit on a Sunday. Jackson, he reports, sent
         them back saying: "If the Northwestern army don't know when
         Sunday is coming, I'll teach them." Taylor says Jackson is "a
         better man than general." In a detailed description 
         <emph render="bold">(Mar. 26, 1862)</emph>, Taylor tells of
         troop movements from Woodstock, through New Market to
         Strasburg and to Winchester, where he was wounded in the
         Battle of Kernstown and then removed by caisson to Staunton.
         Two letters on 
         <emph render="bold">July 23, 1862</emph>pertain to Taylor's
         request because of his injury from Co. F-21st Virginia,
         Infantry, to Co. F., 10th Virginia Cavalry. One of these
         letters is from V. W. Harrison, Surgeon in Charge, Royster
         Hospital, Richmond. In a letter 
         <emph render="bold">(Oct. 4, 1862)</emph>, following his
         transfer, Taylor describes the "splendid current condition of
         the Confederate Army," but comments on the "drain the war has
         had on thoughts and aspirations." He also mentions the Yellow
         Fever epidemic in Wilmington, North Carolina. From a wagon
         camp near Martinsburg, 
         <emph render="bold">(Oct. 14, 1862)</emph>, Taylor writes that
         his mare is unfit for duty, disqualifying him from
         participating in a raid by his company with Gen. J. E. B.
         Stuart into Pennsylvania, remarks on the benefits of the
         cavalry over the infantry, tells anecdotes about Unionists
         tarring houses of Southern sympathizers, and gives a brief
         report concerning Stuart's return from Chambersburg,
         Pennsylvania. On Dec. 9, 1862, he makes reference to Negroes
         being sent en masse to the south. From a camp near Port Royal,
         Virginia 
         <emph render="bold">(Dec. 19, 1862)</emph>, he talks of the
         Battle of Fredericksburg, in which his regiment was not
         involved because of picketing below Fredericksburg at the
         time. He mentions in the letter having seen General Jackson
         and finding him changed since Winchester.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Twelve letters, 
            <emph render="bold">1863</emph>, deal with Lee's march into
            Maryland and Pennsylvania, some operations of the Signal
            Corps, to which Taylor is attached, and a description of
            his visit to Fredericksburg one year after the battle
            there.</title>
      </p>
      <p>From B. [O.] Williamson, Headquarters Signal Corps 
         <emph render="bold">(Feb. 22- 63)</emph>, a letter urges the
         use of vigilance in observations on the Potomac because "the
         enemy might be reinforcing the Army of the Potomac by the
         river." From the Loudon County camp of the 10th Virginia
         Cavalry 
         <emph render="bold">(June 20, 1863)</emph>Taylor describes
         skirmishing, the condition of Lee's army and his march to the
         north into Maryland and Pennsylvania. He includes a drawing
         showing the position of Stuart's Cavalry. On 
         <emph render="bold">July 21, 1863</emph>, he mentions repulse
         of the Yankees by the Cavalry in the area of Shepherdstown and
         speculates about General Lee preparing to cross the Potomac
         again. From Headquarters of the Signal Corps 
         <emph render="bold">(Aug. 3, 1863)</emph>is a request for
         transfer of Charles Elisha Taylor for instruction and duty.
         Taylor 
         <emph render="bold">(Aug. 6, 1863)</emph>describes his arrival
         at his new post, his mastering of the signal corps alphabet,
         the pleasant life at the post, which includes "fine music
         every night " as General Stuart is fond of music. His base is
         changed to Hamilton's Crossing, (about 5 miles from
         Fredericksburg) and 
         <emph render="bold">(Nov. 19, 1863)</emph>, he tells of the
         new base and his reaction to it. In a letter written from
         Hamilton's Crossing over a three day period starting 
         <emph render="bold">Nov. 27, 1863</emph>, Taylor tells of
         General T. L. Rosser's brigade of Cavalry being sent to assist
         General Stuart, leaving no forces between Taylor's group and a
         large column of Yankees occupying Charlottesville. There was,
         however, no action. On 
         <emph render="bold">Dec. 12, 1863</emph>, he meditates upon
         the battle the previous year at Fredericksburg and remarks
         that spent howitzer shells are being used for cracking hickory
         nuts, candle holders, etc. Seven days later, 
         <emph render="bold">(Dec. 19, 1863)</emph>, he describes a
         ride from Hamilton's Crossing to Fredericksburg in which he
         assessed what the town looked like a year after the battle
         there. In a Christmas Eve letter, he describes a temporary
         transfer to "Santee," a large home near Hamilton's Crossing;
         his longings for Christmas at home; his intent to decline to
         drink eggnog at a home in King George County for fear of
         setting "a bad example"; his difficulty of purchasing
         Christmas gifts for the family (he ordered diaries from
         Baltimore, including one for himself) and concludes with his
         wishes for the future.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Ten letters from Charles Elisha
            Taylor in 
            <emph render="bold">1864</emph>deal with diverse subjects,
            including the boredom of Sundays in camp, catching a spy,
            and being taken prisoner briefly.</title>
      </p>
      <p>From Taylor's Farm, Signal Station, 
         <emph render="bold">(Jan. 31, 1864)</emph>, Taylor describes
         his new post, which is about 8 miles from Hamilton's Crossing.
         <emph render="bold">Feb. 21, 1864</emph>, he writes of boredom
         in camp on Sundays and how he counteracts it by reciting
         poetry, reading the Bible, whittling wood, etc. He tells of a
         morning ride to St. Paul's Church-"one of the oldest in
         Virginia"-and how the Yankees had knocked out all the glass in
         the windows. On his return ride, he rides by a 2,000 acre
         plantation where a farmer explains to him why he does not use
         "book farming", stating-"My father never did it and I manage
         to make both ends meet without it."In the same letter, he
         mentions having caught a "spy" who had two horse wagon loads
         of "womens' fixin's, coffee, boots, sugar, needles, soap and
         hats. From Signal Station, Santee, 
         <emph render="bold">(Mar. 20, 1864)</emph>, he points to the
         large number of messages going through the line to General
         Stuart in Fredericksburg and writes a description of the camp
         food --making hominy by boiling corn in lye and then in
         several different waters. "Eggs are plentiful and we are not
         starving." More discussion of food comes from Santee 
         <emph render="bold">(Mar. 22, 1864)</emph>as he relates how in
         camp they are cooking cornbread with snow instead of water,
         using snow from a heavy snowfall that day. "It's fine," he
         says, "just as light as wheat bread. 
         <emph render="bold">May 8, 1864</emph>, he describes a 64-mile
         ride to Mt. Airy from Richmond to see "Mary". From there, he
         goes to Charlottesville, and 
         <emph render="bold">(May 15, 1864)</emph>, he portrays
         Charlottesville as a port for large numbers of wounded, tells
         of visits to Dr. Cabell, Dr. William F. Broadus and Mrs. Fife.
         In a postscript 
         <emph render="bold">( May 19,1864)</emph>, he says he has had
         his wound examined by Dr. Cabell and plans to leave for
         Staunton the next day. 
         <emph render="bold">June 9, 1864</emph>, Taylor writes from
         Staunton of his capture by two Yankee spies and being taken to
         Staunton where he is being treated with "great
         consideration"and expects to be taken to either Grafton or
         Martinsburg the next day because of crowded conditions (over
         800 men). Taylor's next letter, 
         <emph render="bold">July 12, 1864</emph>, is from The War
         Dept. Signal Bureau, Richmond, and is mainly chit-chat.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Civil War Letters to Charles Elisha
            Taylor from W.T. Chandler (fifteen in all)</title>
      </p>
      <p>On 
         <emph render="bold">July 7, 1864</emph>, Chandler writes to
         Taylor about his (Taylor's) escape from the Yankees. 
         <emph render="bold">Sept. 7, 1864</emph>, Chandler asks Taylor
         to help with his request for a transfer to General W. H.
         Fitzhugh Lee's signal corps operation. More letters through 
         <emph render="bold">September and October, 1864</emph>, deal
         with Chandler's request for transfer and for a pair of boots
         he wants. On 
         <emph render="bold">November 4, l864</emph>, Chandler
         describes capture of signal stores in a raid by the
         Yankees.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Civil War Letters to Charles Elisha
            Taylor from other acquaintances (20 in all, including two
            from brothers.)</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Feb. 4, 1861</emph>, George Leftwick from
         Richmond comments about General Jackson being a hero but
         "marching his men to death." Leftwick 
         <emph render="bold">(March 13, 1862)</emph>writes of a company
         of light artillery being formed to go into action under Capt.
         Gaston Otey. From a camp near Conrad's Store, John H. Worsham
         writes 
         <emph render="bold">April 28, 1862</emph>, about being
         stationed near Swift Run Gap with General Jackson. Taylor's
         brother George 
         <emph render="bold">(July 31, 1862)</emph>writes from
         Mechanicsville concerning Charles Elisha's request for
         transfer to the cavalry. From the camp of the 10th Va.
         Cavalry, Brother James describes 
         <emph render="bold">(January 12, 1863)</emph>, the hardships
         and fatigue of being in the cavalry. Two letters 
         <emph render="bold">(February 20 and February 22,
         1864)</emph>from Belton O.Mauldin discuss arrangements for
         care of Mauldin's horse. Benson M. Jones writes 
         <emph render="bold">( May 1, 1864)</emph>to discuss his orders
         to report to Lieut. Hull at Milford.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            his Family (1849-1859) 24 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">(12-21-49)</emph>Sister Jane exhorts
         C.E.T. to pray to God and to follow the examples of good
         people. 
         <emph render="bold">(3-13-54)</emph>Father James P. Taylor
         gives a vivid description of travel down the Mississippi River
         on a boat that carries emigrants, oats, hogs, horses, cattle
         and "wicked boatmen" who swear, drink and carry pistols and
         revolvers. From New Orleans 
         <emph render="bold">(3-18-57)</emph>James P. Taylor describes
         the U.S. Custom House and its construction and costs; the
         activity on the docks with steamers, freight and passengers,
         and the levees and their purposes. 
         <emph render="bold">(no date)</emph>, from Father on the Ohio
         River on the way to Wheeling, in which he asks C.E.T. to
         respect his Mother and gives him rules for leading a Godly
         life. 
         <emph render="bold">(4-21-58)</emph>Father is in Tuskegee,
         Ala., and describes effects of a tornado there the previous
         day. From Wilmington, N.C., 
         <emph render="bold">(4-16-58)</emph>Sister Jane gives an
         account of life with her children. On 
         <emph render="bold">10-15- 59</emph>, Brother J. B. Taylor,
         Jr., writes from The University of Virginia about his "time of
         youth" and how to spend it to build character.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            his family (1860) 29 Letters C.E.T. is in Rockbridge County
            near Natural Bridge, Va.</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">April 10, 1860</emph>, Brother James
         writes about his life at the University of Virginia. 
         <emph render="bold">August 8, 1860</emph>, Mother of C.E.T.
         describes from Malden, Mass., where she is visiting , the home
         of Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. 
         <emph render="bold">August 15,1860</emph>, Mother writes to
         all the children, including C.E.T., telling of her sudden
         return to Richmond because of the death of Sister Fannie's
         baby Minnie. 
         <emph render="bold">8- 19-60</emph>, Father writes from
         Richmond concerning C.E.T.'s colportage work and mentions how
         the discipline of this will aid him when he returns to college
         and decides what profession he wants to pursue. Two letters 
         <emph render="bold">(August 20 and August 24, both
         1860)</emph>tell more to C.E.T. of Minnie's death. There is a
         short poignant letter (no date) to C.E.T. from Sister Fannie
         concerning the death of her baby.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            family (1861) -25 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">These letters in general encompass
            Charles entry into the Army of the Confederacy and
            activities on the homefront in Richmond.</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">[No date-1861]</emph>from an unspecified
         sister in which she describes a braid she has made for C.E.T.
         to wear on his soldier's cap brim. 
         <emph render="bold">[No date-1861]</emph>from Mother in
         Richmond telling of trains of soldiers going through Richmond
         and her sorrow at Charles's sudden departure. On 
         <emph render="bold">5-11-61</emph>, Mother writes that she and
         others in her church are at work sewing pants for South
         Carolina soldiers stationed at race grounds in Richmond. 
         <emph render="bold">5-14-61</emph>, Mother mentions that the
         South Carolina Company has moved to a new location near the
         Reservoir and that all had attended the accompanying parade. 
         <emph render="bold">5- 15-61</emph>, Sister Fannie lists
         several Biblical quotes with reference to war. 
         <emph render="bold">[No date-1861]</emph>Sister Mary mentions
         unpleasant weather and the difficulties it presents for the
         soldiers, some of whom are "lying on the damp ground." 
         <emph render="bold">[No date- 1861]</emph>Mother describes
         clothes and uniform artifacts family has made for C. E.T., and
         tells of Brother James' activities working with the army in
         Columbia, S.C. Mother writes 
         <emph render="bold">(5-15- 1861)</emph>to give an account of a
         break-in at a church, apparently in an attempt to sabotage
         sewing work being done for the soldiers. 
         <emph render="bold">[No date-1861]</emph>, Mother talks of a
         visit by "Pa" and Brother George to the college and the dirty
         conditions for the company stationed there. 
         <emph render="bold">( 5-23-61)</emph>Fannie writes from
         Richmond telling of the departure of the South Carolina
         soldiers from that city toward Manassas Gap and of the package
         of food she and her sister Mary took to them. On 
         <emph render="bold">5-27-1861</emph>, Mother writes that there
         were three women alone in the house but they "felt no fear."On
         <emph render="bold">5-30- 1861</emph>, Mother tells she and
         Fannie have dispatched a packet to C.E.T. containing small
         combs, needles, buttons, pens, buckles, papers, envelopes and
         a linen shade for neck protection. She talks of embankments,
         of being prepared to keep out the enemy, and of Jefferson
         Davis being in Richmond. Fannie includes religious tracts for
         distribution.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">[1861]</emph>Mary writes to C.E.T. about
         many troop movements from Richmond, including some from
         Georgia, Alabama and South Carolina, and how food is taken to
         them as they pass, and she tells more of shirt making by the
         women (1000 shirts needed for 500 pairs of pants).She also
         talks of their Father preaching to soldiers in the Tennessee
         regiment, emphasizing trust in the Lord. On 
         <emph render="bold">6-3- 61</emph>, Fannie mentions the
         "conflict at A. Creek (Aquia Creek) in which no Confederates
         are wounded but many Union soldiers are. She refers to the
         18th Psalm, and "God's greatness and wisdom and help in
         subduing the enemies of David." She also admonishes C.E.T.
         against bathing more than twice a week in salt water, as "it
         is weakening." More troops are arriving in Richmond every day,
         she says, and there are "drum beats at all hours." From
         "Social Retreat" in Richmond, Mary writes on 
         <emph render="bold">7-23-61</emph>, describing a haversack she
         has made for an Alabama soldier, which she filled with a
         "plentiful snack" before he went off for Manassas. Mary has
         heard that many in C.E.T.'s regiment have nothing for their
         haversacks, and thus stuff them with paper and tobacco. She
         also has heard that the Union soldiers are no longer in
         Alexandria and that Confederates are occupying it, with
         Jefferson Davis with them in the field. From Fannie 
         <emph render="bold">7-31-61</emph>is an account of their
         Father going out to preach at the funeral of a soldier. She
         laments that despite the loss of her baby a year ago, she
         still believes "God is good." 
         <emph render="bold">8-7-61</emph>, Mary from Richmond depicts
         the funeral of a Capt. Lee who had been wounded at Manassas.
         There was a "coffin with a sword on it" and a long line of
         soldiers with fellow Masons following it. She adds that they
         "are expecting a fight shortly where Magruder is as he has
         sent for scaling ladders and ropes." Mother, in a letter 
         <emph render="bold">8-14-61</emph>, brings the news of
         Fannie's new baby. Father, she says, is preaching for troops
         at the Reservoir, and occasionally talks with wounded Yankees
         and their reservations about the war. Some believe tales that
         "Southerners would cut them to pieces if captured." On 
         <emph render="bold">10-1-61</emph>, Mother writes that Father
         is off to Norfolk to present the Colportage cause, that there
         are many sick soldiers in hospitals and being boarded in
         homes, and that coffee is being made using half rye. Sister
         Jane, from Wilmington, N.C., 
         <emph render="bold">11- 3-61</emph>, advises C.E.T. to keep
         his heart warm, to be engaged in religious subjects, and to
         derive comfort from the Bible. She mentions that several
         companies are in and around Wilmington and writes of forts and
         batteries along the coast. 
         <emph render="bold">[no date-1861]</emph>, Mother speaks of
         the capture of a "girl runaway" and the recovery from her of a
         quantity of ladies' wearing apparel.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Family-1862-1863-36 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>On 
         <emph render="bold">3-12-62</emph>from Richmond, Mother
         cautions C.E.T. to care even for old clothes because of the
         scarcity and the cost. She is busy knitting socks. The same
         day- 
         <emph render="bold">3-12-62</emph>, Father, from Richmond,
         discusses the draft of soldiers in Richmond City and in the
         county and the formation of artillery company by Capt. Cosby
         for city defenses. 
         <emph render="bold">[No date]</emph>, Mother writes that
         Brother George has been transferred to Staunton to be Post
         Chaplain. Father baptized three persons at [Camp Swinder near
         Amelia] where there were "thirty or more conversions." On 
         <emph render="bold">10-3-62</emph>from Richmond, Fannie writes
         with the sad news that C.E.T.'s friend has been killed in
         battle. Jane on 
         <emph render="bold">10-3-62</emph>speaks of the yellow fever
         epidemic in Wilmington, N.C., and on 
         <emph render="bold">10-12- 62</emph>, Mother relates she
         attended George Leftwick's funeral in Richmond and that [Dr.
         Burrow's] pointed out that seven members of that church had
         been killed in battle. In another comment, she points out that
         Dr. Thruston points out that while Ahard saddles bring on
         piles, a horse chestnut in his pocket is a certain
         preventative. AThis caution supposedly came from an old
         Indian. Mother also writes from Richmond 
         <emph render="bold">10-26-62</emph>that Dr. Thruston has
         written that the soldiers are without tents, with only beef
         and flour to eat, and no clothes except what is on their
         backs. In Wilmington, she hears, the yellow fever epidemic
         seems to be abating, with the Prichard family apparently
         recovering. There appears to be much small pox in Staunton,
         she adds. From Wilmington 
         <emph render="bold">10-27-62</emph>, Jane mentions learning of
         J.E.B. Stuart's raid and remarks that she is happy C.E.T. was
         prevented from accompanying him because of his injury. She
         describes the conditions in Wilmington as being deplorable
         because of the city's being in the "grip of Yellow Fever",
         with "no vehicles on the streets but the hearse and the
         Doctor's buggy." The same day, 
         <emph render="bold">10-27- 1862</emph>, Jane suggests that all
         the family, no matter where each is, sing the same hymn on
         Sabbath evening as a link to each other. She also gives an
         account of reading a copy of "The Watchman" in which the
         editor says "the backbone of the rebellion has been broken."
         On 
         <emph render="bold">11-3-62</emph>, Mother writes from
         Richmond that some of the men at the hospitals are begging for
         food, so Fannie stewed a chicken, put in Irish potatoes and
         baked sweet potatoes and corn bread for them. Fannie- 
         <emph render="bold">11-14-62</emph>- talks of "scholar
         schools", church affiliated groups where she teaches-how she
         has gained five new students-now having a total of fifteen on
         three Sundays. She mentions reading of J.E.B. Stuart's raid
         into Maryland, talks of Father's preaching activities, of
         receiving a letter from Major Thruston telling of hundreds of
         men marching barefooted in the cold, and laments the death of
         Jane's husband, Mr. Prichard.</p>
      <p>On 
         <emph render="bold">6-29-63</emph>, Mary describes a calling
         of all able to bear arms to an appearance at Capital Square in
         Richmond. She says she has heard of a capture of General
         Robert E. Lee and of wounds to him that "might be fatal."
         Fannie writes 
         <emph render="bold">7-21-63</emph>of her despondency over the
         fall of Vicksburg and Gettysburg and of her efforts to collect
         books and magazines to soldiers in camp near Richmond who are
         desperate for reading material. James B. Taylor (Father)
         learns of C.E.T.'s request for transfer to the Signal Corps
         and writes 
         <emph render="bold">8-11-63</emph>of his approval. On 
         <emph render="bold">9-10-63</emph>, Jane describes "Bobbie's"
         adventures on board the steamers Beauregard and the Calypso
         running the blockade. Mother tells C.E.T. on 
         <emph render="bold">10-30- 63</emph>of the scarcity of goods
         in Richmond, of high costs, and how clothes are being remade.
         On 
         <emph render="bold">10-26-63</emph>, Jane writes from Richmond
         to tell of her frustration over the war and how she sees no
         hope of any end. She mentions shortages of wood and coal. 
         <emph render="bold">11-28-63</emph>, Mary refers to gloomy
         tidings from all fronts in the newspapers. 
         <emph render="bold">11-17-63</emph>, Mother tells of many
         conversions in the church of soldiers, and on 
         <emph render="bold">12-25-63</emph>, she tells C.E.T. of
         Christmas at home and of gifts of cakes, nuts and candy.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor From
            Family-1864-22 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1-11-64</emph>Mother writes of "the cause
         being dark." 
         <emph render="bold">1-15-64</emph>Mother describes a trip with
         Mary to the Executive Mansion in Richmond for a reception
         given by Jefferson and Mrs. Davis. Generals John Bell Hood,
         Simon Bolivar Buckner and J.E. B. Stuart were present, and
         Mother gives an account of their physical appearance. On 
         <emph render="bold">2-8-64</emph>, Mother reports that Yankees
         are said to be at Bottom's Bridge in large force. "Our
         soldiers are all in motion to go meet them--three car loads
         came in on the Fredericksburg Road, all shouting as they
         passed down." From Richmond, 
         <emph render="bold">2-17-64</emph>, Fannie informs C.E.T. that
         her Sunday School has grown to 300, that more soldiers have
         been received into church by baptism, and that church
         activities now involve many soldiers. On 
         <emph render="bold">3-1- 64</emph>, Mother writes from
         Richmond that [Mr. D.] is going down to preach a few miles
         below the city, where soldiers only have bread and molasses to
         eat. The severe cold, she says, is destroying seed that was
         planted. More food talk is in Mother's letter of 
         <emph render="bold">3- 28-64</emph>, when she says there has
         been no fresh meat for six weeks, that they are eating bacon
         with corn fritters, turnip salad with turnips from the garden,
         and potatoes. On 
         <emph render="bold">4-1-64</emph>, Mother tells C.E.T. she is
         sending him cakes made from dark flour (no white being
         available), onions and a bottle of molasses. To all her
         children, including C.E.T., Mother writes from Richmond 
         <emph render="bold">5-14-64</emph>, that she hears cannon
         firing every day just across the river. She talks of the sedge
         of Richmond and of General J.E.B. Stuart being wounded in
         battle and being brought to the city where he died before his
         wife and two little children could arrive. She writes about
         Stuart's funeral and tells C.E.T. to look in the May 14th
         "Examiner" for an account of General Stuart's last hours.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters of Charles Elisha Taylor From
            Family-1865-28 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">These letters encompass the period
            from the end of the war to C.E.T.'s enrollment at the
            University of Virginia.</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">[No date-1865]</emph>Mother tells o f a
         visit by "Pete Law" of Danville who is overcome by the
         desolation of the city. She says Law returned to Danville and
         went on to the Carolinas atop boxcars. On 
         <emph render="bold">5-25-65</emph>, Mother writes that "Mrs.
         Colquit" has eight Yankee officers boarding with her- she
         reports that Jefferson Davis has been captured and speaks of
         the reactions of the colored people to the coming of the
         Yankees--"they do not feel they have benefited." Sister Mary
         says 
         <emph render="bold">6- 7-65</emph>, that ladies and the
         Yankees don't get on very well because the ladies refuse to
         walk under the U.S. flag-thus they are threatened to have to
         walk on the Confederate flag. In Richmond, she says, the Yanks
         and the defeated go their separate ways. 
         <emph render="bold">10-11-65</emph>, Mary tells C.E.T. how
         Brother James is instructed in "sermonizing." In the first
         stage-fire them up to get attention, in the second, rouse the
         sleep, and in the third, wind up to give a good impression.
         Brother George has met with the President in Washington,
         D.C.(Andrew Johnson) and on 
         <emph render="bold">10-14- 65</emph>, he speaks of that visit.
         On 
         <emph render="bold">10-19-65</emph>, Mother writes to C.E.T.
         at the University to describe having seen an eclipse through
         smoked glasses and to inquire as to his room and room mate.
         Mary writes 
         <emph render="bold">11-1-65</emph>telling of a Mr. Curry who
         preached for them at church and prayed fervently for Jefferson
         Davis who he "did not think would be tried." Mr. Curry wishes
         he would have a trial so "the South could vindicate
         itself."Mr. Curry had just come from Washington, D.C., where
         he had had a meeting with Andrew Johnson "to obtain pardon."
         Mary says: "he could but rtons, r when he was last in that
         room how different the circumstances. Then &gt;Old Buck' sent
         for him to help him out of some difficulty with the Republican
         Party who he thought were about to impeach him. On 
         <emph render="bold">11-22-65</emph>, Mother tells C.E.T. that
         Fannie has lost another baby and recounts a description of the
         funeral. 
         <emph render="bold">12- 20-65</emph>, Father and George write
         to compliment C.E.T. on his decision to remain at the
         University. 
         <emph render="bold">12-25-65</emph>, Mother tells C.E.T. of
         Christmas callers--Dr. Broadus, Dr. and Mrs. Jeter, and Mrs.
         Dabney, and adds she thinks Brother James has found a "good
         wife." On 
         <emph render="bold">12-27-65</emph>, Mother describes using
         kerosene oil, which she says gives a more brilliant light than
         candles. 
         <emph render="bold">12-29-65</emph>, Brother James writes from
         Culpeper Court House telling about his new home life as a
         married man with his wife Fannie (same name as Sister
         Fannie.)</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor From
            Family-Jan.-June-1866-27 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p><emph render="bold">1-10-66</emph>Father predicts difficult
         times as he describes many banks' failure to pay notes. 
         <emph render="bold">1-28-66</emph>, Mary tells of Father's
         trip to the North where he had his photograph taken and
         brought home oval gilt frames with Lee, Stuart, Johnson and
         Jackson photographs. "Jackson's was not good, looked like a
         real Yankee, so we put one of Father's in its place." From
         Mary in Richmond- 
         <emph render="bold">3-5-66</emph>- comes a description of
         "Kind Words", which she says is "truly Confederate. Five
         hundred copies of it will go to her school. She mentions that
         Dr. Jeter is expecting a co-pastor at the church--possibly
         Harry Thatcher. From home in Richmond, Mary gives an account
         of Mr. John Esten Cooke entertaining the family with thrilling
         tales of Jackson's Valley Campaign. She recalls reading
         "Surry, of Eagle's Nest", which she says brings back many
         "sad, sweet memories, and as I read of so many of these
         heroes, Ashby and Stuart-my heart sinks within one as I think,
         all lost-our bright hopes of our Confederacy forever gone."
         Mother writes 
         <emph render="bold">3-21-66</emph>of having a malady for which
         her doctor has prescribed "drinking lager beer", which she
         says she has done freely while eating oysters and now appears
         cured. Mary describes a church fair 
         <emph render="bold">4-5-66</emph>-where there was a large
         turnout of Negroes "who love the Southern people. The Negroes,
         she says, are sending circulars throughout the city telling
         their friends they were not going to celebrate the fall of the
         Confederacy-only their freedom. Mother advises C.E.T. on 
         <emph render="bold">4-21-66</emph>-to know something of the
         family before becoming serious about proposing marriage to any
         person. From Richmond on 
         <emph render="bold">5-11- 66</emph>, Mother tells of visiting
         Mrs. Dabney-"one of the most agreeable, intelligent ladies I
         know." Mrs. Dabney told many stories about Gen. J.E.B. Stuart
         and talks about a small biography of Stuart which states "his
         best religious friends think he was a true Christian, though
         sometimes given to levity." She also says Stuart was opposed
         to drinking spirits or using tobacco. Mother writes from
         Richmond 
         <emph render="bold">6-4-66</emph>-talking of Dr. Cabell's
         operation on Charles's ear and throat and of Mr. Hatcher now
         preaching at Grace Street Church, but that she doubts that he
         is the man to build it up. On 
         <emph render="bold">6-15-66</emph>, Father encourages C.E.T.
         to return to school for an additional year after summer
         vacation and advises him on his interest in becoming a
         minister. Three things, he writes, are required--a desire for
         the work, evidence of a call to the ministry, and the
         invocation of Providence.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters To C.E. Taylor From
            Family-August-December 1866 - 23 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Most of these letters pertain to
            family matters, social engagements, etc.</title>
      </p>
      <p>On 
         <emph render="bold">10-9-66</emph>, Mother chastises C.E.T.
         for use of tobacco and exhorts him to stop. Brother James
         writes from Culpeper Courthouse 
         <emph render="bold">12-4-66</emph>, how he and his wife are
         thrilled to receive C.E.T.'s letter postmarked the University
         of Virginia--"that seat of learned wisdom." The club, he
         writes, to which he (James's) belonged is no longer in
         existence. "There were only half a dozen members," he writes,
         "and the only chapter was at the University. "Their secret
         will die with us," he writes. Those clubs are humbugs, at
         least in my opinion, and my advice is to let them alone."</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Family-1868-1873-9 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">This folder includes one from C.E.T.
            to family concerning experiences at Wake Forest
            College</title>
      </p>
      <p>On 
         <emph render="bold">4-17-73</emph>, C.E.T. writes to Mother
         from Wake Forest College, where he is teaching, about giving
         exams to students, going fishing, giving sermons, reading--
         particularly "Gray Ashton", in which he says-"I recognize now
         a great deal of our family life." Soon, he continues, "I will
         go actively to work for the endowment."</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor From
            Friends-1858-1865-19 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>From Greenville, S.C., 
         <emph render="bold">10-20-59</emph>, John A. Broadus talks of
         students at his school, including nine from
         Virginia-Boatwright, Hatcher, Shipman, Ryland, Toy, Jones,
         Shepherd (Clarke County), Harrow (Middlesex) and Witt. 
         <emph render="bold">11-19- 60</emph>, Mary Poindexter
         communicates from Wake Forest College that it is "one of the
         dullest places in the world, but a splendid place to study."
         From Peak View, Va. 
         <emph render="bold">6-28- 62</emph>, Bettie [B.S.L.]mentions
         that she has learned that C.E.T. was not in the battle of June
         9, 1862, but that it "must have been a sad sight indeed to you
         so lately returned from your quiet home to behold the corpses
         of so many of your brave comrades with whom you had so lately
         parted in health and gaiety." She continues-"How hard it is to
         feel hopeful and bright when we are constantly hearing of some
         dear friend either dying or dead, away off on the battlefield,
         with no one near to hear their parting words. Surely our
         Father in Heaven will hear his children cry and bring an end
         to this horrid war."Bettie writes again from Peak View 
         <emph render="bold">12-63</emph>-of the approaching Christmas
         holidays and of her weariness of the war. Her only recourse,
         she says, is in the song--"While the Southern boys are
         fighting, we can only pray." 
         <emph render="bold">Dec.-63</emph>, Fannie Prichard from
         Poplar Avenue tells C.E.T. of the "pleasure of those at home
         being able to comfort soldiers by writing to them to express
         their weariness of the war." She continues-"sometimes the
         forbidden thought will come over me like a pall--what, if
         after all the precious blood spilt, we should be overrun--I
         cannot-will not say- subjugated, for oh-that can never, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">never</title>be. On 
         <emph render="bold">1-11- 64</emph>, describes a wedding in
         her town of a neighborhood boy-now a soldier on a 30-day
         furlough from the 2nd Virginia Cavalry. She comments on the
         behavior of the gentlemen guests--"the private soldier telling
         of his many hairbreadth escapes; the starred and striped
         officer looking and talking as if the fate of the Southern
         Confederacy rested solely on him, and the Exempts, men who
         have paid substitutes for war service and their hypocritical
         behavior." R. Snead on 
         <emph render="bold">8-16- 64</emph>acknowledges from Healing
         Springs, Va., receipt of C.E.T.'s letter describing his
         capture by the Yankees, an incident in which R. Snead managed
         to get away. C. Lassiter Allen , from Chaffin's Bluff, Va.,
         tells C.E.T. 
         <emph render="bold">9-22-64</emph>that he feels "shame and
         humiliation of submission. "I feel cast down and broken." In a
         letter from Greenville, S.C. on 
         <emph render="bold">8-7-65</emph>, Belton ". Mauldin depicts a
         garrison of two companies from the 56th New York who "behave
         as well as possible for Yanks, but no one speaks to them." F.
         C. [Cheroniny] replies to a letter from C.E.T. (now at U.Va.)
         telling of the condition of Hanover at the war's end.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Friends-Jan. -Sep. 1866-22 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Jan. 29, 1866</title>, Baltimore County,
         William 
         <persname normal="Norris">N.[orris]</persname>asks C.E.T. to
         recommend a tutor for his children and says he will go to
         Chili shortly where he will enter the army as a Colonel to
         introduce a signal system. On 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">3-1-66</title>, Belton A. Mauldin sends a
         message from Greenville, S.C. poignantly describing his
         feeling about the fall of the Confederacy. Mauldin writes
         again on 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">4-12- 66</title>answering questions about
         C.E.T.'s proposal to enter the seminary there--cost, length of
         time and instruction, etc. A 10-year-old friend, Nannie
         B.Wyant, writes from Augusta, Ga., 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">6-22-66</title>, that she would like to
         visit C.E.T. "The blockade is finished," she says, "and the
         railroads are running again." 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">7-10- 66</title>-, Dr. James Lawrence
         Cabell from U.Va. answers C.E.T.'s request for a prescription
         and tells him how to use it. Nannie Wyatt writes again from
         Augusta. Ga., on 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">9-3- 66</title>telling Charles she misses
         his friendship and promising to find a lovely girl for him in
         Augusta when he finishes school and visits Augusta.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Friends-Oct.-Dec.-1866-12 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>From "The Cottage", Md. [Baltimore}, George Norris tells
         C.E.T. 
         <emph render="bold">11-6- 66</emph>that he is thinking of
         returning to U.Va., and asks him to inquire about living
         quarters for him on Carr's Hill in a "little brick building
         detached from the rest, which is situated at the extreme west
         end of the row next to the pool." Robert S. Prichard writes
         from Wake Forest College 
         <emph render="bold">12-12-66</emph>that "the college is no
         doubt adapted to the wants of its patrons, but is not adapted
         to give any man a polished education.". A friend in medical
         school in New Orleans-R.C. Atkinson-asks C.E.T. 
         <emph render="bold">12-16-66</emph>-to send him information
         about Sigma Alpha Epsilon(S.A.E.) fraternity (grand chapter is
         at U.Va.) as a chapter is about to be formed at the University
         of Louisiana. He thinks of U.Va. as a "choice little world
         like fairyland or the happy valley of bachelors."</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters of Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Friends-1867-28 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>These letters include several-- 
         <emph render="bold">10-3-67,10-13-67, 12-20-67, 12-31-
         67</emph>-- discussing S.A.E. fraternity. On 
         <emph render="bold">1-30-67</emph>, Jefferson Jones from
         Richmond inquires as to how many professors and students at
         U.Va. were in the army and how many are determined to devote
         themselves to the ministry. There also is a letter from C.E.T.
         on 
         <emph render="bold">2-4-67</emph>announcing his intent to
         resign as Chair of The Washington Society because of illness.
         Mary Prichard (C.E.T.'s future wife) is discussed in letters
         of 
         <emph render="bold">1-8-67, 1-19-67, and 2-20-67</emph>.
         Belton A. Mauldin informs C.E.T. On 
         <emph render="bold">10-24-67</emph>from New York that he has
         given up school teaching and gone into business in New York.
         Rick [D.H.] Christian on 
         <emph render="bold">11-4-67</emph>writes about the debut of
         "University Magazine", with which C.E.T. is associated. On 
         <emph render="bold">11-12-67</emph>, J.R. Quarles requests
         from Inglewood that C.E.T. send him a copy of the Constitution
         and By- Laws of the Dualty Society. Rick [D.H.] Christian
         writes again from Richmond on 
         <emph render="bold">11-28-67</emph>discussing "The Negro", a
         publication dealing with attributes of that race.</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Friends-Jan.-Sep.-1868-34 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>Charles S. Converse writes from the College of New Jersey,
         Princeton, N.J. on 
         <emph render="bold">1-18- 68</emph>inquiring about the Young
         Men's Christian Association at U.Va. On 
         <emph render="bold">6-23-68</emph>, the Editor of Harper's
         Magazine acknowledges receipt for "perusal" of C.E.T.'s
         article on "Secret Service of the Confederacy." C.W. [Foy or
         Toy] communicates on 3-11-68 from Berlin, Germany, giving
         C.E.T. items concerning cost of living, libraries, learning
         German, concerts and other requested information. From
         Baltimore, William S. [Hatcher] 
         <emph render="bold">3-11-68</emph>requests support from C.E.T.
         on a lecture he is going to give at U.Va. on "The Advantages
         of Modern Dance." R.C. Atkinson writes from St. Louis on 
         <emph render="bold">6-1-68</emph>describing his attendance at
         the unveiling of a statue of Thomas Hart Benton. "It is
         pronounced a triumph of art" he says, Athough that amounts to
         nothing coming from cities that are ready made and never in
         all their born days have beheld before them a masterpiece of
         art. Virginia is vastly superior to the "Great West."</p>
      <p>
        <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Charles Elisha Taylor from
            Friends-Oct.-Dec.-1868-16 Letters</title>
      </p>
      <p>In two letters, 
         <emph render="bold">10-1-68 and 10-30-68</emph>, A. Fred Fleet
         from Liberty, Mo., portrays William Jewell College, where he
         is studying. R.C. Atkinson on 
         <emph render="bold">10-11-68</emph>from St. Louis calls U.Va.
         " a glorious old shrine".</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
