<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03260">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03260::Papers of the Quinby Family)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03260.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03260::Papers of the Quinby
             Family)//EN" "viu03260.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Quinby Family 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1759(1800-1898)1968</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Quinby Family, Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">2338, -a, -b,
            2871</num></subtitle><author>H. W. Symonds</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Alicia Pearia, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9/30/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03260::Papers of the
            Quinby Family)//EN" "viu03260.xml" converted from EAD 1.0
            to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Quinby Family 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1759(1800-1898)1968</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">2338, -a, -b,
         2871</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Quinby Family 
         <unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1759(1800-1898)1968</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">2338, -a, -b, 2871</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 1300 items (7 Hollinger boxes and one oversize
         folder, 2.8 linear shelf feet).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector">H. W. Symonds</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of the Quinby Family, Accession #2338,-a, -b,
            2871, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the Library in four groups:
            <lb/>Collection #2338 was given to the Library by Mrs.
            Charles, G. Evans of Danville, Virginia, and Mrs. Margaret
            Upshur Franklin of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, on June 24,
            1946. 
            <lb/>Collection #2338-a was given to the Library by Upshur
            Evans of Cleveland, Ohio, on October 30, 1953. 
            <lb/>Collection #2338-b was given to the Library by Upshur
            Evans of Cleveland, Ohio, on January 31, 1969. 
            <lb/>Collection # 2871 was given to the Library by Mrs.
            Charles G. Evans of Chatham, Virginia, on February 5,
            1948.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The Quinby Family Papers consists of ca. 1300 items (7
         Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder, 2.8 linear shelf
         feet, 1759(1800-1898)1968, papers of the Upshur, Teackle,
         Quinby, and other related families of the Eastern Shores of
         Maryland and Virginia, specifically Somerset County, Maryland,
         and Accomack and Northampton counties, Virginia. The
         collection includes correspondence, legal and finanical
         papers, a letterbook, ledgers and journals, class notebooks,
         commonplace books, genealogical information, prayerbooks, and
         memorandum books. The bulk of the collection consists of
         correspondence of Elizabeth (Upshur) Teackle, Littleton Dennis
         Teackle, Elizabeth Anne Upshur (Teackle) Quinby, Aaron
         Balderston Quinby, and Upshur Balderston Quinby with friends,
         family, and business associates.</p>
      <p>Much of the early correspondence, 1778 to 1799, is with
         Andrew D. Campbell. Campbell and his wife were British friends
         of the Teackles and Upshurs and he continued to write lengthy
         letters to members of these families until his death in
         1853.</p>
      <p>In 1800, Elizabeth Upshur (1783-1837) married Littleton
         Dennis Teackle (1777-1850) of Princess Anne, Somerset County,
         Maryland. Many of her letters from the period 1800-1837 were
         written to: her, husband; her daughter, Elizabeth Anne Upshur
         Teackle (1801-1875); and her sister, Anne Eyre of Northampton
         County, Virginia. These letters are of a personal nature but
         contain a few references to historical events, such as one of
         the British landings in the Chesapeake Bay area (Havre de
         Grace) in May 1813. One letter, dated December 2, 1778, from
         Nancy Cunningham (signed "Ruralinda") to Sally Teackle, has a
         note attached, written by Elizabeth Upshur Teackle on October
         1, 1829, which provides background on the 1778 letter. The
         letter refers to Nancy Cunningham's flight from Philadelphia
         in the Fall of 1777 or 1778 and to her later return and
         describes the whereabouts of Severn Teackle, who was being
         held as a prisoner of war by the British on Long Island in New
         York.</p>
      <p>Littleton Dennis Teackle owned and managed a ship supply
         company in Princess Anne, Somerset County, Maryland, from 1805
         to 1807. A letterbook from that business contains a great deal
         of historical information relating to the period prior to the
         War of 1812. It describes Teackle's business and lists
         materials he supplied, such as wooden structural components
         for ships, makes references to domestic and foreign affairs,
         and contains many other details relating to his daily business
         operations during this period.</p>
      <p>Apparently Mr. Teackle was away from home much of the time
         between 1807 and 1815 and between 1824 and 1836. During the
         earlier period he may have been involved in a shipping
         business with headquarters in Baltimore; he was a member of
         the Maryland House of Delgates during the later period.</p>
      <p>Included in Teackle's unbound correspondence is a letter
         from Henry Clay written in 1825 regarding paper money and
         another from James Madison on primary schools in Maryland
         written in 1826, in which he states some of his views on
         education. In 1836 Teackle wrote to Thomas R. Joynes of
         Accomack County, Virginia, as a member of the Maryland House
         of Delegates, regarding that body's consideration of a plan to
         build a railroad through the Eastern Shore of Maryland. He
         presented this information in order that Mr. Joynes could, if
         he were agreeable, support the continuance of the road south
         to Norfolk, Virginia. A railroad was not actually built
         through this area until more than forty-five years later.</p>
      <p>Most of the material dated 1838-1853 consists of personal,
         business and legal business papers of Elizabeth Anne Upshur
         (Teackle) Quinby and her husband, Aaron Balderston Quinby
         (1795-1853), a Baltimore lawyer whom she married in 1839.
         Major correspondents include Henry Clay, dated 1842 on the
         Whig Party; Quinby's brother, Jesse B. Quinby, including on
         English investment in the U. S.; and the Reverend J. W.
         Hoffman, a minister in Monroe, Connecticut, and a friend of
         the family. Material from this period includes several letters
         from United States representative Issac D. Jones and others to
         Secretary of State Daniel Webster, recommending Aaron B.
         Quinby for an appointment in the United States Patent Office,
         and correspondence of Quinby with representatives of the U.S.
         Navy, including James K. Paulding, George E. Badger and James
         Biddle, whom he was asking to test and adopt his invention to
         prevent steam boiler explosions. Also included is an 1841
         letter to Charles Stewart regarding ship propeller.</p>
      <p>Between 1854 and 1875, Elizabeth A. U. Quinby corresponded
         with relatives and friends, such as Henrietta Chauncey, C.E.
         Le Cato and a Mrs. C. Williams.</p>
      <p>Aaron B. Quinby's legal papers include a copy of his will,
         powers of attorney to collect property for clients, and his
         claim to property in the possessions of his wife's father. One
         power of attorney concerns lands in the Virginia Military
         District in the State of Ohio which were acquired as an award
         for service rendered by a soldier during the Revolution.</p>
      <p>Much of the personal correspondence between 1860 and 1897
         is that of Upshur Balderston Quinby (1841-1898), son of Mrs.
         Elizabeth A. U. and Aaron B. Quinby. Upshur Quinby attended
         the University of Virginia (1860-1861), and later became a
         highly respected lawyer in Onancock, Virginia. He and
         Georgeanna ("Georgie") Richardson (1845-1896) were married in
         1864 and had seven children.</p>
      <p>Upshur Quinby's early correspondence with his mother
         includes references to his life as a student at the University
         of Virginia, such as a description of a hike to "Monticello,"
         and records rumored and actual events at the beginning of the
         Civil War. In 1879 Mr. Quinby was involved with the Onancock
         Academy in Onancock, Accomack County, Virginia. Related
         correspondence includes letters from applicants for teaching
         positions and recommendations in support of several of them
         from Professor John B. Minor of the University of
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>Quinby was a candidate for judge of the Eastern Shore
         Circuit in 1880 and his correspondence for that year includes
         letters of support from friends and associates including:
         Charles U. Williams; G. W. Le Cato; L. R. Warren; Robert
         Thruston Hubard; Judge John M. Jeffries; John B. Minor;
         Richard Lee Tuberville Beale of the U. S. House of
         Representatives; and W. W. Walker. Several of these promised
         to recommend him to the governor of Virginia, Frederick W. M.
         Holliday.</p>
      <p>Quinby's personal correspondence from 1883 to 1897 consists
         chiefly of letters from relatives and friends, such as Adaline
         M. Swarts, Dr. W. F. Quinby, I. W. Quinby, and L. D. Teackle
         Quinby, and includes many letters concerned with genealogy. In
         1896 Quinby received many letters of condolence on Mrs.
         Quinby's death.</p>
      <p>Most of Upshur B. Quinby's legal and financial papers,
         which date fron 1828 to 1894, pertain to properties which he
         and Mrs. Quinby owned in Accomack County, Virginia. The papers
         include deeds, copies of deeds, land records, and receipts for
         purchases of building materials. Included in this section is
         some of the Quinby's professional correspondence relating to
         general legal claims and debt collection.</p>
      <p>The genealogical material in this collection includes
         information regarding the related Andrews, Balderston,
         Scarburgh, Stockley, Sturges, Teackle, Upshur, Walter, and
         West families, dating back to the 16th century. Much of the
         correspondence dating from 1886 to 1931 contains family
         information, probably in response to inquiries from Upshur
         Quinby. The genealogy section of the collection contains the
         baptismal certificate of Upshur B. Quinby, birth and death
         records from a family bible, notes, charts, and newspaper
         clippings. Other genealogical information appears in a psalter
         and a Book of Common Prayer which also contains slave records,
         the three commonplace books, and the oversize material.</p>
      <p>The bound volumes include two commonplace books of poems
         written by Elizabeth U. Teackle and her daughter and thirteen
         record books kept by Upshur B. Quinby. The latter include
         three University of Virginia class notebooks; four memoranda
         book which are almost indecipherable; two account books
         containing records of fees paid to the Onancock Academy; and
         three books containing financial accounts of Quinby's farm and
         legal practice.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Organization</head>
      <p>This collection has been divided into six series: I.
         Correspondence, II. Legal and Financial Papers, III.
         Genealogy, IV. Miscellaneous Papers, V. Bound Volumes, and VI.
         Oversize Material.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e221">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e225">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1778-1817</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <physdesc>14 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e235">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818
                  Apr-1857</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>13 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e245">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858-1911, 1927, 1931,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>7 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e259">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers of Upshur B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1882-1894,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e269">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers of Upshur B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878-1884,
                  1893-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Debt Collections</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e280">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial Papers: Accounts of Upshur B.
                  Quinby 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1882-1891</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e290">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>includes Business Correspondence</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e301">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834-1841,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Captain William White</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e312">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837-1842</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Invention of Steam Boiler Safety Device</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e323">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843, 1885</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Will of Aaron B. Quinby</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e334">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1880, 1888, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e342">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Genealogy</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e346">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Family Records and Annotated pages Removed
                  from Bible 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1794 and ca.
                  1850</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e354">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Baptismal Certificate of Upshur Balderston
                  Quinby 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e362">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charts and Lists 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885-1892,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Upshur, Teackle, Quinby, Stockley, Cutler,
                  Revell and Scarburgh Families</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e373">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Quinby Family</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e384">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"My Birthplace and My Home" by Edna Evans
                  Bell 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <physdesc>TMs (electrostatic copy)</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e394">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e398">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Copy Book of Upshur B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1850 [?]</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e406">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Notes 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Anatomy</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e417">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Poems 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862, 1891, n..d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e425">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1844-1895</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e433">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound Volumes</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e437">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Psalter 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1759</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Genealogy</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e448">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Book of Common Prayer 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1768</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Genealogy</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e459">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letterbook 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1805-1807</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Business records of Littleton Dennis Teackle</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e470">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1808-1862</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Poems and notes of Elizabeth U. Teackle</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e481">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1826-1872</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Poems and notes of Elizabeth A. U. Teackle Quinby
                  and genealogical notes</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e492">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby
                  while a student at the University of Virginia 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1860-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>in a law class taught by John B. Minor</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e503">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby
                  while a student at the University of Virginia 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1861,
                  1870-1898</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>includes business records from a later date</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e514">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby
                  while a student at the University of Virginia 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1861,
                  1871-1876</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>in a law class taught by John B. Minor; includes
                  business records from a later date.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e525">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby
                  while a student at the University of Virginia 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1861,
                  1878-1882</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>in a class taught by James P. Holcombe; includes
                  business records from a later date</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e536">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorandum Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1876-1877</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e545">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Journal of The Onancock Academy 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1877-1890</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e553">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ledger of Tuition Fees from The Onancock
                  Academy 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1877-1885</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e561">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorandum Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1878-1879</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e569">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorandum Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1880-1881</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e577">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ledger 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1881-1896</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Farm business records of Upshur B. Quinby</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e588">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorandum Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1882-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e596">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Genealogy</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e607">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ledger 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1896-1897</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Farm business records of Upshur B. Quinby</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e618">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ledger 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1901-1902</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Law fees</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e629">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Genealogy</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e640">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers removed from volumes number 12, 15,
                  and 18 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1877-1897</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e648">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Oversize Material</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e652">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Poems of Elizabeth Upshur Teackle 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e658">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certificate of Residence in Accomack
                  County, Virginia, of Upshur B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 Sep 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e664">
          <did>
            <unittitle>License of Upshur B. Quinby to practice as
                  attorney in the Courts of the Commonwealth of
                  Virginia 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864 Jan 20</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physdesc>handwritten</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e672">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Same as above on vellum 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864 Jan 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e678">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Deed, Edward K. Snead, Executor of the
                  Will of John Snead, deceased, to Thomas S. Richardson
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 May 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e684">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Family tree of the Quinby family
                  (1690-18410 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879 May 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e690">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Family tree of the Quinby family prepared
                  by Thomas B. Quinby 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 June 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e696">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Application for membership in the National
                  Society, Daughters of the American Colonists of Mrs.
                  Elise Quinby Bell 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e702">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Family record of the Dennis and Teackle
                  families from 1728 to 1811 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e708">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Table of descents of Edward Fisher,
                  grandfather of Mrs. Elizabeth Fisher Seymour
                  (deceased, 1864 Jun) 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
