<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01224">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01224::Papers of Louis D. Jones and Related Families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01224.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01224::Papers of Louis D. Jones
             and Related Families)//EN" "viu01224.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Louis D. Jones and
            Related Families, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1945</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Jones, Louis D. and Related Families
            Papers, 1800-1945 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11431</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2000 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">32 Kb.</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word. Date of source: 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01224::Papers of Louis
            D. Jones and Related Families)//EN" "viu01224.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Louis D. Jones and
         Related Families, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1945</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession number">11431</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Louis D. Jones and Related Families 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1800-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11431</unitid>
      <physdesc>The collection consists of ca. 835 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>The collection is without restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>The Papers of Louis D. Jones and Related Families, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1945</date>, Accession # 11431, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville,
            Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Purchased by the Library from L. &amp; T. Respess,
            Charlottesville in July 1998.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are ca. 835 items, 1800-1945, pertaining chiefly to
         Louis D. Jones of New Store, Buckingham County, and also to
         the Jones and LeGrand families of Buckingham, Prince Edward
         and Halifax counties, Virginia. Persons represented include
         William D. Jones and his sons, Louis D. Jones and Charles W.
         Jones. Contained are correspondence, accounts, promissory
         notes, receipts, legal documents, and genealogical
         material.</p>
      <p>Correspondence of the Jones and related families,
         1836-1901, concern various topics, including personal and
         family news, local news, education, estate matters, and
         business matters. Letters, 1836 and 1837, to Mary Leanna Jones
         provide some information about female education. An
         interesting letter, September 4, 1837, from George B. Peters,
         New Castle, Hardeman County [Texas], covers a wide variety of
         subjects. In his letter, Peters discusses his illness of
         "autumnal bilious fever"; the great current of emigration to
         Texas; people in all vocations going into the land business,
         expecting the government to grant a certain amount of land;
         anticipation of fighting with Mexico; the treaty of alliance
         between Texas and the Comanche Indians; trouble with parties
         of robbing Indians; land for sale in the Chickasaw nation;
         thoughts of moving to Arkansas; making obstetrics his chief
         study; a complicated birth; and young women using snuff. Two
         letters discuss social matters, including the antics of the
         "school girls" (November 17, 1855) and the activities of a
         fair, including art and food specialties (ca. 1850s). There
         are letters and papers pertaining to the estate of Monroe W.
         Jones (November 4, 1859; January 12 and April 19, 1860) and to
         the estate of Sally C. LeGrand (January 12, 1860; July 28,
         1868). There are two letters, December 24, 1860 and January
         30, 1861, from R. A. Lancaster, Richmond, concerning financial
         notes of Charles W. Jones on which his father, William D.
         Jones, is security and drawer. The hire of three
         African-Americans and their subsequent arrest for stealing and
         being placed in Grady's jail for safekeeping is mentioned in
         the former letter. General Orders #77, Quartermaster General's
         Office, Washington, D. C., dated December 15, 1865, from
         M[ontgomery] C[unningham] Meigs (1816-1892), concerns the
         recovery of public animals which had been branded by the
         United States. A letter dated February 4, 1867, from "Cora,"
         Southern Female Institute, Richmond, relates that the
         correspondent is fond of school and Mr. [D. Lee] Powell and
         family and that they have ten boarders and about one-hundred
         day scholars; and discusses teachers, students, and others
         associated with the school. There are two official letters,
         December 10 and 11, 1867, pertaining to the suit of Eliza J.
         Ransome and Louis D. Jones and the delivery of a horse to
         Jones. There is a related letter, June 5, 1872, from E[dward]
         D[avis] Townsend (1817-1893), Adjutant General, War
         Department. A February 17, 1869 document concerns the
         reappointment of Louis D. Jones as Justice of the Peace under
         the "Iron Clad" act of Congress; and, a May 29, 1871 document
         concerns his election as supervisor for the township of
         Francisco in Buckingham County. There is an official letter,
         January 26, 1875, concerning Jones holding the positions of
         postmaster and township supervisor simultaneously. On March 2,
         1878, Charles W. Jones, Amherst Court House, writes about
         being busy with his school by day, being pleased with the
         progress of the students being taught, and that the term of
         his school has expired. He also discusses local politics,
         particularly the Barbour Bill and [Virginia] state debt
         controversy and public debts. A letter of May 4, 1878 details
         a contract for tanning leather to be used in a case between
         Louis D. Jones and Edward Evans. A January 1887 letter from H.
         W. Moss details the financial state of his mother, Phebe Moss
         prior to her death. On November 24, 1890, Kate Dibrell Walker,
         Henderson, North Carolina, writes concerning the death of
         Fousos Dibrell by consumption, family news, life in Henderson,
         and keeping one woman servant and one man who also works at
         the factory. A letter of November 24, 1892, from Louis D.
         Jones, Jr., New Haven, Franklin County, Missouri, discusses
         personal and work life in Missouri and mentions the tilling of
         fruit trees being a rough business; New Haven and its
         situation on the Missouri River; cattle and hogs being shipped
         out and wheat being shipped in; and the large mill; and,
         includes a hand-drawn map of New Haven and nearby railroad
         towns. There are two letters, October 25 and November 1, 1899,
         from Ethelyn [Jones], McGaheysville, to Mary (Jones) Forbes,
         about her plans to get married, dissatisfaction with teaching,
         and lack of family support.</p>
      <p>Correspondence, 1909-1966, of Maben S. Jones pertains to
         personal, business and genealogical matters. A December 27,
         1944 letter comments on the engineering education of Cleveland
         [ ] Jr. at Pennsylvania State College and that he has
         African-American boys in his classes. A letter of January 2,
         1945 mentions teaching in Charlottesville and the arrival in
         July of a new superintendent. There are business letters, July
         1945 to August 1946, between Jones, The Letter Shop, Columbia,
         South Carolina, and B. P. Davies, Jr., The Barnwell
         People-Sentinel, Barnwell, South Carolina. A letter of August
         18, 1946 from Dunn, North Carolina, mentions the Stamp
         Defiance [Chapter of the National Society, Daughters of the
         American Revolution, Wilmington]; news of family in Hartsfield
         House near Wake Forest; "John" coming home from war and being
         inspector of drug stores in the eastern part of North Carolina
         for the State Board of Pharmacy. On November 25, 1966, Miriam
         McFarland Callahan writes concerning the LeGrand estate and
         Keswick estate, claiming that she would like to preserve and
         restore Keswick.</p>
      <p>The majority of the collection consists of the business
         papers, 1800-1900 and no date, of members of the Jones and
         Legrand families. These papers include accounts, business and
         tax receipts, promissory notes, and related business papers.
         Business papers, 1800-1839, pertain chiefly to the Jones
         family: Martha W., William D.; and, the LeGrand family:
         Alexander, Mary, William L., and Sally C.</p>
      <p>Items of interest include: note for hire of "Sooky" by
         William J. Moon from William L. LeGrand (December 27, 1815);
         promissory note from Grandison G. Wade to pay the rent of a
         plantation in Halifax and to hire the hands on said plantation
         to William L. LeGrand (November 16, 1824); and, several
         accounts with Captain James Anderson and James Watt. Business
         papers, 1840-1843, pertain chiefly to the Jones family
         (William D. and Mary S.); and, the LeGrand family (William L.
         and Sally C.) Items of interest include: notice of "Public
         Sale" for the residence of William L. LeGrand in Prince Edward
         County (November 3, 1840); account to Edward Redford for
         building a barn and ditching, includes boarding "2 Negro Men"
         and paying "2 freemen" for labor (August 1841); account of
         Mary S. Dibrell with Monroe W. Jones trustee, for work on
         house and lot (June 21, 1843). There are also numerous
         receipts from the clerk of Prince Edward County. Business
         papers, 1844-1849, pertain chiefly to the Jones family -
         William D., Monroe W., and Mary L.; and, the LeGrand family -
         Sally C. and John R. Items of interest include: statements to
         the clerk of Buckingham County from William D. Jones, trustee
         for S[ally] C. LeGrand (July, November 1945); account of Mary
         L. Dibrell with M[onroe] W. Jones, trustee (February 14,
         1846); and, a typed copy of account of William D. Jones with
         Sam B. Christian for medical care (October 7, 1847). There are
         also receipts from the clerks of Prince Edward and Buckingham
         counties. Business papers, 1850-1855, pertain chiefly to the
         Jones family - William D., Monroe W., and Louis D.; and, the
         LeGrand family - Sally C. Items of interest include: statement
         of J. W. Gills, justice of the peace in Buckingham County,
         concerning William Routon, a fugitive from justice from
         Tennessee, and his guard, Louis D. Jones (November 1855).
         There are also receipts from the clerks of Prince Edward and
         Buckingham counties. Business papers, 1856-1858, pertain
         chiefly to Louis D. and Monroe W. Jones. Business papers,
         1859, pertain chiefly to the Jones family - Louis D., William
         D. and Monroe W.; and, the LeGrand family - Sally C. Items of
         interest include: list of debts due the estate of Monroe W.
         Jones (June 24, 1859) and related documents; and, an order to
         return a convict from Nashville [1859]. There are also
         receipts from the clerk of Buckingham County. Business papers,
         1860, pertain chiefly to Louis D. and Monroe W. Jones. Items
         of interest include: bond executed to the administrators of
         the James R. Anderson estate (March 1, 1860); document re the
         estate of Monroe W. Jones (July 1860); and, a list of debts
         due the estate of Monroe W. Jones (ca. 1860) and related
         documents. There are also receipts from the clerk of
         Buckingham County. Business papers, 1861, pertain chiefly to
         Louis D. Jones. Business papers, 1861-1863, pertain chiefly to
         the Jones family - Louis D. and William D.; and, the LeGrand
         family - Sally C. Business papers, 1864-1869, pertain chiefly
         to the Jones family - Louis D. and William D.; and, the
         LeGrand family - Sally C. Items of interest include: documents
         re the sale of one bay mare, public property of the United
         States, to Louis D. Jones (February 29, 1864 and September 11,
         1865); copy of an indenture regarding guardianship and
         entitlements from the estate of William L. LeGrand (September
         20, 1866); and, a note from W. L. Cornish concerning Louis D.
         Jones' kindness to the officers and men of his army (April 17,
         1865). Business papers, 1870-1879, pertain chiefly to the
         Jones family - Louis D. and William D.; and, the LeGrand
         family - Baker and Sally C. There are numerous accounts with
         grocers and dry goods dealers. Items of interest include: an
         appointment of Louis D. Jones as supervisor of registration
         and election at the New Store precinct (October 15, 1872).
         Business papers, 1880-1900, pertain chiefly to Sally C.
         LeGrand. There is an account of Louis D. Jones with Hoge
         Military Academy for tuition and board and other school costs
         (September 13, 1900). There are also some undated business
         papers which pertain chiefly to Louis D. and Charles W.
         Jones.</p>
      <p>There is limited genealogical data on numerous families,
         including Gentry, Gilliam, LeGrand, Rolfe, Walker, and
         Woodson. Items of interest include: one page of a poem, "The
         Lost Road," with biographical notes on Percy Richard Gray; an
         obituary of Mrs. Louis D. Jones; and, a hand-drawn map of
         sites in Buckingham County, bordered by Prince Edward and
         Appomattox counties.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
