<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01219">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01219::A Guide to the Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families ca. 1855-1965//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01219.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01219::A Guide to the Papers of
             the Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families ca. 1855-1965//EN"
             "viu01219.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp;
            Marshall Families 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1855-1965</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families ca.
            1855-1965 Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11412</num></subtitle><author>Sharon Defibaugh</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2016 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">67 Kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by Sharon
         Defibaugh 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 24, 2000</date>.</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01219::A Guide to the
            Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families ca.
            1855-1965//EN" "viu01219.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp;
         Marshall Families 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1855-1965</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession number">11412</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2016</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Physical Description</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
         1855-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11412</unitid>
      <physdesc>22 Hollinger boxes and one oversize box, ca. 9
         linear shelf feet</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Papers of the Buxton, Lea, and
         Marshall families of Pennsylvania and Virginia, ca. 3,000
         items, include personal and business correspondence, diaries,
         journals, ledgers, notebooks and guest books, photographs and
         photograph albums, postcards, newspaper clippings and
         portraits. The correspondence is primarily that of Dr. Harry
         Taylor Marshall (1875-1929) and Nancy Lea Marshall of
         Albemarle County, Virginia, Joseph Tatnall Lea (1840-1916) of
         Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the Cabeen family of Germantown
         [Philadelphia], Pennsylvania, and the Buxton family of Newport
         News, Virginia.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>The collection is without restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>The Papers of the Buxton, Lea &amp; Marshall Families 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1855-1965</date>, Accession# 11412, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville,
            Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the University of Virginia
            Library in honor of William D. Buxton, M.D. and Pauline
            Marshall Buxton, by Lucinda Martin, Charlottesville,
            Virginia, William Buxton, Free Union, Virginia, Susan
            Spencer, Wyndmoor, Pennsylvania, and Nancy Silverman,
            Newtown Square, Pennsylvania, on June 19, 1998.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The earliest material in this collection pertains to the
         Cabeen family, chiefly the letters of Annie Anderson (Cabeen)
         Lea (1842-1921), daughter of Emma (Anderson) Cabeen and Robert
         B. Cabeen, an iron commission merchant of Philadelphia and a
         former president of the Philadelphia &amp; Reading Railway
         Company. Annie Cabeen's brothers and sisters include: Frank
         Cabeen, Ellen Roberta Cabeen (1859-1936), and Louise Wakeman
         Cabeen (1858-1916). The letters are between Annie and her
         family, and Annie and her future husband, Joseph Tatnall Lea,
         whom she married on December 6, 1865, at Germantown,
         Pennsylvania.</p>
      <p>Joseph Tatnall Lea was the son of Mary Mickle (Matlock) Lea
         and Robeson Lea (son of Joseph and Sarah Ann Robeson Lea), a
         grain merchant of Philadelphia. Joseph Lea attended Thomas
         Baldwin's private school in Philadelphia and the Lawrenceville
         School in New Jersey. According to the National Cyclopedia of
         American Biography (Vol. 17, p. 103), in 1857, Lea entered his
         uncle's firm, Hacker, Lea and Company, a dry goods commission
         house of Philadelphia. Two years later, working with another
         uncle, Joseph Lea, he was sent to Baltimore, Maryland, to open
         a branch house of a similar business but was interrupted by
         the outbreak of the Civil War.</p>
      <p>Lea originally enlisted in the 114th Pennsylvania reserves,
         and was promoted to lieutenant and adjutant, serving on the
         staff of General Phillip R. de Trobriand who commanded a
         division of the 3rd Corps, Army of the Potomac. He was wounded
         at the battle of Chancellorsville. Leaving the army in January
         of 1864, Joseph Lea opened a branch house of the family firm
         in New York City under the name of J.T. Lea &amp; Company.</p>
      <p>Eight years later he returned to Philadelphia, and in 1875
         became interested in coal mining operations in West Virginia.
         On the death of his father-in-law, he succeeded him in the
         coal and iron commission business in Philadelphia under the
         name of Cabeen and Company (later J. Tatnall Lea and Company).
         From 1904-1915, he was president of the First National Bank of
         Philadelphia, and also had interests in the Lake Superior
         Corporation, the Pennsylvania Fire Insurance Company, and the
         Pennsylvania Salt Company.</p>
      <p>The children born to Annie and Joseph Tatnall Lea
         (1840-1916) include: Ellen Roberta Lea (b. 1866), Florence Lea
         Fletcher (1868-1911), Langdon Lea who married Belknap Lyons,
         Mrs. William H. Nicholson, Jr. (Katharine Leonard Lea), and
         Mrs. Harry T. Marshall (Nancy Lea). Nancy Lea and Dr. Harry
         Taylor Marshall (1875-1929), married at "Bloomfield," Ivy,
         Virginia, the summer home of the Lea family since 1875, on
         June 17, 1911. Harry Taylor Marshall, son of Charles and
         Rebecca (Snowden) Marshall, graduated from Johns Hopkins
         University (1894 A.B. and 1898 M.D.) and interned at the Johns
         Hopkins Hospital, joining its faculty as a fellow in
         pathology1899-1900, an assistant in pathology 1900-1903, an
         instructor in medicine, 1903-1905, and pediatrics, 1905-1906.
         According to the National Cyclopedia of American Biography
         (Vol. 34, p. 104), Marshall also worked summers as a recorder
         for the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey (1892-1894); interned
         at the Thomas Wilson Sanitarium (1898 &amp; 1903); was a
         travelling fellow for the Rockefeller Institute (1901-1902),
         when he studied under Professor Ehrlich in Frankfort,
         Germany.</p>
      <p>In 1906, Marshall moved to the Philippine Islands, where he
         was pathologist at the Bureau of Science and Professor of
         Pathology at the College of Medicine, Manila. He returned to
         the United States in 1908 to become the Walter Reed Professor
         of Pathology at the University of Virginia until his death in
         1929. The children of Nancy Lea and Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall
         were Marion Pauline Marshall Buxton, (married William Dimmock
         Buxton), Harry Taylor Marshall, Katherine Marshall, Nancy Lea
         ([1915?]- ) who married Thomas Valentine Cooper in 1943, and
         Snowden Marshall (1912- ).</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
        <p>Papers of the Buxton, Lea, and Marshall families of
            Pennsylvania and Virginia, ca. 3,000 items (22 Hollinger
            boxes and one oversize box, ca. 9 linear shelf feet), ca.
            1855-1965, include personal and business correspondence,
            diaries, journals, ledgers, notebooks and guest books,
            photographs and photograph albums, postcards, newspaper
            clippings and portraits. The correspondence is primarily
            that of Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall (1875-1929) and Nancy Lea
            Marshall of Albemarle County, Virginia, Joseph Tatnall Lea
            (1840-1916) of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the Cabeen
            family of Germantown [Philadelphia], Pennsylvania, and the
            Buxton family of Newport News, Virginia.</p>
        <p>The early correspondence of the Cabeen family, March
            28-May 9, 1859, chiefly consists of letters between Annie
            Cabeen and her family, while she is away on a tour of the
            southern states of South Carolina, Georgia, Tennessee and
            Florida, with friends of the family. She describes the
            flora and fauna of the area, the hotels, her activities,
            the people she meets, riding the stage coach, her visit to
            the oldest house in the United States and the old fort in
            St. Augustine, Florida, which held Osceola during the
            Seminole wars, a visit to a coquina quarry in Florida, and
            her visit to the Mammoth Cave and White's Cave in
            Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Other topics in the Cabeen family correspondence include
            a discussion about the beginning of the Civil War,
            especially concerning Baltimore, Maryland (1861 April 21);
            and balloon flight and the concept of "aerostatic
            artillery" (1862 April 26). The courtship correspondence
            between Annie Cabeen and her future husband, Joseph Tatnall
            Lea, begins with a letter from Lea, at Camp with Union
            General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks, Washington, D.C.,
            written September 1, 1862. Lea began his Civil War service
            as an officer in Company "F" 114th Regiment of the
            Pennsylvania Volunteers.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>Civil War Correspondence in 1862</head>
        <p>Lea mentions the desertion of some of the men because of
            the non-payment of bounties upon their arrival in
            Washington, D.C. (1862 September 9 &amp; 25); another letter
            mentions two other officers, Captain Frank A. Eliot and
            Charles A. Robinson, adjutant of the regiment, listening to
            the Germantown Cornet Band, and the flag of the "Zouaves d'
            Afrique" before the door of his tent (1862 September 21,
            Arlington Heights, Virginia).</p>
        <p>On October 7, 1862, Lea is at Hunter's Chapel, Virginia,
            and talks about distributing medicine; a letter dated
            October 19, finds Lea at Poolesville, Maryland, and
            contains his proposal of marriage to Annie Cabeen, rejected
            at that time; and on November 14, he writes from near
            Waterloo, Virginia, disturbed at the removal of General
            George McClellan as head of the Northern army, "it is
            rather hard that the wishes of stay at home abolitionists
            should be consulted in preference to those who are bearing
            the hardships and making the sacrifice." A final letter for
            1862, written from Camp Pitcher, near Falmouth, Virginia,
            describes his quarters and the hardships endured by the men
            because of the weather (December 9).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>Civil War Correspondence in 1863</head>
        <p>While at Camp Pitcher, Lea mentions the capture of the
            Germantown Cornet Band by the Southern forces and refers to
            a fierce battle [Battle of Fredericksburg?] but gives no
            details (January 15); near Potomac Creek, he writes about the
            abolitionists and reports on a wedding in Washington, D.C.
            complete with fireworks that cost two thousand dollars (March
            15) and assures Annie of his lack of sympathy for
            "Copperheads" and "Democrats" and his changed opinion of
            "colored regiments" (April 28). On May 18, he is at home on
            leave because of his arm, having been wounded in the battle
            of Chancellorsville, and on July 16, he sends her his new
            address, Headquarters, 1st Division, 3rd Corps, Army of the
            Potomac, as he plans to rejoin his comrades.</p>
        <p>Letters from Joseph Tatnall Lea assure Annie that he has
            arranged his business affairs so that upon his return from
            the war he will be the head of the family's New York house,
            and will be able to marry her; apparently they came to an
            understanding before he left home; General George Meade has
            crossed the Potomac River after Robert E. Lee, and Lea
            hopes to rejoin his fellow soldiers by accompanying the
            mail carrier of the 3rd Division of his Corps (July 19-20).
            Lea was home on leave in Philadelphia, having escaped from
            Staunton, Virginia (August 17) but returned to Washington on
            August 25.</p>
        <p>His new position, which he assumed at Sulphur Springs,
            Virginia, was that of Aid to the Headquarters, 3rd Brigade,
            1st Division, 3rd Corps, Army of the Potomac, commanded by
            Colonel [Regis , Denis de Keredem, Comte] de Trobriand. Lea
            hopes to soon fill a vacancy with Fitzhugh Birney; and
            mentions that the battle of Chancellorsville reduced his
            brigade from about two thousand to eight hundred men (August
            26-30). While still at Sulphur Springs, Lea mentions his
            disgust with Lt. Colonel Merrill of the 17th Maine, who
            "has a great dread of being put upon an equality with
            Negroes" (September 4); refers to his participation in the battle
            of Chancellorsville where he broke his arm (September 5); says
            the 3rd Corps now commanded by General [William Henry]
            French (1863 September 7); and discusses one woman's attitude to
            patriotic duty (1863 September 10).</p>
        <p>Stationed near Culpeper, Virginia, Lea mentions John
            Minor Botts (1802-1869), "a [former] prisoner paroled by
            the Rebel government" (1863 September 17); the return of two
            regiments to the Brigade who had been in New York enforcing
            the draft, bringing the Brigade up to 1,500 men, with his
            whole division with sixteen regiments containing about
            4,000 men (1863 September 19); mentions the news of the setback
            General William Starke Rosecrans suffered at the battle of
            Chickamauga (1863 September 23); Lea discusses the effects of
            conscription on the quality of the Northern army (1863 September
            24); his dislike of Colonel Charles Henry Tucky Collis, a
            Philadelphia attorney who organized both the independent
            company of Zouaves d' Afrique and the 114th Pennsylvania
            Volunteers; the attempt of Collis to arrange to get Lea's
            regiment transferred from the 3rd Brigade into General John
            C. Robinson's Second Division of the First Corps; his
            contempt for Collis as a commander, who he considered his
            social inferior; and the earlier deaths of his two friends,
            Joe Chandler and Frank Eliot, while serving under Collis at
            battle of Chancellorsville (September 25, 27 &amp; 28); and the
            receipt of new instruments for the band as a gift of
            General [David Bell] Birney (1863 September 26).</p>
        <p>Topics raised in the letters of October 1863 include the
            Third Army Corps Union (October 2); a march to Sulphur Springs
            to prevent the Rebels from outflanking them, crossing the
            Hazel and Hedgmon Rivers, and mention of a cavalry battle
            near Brandy Station (October 10-12). By October 14th, they were
            occupying an almost impregnable position between the old
            Bull Run Battleground and Centerville, with heavy fighting
            at Bristoe Station involving the 2nd and 5th Corps and two
            brigades of his Corps, but from another Division. Both
            Lea's Brigade and the First (Collis') had a sharp
            engagement at Auburn the afternoon of October 13, which he
            describes (October 14). While at Fairfax Station, Lea describes
            the reaction of the Corps to the appearance of General
            Daniel Edgar Sickles (1825-1914) on the road (October 15), and
            the execution of a deserter from his Brigade (October 16). On
            October 19th, they marched to Bristoe Station.</p>
        <p>On October 21st, after marching to Catlett's Station,
            supposedly to rebuild the railroad, Lea voices his
            criticism of General Meade "we are all deeply mortified at
            our recent movements. Lee with about ten thousand men, as
            it now turns out, forced us to retire almost to Washington
            then totally destroyed the railroad, and has quietly gone
            back again to his old quarters." Still at Catlett's
            Station, he complains about General Meade's orders sending
            all the sutlers back to Washington, who were apparently
            captured by John Singleton Mosby on the way, because now
            the forces could not buy any good tobacco or cigars (October
            25); and describes his idea of the role of the wife in the
            home (October 26). After marching to Cedar Run, their
            headquarters was set up at "Pilgrim's Rest," a house owned
            by Union people, part of the "Jersey settlement" of about
            fifty families who emigrated from New Jersey to Virginia
            about a decade before and who had lost all of their
            livestock to marauders, "I am really ashamed of the way our
            men have behaved around here, in some cases entering
            pantries guarded by women, and helping themselves to
            anything they could find. We have had to put safeguards
            around at all the houses to protect the women from insult"
            (October 27). The headquarters moved from "Pilgrim's Rest" to
            Warrenton Junction but the brigade did not go into winter
            quarters yet (October 30). Lea is angry with his
            African-American servant because of his carelessness with
            his horse (November 5).</p>
        <p>Lea's letters are full of details about the action at
            Kelly's Ford, where Lea's brigade drove away the enemy,
            capturing nearly two Confederate regiments, about five
            hundred prisoners, and mentioning General David Bell
            Birney's narrow escape from a Confederate shell (November 7
            &amp; 9). They now occupy the winter quarters of Richard
            Stoddert Ewell's Corps, which was captured during the
            recent fight, of which he furnishes additional details,
            explaining the chance death of Captain Maynard on the staff
            of the First Brigade, killed by a stray bullet from a
            skirmish some distance away, and mentions that part of his
            brigade is camped on the estate of John Minor Botts (November
            10).</p>
        <p>Other topics in November include the order for the men
            from his brigade to rebuild the fence destroyed by the
            Confederates on the John Minor Botts estate, who also
            suffered the loss of his pigs to hungry Union forces nearby
            (November 11); an order to stop building winter quarters, and
            mention of General Meade's General Orders complimenting the
            3rd Brigade on their actions at Kelly's Ford (November 12-13);
            hearing cannon fire at Kelly's Ford, and comments about the
            lack of good chaplains in the Northern Army (November 15); an
            exhibition of the Corps to a few British officers (November 16);
            rumors of a big campaign towards Lynchburg (November 18); the
            homesickness of his servant Adolphus and a mention that the
            Lea family business sales now are at the rate of one
            million per annum (November 19); and notes that three more
            deserters from his Corps will be shot in a few days (November
            21).</p>
        <p>Lea writes that Collis has again made application to
            General Birney to have Lea returned to his regiment which
            Birney did not approve; He has heard a rumor that Collis
            plans to appeal Birney's decision to General French, the
            Corps commander. He also notes that an order, issued before
            the Kelly's Ford battle, has come from the War Department,
            mustering Colonel de Trobriand out of the service, to be
            replaced by Colonel [Thomas Washington] Egan (November 22).
            Although preparations for a troop movement began on
            November 22, the rainy weather has prevented any action.
            Lea is disgusted that the Washington newspapers forecast
            their move twenty-four hours in advance, indicating they
            were crossing the Rapidan River at Germanna Ford (November
            24).</p>
        <p>After a hiatus in correspondence, Lea writes about being
            engaged in a severe fight at a place called Morris' Farm,
            where his division lost 264 men (174 in one brigade); Lea
            was hit in the shoulder by a spent ball when Egan had sent
            him to move forward the 17th Maine to occupy the front line
            during the hottest part of the battle; Lea's brigade was
            the rear guard of the 3rd Corps; he discusses the argument
            between French and Meade at Birney's headquarters, where
            French acccused Meade of taking two thirds of his command
            from him and giving them to a boy (Warren), who then did
            nothing; they lost one field officer and six line officers
            during the engagement [the Mine Run Campaign?], and says
            "the 3rd Division got scared and fell back with very few
            killed or wounded, and our brigade was put in to stop the
            Rebels, which we did, never yielding an inch" (December
            3-4).</p>
        <p>Lea notes that he is busy writing the official record of
            the part taken by his brigade in the late troop movement
            (December 6); recalls participating in the battle at
            Fredericksburg last winter and the famous "mud march" (December
            8); comments concerning General French; describes the
            efforts of his uncle Joseph and T.D. Eliot to secure his
            discharge from the army on account of the family business
            by a visit to the home of Secretary of War, Edwin M.
            Stanton (December 12); refers to the stories about the Kelly's
            Ford fight as described in the 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Illustrated
            Papers</title>and 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Harper's Weekly</title>&amp; 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Illustrated News</title>; the
            presence in Colonel Egan's Regiment, of a former head cook
            at the New York Hotel, a French man, who was detailed for
            special duty as a cook for Headquarters and who prepared
            all sorts of French dishes (December 13); and Lea's receipt of
            the news that Stanton had agreed to receive Lea's
            resignation as soon as it was forwarded with the approval
            of the Brigade commander, but a mix-up caused a delay in
            the document reaching Stanton (December 13, 29-30).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>Civil War Correspondence in 1864</head>
        <p>Lea learns that General Birney has ordered him to report
            back to his original regiment, which had been taken out of
            the Division and put on guard duty at General Meade's
            Headquarters; Birney also had disapproved his resignation
            from the army (1864 January 1); Lea hopes to rejoin his
            regiment as an adjutant and plans to reapply to resign from
            the army; his address would be 114th Pennsylvania
            Volunteers, Headquarters, Army of the Potomac (January 2);
            mentions his dislike of Colonel West and that his
            twenty-fourth birthday is on January 7th (January 4); gives his
            opinion of Botts, whose complaints concerning the troops
            cutting down his trees for fire wood has caused them to
            have to move their camp (January 6); Lea still struggling to
            get his discharge papers to Stanton (January 8); they have
            moved their headquarters to another home two miles from
            Brandy Station (January 10); Lea discusses being made the
            manager of his brigade for the Third Corps Ball given for
            the officers (January 18, 24, &amp; 26); Lea has finally
            received word of action on his resignation from the army
            (January 28); and Lea's resignation has been approved and he is
            in Washington, D.C., on the way home to Philadelphia (February
            3).</p>
        <p>Joseph Tatnall Lea and Annie Cabeen continue to write
            their courtship letters until their marriage on December 6,
            1865, while Lea resides in New York City and works at the
            "rag trade," actually a dry goods commission house, for his
            Uncle Joseph Lea, and Annie Cabeen lives with her family in
            Germantown, a residential section of Philadelphia (1864 February
            10). Other topics include a subscription to the Mercantile
            Library (March 10); the family of Mrs. Ward split by the
            Civil War (1864 March 31); a business sale to Alexander
            Turney Stewart, owner of a dry goods retail store in New
            York (1864 April 12); a reference to a "collapse on Wall
            Street" and its effect upon some businessmen (1864 April 19);
            and mention of "little retail stores kept by women" in
            Philadelphia (1864 May 6).</p>
        <p>After a visit with General de Trobriand, who had orders
            to assume command of New York City and the harbor, Lea
            hears news of the death of General Alexander Hays at the
            battle of the Wilderness in Virginia; agrees to be a
            "volunteer aid" for de Trobriand to help put down any riots
            like those of the summer of 1863; and learns of the death
            of General James Clay Rice (1864 May 8, 10, 11); Lea hears
            of more casualties from his former comrades in the battle
            of the Wilderness and hopes for success under Grant (May
            19); shares news of his old regiment from Ned Bowen (June
            9); and learns of the death of his friend, Fitz Birney,
            from disease (June 20).</p>
        <p>Lea refers to the sinking of the Rebel privateer 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Alabama</title>(July 7); concern over
            Jubal Early's raid on Washington and Maryland, the price of
            gold, and the economy (July 10-14); ideas on marriage (July
            19 and 1865 August 21); opinions on the income tax, the
            restoration of the Union, Abraham Lincoln, and the death of
            Mrs. Kate Ward's nephew during the Ft. Pillow "Massacre"
            (July 21); the hopeful news from the battle of Mobile Bay
            and Atlanta, and concern over the Presidential election in
            the fall (August 9); Lea's ten day business trip to New
            England (1864 September 4-11); warning for Annie not to visit New
            York City in November on election day, as there may be
            violence and trouble (September 25); and mentions the capture of
            Savannah, Georgia (December 14). In one of the few letters to
            Annie Cabeen not from Lea, D.P. Heap, Engineer Camp, near
            Petersburg, Virginia, writes about the celebration over the
            capture of Atlanta and the earthworks around Petersburg
            (1864 September 4).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>Civil War Correspondence in 1865</head>
        <p>Lea goes on a business trip early in the year to textile
            mills in Massachusetts and Rhode Island (January 11-16); writes
            concerning his earlier capture and escape from the Rebel
            forces, brought to mind by meeting a fellow prisoner, John
            M. Sawhill (January 29); mentions friends attending the Purim
            Ball, an annual Jewish masquerade given at the Academy,
            remarking that he sells a large part of the store's goods
            to the Jews in New York (March 14); the premature report of
            Robert E. Lee's surrender to Ulysses S. Grant (April 7); with
            news of immediate peace, Lea hopes they can now be married
            in October and reports on his jury duty (April 11); discusses
            the effects of the death of Abraham Lincoln and the ending
            of the war (April 17, both letters, and 19, 20, &amp; 22);
            and describes a visit to the site of the former Fort
            Washington, on upper Manhattan Island, on the Hudson River
            (April 20).</p>
        <p>Lea reports on a letter received from Ned Bowen, who has
            been charged with treating his superior officer with
            disrespect after a "rupture" with Colonel H.T. Collis (May
            7); while in Massachusetts, he mentions his tour of their
            "braid mill" and the Pacific Mills, which employs 3,200
            operatives, chiefly girls (July 13); refers to the "Ketchum
            failure and forgeries" in New York City, involving over
            four million dollars (August 15); describes his visit with the
            Norris family from Baltimore, Maryland, "true blue
            Unionists," while they were in New York, describing Mrs.
            Norris as a woman who spent four and a half years feeding,
            clothing and nursing Union soldiers (August 21); shares the
            physical effects of the stress of business at the New York
            dry goods house (August 22); and spends the remainder of his
            correspondence discussing the buying and furnishing of
            their house and other preparations for their wedding in
            December.</p>
        <p>Following the marriage of Annie Cabeen and Joseph
            Tatnall Lea in December of 1865, most of the correspondence
            is from friends and family to the Leas and include the
            following topics: Lea's business trip to Chicago, Illinois,
            St. Louis, Missouri, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and Louisville,
            Kentucky (1866 April 18-29); the birth of a daughter,
            Roberta, to Annie and Joseph Lea (1866 October 26); a
            description of life in Dresden, Germany (1867 December 15); a
            description of Rome and Italy (1868 February 27); the birth of
            daughter, Florence, to Annie and Joseph Lea (1868 July 13);
            a description of life in Paris, France (1868 July 31); a
            reference to the wedding of Frank [Cabeen ?] (1879 September 24);
            and political events in Constantinople, Turkey and
            neighboring Greece (1879 September 24 &amp; 1881 March 5).</p>
        <p>The correspondence of Nancy (Lea) Marshall begins with
            letters written to her from family and friends while she is
            on a European tour, 1907, and continues with letters of
            congratulation and best wishes upon her engagement to Dr.
            Harry Taylor Marshall from friends, and love letters from
            Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall, written from the University of
            Virginia, while she is staying at The Aldine, Philadelphia,
            Pennsylvania, January-May 1911. Marshall's letters contain many
            references to his work at the University of Virginia during
            this period.</p>
        <p>They married on June 17, 1911, and their wedding
            photographs were done by Holsinger Studio (1911 June 25).
            Many of the letters following the wedding are from her
            mother, Annie C. Lea, when she is in Philadelphia, and her
            husband, Harry T. Marshall, when Nancy is away visiting her
            family in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Other letters refer to the death of her sister, Florence
            Lea Fletcher (1911 April); a description of Siena, Italy,
            and a recent earthquake there in September (1911 September 17;
            October 31); the birth of a son, Snowden (1912 September); the visit
            of the parents of Nancy Lea Marshall to the Grand Canyon,
            Arizona (1913 February 26 &amp; 28) and Pasadena, California
            (1913 March); an article by Marshall for the 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Alumni Bulletin</title>about
            introducing research into the medical school (1913 March 15);
            a crisis with the nursing staff at the University of
            Virginia (1913 April 5); the proposal to incorporate Preston
            Heights into the city of Charlottesville (1913 March 17); an
            English nurse visited Charlottesville asking for clothes
            and other items for soldiers in hospitals near Verdun,
            France (1916 March 8); the visit of University of Virginia
            alumni to "Bloomfield" during the Centennial celebrations
            (1921 June); the settlement of the A.C. Lea Estate (1921 June
            13; July 25; October 5, 10, 11, 13; November 26; and 1923 October 30);
            description of a world cruise aboard the 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">S.S. Resolute</title>, especially
            the island of Bali (1933 March 20); the birth of Polly's
            baby, Nancy (1947); and the engagement of Katherine Lea
            Marshall (1950).</p>
        <p>The correspondence of Dr. Harry Taylor Marshall begins
            with letters concerning his work with the United States
            Coast and Geodetic Survey in Maine and Massachusetts
            (1892-1894); and a trip to Canada by his friend, Ben Howell
            Griswold, Jr. of Baltimore, who is also his most frequent
            correspondent outside of the family and who often comments
            on the Baltimore social scene and Maryland politics (1897
            August).</p>
        <p>Other letters include: comments on and requests for his
            article on Christian Science (1899-1900); discussion of his
            work in Germany with Dr. Ehrlich by Dr. William H. Welch,
            editor of 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Journal of Experimental
            Medicine</title>and himself (1901 July 27 &amp; August 12; December
            27; 1902 May 18); the assassination of President William
            McKinley in Buffalo, New York (1901 September 7 &amp; 22); the
            controversies over the steel industry and the luncheon
            given by President Theodore Roosevelt for Booker T.
            Washington (1901 October 21); the New York elections, Tammany
            Hall, and the new election law passed in Maryland the
            previous year "with the purpose of disenfranchising the
            Negro" (1901 November 5); Admiral [W.S.] Schley trial before a
            Court of Inquiry (1901 October 21, 28; November 27; December 4, 18; 1902
            January 6); Supreme Court case involving the rights of citizens
            of the Philippines, Puerto Rico, and other possessions
            (1901 December 4); Andrew Carnegie's plans for education (1901
            December 11); the Nicaraguan v. the Panama Canal (1901 December 18;
            1902 January 29); and Guglielmo Marconi's claim to have
            successfully signaled a distance of 1,800 miles (1901 December
            18).</p>
        <p>Other topics include: the death of the father of Harry
            Taylor Marshall (1902 April 23, 28; May 9); his research trip
            out west to Montana and Colorado investigating "locoweed
            disease" in sheep and visit to Yellowstone Park (1903 September 9
            &amp; 20; October 18); Marshall's work in the Philippines (1907
            May 5); a trip to Maine (1907 August 27); Marshall recommended
            for the pathology professorship at the University of
            Virginia by Dr. Welch (1908 February 23; June 17 &amp; attached);
            Bishop C.H. Brent, Manila, Philippines (1909 September 8); and
            letters from Nancy Lea Marshall after their marriage while
            she visits in Philadelphia (1911 October-1913).</p>
        <p>The correspondence of Snowden Marshall include several
            letters describing post-World War II conditions in Berlin,
            Germany, especially the economic hardships in 1947.</p>
        <p>The correspondence of William Dimmock Buxton (1921- ?)
            begins with letters received while attending the University
            of Virginia in 1939. He earned two degrees while in
            Charlottesville, a B.A. (1942) and M.D. (1945), and later
            became an assistant professor of psychiatry at the
            University of Virginia Medical School. The majority of the
            letters during his college days are from family members and
            friends, especially Robert Winter Reese and Charles Kenton
            Matheny, both of whom joined the service during World War
            II. Other friends who write frequently include: Sherman A.
            Selden (joined U.S. Army Air Force), Sage Smith, Mark H.
            Congdon (joined Canadian Air Force), Virginia Chandler,
            C.D. West, Jean Marshall, A.J. Hyde, and Mary Byrd
            Butterworth.</p>
        <p>Topics include: the death of [his mother?] Elizabeth
            Buxton (1941 June); concern over Germany's invasion of
            Russia (1941 July 5); Buxton's 20th birthday (1941Oct 10);
            New Orleans during wartime (1942 March 15); Matheny as an
            aviation cadet at the U.S. Naval Air Station, Pensacola,
            Florida, Corpus Christi, Texas, Miami, Florida, and San
            Diego (1942 April 5, 17; August 9; October 17; 1943 January 27); ideas
            on instructing daughters (1942 May 11); U.S. Navy Lt.
            Edward ("Butch") O' Hare gave a speech at Pensacola,
            Florida (1942 May 15); sexual attitudes of the American
            soldier (1943 February 6); impressions of Italy (1944 June 8);
            comments on the "lost generation" (1944 July 21);
            congratulations on the engagement of Polly Marshall and
            William Dimmock Buxton (1944 June-September); transfer of William
            Dimmock Buxton to the National Medical Center, Bethesda,
            Maryland, and then to Norfolk, Virginia (1945 April 19; May
            15-17); and a review of the career of Sherman Shelden
            during his time in the service (1945 May 21).</p>
        <p>The folder of miscellaneous correspondence contains
            several typed transcripts of letters from an unidentified
            American soldier serving in a Scottish regiment during
            World War I (1917-1918).</p>
        <p>Identified carte-de-visite photographs in the collection
            (Boxes 19-20) listed by folder include the following names:
            in the 1st folder - Commodore James Alden, Julia P.
            [Aldershaul?], John C. Bigelow, Horace Binney, David A.
            Deaderick, David Farragut, Stephen Girard, Ulysses S.
            Grant, Lizzie Hacker, Charlie Heap, Emma Heap, G.H. Heap,
            G.H. Heap, Jr., Lena Heap, Nettie Heap, Porter Heap, Jr.,
            General [Erasmus Darwin?] Keyes, Annie &amp; Langdon Lea,
            James B. Leonard, Abraham Lincoln, Chief Justice John
            Marshall, George Gordon Meade, General Mitchell, Bobby
            Neilson, Vice Admiral David D. Porter, General Fitz John
            Porter, John Randolph of Roanoke, Robert Walsh, Bushrod
            Washington, Daniel Webster, Robert Wharton, Major Winthrop,
            Mrs. Wister &amp; Alice, and several of political
            "cartoons" concerning Civil War events and people.</p>
        <p>People identified in the 2nd folder of carte-de-visite
            photographs include: Mrs. Aulick, John Bessonet, George H.
            Boker, Emma A. Cabeen, Robert B. Cabeen, Sally W.
            Churchman, Mr. Corbit, Captain Crawford, George Davidson,
            [Mrs.?] Duhring, Miss Fisk, Louisa Gibbons, [Mrs.?]
            Gibbons, Eliza &amp; Joseph John Gurney, the Reverend J.
            Pinkney Hammond (Chaplain in the 19th Regiment of the
            Pennsylvania Volunteers), Miss Huntington, Draper Lewis,
            Julia Lodge, McAllister &amp; Brother, Opticians, Mr.
            McIntyre, Hannah Mifflin, Lloyd Mifflin, Miss Morris,
            Captain David D. Porter, General Fitz John Porter,
            Commodore W.D. Porter (with the naval battles involving the
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Essex</title>listed on the back)
            Mrs. S.P. Pusey, Mr. R.A. Rogers, Harris Heap Sharrer,
            Josephine Sharrer, [Mrs.?] Wharton, Bessie White, G. Irvine
            White, Maggie White, William Whitehead, and a group
            photograph of Horatio N. Beatty, R. Cabeen Beatty, Samuel
            Beatty, Kate Bostwick, Annie A. Cabeen, and Lilly U.
            Cabeen.</p>
        <p>None of the individuals are indentified in the 3rd
            folder of carte-de-visite photographs but they probably
            include many members of the Cabeen and Lea families, most
            having been taken in Philadelphia and Germantown
            studios.</p>
        <p>People identified in the 4th folder of carte-de-visite
            photographs include: John Quincy Adams, William Allen, Rosa
            Bonheur, Bishop Bowman, Charlotte Bronte, Princess
            Clotilde, James Fenimore Cooper, George M. Dallas, Millard
            Fillmore, John Hodgkin, William Hogarth, Bishop Hopkins,
            Henry Wadsworth Longfellow &amp; children , James Madison,
            Mrs. O'Sullivan, Tom Paine, John Howard Payne, Rembrandt
            Peale, Bishop Alonzo Potter, Peter Paul Rubens, John
            Sergeant, Zachary Taylor, Alfred, Lord Tennyson, John
            Tyler, the Union League House on Broad Street,
            Philadelphia, Martin Van Buren, Nicholas Waln, George
            Washington, and Benjamin West. Also present are examples of
            art, chiefly Madonna scenes, and humorous pictures of
            children and pets. Many of the photographs of earlier
            historical figures and paintings are actually photographs
            taken of engravings and other art forms.</p>
        <p>The three family photograph albums (Box 20) chiefly
            contain photographs of members of the Lea and Cabeen
            families and are often identified on the back.
            Miscellaneous photographs (Box 20) include: photographs of
            a trip to England, Joseph Tatnall Lea III, Ann Buckley Lea,
            photographs of places and buildings in Oxford, England
            (1914), Joseph Tatnall Lea, Kitty &amp; Nancy Lea, and Mrs.
            &amp; Mrs. Harry Taylor Marshall.</p>
      </scopecontent>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The correspondence in the collection follows a natural
         chronological order, which is preserved between the various
         interrelated family groups. There are basically two series: 1)
         Correspondence (Boxes 1-17) and 2) Miscellaneous Papers, Bound
         Volumes and Photographs (Boxes 18-22 &amp; Oversize Box
         P-25).</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e318">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1960,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1-17</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e326">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cabeen Family 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1859,
                  1861-1862</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e334">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Annie Cabeen and Joseph Tatnall
                  Lea</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1-6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>1862-1863 October (8 folders) 
                  <lb/>1863 November-1864 February (9 folders) 
                  <lb/>1864 March-August (8 folders) 
                  <lb/>1864 September-1865 February (8 folders) 
                  <lb/>1865 March-November (9 folders) 
                  <lb/>1865 November-December; 1866 (2 folders)</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>arranged chronologically</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e356">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cabeen and Lea families 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867-1890,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e366">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nancy Lea Marshall 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904-1960,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6-11</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>1904-1911 February (5 folders) 
                  <lb/>1911 March-December (7 folders) 
                  <lb/>1912 (5 folders) 
                  <lb/>1913-1914 April (6 folders) 
                  <lb/>1915-1950 (7 folders) 
                  <lb/>1951-1960, n.d. (4 folders)</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>arranged chronologically</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e390">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dr. Harry T. Marshall 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1914,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">11-14</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>1890-1900 (3 folders) 
                  <lb/>1901-1906 (6 folders) 
                  <lb/>1907-1913 March (7 folders) 
                  <lb/>1913 April-1914, n.d. (3 folders)</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>arranged chronologically</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e410">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H. Snowden Marshall 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946-1948,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e418">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Dimmock Buxton 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939-1945,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15-17</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>1941 August-1942 October (5 folders) 
                  <lb/>1942 November-1944 April (6 folders) 
                  <lb/>1944 May-1945, n.d. (5 folders)</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <arrangement>
            <p>arranged chronologically</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e436">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Dimmock Buxton, Charlotte Buxton,
                  and Julie [Buxton?], while at school 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1940-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e444">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908,
                  1917-1918</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e452">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers, Bound Volumes &amp;
               Photographs 
               <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1898-1965,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">18-Oversize
               P-25</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e460">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Address Cards &amp; Greeting Cards 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1898-1917,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e468">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Calling Cards &amp; Invitations 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1900-1920,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e476">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial Papers 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865-1926, 1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e486">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1906-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e494">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1897-1942,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>including poetry, identification documents for Dr.
                  Harry T. Marshall, school reports for Hudson Snowden
                  Marshall II, baptismal &amp; confirmation
                  certificates of William Meade Fletcher, Jr., and
                  other memorabilia</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e505">
          <did>
            <unittitle>News Clippings &amp; Printed Materials 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1942,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e513">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1921-1965,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re "Bloomfield," Ivy, Virginia, and Rugby Road,
                  Charlottesville, Virginia, Homes, chiefly
                  inventories</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e524">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cash Book kept by Dr. Harry T. Marshall 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e534">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book belonging to Nancy Lea
                  [Marshall] 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e544">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary of J. Tatnall Lea 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1865-1867</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e555">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Guest Register for "Bloomfield" 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1890-1891</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e565">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Guest Register for "Bloomfield" 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1910-1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Guest Register (chiefly) 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e585">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memoranda Books belonging to Dr. Harry T.
                  Marshall with notes on medical cases 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1897-1901</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e595">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memoranda Book 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e605">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memoranda Book belonging to Nancy Lea
                  Marshall 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1945-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e615">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memoranda Book belonging to Annie Cabeen
                  Lea 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e625">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook of Engravings belonging to Emma
                  Anderson Cabeen 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>due to size placed with larger photograph albums
                  in Box 22</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e638">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carte de Visite Photographs 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1860-1880,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>ca. 120 items</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e651">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carte de Visite Photographs 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1861-1871,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>158 items</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e664">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cabeen and Lea Family Photograph Albums 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864-1886,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e675">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Photographs (Loose) 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1914-1941,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e683">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album - "A Bloomfield
                  Retrospect 1896-1897" 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1896-1897</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e691">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Albums - "A Visit to
                  Bloomfield," Ivy, Virginia 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>numbered photographs in two albums</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e702">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album of Trips to Europe and
                  the American West 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>belonging to Dr. Harry T. Marshall ?</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e713">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album of the Marshall Family 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e721">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album of Vacations, and Hunting
                  &amp; Fishing Trips 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>belonging to the [Marshall ?] family</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e732">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook of Engravings belonging to Emma
                  Anderson Cabeen 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>placed here with photograph albums due to size</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e743">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album of "Bloomfield" belonging
                  to the Lea &amp; Marshall families 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e751">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Postcard &amp; Photograph Album of Dr.
                  Harry T. Marshall's Trip to the East 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1907</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>especially the Philippines, Egypt, &amp; China,
                  including a folder of loose postcards &amp;
                  photos</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e762">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album of the Marshall Family
                  and three large photographs of members of the
                  Marshall Family 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize Box" type="Oversize">
                  S-55</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
