<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04041">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04041::A Guide to the Papers of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., 1924, 1949–1950)//EN" "viu04041.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924,
                    1949–1950</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Stettinius, Edward R., Jr., Papers
                    <num type="collectionnumber">2723-z</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University
                    of Virginia. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924,
                1949-1950</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">2723-z</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924, 1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">2723-z</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">380 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector"/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no access restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no use restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., 1924, 1949-1950, Accession #2723-z, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisitions</head>
        <p>The collection was a gift from Cathy Zimmerman on August 24, 2008.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. (1900-1949), was an American industrialist and
                public servant and the Secretary of State in President Franklin Roosevelt's Cabinet.
                He was born in Chicago, Ill., on Oct. 2, 1900 to Edward Reilly and Judith
                (Carrington) Stettinius. His mother was a Virginian of colonial English ancestry and
                his father was of German descent, and a native of St. Louis who worked for
                financier, J. P. Morgan.</p>
      <p>Stettinius, Jr. received his education at the Pomfret School and the University of
                Virginia although he did not graduate. In 1924 he joined the General Motors Company
                as a stock clerk at 44 cents an hour. On May 15, 1926, he married Virginia Gordon
                Wallace, daughter of a prominent family of Richmond, Virginia. They had three
                children: Edward Reilly, and twins Wallace and Joseph. In 1931 he became Vice
                President in charge of public and industrial relations at General Motors. He worked
                to develop unemployment relief programs and came into contact with Franklin D.
                Roosevelt, for whom he worked briefly in the National Recovery Administration. In
                1934 he became chairman of the finance committee of the U.S. Steel Corporation, and
                in 1938 he became chairman of the board. Two years later he became head of the
                Lend-Lease aid to the allies, a position he held until he became undersecretary of
                state. In October 1943 Stettinius succeeded Cordell Hull as Secretary of State. In
                this capacity he undertook a reorganization of the department, sought to bring it
                into closer relations with other parts of the government, improved the relations of
                the department with the public at large, and labored vigorously in the creation of
                the United Nations. In the winter of 1945 Stettinius accompanied President Roosevelt
                to the Yalta Conference in the Crimea, at which the Big Three, Roosevelt, Winston
                Churchill of England, and Joseph Stalin of the U.S.S.R., attempted to plot the
                future course of international affairs.</p>
      <p>As Secretary, Stettinius made the decision to return a Russian codebook, found in
                Finland, to the Soviet Union. This hampered efforts of the United States to decode
                Russian cables, many of which, when later released, provided information about the
                widespread penetration of Soviet agents into senior United States Government
                positions. The reasons for this act are not clear. Soon afterward, Stettinius
                resigned as Secretary of State to become the first United States Ambassador to the
                United Nations. Stettinius resigned from this position in June 1946, after which he
                became critical of what he saw as Truman's refusal to use the United Nations as a
                tool to resolve tensions with the Soviet Union.</p>
      <p>For three years after his return to private life he served as rector of the
                University of Virginia. A longtime friend of William Tubman,, the president of
                Liberia, he helped form (1947) the Liberia Company, a partnership between the
                Liberian government and American financiers to provide funds for the development of
                that African nation. He lived during his retirement at his estate, Horseshoe Farm on
                the Rapidan River, Virginia. He died of a coronary thrombosis at the home of a
                sister in Greenwich, Connecticut, at the age of 49, and was buried in the family
                plot in Locust Valley Cemetery, Locust Valley, New York.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection contains condolences to Mrs. Stettinius on the death of her husband,
                Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr. and an address list for those who wrote the condolence
                letters. Among the many prominent writers are Bernard Baruch, Harry Byrd, Sr., James
                F. Byrnes, John Foster Dulles, William F. Halsey, J. Edgar Hoover, Cordell Hull,
                Trygve Lie, Archibald MacLeish, George C. Marshall, Eddie Rickenbacker, Eleanor
                Roosevelt (telegram), Adlai Stevenson, William V. Tubman, Henry A. Wallace and Earl
                Warren. Miscellaneous items include letters concerning a gift of stock to Sidney
                James Weinberg; news clippings, photographs, miscellaneous printed items,
                commemorative statements, bound volumes of memorial resolutions and a blueprint of
                his gravesite. There are also nine letters that Edward Stettinius wrote to his
                parents about his travels in 1924. The collection consists of approximately 380
                items, 2 Hollinger boxes, and one linear foot.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined" altrender="table">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="d1e162" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence Edward Stettinius Jr. to his parents
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1924]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          <physdesc>9 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e170" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Address lists of correspondents who wrote condolence letters to
                            Mrs. Edward Reilly Stettinius after her husband's death
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1949-1950]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e179" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Condolences received by Mrs. Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. (A-G)
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
          <physdesc>95 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include Dean Gooderham Acheson (1893-1971); Carl
                            Adams; Hafez Afifi; Henry Harley "Hap" Arnold (1886-1950),
                            General of the United States Air Force; Brigadier General Frank Albert
                            Allen, Jr. (1896-1979); American Consul General Stephen E.
                            Aguirre; Hamilton Fish Armstrong (1893-1973); I Gonzalez Arevalo,
                            Minister of Foreign Relations Guatemala; Warren Robinson Austin
                            (1877-1962), United States Ambassador to the United Nations;
                            Joseph W. Barron; Lucy M. Barringer; Claude Albert Barnett
                            (1889-1967) Founder of the Associated Negro Press; Eugenia Barton
                            and Harry Mason; D. M. Bates; Murray Reed Benedict (1892-1980),
                            President of the Agricultural Economics Association; John James Bennett
                            (1894-1967), New York State Attorney General; Right Honorable
                            Isaac Leslie Hore-Belisha (1893-1957), British Secretary of State
                            for War; Jules Basdevant (1877-1968), President of the
                            International Court of Justice ; Sir Carl August Berendsen
                            (1890-1973), Ambassador of New Zealand; Francis L. Berkeley, Jr.
                            (1911-2003) University of Virginia Archivist and Professor
                            Emeritus ; Scott B. Berkeley; Bernard Mannes Baruch (1870-1965),
                            United States financier, presidential advisor, and statesman; William S.
                            Bernard, Chairman of the War Industries Board; Charles Eustis "Chip"
                            Bohlen, (1904-1974), United States Diplomat; William Marshall
                            Boyle, Jr. (1902-1961) Chairman National Democratic Party; Otto
                            Brandt; Ellen and Jim Bruce (United States Ambassador to Argentina);
                            Barron Foster Black (1893-1974) and his wife Aileen Taylor Black;
                            Henri and Helle Bonnet; Isaiah Bowman 91878-1950), Director of
                            the American Geological Society; Arthur B. Van Buskirk; Senator Harry F.
                            Byrd (1887-1966); James F. Byrnes (1879-1972), Secretary
                            of State; Harry Clemons (1879-1968), Head, University of Virginia
                            Library; Frederic Ren?oudert, Jr.(1898-1972), Assistant United
                            States Attorney for New York; Madame de Chabrieres; Cliff Cobham; Rafael
                            De La Colina, Ambassador of Mexico and representative at the United
                            Nations; Mrs. Fairlie Patton Cooke; Oscar Cox; Colgate Whitehead Darden
                            Jr. (1897-1981), President, University of Virginia; Howard Brush
                            Dean (1918-1950) Vice President of Pan American World Airways;
                            Gabriel L. Dennis, Secretary of State of Liberia; William E. Dennis,
                            Secretary of the Treasury of Liberia; Marjorie Merriweather Post Davies
                            and Joseph E. Davies (1876-1958), United States Ambassador to the
                            Soviet Union; John William Davis (1873-1955), United States
                            Ambassador to the United Kingdom; Gayer G. Dominick; Justice William O.
                            Douglas (1898-1980); Cyro De Freitas-Valle, Secretary of the
                            Ministry of Foreign Affairs; Fleet Admiral William Frederick Halsey
                            (1882-1959); Lewis Williams Douglas(1885-1924), United
                            States Ambassador to the United Kingdom; William A. Drayton; John Foster
                            Dulles (1888-1959), United States Secretary of State; James
                            "Jimmy" Clement Dunn (1890-1979), United States Diplomat; John D.
                            East; Lewis Eldred, President of Elmira College; Helen W. Elting, The
                            English-Speaking Union; Frank S. Emmert; Louise Eriksen; James Aloysius
                            Farley (1888-1973), Postmaster General; Justice Felix Frankfurter
                            (1882-1965), Associate Justice of the Supreme Court and
                            newsclipping; W. L. Finger; Directors of Caribcemco; Harvey Samuel
                            Firestone, Jr. (1898-1973); Baron Oliver Shewell Franks
                            (1905-1992); John Gange, Chairman of the Woodrow Wilson School of
                            Foreign Affairs; Paul Garrett, Vice President of Public Relations for
                            General Motors Corporation; Bettis Alston Garside (1894-1989);
                            Mrs. John Minor Gatewood; [Gil] Gillespie; Albert Goldman, Postmaster of
                            New York; Reverend F. D. Goodwin and the Board of Virginia Theological
                            Seminary; John Gladston Grace, President of the International Press
                            Bureau; Julian Greenup, American Consul General; Mrs. William Gregg;
                            Joseph Clark Grew, United States Ambassador to Denmark.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e248" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Condolences received by Mrs. Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. (H-P)
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          <physdesc>90 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Edward and Dorothy Halifax; Cornelius A. Hall; [ William Averell
                            Harriman] (1891-1986), Governor of New York, Ambassador, and
                            United States Secretary of Commerce, and Marie Norton Whitney Harriman;
                            Joseph M. Hartfield; [Frank A. Hecht,] English-Speaking Union; General
                            Lewis Blaine Hershey (1893-1977), Director of the Selective
                            Service; Russell Hopkinson; John Edgar Hoover (1895-1972)
                            Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation; Cordell Hull
                            (1871-1955), Secretary of State; Patrick Jay Hurley
                            (1883-1963), Secretary of War; Jesse Holman Jones
                            (1874-1956), Secretary of Finance; N. D. [Dean] Jay; Jane B.
                            Kaynor; Vi Kyuin "Wellington" Koo (1887-1985), Chinese Foreign
                            Minister; Jaakko Kahma, General manager of the Finnish Foreign Trade
                            Association; The Baron of Kellie; Charles Franklin Kettering
                            (1876-1958), Scientist; Charles Dunbar Burgess King
                            (1875-1961), Ambassador of Liberia; Reverend Arthur B. Kinsolving
                            (1861-1951); James S. Knowlson; Mrs. Frank Knox; Shawn Kelly;
                            Reverend Paul H. Kratzig, Rector, St. Andrew's Episcopal Church; Sally
                            Cameron Labouisse; Louis St. Laurent (1882-1973), Prime Minister
                            of Canada; James E. Kinard, President of The Student Council at the
                            University of Virginia; Russell Cornell Leffingwell (1878-1960),
                            President of the Council on Foreign Relations and Lucy Leffingwell;
                            Egbert G. Leigh; Admiral Emory Scott "Jerry" Land, Chairman of the
                            Maritime Commission and Head of the War Shipping Administration ; Ed
                            Lincoln; Robert Lodge, Campaign Manager New York Heart Association;
                            Abercrombie Lovett (1895-1986); John David Lodge
                            (1903-1985); The Venerable Albert H. Lucas D. D.; Robert J. Lynch
                            (1902-1989), Executive in the Foreign Trade Industry; J. Malcolm
                            Luck; Trygve Halvdan Lie (1896-1968) Secretary-General of the
                            United Nations and Norweigan politician; Mrs. Lloyd Burlingham; R. J.
                            McDonald, Secretary of International General Electric Company; Archibald
                            MacLeish (1892-1982) Poet, Librarian of Congress, and Assistant
                            Secretary of State; General George Catlett Marshall (1880-1959)
                            Chief of Staff; James K. McClintock, Secretary for The American Red
                            Cross; John Jay McCloy (1895-1989), Presidential Advisor; Doris
                            M. McGovern; Frank McCarthy; Freeman Matthews (1899-1986) ,United
                            States Ambassador; Herbert A. May; Dr. Richard H. Meade, Jr.; Samuel
                            [W.] Meek; Richard King Mellon (1899-1970); Margery Knowles
                            Megargel, wife of Roy Chester Megargel, President of Gulf Texas and
                            Western Railroad and owner of Pepsi Cola; [Guillermo] Mendez, Minister
                            of Foreign Relations of Panama; General Sir Frederick Hoyer Millar
                            (1900-1989), British Diplomat; Francis P. Miller, Virginia Music
                            Festival; Edward G. Miller, Jr., Assistant Secretary of State for the
                            American Republics Area; Jim Mooney Henry Morgenthau, Jr.
                            (1891-1967) United States Secretary of the Treasury; Mauricio
                            Nabuco, Brazilian Ambassador; Richard Lewis Neuberger (1912-1960)
                            , United States journalist and politician; Minister of Luxenbourg,
                            Pierre Dupong (1885-1953); Caroline Preston Mordecai; Wilhelm
                            Morgenstierne, Norwegian Embassy; John E. Orchard; Pete O'Neill; Irving
                            Olds; Redvers Opie; C. F. Palmer; John Orlando Pastore
                            (1907-2000) , Governor of Rhode Island; J. W. Pearson Secretary
                            of Public Instruction of Liberia; Lester Bowles Pearson
                            (1897-1972), Prime Minister of Canada and Chairman of the
                            Political and Security Committee of the United Nations; John Emil
                            Peurifoy (1907-1955), Deputy Under Secretary of State and
                            Ambassador Extraordinary; Alice W. Phillips; Clementine Piltuck; John
                            Lee Pratt (1879-1975), American businessman; Max Preiswerk;
                            Edward A. Price, Jr. (1855-1934), City Attorney for Nashville,
                            Tennessee and President of the English-Speaking Union; F. A. Price,
                            Consulate General of Liberia</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e317" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Condolences received by Mrs. Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. (R-Z)
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          <physdesc>67 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Natale Ritacco; Hayden G. Raynor, Director, Office of British
                            Commonwealth and Northern European Affairs, U. S. State Department;
                            Philip D. Reed, Chief of United States Mission of Foreign Affairs in
                            London; Patrick J. Reilly; Florence Van Rensselaer (mentions her
                            genealogy book);General Richards; Edward Vernon Rickenbacker "Fast
                            Eddie" (1890-1973), American fighter ace in World War I, race car
                            driver and government consultant; Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller
                            (1908-1979); Carlos P. Romulo (1899-1985), President of
                            the United Nations General Assembly; Jack and Julia Rooney; Sir William
                            "Billy" Rootes (1894-1964) and his wife Nora; Telegram from
                            Eleanor Roosevelt; Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Jr.(1914-1988);
                            Lessing Julius Rosenwald (1891-1979), Chairman of Sears, Roebuck
                            and Company; John C. Ross, Deputy Representative of United Nations
                            Security Council; Mary de la Rue; Guillermo Sevilla-Sacasa
                            (1908-1997), Nicaraguan Ambassador to the United States; James
                            Arthur Salter (1881-1975), British politician and professor at
                            Oxford and wife Ethel Salter; Willie Sherwin; [Roth Sherill;] [Willie
                            Sherwin;] S. Silvercruys; A. Russell Slagle; Alfred Pritchard Sloan, Jr.
                            (1875-1966) Chairman and President of General Motors; Spyros P.
                            Skouras (1893-1971), movie executive for Twentieth Century Fox;
                            Blackwell "Blackie" Smith; Mrs. Tanquary Smith; Tse-ven Soong
                            (1894-1971) Chinese minister of finance and wife "Laura"; Kit and
                            Betty Stark; John Roy Steelman (1900-1999), Assistant to the
                            President of the United States, Harry S. Truman; Sir William Samuel
                            Stephenson (1896-1989), inventor, businessman and master spy
                            "Intrepid" and his wife Mary French Simmons; Whitney Stone; Jack Isidor
                            Strauss ( 1900-1985), Chief Executive Officer and Chairman of
                            Macy's Department Stores; Judge Edward Allen Tamm and Assistant Director
                            of the F. B. I. (1906-1985); Admiral Lewis Lichtenstein Strauss
                            (1896-1974 ), Chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission and his
                            wife Alice Hanauer Strauss; Myron Charles Taylor (1874-1959),
                            Chief executive officer and Chairman of the United States Steel
                            Corporation; Walter Clark Teagle (1878-1962), Head of Standard
                            Oil; Channing H. Tobias (1882-1961), Senior Secretary in the
                            Department of Interracial Services; Janine Terrill; Harry S. Truman
                            (1884-1972) (telegram); William Vacanarat Shadrach Tubman
                            (1895-1971), President of Liberia; William Munford Tuck
                            (1896-1983) Governor of Virginia; Grace G. Tully
                            (1900-1984), Secretary to President Franklin Delano Roosevelt;
                            James Thomson; W. W. Trench; Dr. Hugh H. Trout, M. D.; Terence Lloyd
                            Tyson, M. D.; J. E. Valenzuela, Minister of Foreign Relations; Mrs.
                            Cornelius "Grace" Vanderbilt; Robert Waithman, Washington correspondent
                            for the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">News Chronicle</title> of London; John
                            Scott and Marguerite Walker; Charles Montriou Wallace
                            (1866-1957), Attorney, Representative of the House of Delegates
                            and collected African American ballads; Henry Agard Wallace
                            (1888-1965) Vice President of the United States and his wife Ilo
                            Brown Wallace; Justice Earl Warren (1891-1974); Sidney B.
                            Congdon, President of The National City Bank of Cleveland to Charles E.
                            Wilson, President of General Electric; Lindsay Carter Warren
                            (1889-1976), Comptroller General of the United States; Thomas
                            John Watson (1874-1956), President of IBM; Mrs. W. B. Waugh;
                            Elizabeth W. Weddell; Sidney James Weinberg (1891-1969),"Mr.
                            Wallstreet;" Miss Ada R. Woods; Amelie Young; Alexander C. Zabriskie</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e381" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial correspondence from Sidney James Weinberg
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949 November 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included is a letter from attorney John Marsh from Mr. Stettinius's
                            estate concerning one thousand shares of common stock of the World
                            Commerce Corporation that Stettinius left for Mr. Weinberg in return for
                            his advice to Stettinius in business affairs. There is also a letter
                            from Mr. Weinberg declining the gift from Stettinius. There is a letter
                            from John Marsh to Mrs. Stettinius about insurance and her husband's
                            estate.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e398" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>News clippings Edward R. Stettinius Jr.
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
          <physdesc>18 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>including articles taken from his scrapbook</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e409" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>News clippings Edward R. Stettinius
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
          <physdesc>43 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e417" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>News clippings Edward R. Stettinius Jr.
                                <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
          <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e425" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photographs <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1910]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
          <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Two photographs of Edward Stettinius as a boy and two oversize
                            photographs of him sitting at his desk</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e436" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
          <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Program for the United Nations Conference in Staten Island June 26, 1950
                            with charter and blueprint; <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">English-Speaking
                                Union Bulletin</title> Volume 9, Number 2; 1949 and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Saturday Review of Literature</title> November 19,
                            1949 containing a review by Walter Johnson of Stettinius's book, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Roosevelt and the Russians; Words of Comfort
                                booklet; The Second Mile</title> by Harry Emerson Fosdick and a
                            blank University of Virginia greeting card with a Serpentine wall.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e453" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Statements of Admiration <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
          <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e460" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Three bound volumes of memorial resolutions for Edward R. Stettinius,
                        Jr., two are printed on vellum and all three are printed in beautiful
                        calligraphy.</unittitle>
          <container label="Volume" type="volume"/>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e468" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Oversize</unittitle>
          <container label="Oversize" type="oversize"/>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>One blueprint of the gravesite of Edward R. Stettinius</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
