<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03909">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03909::Letters of North Carolina families)//EN" "viu03909.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of North Carolina families, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1914 (bulk 1813-1896)</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">North Carolina families, Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">1030
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7/28/2005 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of North Carolina families, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1914 (bulk 1813-1896)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">1030
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Letters of North Carolina families
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1914 (bulk 1813-1896)
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">1030
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">100 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Letters of North Carolina families, Accession #1030, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The collection was purchased by the Library from Paul Ashburn of McKee Pontiac Company, Washington, D. C., on January 8, 1941.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains 100 letters, 1813-1896 and 1914, dealing with a wide variety of issues, including family life, agriculture, slavery, finances, religion, education, and politics, especially in North
Carolina, but also in South Carolina, Alabama, Georgia, Kentucky, Tennessee, Ohio, Florida, Maryland, and Pennsylvania.
</p>
      <p>The three chief areas of North Carolina represented are: Salem, Forsyth County; Germantown, Stokes County; and, Huntsville, Surry County. For more on Stokes and Forsyth counties and their histories and
families, please see the two editions of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Forsyth, A County on the March</title> (The University of North Carolina Press: Chapel Hill), 1949, by Adelaide Fries, and 1976, by Adelaide Fries,
Stuart Thurman Wright, and J. Edwin Hendricks, contributors. The following are excerpts from the 1976 edition's chapter entitled "The Formation of Forsyth County and the Founding of Winston":
</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>The story of Richmond Town was dramatic and short, for the 1789 Surry County was divided by a north-south line, and new courthouse sites were selected--Rockford in Surry County and Germanton in Stokes County.
The Surry County courthouse records were removed from old Richmond to Rockford; Stokes County set up new records on her own account. The area now called Forsyth was mostly in the new county of Stokes, but straight
lines were still the custom, and the new line crossed and recrossed the Yadkin in an annoying fashion. As a result, Stokes had a long narrow strip west of the river on the Surry side; Surry had a C-shaped tract
east of the river in the part of Rowan which became Davie County. In each case these detached pieces could be reached only by boat, for there were no bridges.
</p>
        <p>In December 1796 the assembly changed the line between Surry and Stokes, giving to Surry the long narrow strip lying on the west side of the Yadkin, the river becoming the boundary there. The Act of Assembly
calls in the land "south of the Yadkin," but old deeds show that for many years everything on the righthand bank of the Yadkin River, looking downstream, was called "south" of the Yadkin, regardless of the actual
direction.
</p>
        <p>For fifty years the county of Stokes remained practically unchanged. The War of 1812 and the Mexican War made but slight demand upon the people, though the former called the attention of the nation to Colonel
Benjamin Forsyth. The population increased slowly, but it did increase, and finally the General Assembly of 1848-1849 was petitioned to divide it. The act dividing Stokes County bears the ratification date 16
January 1849, and it printed in full in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Laws of the State of North Carolina passed by the General Assembly at the Session of 1848-1849,</title> published at Raleigh in 1849 by Thomas J.
Lemay, Printer, Star Office.
</p>
        <p>The act provided for a line "beginning at the South West corner of Rockingham county, and running thence West to the Surry county line." It was further enacted "that all that part of the said county lying North
of said line, shall be erected into a distinct county by the name of Stokes county; and all that part lying South of the said line shall be erected into another distinct county by the name of Forsyth county, in
honor of the memory of Northern frontier, in the late war with England." A supplemental act, passed at the same session of the assembly, appointed Caleb Jones, Frederick Meinung, and John Banner to run the
dividing line, named county commissioners for each county, and provided the necessary machinery for setting up the two county governments. The commissioners for Forsyth County were Zadock Stafford, John Stafford,
Henry A. Lemly, Leonard Conrad, and Francis Fries, who was elected chairman.
</p>
        <p>After the formation of the new county and the naming of her commissioners, it became necessary to select and purchase a site for the county seat; a courthouse and public building had to be erected as soon as
possible. Because Salem was located almost at the center of Forsyth, it seemed apparent to the commissioners that they would have to choose land in that neighborhood.
</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Papers of Forsyth County are chiefly concerned with the Van Vleck and related Blickensderfer and Fries families, and describe life, religion, and education in Salem, Forsyth County (formerly in Stokes County),
North Carolina; Dover, Ohio; and Bethlehem and Nazareth, Pennsylvania. Information on the inhabitants of the county and its history may be found in the multi-volumed <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Records of the Moravians
in North Carolina,</title> particularly Volumes IX (1838-1847) and X (1841-1851). Each volume contains its own index of persons and places. There are numerous mentions of Francis [nee Franz Levin] Fries during the
years 1838-1851, with a detailed record, 1848, of his requests to build cotton and woolen mills as well as buildings and additions, and land transactions; and, there are several mentions of Arthur Van Vleck during
1849-1850. Correspondence of the widow of Carl A. Van Vleck, Christina Susanna (Kramsch) Van Vleck, and her children, Amelia Adelaide, Arthur Lawrence, Lisetta Maria, and Louisa Cornelia, discusses family,
education, religion, travel, and the mission service during 1849 of Arthur. According to the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Moravian Records,</title> in 1846 an appointment was offered to Arthur Van Vleck in Greeneville,
Tennessee, to serve as teacher at Nazareth Hall, [Pennsylvania]; the family arrived in Salem on the following fifteenth. Records for 1849 indicate that the Wachovia Provincial Helfer Conferenz in Salem recommended
Arthur Lawrence Van Vleck for service in a mission school; and, in April 1849 he was called to serve as assistant missionary and assistant teacher at Saron on Barbadoes. In 1850, the records report:
</p>
      <blockquote>
        <p>...that the mission conference in Barbadoes had unanimously expressed <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">this</title> opinion, that the Single Br. Arthur L. Van Vleck was <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">not</title> suited for
mission service, for which reason the U. A. C. had advised his return to North America. It further commends him both to the P. H. C. at this place and to the Pennsylvania P. H. C. for employment as a home
missionary or in some other way.
</p>
        <p>The P. H. C. at this place wholeheartedly regrets that the attempt to place Br. Arthur Van Vleck in the West Indies has failed but considers itself unable to use him in the congregations of this district or in
our home missionary undertaking.
</p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>There are several letters, 1848-1852, from Francis Fries to his wife Lizetta (Vogler) Fries, from areas in South Carolina and North Carolina; these are chiefly personal.
</p>
      <p>Francis Fries (17 October 1812 - 1 August 1863) was descended from an old German family, which in the eighteenth century turned from war and court life to trade. His grandfather, Peter Konrad Fries, studied
theology at Strasbourg and received his Ph.D. in 1741; in 1758 he joined the Unitas Fratrum (Moravian Church), later becoming a member of the Unity's Elders' Conference and holding important posts in this
religious fellowship. His paternal grandmother was Christiane Jaschke, the daughter of a Moravian exile. His father, John William Fries, after receiving a Moravian education in Europe, came to the United States
and settled in the Moravian colony of Wachovia (later Salem), where he married Elizabeth Nissen. Although his parents wished for Francis to become a minister and sent him to the Moravian seminary, Nazareth Hall,
Pennsylvania, he decided against the ministry. After returning home, he taught for a while and then read law with Emanuel Shober and entered practice, soon being appointed clerk of the court and master in equity.
</p>
      <p>Fries' business career began when as agent of the new Salem [cotton] Manufacturing Company, he visited Paterson, New Jersey, and other northern points to purchase machinery, which in 1836 he installed in a
factory building erected after his own plans. In 1838 [May 24] he married Lizetta Vogler, by whom he had seven children [including Caroline Louise, John William, and Mary Elisabeth]. Two years later, with the
assistance of his father-in-law, he commenced woolen manufacture; at first he operated only cards for making rolls of the wool brought in by farmers, and set up a little dyeing and fulling mill for finishing cloth
woven in the homes of the countryside. Being successful in these enterprises, in 1842 he installed spinning machinery, and then looms. He was encouraged in manufacturing by his friend Edwin M. Holt of Alamance,
with whom he made arrangements to make alternate information-gathering trips to the North to study developments in the older textile centers, afterward sharing their information. The South manufactured very little
at this time, but the tradition of the Moravians in North Carolina was one of mechanical enterprise, and Fries did more than any one else to foster this spirit. His brother, Henry W. Fries, was taken into
partnership in 1846; two years later they built a cotton factory which was conducted until 1880, when it was dismantled and became part of the woolen mill.
</p>
      <p>Fries was involved in other endeavors. As a member of the legislature in 1857 he gave special attention to revising the state system of taxation. He was an architect, who designed the court-house for the new
county of Forsyth and the main building for the Salem Female Academy, of which institution he was a principal supporter. He was also mayor of Salem. He was a promotor of the plank road from Fayetteville to western
North Carolina and was associated with Governor John M. Morehead in building the North Carolina Railroad, in which he was a director until his death. Fries built a tannery, conducted a store, and was one in a
small but important group which sought vainly to implant industry in the agricultural ante-bellum South. [from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dictionary of American Biography,</title> Volume VII (Charles Scribner's
Sons: New York), 1931]
</p>
      <p>Papers of Stokes County contain chiefly letters addressed to Hampton Bynum from John H. Farmer in Bowling Green and Russellville, Kentucky, and others. Farmer writes of financial matters and land purchases and
settlements in Kentucky. There is also a letter from John Gray Bynum, Columbia, South Carolina, concerning the selling of slaves and personal finance issues of this attorney. There are also two letters from C. M.
Pepper to his father, John Pepper, concerning his education in Emory and the literary society (9 April 1851), and his preaching circuit and religion (25 May 1853). Letters, 1843-1849, addressed to John Hill (9
April 1797 - 24 April 1861), Clerk of Stokes County Court, concern financial matters; and, a request, July 2, 1849, from John A[dams] Gilmer (4 November 1805 - 14 May 1868), state senator, for a female prisoner,
Jane Hill, to be given the right to take the "insolvent debtor's oath."
</p>
      <p>The letters of Huntsville, Surry County, North Carolina, are chiefly from Isaac Jarratt in various cities in Alabama, to his wife, Harriet A. Jarratt. These letters contain personal content from a husband to
his wife as well as advice and/or news of the family "negroes" and farm, and life in Alabama.
</p>
      <p>Papers of other counties of North Carolina include a variety of correspondents and topics. An interesting letter of May 30, 1838, was written by George D. Phillips, Clarksville, Georgia, to Maj. Thomas B.
Cooper, Jefferson, Cherokee County, Alabama, concerning the escapades of a slave named "George," trouble between Indians and U. S. troops, and frost damage to crops. There is also an interesting letter, November
1, 1841, from Elijah [ ], Yazoo County, to Andrew McCants, Union Post Office, Georgia, describing travels through Mississippi, western Tennessee, Arkansas, and Louisiana, with a lively discussion of the city of
New Orleans. There is a letter, June 28, 1865, from H[enry] P[arker] Sartwell (18 April 1792 - 15 November 1867), physician and botanist, writing about impending botany publications by prominent botanists.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e182">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Salem, Forsyth County, North Carolina
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e186">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Benjamin G. Walz, Baltimore, Maryland, to Rev. [William Henry] Van Vleck, Minister of the Moravian Congregation: [letter in German].
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Sep 21;
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>[William Henry Van Vleck (14 November 1790 - 19 January 1953) of Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, was a Moravian Bishop]
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e196">
          <did>
            <unittitle>American Tract Society to Theodore Schulz, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: religious publications.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Apr 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e203">
          <did>
            <unittitle>American Tract Society to John Vogler, Treasurer, Tract Society, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: religious publications.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Aug 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e210">
          <did>
            <unittitle>E[dmund] S[amuel] Zevely, near Middleburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, to J[ohanna] Sophia Zevely, Salem, Stokes County, North Carolina: personal and family news; the family farm in Charlotte, North
Carolina.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 Sep 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e217">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Cordelia [Levers?], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck, Greeneville, Green County, Tennessee: personal news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 Oct 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e224">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: description of travel to Zoar, Bolivar, Ports Station, and Tuscarawas River, Ohio; history of the "Indian Dancing Ground," personal
and family issues.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 Jul 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e231">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[C. D.] Williams, Greeneville, Tennessee, to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: medical--bilious attack; news of friends in Greeneville, Tennessee; personal news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 Aug 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e238">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck: personal and family news; lengthy description of trip to Zoar for Sunday religious meeting of "Pappy" [Joseph
Michael] Bimeler (ca. 1778-1853), founder of the community of Zoar.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 Nov 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e245">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hannah [ ], "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Louisa [Cornelia] Van Vleck: education, teaching school children at a "select school" at Dover, Ohio.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 Jun 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e252">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary C. Poindexter, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; relations in Ireland.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Feb 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e260">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F[rancis] Fries, Camden, South Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries: personal and family news; return trip from Georgia and stay at Col. James Chesnut's.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Jul 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e267">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: medical pains; personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Dec 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e274">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta M[aria] Van Vleck: personal and family news; mission life and diplomatic service of Arthur Van Vleck.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Jun 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e281">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J[acob] and L[ouisa] C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta [Maria] Van Vleck: illness; domestic issues; and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Sep 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e288">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Arthur Van Vleck], Sharon, Pennsylvania, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: mission teachers and mission life in Sharon, Pennsylvania; "African character" and the effect of "firmness."
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Sep 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e295">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[ ], Dover, Ohio, to her sister Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; mission work.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Sep 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e302">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Lisetta Maria Van Vleck: personal and family news; Whig party.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Nov 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e309">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C. D. [Williams], Greeneville, Tennessee, to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: Episcopal Church congregation in Greeneville, Tennessee; personal and family news; marriage of Robert Barton and Hannah
McFarland.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Dec 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e316">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jacob Blickensderfer and Louisa [C. Blickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Mrs. C[hristina] S[usanna] Van Vleck: Arthur Van Vleck's journey to Bridgetown, Barbadoes; conflict between Postmaster Sandford
Shultz and Jacob Blickensderfer.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1849] Dec 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e323">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Louisa C. B[lickensderfer], Dover, Ohio, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: personal and family news; illness and deaths of Charles Blickensderfer; life at "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Jan 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e330">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F[rancis] [Fries], Pattonsburg to "Lizzie" [Lizetta (Vogler) Fries]: personal.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Apr 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e338">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Harry [ ], Nazareth, Pennsylvania, to Lisetta [Maria] Van Vleck: "wife searching expedition" of Edwin Reinke; work on the new school house in Nazareth, Pennsylvania.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 May 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e345">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Letty" [Lisetta Maria Van Vleck?], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck: travel to Petersburg, Richmond, and Mount Vernon, Virginia, and back to
Pennsylvania [with letter of June 5, 1851].
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Jun 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e352">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jacob Blickensderfer, "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: family life at "Bignonia," Dover, Ohio; personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Aug 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e359">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F[rancis] Fries, Henderson, North Carolina, to "Dear Lisetta" [Lizetta (Vogler) Fries], addressed to Emma A[ntoinette (Reich)] Vogler: paper mill in Henderson, North Carolina.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Aug 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e366">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C[hristina] S[usanna] V[an] V[leck], on Cape Fear River, North Carolina, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C. Van Vleck: personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jun 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e373">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F[rancis] Fries, Salem, North Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries, City Hotel, Philadelphia: personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jun 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e380">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lisetta [Maria Van Vleck], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa and Amelia," addressed to Louisa C. Van Vleck: personal and family news; improvements in Bethlehem, Pennsylvania.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Jun 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e387">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry [W. Fries], Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to "Louisa," addressed to Mrs. Christina S[usanna] Van Vleck: personal and family news; Arthur Van Vleck's impending return; students being pleased at
Nazareth, Pennsylvania.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Aug 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e394">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F[rancis] Fries, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Lisette (Vogler) Fries: personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Feb 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e401">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Aggie," Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: personal and family news; description of landscape in travels in Fayetteville [ ? ] and Portsmouth [ ? ].
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 May 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e408">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Louisa C[ornelia] Van Vleck, to Mrs. C[hristina] S. Van Vleck, Bethlehem, Northampton County, Pennsylvania: Bethlehem Female Academy; personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 Jul-Aug
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e416">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Aggie," Berthelsdorf, Germany, to Amelia A[delaide] Van Vleck: life in Germany; description of area in Berthelsdorf, Germany; description of young ladies there; education and religion in Germany.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 Nov 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e423">
          <did>
            <unittitle>M[ ] [Fries?], Salisbury, North Carolina, to parents Mr. and Mrs. H[enry] E. Fries, Winston-Salem, North Carolina: "good looking men...also some flossed up lassies" on their train.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 Jun 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e430">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e434">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H. and I. McRae and Company, to Mr. R. D. Golding, Germantown, North Carolina: order and account for sundry items.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 Jan 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e441">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure (1807-1883), Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: financial issues; crops, including cotton.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Sep 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e448">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Bowling Green, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: financial.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Oct 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e455">
          <did>
            <unittitle>N. G. Martin, Montgomery, Alabama, to Hampton Bynum: cotton not selling because of low river; selling of slaves; banking issues; nomination of [William Henry] Harrison (1773-1841) for President and the
Whig party.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 Jan 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e462">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure, Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: family estate settlement.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 Feb 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e469">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky to Hampton Bynum: land purchases in Russellville, Kentucky.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 Feb 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e476">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky to Hampton Bynum: business issues; land purchase in Kentucky.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Feb 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e483">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Collins Joseph, Comptroller, to John Hill, Stokes County, North Carolina: financial statement.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 Oct 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e490">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J[ohn] M[cPherson] DeSaussure, Camden, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: estate settlement.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 Apr 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e497">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: personal.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 May 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e505">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: financial.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 Jun 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e512">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John H. Farmer, Russellville, Kentucky, to Hampton Bynum: land settlement near Bowling Green, Kentucky; land and crop prices.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 Jul 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e519">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Huske, Fayetteville, North Carolina, to John Hill, Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina: financial.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 Nov 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e526">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Gray Bynum, Columbia, South Carolina, to Hampton Bynum: selling of slaves; financial issues of John Gray Bynum, attorney.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Mar 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e533">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. D. Scales, Aberdeen, Mississippi, to John Hill, Clerk of C[ounty] C[ourt], Germantown, Stokes County, North Carolina
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Mar 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e540">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John A. Gilmer, Greensboro, North Carolina, to Jailer of Stokes County and John G. Hill, Sheriff, Germantown, North Carolina: requesting that Jane Hill, prisoner be given the right to take the
"insolvent debtor's oath."
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Jul 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e547">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C. M. Pepper, Emory, Virginia, to his father [John Pepper, Germantown, North Carolina]: education in Emory, Virginia; literary society news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Apr 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e554">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C. M. Pepper, "Smithville," to his father John Pepper, Germantown, North Carolina: his preaching circuit and hopes for holding a high position in the [North Carolina] Conference; comments on religion
and the Bible; collecting sea shells and curiosities.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 May 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e561">
          <did>
            <unittitle>B. H. Bynum, [Salisbury &amp; Asheville, North Carolina], to W. H. Bynum: personal and financial news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878 Dec 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e568">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Wade H. Bynum, Winston, North Carolina, to Mrs. C. H. Bynum: personal.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883 Sep 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, Winston, North Carolina, to Wade H. Bynum: taxes on hunting property.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1896 Jan 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e582">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Huntsville, Surry County, North Carolina
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e586">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac Jarratt, Montgomery, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt, Quincy, Gadsden County, Florida: daily life in Montgomery, Alabama.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Feb 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e593">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac Jarratt, Montgomery, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: love and dedication of husband to wife and son; selling of slaves; "Sandy"--last negro sold; wanting to bring "Patty" and other negroes home;
debts; closing business in Montgomery, Alabama and Florida; Chattahoochee River so low steamboats can't run.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Jan 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e600">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac Jarratt, Greensboro, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: slave prices; "Silvy's" escape and return; advice on obtaining a female negro as a cook; mentions "Mary" and "Flora"; instructions for work on
plantation during winter; farming and cotton in Greensboro, Alabama.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Dec 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e607">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac Jarratt, Sumter, Alabama, to Harriet A. Jarratt: not letting negroes be idle; "Mary" and "Eliza"; slave prices; trouble with "Hunter."
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Mar 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e614">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas A. Cash, "Vallencia," Ash County, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 Oct 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e621">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: Indian problems in Wilmington; travel to Boston; personal and family news; medical--leeching.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 Jun 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e628">
          <did>
            <unittitle>M. Gibson, to Harriet A. Jarratt: life in Florida; personal and family news; whooping cough and death among young negroes.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 Oct 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e635">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isaac R. Harris, Quincy, [Gadsden County, Florida], to Isaac Jarratt: prices for hiring negroes next year.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Nov 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e642">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news; medical--whooping cough and scarlet fever.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 May 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e649">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 Sep 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e657">
          <did>
            <unittitle>T[homas] A. Cash, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to "Dear Mother" [Harriet A. Jarratt]: personal and financial issues.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864 Jan 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e664">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Smith, Wilmington, North Carolina, to Harriet A. Jarratt: personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.y. Nov 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e671">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV: North Carolina Counties General,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1849
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e678">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John M. Gordon, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Benjamin James Harris, Richmond, Virginia: power of attorney from John Bullock.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 Feb 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e685">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H. Potter, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Gen. Samuel Simpson, Fort Barnwill, Craven County, North Carolina: seeking debt payment.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 Jan 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e692">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James B. Hamilton to Andrew McCants, Union, Talbot County, Georgia: payment on goods.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Jan 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e699">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C. Dewey, Bank of the State of North Carolina, to James G. Stanley, Newbern, North Carolina: clearance of debt.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Jun 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e706">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John and Mary Walker, Fairfield District, South Carolina, to Andrew McCants, Talbot County, Union Post Office, Georgia: crops, cotton and corn prices.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Dec 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e713">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George D. Phillips, Clarksville, Georgia, to Maj. Thomas B. Cooper, Jefferson, Cherokee County, Alabama: attempt on the life of the overseer by "one of his negro fellows" named "George," history of the
life and recent activities of "George," request for knowledge of "George's" whereabouts; financial matters with William Elliott and others; news of trouble between Indians and U. S. troops, with three companies
from his county and a company of volunteers, minute men ("Silver Greys") consisting of 100 men under Captain James Brannon; frost damage to corn and cotton crops.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 May 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e720">
          <did>
            <unittitle>D. W. Counts, Public Treasurer, Treasury Department, Newbern, North Carolina to J[ohn G. S[tanley], Clerk of the County Court of Craven, Newbern, North Carolina: land assessment in Craven County, North
Carolina.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Sep/Oct 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e727">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H. Hubbard, LaGrange, [Illinois], to R. M. Hubbard, Niagara Company, Lockport, New York: wheat harvest; Canaal Bank closing; land grants and settlements; description and prospects for the LaGrange area;
prices of wheat, corn, oats, and potatoes in Milwaukee,[Wisconsin], as well as the price of cattle and hogs.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 Jul 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e734">
          <did>
            <unittitle>M. A. Marshall and E. W. Marshall, Gaston, Alabama, to Andrew McCants, Daviston, Talbot County, Georgia: cotton harvest, corn crops in area; slave trade; contested elections.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 May 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e741">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Elijah [ ], Yazoo County, Mississippi, to Andrew McCants, Union Post Office, Georgia: contagious diseases, such as yellow fever, in area; description of travels through Mississippi, western Tennessee,
Arkansas, and Louisiana; lively discussion of the city of New Orleans and its inhabitants and their activities.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Nov 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e749">
          <did>
            <unittitle>J. L. Winfield, Brownsville, Tennessee, to Mayor Robert Hairston, Columbus, Mississippi: advice on land in Tennessee owned by Hairston.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 Apr 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e756">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Hill, Raleigh, North Carolina, to James G. Stanley, Newbern, North Carolina: sending a copy of the record of the grant to John Hill.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Apr 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e763">
          <did>
            <unittitle>O. E. Pike, Montevallo, Alabama: re G. W. Johnson, of Farmington, North Carolina, leaving Shelby County, Alabama.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Jul 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e770">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series V: North Carolina Counties General,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1878
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e777">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John B. Doggett, Monticello, Jefferson County, [ ], to John Tillory, Halifax Town, Halifax County, North Carolina: request to his brother to come west and accompany him back east because of ill health.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 Mar 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e784">
          <did>
            <unittitle>N. S. W., to "Nellie": personal and friendly.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 Jan 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e791">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Sicilie T. House, to her cousin: quilting; personal and family news.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 Jan 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e798">
          <did>
            <unittitle>N. G. Hamilton, Clay County, Georgia, to J. W. McCants: personal news; crops doing well; religious meetings and weddings.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856 Aug 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e805">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H[ilary] G[oode] Richardson, Haymarket, Virginia, to John R. Raine, Wentworth, Rockingham County, North Carolina: in the "midst of a bloody war with Lincoln &amp; his Black Republican horde"; North
Carolina being "one of the bright stars of the So. Confederacy"; much on conflict between states.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 May 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e812">
          <did>
            <unittitle>T. C. Hauser, Gadkin County, North Carolina: declaration of ownership of one male slave between ages of 15 and 50 named "Dan," and another hired temporarily between ages of 35 and 40; and the fact that
"Dan" has rheumatism.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863 Oct
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e819">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[ ], Bladen County, North Carolina, to Kate McGeachy: personal and family news of adolescent.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864 Jul 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e826">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Addie?], to J. J. McCants: personal and family news; thoughts on General [Robert E.] Lee never giving up Richmond.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865 Mar 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e833">
          <did>
            <unittitle>H[enry] P[arker] Sartwell, Penn Yan, New York, to Dr. Easley: impending botany publications by [Asa] Gray (1810-1888) and others.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865 Jun 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e840">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jimmy J. Whittle, Cusseta, Georgia, to J. J. "Jack" McCants: personal news written to an old friend and school mate; dating women.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 Feb 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e848">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Jimmy J. Whittle, Cusseta, Georgia, to J. J. "Jack" McCants: personal; thoughts on marriage.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1867 May 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e855">
          <did>
            <unittitle>F. D. C., Castleton, Vermont, to Camilla A. Clingman: life of a medical student at school in Castleton, Vermont.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1878 May 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e862">
          <did>
            <unittitle>R. H. Dudley to N. K. Trout, Staunton, Virginia: financial matters.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
