<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03688">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu03688:: Journal of John Reuben Thompson )//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03688.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu03688:: Journal of John Reuben
             Thompson )//EN" "viu03688.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Journal of John Reuben Thompson
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Thompson, John Reuben, Journal of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3400-e</num></subtitle><author>Mitzi Clark</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia
            Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2003 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 27.5 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Sharon Defibaugh, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 29, 2003</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-23" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 23, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU:: viu03688:: Journal of
            John Reuben Thompson )//EN" "viu03688.xml" converted from
            EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Journal of John Reuben Thompson 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>Special Collections 
         <lb/>The University of Virginia Library 
         <num type="Accession Number">3400-e</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Journal of John Reuben Thompson 
         <unitdate label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3400-e</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of a single bound volume.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Journal of John Reuben Thompson, Accession 3400-e ,
            Special Collections, University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This item, originally on loan in April, 1950, was given
            to the University of Virginia Library on June 6, 1977, by
            D. Tennant Bryan, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>John Reuben Thompson (1823-1873) was an editor, poet and
         journalist who was born in Richmond, Va., October 23, 1823,
         the son of John and Sarah (Dyckman) Thompson. He attended the
         University of Virginia, 1840- 1842 and received an LL.B. there
         in 1845. He was the owner of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Literary Messenger</title>, 1847-1853,
         editor, 1853-60, which published works of leading Southern
         writers. He was editor of the weekly publication 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Southern Field and Fireside</title>,
         1860-1861; Assistant Secretary of the Commonwealth of
         Virginia, 1861-1864, and helped edit the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Record and Illustrated
         News</title>.</p>
      <p>In 1864-1865, he was the chief writer for the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Index</title>, (organ of Confederate
         opinion in England). He prepared 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Memoirs of the Confederate War for
         Independence</title>. for Blackwood's 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Edinburgh Magazine</title>, 1855-1856.
         He returned to the U.S. in 1866 as American correspondent for 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The London Standard</title>. Thompson
         was appointed by William Cullen Bryant to the literary
         editorship of the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Evening Post</title>,
         1867-1873. He died in New York City, April 30, 1873, and is
         buried in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The journal of John R. Thompson begins on February 29,
         1864. Excerpts of his journal which he kept during the year
         1864 were written while he was in Richmond (March through
         June), and traveling in England, Ireland, Scotland and France
         (July through December).</p>
      <p>On March 1, he notes that there has been a cavalry raid by
         the enemy within three miles of Richmond, with vandals
         shelling the dwelling house of James Lyons on the Brooke
         Turnpike and "committing the most wanton rages wherever they
         went." He writes about several skirmishes around the city and
         some prisoners brought into town. The regiments of Colonel
         Danforth and Colonel Evans of the second class militia were
         called out by the Governor.</p>
      <p>On March 2, he says, 300 horses and eighty-nine prisoners
         taken by General Wade Hampton were brought into town. March 3,
         he describes great excitement in Richmond with the reported
         advance of the enemy under General Benjamin Franklin Butler up
         the Peninsula. Alarm bells, he said, rang from two until five
         o'clock, with all furloughed officers and privates of the
         Confederate forces in town called to duty. March 4, Thompson
         cites "deep indignation" in Richmond over orders (commonly
         referred to as the Dahlgren Papers) captured on Colonel Ulric
         Dahlgren at [Turnstall's Station] revealing the purpose of
         Yankees in the recent raid to sack and burn Richmond, and put
         to death the Confederate Cabinet. He adds that ninety
         prisoners, thirty-five Negroes and 150 horses taken at the
         Station have been brought into the city.</p>
      <p>On March 13, Thompson attends services at St. Paul's where
         Generals Robert E. Lee, James Longstreet, Braxton Bragg, John
         Hood, Lafayette McLaws, William Henry Chase Whiting and others
         are present. The next day, March 14, he notes that the
         generals were in Richmond to discuss the future conduct of the
         campaign and that the proclamation of President Davis making
         April 8 a fast day has appeared in the papers. March 15, 655
         Confederate soldiers, including Gen. W.H. F. Lee, Col. J.
         [Lucins] Davis and Hampden Chamberlayne among the officers
         have arrived in town from Point Lookout under new agreement
         for the exchange of prisoners. On March 20, Thompson writes
         that 1,100 prisoners have arrived from Point Lookout, with
         about 10,000 persons on Capitol Square to greet them. March
         23, they experienced a seventeen inch snowfall in
         Richmond.</p>
      <p>On April 30, Thompson reports that Jefferson Davis's small
         son has died from injuries received in a fall from the portico
         of his home. Rumors prevail concerning an attack on New Bern,
         North Carolina.</p>
      <p>May 1, Thompson writes that "young Davis's funeral" has
         been held. On May 5 there is news from the army on the Rapidan
         River that a general engagement is about to begin. Yankee
         gunboats reportedly are ascending the James River, and
         Thompson continues that the Battle of the Wilderness between
         the armies of Ulysses Grant and Robert E.Lee has commenced.
         May 6--intense excitement prevails in Richmond as "the great
         battle continues." May 8--Second class militia ordered out
         midst "flying rumors about town." On May 9, Thompson writes
         that all business has been suspended in the city, with no one
         allowed to leave and no training permitted. May 10- much
         marching and countermarching of the militia. Rumors of every
         kind--good and bad--in circulation.</p>
      <p>May 11, Thompson notes that no mail has been distributed at
         the post office since the previous Friday, and that "Richmond
         is bare of male inhabitants as all have marched off to meet
         the enemy." He mentions a sharp engagement at Ashland that
         morning between Stuart's cavalry under Colonel Thomas T.
         Munford and a heavy force of the Yankees, in which the Yankees
         were repulsed. Severe fighting in the afternoon between the
         same forces, with General Stuart dangerously wounded. A bad
         storm in the evening did severe damage to Richmond structures,
         including the steeple of St. John's church. May 12--the storm
         continues. There also is heavy and continuous cannonading from
         3 A.M. to 11 A.M., and heavy firing in the afternoon in the
         direction of Petersburg. Thompson notes that General J.E.B.
         Stuart died at 8 P.M. at the house of Dr. Brewer on Grace St.
         May 13--firing still heard below town amidst great
         anxiety.</p>
      <p>Thompson describes General Stuart's funeral at 5 P.M. in
         the St. James Church as one of "universal mourning." Stuart's
         widow, he writes, requested no military funeral escort,
         although many of Stuart's companions in arms served as
         pallbearers, including Major Von Borcke. "There was no pomp
         therefore in the Obsequies--the coffin covered with flowers
         was carried to Hollywood."</p>
      <p>May 14--very heavy cannonade below the city in
         Chesterfield, with smoke visible from Thompson's library
         window. He writes of a midnight assault by the enemy on
         Drewry's Bluff from the land side, which was repulsed. May
         15--heavy showers in the morning--two heavy attacks made upon
         Drewrys Bluff at 9 A.M. and 2 P.M., with enemy repulsed--sun
         in the afternoon. May 21--attack on Confederate lines at
         midnight by General Benjamin Franklin Butler, which was
         repulsed. May 22--Johnson continues with a report of a large
         movement of troops from Southside to General Lee near Hanover
         Junction.</p>
      <p>May 23, the enemy crosses the North Anna. May 24,Virginia
         Military Institute cadets reviewed on Capitol Square by
         Jefferson Davis. May 27 there was a presentation of the flag
         of Virginia on Capitol Square to the Virginia Military
         Institute cadets.</p>
      <p>In June, Thompson's entries are brief as he is suffering
         from ill health and plans to go to England. June 2--he notes
         heavy cannonading occurring in the direction of
         Mechanicsville. June 3--reports on heavy fighting near
         Gaines's Mill. June 7-wrote to James Alexander Seddon,
         Confederate Secretary of War, for permission to go to England.
         June 9--Yankees under General August Valentine Kautz advance
         from Fort Powhatan and enter outer entrenchments of
         Petersburg. June 16--Yankees attack and carry outer
         entrenchments of Petersburg, capturing Sturdivant's Battery.
         June 22--Thompson leaves home at 7 A.M. by the Danville
         Railroad for Wilmington, North Carolina via Greensboro, N.C.
         June 24--reaches Wilmington after "hot, tedious, dusty
         trip."</p>
      <p>July 5, Thompson leaves for England on the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Edith</title>from Fort Fisher near
         Wilmington. July 6, he writes of being chased for nine hours
         by a Yankee steamer (supposed to be the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Connecticut</title>) before it gave up
         the chase. July 8--landed in Bermuda, changed ships to 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Alpha</title>to sail for Halifax. July
         23--sails from Halifax on the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Asia</title>. July 30--arrives at Mizen
         Head, south of Ireland. July 31--arrives in Liverpool.</p>
      <p>During August, Thompson settles himself in London, visits
         friends, goes shopping and makes several side excursions.
         August 1--on to London and the Exeter House Hotel. August
         3--moves to 17 Savile Row. August 7- -attends morning services
         at Westminster Abbey. August 8-- takes the train to
         Manchester. August 9--on to Glasgow, Scotland. August 12, from
         Glasgow to the Highlands; August 15, a friend has received a
         telegram talking of a great victory over General Grant in
         front of Petersburg. August 22--27--leaves Kingussie for
         Inverness, takes on boat trip to Fort William and afterwards
         by coach through the heart of Loch Lomond and Glencoe Pass. He
         then takes a steamer and train on to Glasgow and Edinburgh.
         August 27-August 31--returns to Glasgow, then travels by
         steamer to Belfast and by train to Dublin. From there he
         travels to Knocklofty, seat of the Earl of Donoughmore, near
         the town of Clonmel, Ireland, where he remains until September
         10th when he leaves to visit Dublin.</p>
      <p>On September 12, Thompson returns to London where he
         describes his visits and activities in great detail, including
         a visit to hear Charles Spurgeon speak at his Tabernacle on
         September 18, a visit to the Crystal Palace on September 19
         (also on November 5), and a visit to Thomas Carlyle on October
         14, noting their subjects of conversation and summarizing some
         of Carlyle's comments, including some about the Civil War (4
         pages). October 17 through 22, Thompson was at Liverpool.
         Activities continue in London from October 23 through December
         21, mentioning another visit to Carlyle (November 19), a visit
         with Alfred Lord Tennyson (November 24), meeting Mr. Babbage,
         the inventor of the calculating machine (December 9), visit
         with the General and Mrs. Randolph (December 10-22) who he
         accompanied to Paris, France via Dover (December 22-29). The
         journal ends on December 29, 1864, with an account of his
         activities in France.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
