<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02722">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02722::Papers of Lynchburg Families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02722.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02722::Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families)//EN" "viu02722.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Lynchburg, Virginia Families, Papers of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">6138</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by niyi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6/10/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02722::Papers of
            Lynchburg Families)//EN" "viu02722.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Lynchburg Families, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
         <num type="Accession Number">6138</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families 
         <unitdate label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">6138</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">This collection
         consists of ca. 470 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Lynchburg, Virginia Families, Accession #6138, Special
            Collections, University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased by the Library from Miss
            Fanny Edward of Lynchburg, Virginia, through Miss Nellie
            Gregory of Lynchburg, Virginia, on January 5, 1960.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>There is biographical and genealogical data on the Dudley
         and related families in the collection. Some of this
         information is noted here. Captain Peter Dudley married Nancy
         Davis, daughter of Friends William and Mary Davis on January
         31, 1814. They had issue: John William Dudley (died October 2,
         1878) married Andalusia Fourquerean (died March 14, 1878),
         removed to Cincinnati, Ohio; Thomas Stephens Dudley,
         unmarried, died from gunshot wound; Mary Elizabeth Dudley
         married Thomas W. Johns of Appomattox, Virginia; Fanny Jane
         Dudley married James F. Payne (died February 3, 1882) on
         December 2, 1847; Nancy Davis Dudley, died in infancy; Peter
         Lewis Dudley (died December 3, 1856) married Bettie Saunders;
         Henry Davis, unmarried, moved to California; Louisa Susan
         Dudley, died in infancy; Deborah Anne Dudley married Reverend
         William H. Kinckle on October 17, 1865; Maria Rose Dudley
         married J. Edward Calhoun; and, Robert Leslie Dudley (died
         December 6, 1900), unmarried.</p>
      <p>Stephen Adams, lawyer, judge, member of the Virginia House of Delegates, and captain in the Confederate States
         Army, was born in Fulton, New York on Feb. 28, 1829. He attended Albany Academy
         and graduated from Yale in 1850. He came to Virginia and
         married Emma Camm Saunders in a ceremony in Old Court Street Methodist Church on April 26, 1854. Their
         son, William Saunders Adams, studied music in Germany and was
         a professor at Randolph Macon Women's College and organist of
         note. He married Grace Dudley Kinckle, daughter of Reverend
         William H. Kinckle and Deborah Dudley.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are ca. 470 items, (1814-1910)1957 and n.d.,
         pertaining to various families of Lynchburg, Virginia,
         including the Adams, Davis, Dudley, and Johns families. There
         are correspondence, business and legal papers, miscellaneous
         writings, and bound volumes.</p>
      <p>There are letters from Andalusia (Fourquerean) Dudley and
         Ellen Dudley in Cincinnati, Ohio to their sister-in-law and
         aunt, Deborah Anne Dudley. On June 29, 1851 she writes while
         still mourning the loss of a loved one. She complains about
         having to take care of the house and the children because of
         the inexperience and absenteeism of their young
         African-American woman from Lynchburg, Virginia and discusses
         the children and their antics and Dr. Johnston, an apparent
         admirer and frequent visitor to their home. On August 8, 1851,
         she discusses the children and the new "kitchen girl" who is
         better than the previous girl even though she cannot cook and
         is good with the children. She also describes the procession
         celebrated by the firemen through Cincinnati of fifty or more
         companies, each with a different uniform, several bands of the
         most delightful music, and the representation of the different
         states' flags. On March 21st, Andalusia expresses her deep
         sympathy to Deborah over the death of her husband, William H.
         Kinckle. There is an undated letter regarding family news, her
         help "Jane" who is "willing poor thing but is a good deal
         troubled with a disease called laziness," missing the little
         ones since they commenced school, and cleaning up the house.
         There are also letters from Andalusia's daughter, Ellen
         Dudley, following their move from Lynchburg, Virginia to
         Cincinnati, Ohio. On May 18, [1851], she writes describing
         their travel through White Sulphur Springs and Hawk's Nest,
         West Virginia on their way to Cincinnati; she mentions their
         reception upon arrival, taking piano lessons and staying in a
         boarding house until they find a place to live. On May 25,
         [1851], she writes about her new life in Cincinnati,
         mentioning shopping, clothes, finding a new place to live, and
         being visited by a Dr. Johnston who appears to be taken with
         her mother. On December 19, 1851, she writes that hard lessons
         and music take up much time, reminisces over times with the
         family, describes the market houses in the city, and writes of
         family news including a child sick with inflammation of the
         lungs.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1849-1857, from Henry Dudley in various
         places including Cincinnati, Ohio and San Francisco,
         California. Early letters from Cincinnati discuss family news,
         Mrs. Stowbridge the landlady and her sisters, Catholics, the
         ladies of Cincinnati as being "unpretty" (April 11, 1849); no
         news of a fire in the city (May 4, 1849); business reviving
         somewhat following the cholera epidemic and the Ladies of
         Covington holding a fair (June 7, 1849); Deborah's
         presentiment that she will not live long and her growth, his
         preference for Virginia women, and various women acquaintances
         (August 24, 1850). In a letter of January 12, 1851, from St.
         Louis, Missouri, he discusses life at the boarding house and
         being taken care of by Mrs. Avery and her two daughters and
         another boarder, Mose Hillard ("one of those boys you read
         about"); mentions meeting many from Lynchburg including Dick
         Scruggs, John Cannon, Bob and Dick Walton, Apperson
         Fitzgibbons and John William Royall; and, advises brother
         William and family to take up residence in Covington, Kentucky
         instead of Cincinnati with its members of the Free Soil party
         and free African-Americans. There is also an interesting
         letter dated June 24, 1852 from the Steamer 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Cherokee</title>discussing his trip
         from Richmond, Virginia to New York, New York, on the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Baltimore</title>after the Steamer 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Roanoke</title>went aground at City
         Point. His arrival was "amidst all the noise bustle and
         confusion of the Whig Convention" and his stay initially at
         the U. S. Hotel. He describes a tour through Broadway, Fifth
         Avenue, the Italian Opera, Tripler Hall, Cosetti Garden, and
         Brooklyn. He writes about a business man, Mr. Watson, who has
         made a great deal of money with his store and "large factory
         for making sigars [sic], snuff and fine cut tobacco..." He
         also describes his short voyage with some 400 passengers of
         Dutch, Irish, French, Spanish, English, and American and
         mentions a fire on the ship, seasickness and sea animals.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1852-1857, from Henry Dudley while
         living in San Francisco, California. On November 30, 1852, he
         mentions the anticipation when the telegraphic signal is
         displayed on Telegraph Hill that a mail steamer is in sight,
         the rainy reason, destructive fires, cost of living, and Miss
         Catherine Hayes giving a concert at the American Theatre. On
         April 18, 1853, he writes that they expect to have weekly
         communications with the states and mentions the current
         monotonous life in San Francisco, the great robber Joaquin,
         corresponding with a certain young lady, and his failed
         attempt at growing a beard. On May 28, 1853, he writes about
         his change of quarters to the house of Carrington and Jeffrey
         as "chief cook and bottle washer" and describes his living
         arrangement. He refers to Robert Leslie Dudley's
         accomplishments in school, mentions having several chances in
         a grand raffle of jewelry and encloses three gold quarters. On
         July 30, 1853, he writes about the Fourth of July celebration
         during which the military were reviewed by General [John
         Augustus] Sutter (1803-1880) and then formed a procession, and
         mentions going to Sacramento on business. On March 15, 1854,
         he compliments the daguerreotypes of Deborah, Rose, and Robert
         that he has received from Adams and Company and sends regards
         to George Lyman. He also discusses the entertainment in San
         Francisco, writing that there are four theatres, several
         concert halls, and a quantity of stars including Madame Anna
         Thillon, Madame Anna Bishop, the Roussell sisters, and the
         Montplaisir troupe. On July 31, 1854, he mentions their Fourth
         of July celebration with military firing of cannons and an
         attempted display of fireworks; the death of Colonel [ ]
         Irving; the birth of a son to Peter Lewis Dudley; the order of
         'Know Nothings' being organized there; the numerous 'Do
         Nothings'; the fire epidemic over the last two months which
         affected Marysville, Sacramento and San Francisco; citizens'
         reactions and actions during and after the fires; and, his
         thoughts on the prospect of marriage. On December 5, 1854, he
         writes of the difficulties of Peter Lewis Dudley, trying to
         locate Sam Preston, and the retirement of Messrs. Carrington
         and Jeffrey from the storage business. He also discusses the
         weather and how the rain affects the merchant business and
         discusses the markets, which are full of vegetables and fruits
         as well as game such as duck, geese, quail, venison and
         grizzly bears. On January 23, 1855, he writes that he has
         found employment with Goodwin and Company, one of the largest
         wholesale grocery establishments in the area, and discusses
         the current market business. He also mentions the weather, the
         civilization of San Francisco, and several acquaintances, Mr.
         Heath, Captain Fair, and Henry P. Irving. On June
         4, 1856, he discusses the corruption in San Francisco,
         consisting of ballot stuffers, shoulder strikers, and corrupt
         politicians, the murder of the best men in the community, and
         the governor's order to bring out the militia. The writing
         sheet contains two sketches (in life and in death) of James
         King of William, editor of the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">San Francisco Evening
         Bulletin</title>murdered by James P. Casey on May 14, 1856. On
         August 20, 1856, he writes a brief letter on the inside of a
         bulletin, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The California News Messenger</title>,
         compiled by Joseph Weed and published by George H. Leland. On
         July 20, 1857, he acknowledges the sad news of the death of
         their father, Peter Dudley, and comments on the strength of
         their mother, Nancy (Davis) Dudley. He mentions that Captain
         Fair has gone to Yreka, California and that hard times are
         with them, and claims that he still considers Lynchburg to be
         his home. One November 3, 1857, he writes about the shipwreck
         of the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Central America</title>, commenting on
         the gallant conduct of the men who sacrificed their own lives
         in order to help the women and children to safety. On December
         4, 1857, he mentions that the rainy season has commenced, that
         they are in remarkable easy circumstances in comparison to the
         East, and the loss of employment throughout the East. He also
         mentions the news of an altercation between United States
         troops and the Mormons and the possibility of fighting the
         'Utahs'.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1851-1854, from Peter Lewis Dudley to his sisters
         are brotherly in nature, often giving advice and supplying
         news of the family. On March 30, 1851, he writes from
         Richmond, describing his trip with William Dudley to
         Cincinnati, Ohio and then to Louisville, Kentucky and New
         Orleans, Louisiana on the Steamer 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Magnolia</title>. He writes at length
         about attending concerts and operas, including hearing the
         wonderful songstress Jenny Lind as well as a Prima Dona in the
         French Opera and [Isidoro] Truffi and [Teresa] Parodi. On
         August 23, 1852, he comments favorably on social life in
         Lynchburg and negatively in Cincinnati, Ohio and expounds on
         the virtues of the "hospitality &amp; civility of a gentleman"
         while reprimanding his sisters over their lack of courtesy in
         thanking Mrs. Young and Miss Clara Lyman for their hospitality
         while in Baltimore, Maryland. He expresses concern that
         Deborah and Rose will return from Cincinnati with "all sorts
         of notions about the sin and immorality of slavery" after
         being subjected to the words of the Free Soil party. He also
         expresses strong negative opinions about abolitionists, the
         Free Soil party and 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Uncle Tom's Cabin</title>which he views
         as an abolition document causing incitement. On June 28, 1853,
         he announces his engagement to Miss Bettie Saunders and
         expresses apprehension over his character and making her
         happy. On March 31, 1854, he suggests that Deborah and Rose
         buy something for their spring and summer wardrobe on his
         account with Dudley and Johnston while in Richmond. An undated
         letter strongly requests that Deborah and Rose not attend the
         Club that night and promises an explanation later.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1846-1847, from Robert Leslie Dudley
         following his arrival in Ohio. On October 18, 1846, he writes
         from Chillicothe, Ohio, discussing his travel through
         Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, Wheeling, West Virginia, and
         Zanesville, Ohio to his current destination. He writes that
         Chillicothe is the "only respectable community...in Ohio,"
         that he attended the Episcopal Church, and that he is moving
         on to Cincinnati. On October 8, 1847, he writes from
         Cincinnati about attending the theatre, concerts, museums and
         the observatory, mentioning wax figures, paintings and a
         mechanical apparatus representing the 'infernal regions'. He
         writes that he has no female acquaintances and that there is
         too much "Yankeeism" in the women there.</p>
      <p>There are later letters, 1861-1864, from Robert Leslie
         Dudley during the time of the Civil War. On February 8, 1861,
         he writes from Cincinnati about the
         hard times and the dull business, especially in the book line.
         He refers to the Ohio papers and the rumors about Fort Sumter
         and Charleston, South Carolina; the effects of John Brown's
         invasion; and, mentions peoples' hopes that Virginia will save
         the Union and almost wishing that she were for secession. In a
         letter dated December [February ? ]5, 1864, he writes from
         Headquarters Hindman's Corps, Dalton, Georgia, under the
         direction of [Thomas Carmichael] Hindman (1828-1868), about
         the death of Bettie Saunders' father and being busy int he
         office because of the system that has been established in
         regard to furloughing the army. On March 4, 1864, he writes
         from Headquarters Hood's Corps, Dalton, Georgia, under the
         direction of [John Bell] Hood (1831-1879), that General
         [Thomas Carmichael] Hindman sends thanks for the tobacco and
         that he is awaiting a furlough. He also refers to the skirmish
         with the Yankees and "Old Joe" [Joseph Eggleston Johnston
         (1807-1891)], probably referring to the Demonstration on
         Dalton which ended with a skirmish near Catoosa Station. On
         August 14, 1864, he writes from Headquarters Bate's Division,
         Atlanta, Georgia, under the direction of [William Brimage]
         Bate (1826-1905), about food, Bate being seriously wounded,
         General J. C. Brent being in command of the division, Hood
         seeming to provide satisfaction and gaining the confidence of
         the Kentucky Brigade, and longing to go on a rampage.</p>
      <p>Correspondence of Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and Thomas W.
         Johns often relates to family news. There are two letters, ca.
         1860s, from Mary Elizabeth "Lizzie" Johns in Appomattox Court
         House concerning the location of the Yankees around Lynchburg
         and Virginia and Mary O. Christian's ill child, Maggie and her
         son, Davis, being sent to the country for care. A letter, May
         18, 1882, from Deborah A. Dudley to Thomas W. Johns, mentions
         her efforts to have published his poetry honoring a Mr.
         Rawlings. There is a long letter full of sadness and grief,
         September 23, 1899, from Thomas W. Johns to Deborah A. Dudley,
         concerning the last tormented days of his wife, "Lizzie"; the
         "heavy burden of a lunatic child" such as his daughter Bettie;
         disputes over the settlement of a family estate; being unable
         to attend Mr. Underwood's nightly church meetings because of
         his daughter's care; and, good crops of tobacco, corn and
         sweet potatoes. There are two undated letters from "Lizzie"
         concerning a plan for laying off ground for a cemetery for
         soldiers supported by the Ladies of the Memorial Association;
         Mr. Day's lecture on love, courtship and marriage;
         African-American servant "Sallie" leaving to get married; the
         education of Alice, Fannie, Deane, and Willie; and, a request
         for good snuff.</p>
      <p>There are twelve Civil War letters, 1864-1865, from William
         G. Luck, a medical practitioner, of Graham's Horse Artillery,
         Virginia Volunteers, Dearing's Cavalry Brigade near
         Petersburg, Virginia. On March 20, 1864, he writes from camp
         near Garysburg, North Carolina, about having to "physic"
         Graham's Artillery and Dearing's Regiment of Cavalry; their
         very long march; social activities during a trip to Suffolk
         and Norfolk, including a visit to Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and
         Thomas W. Johns; a charge on the Yankees in the Dismal Swamp
         and the capture of several prisoners; the high opinions of
         Colonel [James] Dearing (1840- 1865); their order to Suffolk
         and their fight with the African-Americans; returning to
         Dismal Swamp with Dearing and killing seventy-five
         African-Americans; the confiscation of bacon, sugar, and
         coffee; and, not expecting to marry soon. On June 12, 1864,
         near Petersburg, he claims that Dearings Cavalry andGraham's
         Battery saved Petersburg from ashes and mentions Lieutenant
         [J. C.] Rutherfoord of Dearing's staff. On July 25, 1864, he
         mentions a visit to lady acquaintances in Petersburg, Captain
         [J.C.] Rutherfoord being a gallant man, fighting and
         confiscation of goods around Plymouth and Washington, and
         wanting to get a furlough to visit the Johns. On July 26,
         1864, he mentions a visit with a certain widow, an invitation
         to dine with Captain Cavendish on [William Henry Fitzhugh]
         "Fitz" Lee's (1837-1891) staff, and men being shot for
         desertion. On August 5, 1864, he writes about there being no
         chance for a furlough and the capture of "smoked Yankees"
         [African- Americans], who were put in front and forced to face
         the torrent of bullets; he also mentions his loneliness and
         the pursuit of female companionship. On August 16, 1864, he
         mentions his low spirits and his young slave, "Penn," running
         off after a thrashing for bad conduct. On September 2, 1864,
         near Petersburg, he writes that the Yankee cavalry broke
         through the picket lines and nearly got to the camp before
         they retreated and of their anticipation of a Yankee attack at
         any time. He also mentions the pursuit of sweethearts and
         correspondence with a special young lady in Chesterfield
         County and sends compliments to the Johns family. On December
         12, 1864, Luck writes that he has been promoted to full
         surgeon and that they are in camp at Belfield, twenty miles
         from Weldon, North Carolina without any comforts. In December
         1864, he sends a souvenir from a pine tree where [Ulysses S.]
         Grant was during his last advance to be added to her curious
         collections gathered during the war. On January 28, 1865, he
         requests a pair of white gloves in order to attend the wedding
         of Captain [J. C.] Rutherfoord. On March 4, 1865, he sends
         compliments to the whole family, especially the Johns, and
         describes the wedding. He expects the war to become active
         again and has faith that [Robert Edward] Lee will not give up
         Petersburg; he mentions the transfer of Colonel Dearing to
         command [Thomas Lafayette] Rosser's old brigade near
         Staunton.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1849-1860, from James F. Payne of
         Lynchburg to Deborah A. Dudley. In October 1849, he suggests
         that she not attend a confirmation meeting held by [William
         H.] Kinckle, discusses opinions on confirmation, church and
         religion, advises her on a trip to Baltimore and Lynchburg,
         and mentions the fair and its fine exhibit. In July 1852, he
         discusses family and social activities, vegetable prices,
         Friends Warehouse business, the organization of the District
         Court by judges Taliaferro, Nash, Leigh and Baker, and
         Kinckle's sermon on the death of Henry Clay. There is a
         touching letter from E. S. Winslow to Payne concerning the
         death of Winslow's wife (November 18, 1859). There is also an
         undated letter discussing Deborah A. Dudley's character and
         how to complete her fine character, religious thought, and the
         importance of the family circle.</p>
      <p>There are two letters, 1864-1865, from Robinson C. Pierce
         in camps near Richmond and Chester. On October 3, 1864, he
         writes of rumors of Union movement through Nelson towards
         Lynchburg and his advice to people to join armed forces in
         order to save their homes and mentions orders to go into
         Buckingham and Appomattox to forage. On January 2, 1865, he
         writes that he has just returned from six weeks of detached
         duty in Madison, following a narrow escape by William P.
         Holland and himself with eight wagons because of a delay in
         orders to leave.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1863-1864, from G. K. Turner, 11th Virginia
         Regiment, Kinston, North Carolina, are chiefly of a social
         nature. In January 1864, he describes the packed trains on his
         trip from Danville which included waiting on a train platform
         with two sick soldiers and several ladies who were oblivious
         to the sick men. He also mentions his orders to the Sixth
         Cavalry, Dr. Houston leaving for Richmond to be promoted to
         its surgeonry. On February 28, 1864, he writes that Dr.
         Greenlee is being sent to assist him and he then plans to
         apply for a furlough as he has not had a day off since being
         volunteered into the 11th Virginia Regiment. He also writes
         about the cleanliness of his hospital and the long death list
         contributed to by "sickly North Carolinians."</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1852-1862, to Deborah Ann Dudley from
         various relatives and friends, concerning family news, social
         life and the Civil War. A letter of May 11, 1852, discusses
         life in Black Walnut, Virginia, mentioning the family
         plantation; her mother having two boarders, a teacher and her
         scholar; picnic parties; improvements to Black Walnut; and, a
         local beauty, Mary Eliza Owen. There is a letter, July 26,
         1861, from R. M. McKinney, Headquarters 5th Regiment, South
         Carolina Volunteers, Yorktown, Virginia, discussing life
         during the war. He writes that his time is taken up by his
         work signing orders and passes and by drills, parades and
         guard mounting the rest of the time; he has a preference for
         surviving the war over posthumous fame; he sent mementoes from
         Fort Sumter and Fort Caswell and that they dug up shell
         fragments and the bones of men who died at Yorktown during the
         [Revolutionary War]; there are about 1150 men in his regiment;
         there was a violent death of a man in camp and there are many
         sick men; he rides outside the line every evening with Major
         Green; there are an abundance of mosquitoes; they will never
         submit to Lincoln; and, he was in the Alabama troops prior to
         this command. Letters, November 1861, from a soldier in
         Centreville, Virginia, mention retreating from Fairfax, a
         social visit with the attention of several females, and the
         discomforts of camp life due to rain and wind and lack of
         food. There is a letter, March 23, 1862, from "Cousin William"
         at Cavalry Camp near Orange Court House, which mentions
         retreating from Leesburg to Rapidan River; the destruction of
         supplies prior to leaving; friends fleeing from Belmont to
         Richmond; support of the draft; the evacuation of the Army of
         the Potomac; his regiment still being in the rear; being in
         command of the Guard with the Army of Leesburg; and, marching
         most of the time, exposed to all kinds of weather and sleeping
         on the ground. There is another letter, April 24, 1862, from
         "Cousin William" at "Bivouac" six miles from Gordonsville,
         discussing life and activities during the war. He mentions
         moving around in the vicinity of the Yankees; the lack of
         comforts; various adventures, including the capture of
         prisoners and arms and horses; his company and Albemarle
         troops dashing into Warrenton after the Yankees has taken
         possession; scouting near the Yankee camp; awaiting more
         orders; rumors of reinforcing ["Stonewall"] Jackson against
         [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks (1816-1894); having about ten
         thousand men in fine condition and ripe for a fight; being
         under the command of General [Richard Stoddert] Ewell
         (1817-1872) who is under Jackson; the death of Colonel [R. M.]
         McKinney who fell gallantly leading his regiment; expecting to
         lose more friends in this war; anticipating the plans of
         [George Brinton] McClellan (1826-1885); marriage; hoping that
         the Ladies of Lynchburg will succeed in their gunboat
         enterprise; the re- organization of regiments and elections,
         with Hale, Flood, Whitehead, Radford, Mumford and Pitzer;
         recruits being mustered into the 13th Virginia Regiment at
         Gordonsville; and, having no respect for those drafted,
         feeling that they should have volunteered.</p>
      <p>Other Civil War letters to Deborah Anne Dudley include one,
         June 11, 1864, from Samuel K. Huys in Clinton, Louisiana
         during the Red River Campaign. Huys mentions troop movement to
         Red River, Louisiana from Abingdon, Virginia, describing the
         trip on horseback through rough and mountainous country to
         Atlanta, Georgia and through pine woods from Mobile, Alabama
         to Clinton, Louisiana. He refers to the lack of food for
         people throughout, the suffering of people in east Tennessee
         and in the mountains of North Carolina, and life in Clinton,
         describing the Red River, Louisiana area and mentioning the
         high incidence of widows.. He mentions his brother being in
         the prison camp at Point Lookout, Maryland; being in charge of
         the officer's hospital; and being pleasantly situated for now.
         He refers to his traveling party, including officers,
         servants, horses and wagons, and mentioning [Simon Bolivar]
         Buckner (1823-1914), R. A. Johnson, [Patrick Ronayne] Cleburne
         (1828-1864), and [Randall Lee] Gibson (1832-1892). He
         discusses activities of the Red River Campaign and the
         Trans-Mississippi. He mentions Colonel John Scott of the 1st
         Louisiana Cavalry being in charge of the district; the breakup
         of a Yankee plantation and the capture of sixty mules and some
         "Negroes"; the enemy entrenched camp at Morganza, Louisiana;
         General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks having lost over twenty
         thousand men, fourteen gunboats and some twenty transports;
         General [Frederick] Steele having lost some five thousand men
         and as much transportation; Steele last being seen in Little
         Rock, Arkansas pursued by [Sterling "Pap"] Price (1809-1867)
         and [John Sappington] Marmaduke (1833-1887); the impression
         that Steele will fall back to Missouri; opinions on the Army
         of General [Joseph Eggleston] Johnston and a diversion in the
         direction of St. Louis, Missouri and General [William
         Tecumseh] Sherman (1820-1891); General [Richard] "Dick" Taylor
         (1826-1879) being between General [Nathaniel Prentiss] Banks'
         Army and News Orleans, Louisiana; General [Edward Richard
         Sprigg] Canby (1817-1873) assuming Banks' command; and,
         sending greetings from [Simon Bolivar] Buckner.</p>
      <p>There is a letter, October 10, 1865, to Deborah Anne Dudley
         on her wedding day, from Anne E. Johns in Leamington, England,
         discussing her marriage to William H. Kinckle and describing
         travel in England, including Leamington, Kenilworth, Warwick
         Castle, Oxford, and Blenheim. She discusses various places
         relating to Shakespeare, including Stratford-upon-Avon and the
         burial place of Shakespeare and Anne Hathaway. There is a
         letter, July 24, 1868, from John R. Lee of Martinsville, Henry
         County, Virginia, concerning the death of William H. Kinckle
         and including religious thought and advice of
         child-rearing.</p>
      <p>There is miscellaneous correspondence, 1828-1913, and no
         date, relating to family news, social life, and other matters.
         A letter of September 23, 1828 from Nancy Davis to Peter
         Dudley elaborates on a visit to Lynchburg by Henry Clay. There
         is a letter, February 5, 1858, from [ ] Barrett in Richmond
         concerning political activity and an upcoming election. A
         letter, November 15, 1865, from Nannie McCorkle of Lynchburg
         concerns the organization of a Ladies Aid Society formed in
         order to provide aid to poor preachers by collecting
         provisions, clothes and money. There is a lengthy and
         expressively descriptive letter, March 20, 1866, from Anne E.
         Johns in Rome, Italy, concerning travel in London, England;
         Paris, France; and, Rome and Naples, Italy. The letter
         mentions the "Piazza di Spagna," the ruins, the Dome of St.
         Peter, the Roman Aqueduct, an omnibus accident, and a
         pickpocket attempt. There are three letters, 1895 and 1901,
         from "Wes" at Greenbrier, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia
         and Arlington Stables, Washington, D. C., mentioning the fine
         potato crops, the livery stables at the spa, and social news.
         There is a (copy of a) letter to Franklin Owens mentioning the
         birth of his son, Benjamin Franklin Owens, Jr.; describing the
         St. Paul's (Episcopal Church) Fair in Lynchburg with a
         discussion of the goods sold; and, seeking assistance in the
         settlement of the estate of his [late wife] Jane's uncle,
         George Latham, of Savannah, Georgia.</p>
      <p>There are also business and legal papers of the Adams,
         Davis, Johns, and related families. Among the legal papers of
         Stephen Adams are: Albany Academy certificates, 1843-1844;
         copy of his will, January 21, 1869, leaving his property to
         his wife Emma C. Adams; papers, 1903, concerning the claim of
         an invalid pension for Robert E. Mitchell who became ill
         during detached service to Yosemite Park; and, a "Report of
         Alumni Advisory Board to Yale Corporation on the Stimulation
         of Intellectual Activity among Undergraduates," June 20,
         1910.</p>
      <p>Among the Davis family business papers are accounts for
         whitewashing and plastering (September 11, 1827 &amp; October
         3, 1828), hat and hat repair (May 23, 1828), cart and
         wheelbarrow parts (September 1828), dental work (1854),
         [horse] shoe and shoe repair (February 15, n.y.), and sundry
         items. There is also a note regarding an allowance to a Mrs.
         Murphy by the Board of Overseers of the Poor (February 21,
         1829), the settlement of partnership business of Davis &amp;
         Byars (18[ ]8 March 25), a proposal from Elizabeth Thomas to
         wash, lodge and board for $1.50 per week (n.d.), an account
         for carpentry and building (n.d.).</p>
      <p>Among the accounts of John Johns are purchases of various
         sewing materials and accessories, ladies shoes and boots, and
         clothing; accounts for smith work; and, receipts for payments
         for shares in the stock of the Office of the Virginia and
         Tennessee Railroad Company. Among the accounts of Thomas Johns
         are purchases for various foods and sundries. There are also
         accounts for work done on stables and kitchen by James W.
         Wright, including a list of hired hands (May 1865); smith
         work, listing specific items made, mended, repaired or
         removed, by Charles P. North (January 29, 1866); work on
         ambulance, wagon wheels, and wagon by John A. Roper (February
         22, 1868); gold fillings (May 16, 1871); and, horseshoes
         (April 20, 1904). Thomas Johns also has tobacco accounts,
         1880-1900, with Lynchburg commission merchants, Jacob H.
         Franklin and Company, Callahan and Franklin, Murrell, Fleming
         and Company, Green H. Nowlin, and Walter S. Fore and Company.
         Legal papers of Thomas Johns relate to the sale of tracts of
         land in Campbell County (June 19, 1856 and February 1, 1871);
         the milling business (December 3, 1870 and December 21, 1877);
         and agreements to cultivate land (October 17, 1872 and
         September 14, 1878). Among the receipts of Thomas Johns is a
         receipt, January 12, 1858, from D. P. and G. Diuguid "For
         Burial of Black Man 8.00." There are also tax receipts for
         Campbell County and Appomattox County to Thomas Johns.
         Miscellaneous business and legal papers include a summons to
         the proprietors of Friends Warehouse in Lynchburg (September
         1850); a certification that Reverend William H. Kinckle has
         taken the Oath prescribed by the President in his proclamation
         of December 8, 1863; and, a statement of tobacco sold at
         Friends Warehouse (September 30, 1889).</p>
      <p>There is genealogical data on the Davis, Dudley and Payne
         families and historical data on Lynchburg. The social items
         include a marriage invitation for Grace Dudley Kinckle and
         William Saunders Adams (December 23, 1890) and a souvenir menu
         and ribbon from the Columbian Naval Parade Steamer 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Howard Carrol</title>. Among the
         writings are a diary entry, September 1849, of religious
         thoughts and activities [kept by Deborah Ann Dudley],
         religious essays, a tribute to John Kirkpatrick, and an
         address to the Ladies of the Memorial Association (pages 1 and
         2 missing). There is an autograph book of Yale College
         graduates kept by Stephen Adams which include comments by
         Denison Olmsted (1791-1859), Noah Porter (1811-1892), Thomas
         A[nthony] Thacher (1815-1886), James Hadley (1821-1872),
         Nathaniel Shipman (1828- 1906), William R[oot] Bliss (1825-
         1906), Martin Kellogg (1828-1903), and Ellis H[enry] Roberts
         (1827-1918). The diary and commonplace book, 1900-1901, of
         Grace Kinckle Adams contains entries concerning her daily
         life, family and friends, and, especially, her parents, Grace
         Dudley (Kinckle) and William Saunders Adams. The scrapbook,
         1881-1898, kept by Stephen Adams includes newspaper clippings
         of editorial correspondence, 1881, during a trip to Rotterdam,
         Amsterdam, Cologne, Wiesbaden, Antwerp, Brussels, Paris, and
         London; on various historical and political figures; on a
         great fire in Lynchburg in 1883; and, of poetry. There is also
         an extract from the oration, "Biographical Sketch of General
         Robert E. Lee," by John W. Daniel at the unveiling of the Lee
         statue (June 28, 1883).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e257">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e261">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Andalusia (Fourquerean) Dudley 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851, 1887, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e269">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Dudley 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1849-1857</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e279">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Peter Lewis Dudley 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1851-1854</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e287">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robert Leslie Dudley 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1846-1864</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e295">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mary Elizabeth (Dudley) and Thomas W.
                  Johns 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1880-1899</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e303">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William G. Luck 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1864-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e311">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James F. Payne 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1849-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e319">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Robinson C. Pierce 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1862-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e327">
          <did>
            <unittitle>G. K. Turner 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1863-1864</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e335">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Deborah Anne Dudley 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1871,
                  1907</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e346">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Letters 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828-1913,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Business Papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e360">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Stephen Adams: Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1843-1910</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e368">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Davis: Account Book 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1814-1821</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e376">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Davis Family: Business Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1774-1860,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e386">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Johns: Business Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1820-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e394">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Johns: Accounts 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e404">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Johns: Accounts for Tobacco 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1880-1900</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e412">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Johns: Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1856-1879</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e420">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Johns: Receipts 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1848-1903</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e428">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas W. Johns: Tax Receipts 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1852-1888</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e436">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Johns Family: Business Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1879-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e445">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Business Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1818-1909</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e453">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Topical</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e457">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogical and Historical Data 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1957,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e465">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Poetry 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e473">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Social 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1853-1892</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e481">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Writings 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e489">
          <did>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e493">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound Volumes</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e497">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Autograph Book of Yale Graduates kept by
                  Stephen Adams 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e505">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Class Notes for Senior Regular Law kept by
                  John L. Adams 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1882</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e513">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Commonplace Book kept by Grace Dudley
                  Kinckle 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1876</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e521">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diary and Commonplace Book kept by Grace
                  Kinckle Adams 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1900-1901</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e529">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook kept by Stephen Adams 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1881-1898</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
