<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04084">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04084::A Guide to the Diary of Fontaine Newton Taliaferro 1917-1918)//EN" "viu04084.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Diary of Fontaine Newton Taliaferro, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1917-1918</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Taliaferro, Fontaine Newton, Diary 
<num type="collectionnumber">14276</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Diary of Fontaine Newton Taliaferro, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1917-1918</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">14276</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Diary of Fontaine Newton Taliaferro, <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1917-1918</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">14276</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Extent">22 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Diary of Fontaine Newton Taliaferro, 1917-1918, Accession #14276, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased from Swann Auction Galleries, New York, New York,
                    on July 24, 2008, by the University of Virginia Library.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Fontaine Newton Taliaferro III (1894-?) came from a well-to-do Hicksville, Long
                Island, New York family, attended Poly Prep, Brooklyn, the Stone School at Cornwall,
                New York, and graduated from the University of Virginia, which he attended from
                1914-1916. He then enlisted in the United States Ambulance Corps on May 28,
                1917. He arrived in Europe in August 1917 and was attached to the French army as a
                mechanic for the ambulance service. In May 1918, he was awarded the Croix de Guerre.
                After the war, he sold insurance for Seaman &amp; Taliaferro in Hicksville, New
                York, and ran for public office on Long Island, for Assemblyman in the Second
                District.</p>
      <p>Additional Information about his section can be found in the 1919 edition of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Corks and Curls,</title> pages 230-237, "S.S.U. 517" by R.H.
                Baker who furnishes a brief outline of life in Section 517 of the ambulance corps,
                mentioning short anecdotes and many of the men in this diary.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>Taliaferro enlisted with the University of Virginia unit and was stationed at a base near the Alsace region and later near Dunkirk. The diary contains details of his training, voyage to France on the San Jacinto, mechanical work on Ford ambulances, driving through bombardments, adventures of his fellow drivers, Croix de Guerre awards, sightseeing, and off duty carousing. He frequently mentions fellow University of Virginia students including Louis Astor, R. H. Baker, Marvin L. Bishop, Frank S. Darwin, Joseph H. Fee, Edward G. Fenwick, Charles D. Fox, Edwin C. Hathaway, Tarleton F. Heath, Philip L. Johnson, Jack Leathem, James E. Moore, Peter Upton Muir, William H. Rogers, Jennings B. Rust, [George Scott Shackelford?], Charles H. Sheild, Philip B. Sheild, Brenton A. Tilghman, Charles V. Tompkins, and Dr. Benjamin C. Willis.</p>
      <p>Annotated entries for the Diary</p>
      <p>May 1917</p>
      <p>28- enlisted in the United States Ambulance Corps in Charlottesville; played pool
                with Charlie Sheild; went to the movies ("low as the dickens")</p>
      <p>29- went back to the hospital for orders; "sworn in" to service; wired for a leave to
                spend money on girls and dancing at "the Beach" in Fry Springs; took train to New
                York in coach; helped Pete Lawrance build a greenhouse at home on Long Island;
                Decoration Day Parade</p>
      <p>31- mixed concrete for greenhouse; went to the Lodge for meeting</p>
      <p>June 1917</p>
      <p>1- greenhouse finished; went with Mother to collect rent in Brooklyn and shop; Scout
                meeting; party at the farm school given by Mrs. Johnson</p>
      <p>2- "ran around like a chicken without a nest;" broke up with girlfriend, Harriet
                Lines; went to Louise Hewlitt's house- "any man's girl" but made him feel better</p>
      <p>3- lots of calls at the house; went out with Mother, Katherine Lawson, and Emma
                Foster to church; spent the rest of the day talking with them</p>
      <p>4- last day at home; Mother and Katherine saw him off; homesick; late to Philadelphia
                so must wait to be mustered in; went to the pictures; stayed at Bingham Hotel</p>
      <p>5- must wait until the 7th for Virginia men to arrive; staying with Irwin, from
                Virginia; passing time by eating and watching the pictures</p>
      <p>6- ate at famous Child's Restaurant; did some shopping; went to pictures; finds
                Philadelphia boring- but there are lots of soldiers</p>
      <p>7- went to Armory; learned nothing until later found that they were to meet on the
                morning of the 8th; saw organ recital</p>
      <p>8- now not leaving until the 9th; something secret happened at the hotel; met Mabel
                Beirut; went to show again</p>
      <p>9- transferred to camp; meal; learned how to make cots- "hard as the dickens"</p>
      <p>10- drilled by Corporal Miller; went with Al Store to Central Park to see girls</p>
      <p>11- up early for drills and "fatigue duty;" had to clean whole camp; went downtown
                with Charlie Sheild</p>
      <p>12- guard duty and lots of work around the camp</p>
      <p>13- guard duty; learning to love hash; never had so much work to do</p>
      <p>14- marched in parade; disgusted with meals- not eating much</p>
      <p>15- marched in heat; got shots from Old Lieutenant Klapp- arm got really sore and
                felt sick for a few hours</p>
      <p>16- rotten night with sore arm; girls came to see camp; went dancing</p>
      <p>17- listened to lectures by Major Persous; went to the Post to meet girls and show
                them around camp</p>
      <p>18- marched all morning; went dancing- danced with a professional dancer</p>
      <p>19- drilled for the usual 3 ½ hours; learned First Aid and how to carry the injured;
                went to New Columbia for dinner; at night, went dancing</p>
      <p>20- drilled; Mother visited- showed her all around and went to the pictures</p>
      <p>21- went shopping with Mother; had First Aid training; some friends visited and ate
                ice cream; went on a date to the Orpheus Club</p>
      <p>22- Lieutenant Harley made everyone do exercises; learned rules and regulations; all
                penalties seem to be death; First Aid class; dancing</p>
      <p>23- inspection day- "some kind of Hades;" Allentown for dinner; dancing</p>
      <p>24- played soccer with men; chest expansion decreased; caught "hail Columbia" for not
                saluting older men; met Marie Boyle; second round of immunizations</p>
      <p>25- First Aid class; shots at the hospital; date at the Orpheus Club again</p>
      <p>26- got uniforms- most didn't fit but his did; went with Charlie Sheild to dinner at
                girls' houses</p>
      <p>27- worked in Mess Hall; took driving test in a Ford and became a government
                qualified driver; went to Central Park for a band concert</p>
      <p>28- had cornflakes for breakfast; listened to anatomy lectures; marched downtown in
                uniforms but crowd was quiet</p>
      <p>29- talk on politeness; lecture on aphasias; went downtown to see "Within the Law"
                for the third time</p>
      <p>30- weekly inspection; pay roll- don't get any money yet</p>
      <p>July 1917</p>
      <p>1- service at church was on missionaries in China; dates came to camp and ate with
                the men</p>
      <p>2- exercises; Ford detail; lecture on diseases; date</p>
      <p>3- usual work around barracks; went to the Orpheus Club to see a cheap vaudeville</p>
      <p>4- shopping; lots of visitors to camp; ladies made "rare promises" </p>
      <p>5- lecture on wounds; more immunizations at hospital; dancing</p>
      <p>6- marched in very hot weather; afternoon lectures</p>
      <p>7- inspection; took train to New York; went to eat with Ethel Stillson at Westbury
                Garden Inn; saw Margaret Cocks; Scouts visited</p>
      <p>8- visited Aunt Lee; saw Central Park; back to camp</p>
      <p>9- drove around in the rain; went downtown for dinner; visited a steel works 46 miles
                away</p>
      <p>10- drove to Philadelphia; date with Marie Boyle</p>
      <p>11- worked as orderly- sweeping; went downtown for lunch with Mother; in evening, had
                to stay at camp instead of going downtown</p>
      <p>12- have been issued raincoats; lunch and dinner with Mother</p>
      <p>13- drilled in the street; not much happened despite being Friday the 13th</p>
      <p>16- new schedule with less rest time; took Mr. and Mrs. Henderson out for a drive;
                went on a merry-go-round</p>
      <p>17- new schedule is very difficult- more drill time</p>
      <p>23- got up early to pack for hike; hiked 12 miles to Oakland Park with only 3 rests;
                packs taken by truck back to camp</p>
      <p>24- got up early again; hiked to Fishkill Park- 8 miles</p>
      <p>25- rode in the Ambulance after guard duty; went dancing</p>
      <p>26- hiked back to Fishkill Park; then hiked back to Oakland Park; had lots of food
                and lots of mosquitoes</p>
      <p>August 1917</p>
      <p>3- left Oakland Park early; received orders that Section 17 (his section) was to pack
                up immediately for France- greeted with much joy; got new uniforms, utensils, and
                canteens; Mother came down to visit</p>
      <p>4- telegram from Margaret Cocks</p>
      <p>5- not allowed to leave camp; lots of visitors came to see them off; played card
                game, 500, with other men</p>
      <p>6- expected orders but still in Allentown; spent day with Mother; hours are numbers-
                expect to leave in morning</p>
      <p>7- took train to Jersey City and boarded a boat to wait for the rest of the convoy;
                very hot quarters because beside the boiler room; feeling homesick</p>
      <p>8- could see Long Island and three other ships- The Antilles, Henderson, and[ Finland
                Leuope ?] and his own ship called San Jacinto; some men assigned to submarine
                duty</p>
      <p>9- won some card games; passed a few friendly ships; better food</p>
      <p>10- still at sea; enjoying watch because not in the bottom of the boat; sat in crow's
                nest and spotted another ship</p>
      <p>11- morning exercises; beautiful sunrise; played cards all day</p>
      <p>12- some men spotted a German submarine and shots were fired; then two huge American
                tankers scared everyone</p>
      <p>13- less sleep; played cards; thinking of Harriet Lines often</p>
      <p>14- getting bumps and blisters from the boat</p>
      <p>18- lots of training exercises; ships travelling in zigzag direction; strike aboard
                the Finland- crushed</p>
      <p>19- kept watch; saw lots of fishing boats; choppy seas; feeling very anxious</p>
      <p>20- spotted land on watch and more submarines; shots very fired again- very scary;
                but landed safely</p>
      <p>21- got off boat- sick; large camp used by French and English; will leave soon; also
                lots of prisoners</p>
      <p>22- walked around; all women are "crooked;" have to sleep on the ground</p>
      <p>23- drilled all day; got pass downtown to sample wines; back to camp by 9</p>
      <p>24- went on a 9 mile run/hike; played guitar and talked until bed</p>
      <p>25- Captain Berry mixed up orders so inspection took a long time; talked to a German
                prisoner who said war was not great; pass downtown- but what happened is secret</p>
      <p>26- walked toward La Baule; listened to a concert by Marines at Y.M.C.A. </p>
      <p>27- drilled; washed clothes; played and sang at night</p>
      <p>28- very windy- hard to keep tents in place; guard duty</p>
      <p>29- drill was miserable in the rain; had lecture on First Aid</p>
      <p>30- all day hike- 5 miles past La Baule; saw German submarine that had been captured
                by an American crew</p>
      <p>31- another hike to Nantes- very tiring (15 miles) </p>
      <p>September 1917</p>
      <p>1- forgot mess kit in inspection so had to work as orderly all day; wrote letters and
                read papers all day; wished to hear from Harriet Lines</p>
      <p>2- went to Nantes- saw cathedral, castle, and gardens ("if a person has seen one, he
                has them all"); went to Hotel Europe for dinner; two boys got "tight" (drunk?); he
                and Doc Willis caught by guard when coming back to camp late</p>
      <p>3- had tent pitching contests- Section 17 won; got extra sugar and butter; snuck out
                of camp to get dinner</p>
      <p>4- punishment for coming in late- guard duty all day in full equipment while other
                boys went for a hike</p>
      <p>5- convoy came in; went downtown</p>
      <p>6- challenged to football game by Section 1- tie; signal drill; tore new breeches and
                lost two 10 dollar gold pieces</p>
      <p>7- payday</p>
      <p>8- supervised a gang of German soldiers; saw French acrobats perform at the Y.M.C.A. </p>
      <p>9- went downtown and moved fright cars around (can be pushed by 5 men) ; then moved
                bags of oats and hay</p>
      <p>10- Ford detail at the docks- putting together cars; supervised another German gang
                because knows German well</p>
      <p>11- received orders to go to the Front with Section 93; issued overcoats, heavy
                underwear, and blankets; cutting hair in preparation to leave</p>
      <p>12- first mail from home; first class private appointed- Leathem, Irwin, and
                Saunders; Jack Bocock got his commission; was appointed mechanic</p>
      <p>13- Pat Calloway appointed top sergeant; Bishop also appointed mechanic- very bossy,
                a "typical roughneck and murders his English;" Ford detail; took Louis Astor out-
                bad driver</p>
      <p>14- replaced broken springs; sang songs together at night</p>
      <p>15- changed and cleaned all the spark plugs; went downtown one last time</p>
      <p>16- Sections 17, 93, 10, and 85 left in ambulances; many tire punctures along the
                road which he and Bishop had to fix; stopped in Saint-Nazaire, Nantes, and
                Angers</p>
      <p>17- on the road again; more tire punctures; stopped in Le Mans and
                Nogent-Le-Rotrou</p>
      <p>18- stopped in Chartres to see Cathedral; lots of tire punctures; passed through
                Maintenon and Rambouillet; stopped in Neuilly-Sur-Seine- lots of Americans; very
                happy to finally be in Paris</p>
      <p>19- toured American Hospital No. 1; repaired cars</p>
      <p>20- exercises; French lessons at hospital; drove through streets- saw lots of ladies;
                thinks Paris is cliché and the Eiffel Tower too big</p>
      <p>21- given new rules and regulations</p>
      <p>22- two inspections</p>
      <p>October 1917</p>
      <p>27- orders to drive to the Front for New York State elections</p>
      <p>28- went to see his "Petite" – Parisian women are good to men with money</p>
      <p>29- ran errands for command center in Chateau in Paris</p>
      <p>30- up early to drive north for voting for New York elections; driving all over
                collecting votes</p>
      <p>31- driving south through Montreuil-sur-Mer to Douriez, then to Arras- in complete
                ruins; almost ran into German trenches- fired at</p>
      <p>November 1917</p>
      <p>1- another raid- very close to being hit; drove to Verdun- under fire again; raids
                were very scary</p>
      <p>2- drove all day again; very cold and wet- felt as if going to freeze</p>
      <p>3- broke a front spring; finally arrived in Peronne; misses men in Paris</p>
      <p>4- last day of the trip; finally back in Paris</p>
      <p>5- rested; leaving Paris again tomorrow</p>
      <p>6- said goodbye to Mr. Osterheit; car trouble- punctures and bad engines along the
                road</p>
      <p>7- passed through Troyes; had lunch in Bar-sur-Seine- huge mob watched them eat; lots
                of rain; spent night in Nogent</p>
      <p>8- saw the remains of a German zeppelin in Bourbonne-les-Bains; ate lunch in
                Plombieres-les-Bains; spent night in Remiremont, where there is a prison camp; all
                the cars seemed to be in pretty good condition</p>
      <p>9- drove to Rupt-sur-Moselle; washed cars- from brown to green; not sleeping well</p>
      <p>10- took an old Frenchman on tour of inspection; one of the cars wrecked so tried to
                fix it the best he could- had to go back to Remiremont for parts</p>
      <p>11-trouble starting the cars because the engines were wet- late start; stopped in
                Belfort; finally reached Rougemont-le-Chateau, new headquarters</p>
      <p>12- taught Phil Johnson how to drive; divided up cars with Bishop to split
                responsibilities; Guggenheim was bombed and Joe Fee was in the area- anxious to see
                him</p>
      <p>13- can hear bullets; helped fix up cars; fighting in the camp between the Frenchmen
                and Americans</p>
      <p>14- lots of airplanes and troops coming through; bombing</p>
      <p>15- went scouting for escape roads in case of bombardment with Lieutenant Harley;
                went through Lachapelle-sous-Rougemont and a place near Guggenheim; saw shell hole
                along the way; very cold</p>
      <p>16- fixed up cars; found a hayloft to sleep in but had to move as it was being used
                as a distillery; new place has rats</p>
      <p>17- on orders from Lieutenant Dobes, went to the Front with Jack Leathem and Jimy
                Howell- could hear the cracking of rifles; went to the famous Hotel Hartman for
                dinner</p>
      <p>18- went to the market with the Frenchman; mail came in the afternoon- now feeling
                very homesick</p>
      <p>19- hearing shells has become a usual event; went out driving with Phil Johnson;
                still feeling homesick</p>
      <p>20- took the Medecin Chief Divisionaire on a tour of inspection; went very near the
                trenches- could hear whizzing of bullets</p>
      <p>21- cold and dark; went with Leathem to get coffee at Café Hartman all day; car broke
                down so didn't go to the Front</p>
      <p>22- worked on Joe Fee's car and then the staff car; went driving with Dutch Miller
                and Jack Leathem and then to Hartman's; not cloudy tonight so they expect gas
                bombs</p>
      <p>23- working on Hudson Rogers' car so missed paymaster- will have to wait 2 months</p>
      <p>24- cleaned Jimy Howell's car; Jack Leathem is at Masevaux- lots of injured because
                he had already made two trips to Belfort; Duke Fenwick has been sent out and got
                lost; very clear weather- can see the Alps</p>
      <p>25- fixed up Phil Sheild's car from a crash in secret; borrowed money since he missed
                pay; sitting in Hartman's drinking coffee; Lieutenant Dobes has left for Paris</p>
      <p>26- partied last night and drunkenly told the sergeant to go to hell- serving guard
                duty as a punishment; worked repairing punctures</p>
      <p>27- went to Masevaux with Jimmy Jones and bought a Browne Autographic; drove back
                with Duke Fenwick to work on Johnnie Woods' car; received nine letters in the mail;
                air raid last night- expecting another one</p>
      <p>28- worked on Phil Sheild's car; drove out to collect wood- crashed into a ditch; got
                back to camp late; went out with Leathem and Fenwick to buy food</p>
      <p>29- Thanksgiving- lots of food; walked the aviation field with Leathem and Duke- saw
                a man killed and his machine burned</p>
      <p>30- tried to go to Masevaux for a bath with Duke- but no warm water; did drills at
                camp; boys at Front being bombed quite heavily; had party with Duke- eating cheese,
                fruit cake, and champagne</p>
      <p>December 1917</p>
      <p>1- lots of snow; planning to work on Dick Baker's and Pete Muir's cars when they get
                back from Masevaux; lots of German planes overhead- but no bombs</p>
      <p>2- wrote letters back home with Jack Leathem; Duke is out in a heavily bombed area;
                boys brought in pieces of shells found along a road</p>
      <p>3- finished work on Pete Muir's car; both Pete Muir and Dick Baker had to go to
                Belfort for gas patients; had to drive to the Front because heard one of the boys
                was injured- false alarm</p>
      <p>4- went to Masevaux to buy a few things; fixed Phil Sheild's car again because he had
                driven off the road; waited until he got all the injured men to the hospital; Jimmy
                Moore's car was covered with bullet holes when he returned to camp- will probably
                get the Croix de Guerre</p>
      <p>5- so cold that there was lots of trouble with the cars; Darwin's car overturned and
                he disappeared- had to drive to the Front to collect the wounded men</p>
      <p>6- went with Bill Jones to tow Johnnie Woods' car- false alarm; lots of artillery
                fire</p>
      <p>7- more mail delivered; took pictures of cars with Leathem; felt lonely and sad;
                hasn't had a wash in a while</p>
      <p>8- French general arrived at camp and complained that his patients were not being
                well cared for- found that it was one of the Section 93 boys</p>
      <p>9- going to be awarded sergeant's rating- with Charlie Fox as a helper and Bishop
                demoted to a private; Lieutenant Abbey hit a horse</p>
      <p>10- annoyed at bad management; advised that he will get the Chief Mechanic rating;
                French taking down German planes</p>
      <p>11- went to Masevaux to collect his picture prints; lots of work on cars- put in
                brake linings</p>
      <p>12- car work; air raid while on the road to fix Rogers' car- only one on road</p>
      <p>13- lots of planes overhead; worked on cars; played association football and later
                cards with Leathem, Fenwick, and Fox</p>
      <p>14- finished working on Rogers' car; then worked on "Noisy" Tilghman's broken
                radiator; wrote letter home- missing Harriet Lines</p>
      <p>15- may go on repos- days of drilling and marching; fixed a couple punctures;
                received a writing kit from Ethel and Fred Reinhardt</p>
      <p>16- afraid that they will have to move; repaired magnets with Charlie Fox; Duke went
                out to "Massvolt-" as he calls it</p>
      <p>17- woke up to loud thundering; drove to Front- shell hit right behind him; played
                card with Leathem, Fox, and Duke</p>
      <p>18- got pay- two months behind; paid off 20 dollars of his Christmas Bonds; went to
                Masevaux for value connections; got a pass to go to Belfort with Bill Jones who had
                too much to drink</p>
      <p>19- worked on Pete Muir's car; gave talk on Fords; issued oilskins and knee boots;
                went downtown with Leathem- saw happy troops coming in from the Front; played cards
                and ate cake</p>
      <p>20- went to Belfort with Vaughn; bought a watch; left Vaughn because it was
                curfew</p>
      <p>21- went out to fix a puncture; orders to leave Rougemont-le-Chateau on Monday the
                24th </p>
      <p>22- went out after Hathaway to fix car; in afternoon, went with Leathem to Belfort to
                change the watch; wrote Elise a letter in French telling her he loved her</p>
      <p>23- skipped breakfast with Leathem- the Lieutenant had to wake them; worked on
                Tilghman's car</p>
      <p>24- started all the Fords in the morning and drove to Lauw- open kitchen and no
                garage; went to Masevaux, Guewenheim, and Roderen to give the boys their meals; went
                to church and a party</p>
      <p>25- sad Christmas because away from home; had to drive to Masevaux, Guenwenheim, and
                Roderen two times; lots of food, music, and dancing</p>
      <p>26- drove to the Front to bring the troops some food; had order to help Joe Fee- no
                oil; delivered messages to Sentheim and Masevaux</p>
      <p>27- visited Doc at Masevaux- had coffee together; went downtown with Leathem later to
                get coffee; the closer to Germany, the worse the beer</p>
      <p>28- so cold the cars wouldn't start; lots of errands and work; </p>
      <p>29- had problems starting the cars again; lots of shooting; worked on Willis's and
                Phil Sheild's car</p>
      <p>30- drove to Roderen- heavily shelled road; then went back to Masevaux to pick up
                photo prints; went out after dinner to visit Doc- drank two quarts of champagne</p>
      <p>31- accomplished a lot of work in the morning; went to Café Auguste Meyer with
                Leathem; fell asleep before new year</p>
      <p>January 1918</p>
      <p>1- slept in- had to rush to get cars ready; had to drive to Masevaux to fix Sheild's
                car- visited Doc and his wife on the way; gossiped about girls with the boys</p>
      <p>2- drove M. de Baron to Masevaux- rough ride</p>
      <p>3- lots of planes overhead- saw one shot and men escape with parachutes</p>
      <p>4- started the cars in the morning; sat by the fire for the rest of the day; had a
                call from Mark Skinner- but he managed to fix his car</p>
      <p>5- lots of car trouble in the morning; got a haircut for 10 cents; started back for
                Rougemont-le-Chateau; stopped at Hartman's; Johnson and Baker have left for
                Paris</p>
      <p>6- went from Belfort to Lachapelle-sous-Rougemont to Rougemont-le-Chateau fixing cars
                all day</p>
      <p>7- had to work on Bill Jones' car; got package from Thanksgiving; wrote letters home;
                Pete Muir stuck in the road so had to borrow Leathem's car</p>
      <p>8- worked on cars in the morning; had to drive to Masevaux to fix Bill Jones' car;
                Leathem felt bad</p>
      <p>9- Leathem sick so Duke took his place at Guewenheim; worked on Hathaway's and Fee's
                cars; feeling sick and tired</p>
      <p>10- 25 inches of snow; trouble starting the cars; Jim Moore got a Croix de Guerre</p>
      <p>11- first time in two weeks that all the cars started; called to help a car that was
                200 yards from the German lines- shot at with machine guns; had to lay in the ditch
                until dark</p>
      <p>12- many airplanes; went to Masevaux to work on a few cars; Johnnie Woods out of the
                hospital and acting as cook; wants to transfer away</p>
      <p>13- French fired hundreds of shots at airplanes- but didn't hit one of them; worked
                on cars in afternoon; many of friends were drinking red wine- but had to take
                Lieutenant Dobes to Rougemont-le-Chateau</p>
      <p>14- picked up Lieutenant Dobes from Rougemont-le-Chateau; Sheild said that the
                Germans were shelling Sentheim- may leave soon</p>
      <p>15- went to hospital- feet are frostbitten and had a bad cold; given 36 pills and
                order to soak feet for three hours a day; friends came to visit at the hospital</p>
      <p>16- still in the hospital; almost every boy in the section has stopped in to visit;
                raid on the French trenches</p>
      <p>17- depressed after reading letters from home- Mother is lending out his Cadillac;
                cold</p>
      <p>18- felt better so left hospital a little bit to work on cars; played cards with the
                French</p>
      <p>19- very warm at night; hoping for a discharge from the hospital soon; some in the
                hospital are sick, but most are just lazy; likes the Medecin Chef</p>
      <p>20- watching airplanes and piece of shrapnel landed 10 feet away- scared it was a gas
                bomb; French are terrible at aviation</p>
      <p>21- watched airplanes at camp; French need much better airplanes in order to fight
                the Germans; Lieutenant Dobes left from Remiremont</p>
      <p>22- slept in the barn with the boys; leaving hospital; cars are not clean so lots of
                work ahead</p>
      <p>23- still sick; Bishop has taken place in the shop</p>
      <p>24- warm weather- helped out with some of the cars; went with Charlies Fox to
                Masevaux- air raid, but had gas masks</p>
      <p>25- went out to repair Doc's car- shot at by machine guns and had to pretend to be
                dead</p>
      <p>26- had to wear gas mask because of numerous bombs; felt so sick- back in the
                infirm</p>
      <p>27- laid in bed without sleeping; still planning on getting a commission in another
                department</p>
      <p>28- Lieutenant Dobes came to visit; diagnosed with trench itch from un sanitary
                conditions; has to bathe two times a day</p>
      <p>29- scratched all night; lots of sick people</p>
      <p>30- losing Mechanics rating- hard getting it back; asked to move to headquarters</p>
      <p>31- waiting for Jack Leathem to return; Vaughn and Fenwick leaving; learned a little
                more French</p>
      <p>February 1918</p>
      <p>1- no word from Jack Leathem; French are not good fighters</p>
      <p>2- had rating officially reduced; played cards with the Frenchmen</p>
      <p>3- asked Lieutenant Dobes for a transfer- choked him; played cards with Jim Moore,
                Duke, and Baker; still no word from Leathem</p>
      <p>4- very worried about Leathem- still no news; deserters are punished with ten years
                of hard labor</p>
      <p>5- no word from Leathem; treated very nicely in the infirm- but itch is getting
                better</p>
      <p>6- word that Jack Leathem is in American Hospital #2; given new uniforms- much
                needed; bought some good medicine in Masevaux</p>
      <p>7- his itch is better; will be out in one week; watched good airplane fight</p>
      <p>8- Pete Muir to get Croix de Guerre; inspection soon</p>
      <p>9- 3 new boys for section; wants to leave ambulance corps; new trenches- barbed wire
                everywhere</p>
      <p>10- went to Masevaux for writing paper and figs; met Marguerite- date next Sunday</p>
      <p>11- nice weather; only a few cars at Masevaux now; lots of artillery</p>
      <p>12- captured German officer and stripped him of his buttons; bought dates and had
                film developed in Masevaux; helped Johnson fix his car after dinner</p>
      <p>13- shells falling so can't use roads; will move soon for car safety</p>
      <p>14- captured a bunch of Germans; waiting for his pictures to be developed</p>
      <p>15- talked to Lieutenant Dobes about transferring and promotions; had a "gunning"
                session with Jim Moore</p>
      <p>16- felt sick; lots of shells; Vaughn left- sorry to see him go</p>
      <p>17- Bishop was annoying and bossy; size of army is getting smaller but will not give
                up</p>
      <p>18- Bishop leaving many cars in bad shape; still lots of firing</p>
      <p>19- worked on Charlie Tompkins' car; played a game of 500 with Rust, Tompkins, and
                Fox</p>
      <p>20- worked on Fee's car; still has to report to infirmary for baths; had "gunning"
                session around the fire</p>
      <p>21- got 500 dollars worth of insurance; Frenchmen gave them pointers on battle</p>
      <p>22- making final preparations to leave- checked tires and spark plugs</p>
      <p>23- got up early to leave- went to Guewenheim, Roderen, and Sentheim; one car that
                Bishop supposedly fixed broke down (continued in Memoranda) </p>
      <p>24- attack on Germans failed- will not get their Croix de Guerres; heavy bombing and
                fire- lots of wounded; talked to Marguerite for a while</p>
      <p>25- Germans bombed and gassed a camp at Mortzwiller; lots of work at the Front;
                mail</p>
      <p>26- air raid; worked on cars all day; poker game at night</p>
      <p>27- fixed tires; went out with Lieutenant Dobes to Niederbruck on motorcycle; played
                cards with some of the Frenchmen</p>
      <p>28- snow-disgusted; picked up motorcycle with Bill Jones; Shack, Hathaway, and Doc
                Belle started on their permission </p>
      <p>March 1918</p>
      <p>1- worked on motorcycle; had to get wood- hard because the roads are closed</p>
      <p>2- air fights this morning- German planes in flames; lots of work to be done on
                cars</p>
      <p>3- have to keep moving the garage because of bombs</p>
      <p>4- Charlie Jenkins, Heath, and Maclin were at S.P.A. 46; a bunch of boys from the
                States are joining; played cards in the evening</p>
      <p>5- saw Italian troops; works on cars and the motorcycle; went to Belfort</p>
      <p>6- patched tires and worked on motorcycle; went to Masevaux and found a place to
                bathe for one franc; went for a walk to Sentheim with Duke and Jimmy Moore </p>
      <p>7- put in new brake bands and radiators; 4 planes fell; went for a walk</p>
      <p>8- went over Masevaux to visit Docs; climbed tress with Duke; fixed Jim Moore's car;
                poker game in the evening</p>
      <p>9- skipped morning exercises; visited Masevaux; played baseball; more action each
                day</p>
      <p>10- worked on cars because inspecting officer was coming; had to rescue Fenwick;
                Germans stealing cars</p>
      <p>11- got some letters from November; stayed in Masevaux for the night- but didn't get
                in trouble</p>
      <p>12- worked in garage in the morning; then went out with Vaughn, looking for pigs</p>
      <p>13- had to make a schedule of repairs for Lieutenant Dobes; went to Masevaux with the
                Lieutenant and got a shave; kicked football with the boys</p>
      <p>14- lots of work on cars; dusk came early- very dark; worked on Bill Jones' car a
                little; went for a walk with Duke</p>
      <p>15- went to exercises for the first time in two weeks; worked on Bill Jones' car;
                lots of shooting; Leathem wrote to say he was coming back</p>
      <p>16- took M. de Redon to Masevaux and Rougemont-le-Chateau; worked with Bill Jones' on
                his car; walked out for coffee in the evening</p>
      <p>17- finally finished Bill Jones' car; drove out to the highest point in the Alsace
                region with Astor, Bishop, and Jones; went for a walk with Duke Fenwick in the
                evening</p>
      <p>18- more testing of Bill Jones' car; Jack Leathem returned- visited Auguste Myers
                with Duke and stayed up quite late</p>
      <p>19- clutch is burning in Bill Jones' car because there is not enough oil; patched
                tires; French raided the German lines; Leathem left again this morning</p>
      <p>20- went to Belfort for parts- saw Germaine Hubert; J. Jones, Astor, and Tilghman
                left on their permission; went to Masevaux with Duke</p>
      <p>21- fixed motors in the morning- but had a headache; new boy from Section 16; took
                lots of pictures of the moon</p>
      <p>22- got up for morning exercises; tested finished cars</p>
      <p>23- news of a German offensive; went to Belfort with Skinner- air raid and people
                went crazy running for shelter</p>
      <p>24- slept in until 11; worked in the garage; took and walk to take pictures; went to
                Belfort</p>
      <p>25- orders came sending them to an English camp- later cancelled; worked on Tompkins'
                car</p>
      <p>27- Lieutenant Dobes went to Roderen and found that the Bourbach-le-Bas to Rodern
                Road was shelled badly; Lachapelle-sous-Rougemont being evacuated; John Wood,
                Charles Tompkins, Richard Baker, and Jimmy Jones received their Croix de Guerres</p>
      <p>28- French division is leaving but ambulance corps must stay; drove to
                Lachapelle-sous-Rougemont, Rougemont, and Masevaux; confined to quarters for a week
                for leaving without a pass</p>
      <p>29- worked on Bill Jones' car; lots of shells</p>
      <p>30- worked in the garage; ran a couple errands</p>
      <p>April 1918</p>
      <p>3- on the road- passed through Rougemont-le-Chateau and Lure; Rogers and Fee had flat
                tires; arrived at camp in Fayl-Billot- good quarters; had to tow the staff car with
                Charlie Tompkins</p>
      <p>4- got up early to work on the staff car and motorcycle; drove to Langres to get
                clutch repaired; had lots of car problems on the road- blow out, no gas; got lost in
                Chaumont; finally arrived in camp at Vendeuvre-sur-Barse</p>
      <p>5- very long day; drove through Troyes, Mery-sur-Seine, Granges-sur-Aube, Anglure,
                Sezanne, and Montmirail; in territory that was occupied by the Germans; saw an
                American division; had two quarts of milk</p>
      <p>6- lots of punctures on the road; drove to Meaux to fix cars; continued a bit further
                to stop just outside Paris- right near an American aviation school</p>
      <p>7- up early to finish the trip at Beuavais; lots of trouble with cars along the
                way</p>
      <p>8- worked on Hudson Rogers and Joe Fee's cars; living in a chateau built in the
                thirteenth century and owned by Rothschild; most people in the area speak
                English</p>
      <p>9- worked on Phil Sheild's car; got spare parts from Beauvais; met up with boys from
                Section 92 and partied together at a nearby café</p>
      <p>10- worked on cars with Willis; went for a walk with Duke; raining hard</p>
      <p>12- orders to leave Beauvais; drove to Goincourt; developed a very bad cold</p>
      <p>13- drove into Beauvais; lost convoy- but finally managed to get to Fourdrinoy, near
                Amiens?; slept in a barn with mice</p>
      <p>14- left in the afternoon for a British hanger- sleeping the in open; went over to
                the British Y.M.C.A. but they won't sell Americans candy</p>
      <p>15- helped cook breakfast- cut off a nail; worked on Duke's car; may travel to Ypres
                to meet up with French division again</p>
      <p>16- Amiens was on fire; worked on Jones' car; drove to Picquigny; bought food at the
                Y.M.C.A.; talked about fighting experiences with a Canadian</p>
      <p>17- moved to Picquigny- good sleeping quarters; fixed a man's car for five francs;
                bought chocolate and cigarette</p>
      <p>18- moved a little north to a small town- most building made of mud; rain/hail all
                day- miserable</p>
      <p>19- orders to move to Ivergny-car and map trouble; quarters filled with rats; all
                French town- but Canadian lumber camp nearby</p>
      <p>20- cleaned motor heads and tested all motors; bombardment at Arras</p>
      <p>21- warmer day so all men cleaned and shaved; tried to steal chickens; at dark,
                Germans started bombing</p>
      <p>22- man broke arm at the lumber camp- so stayed and bathed while Jim Moore helped
                him; collected wood</p>
      <p>23- more order to move to Buneville; Pete Muir's car had three broken bolts; went
                with Charlie Tompkins to Saint-Pol-sur-Ternoise- but had to leave quickly because of
                bombs</p>
      <p>24- work on cars; had to wear gas masks because of German tear gas</p>
      <p>25- tried to make a gasket for Pete Muir's car- had to tow; not many planes</p>
      <p>26- went for a walk near Saint-Pol-sur-Ternoise; there is a cave where all the
                villagers sleep because of the bombs</p>
      <p>27- orders to move but Pete Muir's car kept breaking down; arrived in Renty late</p>
      <p>28- moving again; passed through Cassel; truck broke down; lots of bombs</p>
      <p>29- hit traffic ("a regular 5th Avenue'); terrible bombardment</p>
      <p>30- hard to sleep because of all the bombs; went with Lieutenant Dobes to a Parc at
                Dunkerque; saw prisoners- looked very sick; also saw bad car accident</p>
      <p>May 1918</p>
      <p>1- talked to Jim Moore; went to Y.M.C.A.; so much artillery it was deafening and the
                ground shook</p>
      <p>2- guns all night long; orders to move to Remy; really irritated by noise from
                bombs</p>
      <p>3- bought candy, cigarettes, and food; going to evacuate to Mount Kimmel- the worst
                place on the Front</p>
      <p>4- drove to the Front- men, horse, cars, building lying everywhere; very forlorn and
                sad trip</p>
      <p>5- fixed up cars all day; one day is blending into the next; shrapnel is terrible</p>
      <p>6- worked on Pete Muir and Rust's cars; bomb hit camp- but no one was hurt; boys in
                other sections are wounded though</p>
      <p>7- up early fixing cars; took apart two broken ones to make one new car; stayed up
                through the night fixing cars; lots of tear gas; had to drive out to help Vaughn;
                Charlie Tompkins' car was smashed by a shell; Jimmy Howell and Fee both crashed</p>
      <p>8- bombardment at its worst; Charlie Fox was gassed and had to go to the hospital; no
                sleep for over 24 hours; fully expect to be killed</p>
      <p>9- woke up early to go help Wood, Fee, and Howell at the Front; worked on Baker and
                Willis' cars; drove through Poperinge- used to have over 20,000 people but now not a
                soul in sight; bombs and shells will make a man go crazy</p>
      <p>10- quieting down; got spare parts from Dunkerque with Lieutenant Dobes; French
                captures 200 men</p>
      <p>11- had to tow Howell- "shells were dropping and gas was thick;" lots of planes; went
                through Poperinge again- terrible sight</p>
      <p>12- average day on the Front- but lots more noise than in Alsace region; lots of work
                to do</p>
      <p>13- went to Dunkerque for a new car; heavy bombardment for a few hours; more
                divisions arriving to help</p>
      <p>14- little to do because other divisions took over; terrible barrage; caught Flemish
                fever</p>
      <p>15- sick; lots of shells</p>
      <p>16- left camp after breakfast; drove through Poperinge- cars had a bit of trouble;
                stopped near Dunkerque- lots of air craft fire</p>
      <p>17- started overhauling Jimmy Jones' car; tried to get a new car- failed; English
                airplane bombed the camp by accident</p>
      <p>18- up very early to finish Jones' car because had new orders to leave; drove to
                Loon-Plage; set to work on building a camp; went downtown for food</p>
      <p>19- church bells rang for a while in the morning- wants to go to church but all are
                Catholic; put new bands on Fenwick and Moore's cars; two new boys joined- Cohen and
                Clark; went downtown for beer</p>
      <p>20- German propaganda on the radio announced 200 planes and lots of bombing- no one
                believed it; needed more spare parts to work on cars</p>
      <p>21- told Lieutenant Dobes about plans to leave- must wait until the section gets a
                new mechanic; wants to go back to school and see Mother</p>
      <p>24- went to the Parc for the new car- very stiff wheel; also brought back Baker and
                Fee's cars in "A condition" </p>
      <p>25- went to a farm and bought milk; drove to Cassel and Saint-Omer-Capelle and then
                back to camp</p>
      <p>27- received Croix de Guerre</p>
      <p>Memoranda</p>
      <p>Page 184- Copy of Speech by Medicine Chief Divisionnaire on January 9th, 1918- about
                James Moore receiving his Croix de Guerre</p>
      <p>Page 186- Entry from February 23rd, 1918 continued</p>
      <p>Page 192- Description of Peter Lawrance</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
