<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04089">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04089::A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers)//EN" "viu04089.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">O'Brien, Nancy, Papers 
                    <num type="collectionnumber">14815</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">14815</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Nancy O'Brien Papers <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">14815</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">ca. 4000 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Nancy O'Brien Papers, Accession #14815, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisitions</head>
        <p>The papers were a gift to the University of Virginia Library from Nancy O'Brien on August 31, 2009.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Nancy Kilpatrick O'Brien was born in Newark, New Jersey in 1936. From
                1954-1957 she attended Massachusetts General Hospital School of Nursing
                earning her nursing degree. She became active in politics at age thirty-nine when
                she moved to Charlottesville because her husband, Dr. William O'Brien accepted a
                position in Internal Medicine at the University of Virginia. She joined the Women's
                League of Voters and was appointed Treasurer of the Thomas Jefferson Planning
                District Commission by City Council in 1973-1974, and Chairman in 1974. She
                ran for City Council and was elected first woman mayor of Charlottesville in 1976.
                She also served on many community organizations including the Jefferson School Task
                Force, the Community Development Task Force, the Advisory Committee on the South
                Rivanna Reservoir study and many housing committees. She also worked as a
                facilitator to improve the services of many community service organizations. Early
                in her political career she met Francis Fife, a former mayor of Charlottesville
                (1972-1974) who later became her second husband. She has four children.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The papers of Mayor Nancy O'Brien contain correspondence, political campaign
                information, and topical files regarding many issues that were facing the city of
                Charlottesville, Virginia from 1973 to 1981; [1982-2008]. The correspondence
                includes general correspondence, letters to the Mayor about routine issues, and
                congratulations from political figures such as Charles S. Robb, Thomas J. Michie,
                Tim Kaine, J. Kenneth Robinson, and Mark Warner. The political files include
                information about upcoming primaries. The topical files reflect O'Brien's interest
                in the community with a particular focus on the development of strong neighborhood
                communities, economic development, city annexation, city planning, housing, and
                local transportation issues. The collection contains ca. 4000 items and 22 Hollinger
                boxes which make up 9 linear feet.</p>
      <p>Specific economic issues mentioned are the construction and revitalization plan of
                the Downtown Mall, the decision to construct the Fashion Square Mall, plans for the
                Vinegar Hill area ten years after it had been destroyed and then left abandoned, and
                the designation of Fifeville as a historic neighborhood. There are also
                Charlottesville Albemarle Transportation Studies on the Meadowcreek Parkway, and
                extension of McIntire Road, Schenks Branch, and Preston Avenue. Other events
                mentioned are Queen Elizabeth's visit to Charlottesville for the bicentennial,
                racial diversity, and a sister cities program.</p>
      <p>There are also minutes and correspondence from City Council and strategies for
                sharing services between the City and the County. There are similarly joint
                committees between the City and the University of Virginia. Of particular interest
                regarding the University is a photocopy of a letter written by Thomas Jefferson
                about the opening of the University of Virginia.</p>
      <p>There are also student papers from 1983-1986 when O'Brien obtained a Masters
                degree in Public Administration at the University of Virginia (after being Mayor).
                There are also papers from when O'Brien taught planning courses (on Fifeville) at
                the University. There is a copy of her thesis (and thesis research) on Planning
                District Commissions in Virginia. (Series II UVA Graduate Student and Professor)
                There are also papers from her work as executive director of the Thomas Jefferson
                Planning Commission [1979-2006] (Series III TJPDC) and papers from her
                private work in which she acted as a facilitator for agencies that served the needs
                of the community. (Series V Facilitator) There are a few papers from her work with
                the Housing Authority.</p>
      <p>There are also minutes from the Jefferson School Task Force which was appointed by
                City Council to preserve Jefferson School as a historical institution. Included is
                information about grant funding (Bama funds from the Dave Mathews Band) and
                information about the history of Jefferson School and early African American life in
                Charlottesville. There are copies of photographs from the Rufus Holsinger
                collection. (Series IV Jefferson School)</p>
      <p>There is information on racial diversity from a group titled, "Many Races, One
                Community" which was organized by Nancy O'Brien to address racial tensions. These
                tensions had arisen in 2002 following an occurrence of violence by several African
                American Charlottesville High School students against white University of Virginia
                students. "Many Races, One Community" planned events in an attempt to unite people
                from different cultural experiences. (Series I Mayor and City Council topical files:
                Race)</p>
      <p>There are also speeches of Nancy O'Brien from 1971 to 2008 including when she was
                mayor (Series VI Speeches) and awards, certificates, and a scrapbook of newspaper
                clippings and photographs (Series VII)</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is organized into seven series, Series I Mayor of Charlottesville and
                city council member A. Correspondence files B. Political files C. Topical files;
                Series II UVA classes A. Graduate student B. Professor; Series III Thomas Jefferson
                District Planning Commission; Series IV Jefferson School; Series V Facilitator;
                Series VI Speeches, and Series VII Scrapbook pages, photographs, awards,
                certificates, and trophies</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents Listing</head>
      <c01 id="d1e174" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Mayor of Charlottesville and City Council Member</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e179" level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A. Correspondence Files</unittitle>
            <container/>
          </did>
          <c03 id="d1e184" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> General Correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
              <physdesc>70 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Constituents and colleagues correspond about a variety of issues
                                pertaining to Charlottesville including drainage problems on Meade
                                Avenue, parking tickets, street improvements, preservation of the
                                Fifeville neighborhood, danger and confusion due to duplicate street
                                names, fasting and prayer day, lights and pedestrian safety near the
                                hospital, girls attention home, twin sister city in Italy, policing
                                of Wertland Street, school invitations, and resignations</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e200" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1980; 1992</unitdate> General
                                Correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
              <physdesc>58 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Constituents and colleagues correspond about a variety of issues
                                pertaining to Charlottesville including parking tickets, sidewalks
                                on Old Lynchburg Road and Jefferson Park Avenue, WVPT month,
                                advertisement for convention bureaus, separation of the chamber of
                                commerce from local governments, law week, tennis week, regional
                                jails, attrition of jobs, Charlottesville High School gymnasium,
                                invitations, resignations, and thank you letters. There is a tribute
                                to Bill Elwood. There is also a hate letter addressed to Nancy
                                O'Brien.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e219" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980</unitdate> General Correspondence
                                from children</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
              <physdesc>103 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are letters to the Mayor from school children</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e230" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 July-September</unitdate> Mayor
                                correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
              <physdesc>53 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Letters are organized alphabetically by their original authors,
                                Abernathy-Woodson. Topics include a park off Calhoun Street, a song
                                about Charlottesville, inclusion of more Council members, paving the
                                Charlottesville High School Parking Lot, Community Attention Home
                                Board, DMV use of Wilder Road, Trainees for Rivanna Water and Sewer,
                                a limit on sewer connections, business education class, Youth
                                Employment Service year round, letter of support for Bob Wenger,
                                McGuffey artist space, resignations and appointments, invitations to
                                speak at Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority, and the Bayly Museum and other
                                concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.
                                Included is a handwritten statement by Francis Fife nominating Nancy
                                O'Brien for mayor.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e252" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 October-December</unitdate> Mayor
                                correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
              <physdesc>23 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Letters are organized alphabetically by their authors, Black-Wiley
                                Topics include noise control, list of task force members on the
                                Social Development Commission, industrial development, student city
                                council, paving of Charlottesville High School Parking Lot, Federal
                                and State Library Funds, Community Attention Home for Girls, visit
                                to the Joint Security Complex, Senator James Harry Michael dinner,
                                and resignation of George Wiley from the Planning Commission and
                                other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and
                                citizens.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e271" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 January-April</unitdate> Mayor
                                correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
              <physdesc>36 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Letters are organized alphabetically by their authors,
                                Berman-Williams There is a letter of protest from Mayor O'Brien
                                against the Criminal Justice Planner making public comments about
                                police salaries. Other topics include tax abatement for
                                rehabilitative housing, a workshop on low income housing, economic
                                development, energy conservation, Virginia State Federation of
                                Colored Women's Club Convention in Charlottesville, Sunset Club for
                                senior citizens asking for help with meals, public service
                                corporations to pay taxes, Charlottesville Albemarle Planning
                                Committee for a Cultural Center, invitation to speak to the
                                Delegates at the 43<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">rd</title> Annual Grand
                                Communication, invitation to welcome the Municipal Electric Power
                                Association, Bicentennial commission donation of emergency fuel to
                                the city, coat of arms for the city, bicycle paths, a reference for
                                Doug Venable and various resignations, and other concerns from
                                community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e297" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 May—November</unitdate> Mayor
                                Correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
              <physdesc>41 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Alphabetical: Arnett-Williams Selection of Architects for
                                Library/Post Office renovation (includes correspondence into 1978),
                                McGuffey bid, invitation to speak to the American association of
                                Retired Persons Area Council, funding for additional youth programs,
                                Housing Authority on the Garrett Street Project, Housing Authority
                                to report to City Council, developing a plan with the county for
                                fuel distribution, zoning ordinance, Jefferson Cable, "Dick Gilliam
                                Day," Virginia Council on Health and Medical Care asked for funding,
                                State Air Control Pollution Board, testimony delivered about the
                                Rape Crisis Group, teacher of the year recommendation, Chamber of
                                Commerce was unable to support the Convention Bureau Activities,
                                Virginia National Bank loan to the Housing Authority, resignations
                                and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and
                                citizens.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e321" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Mayor Correspondence</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
              <physdesc>60 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Alphabetical: Aaron-Wood</p>
              <p>Some topics include: The Perry Foundation gave sixty thousand dollars
                                to the city to construct tennis courts at Pen Park, cooperation with
                                the Chamber of Commerce, failure of attrition program, Schenk's
                                Branch Project, school transportation for the hearing impaired
                                (Aaron Farley,) drainage problems on Chesapeake Street,
                                Charlottesville Development Group, Charlottesville Retail
                                Association, "Keep America Beautiful" Campaign, Rivanna Water and
                                Sewer Authority to place a screen over pipes, housing efforts for
                                the handicapped, resignations, appointments, thank you notes for
                                community service, parking for Martha Jefferson Hospital, fuel
                                relief program, sign ordinances, lighting , tax issues, city
                                planning survey, and other concerns from community leaders, parents,
                                businessman and citizens.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e344" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1978</unitdate> General Correspondence
                                Memos of City Council</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
              <physdesc>20 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are memos about the gas rate case, coat of arms, library
                                budget, architects for the library, Virginia Municipal League tour,
                                Conservation Council of Virginia grant for Ivy Creek Natural Area,
                                Centel Board of Directors, donation of "mini-park," railroad plans
                                in the state, bridge on Park Street extended, and legality of the
                                CHIP Program</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e360" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1978</unitdate> General Correspondence
                                Neighborhood Meetings about Budget</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
              <physdesc>44 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>List of neighborhood presidents, capital improvements, newsletters,
                                City Council memos about neighborhood meetings and budget, notes by
                                Nancy O'Brien for a public service announcement encouraging
                                attendance at the meeting, and instructions and invitation to a
                                budget game.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e375" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1978; 2002-2005</unitdate>
                                General correspondence Neighborhood Meetings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
              <physdesc>39 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is correspondence about neighborhood communities such as,
                                Rose Hill, Jefferson Park Avenue, Ridge Street, Greenbrier, Belmont,
                                Fifeville, and Venable</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e388" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1978; 1980; 1998; 1999</unitdate>
                                General Correspondence thank you letters to Nancy
                                O'Brien</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
              <physdesc>9 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Correspondents include Eugene German, Peggy King, Donna P. Massey,
                                Bessie E. Avent, Agnes W. Sullivan, Opal D. David, Thomas B. Leitch,
                                Roger C. Wiley, and Robert Gilmore</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e402" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1986</unitdate> Personal correspondence
                                Nancy O'Brien</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
              <physdesc>20 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are letters from the community about her hair styles,
                                congratulations on receiving her master's degree, thanks for giving
                                a memorial speech at the funeral of Marcia Mashaw, and
                                congratulations on obtaining the position, Executive Director of the
                                Thomas Jefferson Planning Commission. Correspondents include H.
                                Bernhard Ewert II, Carol E. Haberly, Priscilla Whiting, Francis
                                Fife, Carl and MaryJo Ayers, Alice Howard, Mario Cazzamiga, and Opal
                                E. David.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e420">
            <did>
              <unittitle>VIP Correspondence (alphabetical by name of VIP)</unittitle>
              <container/>
            </did>
            <c04 id="d1e425" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 August 3</unitdate> Nancy O'Brien letter
                                    to Senator Harry F. Byrd</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7</container>
                <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>O'Brien wrote letters asking him to support the general revenue
                                    sharing bill.</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e437" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 May-June</unitdate> Nancy O'Brien letter
                                    to John Casteen</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8</container>
                <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>The letter is a response to a form letter sent by the University
                                    asking her (as an Alumnus) for donations to the University.
                                    Nancy O'Brien responded directly to President Casteen that since
                                    the University did not consider their own impact on the
                                    community or on their own poorly paid staff, she would use her
                                    funds to help the community instead of the University.</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e453" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 October 6</unitdate> Nancy O'Brien letter
                                    to Governor Mills E. Godwin</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9</container>
                <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Nancy O'Brien asked the Governor to declare Charlottesville a
                                    drought emergency and grant the City authority to enact
                                    mandatory water conservation ordinances</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e466" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978 February</unitdate> Nancy O'Brien letter
                                    and Frank Hereford</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10</container>
                <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>President Hereford wrote to Nancy O'Brien recommending Dennis
                                    Barnes to serve as the University representative at the
                                    Charlottesville Development Group and Nancy O'Brien thanked
                                    him.</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e480" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 July 25</unitdate> Tim Kaine to Nancy
                                    O'Brien</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11</container>
                <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>He wrote that he enjoyed visiting Nancy and Francis Fife last
                                    week</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e492" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 March 3</unitdate> Thomas J. Michie, Jr.
                                    to Nancy O'Brien</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12</container>
                <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Michie congratulated O'Brien on winning the Democratic nomination
                                    for City Council</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e504" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 July 6</unitdate> Charles S. Robb to Nancy
                                    O'Brien</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13</container>
                <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Charles Robb wrote that he enjoyed meeting her and mentioned that
                                    her office is off to a great start with meeting the Queen of
                                    England and the President of the United States. He wrote, "What
                                    are you going to do for an encore?"</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e518" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 January 4</unitdate> Nancy O'Brien letter
                                    to Charles S. Robb</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14</container>
                <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Nancy O'Brien wrote a letter to Mr. Robb wishing him well in his
                                    campaign for Lieutenant Governor. There is also a letter from
                                    the Secretary of the Commonwealth notifying Nancy that she would
                                    not be appointed on the State Board of Community Colleges.</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e532" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 March 15</unitdate> J. Kenneth Robinson to
                                    Nancy O'Brien</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15</container>
                <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Congressman Robinson wrote Nancy O'Brien that he would be
                                    supportive of H.R. 1522.</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
            <c04 id="d1e544" level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 August 5</unitdate> Governor Mark Warner
                                    to Nancy O'Brien</unittitle>
                <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16</container>
                <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
              </did>
              <scopecontent>
                <p>Governor Warner thanked Nancy for her help in recommending Al
                                    Weed to be appointed member of the Virginia Land Conservation
                                    Foundation Board of Trustees</p>
              </scopecontent>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e559" level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>B. Political Files</unittitle>
            <container/>
          </did>
          <c03 id="d1e564" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> City Council Elections Nancy
                                O'Brien</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17</container>
              <physdesc>115 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>H. Lane Kneedler and Nancy O'Brien ran for City Council. Also running
                                for the three seats were Frank Tomlin, Sherman R. White, Robert W.
                                Stroh, Norman Lushbaugh, Ed Gatewood, and Laurence Brunton. Included
                                are resumes for Nancy O'Brien and H. Lane Kneedler. There are news
                                clippings, campaign flyers, and statements about political beliefs
                                and policies. There are also letters of congratulations to Nancy
                                O'Brien including one from Mrs. Edgar F. Shannon.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e581" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> City Council Elections Thomas Albro
                                and Frank Buck</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18</container>
              <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a statement by Francis Fife announcing that he would not be
                                seeking reelection for City Council Member. There are newspaper
                                clippings and editorials about the campaign in which Frank Buck and
                                Thomas Albro were elected and James Hicks lost.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e595" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> City Council Election Blake
                                Caravati and Alexandra Searls for City Council</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19</container>
              <physdesc>75 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>The e-mails are critical of Alexandra Searls. There are campaign
                                flyers, editorials, newspaper clippings, and e-mails about issues
                                and strategies in the City Council election in which Rob Schilling
                                won the Council Seat in an upset over Alexandra Searls. The e-mails
                                include vivid descriptions of other politicians and officials
                                (including Waldo Jaquith, Joan Fenton, and David Simmons) in the
                                Charlottesville community. Also included are e-mails from the
                                democrats about debriefing of the election and making plans for
                                Meredith Richards campaign.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e614" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate> City Council Elections David
                                Brown</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20</container>
              <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is an editorial to the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Daily
                                    Progress</title> from Nancy O'Brien declaring her support for
                                David Brown, Kendra Hamilton and Kevin Lynch</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e627" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984</unitdate> Congress Election Francis
                                Fife</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:1</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Francis Fife ran for the 7<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> District
                                Democratic nomination for Congress. Included are campaign
                                literature, flyers, and photographs of press conferences.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e640" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> County Supervisor Election Connie
                                Brennan</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:2</container>
              <physdesc>12 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about the election for east and central
                                seats on the Nelson County Board of Supervisors in which Connie
                                Brennan and Gary Wood were running against Bob Rose, and R. Carlton
                                Ballowe</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e654" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> State Senate Special Election Emily
                                Couric seat</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:3</container>
              <physdesc>38 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are news clippings about Nancy O'Brien running in a special
                                election to fill the 25<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> District
                                Senate seat (Emily Couric's seat) along with Meredith Richards,
                                Blake Caravati, David Toscani, Susan Payne, Al Weed, and Creigh
                                Deeds. There is also correspondence and campaign literature.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e669" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> Congress Election Meredith
                                Richards</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:4</container>
              <physdesc>70 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are descriptions of how to organize the campaign for Richards
                                in the 5<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> Congressional District
                                against Virgil Goode, including information about results of their
                                debate, map of voting precincts, Democratic Committee lists,
                                handwritten notes about campaign strategies by Nancy O'Brien,
                                calendar of Meredith Richards events, and e-mail messages between
                                David Simmons, Tina, Reese, Valerie L'Herrou, Brian Wheeler, Cheryl
                                Oliver, Parthy Monagan, Lloyd Snook, Will Harvey, Nancy O'Brien, and
                                Alexandra Searls</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e688" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate> Congress Election Al
                                Weed</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:5</container>
              <physdesc>45 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are e-mails, flyers, and notes about Al Weed's campaign.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e699" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2003</unitdate> Democratic
                                Party</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:6</container>
              <physdesc>21 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Statement of democratic principles, By-laws of the Charlottesville
                                Democratic Committee, maps of voting precincts, donation lists,
                                e-mails between Russell Perry, Kevin Lynch, David Repass, Lloyd
                                Snook, Valerie l'Herrou, Felice Boling-Key, Alexandra Searls, and
                                Waldo Jaquith. There are handwritten notes by Nancy O'Brien.
                                Photographs from fundraising events</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e716" level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>C. Topical Files</unittitle>
            <container/>
          </did>
          <c03 id="d1e721" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977</unitdate> Affirmative Action</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:7</container>
              <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is a memo from City Manager, Cole Hendrix to W. P. Mitchell
                                on recruitment activities and notes written by Nancy O'Brien</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e732" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971; 1979</unitdate> Annexation</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:8</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are memos and letters about the county usage of city utilities,
                                Bill Number 328, and the tensions between city and county annexation
                                law suits. Also included are ordinances, resolutions, a typescript
                                of a radio broadcast, and newspaper clippings (including a map of
                                city county boundaries). There are also clippings and maps about
                                annexation and legislation proposed by Thomas J. Michie Jr.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e747" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975; 2003</unitdate> Piedmont Council for the
                                Arts</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:9</container>
              <physdesc>6 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a newspaper clipping about converting McGuffey School into a
                                community arts and crafts center. There is also a nomination for
                                Helen B. (Sandy) Snook for the PCA Arts award for 2003.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e760" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971-1978</unitdate> Administrative Files:
                                Budget</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:10</container>
              <physdesc>44 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are memos, notes, and newspaper clippings pertaining to the
                                local and state budget</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e772" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1981</unitdate> Charlottesville Area
                                Transportation Study (CATS)</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:11</container>
              <physdesc>39 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are correspondence, newspaper clippings, and minutes of the
                                Policy and Technical Committee for the Charlottesville Area
                                Transportation Restudy. There is information about speed limits,
                                road improvements, bypass routes, roads, and highways in
                                Charlottesville and Albemarle County including Route 29, 250,
                                McIntire Road, Hydraulic Road, and Michie Drive.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e788" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977; 1978-1979</unitdate> City-County Joint
                                Activities</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:1</container>
              <physdesc>24 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a proposal to Albemarle County from the City of
                                Charlottesville recommending that they form a community with common
                                interests. There is correspondence between Board of Supervisors,
                                Gerald Fisher and Mayor Laurence Brunton and a statement to the
                                Board of Supervisors about negotiations to avoid annexation and
                                encourage revenue sharing. Also included is a Summary of Joint
                                Activities</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e805" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980</unitdate> City-County Joint
                                Activities</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:2</container>
              <physdesc>51 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e813" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> City Council</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:3</container>
              <physdesc> 50 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>City Manager, Cole Hendrix set up a Council Retreat to study the
                                priorities and needs of the city in the future. There is a list of
                                possible income sources estimated for five years ahead. There are
                                also newspaper clippings regarding office locations for the City and
                                a new representative for the Belmont Neighborhood and other city
                                council agendas</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e828" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> City Planning
                                Commission Minutes</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:4</container>
              <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>The minutes from January 11, 1977 mentioned the request for a zoning
                                change at University Circle; drainage problem from Hydraulic Road as
                                well as other zoning changes and road concerns.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e841" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 -1980</unitdate> City of Charlottesville and
                                the University of Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:5</container>
              <physdesc>26 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings and a copy of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The University Register</title> (Nov. 15, 1976 vol. 6, no. 21)
                                There is correspondence from Cole Hendrix, UVA President, Frank
                                Hereford, Nancy O'Brien and the Jefferson Park Avenue Neighborhood
                                Association about communicating more directly with each other so
                                that there would be less confusion about statements attributed to
                                them in the media. There is also a memo about establishing a
                                "Fraternity Committee" For document about the opening of the
                                University of Virginia by Thomas Jefferson (photocopy) see
                                University of Virginia</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e861" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1995</unitdate> Cole Hendrix</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:6</container>
              <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Tribute to Cole Hendrix</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e871" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1975</unitdate> Disaster
                                Preparedness</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:7</container>
              <physdesc>5 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about a flood plan notes by Nancy
                                O'Brien</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e883" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Commission</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:8</container>
              <physdesc>80 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included are newspaper clippings, by-laws of the
                                Charlottesville-Albemarle Economic Development Commission, an annual
                                report, a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Mitchell Van Yahres promoting
                                the commission, a Chamber of Commerce Report, a list of
                                Charlottesville businesses, a statement by Francis H. Fife, notes on
                                a work session, and a position paper by Joseph W. Teague. Also
                                included is information on the Heritage Land Company,
                                Charlottesville Development Group, and condominiums on East Market
                                Street. Correspondents include David W. Parrish, Jr. and Sandy
                                Lambert</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e903" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1979</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Commission</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:9</container>
              <physdesc>29 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a resolution by Cole Hendrix for a basic policy on economic
                                development, a memo about Industrial Cost Recovery in Sewage
                                Treatment, a list of proposals from the Schnitzel House, Michie
                                Company, Rock Hill Academy, Vinegar Hill, McGuffey, and Starr Hill.
                                There are printed copies of radio editorials about growth in
                                Charlottesville and a symposium and discussion about economic
                                development commissions for the city and the county.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e920" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1980</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Downtown Mall</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:10</container>
              <physdesc>52 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are questions about the Downtown Mall from the Land use
                                Committee of the League of Women Voters, a statement by Mayor
                                Charles Barbour in favor of constructing the Downtown Mall, letters
                                of protest about traffic being allowed on the mall, an ordinance for
                                a special assessment for all property owners, a copy of the downtown
                                assessment, a list of the property owners, itemized costs for the
                                mall, guidelines for improvements in the mall by the University of
                                Virginia School of Architecture, a resolution to extend the Downtown
                                Mall, contract with Lawrence Halprin to finish the mall, petition
                                for Monticello Hotel to be converted into condominiums, a list of
                                the bids for completing the Downtown Mall and a resolution awarding
                                the contract to R. E. Lee. Topics include land for Central Place on
                                the mall, use of allocated funds from Vinegar Hill, definition of
                                the Downtown Charlottesville, Incorporated, downtown bike race, Arts
                                Education Festival, signage, lighting improvements, stage for
                                Central place, usage for CSX property, and Leggett's Department
                                Store leaving the downtown location.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e947" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1978</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Downtown Mall Newspaper clippings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:11</container>
              <physdesc>130 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about the work on the new downtown mall
                                including its opening</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e959" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> Economic Development Farber Mall
                                Constituents</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:1</container>
              <physdesc>34 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are letters from constituents about the Fashion Square Mall.
                                There is a resolution from the Greenbrier Neighborhood Association
                                asking for the Planning Commission to undertake a study on water
                                run-off and traffic issues; a memo outlining capital cost estimates
                                and suggestions for sharing the cost between the city and the
                                developer; an economic analysis and a traffic study report</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e975" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977</unitdate> Economic Development Farber Mall
                                Constituents</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:2</container>
              <physdesc>92 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are many letters from constituents and business owners to City
                                Council about the mall proposal. (Included is a letter from Mrs.
                                John Cooke Wyllie commenting on the changes in Charlottesville and
                                her fears about going out at night alone; January 10, 1977.)</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e989" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Farber Mall (City) Petyon Property</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:3</container>
              <physdesc>49 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is an editorial from Francis Fife defending Nancy O'Brien in
                                the controversy surrounding Leonard Farber's proposal for a shopping
                                mall in the City of Charlottesville. There is correspondence from
                                Leonard Farber and a press release describing a situation in which
                                Farber did not want to pay the offsite costs for road improvements.
                                There are memos from City Manager Cole Hendrix and recommendations
                                from the Director of Planning and Development Satyrendra S. Huja.
                                City Council passed the rezoning proposal for the mall. Meanwhile
                                Farber had asked for a delay, and had presented the mall to the
                                County. There are news clippings and reports about the mall idea
                                moving to the County. (The mall was built on Rio Road and named
                                Fashion Square Mall)</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1011" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Economic Development Farber Mall
                                (County)</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:4</container>
              <physdesc>10 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are letters about the mall being constructed on Rio Road in
                                Albemarle County including a letter from Wallace Reed to the State
                                Air Pollution Control Board about the potentially harmful effects of
                                traffic and pollution from the mall; a radio editorial about roads
                                that need to be built or improved for the mall; a letter from Nancy
                                O'Brien to Gerald Fisher, Albemarle County Board of Supervisors,
                                about her concerns for the proposed mall site; a Rich Collins letter
                                to Nancy O'Brien about air pollution from increased traffic due to
                                the mall; a letter from Bernard J. Haggerty to Nancy O'Brien
                                accusing her of misrepresenting the majority vote for the mall and
                                there is a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Haggerty defending her
                                position and suggesting that he check his facts. There is also the
                                official resolution adopted by the Charlottesville Albemarle
                                Economic Development Commission to locate the mall in the community.
                                (Louis Scribner)</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1036" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1980</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Farber Mall Newspaper clippings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:5</container>
              <physdesc>130 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1044" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> October-December Economic
                                Development Farber Mall (City) Rezoning notebook</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:6</container>
              <physdesc>1 notebook</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Minutes of the Charlottesville City Planning Commission, applications
                                and correspondence for rezoning of Fashion Square Mall</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1056" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 December 30- 1977 January 7</unitdate>
                                Economic Development Farber Mall (City) Rezoning
                                notebook</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:7</container>
              <physdesc>1 notebook</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Minutes of a special meeting of the Charlottesville City Planning
                                Commission on January 7, 1977 and correspondence regarding the
                                Fashion Square Mall</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1070" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Farber Mall (City) rezoning reports</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:1</container>
              <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are three reports, Impact Analysis on proposed commercial
                                rezoning and stream relocation for mall, Correspondence about the
                                mall which was received after the closing of the public record on
                                January 10, 1977, and Rezoning Public Record</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1084" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Farber Mall (City) Traffic reports</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:2</container>
              <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are two traffic impact analysis reports and related papers
                                regarding the Farber Mall and the effects of the mall on the
                                environment.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1097" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Farber Mall Work Sessions</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:3</container>
              <physdesc>23 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1105" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004-2005</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Fifeville</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:4</container>
              <physdesc>39 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a proposal from Southern Development to purchase lots in
                                Fifeville and Ridge Street (near Tonsler Park) and build apartments.
                                There is extensive e-mail from Antoinette Rhoades about preserving
                                the area for historic reasons. Dr. Charlie Hurt is also mentioned.
                                There are also documents related to preservation of historic areas
                                including a cd. There is a description of the history of Fifeville
                                including information about Allen Hawkins and John Hartwell Cocke
                                who were in business together.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1123" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974; 1978-1979</unitdate> Economic
                                Development McIntire Road Extension pt.1</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:5</container>
              <physdesc>50 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is information from the North Downtown Residents Association,
                                Starr Hill Neighborhood Association, City and County officials,
                                design engineers and officials from the Virginia Department of
                                Highways. There are study plans for an extension of McIntire Road
                                with Rio Road. Also mentioned are improvements to Ridge Street,
                                Cherry Avenue, McIntire Road, and Preston Avenue. There are also
                                letters to Nancy O'Brien from constituents about McIntire Park.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1140" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980</unitdate> Economic Development McIntire Road
                                Extension pt.2</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:6</container>
              <physdesc>21 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are constituent letters to Nancy O'Brien about McIntire Park; a
                                McIntire Road Report by City Council, letters to Commonwealth
                                Attorney Richard Barrick, City Attorney Roger Wiley, and Attorney
                                General Marshall Coleman concerning an alleged conflict of Interest
                                for Thomas Albro; City and County Resolutions approving the proposed
                                extension, a Design Advisory Committee's Report to City Council, an
                                opinion paper "North-South Route," recommendations by Wallace Reed,
                                a report by Charles A. Kulp, letter from Don Wagner, Virginia
                                Department of Highways and Transportation approving the report, and
                                printed materials about McIntire Road and the Virginia Department Of
                                Highways and Transportation</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1161" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980</unitdate> Economic Development
                                McIntire Road newspaper clippings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">6:7</container>
              <physdesc>39 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1169" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> Economic Development Meadowcreek
                                Parkway e-mails</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:1</container>
              <physdesc>16 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are e-mails from Mary E. MacNeil, Bruce Appleyard, Rich
                                Collins, John L. Pfaltz, John Dean, George Loper, and Kevin
                                Lynch</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1182" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1979</unitdate> Economic Development
                                newspaper clippings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:2</container>
              <physdesc>67 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about potential developments in
                                Charlottesville and Albemarle County including revenues from the
                                airport, proposal for a downtown seven story condominium, Miller and
                                Rhoads relocating to Fashion Square Mall, widening of route 29,
                                General Electric plant, Industrial Park near airport, Biscuit Run,
                                Federal Executive Institute, sign regulations, and Dr. Hurt's
                                illegal bridge over the South Rivanna River</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1199" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Economic Development Vinegar
                                Hill</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:3</container>
              <physdesc>13 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a resolution allowing that funds from the Charlottesville
                                Development Group be used to complete an analysis of public costs
                                for a Vinegar Hill Hotel and Conference Center; Correspondents
                                include John W. Galbreath, Robert C. Stripling, Peter Kory, Mitchell
                                Van Yahres, Robert L. Vickery, John B. Slidell of Zuchelli, Hunter
                                &amp; Associates, Inc. Included is a contract for consultant,
                                Zuchelli, Hunter &amp; Associates, Inc. to prepare a feasibility
                                analysis for the City. Topics include a selection of a consultant
                                for a market study and that the construction of a hotel downtown be
                                a top priority of the Charlottesville Development Group. There are
                                also news clippings</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1220" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1980</unitdate> Economic Development
                                Vinegar Hill</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:4</container>
              <physdesc>33 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a resolution by the Charlottesville Development Group to
                                have a downtown hotel and conference center, an announcement
                                designating the construction to the Park-Tower Development Group of
                                New York and correspondence about federal grants not coming through
                                for the hotel. Also included is a report on Vinegar Hill Project
                                Financial Costs and Benefits by Zuchelli, Hunter &amp; Associates,
                                Inc., a Vinegar Hill newsletter, a Starr Hill neighborhood letter
                                requesting rehousing for the original Vinegar Hill residents, a
                                letter discussing the inclusion of the YMCA in the hotel, a Vinegar
                                Hill Impact Committee Report, a report by Scurlock Associates, Inc.,
                                and questions from the League of Women Voters.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1241" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1980; 1982</unitdate> Economic
                                Development Vinegar Hill History news clippings</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:5</container>
              <physdesc>36 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings showing how Vinegar Hill used to look
                                before it was destroyed in 1960 for "urban renewal." There are also
                                articles about the planned development of Vinegar Hill.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1254" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Economic Studies</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:6</container>
              <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are research papers by Hal Wolman and George A. Reigeluth from
                                The Urban Institute about local economic development
                                decision-making.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1266" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Historical Landmarks in
                                Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:7</container>
              <physdesc>16 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is correspondence about a request for restoration of a building
                                located at 609 East High Street. There is also a mission statement
                                of the Virginia Historical Landmarks Commission, notes about the
                                Levy Opera House, grant application for help with Midway Mill
                                Restoration and various newspaper clippings about the Levy Opera
                                House, Midway Mill, Charlottesville's First Street, Ivy property
                                allegedly belonging to Thomas Jefferson, Paramount Theatre, Post
                                Office and McIntire Library.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1284" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1984</unitdate> Housing
                                Issues</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:8</container>
              <physdesc>57 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a research paper on "Housing Issues and Strategies for
                                Charlottesville" prepared by the Department of Community Development
                                and many newspaper clippings (1974-1978). Included is a paper
                                by Nancy O'Brien from her UVA class on Policy Analysis GFAG 866 in
                                1983.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1299" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1978</unitdate> Invitations</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:9</container>
              <physdesc>54 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are various programs and invitations to dinners, fundraisers,
                                and events</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1310" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979</unitdate> Ivy Creek Natural Area</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:10</container>
              <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a memo about a proposal for the revised master plan for Ivy
                                Creek</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1321" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Lane High
                                School</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:11</container>
              <physdesc>15 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about the use of the Lane High School
                                Building</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1333" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972</unitdate> Legislation</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">7:12</container>
              <physdesc>6 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is correspondence to Mitchell Van Yahres from various senators
                                regarding their support for Van Yahres opposition to Bill 328 which
                                would place a moratorium on annexation in Virginia.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1345" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1979</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                community service</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:1</container>
              <physdesc>46 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about museums, libraries, law programs,
                                UVA and other organizations that offer cultural experiences to the
                                community.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1358" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on drug
                                abuse</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:2</container>
              <physdesc>8 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1366" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                elderly</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:3</container>
              <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1374" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975; 1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                environment</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:4</container>
              <physdesc>9 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1382" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                labor</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:5</container>
              <physdesc>18 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1390" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                landfill</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:6</container>
              <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1398" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                land planning</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:7</container>
              <physdesc>30 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1406" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> Newspaper clippings on
                                Charlottesville Mayors</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:8</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1414" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Miscellaneous</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:9</container>
              <physdesc>12 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are articles about Asateague Island, the office of the Public
                                Defender, government regulations, and business news</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1426" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Newspaper clipping on Chic
                                Moran</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:10</container>
              <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is an article on oral histories about the University of
                                Virginia</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1438" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Police</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:11</container>
              <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are articles about DNA, crime rates, and salaries</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1449" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Pollution</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:12</container>
              <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include Morton Frozen Foods and phosphorus removal to protect
                                the Rivanna River and Reservoir, waste in the Rappahannock River
                                Basin, studies on the South Fork Rivanna Reservoir, and noise
                                ordinances</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1463" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Prisons</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:13</container>
              <physdesc>13 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include the creation of the Charlottesville Albemarle Regional
                                Jail Board, programs to improve jail conditions, increased prisoner
                                protection, study on work release program, alternatives to
                                prison,</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1477" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Schools</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:14</container>
              <physdesc>56 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include a discipline task force, school bus costs, budget
                                cuts, salaries, shortening of elementary school day, quality of
                                schools, Learning Exchange Program, and school improvements</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1490" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1976</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Sewer</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:15</container>
              <physdesc>10 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include upgrading sewer treatment plants, sewer rates,
                                suspension of Moores Creek Sewer Treatment Plant, and a "living
                                filter" concept in Crozet</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1503" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Taxes</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:16</container>
              <physdesc>33 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include tax reform, tax increases, cigarette tax, and Virginia
                                Proposition 13.5</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1515" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976; 1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Tourism</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:17</container>
              <physdesc>5 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics mentioned are the Chamber of Commerce, Piedmont Airlines, and
                                a new Visitor Bureau</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1527" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1978</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Transportation and Parking</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:18</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics mentioned are transit studies, bike paths, downtown parking,
                                underground parking facility below Madison Bowl, taxi rate
                                increases, bus rates, saving the Southern Crescent train, conditions
                                of 29 North, and the resignation of the Charlottesville traffic
                                engineer</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1542" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971</unitdate> Newspaper clippings
                                Voting</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:19</container>
              <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics included are the new voting process regulation of address
                                registration and the Democratic Party meetings</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1554" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1977; n. d.</unitdate>
                                Ordinances</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:20</container>
              <physdesc>33 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics included are Constitution Highway Senate Joint Resolution No.
                                41; amendment to city code regarding group homes; budget
                                appropriation for construction of taxi road at the airport,
                                pedestrian mall, and visit to a sister city. There are ordinances
                                about yard regulations, Blenheim Avenue, on-street parking, control
                                of rainfall runoff, and anti-trust laws. There are also newspaper
                                clippings about billboards, and new zoning ordinances.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1571" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> Queen Elizabeth's Visit to
                                Charlottesville</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:21</container>
              <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings (<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">University
                                    Register, The Cavalier Daily, The Daily Progress, and The
                                    Washington Post</title>) about the visit, press statements,
                                programs, a detailed itinerary, as well as printed instructions on
                                how to address the Queen and other important members of the
                                government. See also Scrapbook pages 1976 July (Box18)</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1587" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1978; 2002</unitdate> Race
                                Issues</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">8:22</container>
              <physdesc>20 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a study of racial problems in the schools and
                                Charlottesville, recommendations from the Social Development
                                Commission, and an article, "Patterns of Black Excellence." There is
                                also a program for a fashion show sponsored by the National
                                Association of Advancement of Colored People. There are also
                                newspaper clippings about racial issues including acts of violence
                                against the Safeway Store</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1604" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> Race: Many Races, One
                                Community</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:1</container>
              <physdesc>75 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings and statements from the police about a
                                racial incident in Charlottesville where several high school
                                students attacked University students. There are minutes, and
                                reports from the group, Many Races, One Community which outlined a
                                list of problems, a resolution of apology to the students, and
                                outreach programs. The group was facilitated by Nancy O'Brien.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1620" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</unitdate> Race: Many Races, One
                                Community</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:2</container>
              <physdesc>39 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are lists of members of the group Many Races, One Community
                                with e-mails, minutes and reports. Also included are brief histories
                                of William Elwood, Drewary Brown, Robet H. Cooley III, Frances
                                Brand, Sally Hemmings, Martha Jefferson, Lawrence Richardson, George
                                Inge, Nannie Cox Jackson, Mollie Ingle Michie, Henry Martin, Sarah
                                Patton Boyle, Anna Gardner, Rebecca McGinness, James T. S. Taylor,
                                Rufus Holsinger, Uriah Levy, Nancy West, Carter G. Woodson, Edwin
                                Anderson Alderman, Charles E. Coles, R.T. W. Duke Jr., Ben York,
                                William Clark, Charles L. Barbour, Meriwether Lewis, Raymond Bel,
                                Isaac and Simon Leterman, Ruth B. and George T. Huff, Dr. George
                                Ferguson, Booker T. Reaves, Charles E. [Chic] Moran, Thomas
                                Jefferson, Elizabeth Hemmings, J. J. Sylvester, Tucker Isaacs, Eli
                                Howard, Sarah Ann Strickler, John West, T. J. Williams, Gregory H.
                                Swanson, Monacan Indian George Whitewolf, Ellis Mopsik, and Alice
                                Carlotta Jackson. The biographies were written by the Citizens for a
                                United Community.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1646" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2002; n.d.</unitdate> Race:
                                Resources</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:3</container>
              <physdesc>8 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is an article from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Washington
                                    Post Magazine</title>, "The Lessons and Legacy of the Prince
                                Edward School Closings" and articles from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">National League of Cities</title> about racial issues. There is
                                also literature from the Focus Women's Resource Center titled, "Days
                                of Dialogue 2002" and articles on "Conversation Cafes"</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1662" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008-2009</unitdate> Sister
                                Cities</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:4</container>
              <physdesc>25 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings from <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Daily
                                    Progress</title> about the success of sister cities programs.
                                Also included are proposals and guidelines for the program and
                                by-laws.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1676" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2002</unitdate> Transportation:
                                Commonwealth Transportation Board</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:5</container>
              <physdesc>50 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is an application from Nancy O'Brien for the appointment to
                                the Commonwealth Transportation Board; e-mails and letters of
                                recommendation from Al Weed, R. Creigh Deeds, Katherine E. Slaughter
                                and many others. There are also planning reports for highway
                                construction and flyers about stopping the Route 29 Bypass.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1691" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.; 1976-1978</unitdate> University of
                                Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:6</container>
              <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Photocopy of a document written by Thomas Jefferson about the opening
                                of the University of Virginia. There are also newspaper clippings
                                about the University of Virginia regarding fraternities, Easters,
                                better lighting, football star Billy Copeland, and experiments in
                                solar energy</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1706" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1978</unitdate> Water South Rivanna
                                Fork Articles and Reports</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:7</container>
              <physdesc>90 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Topics include marine growth in the reservoir, Moore's Creek Sewage
                                Treatment Plant, moratorium on construction near the South Rivanna
                                Fork due to pollution concerns, pollution from Morton Frozen Foods
                                and farming near the basin, sewage interceptor line to Crozet,
                                pollution studies, price increases for water, and an article on the
                                history of water issues in Albemarle County since 1868. There are
                                also some articles about the James River.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1723" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978; 1980; 2000</unitdate> Water South Rivanna
                                Fork Reports</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:8</container>
              <physdesc>9 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is a report to City Council, a request for 1979 funds, notes
                                from a conference on water resource management and planning, a
                                Watershed Management Plan, and assessment</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1736" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1977; 1990-2000</unitdate> Water
                                Crisis</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:9</container>
              <physdesc>75 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are newspaper clippings about a water shortage. Also included
                                is a water shortage contingency plan, a declaration by Governor
                                Mills E. Godwin, Jr. of a local emergency in the city of
                                Charlottesville, memos from the Rivanna Water &amp; Sewer Authority
                                about conserving water, and ordinances to reduce water consumption.
                                There are also letters from constituents and business owners
                                regarding the water restrictions. There are minutes from the
                                Charlottesville Albemarle Board of Realtors meeting on "Water Talk"
                                in 2000 and reports on water demands from 1990 to 1999.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1755" level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1978</unitdate> Women</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">9:10</container>
              <physdesc>33 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is statistical information about the numbers of women in
                                politics, and minutes of a Citizens Task Force on Abused Women.
                                There are also newspaper clippings on a variety of issues regarding
                                women.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e1770" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: UVA Classes</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e1775" level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A. Graduate Student and Thesis</unittitle>
            <container/>
          </did>
          <c03 id="d1e1780">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1985</unitdate> UVA Admission
                                letter</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:1</container>
              <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a letter from the director of the Graduate Program in Public
                                Administration advising Nancy O'Brien that she should take some
                                social science classes since she did not have a bachelors degree.
                                There is also a letter of acceptance for her to begin in the 1984
                                Spring term. Also included are her graduate record exam scores,
                                transcripts from Massachusetts General Hospital School of Nursing,
                                and grades from courses taken at the University of Virginia.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1797">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984-1985</unitdate> UVA Assignments and
                                Papers</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:2</container>
              <physdesc>21 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included are tests and papers by Nancy O'Brien such as "The Exercise
                                of Discretion in Police Service," "Citizen Participation in School
                                Systems," "Ethnography of the Charlottesville Democratic Party City
                                Council Campaign Committee," " Effect of '85 Budget on Subsidized
                                Housing, A Theory on the Effect of Registration Drives on Voter
                                Turnout," "Analyzing Alternative Delivery Systems," "Stare Decisis,"
                                and "The Executive."</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1814">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1985</unitdate> Thesis notes on
                                Planning District Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:3</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included is a study on Planning District Commissions in Virginia;
                                title, and a publication, "Virginia Planning, Housing &amp;
                                Districting Legislation 1973." There is also a list of city codes
                                and legislative acts; notes on Stanley Kidwell and Virginia Planning
                                Commissions, Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, and William
                                Shelton (interview)</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1830">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate> Thesis notes on Planning District
                                Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:4</container>
              <physdesc>18 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Included are notes on budget and work programs, articles by Nelson
                                Wikstrom</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1842">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985-1986</unitdate> Thesis notes on
                                Planning District Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:5</container>
              <physdesc>35 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a copy of House Bill 1479 that amended Virginia Code to
                                allow funding for the commissions. There are articles and memos
                                about financial funding for PDC's and their role in government.
                                There are also notes from her research on T. Marshall Hahn, and
                                "Five Metropolitan Governments"</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1857">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate> Thesis notes on Planning District
                                Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:6</container>
              <physdesc>17 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are notes from speeches made by President Lyndon F. Johnson
                                regarding government organizations and research surveys about
                                PDCS.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1870">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate> Thesis Prospectus on Planning
                                District Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">10:7</container>
              <physdesc>6 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are several drafts of the prospectus and some comments from
                                Professor Stephen L. Percy.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1882">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate> Masters Thesis Planning District
                                Commissions in Virginia</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:1</container>
              <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is a copy of Nancy O'Brien's thesis</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1894" level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>B.Professor O'Brien</unittitle>
            <container/>
          </did>
          <c03 id="d1e1899">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1994</unitdate> O'Brien class on
                                Federal &amp; State Housing</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:2</container>
              <physdesc>25 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There is paperwork for UVA instructors including memos about student
                                rolls, other correspondence about the course, reading materials, and
                                outlines for assigned projects on housing</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1912">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998</unitdate> UVA class on Fifeville</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:3</container>
              <physdesc>13 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>There are several copies of a neighborhood report of Fifeville and
                                research information including census records</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 id="d1e1923">
            <did>
              <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate> UVA class on Fifeville</unittitle>
              <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">11:4</container>
              <physdesc>12 items</physdesc>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>UVA Professor Nisha Botchwey taught a class on Fifeville 2003 and
                                Beyond. There is a study of Fifeville which was researched by the
                                students in this class. Two cd's containing information on Fifeville
                                and the Fifeville Neighborhood Association are included.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e1938" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e1943" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:1</container>
            <physdesc>8 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are outlines for a strategic plan to find common grounds among
                            organizations in the Charlottesville community and a presentation on
                            TJPDC extension services, Jefferson Area Bicycle, Pedestrian, and
                            Greenway Plans. There are also a few newspaper clippings.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1957" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1996</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Build Out Analysis Report</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:2</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1965" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970- 1990; 1995</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Census Reports</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:3</container>
            <physdesc>40 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included are figures for the reports and a report by the
                            Charlottesville-Albemarle Children and Youth Commission</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1977" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1988- 1991</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Census Reports</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:4</container>
            <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are Albemarle County Census reports</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1988" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1988; 2001</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Economic and Environmental Reports</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:5</container>
            <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a Thomas Jefferson Sustainability Council report (in which Nancy
                            O'Brien attached notes to the reports such as "we nearly killed each
                            other getting though this," a Regional Economic Development Plan, and an
                            employment survey</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2002" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998-1999</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Hourly Rates</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:6</container>
            <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a list of salaries for the staff of TJPDC and a breakdown of
                            hours worked for the fiscal year</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2014" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1994</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Minority Health</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:7</container>
            <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are minutes from the Minority Health Concerns Committee</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2025" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Poverty Studies</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">12:8</container>
            <physdesc>25 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Facts and figures reported by the Monticello Area Community Action
                            Agency</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2037" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Housing Improvement
                            Corporation: Retirement</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:1</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a photograph of Nancy O'Brien's retirement party</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2048" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Retirement</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:2</container>
            <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a letter from Nancy O'Brien to Harry Harris, chair of the TJPDC
                            regarding her remaining projects. There is also information from her
                            release time record.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2061" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1996-2001</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Tourism Reports</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:3</container>
            <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are reports on the Thomas Jefferson Venture Heritage Tourism
                            Project. Included is a description by Nancy O'Brien about the
                            difficulties with the project because of the different interests of the
                            committee (economic development vs. preservation.) She also mentioned
                            the kindness and strengths of certain individuals and a wine bottle of
                            "Il Fiasco" that she received as a gift. (She wrote that State Senator
                            Emily Couric made public corrections of O'Brien's statements and later
                            called O'Brien and apologized, confessing that she was the one who had
                            inaccurate information.)</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2080" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1994</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission: United Way</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:4</container>
            <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a report on the needs and priorities of the community which was
                            based on surveys given to the community. The surveys and results are
                            included.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2093" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1991-1993</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning
                            District Commission Visions Forums</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:5</container>
            <physdesc>9 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are transcripts of the tape record of speeches by Nancy O'Brien and
                            other leaders of the community on their visions of the future as well as
                            participation and discussion by the attendees.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2106" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Water Report</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:6</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a TJPDC report on the Rivanna River Basin Project. Included is
                            an article on the Moore's Creek Watershed.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2118" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999</unitdate> Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission Water Report</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:7</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a report on present conditions and recommendations for
                            preservation and restoration for water resources in Fluvanna County</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e2131" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV: Jefferson School</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e2136" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2006</unitdate> Citizens for Jefferson
                            School</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">13:8</container>
            <physdesc>24 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Citizens formed a group to save Jefferson School as an educational
                            institution and requested City Council to designate a task force to
                            study its future usage. Included are e-mails, minutes of meetings and
                            work sessions. There is a request for a proposal for preparing a
                            National Historic Register Nomination and a historical architect, and
                            plans for a Jefferson School Reunion for the classes of 1930- 1951.
                            Newspaper clippings, photographs and information about a highway marker
                            are also included.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2154" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> Citizens for Jefferson School
                            By-laws</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:1</container>
            <physdesc>25 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are by-laws, a certificate of incorporation for the organization,
                            Citizens for Jefferson School Steering Committee minutes, a list of
                            members, and a proposal for a task force.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2167" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004-2005</unitdate> Jefferson School as a
                            Cultural Heritage Center</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:2</container>
            <physdesc>1 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included is information on funding opportunities, e-mails, an
                            interpretive plan, a letter from Jefferson-Madison Regional Library
                            about space at the school, a proposal from architectural historian,
                            Maral S. Kalbian, and design plans for a culture heritage center at
                            Jefferson School</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2182" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Grants and
                            Fund Possibilities</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:3</container>
            <physdesc>15 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is information on grants from Bell South, Oak Hill Fund, Save
                            America's Treasures, Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation e-mails, and a
                            grant application</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2195" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate> Jefferson School BAMA
                            Grants</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">14:4</container>
            <physdesc>15 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a grant application to the BAMA works fund in the
                            Charlottesville-Albemarle Community Foundation and of the Dave Mathews
                            Band. There is correspondence and a rough draft of the application</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2208" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School and
                            African American History</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:1</container>
            <physdesc>12 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a typed copy of the School Board minutes from 1922 about
                            expanding the Jefferson Colored School; a history of Jefferson School,
                            and African American history in Charlottesville including a petition to
                            save Jefferson School, a newsletter <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The New
                                Jeffersonian</title>, an oral history project, reunion events, and
                            copies of Holsinger photographs. There is also a <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Preservation Piedmont</title> Newsletter, a history of the
                            Jefferson Preschool Center, an article, "We Shall Overcome," <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">http://www.nps.gov/history/nr/travel/civilrights/intro.htm</title>
                            and an essay about the lack of historical sources on African American
                            lives in Charlottesville. The entire essay can also be read online at
                                <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">http://www2.vcdh.virginia.edu/afam/aas405/syllabus/essay.html</title></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2232" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2006</unitdate> Jefferson School Newspaper
                            clippings</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:2</container>
            <physdesc>36 items</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2240" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1950] n. d.</unitdate> Jefferson School
                            Photographs</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:3</container>
            <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Photocopies of students at Jefferson School</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2251" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 March-July</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Minutes</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:4</container>
            <physdesc>26 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are Jefferson School Task Force minutes from April through July.
                            Minutes from June 18<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="super" xlink:href="">th</title> are not included
                            here but can be found with the Jefferson School Task Force Proposal A-N
                            and minutes from January 3, 30, March 4, and March 13, 2003 meetings are
                            located in the Jefferson School Task Force Proposal 0-Y. The minutes
                            mention a set of guiding principles, and the Jefferson School as a
                            historical site. (This issue is discussed throughout the Task Force
                            minutes.) There are e-mails, notes, reports, transcript from a community
                            held meeting, and a proposal from the Reunion Committee.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2270" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 August</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Minutes</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:5</container>
            <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>They discussed the impact of other development downtown near the
                            Jefferson School, sources of funding and anchor tenants that would offer
                            multiple uses and fit within the historic culture of the site. They also
                            discussed requesting an extension from City Council to finish their
                            report. Also included is a Report &amp; Recommendations of Social
                            Service Non Profits in the area</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2286" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 September</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Minutes</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:6</container>
            <physdesc>21 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The minutes discuss the plans for a community held meeting. Included with
                            the minutes are e-mails from facilitator, Jinni Benson of Mary Means
                            &amp; Associates, and long time community leader Grace Tinsley, maps, a
                            power point with cost estimates, reports, and a site analysis of the
                            Jefferson School building by Frazier Associates. There is a website for
                            a school that was built in 1915 in Portland, Oregon which was renovated
                            to be a hotel, gymnasium, restaurant, store and civic center, and it can
                            be seen at <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="underline" xlink:href="">http://www.mcmenamins.com/427-kennedy-school-home</title></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2305" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 October-December</unitdate> Jefferson School Task
                            Force Minutes</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">15:7</container>
            <physdesc>19 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included with the minutes are e-mails, a report by Lois Sandy, a report
                            by Genevieve P. Keller, letters from potential tenants of the school,
                            maps, revenue calculations, and a draft report to City Council from the
                            Task Force. The minutes reveal discussions about expanding the streets
                            around the Jefferson School, evaluation of the variety of options for
                            use, search for a lead organization to run the facility, and the idea of
                            connecting the Jefferson School with other historic sites in the
                            area.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2323" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 January-August</unitdate> Jefferson School Task
                            Force Proposal 1-8</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:1</container>
            <physdesc>1/5 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The notebook is in reverse chronological order and is a proposal to City
                            Council from Nancy O'Brien to act as facilitator of the Task Force.
                            (included are photographs and a CD) City Council had placed a bid for
                            proposals for a facilitator and chose Mary Means &amp; Associates as the
                            facilitator.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2338" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Proposal A-N</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:2</container>
            <physdesc>2/5 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a list of Task Force Members, staff from City Council, a
                            timeline, appraisal, tax credits, grants, research of best practices,
                            community survey, correspondence, and minutes.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2351" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Proposal O-Y</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:3</container>
            <physdesc>3/5 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are minutes from February 10, 25, March 4, and March 13, 2003. The
                            Task force worked towards finding our more about the history of the
                            school, obtaining a historic register, relocation of programs at the
                            school, maps and a list of individuals that were allowed to speak with
                            the media.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2366" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Goals, Proposal Z</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:4</container>
            <physdesc>4/ 5 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are minutes from September 30, November 19, December 3, 31, 2002,
                            January 6, 7, 14, 21, 28, 2003 Task Force meeting and a letter to City
                            Council outlined the benefits of placing the school on the National
                            Landmark register. There is also a list of project goals and ground
                            rules for the Task Force. Topics include cost estimates for renovation,
                            repairs, survey of existing conditions, tax credits, and housing
                            options. There are several documents presenting facts about the National
                            Register. Also included is a proposal from Mary Means &amp; Associates
                            to serve as facilitator for the Jefferson School Task Force.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2385" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Proposal 1-15</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:5</container>
            <physdesc>5/ 5 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is information about the original work of the task force including
                            mission statements from the Citizens for Jefferson School.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2397" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003-2004</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Report</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">16:6</container>
            <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included is a draft of the Jefferson School Task Force Report and
                            recommendations of the task force</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2409" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003-2005</unitdate> Jefferson School Task Force
                            Report</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:1</container>
            <physdesc>5 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Jefferson School Report on Historic Designation and Design Concept
                            Update, and the final report to City Council with recommendations of the
                            Jefferson School Task Force (Bringing Life Back to Historic Jefferson
                            School) There are three photographs of the parking lot and city yard in
                            front of the school.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2424" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Jefferson School Task
                            Force</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:2</container>
            <physdesc>1 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included is information on other cultural centers, and schools, a
                            Jefferson-Madison Regional Library fact sheet, e-mails, ideas for
                            Jefferson Children and Family Center, and summaries from the education
                            work group sessions.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2438" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 January</unitdate> Jefferson School Exhibits
                            A-H</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:3</container>
            <physdesc>1 of 2 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included are capital plans for the City of Charlottesville</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2449" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002 January</unitdate> Jefferson School Exhibits
                            I-N</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:4</container>
            <physdesc>2 of 2 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included in the notebook is an appraisal for the Jefferson School
                            property, information for nomination of the school as a historic
                            landmark, a community survey about uses for the school, copies of
                            newspaper articles, estimate of project costs and survey of existing
                            conditions, illustrations, guidelines for usage, history of the school,
                            and information from the Citizens for Jefferson School (mission
                            statement, and petition)</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e2467" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series V: Facilitator</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e2472" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975</unitdate> Facilitator Monticello Area Community
                            Action Agency</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:5</container>
            <physdesc>10 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are a few monthly reports for MACAA. There is also a Request for a
                            Proposal from MACAA for Organizational Consulting Services which was
                            awarded to Nancy O'Brien. Included is the revised mission statement
                            which O'Brien wrote for them</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2486" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1997</unitdate> Facilitator Virginia Conservation
                            Network</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:6</container>
            <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Included is a report and a floppy disk</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2497" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> Facilitator for the Louisa County
                            Resource Council</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:7</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is a report [by Nancy O'Brien] titled, "The County of Louisa,
                            Virginia Comprehensive Plan. The County Board of Supervisors wrapped the
                            report in a red ribbon and gave it to Nancy O'Brien when she retired.
                            They signed their names and wrote thank you notes on the inside front
                            cover. Nancy attached a note saying that "getting this passed was a
                            Herculean effort"</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2513" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate> Facilitator Louisa County
                            Resource Council Retreat</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:8</container>
            <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is an agenda, planning strategies town meeting, and a synopsis</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2524" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate> Facilitator Minority Health
                            Project</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:9</container>
            <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is information about identifying minority health issues in the
                            community</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2536" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004</unitdate> Facilitator Senior Center Focus
                            Groups</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">17:10</container>
            <physdesc>18 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are strategy meetings, notes and a report</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e2548" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VI: Speeches</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e2553" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971; 1976-1977</unitdate> Speeches and Press
                            Releases</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:1</container>
            <physdesc>27 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are speeches about running for office and her acceptance speech for
                            City Council, a statement of Nancy O'Brien and K. Lane Kneedler,
                            speeches to the Business Women's Club, Jefferson Society, First
                            Christian Church, Ebenezer Baptist Church, Charlottesville High School
                            Chapter of the National Honor Society, Charlottesville Public Schools,
                            Virginia Nurses Association, Commencement at Piedmont Virginia Community
                            College, Saint John Grand Lodge of Virginia, and speeches on Economic
                            Development, South Fork Rivanna Reservoir, Services for the Ageing,
                            Women in Political Process, Passing the ERA, and burying a time capsule
                            at Vinegar Hill</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2573" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1981</unitdate> Speeches and Press
                            Releases</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:2</container>
            <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are speeches to the Unitarian Church on "Civic Virtue, Monticello
                            Toastmistress Club, University Baptist Church, and include subjects such
                            as "Highrise for the Elderly," "Process Used to Construct the Downtown
                            Shopping Mall," and "Piedmont Land Use"</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2587" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986-2003</unitdate> Speeches and Press
                            Releases</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:3</container>
            <physdesc>6 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Speeches included are to the Virginia Society of Professional Nurses, a
                            "Toast to Mitch Van Yahres," "Independence Day Exercises at Monticello,"
                            the Senior Center, and Historic Garden Week</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2600" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:4</container>
            <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are speeches on Leadership, nomination of Karen Waters for one of
                            the "Distinquished Dozen," celebration of the life of Mary Alice Gunter,
                            and "Breaking Through Barriers" to the American Association of
                            University Women</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e2614" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VII: Scrapbooks</unittitle>
          <container/>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e2619" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 February-June</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:5</container>
            <physdesc>1/4</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings and correspondence</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2630" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976 July-December</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:6</container>
            <physdesc>2/4</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are newspaper clippings and invitations. Also included is
                            information on Queen England's visit. (Luncheon menu)</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2642" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 January-May</unitdate> Scrapbook pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">18:7</container>
            <physdesc>3/4 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2652" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 June-September</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:1</container>
            <physdesc>4/4 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2663" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 October-December</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:2</container>
            <physdesc>1/4 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2674" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978 January-February</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:3</container>
            <physdesc>2/4notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2685" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978 March-June</unitdate> Scrapbook pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">19:4</container>
            <physdesc>3/4 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2695" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978 July-December</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:1</container>
            <physdesc>4/4 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2706" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979 January-May</unitdate> Scrapbook pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:2</container>
            <physdesc>1/3 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2716" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979 June-December</unitdate> Scrapbook
                            pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:3</container>
            <physdesc>2/3 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings and a biography of Nancy O'Brien</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2727" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980-1981</unitdate> Scrapbook pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:4</container>
            <physdesc>3/3 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings and correspondence</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2737" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Scrapbook photograph pages</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:5</container>
            <physdesc>1 notebook</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2744" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Yearly Planner</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">20:6</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2751" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate> Awards- McIntire Citizenship
                            Award</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:1</container>
            <physdesc>51 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are e-mails and numerous congratulation letters for receiving the
                            Paul Goodloe McIntire Citizenship Award</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2763" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate> Awards- McIntire Nominees</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:2</container>
            <physdesc>46 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There is information about Nancy O'Brien and other nominees for the
                            McIntire Award</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2774" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005-2006</unitdate> Awards</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:3</container>
            <physdesc>20 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are e-mails of congratulations for receiving the Drewary Brown
                            Award, and the Bridge Builders Award</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2785" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-2001</unitdate> Certificates</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:4</container>
            <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p/>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2795" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-2003</unitdate> Printed
                            Materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">21:5</container>
            <physdesc>16 items</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>There are newsletters from the Thomas Jefferson Planning District
                            Commission the University of Virginia Newsletter, Preservation Piedmont,
                            Cville Magazine, Charlottesville Observer, League of Women's Voters,
                            Chamber of Commerce, and a newsletter from the Westminster Presbyterian
                            Church Oversize items include a UVA diploma, other certificates of
                            appreciation and a brick with a plaque on it from the Charlottesville
                            Historic Downtown Mall.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2812" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate> Trophies: Gift for Graduation from
                            UVA</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">22:1</container>
            <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A tile of the Rotunda that was a gift from John Connover and Virginia
                            Daugherty (on Nancy O'Brien's graduation from the University of
                            Virginia)</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2825" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate> Trophies: Executive Director
                            Award</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">22:2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Executive Director of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission
                            Award</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e2836" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006</unitdate> Trophies: Drewary J. Brown
                            Award</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">22:3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Drewary J. Brown Award given by the Charlottesville Democratic
                            Committee</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
