<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04086">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04086::A Guide to the Henkel-Miller Family Papers 1793-1910)//EN" "viu04086.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Henkel-Miller Family Papers, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1793-1910</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Miller-Henkel Collection, 1793-1910
                    <num type="collectionnumber">14434</num></subtitle><author>Processed by Dan Weiss, Special Collections Dept. staff in July 2009; machine-readable finding aid
                    created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University
                    of Virginia. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Henkel-Miller Family Papers, <date type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1793-1910</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">14434</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Henkel-Miller Family Papers
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1793-1910</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">14434</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Extent">606 items contained in 5 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 linear feet</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector"/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no Restrictions</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no Restrictions</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Henkel-Miller Family Papers, 1793-1910, #14434, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased from the Museum of Early Southern Decorative Arts,
                    Winston-Salem, North Carolina, on November 17, 2008.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>The Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, operated the Henkel printing press which
                became the most important bilingual printing establishment for German Lutherans in
                the states of Virginia, Tennessee, and North Carolina during the nineteenth century.
                Paul Henkel (1754-1825) was an itinerate Lutheran preacher involved with
                various synods in Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Maryland and North Carolina.
                Solomon David Henkel (1777-1847), Paul's son, was a physician, teacher and
                head of the Henkel Press along with his brother, Ambrose (1786-1870). Andrew
                Henkel (1790-1870), was also the son of Paul Henkel as well as an itinerate
                preacher and educator. Samuel G. Henkel (1807-1863), was the son of Solomon
                and continued running the press after his father's death.</p>
      <p>For more information concerning the contributions of the Henkel family to the
                printing of religious works and preaching in the Lutheran Church, consult Klaus
                Wust's <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Guide to the Henkel Family Papers</title> and Christopher L. Dolmetsch's book,
                    <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The German Press of the Shenandoah Valley.</title></p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains 606 items contained in 5 Hollinger boxes (2.5 linear feet)
                concerning the Henkel Family of Shenandoah and the operation of the Henkel Press in
                New Market, Virginia. The dates of the materials range from 1793-1910, with
                the bulk of the material coming from the first half of the nineteenth century.</p>
      <p>The journals of Paul Henkel give a history of his travels and family as well as the
                history of the Shenandoah Valley. The journals also are a depiction of parts of
                Pennsylvania, Maryland, the Carolinas, Tennessee and Ohio that interacted with the
                Shenandoah Valley. Many of these journals along with Paul Henkel's correspondence
                were used by Dr. William J. Finck to write the "Chronological Life of Paul Henkel"
                (MSS 2827).</p>
      <p>Solomon D. Henkel is the chief recipient of the correspondence as he, along with his
                brother, Ambrose, is the head of the press. He also served as the postmaster of New
                Market, physician and educator. The correspondence covers a variety of subjects
                concerning Solomon's multiple expertise. He does not only receive letters concerning
                his own business, but also in regard to the business of others due to his position
                as postmaster. The collection is invaluable as a source of information on the Henkel
                Family, the starting and operation of the press, the decline of German as a
                prominent language in the Shenandoah Valley, and the activities of Lutheran
                Preachers during this period. Many of the Henkels' business contacts were also
                personal friends so the letters include aspects of daily life as well as the
                logistical matters of the business.</p>
      <p>Much of the later material in the collection is the correspondence, both to and from,
                Samuel G. Henkel, Solomon's son. Samuel's memorandum books are also a tremendous
                source of logistical information especially as it pertains to the history of
                commercial imports to the Winchester Millers and the New Market Henkels from New
                York, Philadelphia, Baltimore and Alexandria. Information includes names of
                merchants, locals, printing, medicines, books, etc.</p>
      <p>Some items of interest are the correspondence of John Barnett (1814-1819)
                which concerns a variety of subjects, including the treatment of maladies, crop
                prices and book sales; a series of letters from the War of 1812, including a discussion of the moral implications of military service, conditions at Camp Crossroads and the defense of Baltimore particularly the battle of North Point and the bombardment of Ft. McHenry where the writer, William Warner, noted "naught could be seen but the light of Rockets and the bursting of Bombs thrown from their shipping at our fort...."; a letter from Jacob Woltz of February 9, 1811 concerning retribution against slaves that killed their
                masters; the correspondence of Warner and Schaeffer from Baltimore, March 26, 1813,
                who must take into account the positions of British troops when shipping goods to
                New Market. The two letters of Gideon Jones from November 1818 describe relations
                with the Cherokees of Georgia, the Secret Green Corn Dance, and the African slaves
                of the Native Americans.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in three series topically, alphabetically and
                chronologically. The manuscripts for publication are organized alphabetically by
                title. Series I is correspondence of the Henkel Press, Series II is the
                correspondence of the Henkel Family and other items of historical importance, and
                Series III is manuscripts intended for publication. Boxes 1 and 2 contain
                correspondence, primarily letters addressed to Solomon or Ambrose Henkel or to the
                Henkel Press in general. Boxes 3 and 4 contain other historical resources on the
                Henkel Press including historical notes by a later hand and the journals and
                memoranda books of the Henkels. Box 5 contains the remainder of the journals and
                memorandum books as well as manuscripts for items that might have been meant for
                publication.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 id="d1e172" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Correspondence of the Henkel Press</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e176" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805-1811</unitdate> Henkel Press Correspondence
                               -General (16 items). Correspondence both in English and German.
                                Correspondents include: John Stock, Samuel Strickler, Hannah Lee,
                                Abraham Lauck, Samuel Nicholson, Solomon Perrin, J. Herschberger,
                                Starck and Lange, George Hudson, Joseph Graff, William Chambers,
                                Daniel West, Jacob D. Dietrich, Bryan Hampson, and Simon
                                Yager.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e188" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1815</unitdate> Henkel Press Correspondence
                               -General (22 items). Correspondence both in English and German.
                                Correspondents include: Daniel West, Charles B. Rhoades, W.F.
                                Thornton, Matthias Kin, Christian Friedrich Schaaf, David Irving,
                                John Blessing, Anthony Weier, David Crawford, Webster Lewis, Peter
                                Eckle (Eckel), George Bourne, Littleberry Purty, John Brown, John B.
                                Groves (Grovis), Slingluff and Fahnestock, A.D. Carden, and George
                                Brittan. Letter of note: June 8, 1815, Matthias Kin to Solomon
                                Henkel: death of Heinrich Muhlenburgh (Muhlenberg)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e202" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816-1818</unitdate> Henkel Press Correspondence
                               -General (19 items). Correspondence both in English and German.
                                Correspondents include: Abel Gibbons, Matthias Sommer, Samuel
                                Harshaw, Jacob Stiegel, Jacob Binckle (Bueklü), Henry Printz,
                                William Marye, Gideon Bottler, John Hoke, Abraham Fravel, Bryan
                                Hampson, John Walker Jr., Peachy Hampson (Harrison), Michael
                                Meyerhoeffer, Margret (Margaretha) Fisher, and Gideon L.
                                Jones.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e215" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819-1821</unitdate> Henkel Press Correspondence
                               -General (22 items). Correspondence both in English and German.
                                Correspondents include: R.C.P. Barton, Samuel Brown, G. McGlassin
                                (McGlassen), Zachariah Shugart, Linn Banks, Henry Fry, Abraham
                                Fravel, John Koontz, B.L. Bogan, J.H. Smoot, William Widdifield, B.
                                Allen, Jacob Garst, Daniel Smith, Edward Almond, William F.
                                Dinninger, Joseph Funk, Stephen North, and H. Swann.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e227" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822-1825, n.d.</unitdate> Henkel Press
                                Correspondence-General (11 items) Correspondence both in English
                                and German. Correspondents include: Sam H. Davis, Jacob Pinkey,
                                David Schweitzer, Kaspar Reinardt (Keinack), Martin Walter, David
                                Ruffner, Pastor Schullehrer, G.H. Riemenschneider.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e237" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814-1819</unitdate> John Barnett to Solomon
                                Henkel (5 items). John Barnett is a resident of Rockbridge County,
                                Virginia. He writes chiefly about health issues of his own and the
                                people in the vicinity. November 12, 1814: two sons in the service,
                                request some high quality paper; June 4, 1816: no colic for several
                                months, crop prices, lots of people dying of consumption; June 15,
                                1816: just had the severest spell of colic, reference to mail not
                                getting through; December 8, 1816: had a severe spell of colic about
                                two weeks ago, hurt leg, boils on other leg, received a hymn book;
                                August 29, 1819: unwell, "sore through the whole system" and refers
                                an ailing Eliza McKnight to Solomon. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e253" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1804-1820</unitdate> John Bottler to Solomon
                                Henkel (2 items). Business, primarily pharmaceuticals. Letters in
                                English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e261" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818-1820</unitdate> Augustus Bournier to Solomon
                                Henkel (5 items). February 25, 1819: Bournier's father is engaging
                                him to go to France and Bournier would like to spend his last months
                                in America near Solomon in New Market; May 3, 1819: News of the
                                success of the school and the regular visits of a Lutheran preacher;
                                April 29, 1820: Bournier has spoken with the French Ambassador, Hyde
                                de Neuville, and will set off for France, leaves for Annapolis the
                                following day. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e274" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811-1820</unitdate> John Buckius to Solomon
                                Henkel (8 items). John Buckius (Buckus) was a coppersmith from New
                                Market working in Canton, Stark County, Ohio. Letters in English and
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e283" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819-1821</unitdate> William Davison (Davidson)
                                to Solomon Henkel (3 items). Coppersmith in Winchester, Virginia.
                                October 7, 1821: concerns a request made by Solomon, acknowledges a
                                packet received. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e292" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817-1820</unitdate> Ananias Davisson (Davidson)
                                to Solomon Henkel (9 items) Harrisonburg, Virginia. Singing school
                                teacher and publisher. Correspondence chiefly concerns the
                                publishing of books for use in his school, especially the famous
                                "Kentucky Harmony." October 25, 1817: 200 copies sent to Solomon,
                                the whole 1000 were not sent because Mrs. [Mortinen?] failed to get
                                them folded; October 29, 1817: book business, specifications, books
                                received; November 3, 1817: 1000 books sent to Solomon along with
                                blank paper, wants leather bound, wrote a small treatise on the
                                nature of music; November 13, 1817: request for one dozen books;
                                November 19, 1817; printing business, pamphlets; November 26, 1817:
                                Angry letter, not getting books on time because Ambrose will not do
                                anything until his wife is restored to health; December 11, 1817:
                                Ambrose finishing some full bound books, request to add names on
                                "back or cover", relays a book order from Mr. H.D. Carden; November
                                12, 1818: request to get a copy of book binding prices in Baltimore;
                                November 15, 1820: money business. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e314" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1814</unitdate> Heinrich Diefenbach to
                                Solomon Henkel (2 items). Lutheran minister and fraktur artist.
                                Greenwich Township, Bercks (Berks) County, Pennsylvania. Letters in
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e323" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1843</unitdate> Adolph Flodoardo to Solomon
                                Henkel (3 items). Resident of New Market. Correspondence chiefly
                                concerns printing orders and German medicine. Letters in
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e332" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1816</unitdate> Jonathan Foster to Solomon
                                Henkel (6 items). Proprietor of the 
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Republican Constellation Establishment,</title> Winchester,
                                Virginia. Letters all concern subscriptions. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e342" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1801-1819</unitdate> John Gruber to Solomon
                                Henkel (18 items). John Gruber and D. May, printers in Hagerstown,
                                Maryland, concern the formation of the Henkel Press and often
                                request to exchange some of their product for books from Henkel
                                Press. November 9, 1801: twelve dozen calendars sent to Solomon,
                                newspapers, invoices, accounts of various people; July 12, 1802:
                                regrets that he cannot assemble the money soon enough; July 27,
                                1802: Solomon is having difficulty with subscribers to the 
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Westliche Correspondenz</title>, a newspaper
                                from Hagerstown; September 28, 1802: twelve dozen calendars and can
                                get more from Baltimore; May 23, 1803: reference to Jacob Ohlinger,
                                selling of calendars and books, subscriptions; September 16, 1803:
                                twelve dozen calendars at 6/10 Maryland currency per dozen; July 9,
                                1804: Michael Zirkle, Abraham Hiertand, Caspar Hoffer, and other
                                news concerning acquaintances; July 24, 1804: writing in haste, the
                                almanac is finished in part; December 23, 1804: sent eight dozen
                                calendars for 1805 and one half dozen books, explanation of
                                shipping; September 16, 1805: has sent eight dozen calendars, John
                                Beckley, did not want this opportunity to pass by; October 27, 1805:
                                bill for German and English almanacs, will send news with the next
                                books and pamphlets, has no time now; January 20, 1806: has printed
                                500 confessionals; February 24, 1806, calendars, printing,
                                newspapers; March 17, 1806: John Bock, printing business, ABC books;
                                July 14, 1806: hears that Solomon wants to start a printing press in
                                New Market, refers him to Mr. Zentler, some information regarding
                                printing (translation on insert); August 18, 1806: David Harry,
                                Isaac Reidenaur, sending calendars and the shipping of items;
                                November 14, 1817: copyright and prices; April 26, 1819: wants to
                                exchange extra English Heidelberg catechisms in loose sheets for
                                German spelling books, no bindery in Hagerstown. Letters in English
                                and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e378" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806-1814</unitdate> J.H.C. Helmuth to Solomon
                                Henkel (5 items) Preacher from Philadelphia who makes use of the
                                books the Henkels print. Letters in German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e386" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799-1812, n.d.</unitdate> David Jackson and his
                                wife, Susan Jackson, to Solomon Henkel (13 items) Jackson and Betton
                                is a druggist firm in Philadelphia. Correspondence is chiefly
                                business and invoices with some personal topics. Letters of note:
                                December 31, 1799: discusses the advanced prices due to the war in
                                Europe; September 21, 1801: announces the death of David Jackson
                                (Sr.) and the continuance of business; April 12, 1803: announces a
                                separation of a partnership in Germantown; July 25, 1803: David
                                Jackson (Jr.) has taken on the family business. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e401" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811-1822</unitdate> Henry Keerl and Sons to
                                Solomon Henkel (8 items). Druggist in Baltimore. Correspondence is
                                chiefly business with very little personal content. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e410" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811-1812</unitdate> William Kreps to Solomon
                                Henkel (3 items). Post master of Hagerstown. March 30, 1811: account
                                of Mr. Pennybaker; September 14, 1811: has written Mr. Pennybaker
                                concerning his debt, but has not received and answer; Letters in
                                English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e420" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816-1822</unitdate> Jacob Lawton-Solomon
                                Henkel (3 items). Father of a student of Solomon's buys land in
                                Arkansas. He inquires as to the health and whereabouts of his family
                                and relates information on 19th century Arkansas. May 11, 1816: requests that Solomon tell his son
                                to write. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e430" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810</unitdate> William Marshall to Ambrose Henkel
                                (2 items). Informs Henkel of the need for a printed title page.
                                August 6, 1810: requests a title page printed according to law so
                                that a copyright can be made. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e439" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1813</unitdate> F.A. Mayo to Solomon Henkel
                                (3 items). Bookseller from Staunton wishes to purchase or exchange
                                English and German books of various sorts with the Henkel Press.
                                January 29, 1812: request for a small quantity of German books that
                                he can sell, he would be happy to send something as soon as
                                possible; April 21, 1813: request for more writing paper; June 1,
                                1813: has books of writing paper, needs to buy more from Solomon;
                                Letters in English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e452" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1809 October 18</unitdate> Solomon Meyer, Washington
                                City, to Solomon Henkel (1 item). Meyer was the printer of 
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The York Gazette</title>. Writes concerning his
                                plan to set up a new printing business in Washington for his sons
                                while he continues to run a "Congress boarding house"; Letter in
                                English</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:22a</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e463" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1821</unitdate> Abraham Miller to Solomon
                                Henkel (21 items). Most letters are from Winchester, Virginia. The
                                Millers were frequent suppliers to the Henkel Press and to Solomon
                                Henkel as a physician. Some letters are from business trips to
                                Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Content concerns business, medical and
                                personal topics. August 13, 1800: Advises Solomon on buying a house;
                                March 15, 1802: will be visiting March 29 to see a child with a
                                harelip; April 6, 1802: follow-up on the child's lip; July 6, 1802:
                                Response to Solomon who did not get all the medicine he ordered;
                                December 27, 1803: Abraham's father died; February 26, 1805: Mother
                                has a relapse of rheumatism in her arm; November 18, 1805: Business
                                in Stanton (Staunton); April 2, 1806: plans to visit; May 20, 1808:
                                Miss Kurtz's death; October 30, 1808: Going to New York and asks if
                                Solomon needs anything from there. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:23</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e482" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819, 1844</unitdate> Frederick (Friedrich) and
                                Louis Miller to Henkel Press (3 items). Hagerstown, Maryland and
                                Winchester, Virginia. Matters of business and health. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:24</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e491" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1803-1823, n.d.</unitdate> Godfrey (Gottfried)
                                Miller to Solomon Henkel (39 items). Winchester, Virginia. Majority
                                of content concerns the Miller's business which sold a variety of
                                items and was closely affiliated with the Red Bud Paper Mill.
                                December 7, 1803: father is very sick; August 23, 1808: family
                                matters; November 28, 1808: offers Solomon the services of a house
                                servant; June 5, 1809: family news, Solomon should visit in the
                                Summer; January 15, 1811: concerning a house table "Haus Dafel" sent
                                by Solomon that the Millers will put in their parlor; July 8, 1811:
                                paid Ambrose $50; March 13, 1812: McNester died, whole city is
                                grieving; September 12, 1812: hopes for a visit in the Fall; July
                                23, 1813: Abraham returned on Tuesday the 20th; July 31, 1813: Abraham Miller is on his way to
                                Philadelphia; October 12, 1814: Lewis Sherry is looking to settle in
                                New Market; March 1, 1815: German almanacs are on their way to
                                Solomon from Mr. Murdock's bookstore; August 9, 1815: honey and
                                family business; January 20, 1816: books sent, information on
                                counterfeit bills; May 18, 1816: reference to Adam Kurtz and his
                                wife, Silas and Abraham in Philadelphia: December 31, 1816: books
                                and a coffee mill; January 30, 1817: business and family; April 5,
                                1818: Godfrey send a number encyclopedia, request for two dozen
                                English catechisms, one dozen German ABC books, and some coffee;
                                January 7, 1819: business concerning books and medicine; January 27,
                                1819: trouble finding writing paper; February 6, 1819: business;
                                March 4, 1819: goods sent to Solomon; August 5, 1819: handmade gifts
                                sent, prospect of coming to New Market; August 19, 1821: request for
                                three dozen English catechisms, Solomon's "boys" are in Winchester;
                                August 16, 1823: Books received; July 9, 18 [?]: has bought oil that
                                he is willing to sell. Letters in German and English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:25</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e524" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1801-1813</unitdate> John (Johannes) Miller to
                                Solomon Henkel (26 items). Winchester and Norfolk, Virginia.
                                Business and personal correspondence. The Millers in Winchester were
                                frequent suppliers to the Henkel Press and to Solomon Henkel as a
                                physician. January 13, 1801: singing schools in New Market, books;
                                January 20, 1801: copies sent; February 18, 1801: Medicines sent to
                                John Groves in New Town; June 5, 1801: invoice and business news;
                                November 17, 1801: returned from Baltimore, bought some goods,
                                indigo, etc.; December 4, 1801: indigo, will no longer deal with
                                Jackson and Betton (prices too high), will try Charles Marshall and
                                Son; January 12, 1802: business proposition (diversification);
                                February 2, 1802: shipping mistake; December 27, 1802: prices for
                                advertising, Helena with the measles; June 22, 1807: Family and
                                friends, travelling and visiting; January 12, 1808: business with a
                                shoemaker in New Market; December 27, 1808: drug prices on the rise;
                                June 6, 1809: received the potash but it was soft and had to dry
                                out; July 18, 1809: business, hopes to visit; August 5, 1809: Sends
                                money that he got from Abraham; August 15, 1809: Mother, wife and
                                child arrived safely; November 21, 180[9]: Death of Gotlob Miller
                                (Uncle); April 22, 1811: business and the quality of Daniel Hoof;
                                July 20, 1812: invoice and business; September 22, 1813: writing
                                from Norfolk, seeks medical advice; October 2, 1813: writing from
                                Norfolk, back in perfect health, British have taken one of the
                                vessels from Baltimore. Letters in English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e553" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814-1823, 1845</unitdate> John Miller to Solomon
                                Henkel-includes John Bell to Solomon Henkel announcing the death
                                of John Miller (23 items). All letters from Winchester except April
                                2, 1821, which is from Frederick Lawn, Maryland. Some letters are
                                signed J &amp; A Miller, presumably meaning John and Abraham. June
                                27, 1814: John Lutz from Georgetown on his way to Kentucky, medical
                                business; July 4, 1814: goods and medicines; August 1, 1814: fever,
                                Helena and Maryann begin school with Mr. Curlet; October 17, 1814:
                                Helena in Winchester, Abraham in Philadelphia; October 29, 1814:
                                medicine has not yet arrived, nor has Abraham from Philadelphia;
                                January 8, 1815: Miller's father-in-law died on November 9 (74 years
                                old), wife's mother also died, Adam Kurtz's wife died in childbirth,
                                missed Helena; April 18, 1817: wants Helena to visit, Mr. Hill will
                                take female scholars, Abraham in Philadelphia; October 15, 1817:
                                Peter is very sick; October 28, 1817: Peter is well again, store
                                business; December 1, 1817: Aunt Kurtz died, will send Helena a jar
                                of preserves; December 13, 1817: business, various goods; May 2,
                                1818: request to reserve a pair of rabbits for the boys; September
                                5, 1820: coming to New Market, bringing his sister, Rebecca, and his
                                daughter, Maryann: October 3, 1820: arrived safely home, Adam Bowers
                                died last Saturday night; December 2, 1820: business; April 2, 1821:
                                business concerning a box of type; January 23, 1822: Peter's wife
                                died last Saturday night; November 21, 1823: response to the news of
                                Helena's death. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e582" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810-1820</unitdate> Red Bud Paper Mill (26
                                items). Frederick County, Maryland. Correspondence chiefly concerns
                                the supply of paper to the Henkel Press. Correspondents include:
                                John Martin, Ann Martin, Rebecca Gildtz, John Geisinger (Guisinger),
                                John Carter, and Smith and Barton. Some letters contain the Red Bud
                                Paper Mill watermark. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e593" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1801-1814</unitdate> Heinrich Muhlenberg to
                                Solomon Henkel (7 items). Lancaster, Pennsylvania. January 21, 1802:
                                responds to Solomon Henkel's news about the religious revival in
                                Carolina, some pharmaceutical matters; July 13, 1802: business,
                                plants and other goods; August 18, 1805 short note on business,
                                books and a horse doctor; January 6, 1806: reference to the Synod,
                                books and business with Great Britain; June 23, 1808: reference to
                                the Synod, some opinions on what a missionary should do; July 25,
                                1814: business both in America and abroad. Letters in
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e608" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1809-1812, n.d.</unitdate> Samuel Saur (Sower,
                                Sauer) to Solomon Henkel (8 items). Baltimore, Maryland. Concerns
                                the selling of printing type to the Henkel Press. August 1, 1812 is
                                from Ambrose Henkel, New Market, Virginia, to Saur. February 20,
                                1809: type sent to Alexandria; March 23, 1809: business with Bryan
                                Hampson in Alexandria; June 12, 1811: received the catechism, but a
                                letter must have fallen out; August 9, 1811: has directed their
                                italic type to B. Harrison in Alexandria; August 1, 1812: Ambrose
                                cannot go to Baltimore as he is going to the southern states,
                                request for type; September 7, 1812: shipped two boxes of type for
                                the Henkels to B. Harrison in Alexandria; December 22, 1812:
                                settlement of accounts. Letters in German and English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e625" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854</unitdate> Charles Shaeffer to Henkel Press
                                (12 items). Easton, Pennsylvania. Concerns the editing and
                                proofreading of Henkel Press texts, especially the translation of
                                the Concordien Buch (Book of Concord). Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e635" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806-1817</unitdate> George (John George, J.G.,
                                Johann Georg) Schmucker to Solomon Henkel (7 items). Hagerstown,
                                Maryland. June 9, 1806: relays a letter from Mr. Helmuth, an author;
                                July 1806: handwritten copy of the "Constitution of our German Book
                                Business"; September 7, 1806: printing business and a reference to
                                John Gruber; November 20, 1807: ABC books; January 6, 1808: business
                                with Ambrose, Andrew and Mr. Schmidt from Lexington; February 1,
                                1809: pleased to see that Solomon spoke with Mr. Woltz about the
                                books, instructions to Solomon regarding the selling of books,
                                regards to Ambrose; January 21 1813 (York): business, magazines,
                                printing, references to Ambrose and Charles. Letters in
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e652" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805-1811</unitdate> Congressman John Smith to
                                Solomon Henkel (18 items), Washington City. January 3, 1805: House
                                and Senate business, new territory of Michigan; January 17, 1805:
                                Burr's Trial for killing Hamilton; January 21, 1805: bill for
                                dividing Indiana territory has passed; January 31, 1805: Business in
                                Washington, "Mr. Randolph has shown his violence"; February 15,
                                1805: Trial of Judge Chase, Dr. Dulaney opposes the delegation of
                                John Smith; December 11, 1806: War in Europe; November 21, 1807:
                                talk of war and Bonaparte; December 20, 1807: trouble with Britain
                                and France; January 30, 1808: Supposition of war; February 23, 1809:
                                embargo; February 11, 1810: preparations for war; January 17, 1811:
                                President's confidential message, closing of [United States?] Bank.
                                Letters in English</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e670" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827-1829</unitdate> J.N. Stirewalt to Solomon
                                Henkel (2 items). Abington, Virginia and Lincoln County, North
                                Carolina. Business partner of the Henkels, these letters are travel
                                reports with some business matters. August 31, 1827: details the
                                difficulties of a journey, asks Solomon to relay the details to his
                                mother, viewed Natural Bridge; September 9, 1829: states that some
                                of Solomon's pills helped with a fever, requests a copy of Luther's
                                entire work. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e683" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1808-1812</unitdate> L. Trimper to Solomon Henkel
                                (6 items). Staunton, Virginia. Concerns the purchase of books from
                                the Henkel Press. November 4, 1808: request for one dozen Lutheran
                                or church catechisms in German for selling, and four dozen German
                                almanacs as well as English ones; June 13, 1809: there is a German
                                teacher in Staunton but no books, request German spelling and
                                grammar books; May 22, 1811: requests German grammar and ABC books
                                to sell to many men in the area. August 17, 1811: sending money for
                                twelve ABC books and "Sprechen Lehrer" (German language books);
                                April 24, 1812: request for more books. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e699" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817-1836</unitdate> Valley Iron to Solomon
                                Henkel (7 items). Correspondence of various iron works in the
                                Shenandoah Valley, to include: Union Forge, Adam Douglass, Isabella
                                Furnace, Liberty Furnace, and Caroline Furnace. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e709" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811-1822</unitdate> Warner (William) and
                                Schaeffer (F.G.) to Solomon Henkel (11 items). Baltimore, Maryland.
                                A supplier of the Henkels, often sending goods through Henry Keerl
                                &amp; Sons. Letter of note: March 26, 1813: "We have received two
                                boxes from Philadelphia addressed to you. To send you them via
                                Alexandria would expose them to the fangs of the British squadron"
                                asks for alternate means of conveyance. Letters in
                                English</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e722" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812-1814, n.d.</unitdate> War of 1812 Subject in
                                Letters.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>May 8, 1812: Jacob Stiegel to Solomon Henkel, concerns the moral
                                implications of serving one's country; May 23, 1813: John Miller to
                                Solomon Henkel, Informs Henkel that he is now a Lieutenant serving a
                                six month tour at Norfolk; September 9, 1814: Webster Lewis to
                                Solomon Henkel, disrupted business and the defense of Baltimore;
                                September 24, 1814: William Warner to Solomon Henkel, Battle of
                                North Point; November 14, 1814: Martin Harry to Solomon Henkel,
                                conditions at Camp Crossroads (XRodes); n.d.: "A New Song about the
                                Defeat of St. Claire in the Western Territory".</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e740" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1824, n.d.</unitdate> Laurentz Wartmann to
                                Solomon Henkel (13 items). Harrisonburg, Virginia. Printer/publisher
                                in Rockingham County and editor of the 
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Rockingham Register</title>. April 27, 1813: Apologizes for
                                creating so much work for Solomon, some business about a cow;
                                January 10, 1814: three letters in one, extremely cordial,
                                essentially a "Happy New Year" letter; March 9, 1814: death of
                                Elisabeth, request for one dozen English [ __ ] and two songs; May
                                16, 1815: Letter of introduction for Mr. Stone; enjoyed the visit,
                                requests Solomon to tell Mrs. Dairy that she must have patience
                                until Mr. Bourne returns from Philadelphia in four weeks; March 26,
                                1816: book business; July 17, 1816: sends an example of a music
                                book, needs letters (type); August 27, 1816: hopes Solomon is happy
                                with the books, will visit in four weeks; October 2, 1816; must
                                cancel his visit because of money, hopes music books have been
                                bound; January 29, 1817; has received the letters (type) from Mr.
                                Hauck and will send them back to Solomon at the first opportunity;
                                December 1, 1821: currently building a printing press; May 23, 1823:
                                tells Solomon to get a thaler from Philip Knopf to give to John Will
                                and to get a receipt; January 23, 1824: expects paper from
                                Winchester this week, needs to get some from Solomon; September 10
                                18__: Mr. Davison is disposed to print something, might print and
                                publish in Harrisonburg, needs help from Solomon and will share the
                                profits. Letters in German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e769" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814-1819</unitdate> Philip Williams to Solomon
                                Henkel (4 items). Woodstock, Virginia. Business and Religious
                                matters. April 15, 1811: requests blank books to be made as soon as
                                possible, legal issues concerning apothecaries; May 21, 1814: legal
                                issues concerning drugs and medicines; May 30, 1814: additional help
                                with legal matters pertaining to the selling of medicine; July 2,
                                1819: Reverend William Armstrong will preach in New Market and
                                requests notice be given, discussed salary for Armstrong. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e783" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1807-1811</unitdate> Jacob Woltz to Solomon
                                Henkel (7 items). Fincastle, Virginia. Purchases various articles
                                from Solomon Henkel. April 21, 1807: medicine received, "waggoner"
                                was paid twice, calls him a 'raskel.'; May 26, 1807: clears up a
                                matter of a transaction, includes additional list of items
                                requested; June 18, 1807: asks Solomon if he has received sent
                                money; August 18, 1807: all things arrived safely, issue of cost;
                                October 5, 1809: requests some medical items to be sent; April 7,
                                1810: a man had his brains knocked out by the fall of a tree,
                                requests lampblack and verdigris; February 9, 1811: reference to
                                slavery, "have had a busy time of it for some time past with some
                                Negroes that murdered thare masters. We hung five the first day of
                                this month." Asks for a barrel of sugar candy. Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e803" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Correspondence of the Henkel Family</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e807" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1821</unitdate> Andrew Henkel to Solomon
                                Henkel (20 items). Various locations. 1803 February 13, Family
                                events with a sketch of flowers; June 10, 1810: "Are you all dead?
                                Or are you sleeping," has received no response to all his letters,
                                request for English song books; August 8, 1811: has sent as much
                                money as he has received; September, 1811: was at a conference the
                                Monday prior where Mr. Miller told him that Mr. Dreher wants five
                                hundred English catechisms; September 7, 1811: Philip arrived last
                                night from the city, horse is sick (the old Gaul), short poem at the
                                end; July 7, 1812: will remain in Point Pleasant for the time being,
                                trying to get some items sent; January 31, 1813: has received the
                                letter from Paul forwarded by Solomon, pleased to hear that the
                                press will stay in New Market; November 12, 1813: departs by boat to
                                the land Kugert bought, believes a German school here would be a
                                greater advantage than preaching itself; November 15, 1813: believes
                                that a lot of books can be sold in Ohio; June 23, 1814: reference to
                                Heinrich Zerkel, staying with the brothers-in-law of Kugert, wants
                                to visit next winter; July 12, 1814: Kugert and Mammi (Nanni) are
                                sick, set up a children's school; August 15, 1814: Nanni has been
                                very sick for 6 weeks, but not consistently, preaching and teaching;
                                March 28, 1816: preached sixteen times in four weeks; April 19,
                                1817: writing a fourth time in hopes of an answer, has received a
                                letter from father (Paul), preaching, it is 11AM and he is fourteen
                                miles away from where he wants to be in the afternoon; April 11,
                                1818: Cannot help it if father moans about him, most of the books
                                are sold; December 19, 1818: Money matters (owes Solomon), printing
                                matters, but primarily details of all his business matters and how
                                he will get the money to Solomon; January 20, 1820: has not written
                                in a while, sold a house, thanks Solomon for the money, church
                                business; Letters in German and English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e842" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1793-1825, n.d.</unitdate> Paul Henkel to Solomon
                                and Ambrose Henkel (23 items). Various locations. November 26, 1803:
                                Wythe County, Virginia, business with George and Carl Greim,
                                itinerant activities in Virginia, preaching several places by name;
                                May 7, 1804: [Margintown ?] (not entirely at the end of the world),
                                reference to Mr. Jacob Scharrer, he is 110 miles from home,
                                itinerate preaching, reference to Laros; May 10, 1804: Philip's
                                progress in the office of Preacher, includes a watercolor by the
                                young Andrew Henkel; February 23, 1805: has had the hardest winter,
                                family news, a great abundance of blacks in Charleston; January 12,
                                1812: need for an English catechism, the ones he has are all in use
                                for the instruction of youth, Mr. John Hofmann has begun a German
                                school; February 7, 1812: selling of books, earthquake; February 12,
                                1812: "almost impossible this Winter to write something proper,"
                                North Carolina needs more hymn books and Ohio want more as well,
                                refers to letter of January 12 where he states that he has not done
                                (or received) an English catechism, yet now there has been a mention
                                of requests for English hymn books; February 13, 1812: reference to
                                1805, Stocks County, North Carolina, via some verse, printing
                                matters; March 15, 1812: today he preaches in the house of Daniel
                                Rausch in German and English, tomorrow he has to educate the youth
                                18 miles away, reference to Laros (reformed preacher); April 6,
                                1812: concerns educational books, Mrs. Sterrit, invitation to visit
                                in May; August 4, 1812: arrived in Harrisburg yesterday evening,
                                business with a Mr. Sufren; December 8, 1812: mentions a print shop
                                in Lincoln, North Carolina, reference to conference, wants to allow
                                to be published the accomplishments of the North Carolina conference
                                in Lincoln; 1812: he is on his trip to Richmond; September 23, 1821:
                                from the house of Caspar Reinard, will be staying the night with the
                                church of a Mr. Schlager, reference to General Synod, Bluntsville,
                                Sulivin (Sullivan) County, postscript in a different hand says they
                                were in Fairfield with Mr. Albrecht; November 23, 1825: Death
                                announcement of Paul Henkel; n.d.: genealogy of Paul Henkel and his
                                descendants. Letters in German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e881" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800-1811</unitdate> Philip Henkel-Various
                                Correspondence (4 items). Martinsburg, Virginia and Lincolnton,
                                North Carolina. February 3, 1807: received the handbill, settled in
                                Lincolnton and has a house and lots; January 31, 1810: relays news
                                about the Lorntz and Milli (Miller?) families, people think that Old
                                Man Milli left a wife and son in Switzerland, possibility of selling
                                land to a neighbor (Motz), genealogical notes on himself and his
                                family; November 5, 1811: evangelistic and personal matters; Letters
                                in German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e895" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825-1854, n.d.</unitdate> Correspondence of
                                Samuel G. Henkel (23 items). Various locations. Correspondence to
                                and from Samuel G. Henkel. Correspondents include:, William A. Evans
                                (Columbus, Mississippi), [K] Krauth (Gettysburg, Pennsylvania), the
                                Rev. J.G. Morris (Baltimore, Maryland), William M. Reynolds
                                (Colubus, Ohio), Jacob Savage (Wayne County, Indiana), H.J. Schmidt
                                (New York), and C. Spielmann (Columbus, Ohio). September 11, 1825:
                                Samuel G. Henkel to Solomon Henkel: has arrived in Winchester Uncle
                                Abraham will come in a few weeks from Baltimore, prices of goods in
                                Winchester, observations on a church and minister there; August 10,
                                1832, William A. Evans to Samuel G. Henkel: medical practice,
                                description of Lowdes County, cholera and President Jackson "who is
                                almost idolized in this part of the country."; January 27, 1833,
                                Samuel G. Henkel to Solomon Henkel: shipping of a cupboard and other
                                unspecified articles; March 13, 1843, L. Salyards to Henkel Press:
                                praises the village of New Market, applies for job at the academy;
                                January 6, 1844, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: request for money
                                and medical advice; May 14, 1844, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel:
                                death of Silon (Solon?, Silas?) A. Henkel; April 20, 1849, Jacob
                                Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: domestic matters, request for a loan;
                                July 10, 1849, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: money matters,
                                continuation of business from April 20 letter, November 3, 1851, C.
                                Spielmann to Samuel G. Henkel: concerns the publication of a
                                manuscript; December 15, 1851, C. Spielmann to Samuel G. Henkel: has
                                mailed the manuscript of Salyard's article referred to in November 3
                                letter, notes on the revision of a theological book; May 28, 1852,
                                William M. Reynolds to Henkel Press: has carefully revised his
                                portion of the Book of Concord, notes concerning it; November 5,
                                1852, Krauth to Samuel G. Henkel: refers to Drs. [Charles N.]
                                Schaeffer and Schmidt as gentlemen who can help with revisions; July
                                24 and 27, 1853, Rev. J.G. Morris to Samuel G. Henkel: translation
                                of the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Concordien Buch</title> is finished;
                                November 21, 1854, H.J. Schmidt to Solomon D. Henkel (who is
                                deceased) and Bros: has received a copy of the 
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Concordien Buch</title>; n.d., Jacob Savage to
                                Samuel G. Henkel: cholera in the area, people dying fast. Letters in
                                English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e937" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824-1825</unitdate> Sylvanus Henkel to Samuel G.
                                Henkel (3 items). Sommerset, Ohio and New Market, Virginia. Letters
                                account of his journey to Ohio: mileage, cost, etc. References to
                                Uncles David, Andrew (Andreas) and Charles (Carolus), Herr
                                Riemenschneider. November 19, 1825 notes that Grandfather (Paul
                                Henkel) is very sick. Letters in German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e948" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799-1857</unitdate> Correspondence of the Henkel
                                Family (12 items). Various locations. Correspondents include: Gideon
                                Henkel, Moses Henkel, Jacob Henkel, Charles (Carolus) Henkel,
                                Ambrose Henkel, David Henkel, William M. Reynolds, and Sarah C.
                                Ayer. Letter of note: June 30, 1857, Sarah C. Ayer to Rebecca M.
                                Henkel: she is teaching and will remain in Warrenton because the
                                school is good, German is becoming "quite fashionable now." Letters
                                in German and English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e961" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815-1910, n.d.</unitdate> Henkel Press Business
                                Items (12 items). Includes accounts and shipping orders with various
                                clients. Letters in German and English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e969" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1804-1848, n.d.</unitdate> Legal Documents (18
                                items). Items include: Saul Henkel's appointment to Lieutenant in
                                the militia, debt notes of John Bury (New Market cabinet maker), an
                                original manuscript for the printing of an advertisement broadside
                                for selling a carding machine by Strasburg merchants, an indenture
                                between James and Ann Booker and John Savage, an Article of
                                Agreement between John Savage and Samuel G. Henkel, a Note of
                                Agreement of John Savage, an Indenture between James and Ann Booker
                                and Ambrose Henkel, and Article of Agreement between Solomon Henkel
                                and Christian Whitmire (miller at Plains Mill), a boarding agreement
                                for Rachel Deary, a draft of an address delivered to the Imitative
                                Legislature by Samuel G. Henkel, a fine on Samuel G. Henkel for
                                nonattendance at muster, a lawsuit of Ambrose Henkel et.al. against
                                George Goodman et.al., and specifications of Summer's Dam to be
                                built next to the land of John Savage.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e989" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> "Second Journey of Dr. Solomon
                                Henkel to Philadelphia." Transcription in a later hand with added
                                notes. Contains references to traveling as well as to family members
                                and acquaintances. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e998" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Historical Notes on the Henkel
                                Family (7 items). "Family Record of Samuel Godfrey Henkel"; "A
                                Journey to Philadelphia over a Century Ago" notes on a diary of
                                Solomon Henkel in a later hand; a timeline and a list of books
                                printed in New Market by Ambrose Henkel's office (also in a later
                                hand). Draft article entitled "The Comstock Lode" for the Shenandoah
                                Valley Folklore Society newsletter. Letters in English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1010" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> "Sons of Rev. Paul Henkel" -
                                Pictures. Photographs, or photographs of paintings of, Solomon,
                                Ambrose and Andrew Henkel, Drawing of David Henkel, Silhouette of
                                Philip Henkel.</unittitle>
            <container type="5">3:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1019" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Marbling Paper. Sample used for
                                books from the Henkel Press.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1026" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c.1890</unitdate> Photograph of Original Henkel
                                Press Building in New Market, Virginia.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1033" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Photograph of Solomon Henkel (or of
                                a painting of him)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1040" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Booklet Written to Ambrose Henkel
                                [by Solomon] on Lutheranism. German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1047" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1862</unitdate> Album of Gems-owned by
                                Julia Henkel. A memento book containing poems, keepsakes, and
                                entries written by friends addressed to "Ginnie." One entry states:
                                "This leaf was sent to me by my brother Caspar, whilst on picket
                                near Fredericksburg, on the Rappahannock. December 26th, 1862." Letters in
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1058" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799</unitdate> Travel Diary and Religious Notes of
                                Paul Henkel. German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1065" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1804-1806, 1814</unitdate> Day Book of Paul
                                Henkel. German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1072" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811-1816</unitdate> Personal Diary of Paul
                                Henkel. Contains brief daily entries as well as birth records.
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1080" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Memoranda Travel Book of Paul
                                Henkel. Records many Valley births in 1782-3 as well as a contract
                                for bonding and some German-Latin vocabulary.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1088" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Devotional Booklet of Paul Henkel.
                                German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1095" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Notebook of Philip Henkel. Records
                                a trip. German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1102" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 April 3</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Book of
                                Biblical Verses</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1109" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 April</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. English</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1116" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 April</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. English</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1123" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 October</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. Includes a sketch of the bridge at Harpers Ferry.
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1131" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 April</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. English and German.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1138" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 October</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. English.s</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1145" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 October</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book. English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1152" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 October 14</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's
                                Memorandum Book. English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1159" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849-1851</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's
                                Memorandum Book. English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1166" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852-1856</unitdate> Samuel G. Henkel's
                                Memorandum Book. English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1173" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 April 8</unitdate> Siram P. Henkel's Memorandum
                                Book</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1180" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845</unitdate> Day Book of Socrates Henkel.
                                English.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1187" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Personal Booklet of a Henkel Family
                                Member with a French-German Learning Device</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1194" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823</unitdate> Notebook of Joseph S.
                                Rupert</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1201" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829</unitdate> "Memorandum of Books, etc. Placed
                                in the Care of Several Agents in N.C. and Tennessee."</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1208" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839</unitdate> Memorandum Book</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e1215" level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Manuscripts Intended for Publication</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="d1e1219" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Manuscript-"Bedenken über
                                den Thorheit der Menschen"</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1226" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805 September 4</unitdate> [Manuscript]-"Ein Christags
                                Geschenk für Kinder die im neuen Testemente lesen über
                                das sogenannte Christkindlein"-by Paul Henkel</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1234" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> [Manuscript]-<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Church Hymn Book</title> 2nd Ed.-by Paul Henkel</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1241" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Manuscript-
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Kurzer Anzug der Teologiae</title></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1248" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> [Manuscript]-Latin-German Study
                                Book written by Solomon Henkel</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1255" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Manuscript-"Ein Memorial an die
                                ehrw. Lutherische Synode von Märeland und
                                Virginia."</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1263" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805</unitdate> [Manuscript]-"Negro Song"-made
                                by Saul Henkel</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1270" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">c. 1817</unitdate> [Manuscript]-"Proceedings of a
                                Special Conference Held in Madison County"</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1277" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Religious Manuscripts meant for
                                Publication</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:15</container>
            <physdesc>3 items</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1285" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Science and Medicine Manuscripts -
                                Possibly for Publication</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:16</container>
            <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1293" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823</unitdate><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Tieren Büch</title>-Samuel G.
                                Henkel</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1301" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823</unitdate> Accompanying Illustrations for
                                    <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Tieren Büch</title></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="d1e1308" level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate> Vocabulary Book</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">5:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
