<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03945">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03945::Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from
Claytor's Book Store)//EN" "viu03945.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1789-1938</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store
<num type="collectionnumber">1166, etc.
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Word, created by Brian Bader, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 13, 2005 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1789-1938 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">1166, etc.
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1938
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">1166, etc.
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection consists of ca. 250 items (2 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot).
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased from Claytor's Book Store, Accession #1166, etc., Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased from Claytor's Book Store, Charlottesville, Va. in July 1941.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This is a collection of Americana whose contents and dates vary widely, with most of the materials dating from various time periods throughout the Nineteenth Century. There are numerous documents from Virginia
and Pennsylvania, but other states in the eastern U.S. are represented, including Georgia, New York, West Virginia, and New Jersey. There are financial documents, correspondence (letters and postal cards),
marriage records, diaries, unpublished poetry and a fragment of a novel, land grants and surveys, and school workbooks. There is material concerning the Fulkerson, Vance, and Stringfellow families, all principally
located in Virginia, and Edwin and W.J. Robinson of Pennsylvania (relationship unknown). Specific items include an 1861 Pennsylvania Militia document, a late 1890s visiting list for a home in Washington, D.C.,
U.S. Navy pay records for the Washington Navy Yard from the 1850s, and paperwork from the 1930s for the Green Bookman bookstore in Charlottesville.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>According to a guide prepared in 1972, there was no original filing order of this material. They were initially filed by specific designations and general classification of miscellaneous items. This arrangement
has been generally retained, with the papers arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within topic.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e131">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Account book from Cartersville, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1793-1796
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Account book from Cartersville, Va. Sales are recorded for crops (corn, tobacco, etc.), alcoholic beverages, clothing, and other items. Dates covered are October 10, 1793-July 11, 1796.
<num>#1166
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e146">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Daniel Stickley's cyphering book
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>An arithmetic workbook containing "vulgar fractions" and word problems. The title page is also signed by Thomas Coles.
<num>#1166-a
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e161">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Democratic Party miscellanea
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Newspaper clippings, broadsides, and handwritten speech transcript by an unknown author, concerning Glover Cleveland and the Democratic Party in Pennsylvania and Virginia during the 1890s.
<num>#1166-b
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e176">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Diaries
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841, 1874
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Two diaries. The first (a fragment) is probably from 1841-1842 (there is an entry for Saturday, Dec. 25th, Christmas Day). Its author is anonymous, and it mentions names such as Wm. H. Blackwell, Alex Brown,
Wm. S. Bridgforth, Joe Winn, Joel M. Ragsdale, Josiah B. Wilson, and others. Also mentioned are Petersburg and visitors from Stokes County, N.C. There is much discussion of money lending and owed debts. The second
diary is from Minnie Harris of Shady Glen. The diary is written in a <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Scholar's Guide to Chirography,</title> printed in Portsmouth in 1827. The year of the diary entries is 1874 and the tone of many entries is melancholy. There is much mention of visiting, Bible study, and church attendance. A place name, Middlebrook, is also mentioned, so the author was possibly living in Virginia.
<num>#1166-c
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e194">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833-1867
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5-6
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Financial papers include an 1833 paybook kept by Samuel Hattaman for the NS Company, 1840s-1850s wood sales by Henry Walker of Petersburg, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Trial Balance for Year Ending 1st March 1848,</title> an 1840s-1850s account
book, an 1830s-1850s account book of the Fork Mine and other mining companies, and an 1867 sales book from John F. Rison with Grasty &amp; Rison, Danville, Va. Other names mentioned in the papers are Thomas
Anderson (1838) and Henry Walker of Petersburg, Va. (1851). There are numerous papers about Botetourt County, Va. resident George Deisher and his estate from the 1830s-1840s. There is a census or tax report, from ca. 1857, listing names and numbers of white laborers, black laborers, slaves, and hogs.
<num>#1166-d
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e212">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Fulkerson and Vance families correspondence
</unittitle>
          <physloc>1810-1862
</physloc>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence of the Fulkerson and Vance families in Abingdon, Va., and in Tennessee, Kentucky, Indiana, Missouri, and South Carolina. Primary topics include family and domestic affairs. An October 8, 1814, letter from James Vance to his mother comments on his readiness to fight in the War of 1812. An October 30, 1851, letter from Jim Fulkerson to his sister Kate mentions "an exciting election here between the secessionist and the cooperationist, [the latter] carried the day by a long majority." He mentions "They are all disunionist but the party that carried the day were for waiting untill the other states help them to break up the
Union." There is a January 20, 1862, letter from Margaret Fulkerson to "My dear Son," in which she writes that "it gave us considerable relief to know that you were once more in Camp." She often thinks "how little
the bad weather affects us in comparison with those in the Army." There is much discussion of family and home events.
<num>#1166-e
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e226">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Green Bookman (bookstore) papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1936-1938, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, an invoice, and merchandise lists from the Green Bookman, a bookstore located in Bridgewater and later Charlottesville, Va., and its proprietor, Charles L. Worthington. There is a correspondence
about a possible book purchase between Worthington and George B. Zehmer, University of Virginia Extension Division director.
<num>#1166-f
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Land grants and survey from North Carolina, Pennsylvania, and South Carolina
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1789-1799
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9, oversize
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>A 1789 Bladen County, N.C., land grant; a 1797 Franklin County, Pa., land grant from Thomas Durboraus to James Meeks; and a 1799 Prince George's Parish, S.C., land survey for Caleb Sutton and Thomas Hoddy.
<num>#1166-g
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e256">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Legal documents from Virginia and Georgia
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851-1929
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>A March 1, 1851, deposition of Asa Brown in Loudon County, Va., attesting to the War of 1812 service of Robert Bogue in the company commanded by Captain Stephen Daniel in the 5th Regiment of Virginia Militia
commanded by Colonel Street and later in the 5th Regiment of Regulars commanded by Colonel Peter Little. Also included is a July 2, 1866, notice of debt in Leesburg, Va., for William and John Grimes to the
Commonwealth of Virginia. There is a mostly illegible 1873 legal document from Bibb County, Ga. Also included is "An ordinance to further prohibit ...ardent spirits" in Petersburg, Va., dated March 19, 1918, with
a handwritten note indicating "Passed Sept. 20, 1921." There is a January 1926 legal document concerning an adultery charge involving Mary Lillian Licklider and Harry G. Tonkin. Also included is a document
addressed to the Judicial Council in Virginia elaborating upon an April 30, 1929, report on handling court records.
<num>#1166-h
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e271">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from various correspondents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844-1932
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Miscellaneouse letters. Many are without dates and the names of correspondents on some are illegible or hard to read. Names and places mentioned include: "Mrs. Frank W. Edmonson, Oak Point;" "Dear Mrs.
Faulkner" [from] Lila R.; and "My Dear Mr. Ritchie." Other names, locations, and dates include: Henry Buckler, Harrisburg, Pa., from a correspondent in Pittsburgh (October 14, 1844); Mr. W.G. Catlett from a New
Orleans correspondent (November 10, 1866); to Aunt Mat and Kate from Mary (Mrs. Thomas Totterdale), Clarksburg, W.Va. (December 1, 1908); to Mr. J.A. Patterson of Charlottesville, Va., from the Jones Brothers
Company, Boston, Mass. (November 5, 1930); to John Armstrong Chanler from W.G. Maxwell, New York (April 13, 1931); and to Mrs. Findley Braden from the Presbyterian Publishing Company (June 22, 1932).
<num>#1166-i
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e287">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Manuscript of unidentified Southern novel
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1850
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1-2
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Pages 200-620 of a handwritten manuscript novel. Two of the characters are named Eustace Mortimer and Garnet. Some of the story concerns an insurgency to "incite a servile insurrection" in the South and the
measures taken to counter it (see page 372). The manuscript is divided into 2 parts, each bound on the left margin with string.
<num>#1166-j
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e302">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Marriage licenses and records and wedding invitation from Virginia and New York.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838-1914
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Marriage licenses of Abraham Alger and Rebecca Stover (February 26, 1838, Shendandoah County, Va.) and John Wade, Jr., and Adelia Ann Ashingherst (December 3, 1863, Franklin County, Va.). Record of marriages in
East Hamburgh, Erie County, N.Y. (1891-1893). Invitation with envelope sent to Mr. and Mrs. E.R. McKethan for the wedding of Alfred Moore Scales and Mary Leigh Pell (daughter of Reverend Edward Leigh Pell)
(September 16, 1914, Richmond, Va.).
<num>#1166-k
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e317">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous items
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865-1919, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Undated items include: a needlwork bookmark; a calling card with Miss Kate Chambers written on it; handwritten notes (and examinations--"Preliminary Examination") on physiology; geography, and history;
potpourri preparation directions; a note about Presbyters and the Directory of Worship revision; an undated list of names; and a mostly illegible speech transcript ("With the permission of our President, leaders,
members of the senate, I have prepared..."). An 1865-1866 copy book with "Josephine Strickland" written in it. An 1878 list of merchandise. Three 1882 postal cards to Henry Lowry, Bedford, Va. 1887 Ladies Note-
Book and Calendar. A 1908 postal card to Samuel Shreckshire, Raphine, Va. January 1911 newspaper clippings which appeared in the Evening bulletin. ("The story of Long Beach, New Jersey"). Robert D. Coxe
contributed to reminiscences about the New Jersey shore area. A February 10, 1911, poultry farming scholarship certificate from the International Correspondence School, Scranton, Pa., for R.N. Watts of Memphis,
Tenn. An April 14, 1913, telegram to Richard Oulahan about McAdoo. A July 1919 certificate from the Virginia Board of Education for Margaret Lassiter to teach in public elementary schools.
<num>#1166-l
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e332">
        <did>
          <unittitle>An act providing for the immediate expenses of the Volunteer Militia of this State now in Actual Service
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 May 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>A handwritten legislative document authorized by the Pennsylvania General Assembly to supply the necessary contingent expenses of Pennsylvania militia in the service of the United States. The names (but not
signatures) of the Speaker of the Pennsylvania House of Representative, the Speaker of the Pennsylvania Senate, and the Governor of Pennsylvania are at the end of the document (Elisha W. Davis, L.W. Hall, and A.G
Curtin).
<num>#1166-m
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e347">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Poems
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Two undated, anonymous poems: Tired and The wanderer's return. Also included is Memories of the scarlet and blue by Frank G. Dawson.
<num>#1166-n
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e362">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edwin P. and W.J. Robinson papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858-1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters, receipts, telegrams, envelopes, and a cancelled check indentified to Edwin P. and W.J. Robinson. Their relationship, if any, is not known. Locations named on the documents include places in New York,
Missouri, Illinois, and Pennsylvania, with the latter most prevalent. (Dauphin, Pa., is mentioned on a number of documents.) Edwin Robinson's name includes the title "Rev." on several documents. He may have been
Presbyterian.
<num>#1166-o
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e377">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Stringfellow family papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833-1860, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Letters, legal documents (wills, indentures, estate papers, etc.), deeds, financial documents, invitations, and other papers from Stringfellow family members living principally in Culpeper County, Va. Most of
the papers were are related to James L. Stringfellow, but there is also mention of Thornton and Lawrence Stringfellow. Various papers concerning George Deisher (of Botetourt County, Va.) and his estate are
included in the materials but the relationship of any member of the Stringfellow family to Deisher is unclear. Many of the documents concern estate law and there are numerous legal documents prepared in Fauquier
County, Va.
<num>#1166-p
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e392">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Study notebook of Alexander R. Pendleton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866-1869
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bound notebook belonging to Alexander R. Pendleton, Martinsburg, Va. while a student at the College of New Jersey (Princeton University). Topics include elocution and geology. Professor Guyot is mentioned as a geology instructor and there is also mention of Nassau Hall.
<num>#1166-q
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e407">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Surveying book of F.D. Eastham
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858-1896
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Surveying book kept by F.D. Eastham, covers the stating and working out of problems in geometry and trigonometry as the two relate to land surveying. There is an entry dated March 16th, 1896, entitled "Scholars
present March 16th, 1896."
<num>#1166-r
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e422">
        <did>
          <unittitle>United States Navy documents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854-1856
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Pay receipts for officers signed at the Washington Navy Yard by Thomas B. Nalle, purser in the United States Navy. Also included is a 2-page handwritten copy of Navy regulations.
<num>#1166-s
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e437">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Visiting list for 1710 16th Street
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1898-1899
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bound notebook embossed on the cover with "Visiting List." Names and addresses of visitors in 1898-1899 to 1710 16th Street, Washington, D.C., are handwritten in the notebook, alphabetically by visitors'
surnames. There is no information on the owner of the home for which the book was kept.
<num>#1166-t
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e453">
        <did>
          <unittitle>West Virginia documents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1898-1904
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Fayette County tax receipts from 1904 for the Low Moor Iron Company, made out to Sheriff N. Daniel, and an 1898 lawsuit concerning the location of the county seat of Randolph County, W.Va.
<num>#1166-u
</num></p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
