<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01479">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01479::John Brooks Henderson Journal, 1895)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01479.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01479::John Brooks Henderson
             Journal, 1895)//EN" "viu01479.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the John Brooks Henderson Journal 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1895</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Henderson, John Brooks Journal, 1895 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11057</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">24 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 16, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01479::John Brooks
            Henderson Journal, 1895)//EN" "viu01479.xml" converted from
            EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-03-01" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Mar 01, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the John Brooks Henderson Journal 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1895</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11057</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>John Brooks Henderson Journal 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1895</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11057</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         contains 1 volume (bound, unpaged), a 1991 typescript of the
         journal prepared by Helen Marie Hawkins, and an electrostatic
         copy of a photograph of Henderson.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This is a journal of a trip to
         Formosa with the Chinese Commission, for the purpose of
         transferring officially that Island to the
         Japanese.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>John Brooks Henderson Journal, 1895, Accession #11057,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the Library on September 2,
            1992, by Helen Marie Hawkins of Richmond, Virginia.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>John Brooks Henderson, Jr. (1870-1923) was born in
         Louisiana, Missouri, and attended Harvard, receiving his law
         degree from George Washington University in 1893. He was later
         a Republican candidate for Congress in 1906 from the eighth
         Virginia district. In 1901, he wrote 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">American Diplomatic Questions</title>.
         Henderson served as private secretary to former Secretary of
         State (under President Harrison) John Watson Foster
         (1836-1917). Foster was born in Pike County, Indiana, and
         received two degrees from Indiana University and attended
         Harvard Law School for one year. He was admitted to the
         Indiana Bar and practiced law at Evansville, 1857-1861, until
         he entered the Union Army as a major in the 25th Indiana
         Volunteers. He served as editor of the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Evansville Daily Journal</title>,
         1865-1869 and became postmaster of Evansville in 1869-1873.
         After that he began his diplomatic career, serving as minister
         to Mexico (1873-1880), to Russia (1880-1881), to Spain
         (1883-1885), and as Secretary of State (1892- 1893).</p>
      <p>In 1894, Foster was invited as a private citizen by the
         Emperor of China to participate in the peace negotiations with
         Japan at the conclusion of the Sino-Japanese War; at that time
         he held no United States government position. The United
         States, being on friendly terms with both powers had
         maintained a policy of strict neutrality throughout the
         conflict. Foster had served as legal counsel to the Chinese
         legation in Washington, D.C., during the war and was well
         aware of the events transpiring in the Far East.</p>
      <p>On December 22, Foster received a telegram from the Tsungli
         Yamen (Foreign Office) requesting his counsel in assisting a
         Chinese commission headed by the elderly Viceroy, Li
         Hung-chang, appointed to negotiate the peace with Japan.
         Foster accompanied the Viceroy and his son, Li Ching-fong, to
         Shimonoseki, where negotionations were to be held. As a result
         of difficult negotiations with the Japanese, the peace terms
         proposed by the Japanese in the Treaty of Shimonoseki were
         finally reduced to the recogition by China of Korean
         independence, the cessation of Taiwan, the Pescadores, and the
         Liaotung Peninsula to Japan, the opening of four Chinese port
         cities as treaty ports, guarantees for Japanese citizens to
         operate factories in China and an indemnity of two million
         taels. The formal signing of the treaty took place in
         Shimonoseki on April 17, 1895. Later the Japanese relinguished
         their demand for the Liaotung Peninsula.</p>
      <p>Foster then traveled to Peking, where he encouraged the
         Tsungli Yamen on behalf of Li Hung-chang, to ratify the
         treaty. On May 8, 1895, the treaty was signed at Chefoo but
         the unpleasant task of transferring the island of Formosa
         (Taiwan) to the Japanese remained. The people of Taiwan had
         declared their independence in late May, establishing the
         Republic of Taiwan forcing the Japanese to fight to gain
         control of their new territory. The Japanese had demanded that
         the Chinese appoint a commission to handle the transfer so the
         Tsungli Yamen appointed Li Ching-fong, the son of the Chinese
         Viceroy Li Hung-chang, to this unpopular assignment. The
         Viceroy pleaded with Foster to accompany his son on this
         dangerous mission and he agreed to do so. The journal in this
         collection was kept by Henderson about this part of Foster's
         mission to China.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of a bound autograph manuscript,
         1895, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Journal of Trip to Formosa with the
         Chinese Commission, for the purpose of transferring officially
         that Island to the Japanese</title>kept by John Brooks
         Henderson, Jr. (1870-1923), private secretary to former
         Secretary of State (under President Harrison) John W. Foster
         (1836-1917). Also present is a 1991 typescript of the journal
         prepared by Helen Marie Hawkins with an electrostatic copy of
         a photograph of Henderson.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Select Journal Entries</head>
      <p>In the beginning of his journal, Henderson mentions the
         signing (April 17) and the ratification (May 8) of the Treaty
         of Shimonoseki at Chefoo; the opposition to the liberal reform
         policy of Viceroy Li Hung-chang; the actions of Russia,
         France, and Germany, forcing Japan to relinquish her claim on
         the Liaotung Peninsula; the appointment of Li Ching-fong to
         carry out the transfer of Formosa (Taiwan); the indigenous
         warriors, the "Black Flags" who threatened to kill anyone who
         landed on Formosa for purposes of cession; the plea of the
         Viceroy for Foster to accompany his son to Formosa; and
         traveling on the steamer, May 21-24, Kung Yi.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 25 / Shanghai</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Henderson also mentions Consul General Jernigan; his
         observations about Lord Li Ching- fong and his fear of attack
         in Shanghai; news of the Formosan secession and the formation
         of the Republic of Formosa; and the secret shipment of arms to
         Formosa from Shanghai and Canton.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 26 / Shanghai</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Foster sends a telegram to Nagasaki inquiring about the
         departure of Admiral Kabayama from Japan; Henderson writes
         concerning the possibility of having to wait for the Japanese
         conquest of the island; the strongly fortified port cities
         Tamsui and Keelung; a social function aboard the man-of-war
         U.S.S. Petrel; a comparison of American and European
         travelers; the detrimental effect of not having a Consular or
         Diplomatic Service with a proper system of training and of the
         spoils system at foreign posts; Foster's desire to leave at
         once for Formosa to meet the Japanese; the procurement of the
         medical services of Dr. Johnson, a missionary in Chinese
         costume, who brought probes and other equipment for removing
         bullets; his shell collection and those of a collector friend
         of his, Mr. Schmacker, head of Carlowitz and Company.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 27 / Shanghai</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Henderson writes concerning the Japanese fleet off the port
         of Tamsui, where Kabayama is waiting for Lord Li (the son);
         the bad judgment of Viceroy Li in delaying his return to
         Peking; and his opinion of Consul General [Thomas R. ?]
         Jernigan.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 28 / Shanghai</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>He mentions the concern of Viceroy Li for the safety of his
         son who wants to send 100 Chinese soldiers as a bodyguard; his
         opinion of Chang Yen Hoon (a Chinese mandarin ?); Dr.
         Johnson's bill for medicines and bullet extractors; "The scum
         of Keoang Tung, the Canton province, the rowdies and pirates
         of the coast are assembling under the black flag"; and the
         desertion rate aboard the Kung Fi, especially the loss of the
         cook.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 29 / Shanghai</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>He discusses the cosmopolitan state of Shanghai and his
         opinion of Oriental women. May 30 / traveling down the Yangtze
         River</p>
      <p>On the Kung Yi, receives news that the Japanese have landed
         at Taipehou and have notified the government that it must
         vacate; and mentions the presence on board of Manlicher rifles
         and personal revolvers.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">May 31 / On the Kung Yi</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Having left Woosung, they arrived a few miles north of
         Tamsui; and considerable time spent preparing a document
         stating that Li Ching-fong had been appointed Commissioner
         with full powers to transfer Formosa.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">June 1/ East of Keelung, Formosa</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Mentions the preparation of the Japanese to land on
         Formosa; the report of Mr. Morse, the American commissioner of
         customs for the port of Tamsui that the heart of the people
         was not in the revolution; the journey to a point about twelve
         miles away from Keelung, anchored next to the Yokohama Maru,
         the vessel of Admiral Kabayama; and his opinion of Oriental
         music.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">June 2 / East of Keelung,
            Formosa</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>Henderson writes concerning the visits of Lord Li to see
         Admiral Kabayama on the Yokohama Maru and the visits of
         Kabayama to the Kung Yi, until a form of transfer was
         eventually agreed upon; the purchase of some shells from
         indigenous peoples, and his sorrow over missing the battle on
         the morrow.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">June 3 / At sea</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>He writes about the bad weather on the return to Shanghai;
         his pleasure in reading Alfred Russel Wallace's Malay
         Archipelago; and his views on health.</p>
      <p>
        <emph render="bold">June 4 / At sea</emph>
        <lb/>
      </p>
      <p>He relates the facts concerning the up and down career of a
         Chinese naval officer, Len Mon-king; and reached Shanghai
         about four. At the end of the journal, Henderson supplies an
         itinerary for his and Foster's journey to China on the mission
         for the Viceroy.</p>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
