<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03950">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03950::Papers of Richard D. McDowell)//EN" "viu03950.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Richard D. McDowell <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1967 July 24-1968 August 24</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">McDowell, Richard D., Papers 
<num type="collectionnumber">13373
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Word, created by Brian Bader, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 28, 2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Richard D. McDowell<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1967 July 24-1968 August 24.</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">13373
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Richard D. McDowell
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 July 24-1968 August 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">13373
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection consists of 46 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Richard D. McDowell, Accession #13373, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Gift of Richard D. McDowell, Pungoteague, Va., 2005 July 22.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Richard D. McDowell was an E-5 staff sergeant in the U.S. Air Force in 1967 when he was transferred from the 544th Strategic Reconnaissance Wing in Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska, to service in Vietnam. At
this time he had served 12 years in the Air Force. He saw duty at Tan Son Nhut Air Base as a photo interpreter from September 1967-September 1968. His unit was the 6470th Reconnaissance Tactical Squadron. He later
served two tours of duty in Thailand (1971-1972 and 1973-1974) with the 432nd Reconnaissance Tactical Squadron. The correspondence in this collection dates from his Vietnam service and is written to his stepfather
and mother, Newton and Frances Thomas.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection consists chiefly of letters and postcards written by McDowell from Vietnam to his parents in Houston, Tex. McDowell was stationed at Tan Son Nhut Air Base and several letters describe the Tet
Offensive in January-February 1968. There are also some vivid accounts of Communist rocket and mortar attacks on the air base.</p>
      <p>
Many of the other letters provide insight on daily life at Tan Son Nhut including such
matters as pay, the Vietnamese people and military, living arrangements, work, food, weather, photography (there are no photos in the collection), and leave to Hong Kong in July 1968. McDowell also discusses, in
response to correspondence sent to him, family matters at home (there are no letters from his parents in the collection), his desire to return to the States, and his plans for his return. He also occasionally
mentions his then-girlfriend, Janice.
</p>
      <p>With the letters is a 42-page memoir <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">What did you do in the war Daddy?</title> containing background information on McDowell, transcripts of the letters, and commentary.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The papers are divided into two series: Series I: the memoir <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">What did you do in the war daddy?</title> and Series II: Correspondence, which is arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e146">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Memoir : <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">What did you do in the war daddy?</title></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Complete typed transcriptions of almost all of McDowell's postcards and letters included in the collection. Salutations and signatures are omitted and parenthetical punctuation is used to indicate paragraph breaks. McDowell precedes the transcriptions with some biographical background on his life before his Vietnam service mentioning how the U.S. Air Force Strategic Air Command (SAC) was trying to find ways to get into the Vietnam War "action" and at the same time losing intelligence personnel known as Photo Interpreters (PIs) to service in Southeast Asia. He notes the massive increase in PI numbers in the Air Force during 1966-1967. He volunteered for PI training and upon completing a long course was quickly processed for duty in Vietnam. The memoir concludes with a brief account of his post-Vietnam War activities. Throughout the memoir, he provides commentary on his letters. Highlights of the commentary are provided below, and direct quotes from the commentary are given in quotation marks.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his October 14, 1967, letter unflatteringly describes the colonel in command of his unit.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his Thanksgiving 1967 letter elaborates on his work using Defense Environment Mosaics made from SR-71 (high-altitude reconnaissance aircraft) photography of North Vietnam. McDowell "mosaicked"
North Vietnamese antiaircraft artillery and surface-to-air missile sites in the Hanoi/Haiphong area but just as he completed his work President Lyndon Johnson called another bombing halt over North Vietnam.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his January 11, 1968, letter mentions the hazards of the fumes which came from classified aerial photography films he had been destroying by burning.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his January 31, 1968, letter corrects his letter's description of the "A.P.s" [Air Police] reaction to Tet Offensive Viet Cong attacks on Ton San Nhut. In the letter McDowell reported the "A.P.s handled it." He later learned that the "apes" were almost overwhelmed and that Army units saved them. After Tet, McDowell notes that A.P. organization and training changed from guard duty to combat-oriented.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his February 3, 1968, letter notes that "the General" [unidentified, possibly the commanding officer of Ton San Nhut ] was lobbying prior to Tet to have the air base removed from the combat pay area and have it beautified by removing bunkers. McDowell also comments that a mass grave was dug for dead Viet Cong along the air base perimeter road and that the Americans "started to really win, but not in the press at home."
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his February 4, 1968, letter describes an incident which McDowell characterizes as the "Best thing I did in the war." He saw a bunch of "grunts" (Army troops) resting by nearby helicopters and called them over to clean up with hot showers. He gave them towels and noted that most of them went in fully clothed and stripped in the hot water. Done without authorization, this act may have gotten McDowell into trouble but he did not care about any consequences.
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his May 6, 1968, letter notes that their new commanding officer had an excess of unemployed lieutenants who were made into "instructors" for on-the-job training. His "worse dim bulb, draft dodging, pot smoking A2C [airman, 2nd class] knew more than they [the lieutenants] did."
</p>
          <p> Commentary to his July 18, 1968, letter describes an error in his post-Vietnam training assignment. McDowell was ordered to "Advanced SAC PI school at Offutt [Air Force Base]" but on his arrival was told he did not belong there. Although this assignment did permit him to get out of Vietnam early, problems with his security clearance and his lack of need for learning satellite photography techniques kept him from attending the school.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e174">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 24 1967-August 25 1968
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e181">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 July 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes a copy of his orders (Form AF 899, Permanent Change of Station Order - Military). Mentions his travel plans and completion of schooling and inquires about the selling of his parents' house.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e195">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Newt"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 August
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Mentions shipping home some of his personal items and his expert score shooting the M-16 rifle. Letter is dated only by month and year.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e209">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Three Postcards to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 September
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1
</container>
            <physdesc>APCSs
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Three postcards describing airplane travel to Vietnam and his activities at a stop in San Francisco. He reports being awake for 28 hours and tired.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e223">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Y'all"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 September 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A "quick note" which gives his new APO address.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e237">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 October 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Reports that it is "hot and humid and stinks, but that's Asia" and that he works in an air conditioned building. Discusses pay and savings, the food ("not bad - fresh eggs and vegetables"), plenty of beer, not
being issued a weapon, no mortar harassment of the base. "This could turn into a good tour of duty."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e251">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 October 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Still has not received mail. Writes that he has been assigned to a newly formed section and discusses his work schedule. Needs an alarm clock and a lamp from home. Lists liquor prices ("Jack Daniels Black Label
$3.30 a quart") and describes the new "mamasan" who cleans the barracks with a pretty smile and giggle.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e265">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Mom, Newt"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 October 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Writes that mail has arrived and discusses his work schedule. Asks his parents to write Janice (his girlfriend) but to give him a week to warn her.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e279">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Mom"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 October 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Writes that he got the letter and package and praises the lamp which was sent to him. Has received "fan mail" from two 13-year old girls who evidently were alerted to his duty in Vietnam by a friend who posted
his address to the World Herald. Discusses plans to purchase a camera.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e293">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 October 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Writes that he is sorry to hear about a house deal coming out so bad at home. Inquires about Janice and requests a print of him in uniform to send to her. Discusses slides which he has been taking with his
camera.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e307">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 Thanksgiving
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>. "Today is just another workday." Writes that when they leave "20 years from now the Vietnamese will have a fine city. Plenty of public housing, shopping centers, recreation..." Discusses the AC-47 airplane (a
combat version of the Douglas C-47 Skytrain, known as the Dragonship or the Goony Bird).
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e322">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Y'all"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967 December 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Comments about his parents new living arrangements in an apartment. Writes that he bought a bicycle and may be requesting inner tubes from home if the Indian Dunlops and Vietnamese Michelins don't work out.
Discusses at length the camera and accessories he has ordered.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e336">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Begins the letter with the greeting "I come home this year!" Discusses Christmas presents exchanged with his parents. Discusses plans for his next assignment, in Europe or the United States.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e350">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses mail delays. Discusses burning classified material all week and how "this physical labor is hard on an old softie like me."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e364">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes commentary on pictures he took (not included in collection) including the National Palace, the downtown Saigon monument, a Studebaker car, and other subjects.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e378">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>. Discusses liquor prices and partaking of a drink, wages earned in 1967, and other financial matters.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e392">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses packages sent to and from the States.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e406">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 January 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A 5-page letter which begins "The VC [i.e., Viet Cong] sure know how to mess up a payday!" Reports waking up to the sound of M16s and AK47s and that the VC penetrated deep. They have had 1 KIA and 25 wounded so
far and a battalion of airborne soldiers has been flown in as a precaution. "Thank God everyone doesn't have a weapon, it would have been a slaughter...I've never seen such idiots...Standing outside...trying to
see who was shooting." Writes that this was going to be the Diem Bien Phu of the 2nd Indochina War but thinks that things will come out different this time. He has been inconvenienced by lack of sleep and a cold
C-ration lunch with a cute WAF lieutenant.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e420">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A 10-page letter describing in detail combat at Ton San Nhut. The letter is entitled "Payday Battle Report #2." What was thought to be a diversionary attack is now know to be some full-fledged battles. ARVN
(Army of the Republic of Vietnam) and Korean troops are slugging it out with the VC who continue to penetrate into the air base and are using rocket propelled grenades (RPGs) in their attacks. "This is a big push
to win and we are clobbering the hell out of them." Air support has been instrumental in stopping the Viet Cong and McDowell will not "complain about the helicopters anymore. Without them I might be walking to
Hanoi by now." One of his troops unloaded ARVN bodies into big refrigerators (the morgue was full) and came back looking green.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e434">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A 5-page letter continuing his account of the Tet Offensive battles. "War is over as far as TSN [Ton San Nhut] is concerned." Aircraft continue to attack retreating Viet Cong, most putting on civilian clothing
and leaving the way they came. He describes casualties on both sides and the continued fighting in various locations outside the air base.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e448">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Not much to add to the letters I've already written." Describes pullout of U.S. Army troops and various aircraft used in battle during the past couple of days including the new "Huey Cobra" helicopter gunship.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e462">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"The VC continue to plague us (Walter Cronkite's quaint way of putting it)" and "the 'war' in Saigon is not over." Discusses continued nearby combat, casualties, curfews and movement restrictions, and shortages
in food and base exchange merchandise.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e477">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Attacks and rumors of attacks continue." Describes operations to isolate the Viet Cong and long lines on the base for meals, etc. Vietnamese maids have returned but are under a curfew and have limited working
hours.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e491">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>TLS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Mentions receipt of a package, leave plans, and plans to purchase clothes and a slide projector ("I am sure gathering the plunder over here").
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e505">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p> Describes an early morning mortar and rocket attack and many explosions from incoming and friendly fire.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e519">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Describes sweating out another rocket attack and provides a description of the weapon being employed against them (its operation, range, explosive charge, etc.). Notes that the chapel was hit in an attack. They
have not had rain since November, and he facetiously writes "wait til the 'Annual Monsoon Offensive'" when "there won't be an able bodied male Vietnamese between 13-40 on either side by the time the monsoon gets
here."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e533">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 February 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Describes another rocket attack by "Charlie" and its effects on buildings and personnel at the air base. They continue to sandbag their barracks for protection "Rumor has it that the VC/NVA want this base as
the victory he needs so bad."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e547">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 March 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Recounts his efforts to pick up his new camera at Cholon but the base exchange there was closed. More rocket shelling is described; it is "kinda routine now."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e561">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 March 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>TLS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Threat reports indicate a major mortar attack is pending. Likens the attacks to "being scared by a really close lightning strike" and then "the adrenaline really starts pumping." Fears that they are being
lulled into ignoring threat reports and then a real attack will hit them. A recent explosion from a friendly weapon sent everyone under beds after which there was the "sound of bunks being lifted off of middle
aged bellies" as they emerged from hiding.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 March 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Its so damn peaceful here again, its boring!" Writes that he finally got his new camera and that he needs quality film for it mailed from home.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e589">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 March 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"All's quiet on the TSN front." Open food left around since the emergency has attracted rats and bugs which are being trapped. Has been issued field gear (helmet and flak vest).
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e603">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 March 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>. Discusses photography and mentions that with the passing of the "emergency" things have gone to pot again.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e617">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 April 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Has received letters and film from home. Mentions some artillery or rocket fire including possible friendly fire from American howitzers or "Charlie" using captured ARVN guns. Heard Lyndon Johnson announce the
bombing pause ("couldn't hear anything else he said for the sound of NVA [North Vietnamese Army] trucks starting up &amp; heading south!") and that he would not run again for president ("I don't believe that
liar").
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e632">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 April 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses film developing and beginning of the monsoon.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e646">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 May 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"The VC are getting brave again." Mentions a few mixed mortar and rocket rounds exploding off the base.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e660">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 May 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses taking pictures, sending savings bonds to his father's children by his second marriage, and the appeal to him of a new BMW automobile, the 2002 model. Discusses his girlfriend Janice's situation back
in the States.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e674">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 June 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>TLS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Describes his next Air Force assignment at England Air Force Base, Lousiana, with the 1st Air Commando Wing. He is unhappier about this than he was about coming to Vietnam.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e688">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 June 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses slides accompanying the letter and an incident involving two Australian girls needing a ride and the enthusiastic response of the troops to their needs. Compares Air Force and U.S. Navy photo
interpreter procedures and notes that the Navy's response time in attacking identified targets is often much quicker than the Air Force's.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e702">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 July 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>In a letter written from Hong Kong, discusses leave in that city (rainy weather, going on tours, dating, food, and spending money).
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e716">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 July 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>More discussion of leave in Hong Kong, taking pictures, spending money, and shopping.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e730">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to his parents
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>More discussion of leave in Hong Kong, taking pictures, spending money, and shopping.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e744">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 July 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses his departure date from Vietnam and asks for directions to his parents' home.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e758">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Mom"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 August 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses sending items to his parents and financial matters.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e772">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 August 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Discusses worsening working conditions, his finances, and how "Charlie is getting a little bold again &amp; the B52s are hitting 3-5 times a night close to town ... everything shakes."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e787">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letter to "Dear Folks"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968 August 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>TLS. 
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Gives his departure date (September 2).
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
