<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01442">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01442::Lewis Family Papers, 1835-1866)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01442.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01442::Lewis Family Papers,
             1835-1866)//EN" "viu01442.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Lewis Family Papers 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835-1866</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Lewis Family Papers, 1835-1866 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11231</num></subtitle><author>Sharon Defibaugh</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">29 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 12, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01442::Lewis Family
            Papers, 1835-1866)//EN" "viu01442.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Lewis Family Papers 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835-1866</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11231</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Sharon Defibaugh</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Lewis Family Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1835-1866</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11231</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         contains 36 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection consists chiefly of
         Civil War letters from George Samuel Lewis to his family in
         Lexington, Va.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Lewis Family Papers, 1835-1866, Accession #11231,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given by Marshall Carter,
            Alexandria, Virginia, to the University of Virginia
            Library, on April 1, 1996.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of letters and documents of the
         Lewis family of Amherst County, Virginia, 1835-1866, chiefly
         Civil War letters from George Samuel Lewis (1844-1864) to his
         family in Lexington, Virginia, but also including memoranda,
         journal entries and documents concerning the religious
         activities of the Reverend Reuben Lewis (1807-1886), a
         Presbyterian minister, and genealogical notes regarding the
         Lewis family.</p>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>1862 CORRESPONDENCE</head>
        <p>George Lewis, from Swift Gap, Rockingham County,
            Virginia, names the officers elected by the company and
            mentions cavalry skirmishes and the tent sleeping
            arrangement (1862 Apr 28); and writing from Howard's Grove
            Hospital, Second Division Ward, Richmond, after being
            wounded in both thighs, George Lewis asks his father
            [Reuben Lewis] to come and get him to recuperate at home;
            Sam Imboden is also at the hospital (1862 May). John David
            Lewis (1841-?), Staunton, to his mother, Anna E. Lewis
            (1817-1876), writes that he and George were glad to see
            their father at camp, appreciated the provisions that he
            brought, and were nearly out of paper (1862 May 16).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>1863 CORRESPONDENCE</head>
        <p>George Lewis, Camp Winder, [Caroline County, Virginia]
            to his mother, has just arrived at camp, Lt. McCorkle found
            his knapsack with some clothes still remaining in it, and
            asks her to address her letters to Stonewall's Brigade,
            Company H, 4th Regiment, Virginia Volunteers (1863 Jan 2);
            to his father and mother, several of them traded tobacco
            for coffee to Yankee soldiers across the Rapidan River,
            about 130 of their men are in the guardhouse, they have
            built a courthouse and a church in camp, includes details
            of camp life and observes that the men, who all take turns
            cooking, cook better than they used to (1863 Jan 18); to
            his brother, mentions exchanging newspapers with the
            Yankees, standing guard at the guardhouse, the
            fortifications along the river from Port Royal to
            Fredericksburg, and asks for the recipe to start yeast
            (1863 Feb 14); to his sister, very cold and snowing hard in
            camp, due to the bad weather they cannot get provisions or
            wood, have plenty of newspapers in camp, and has become
            quite proficient at bread-making (1863 Feb 22).</p>
        <p>George continues writing to his mother and father, they
            have built a fireplace in their tent for heat and sleep on
            a bed of pine tops, while on picket they sleep with
            blankets stretched over forks and poles, six men have been
            whipped and one shot for desertion, Jim Eads brought a
            black boy to cook for some of the men, rumors of two or
            three "Negro" regiments in Winchester (1863 Mar 7); to his
            sister Nannie, two more men have deserted to the Yankees,
            and lists the men in his mess, Jim and Bob Eads, Joe and
            William Tribbell and himself (1863 Mar 14); to his sister
            Nannie, prefers to stand guard in good weather than to
            drill, no hope for a furlough during the summer, and does
            not draw full rations presently, especially flour (1863 Apr
            2); to his brother, John D. Lewis at home in Lexington, ate
            some fish and greens in camp, rumors of fighting at
            [Charleston?], his regiment drew a ration of fish all
            caught in a net at Port Royal, needs paper and asks for a
            non-boiled ham to be sent to him with a box of necessities
            (1863 Apr 11); to his mother, thinks it is not a good idea
            for his father to try to farm at this time, apparently
            Elisha Paxton is trying to get Reuben Lewis out of his
            pastorate, will send his coat home until next winter for
            safekeeping, asks for soup beans, mentions a swamp near the
            camp, the presence of Yankee gunboats at Port Royal and
            Confederate artillery at Buckner's Bend, see Yankee
            observation balloons every day, and did not receive any
            soap or yeast as of yet (1863 Apr 18).</p>
        <p>Other letters include one to his brother Henry, camp
            near Rapidan River, built breastworks about twenty-five
            miles from Orange Courthouse, believes Jim Harrison has
            deserted to the Yankees, mentions the Confederate victory
            in Tennessee [Battle of Chickamauga ?] (ca [1863 Sep ?]);
            to his sister Nannie, Camp Stonewall Brigade, near Rapidan,
            describes an engagement with the Yankees at Jacob's Ford
            where they were surprised on a march by cavalry attempting
            to isolate their ambulance train, threw up breastworks, led
            by General Johnson in an advance and fought all day, four
            wounded in his company, Tom Anderson, John B. Wilson, Ben
            Hill, and Sam Cox, who was helped to the rear of the lines
            during the battle by George (1863 Dec 4); to his brother
            Henry, rations are very short now, eats half a flapjack a
            day, would love to have a mess of squirrels or a fat possum
            to eat, mentions seeing worms in his allotment of four
            crackers a day when he bites into them (1863 Dec 9).</p>
        <p>John D. Lewis, Headquarters Stonewall Jackson Brigade to
            his brother Henry, heard some skirmishing with the Yankees
            along the Rapidan River, saw his brother George on the
            ninth, and describes how they constructed a good wooden
            chimney in their tent (1863 Dec 4).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>1864 CORRESPONDENCE</head>
        <p>George Lewis to his father, Orange Courthouse, he and
            his brother John hope to send money home to the new farm
            while John is on furlough so they can purchase a yoke of
            oxen for plowing, they have caught a lot of rabbits and
            opossums to eat (1864 Jan 17); to his sister Nannie, his
            regiment might move to Gordonsville soon, describes how he
            built "his little house" at camp, and mentions the song 
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">When The Cruel War is
            Over</title>(1864 Jan 27); the Yankees crossed the river at
            Morton's Ford and eleven of his brigade were taken prisoner
            in the skirmish, reports another man was shot to instill
            discipline in the army (1864 Feb 11); to his sister, has
            been on picket for twelve days and cannot be relieved due
            to the constant raiding by the Yankees, and his clothes and
            person are very dirty (1864 Mar 6); to his father and to
            Henry, urges him to get rid of his old Confederate money
            before the new issue comes out, John is deemed fit for
            service and ordered back to his company, and asks about
            Henry's new dog (1864 Mar 10); to his sister, mentions the
            Emperor Napoleon and his hopes of getting a furlough soon
            (1864 Mar 21); to his brother, he has no chance of a
            furlough before winter, has been in the war for three
            years, hopes the war is over before his brother is old
            enough for service and warns him not to join the army if
            possible (1864 Apr 6); to his father at Holcomb's Rock,
            Bedford County, writing from Point Lookout, Maryland,
            George was taken prisoner by the Yankees on May 12 along
            with eight others of his company, all the boys taken at
            Gettysburg are also at Point Lookout (1864 May 24); to his
            father, writing from Elmira, New York, moved to a new
            prison, at Barracks No. 3, Ward 39, Prisoners' Camp,
            expresses concern for his brother John (1864 Aug 12).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>1866 CORRESPONDENCE</head>
        <p>Letters from C. Dickson and Charles S. Greenleaf,
            Medical Director's Office, concerning the death of George
            S. Lewis in Baltimore on October 18, 1864.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <scopecontent>
        <head>MISCELLANEOUS</head>
        <p>Other papers pertaining to the Reverend Reuben Lewis,
            ca. 1827-1861, include: the covers of a "pocketbook"
            (1827); list of marriages performed and accounts; the call
            from the Church of Fairmont (1856); an account with the
            board of school commissioners of Craig County, for tuition
            of indigent children (1861); an exegesis regarding [Infant
            Baptism ?] in Latin (1835); a memorandum book recording
            church services and other religious activities conducted by
            Reuben Lewis (1848-1854); and genealogical information
            about the Lewis family.</p>
      </scopecontent>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
