<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03542">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03542::Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03542.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03542::Woodrow Wilson Letters to
             Richard Heath Dabney)//EN" "viu03542.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881-1926</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Wilson, Woodrow, Letters to Richard Heath Dabney 
            <num type="collectionnumber">505, 542</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by niyi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7/8/2003</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-23" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 23, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03542::Woodrow Wilson
            Letters to Richard Heath Dabney)//EN" "viu03542.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881-1926</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
         <num type="Accession Number">505, 542, 9852-i, -j, -k</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney,  
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1881-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">505, 542, 9852-i, -j, -k</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of 112 items (including enclosures).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Woodrow Wilson Letters to Richard Heath Dabney, Accession #505, 542, 9852-i, -j, -k, Special Collections, University of
            Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>#505, #542: Gift of Richard Heath Dabney, 1939 June 3. #9852-i, -j, -k: Gift of Fleming Rutledge, 2007 July 5. </p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Wilson writes to Dabney, his former University of Virginia
         classmate (and later history professor at the University)
         regarding his life after ill health forced him to discontinue
         his studies.</p>
      <p>Of interest are twenty letters, 1881-1889, written after
         Wilson left the University of Virginia. In them he discusses
         his law studies, health, the University, the Jefferson
         Society, fellow students including future University of
         Virginia professor Charles Kent, impressions of Johns Hopkins
         and Bryn Mawr, his early writings, marriage, history, and
         politics. Later letters are shorter and more conventional in
         content, but contain occasional allusions to public affairs
         and the presidency.</p>
      <p>The collection also contains one letter from Wilson to the
         University of Virginia Board of Visitors recommending the
         hiring of Dabney as a professor.</p>
      <p>In addition to the letters from Wilson, the collection
         contains letters or telegrams from Ellen A. Wilson, Edith
         Bolling Wilson, Newton Baker, John Randolph Bolling, A. S.
         Burleson, Assistant Secretary of State William Phillips,
         Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, William Howard Taft, J. P.
         Tumulty and the Italian ambassador. Most of these letters
         concern issues that Dabney brought to Wilson's attention.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e180">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 February 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing
               Wilson's return to Wilmington after leaving the
               University of Virginia because of health reasons.
               Mentions he is still studying law. Wilson also inquires
               about various former classmates, including future
               University of Virginia professor Charles "Chucky" Kent,
               and about events since his departure from his
               fraternity. The letter is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson."
               Marked with modern red "UVA library" stamp next to
               signature.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e193">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 March 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing
               the receipt of letters from Dabney and another classmate
               from the University of Virginia. Wilson describes his
               attempts at "courting" local girls. Wilson mentions that
               he is still recovering from his "stomach" illness. He
               writes of a book he is reading ( 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Early History of Charles James
               Fox</title>by George Otto Trevelyan) and highly
               recommends to Dabney that he read it also. Wilson
               mentions he is still studying his law books and requests
               that Dabney write back with news and "gossip" from the
               University.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e209">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 April 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing
               receipt of Dabney's letter, and his apologies for not
               having answered it sooner. Much of the letter contains
               questions about various situations at the University of
               Virginia and his fraternity. Wilson also mentions that
               Wilmington has "no schools here of any worth at all,"
               and that he is now instructing his younger brother in
               Latin; his brother is being taught at home because of
               the lack of good schools. Wilson mentions that he is
               reading (in Latin) 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Life of Cicero</title>.
               Wilson also mentions the newspaper's account of the
               death of Beaconsfield and says that Beaconsfield's
               "scheming" has come to an end with his death. The letter
               is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e225">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 May 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Wilmington, North Carolina, describing
               receipt of other letters from former classmates at the
               University. Wilson comments on the results of
               competitions at the University at the 
               <persname normal="Washington Society">Wash[ington
               Society]</persname>. He expresses displeasure for the
               winner of the Oratorical Contest winner, calling him a
               "greasy junk-shop Jew." The letter also describes the
               lack of entertainment in Wilmington except for wedding
               receptions. Wilson contemplates how long he will wait
               before he "risks his fortunes" and ventures into
               marriage. He inquires about Dabney's studies. The letter
               is signed "T. Woodrow Wilson.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883 January 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 8 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Atlanta, Georgia, to Dabney in Munich,
               Germany. Wilson asks about Dabney's studies in Germany
               and the whereabouts of former University of Virginia
               students. Wilson tells Dabney that he has spoken before
               the Tariff Commission. He says he would like to start a
               group in Georgia, called the "Georgia House of Commons,"
               but for now will be organizing a "Free Trade" group
               there. Wilson says that young attorneys have a hard time
               in Georgia because older lawyers are "unscrupulous" in
               their practice making it difficult for younger attorneys
               to get started. The letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e254">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1883 May 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 12 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Atlanta, Georgia, to Dabney in Munich,
               Germany. Wilson acknowledges receipt of Dabney's letter
               and says that he envies Dabney studying in the "old
               world" while he is buried in the hum-drum life in "slow,
               ignorant and uninteresting Georgia." Wilson talks about
               practicing law in Georgia, and the lack of intellectual
               companionship he has found there. Wilson hopes to study
               at Johns Hopkins University. Wilson talks of the
               election of a new Georgia Governor due to the death of
               Governor, 
               <persname normal="Alexander Hamilton">Alex[ander
               Hamilton]</persname>Stephens. He says that Georgia is
               too thrifty to have a Lieutenant Governor, and that
               while the expense of the legislative session and special
               election would have cost more than a Lieutenant
               Governor, the people of Georgia are happier thinking
               that they have saved money. Wilson says that Tennessee
               offered to send Georgia a candidate to run for governor
               because Georgia did not have anyone worthy of running.
               Wilson says the new governor is unremarkable except that
               he is honest, which Wilson says is rare for politicians.
               Wilson says the new governor has a speech impediment,
               stuttering, that makes it hard for him to talk; he
               quotes someone as saying that they have traded a
               governor who could not walk for a governor who could not
               talk. Wilson describes the temporary capital in Atlanta
               as ugly. If he is not accepted at Johns Hopkins he will
               go to Baltimore anyway and spend time in that
               "beautiful" city's libraries. The letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e270">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1884 February 17</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 8 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dabney in
               Berlin, Germany. Wilson writes that he had received
               Dabney's letter two months previously even though it had
               been written in July, and had gone through many "notable
               wanderings" before it reached Wilson. Wilson explains to
               Dabney that he has moved since the letter was written.
               He says that he was denied the Fellowship at Johns
               Hopkins that he wanted, but was admitted as a graduate
               student. Even though Johns Hopkins is the best place for
               study at the time, he is disappointed with the school
               and his professors. He says that if his knowledge of
               German were better, he would move to be with and study
               with Dabney in Germany. Wilson also announces to Dabney
               that he has met, fallen in love with, and become engaged
               to Ellen Louise Axson, the daughter and granddaughter of
               a minister. He says she is very intelligent, well read,
               and "the most domestic of maidens." He notes that she
               has worked as a portrait painter. Wilson talks of his
               desire to become a professor, but fears it will be at a
               school in the West or South, because the job market for
               professors in the East is difficult. He has not heard
               from his former classmates from the University of
               Virginia and inquires if Dabney has heard from any of
               them. Wilson asks Dabney to notice that he has dropped
               the "T." from his signature. The letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson." Notes on envelope appear to be in
               Dabney's hand and read "Answered on May 6th 1884 about
               his engagement to be married."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e283">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885 February 14</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 12 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dabney in
               Berlin. Wilson apologizes for the lack of
               correspondence. Wilson explains that he has not only
               been made a fellow at Johns Hopkins, but has written a
               book entitled 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Congressional Government: A Study
               in American Politics</title>. He is more content with
               Johns Hopkins than he was in the beginning. He has
               accepted a job that involves setting up the history
               department at the newly-established Bryn Mawr School. He
               says that he could not refuse the job as it offered a
               good starting salary and was near the civilized part of
               the country and good libraries. He mentions his upcoming
               wedding in June, and offers to introduce Dabney to the
               new Mrs. Wilson when he returns from Germany. He
               inquires about University of Virginia friends and refers
               to Dabney as having an "Old West Range Heart." The
               closing is "your Loving Friend," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson." Envelope has a forwarding
               correction to Heidelberg in blue and a pencil notation
               that reads, "Answered Oct 19 1885."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e299">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1885 October 28</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 8 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in
               Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson apologizes for having not
               written sooner, but explains that Mrs. "W" has been ill.
               Wilson tells Dabney he is glad to have him back on this
               continent again, and he feels like he has him back on
               the East Range again [there is an autograph note by
               Dabney stating that Wilson meant "West Range"]. Wilson
               thanks Dabney for his comments on Wilson's book 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Congressional
               Government</title>and is assured that Dabney's kind
               comments are genuine. A large portion of the letter
               concerns Wilson's happiness since marriage; he describes
               it as "rhapsody." Wilson congratulates Dabney on having
               received his Ph.D. in Germany and assures him of its
               value, and says that he will look out for a job for
               Dabney. He says that it may be difficult as schools are
               teaching history in "shamefully small numbers." He ends
               by saying that the girls at Bryn Mawr are interested and
               intelligent. The letter is signed "Your Very Sincere
               Friend Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date 18 Dec
               1887 pencilled on and is postmarked Dec. 10 Bryn
               Mawr.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e307">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1886 June 6</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney. Wilson xplains that his failure to write resulted from intense studying for his Ph.D. examinations at Johns Hopkins which he passed. Expresses his admiration for "Don Miff" which is pervaded with a "true Southern spirit which warmed my heart." He finds the Negro dialect perfect. He wrote a notice of it for the Wilmington papers but doesn’t know if it has been printed. He announced the he is now weighted down with the dignities of fatherhood, although he has not yet seen his little daughter, as his wife was visiting an aunt in Gainesville, Ga., when the baby arrived. He intends to summer in Tennessee where his father is living. Wants to know the fate of Dabney’s prospects at Indiana University.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e315">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1886 November 7</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 16 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney.
               Wilson is concerned with Dabney's situation at the
               school in which he is teaching. He has not written for
               many reasons, one of which is that his baby has been
               sick. Wilson has been to Cornell to give a lecture and
               while there visited a fraternity house and spoke to a
               "brother" who confirmed the situation in Bloomington was
               as Dabney had written. There is discussion of his
               teaching methods - "whether that truth be on the side of
               Webster or of Calhoun." Wilson says that he has an even
               greater concern since it was he who "advanced his
               candidacy" for the job at Indiana University. He asks
               Dabney to write him more about it. Wilson then writes of
               a Wilmington editor who did not respond to a letter
               written to him to go along with a "notice" he had
               written for the paper on "Don Miff." Wilson says that he
               does not know if the editor even published the piece,
               but hopes the editor would "play gentleman for once."
               The remainder of the letter is chiefly about Dabney's
               opinion of Wilson's moving to Berlin for one to two
               years. The purpose would be to both learn German and to
               have some "Leisure time." He inquires how much could he
               expect to pay for two people and a baby and possible a
               nurse to live in comfort without a "peppercorn's" regard
               to style. He asks for Dabney's "whole" opinion. Wilson
               would like to go now while he is young and his learning
               abilities are at their best. He asks for Dabney's candid
               answer. The letter has a P.S. that sends Mrs. Wilson's
               warm regards and asks for [Charles?] Kent's address. The
               letter is signed "your sincere friend, Woodrow Wilson."
               The envelope has the date 1886 pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e329">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887 January 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 8 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney at
               Indiana University. Wilson describes a teaching position
               that is open at and suggests that Dabney come teach at
               Bryn Mawr. He states that the cost of lodging will be $7
               per week. This is for a third floor room, which Wilson
               feels is just as nice as the more expensive rooms on the
               first or second floor. Wilson says that if he and Mrs.
               Wilson are still keeping house the next year, they would
               invite him to take a room with them. The salary of $600
               a year may be $400 less than Dabney makes in Indiana,
               but that it is higher than some of the new professors
               will be getting and Wilson says that there will be a
               good potential for salary advancement. He says the
               Quakers who operate the school are cautious and never
               promise anything, but do as they have means. Wilson says
               that the region around Philadelphia is good for those
               who have an interest in history. Wilson writes that he
               is trying to be careful in suggesting Dabney move
               because Wilson is unsure if it would be for selfish or
               unselfish reasons that he would make the suggestion. He
               describes the Bryn Mawr classes as intelligent and the
               administration as honest and straightforward. The letter
               concludes with warm regards from Mrs. Wilson and is
               signed "Your Affectionate Friend, Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e342">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887 February 17</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson to Dabney. Wilson has received Dabney's
               letter announcing his engagement. Wilson tells Dabney of
               his own happiness in his marriage. He says that the good
               news of his engagement is second only to that of his
               news that Dabney might be getting a teaching position at
               the University of Virginia. Wilson writes that he "loves
               that old place" and the faculty is the most influential
               in the South. Wilson is resigned to the fact the Dabney
               will not come to Bryn Mawr to teach as his assistant,
               but does increase his offer of salary to $850 the first
               year and $1000 the next. He says that the choice of an
               assistant is up to him, and while he can't really wait
               until Dabney finds out if he will be teaching at the
               University of Virginia, he says it very well might be
               June when he makes his decision. The letter is signed
               "With love as ever Your Sincere Friend, Woodrow Wilson."
               The envelope has the date 17 Feb. 1887 pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e355">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1887 December 18</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 8 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson to Dabney at the University of Indiana.
               Wilson has been thinking of Dabney often, but was in a
               small Georgia town for the summer and so out of touch.
               He was also preparing to lecture at Johns Hopkins as
               well as preparing for his work at Bryn Mawr. For these
               reasons, he has failed to write to Dabney. Wilson
               acknowledges receipt of Dabney's "Memorials of a
               Southern Planter" about his grandfather. Mrs. Wilson has
               also read it and they enjoy the "retelling of its
               contents." Wilson praises Dabney's grandfather and says
               that he fears this country will never see another such
               man again. Wilson says all of the North should read this
               book. Wilson says if there were more people like
               Dabney's grandfather there would be no "labour" problems
               because his "conscience was the only kind of arbitrator
               between master and workman that will ever bring peace
               and cooperative friendship." The remainder of the letter
               is information trying to persuade Dabney to come teach
               at Bryn Mawr. Wilson has increased the salary offer to
               $1200 or possibly $1500 since the area is expensive to
               live in. Wilson also writes that the area is ideal for
               those studying history because of the libraries and
               such. He ends by inviting Dabney to visit during the
               holidays. The letter is signed "Your all-the-time chum,
               Woodrow Wilson." The envelope does not appear to belong
               to this letter. It is addressed to Dabney at a New York
               address and is postmarked 1885. It also has pencilled
               notes which read "answered Jan'y 11th 1888" at the top
               and in pencil on the bottom portion is written
               "Something about his marriage." Also in pencil but in
               what appears to be a different handwriting is the words
               "this seems to be in the wrong envelope" and a date of
               28 Oct. 1885 that has been scratched over in pencil.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e368">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1888 January 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 6 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in
               Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson has not written because
               "things have been at a stand still" regarding the
               teaching position at Bryn Mawr. Wilson addresses
               Dabney's concern about whether or not he would be able
               to break his contract at Bryn Mawr if a better offer
               came along. Wilson says a previous professor was going
               to leave, and the school gave him a raise to stay and
               the promise of no contract. Wilson tells Dabney that the
               cheapest first class housing he can find would be $16 to
               $18 dollars per week. Bryn Mawr is trying to build
               cottages to house professors and Dabney would qualify
               for them. Wilson also suggests that Dabney take a house
               in the city and pay $5 per week for car fare. Wilson
               will continue with inquiries into the matter. He
               congratulates Dabney on the book he will publish. There
               is a note added on the first page by Wilson stating that
               he was sorry Dabney did not visit them over the
               holidays. The envelope has the date "20 Jan, 1888"
               pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e381">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1888 March 26</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania to Dabney in
               Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson is disappointed with the
               negotiations to hire a professor for his assistant at
               Bryn Mawr. The salary offer has actually now decreased.
               The offer is $1100 and would require a two-year
               commitment. Wilson states that is less than what he
               received when first at Bryn Mawr and that he can not
               survive now on his $2000 per year salary, except that he
               gets $500 a year for work he does for Johns Hopkins.
               Wilson is considering leaving Bryn Mawr to seek better
               pay and to get a chair teaching public law "or the like"
               somewhere else. Wilson mentions now having two babies.
               He thanks Dabney for the copy of his book and promises
               to read it over Easter vacation. The letter is signed
               "Affectionately Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has
               the date 1888 pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e394">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson To Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1888 May 16</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>From Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in
               Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson apologizes for not writing
               sooner, but explains that he has been busy with work and
               the death of his mother. Wilson writes that his mother's
               death was sudden and the only news he had of her illness
               was the notice that she was dead. He says he went to
               Tennessee to be with his father for as long as his job
               would allow. Wilson says his father will be alone since
               Wilson's sisters are all married and his brother is in
               college. Wilson says her death makes him feel like his
               youth has also died. He praises Dabney for a piece that
               he has written to the "University Bulletin." Wilson begs
               Dabney to please make time to visit him over the summer.
               The letter is signed "Yrs. Affectionately, Woodrow
               Wilson." The envelope has " 16 May 1888 about his
               mother's death" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e407">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1888 May 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, to Dabney in
               Bloomington, Indiana. Wilson was glad to receive
               Dabney's letter of the 22nd. He congratulates Dabney on
               the announcement of his engagement and his upcoming
               marriage on June 19. The remainder of the letter is
               filled with Wilson's praise for marriage. Wilson
               compares his life before and after marriage, and
               strongly suggests marriage as a good thing for his
               friend Dabney. The letter ends by Wilson writing that he
               would like to have Dabney and Miss Butler spend their
               wedding trip in Bryn Mawr. The letter is signed "Mrs.
               and Mr. Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "about
               marriage" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e420">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1889 October 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Middletown, Connecticut, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson sends his sympathy to
               Dabney regarding the loss of his baby. Wilson writes
               that being back at the University of Virginia must give
               Dabney some comfort, as it is so familiar. Wilson asks
               that Dabney write him with details of his work. Wilson
               also asks about the textbook that he sent to Dabney.
               Wilson closes with messages of friendship and sympathy
               from him and Mrs. Wilson. It is signed "Your
               Affectionate friend, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has
               the date "31 Oct 1889" and "About the death of my wife
               &amp; child" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e433">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891 July 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson begins by apologizing
               for having sent a typed letter instead of handwritten
               but explains his writing pen is elsewhere. Wilson thanks
               Dabney for the review of his book. Wilson writes a great
               deal about his friendship with Dabney and what it has
               meant to him. Wilson closes by urging Dabney to come to
               Princeton for a visit. The letter closes by saying "As
               ever of old," and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e446">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to the Rector and Board of
               Visitors of the University of Virginia 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1897 December 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letter of recommendation from Wilson to the Rector
               and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia,
               requesting that Dabney be given the position of Chair of
               Historical and Political Science. This is a seat that
               Wilson notes was vacated by the death of Professor
               [George F.] Holmes. Wilson describes the service that
               "sons" of the University have given. The letter is
               signed "Very Truly Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope
               has no stamp or postmark.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e459">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899 November 12</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson congratulates Dabney
               on his engagement to a Miss. [Lily Heth] Davis. Wilson
               regrets that he will not be able to attend the wedding
               because of work commitments, but assures Dabney he will
               be thinking of him. Wilson asks that Dabney "Commend"
               him to Miss. Davis. The letter is signed "Affectionately
               Yours, Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "12
               Nov 1899" and "Congratulating me on my approaching
               marriage" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e473">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902 October 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter and thanks him for his kind words regarding
               Dabney's visit to Princeton. Wilson comments on the
               selection of a new president for the University of
               Virginia and says that because of his affection for the
               University, he would only suggest the very best man for
               the job. Wilson says that he does not know of any such
               man at this time, but will write Dabney should someone
               come to mind for the position. The letter ends with
               regards from Wilson and his wife to Dabney and Mrs.
               Dabney. The closing is typed "Faithfully yours," and
               signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date "13
               Oct 1902" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e486">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1902 November 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that the
               presidency of the University of Virginia has been
               offered to him three times. He never gave any indication
               that he would accept the position. Wilson says that
               Dabney is at perfect liberty to state the "whole case"
               to anyone. Wilson says that he was unaware of any
               opposition to him as president, just opposition to
               having any president at all, but that if they must have
               a president, the "opposition" would agree to Wilson.
               Wilson writes that he still does not know of anyone that
               he could strongly recommend for the position. The letter
               closes with regret that Dabney has been distressed by a
               "cock and bull" story. The typed closing reads
               "Cordially and Faithfully yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e499">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1910 April 19</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Princeton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes of his receipt
               of a recommendation for a professor to be hired at
               Princeton and promises to forward the letter to the
               appropriate person. Wilson then says that he is very
               much "disinclined" to go into politics, but the
               situation there makes it difficult not to do so. Wilson
               writes that he would like to see Dabney, and that being
               with Dabney makes Wilson feel like a boy again. The
               typed closing reads "affectionately yours" and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e512">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 November 16</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope (negative
               photostat)</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Staunton, Virginia, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he and
               Dabney did not have a chance to talk about the
               initiative, referendum and recall when they were
               together so Wilson says it would be worthwhile for him
               to "summarize" it somewhat more formally. The remainder
               of the letter is Wilson's summarization. The closing
               reads "Faithfully Yours, Woodrow Wilson. On the
               photostat of the envelope, there is a note in Dabney's
               hand that reads "16 Nov., 1911 I had this letter
               published with the extended comments of my own, in the 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">[Richmond] Times
               Dispatch</title>, and it was reprinted in many other
               paper. Reprints of it were also distributed from the
               Woodrow Wilson Headquarters in New York!"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e528">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 November 4</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson apologizes for not having told Dabney
               of his travel plans. Wilson has received Dabney's
               request to publish his letter and gives his approval.
               Wilson says that if Dabney thinks the letter needs to be
               put in a better form, to let him know and Wilson will
               put it in "shape." The typed closing reads "Faithfully
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e541">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 December 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, in Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson responds to Dabney's
               letter of the sixth. The letter includes a sentence
               Dabney suggests adding to Wilson's "Staunton" letter
               before it is published. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e554">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 December 18</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his
               letter sent on December 14. Wilson mentions a
               controversy between him and "Proctor of Cincinnati"
               regarding the Graduate College in Princeton. The typed
               closing reads "Always affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e567">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 December 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               in Trenton, New Jersey to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his help in the
               publication of his letter. Wilson also mentions the
               editorial by Mr. [John Stewart] Bryan in the 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">[Richmond] Times
               Dispatch</title>. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately and gratefully yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e583">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911 December 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letter of
               December 21 and thanks Dabney for what he is doing and
               the "value of what you are telling me from time to
               time." Wilson mentions making a series of speeches in
               Virginia, and suggests that Dabney is in a better
               position to judge if the Virginia legislature should
               invite him to do so. Wilson says that the letter Dabney
               amended has been well received by Wilson's New York
               headquarters. The typed closing reads "Faithfully
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e596">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 January 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letters and their
               enclosures. Wilson mentions that he has received an
               answer to a letter from Archie Patterson. Wilson says
               that he is willing to come to Richmond to speak after
               February. The typed closing reads "Always faithfully
               yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e609">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 January 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of the
               sixth. He mentions friends of [William Jennings] Bryan
               and how [Robert M.] LaFollette is regarded. Wilson says
               that it is unjust to "indulge in flings at either of
               those men." Wilson describes this as dropping a hint to
               Dabney. Wilson describes the process of the campaign as
               interesting and promising. The typed closing read
               "Faithfully and affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e623">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 January 16</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson mentions a suggestion he gave to Dabney
               and the results thereof. Wilson also thanks Dabney for
               polling Virginia's congressmen. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e636">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 January 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson apologizes to Dabney for not writing
               but explains that he knows Dabney will understand why.
               Wilson acknowledges Dabney's letters. Wilson says that
               his days are "one continual absorbing rush." Wilson
               mentions the response in Virginia to the
               "Harvey-Watterson affair." Wilson ends the letter by
               saying he is surprised to hear that he has been invited
               to speak in Richmond, as Wilson says no such invitations
               have reached him. The typed closing reads "Faithfully
               and affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e649">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ellen Axson Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 February 9</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 12 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ellen Wilson, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson sends more
               details of the "Carnegie pension affair." Most of the
               letter describes who is eligible for the pension, and
               the requirements thereof. She writes concerning Woodrow
               Wilson's financial situations, his lack of income since
               leaving Princeton, and the costs he has incurred doing
               "public service." She says that she supposes he could
               take a "paying" job, but that would force him to give up
               his leadership in the reform movement. Mrs. Wilson
               writes that he only receives $1000 a year from his
               books, and that goes to pay for "life insurances." Mrs.
               Wilson writes that when Wilson applied for the Carnegie
               pension he had not been elected governor, and had no
               means of support. She trusts Dabney's discretion in the
               matter: "I don't know what he would do to me if he knew
               I was writing all this." The closing is "Yours very
               cordially," and the letter is signed "Ellen A. Wilson."
               The envelope has "From Mrs. Woodrow Wilson" and "Feb. 9
               1912" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e662">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 February 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson extends his sympathy
               to Dabney over the loss of his daughter [Lucy Davis
               Dabney, who died of juvenile diabetes at age nine]. The
               typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter
               is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has the date
               "1902 16 March" and "About Lucy" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e675">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ellen Axson Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 March 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Ellen Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson requests a copy
               of her letter of 1912 February 9 regarding the pension
               issue. The closing reads "Yours very cordially, Ellen A.
               Wilson." The envelope has "From Mrs. Woodrow Wilson."
               and "March 13, 1912" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e688">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 March 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson discusses the issues
               of the "pension question" and agrees that is too late
               now to take up the matter. Wilson also mentions the
               difficult time Dabney is going through and Wilson is
               touched that Dabney should think of him during this time
               of "infinite pain and depression." The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately Yours" and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e701">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 May 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson assures Dabney that he has not suffered
               a reported breakdown, only a severe cold. Wilson also
               expresses concerns that Dabney has had "nerve" trouble
               and has been unable to sleep. He says that he thinks
               Dabney's intention to go to the "other side of the
               water" to recuperate is a good idea. Wilson reports that
               things politically are in good shape. Wilson is
               disappointed in the small numbers of people who have
               voted in the primaries and he thinks the "purpose" to
               nominate him is as strong as ever. The letter ends with
               Wilson mentioning that he saw Dick Byrd and Mr. Byrd was
               hopeful that the "Virginia situation" would be
               controlled in Wilson's favor. The typed closing reads,
               "With genuine affection, Faithfully yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e714">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 August 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Sea Girt, New Jersey, to Dabney in Paris,
               France. Wilson apologizes that he did not notice the
               change of address that Dabney gave in his last letter.
               Wilson fears that his last letter is "wandering" around
               Europe seeking Dabney. Wilson mentions that Dabney has
               had troubles and political disappointments in Virginia.
               Wilson also mentions that results in Baltimore should
               cheer Dabney. Wilson concludes that he has "piles" of
               letters and cannot write more then a few lines. The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately Yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e720">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Mrs. Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 August 12</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Sea Girt, N.J. to Mrs. Dabney. Thanks her for her note of congratulations and begs her to pardon his delayed reply.  Has gotten several notes from Heath but they did not include his European address so he couldn’t reply. Asks her to convey his love.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e727">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 August 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelopes</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Paris
               (forwarded to Charlottesville, Virginia). Wilson
               explains that he has not written because he was not sure
               what address in Europe to use, but that he wrote Mrs.
               Dabney and received a correct address from her. Wilson
               is touched by Dabney's support for his nomination and
               that he often thinks of Dabney, even if he is unable to
               write. Wilson sends wishes that Dabney is getting
               refreshed and renewed. The typed closing reads "Always
               faithfully and affectionately yours'" and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e740">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 September 6</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Sea Girt, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson congratulates Dabney
               on the birth of his daughter, Alice Saunders Dabney. The
               typed closing reads "Always affectionately yours," and
               the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has
               "About Alice's birth" pencilled on.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e753">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 October 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson is home for a few days
               until "Mr. Roosevelt is fighting for himself again."
               Wilson is delighted Dabney's daughter and wife are
               getting along so well. The typed closing reads
               "affectionately yours," and the letter is signed Woodrow
               Wilson.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e767">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 November 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Bermuda to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson tells Dabney that he would very much
               like to visit the University of Virginia when he comes
               to Staunton, but with as little ceremony as possible.
               Wilson says that he loves the University of Virginia for
               its "simplicities" and not for the trouble he has gotten
               into. Wilson says that he is settled in Bermuda for a
               little period and hopes to come back with new zest and
               refreshment. The typed closing on letter one reads
               "Faithfully yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson." A second letter of the same date is about
               Dabney's letter regarding Randolph Harrison. Wilson ends
               by wishing Dabney were in Bermuda. The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "Bermuda, Nov. 20
               1912" noted on it.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e780">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 December 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Bermuda, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson says he understands perfectly Dabney's
               actions regarding office appointment recommendations.
               Wilson will only be able to spend a few hours in
               Charlottesville. He is struggling with masses of
               correspondence, even "down here." The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has "Bermuda Dec. 3 1912"
               written on it.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e793">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 December 12</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. The letter is regarding two
               names ([Paul B.?] Barringer and [Henry St. George?]
               Tucker) that Dabney recommended for consideration by
               Wilson. The typed closing reads, "Faithfully yours," and
               the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e806">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mr. Tumulty, Secretary to the Governor of New
               Jersey, to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 December 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letter from Wilson's secretary to Dabney regarding
               the nomination letters for Mr. Bryan and Mr. Townsend
               with reference to Mr. William Scott.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e819">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912 December 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson writes that he is too busy to spend more than
               the exact amount of promised time in Staunton. Wilson
               will arrive at 8 o'clock in the evening. He asks Dabney
               to be "on hand" in Staunton. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e832">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mr. and Mrs. Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath
               Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Undated [1912
               December?]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>Western Union Telegram with
               envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Wilsons regret that they cannot stop in
               Charlottesville and send Christmas greetings.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e845">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 January 7</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for
               sending Tucker's letter. Wilson mentions a business
               failure connected with him at the Jamestown Exposition.
               Wilson adds that it was a joy to see Dabney. Wilson
               mentions Dabney's nose "trouble" and says that he
               thought Dabney did not look well. Wilson says the trip
               to Staunton did him no harm, but he came back feeling
               better that when he started. Wilson says that there had
               been some suggestion, perhaps in the 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">[Richmond]
               Times-Dispatch</title>, that it was not in "good taste"
               to give a talk to the machine men in Virginia. Wilson
               hopes this is not the general impression. Wilson writes
               that his friends will have to get used to his way of
               always having a dart for somebody. Wilson writes that
               his passage was on the spur of the moment. The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e861">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 January 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson replies to Dabney's letter of the 26th.
               Wilson writes that the papers enclosed with Dabney's
               letter will receive his careful attention. The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e874">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 February 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the information he
               sent from Seattle. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e887">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 February 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 2 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on State of New Jersey Executive stationery),
               Trenton, New Jersey, to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the information he
               sent regarding Bernard Mann. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e900">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 March 12</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his
               letter of the ninth and says that he has only time
               enough to send Dabney "only this line with my love." The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e914">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 March 14</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson refers to
               recommendations Dabney has made regarding a Postmaster
               appointment. Wilson also mentions a recommendation
               Dabney has made for the position of Naval Officer for
               the Port of New Orleans. The typed closing reads
               "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e927">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 March 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               recommendation letter of March 20. The typed closing
               reads "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson." There is an autograph note at
               the bottom that reads "Dear Heath, This is a 'form
               letter' It should have ended Yours affectionately,
               W.W."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e940">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 March 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson says a statement
               regarding lawyers was exaggerated and goes on to discuss
               lawyers and their connections to corporations. Wilson
               ends by saying that all of Dabney's letters are welcome.
               The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours", and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e953">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 April 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson responds to Dabney's
               recommendation of Mr. Williams. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson." There is an autograph note that reads
               "I'm afraid I'm committed to another man W.W." There is
               a red "UVa Library" stamp beneath the signature.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e966">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 May 29</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson comments on an article
               written about him by Dabney in 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Corks and Curls</title>and
               expresses his gratitude for it. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e982">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 June 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for
               sending information on Mr. Watts and Mr. Davis. The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e995">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 June 17</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for
               sending information on Dr. Eigenmann and Mr. de Saulles.
               The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1008">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 June 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Maine. Wilson acknowledges receipt of information from
               Dabney regarding Mr. Lewis Aylett. Wilson hopes Mr. and
               Mrs. Dabney will have an enjoyable vacation. Wilson
               mentions that he, the First Lady, and their daughter
               will be leaving for their vacation home in Cornish and
               that he is looking forward to the vacation. The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson." The letter has one autograph
               correction.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1021">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 July 14</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Maine. Wilson thanks Dabney for his letter of July 10
               regarding Lewis Aylett. The President writes that he has
               just returned from Cornish and is refreshed and enjoyed
               being on the links. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1034">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 July 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Maine. Wilson is disappointed that he cannot appoint
               Louis Aylett as Richmond Postmaster but there are many
               things "one cannot do." The President writes that he is
               envious of Dabney being on vacation. The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1047">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 September 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of September 4, and its enclosure from Mr. Burke.
               Wilson writes that it is always a comfort to hear from
               Dabney and hopes that what he is doing is meeting with
               Dabney's approval. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1061">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 November 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter regarding Col. Lincoln Karmany. Wilson says he is
               following strict professional standards in all
               promotions. He thinks the Mexican situation is slowly
               working itself out. Wilson says the Mexican situation
               and the currency situation are playing havoc with his
               golf game but that someday when his nerves are in shape
               he will challenge Dabney to golf. The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson." The envelope has written on it "About
               golf" in pencil.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1074">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 November 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter about Mr. Burke regarding the postmaster position
               in Bedford City. The typed closing reads "Affectionately
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1087">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 December 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>Telegram</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson invites Dabney to dinner on Thursday at 7
               p.m.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1100">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 January 19</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope and
               enclosure</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of the 13th and responds to an inquiry about
               placing a regional reserve bank in Richmond. Wilson
               returns a telegram from Charles Pinckney on the same
               subject that Dabney had forwarded with his letter. The
               telegram is 3 pages and dated January 13, 1914, 3.24
               p.m. Wilson also mentions receiving an article from
               Dabney, but does not elaborate on its contents. The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1113">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 February 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>Western Union Telegram and envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson invites Dabney to lunch on "Saturday at one
               o'clock."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1126">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 March 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges with
               thanks Dabney's letter of the 18th regarding Hampson
               Gary for a post in Persia. Wilson also sends a thank-you
               from his daughter, Eleanor, regarding Dabney's kind
               words on Eleanor's engagement. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1139">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 April 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope and 1 unidentified tree
               leaf</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of the 23rd and mentions he will call Dabney's
               information about "Taylor" to the attention of the
               Secretary of the Navy.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1152">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1914 August 20</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of August 7. The typed closing reads "Faithfully
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1165">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915 January 4</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               New Year's letter and reciprocates Dabney's good wishes.
               Wilson mentions that he is interested in what Dabney has
               to say about Mr. Raleigh Minor's work. Wilson says that
               he must remain aloof about it for fear of seeming to
               "press the matter." Wilson tells Dabney that he will
               write Mr. Minor. The typed closing reads "Affectionately
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1178">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915 February 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of February 12. Wilson states that he is already
               aware of the article to which Dabney had referred in his
               letter and is appreciative of Dabney's kindness. The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately your," and is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1191">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 14, 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for the
               "fine letter" he wrote May 11. Wilson says he wishes he
               had more time to send an adequate answer. The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1205">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1915 October 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of October 8 and of the happiness that has now
               come to him [his engagement to Edith Bolling Galt].
               Wilson states that he hopes that it will soon be
               possible for Mrs. Galt to know Dabney as the
               "delightful" friend he is. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1218">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 January 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of January 10 concerning Mr. [John] Powell.
               Wilson says they were considering having him at the
               White House, but the musical "programme" already had
               been made. He and Mrs. Wilson send good wishes for the
               New Year. The typed closing reads "Affectionately
               yours," and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1231">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 April 26</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of April 23. Wilson writes that he is full of
               gratitude and affection that Dabney should feel as he
               does about what Wilson is doing. Wilson says that these
               are times that try men's souls and that he hopes fire
               will purify the whole nation. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1244">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 May 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson regrets that he will
               not get to see Dabney, but that he is going "down the
               river" to get away for needed rest. Wilson writes that
               he is not "very keen" for any public dinner. Wilson
               writes a reference to a German note, but gives no
               indication what it was about. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1257">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 August 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope, (with enclosures: TLS
               4 p. from the Postmaster General)</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) from the U.S.S.
               Mayflower to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson
               has sent Dabney's letter regarding the Brook Hill post
               office to the Postmaster General and encloses the
               Postmaster General's response. The Postmaster General
               writes that at the "instance" of Virginia Senators, the
               Governor of Virginia and a Virginia Representative, any
               change to the mail service has been postponed. He will
               look in to the taking the best action for the Brook Hill
               post office.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1270">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 November 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson expresses pleasure in
               the message Dabney sent. The typed closing reads
               "Cordially and sincerely yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1283">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1916 November 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of the 23rd and says that it "warmed the cockles
               of my heart." Wilson states he is "submerged" in
               messages from "many quarters." The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1296">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 January 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges receipt
               of a letter regarding a Mr. Jenkins. Wilson says it will
               not be possible to excuse an individual guardsman and
               that "they" will probably not be much longer detained at
               the border. Wilson will send Dabney's and Jenkins'
               letter on to the Secretary of War. The typed closing
               reads "Cordially and faithfully yours," and the letter
               is signed "Woodrow Wilson." "Confidential" is typed at
               the top.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1309">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 January 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of the 7th regarding Hampson Gary. The letter
               reached him too late to consider Gary for the Third
               Assistant Secretary of State, but Wilson will forward
               the letter to the Secretary of State in the case that
               there might be other positions available. Wilson tells
               Dabney that he need not apologize for writing and says
               that it is a joy to hear from his old friends. The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1322">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. P. Tumulty, Secretary to President Wilson,
               to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 January 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. and enclosure (TLS 1 p. carbon to
               President Wilson from Newton Baker, War
               Department)</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Tumulty (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Tumulty acknowledges Dabney's
               previous letter to the President regarding John B.
               Jenkins, Jr. The War Department has written President
               Wilson regarding the matter and a copy of the War
               Department letter is enclosed. The War Department letter
               acknowledges a discharge of Mr. Jenkins. The letter from
               the War Department has the stamped signature of Newton
               D. Baker.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1335">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 March 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that only
               illness has prevented him from acknowledging sooner
               Dabney's letter of March 3 and its enclosure, which
               brought him gratification. Wilson says it is delightful
               to have backing from such people. The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1349">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 April 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that his
               address to Congress the previous evening was a response
               of a sort to Dabney's letter, although Wilson had not
               read it until that morning. Wilson appreciates what
               Dabney has sent him. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1362">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 April 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his
               letter of the 10th. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1375">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">13 April 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes in regard to
               John Thompson Brown and an appointment to the Federal
               Board for Vocational Education. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1388">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">21 June 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges a letter
               from Dabney regarding a Mr. [Andrew] Hawkins. Wilson
               will put the matter in the hands of the Secretary of the
               Navy and assures Dabney that the Secretary will have a
               big heart in the matter. Wilson says that he is sorry
               not to have seen Dabney. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1401">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 June 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes in regard to
               Andrew Hawkins. Wilson received a note from the
               Secretary of the Navy in which the Secretary confirmed
               Mr. Hawkins' discharge. Wilson writes that this ends the
               matter and he is sorry the fellow is "not what he ought
               to be, but probably a good riddance!" The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1414">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 August 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of the 9th. He is glad the Dabney has been
               "paying his respects" to the People's Council; it is for
               the most part a "bad and mischievous lot." The typed
               closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is
               signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1427">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 September 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes regarding Mr.
               Strickling's letter. He will put it in the hands of the
               Secretary of War. Wilson was obliged to Dabney for
               sending him the "very pointed reply" to Dr. Eliot. The
               typed closing reads "Affectionately yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1440">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 December 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson acknowledges Dabney's
               letter of December 7th. Wilson will "see what can be
               done about it." There is an autograph note in Dabney's
               hand stating that the letter refers to "my request" that
               the President ask the Italian Ambassador to allow
               Lieutenant Bruno Roselli to stay two weeks longer in the
               United States to deliver his speech to more
               universities.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1453">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917 December 12</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope and enclosures (TLS 1
               p. from Assistant Secretary of State William Phillips
               and TLS 2 p. from the Italian Ambassador.)</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson encloses a letter from
               William Phillips, Assistant Secretary of State. Phillips
               states he has contacted the Italian Ambassador and
               requested Lieutenant Roselli be allowed to remain in the
               United States for two additional weeks. The Ambassador
               reported that Roselli had been recalled not because he
               had offended Americans, but because Italy needed
               officers in light of the great numbers that had been
               killed. Phillips also states that the Ambassador would,
               in light of the request, extend Roselli's visit for two
               weeks, and has telegraphed permission to Roselli. The
               Italian Ambassador writes that he has already taken
               steps to arrange for Roselli's visit to be extended.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1466">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918 January 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 4 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he is
               unable to appoint Mr. Rutledge to West Point. He will
               only appoint sons of Army officers since to do otherwise
               would "ruin" him. Wilson explains that officers have no
               "political residence" and cannot obtain appointments
               through their House or Senate members. The typed closing
               reads "Faithfully yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1479">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918 June 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson writes that he has
               received a letter from the Secretary of War telling
               Wilson that Corporal Charles W. Strickling has been
               commissioned as a First Lieutenant and assigned to Camp
               Jackson, South Carolina. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours" and the letter is signed "Woodrow
               Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1493">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919 February 26</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for
               sending a letter from Professor Richard Henry Wilson.
               The typed closing reads "Faithfully yours," and the
               letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1506">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William H. Taft to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919 March 18</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Taft thanks Dabney for his letter of March 14 and
               states that he is unable to visit the University of
               Virginia "for my work is too heavy to take on other
               engagements, much as I would enjoy coming to your
               Jeffersonian center."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1519">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920 November 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his
               letter of October 28 and states that he "need not assure
               you of the pleasure with which I receive any message
               from you or of my profound appreciation of your
               continued trust and friendship." The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1532">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920 November 10</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson (on White House stationery) to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for
               consulting "about the publication of the letters" and
               asks Dabney not to consent to publication. Wilson states
               that he has "all my life had a passion for privacy which
               I hope may be indulged in this case." The typed closing
               reads "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1545">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922 December 7</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington, D. C., to
               Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson says that he
               must decline to sit for a portrait by Wight as he finds
               it "the most fatiguing of all preoccupations." Wilson
               states that he is "getting slowly well, and there is so
               much remaining to be done that I cannot afford any other
               course." The typed closing reads "Affectionately yours,"
               and the letter is signed "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1558">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Woodrow Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922 December 29</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington to Dabney in
               Charlottesville, Virginia. Wilson thanks Dabney for his
               letter of December 27 and says it came "as a peculiarly
               welcome birthday message." He thanks Dabney for his
               continued support and friendship and closes with best
               wishes for the New Year. The typed closing reads
               "Affectionately yours," and the letter is signed
               "Woodrow Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1571">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edith Bolling Wilson to Richard Heath Dabney 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926 October 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mrs. Wilson, 2340 S Street N.W., Washington, D. C.,
               to Dabney in Charlottesville, Virginia. Mrs. Wilson
               writes in response to Dabney's letter regarding his
               manuscript. She asks Dabney to send it to her so she can
               read it; she will then "take up the matter with my
               attorney, should there be any need for advice, and am
               sure you will understand that my effort is to safeguard
               you as well as myself from any embarrassments in the
               future." The typed closing reads "Very cordially yours,"
               and the letter is signed "Edith Bolling Wilson."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1584">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John Randolph Bolling to Richard Heath Dabney
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926 October 26</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>TLS 1 p. with envelope</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Boling, on Mrs. Wilson's stationery for 2340 S Street
               N.W., Washington, D.C., to Dabney in Charlottesville,
               Virginia. Bolling thanks Dabney for his letter of
               October 23 and says that Mrs. Wilson will read Dabney's
               article as soon as she can. The typed closing reads
               "Cordially yours," and the letter is signed "John
               Randolph Bolling."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
