<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03169">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03169::A Guide to the Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03169.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03169::A Guide to the Luther P.
             Jackson Oil Painting)//EN" "viu03169.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Jackson, Luther P., Oil Painting 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11085</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Katherine Schumann, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09/09/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03169::A Guide to the
            Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting)//EN" "viu03169.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11085</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1978</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11085</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of one item.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Luther P. Jackson Oil Painting, Accession #11085,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The majority of Jackson's papers are housed at Virginia
            State's Special Collections/University Archives, Johnston
            Memorial Library; others are held under accession number
            3615, Papers of Wilbur Earnest MacClenny, Special
            Collections Department, Alderman Library, University of
            Virginia. The Jackson portrait was placed on deposit in the
            Library on March 17, 1993 by Mr. M. Rick Turner, dean of
            the Office of Afro- American Affairs. It is not to be
            removed from the Special Collections Department without the
            permission of the Office of African-American Affairs.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Luther P. Jackson was born July 11, 1892, in Lexington,
         Kentucky, one of 12 children of a dairyman, Edward, and a
         schoolteacher, Delilah. He earned his bachelor of arts degree
         at Fisk University in 1914 and a master of arts degree at
         Columbia University in 1917. He taught at colleges in South
         Carolina and Kansas, and in 1922 joined the faculty at
         Virginia State College (now University) and eventually became
         a full professor and chairman of its history department.
         During that same year he married Johnnella Frazer, a native of
         Shelbyville, Kentucky, and they ultimately had four children:
         Luther, Jr., Edward, John, and Laura.</p>
      <p>Long before receiving his doctorate from the University of
         Chicago in 1949, Dr. Jackson had dedicated his life to the
         research and writing of African-American history and the
         securing of civil rights for blacks, especially the right to
         vote. He published numerous articles and specialized in the
         history of blacks in Virginia; his major monographs were Free
         Negro Labor and Property Holding in Virginia, 1830-1860
         (1942), Virginia Negro Soldiers and Sailors In The
         Revolutionary War (1944) and, Negro Office-Holders in Virginia
         1865-1895 (1945).</p>
      <p>Jackson was widely respected as an historian and crusader
         for civic freedom. James H. Brewer, another African-American
         historian who taught at Virginia State, wrote an acclamatory
         preface for the 1969 reprint of Jackson's Free Negro Labor:
         "In this book, my former history professor is content to be a
         scholar. His style is simple, and his tone is measured. He has
         presented the facts as they are, believing that facts properly
         set forth will speak for themselves."</p>
      <p>Jackson chaired the Virginia chapter of the Association for
         the Study of Negro Life and History (now the Association for
         the Study of Afro-American Life and History); was an editor of
         The Journal of Negro History; secretary of the all-black State
         Teacher's Association; a founder of the Petersburg Negro
         Business Association; founder of the Virginia Voters League;
         wrote a weekly column in the Norfolk Journal and Guide; and
         published annual reports the voting status of black Virginians
         from 1941 until his death. This community activist and
         historian died on April 13, 1950. His funeral was held at
         Virginia State College. At the time of his death he was
         editing a manuscript later published as Memoirs of A
         Monticello Slave, the reminiscences of Isaac Jefferson, a
         slave of Thomas Jefferson.</p>
      <p>In October 1977, the University of Virginia dedicated the
         Luther P. Jackson House (#4 Dawson's Row) as the home for its
         Office of Afro-American Affairs (OAAA), the first university
         building named in honor of a black Virginian. His son, Luther
         P. Jackson, Jr., a professor of journalism at Columbia
         University, was the guest speaker. As part of ceremonies of
         the tenth anniversary of its founding, the Jackson House was
         rededicated in October 1987 after renovations the previous
         summer. The keynote speaker was Dr. Harold K. Braxton, Dean of
         the School of Humanities and Social Sciences and Coordinator
         of Religious Studies at Virginia State University and a
         University of Virginia alumnus.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This item is a 1978 oil painting of Dr. Luther Porter
         Jackson (1892-1950), a professor of history at Virginia State
         College and civil rights activist. The artist is Professor
         Charles R. Flynn, Jr., of Virginia State; the painting,
         measuring 119 x 92 centimeters in its frame (99.5 x 74
         exclusive of frame), was presented to the Luther P. Jackson
         House, Office of Afro-American Affairs, University of
         Virginia, by the Omega Psi Phi fraternity and bears a small
         brass plate: "Bro. Luther P. Jackson/Donated by Omega Psi
         Phi."</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
