<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01591">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01591::Sister Lucy Julien letters to Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane, 1964-1990)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01591.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01591::Sister Lucy Julien letters
             to Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane, 1964-1990)//EN"
             "viu01591.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Sister Lucy Julien letters to
            Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1990</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Sister Lucy Julien letters to Amanda
            Stewart Bryan Kane, 1964-1990 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10888-a</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">27 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">August 10, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01591::Sister Lucy
            Julien letters to Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane,
            1964-1990)//EN" "viu01591.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Sister Lucy Julien letters to
         Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1990</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10888-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Sister Lucy Julien letters to Amanda Stewart Bryan
         Kane 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1964-1990</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10888-a</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">There are 356 items
         in this collection.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Sister Lucy Julien letters to Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane,
            1964-1990, Accession #10888-a, Special Collections Dept.,
            University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The material of this collection was made a gift to
            Alderman Library in accordance with the wishes she
            expressed during her life by Mrs. Amanda Stewart Bryan Kane
            of Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 28, 1992.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Lucy Kearney Hill was born in Richmond, Virginia, on April
         4, 1904, to a prominent banking family. She was reared and
         educated in Richmond, vacationing at the family house at Cape
         May, New Jersey, and at her grandfather Kearney's home on
         Lewis Mountain in Charlottesville. She graduated from
         Manhattanville College in New York in 1924. Preferring a
         contemplative order, she entered the French Roman Catholic
         order of Servantes du Sainte-Sacrement in 1929 and made her
         "Final Profession" on May 24, 1932, taking the name of Sister
         Lucy Julien. For over the next fifty years she lived in
         convents throughout France: Angers, Chalonnes, Paris, and
         Lyons.</p>
      <p>Sister Lucy met Amanda Stewart Bryan, also born in 1904, in
         1908. The Bryans, a very influential Richmond family, lived at
         Laburnum; as the girls went to school and played together Lucy
         spent many days at Laburnum, of which she retained fond
         memories. In 1930 Amanda Bryan married Keith Kane, a prominent
         attorney in New York City, and together they reared four
         children. The Kanes lived mostly in New York and moved in
         distinguished political and diplomatic circles, traveling
         extensively in Europe. They retired to Charlottesville in
         1973, where Mrs. Kane remained after her husband's death in
         1974 until her own death in 1990. Sister Lucy and Amanda
         Kane's friendship spanned eighty-two years of which the last
         twenty-six are documented by this collection.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are 356 items in the collection ranging from January,
         1964 to November, 1990, chiefly letters from Sister Lucy
         Julien Hill to Amanda Bryan Kane.</p>
      <p>The collection as a whole demonstrates the strength and
         value of a remarkable friendship between two women whose lives
         followed very divergent paths. Sister Lucy's gentle life of
         trust and love for God permeates her letters, as does her
         affection for Mrs. Kane, which is obviously warmly
         reciprocated. The letters chiefly discuss religious issues:
         doctrine, news of the order as a whole and of Sister Lucy's
         specific convent, and the spiritual life. Current events are
         discussed as they intrude on convent life; and virtually every
         letter details family and personal news.</p>
      <p>Of particular interest is the description of the
         charismatic movement within the Roman Catholic church, the
         death and subsequent election of popes, the interest in
         ecumenism, and the changes wrought by Vatican II. The
         collection provides a picture of late twentieth century
         convent life and specifically the aging of the "convent." Of
         interest to students of the life of the University of Virginia
         is the commentary on the death of "Billy" Hill, Sister Lucy's
         nephew and a well-known University alumnus.</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1964: Sister Lucy was living at the convent at
         Chalonnes. The few letters are concerned with convent (Sep 29)
         and family news, and with world peace in the light of
         President Kennedy's assassination (Jan 8).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1965: Letters focus on religious issues and
         concerns: doctrinal and spiritual discussions (May 19, Jun 10,
         Aug 1), the Pope's visit to New York (Oct 17), and the many
         changes in convent life expected from Vatican II (Oct 17, Dec
         19). Sister Lucy was named Assistant Mother Superior at the
         convent at Lyons; she describes a local harvest festival,
         known as a kermesse (Sep 5).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1966: Sister Lucy discusses convent life and daily
         routines (May 20, Nov 26, Dec 18); her memories of Virginia
         childhood (May 20), her desire for ecumenism and world peace
         (Feb 13); she describes Lyons at Christmas (Dec 18).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1967: She relates news of Kane and Hill family
         members (Jan 3, 11), and mentions family memories (Jan 11);
         the University of Virginia's Alderman Library (Jan 3);
         religious and Servantes order news (Jun 10), and comments on
         changes in Servantes order life which engage the nuns in more
         discussion and less silence (Feb 7).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1968: One letter: Sister Lucy sent to the Paris
         house to be organist; upheaval in Servantes from Vatican II;
         Sister Lucy asks help from Amanda and Keith Kane in writing a
         study on ecumenism for the order as part of the
         re-organization.</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1969: One letter: Sister Lucy returns to the house
         at Lyons, where, with the exception of "emergency" trips, she
         remains at the present. She voices concerns over the changes
         wrought by Vatican II, and questions being "stuck" in Lyons
         after her time in Paris.</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1970: All family news.</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1971: Family news; and commentary on changes in
         convent life, particularly the increase in personal freedom
         and privacy (May 6).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1972: Gratitude for the Kanes' previous visit and
         their spiritual life (Mar 30); personal and convent anecdotes
         (Apr 4).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1973: St. Polycarp's Day reminds Sister Lucy of the
         Sisters' arrest and detainment by the German army during the
         Second World War (Feb 23); the convent succumbs to influenza
         en masse (Dec 3); the Kanes retire to Charlottesville from New
         York (Dec 13).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1974: Sister Lucy shows concern over current
         events: upcoming French elections, possibility of Communist
         takeover (May 16, Dec 15), President Nixon's resignation (Sep
         22), French postal strike (Sep 22, Dec 15); she discusses
         convent news (Jun 9, 30, Jul 10), the international Catholic
         charismatic movement (Jul 7); Kane and Hill family news (May
         31, Jun 9, 13, Sep 22), memories of entering convent (Jun 13,
         Jul 31); she responds to news of Keith Kane's death (May 31,
         Jun 30, Dec 15).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1975: Few letters; they focus on Kane and Hill
         family news and Amanda Kane's visit (Apr 14, Aug 24); Sister
         Lucy comments on a charismatic conference (May 18).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1976: Few letters; news of family and the
         Servantes. One house has been closed and the sisters
         re-distributed; changes in governance because of dwindling
         numbers (Feb 23).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1977: Letters are filled with family (May 13) and
         religious news: Amanda Kane's visit (Jul 21); relaxing of
         convent rules (Jul 7), and Sister Lucy's growing interest and
         involvement in the charismatic movement (May 31, Jul 21, Aug
         27, 29).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1978: From September through December letters
         concentrate on death of Pope Paul VI, the election and death
         of John Paul I and election of John Paul II (Oct 5, 28, Nov 9,
         Dec 31), and also spiritual and charismatic concerns (Jan 21,
         Jun 30).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1979: Religious and convent news dominate the
         letters, especially the relaxing of convent restrictions (Feb
         20, Mar 6, Jul 15), Pope John Paul II's pilgrimage to Poland
         (Jun 15), and Sister Lucy's fiftieth anniversary of entering
         the convent (May 24); current events are mentioned(Feb 20, Nov
         12), Bastille Day celebrations (Jul 13); amusing personal
         anecdotes (Apr 8, Nov 12).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1980: Sister Lucy relates convent and Servantes
         order news (Mar 29), provincial meeting (Feb 17); Hill and
         Kane family news (Dec 16); she worries over current events:
         Iran hostages (Jan 20), Polish strikes (Sep 1), the American
         presidential election, and is excited about her newly acquired
         right to vote in an election (Sep 1, Oct 7).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1981: Sister Lucy comments on current events: royal
         wedding (Jul 8, 26), Iran hostages (Jan 19), French elections
         (May 28), attempted assassination of President Reagan (Apr 4),
         attempted assassination of Pope John Paul II (May 28); family
         and convent news (Jul 8, 26, Aug 18, 19, Oct 4); charismatic
         conference (Jul 26); death of "Billy" Hill, Sister Lucy'
         nephew and University alumnus (enclosed elegy, Nov 5, 6, Dec
         8).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1982: Current events and issues of doctrine almost
         disappear from the letters and convent life and family news
         dominate from this point on. Convent news (Jan 9, Feb 22, Mar
         1, Apr 6, May 8, Jul 6), a thief sneaks into the convent (Dec
         15), Sister Lucy's Jubilee-fiftieth anniversary of Final
         Profession: preparations and proposed family visits (Feb 22),
         description (Jun 22).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1983: News of convent and family life begins to
         have medical overtones as the years progress (Apr 4, Aug 6,
         Sep 7, Dec 2, 17); nuns visit on way to Sri Lanka (Oct 17),
         convent enjoys religious television programming (Dec 17),
         memories of German imprisonment (Sep 8); French postal strikes
         (Jul 6).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1984: Sister Lucy reacts to Kane family news (Feb
         20); she recounts memories of their Richmond childhood (Feb
         20, May 7, Nov 30), and gives comfort to Amanda Kane on tenth
         anniversary of husband's death (Jun 8). She reports on convent
         and Servantes order news (Jan 31, May 7, Jul 7, Oct 28): the
         "convent" visits a monastery (Sep 7), concerns are voiced on
         the age and infirmity of the sisters (Jul 7, Oct 28), she
         discusses a religious doctrine (Mar 6).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1985: All of these letters detail personal,
         convent, and family news (especially Feb 4, Apr 6, Nov 12, Dec
         8), Sister Lucy is healthiest one in the convent (Feb 4).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1986: Sister Lucy seems much older; she writes many
         more letters to Amanda Kane. She repeats news several times,
         remembers the distant past better than the immediate past. She
         takes a cane (Jan 20); memories of Virginia childhood (Jan 20,
         May 30, Jun 6, Jul 5, Nov 1, 25), memory of visit of General
         Pershing to her parents' house (Jun 6); Amanda Kane's illness
         (Oct 20, 26; Oct 20 to Shelah Scott); renovations to convent
         (Jan 6, May 24); Pope John Paul II's visit to Lyons (Jul 5,
         Oct 7).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1987: Memories of Richmond, Laburnum, and debutante
         balls pervade the letters (Jan 4, 20, 24, Jul 13, Oct 30).
         Family news is given (Jan 4, 20, May 31, Jul 4, Sep 15);
         convent news (Jan 13, Aug 11, Sep 26), resident priest dies at
         age of 85 (Jul 4), a new Mother General (Sep 30), a young nun
         sent to help convent (Jan 13).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1988: Sister Lucy recalls childhood memories (Jan
         22, Feb 12, May 4, 28). She receives a book about her
         grandfather, Civil War General Kearney (Jun 23), expresses
         pride in being a Virginian (Jun 23). Convent news: Sister Lucy
         disagrees with the plan for the convent to become a rest home
         (Mar 19), infirmities curb charitable works for the convent
         (May 4), nuns may now go home to visit on weekends (Aug 5).
         Current events: she comments on Empress Zita's funeral (Apr
         4), American canonizations (Dec 16). This year marks Amanda
         Kane's last visit to Sister Lucy.</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1989: Sister Lucy discusses her imprisonment by the
         Germans more thoroughly (Jan 26); She gives opinions on
         current events: President Bush is seen on television (Apr 25),
         Bastille Day celebrations (Jul 14), University of Virginia
         President O'Neill's resignation (Oct 17), trouble in the
         Philippines (Dec 18). Sister Lucy ill (Apr 25), in hospital
         (Jul 5, 11, 12), Amanda Kane ill (Jul 11, 12, Aug 2, Nov 23);
         discussion of eucharist (Jul 27, Aug 2).</p>
      <p>LETTERS 1990: She recounts memories of childhood (Feb 28,
         Jun 9, Jul 24). Enclosures sent by her younger sister evoke
         memories of Charlottesville (Aug 9, Oct 25, Nov 2). Convent
         news: a discussion of loyalty to one's order (Feb 9); the
         convent's yearly retreat prompts complaints about the order's
         modernization (Jun 13, 23). A letter from Sister Lucy's
         younger sibling Anne Hill Bowers to Amanda Kane describes
         Sister Lucy at 86 years old (Jul 24). Although Sister Lucy had
         trouble with her eyes and legs, she was relatively healthy.
         Amanda Kane, on the other hand, was in failing health and was
         transferred to the infirmary at Martha Jefferson House early
         in the year. Amanda Kane's health was a constant worry to
         Sister Lucy. Most of the letters in this year focus on the
         weather, particularly sunshine, Amanda Kane's health, and
         family news. Amanda Kane died in early December, 1990,
         approximately two weeks after the last letter in this
         collection (Nov 26) was written.</p>
      <p>Also present in the collection are three photographs of
         Sister Lucy, two of which include Mrs. Amanda Kane.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
