<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03924">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03924::Papers Pertaining to The Enchanted Years)//EN" "viu03924.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers Pertaining to The Enchanted Years, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1921</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">The Enchanted Years, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">38-429
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8/10/2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers Pertaining to The Enchanted Years, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1921</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">38-429
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers Pertaining to The Enchanted Years
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1919-1921
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">38-429
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">160 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers Pertaining to The Enchanted Years, Accession #38-429, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was a gift of John Calvin Metcalf and James Southall Wilson, ante 1938.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection of 160 items, letters and poems, 1919-1921, concerns the publication of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Enchanted Years,</title> a book of contemporary verse dedicated by poets of Great Britain and
America to the University of Virginia on the occasion of its one-hundredth anniversary. John Calvin Metcalf and James Southall Wilson of the University were the editors of the volume (New York, 1921). Included are
letters between the poets and the editors, and poems that were published in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Enchanted Years.</title></p>
      <p>Poets and correspondents include: Zoe Akins, Richard Aldington, Josephine Dodge Daskam Bacon, James Cook Bardin, Katharine Lee Bates, Hilaire Belloc, Frances Neil Rose Benét, Stephen Vincent
Benét, William Rose Benét, John Randolph Bolling, Kate Langley Bosher, Gordon Bottomley, Gamaliel Bradford, William Stanley Braithwaite, Anna Hempstead Branch, Amelia Josephine Burr, Maxwell
Struthers Burt, Richard Burton, James Branch Cabell, John Vance Cheney, George Herbert Clarke, Sarah Norcliffe Cleghorn, Helen Gray Cone, Grace Walcott Hazard Conkling, Eleanor Rogers Cox, Olive Tilford Dargan,
Mary Caroline Davies, W.H. (William Henry) Davies, Fannie Stearns Davis, Walter De la Mare, Lee Wilson Dodd, John Drinkwater, Louise Driscoll, Baron Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett Dunsany, Harry Stillwell
Edwards, John Erskine, Florence Wilkinson Evans, Arthur Davison Ficke, John H. (John Hurtson) Finley, John Gould Fletcher, Jeanne Robert Oliver Foster, John Freeman, Theodosia Pickering Garrison, Adolphine
Fletcher Gerry, Basil L. (Basil Lanneau) Gildersleeve, Armistead C. (Armistead Churchill) Gordon, Robert Graves, William Griffith, Hermann Hagedorn, H.D. (Hilda Doolittle), Ralph Hodgson, Robert Underwood Johnson,
Alfred Kreymborg, D.H. (David Herbert) Lawrence, Agnes Lee, William Ellery Leonard, W.M. (Winifred M.) Letts, Vachel Lindsay, Amy Lowell, Helen Hoyt Lyman, Virginia Taylor McCormick, Percy MacKaye, Edwin Markham,
John Masefield, Theodore Maynard, John Calvin Metcalf, Scudder Middleton, Houstin Mifflin, Lloyd Mifflin, Harold Monro, Margaret Prescott Montague, Anne Moran, Angela Morgan, John Gneisenau Neihardt, Grace Fallow
Norton, Norreys Jephson O'Conor, Thomas Nelson Page, Lizette Woodworth Reese, Cale Young Rice, Amélie Rives, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, Edwin Arlington Robinson, George William Russell, Mary Sands, Robert
Haven Schauffler, Clinton Scollard, Margaret Pollock Sherwood, Benjamin Franklin Sledd, May Riley Smith, Sir John Collings Squire, George Sterling, Charles Wharton Stork, Arthur Symons, Sara Teasdale, Edith
Matilda Thomas, Pierre Troubetzkoy, Jean Starr Untermeyer, Louis Untermeyer, Henry Van Dyke, Tertius Van Dyke, Willoughby Weaving, John Hall Wheelock, Marguerite Ogden Bigelow Wilkinson, James Southall Wilson,
Clement Wood, George Edward Woodberry, and Francis Brett Young.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The folders are arranged alphabetically by poet's surname.
</p>
    </arrangement>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
