<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03293">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03293::A Guide to the Bland-Ruffin Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03293.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03293::A Guide to the
             Bland-Ruffin Papers)//EN" "viu03293.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Bland-Ruffin
            Papers</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Bland-Ruffin Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3026</num></subtitle><author>Ann Marie Harkins</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Katherine Schumann, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">10/11/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03293::A Guide to the
            Bland-Ruffin Papers)//EN" "viu03293.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Bland-Ruffin Papers 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1741-1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3026</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Bland-Ruffin Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1741-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3026</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 100 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Bland-Ruffin Papers, Accession #3026, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The papers were a gift to the library in memory of
            Kirkland Ruffin, M.D. (1862-1923) by his daughters, Mrs.
            Lawrence Fontaine Tucker, Virginia Beach, Virginia, and
            Mrs. Braden Vandeventer, Virginia Beach, Virginia on 26
            August 1976.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p><emph render="bold">Theodorick Bland</emph><lb/>Born in Prince George County, Virginia, on March 21,
         1742, Theodorick Bland was the son of Theodorick Bland of
         Cawsons on the Appamatox River and Frances (Bolling) Bland.
         Bland was educated in England, studying first at a school in
         Wakefield, Yorkshire, from 1753 until 1759. He attended an
         infirmary in Liverpool as a student of medicine from 1759 to
         1761, and then entered the University of Edinborough, from
         which he recieved an M.D. degree in 1763. Returning to
         Virginia in 1764, he began practicing medicine in Prince
         George County. Bland's health suffered as a result of his
         practice, and in 1771 he retired and became a planter; he
         married Martha Dangerfield.</p>
      <p>Bland strongly supported the American cause during the
         Revolutionary War. On June 24, 1775, he participated in a raid
         on the governor's palace in Williamsburg, in which a group of
         twenty-four patriots removed from arms from the palace to the
         powder magazine. At the end of that year, he wrote harsh
         letters in the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Virginia Gazette</title>against the
         royal governor of Virginia, Lord Dunmore, under the signature
         of "Cassius". Bland was appointed captain of the 1st Troop of
         Virginia Cavalry on June 13, 1776, and colonel of the 1st
         Continental Dragoons on March 31, 1777. He commanded mounted
         troops in the New Jersey and Philadelphia Campaigns and fought
         in the battle of Brandywine.</p>
      <p>On November 5, 1778, Washington ordered Bland to take
         command of an escort to conduct the Convention Army troops
         from Massachusetts and Connecticut to Albermarle County,
         Virginia. He was then placed in command of the post in
         Charlottesville, the Albermarle Barracks, where the prisoners
         were housed, and remained there until November 1779. In 1780,
         the Virginia General Assembly elected him a delegate to the
         Continental Congress. At the end of his term, he returned to
         his plantation, Farmingdale, which had been plundered by the
         enemy.</p>
      <p>Bland served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1786
         to 1788, and was an unsuccessful candidate for governor
         against Edmund Randolph in 1786. He was a member of the
         Virginia convention of 1788 for the consideration of the
         proposed Federal Constitution, and voted against its adoption.
         Elected a member of the first House of Representatives, he
         died while attending the session in New York on June 1,
         1790.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Edmund Ruffin</emph><lb/>Edmund Ruffin was born on January 5, 1794, in Prince
         George County, Virginia. His parents were George and Jane
         (Lucas) Ruffin. He was educated at home until the age sixteen
         when he entered the College of William and Mary. Ruffin soon
         was suspended, however, for neglecting his studies. He served
         as a private in the War of 1812, but saw no active duty. On
         returning home, he married Susan Travis of Williamsburg and
         took charge of his father's Coggin's Point Farm.</p>
      <p>Ruffin grew increasingly concerned about the unproductive
         land of the Tidewater region, and the seemming indefferencte
         of most other planters. The soil had worn out from continual
         planting of the same crop and many persons were moving
         westward. Ruffin attempted to solve the problem on his own
         farm by sturdy and experimentation. After reading Sir Humphrey
         Dave's 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Elements of Agricultural
         Chemistry,</title>he speculated that vegetable acids made the
         soil sterile and unable to return manure. He decided that the
         use of marl (a mixture of clay and carbonate of lime),
         fertilizers, crop rotation, drainage, and proper plowing would
         revitalize the soil. Ruffin's experiments proved extremely
         successful, and in 1818 he presented his findings to the
         Prince George Agricultural Society and then printed them in
         expanded form in the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">American Farmer.</title>In 1832, he
         published a book about his theories, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">An Essay on Calcareous
         Manures,</title>and in the following year launched an
         agricultural journal, the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Farmer's Register.</title>The journal
         was extremely influential in spreading Ruffin's methods of
         scientific farming throughout the South. Ruffin served on the
         first Virginia State Board of Agriculture, and in 1842 became
         agricultural surveyor of South Carolina. He was elected the
         first president of the Virginia State Agricultural Society in
         1845, but declined because he felt that his work was not
         sufficiently appreciated in his home state. He reconsidered,
         however, and took the post in 1852. He actively encouraged
         experimental farming and agricultural education, and continued
         to write and speak extensively about agriculture.</p>
      <p>Ruffin was always interested in politics, but his tenure in
         the Virginia Senate (1823-1826) left him disgusted with
         politicians. He was first a Whig, but became a Democrat when
         the slavery and states' rights clash developed. An ardent
         defender of slavery and one of the first secessionists in
         Virginia, Ruffin discussed his ideas in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">De Bow's Review</title>and the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Southern Literary Messenger.</title>He
         also published serveral pro-slavery pamphlets. He was an
         advocate of direct trade with Europe, attended three Southern
         commercial conventions, and started the League of United
         Southerners. Hoping that John Brown's raid would galvanize the
         South, he secured Brown's pikes and gave one to the governor
         of each Southern state. Ruffin was invited to sit in three
         seceding conventions, and while serving as a volunteer with
         the Palmetto Guard of Charleston, was allowed to fire the
         first shot from Morris Island against Fort Sumter. He joined
         with the Palmetto Guards again as a "temporary" private at the
         First Battle of Manassas.</p>
      <p>During the Civil War, Ruffin travelled throughout the
         South, visiting many military camps, despite his failing
         health. He became increasingly pessimistic about the outcome
         of the war after the Battle of Gettysburg. Northern soldiers
         occupied his plantation, Malbourne in Hanover County, and
         ransacked his library. Totally devastated by the collapse of
         the Confederacy, Ruffin committed suicide on June 18, 1865,
         and was buried in the family cemetery at Marlbourne. He was
         survived by three of his eleven children.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The Bland-Ruffin Collection, 1741-1788;1859-1865 (100
         items) consists of letters and papers of Revolutionary soldier
         Theodorick Bland and secessionist Edmund Ruffin, and relates
         primarily to their wartime experiences. Students of both the
         American Revolution and the Civil War would find this
         collection very valuable, since it contains letters written by
         leaders of both periods and some first-person narratives of
         military events. The majority of the letters were written to,
         rather than by, Bland and Ruffin, and over two-thirds pertain
         to the Civil War.</p>
      <p>Bland himself wrote to the loyalist Reverend Jacob
         Duché, attacking his views and character, to St.
         George Tucker (in cipher), to Lieutenant Colonel Muir, and to
         his wife Martha "Patsy" (Dangerfield) Bland. In a circular
         letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson requested that Bland provide
         information about the arms furnished by his regiment to the
         Continental army, and Colonel Armand (Marquis de la Roulerie
         Tuffin) expressed his displeasure at the failure of the
         Continental Congress to promote him. Hessian officers Major
         General von Riesedel and General Specht wrote to Bland
         concerning affairs of the Convention Army at the Albermarle
         Barracks. Other correspondents of note are Richard Bland,
         Edmund Randolph, and John Page, the last offering an
         interesting account of Benedict Arnold's invasion of Virginia
         in 1781. In addition to the letters, the Bland material
         includes a number of papers relating to Prince George County.
         There is a fragment of a loyalist petition circulated in the
         summer of 1781 by Archibald Robertson, some political
         lampoons, a few military documents, and one unidentified
         drawing.</p>
      <p>The letters to Edmund Randolph form a more cohesive unit
         than the Bland papers, and document Ruffin's unflagging
         support of the Confederacy. P.G.T. Beauregard, S.W. Ferguson,
         and other military leaders provided Ruffin with passes to
         various military encampments, and individuals sought his help
         in obtaining appointments or transfers. In a letter to C.G.
         Memminger, the Confederate secretary of the treasury, on
         January 22, 1864, enclosing a check for four hundred dollars,
         Ruffin stated that he would contribute as much of his income
         as possible to the cause. Letters of thanks from Charles
         Marbeth, mayor of Charleston, and R.R. Harrison of
         Fredericksburg indicate that Ruffin was true to his word. Most
         of the largely personal letter from such individuals as
         Rebecca Hewitt to Ruffin comment on the course of the war and
         its impact on daily life. Of special interest is a letter from
         Captain John Scott to Ruffin, enclosing a copy of the detailed
         report he submitted to General Holmes on the First Battle of
         Manassas. Completing the collection is a fragment of a note
         apparently written by Ruffin shortly before his death, in
         which he states that he wishes to be buried in South Carolina,
         and hopes that the next generation will uphold his
         reputation.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The papers were in chronological order when they arrived at
         the library. The correspondence and papers of Bland precede
         those of Ruffin, and both groups are arranged
         chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Other Descriptive Data</head>
      <p>Charles Campbell found the Bland papers at Cawson's, but
         unable to carefully examine, wrote to Edmund Ruffin about
         them. Campbell subsequently published an edition of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Bland Papers.</title>A number of
         the letters in our collection appear in this volume (available
         in the McGregor Library A 1840 .B53). In a note, Ruffin states
         that he appended to the original Bland papers some additional
         items of related interest, "derived from different
         sources."</p>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e242">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edmund Ruffin's List and Explanation of the
               Bland Papers 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e250">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Richard Randolph to Theodorick Bland;
               Reverend John Tyler to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1741 July 20; 1744
               July18</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e258">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robert Walker to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1764 July 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e266">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Marchioness Waldegrave to Anne Blair 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1772 March 27;
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e274">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Richard Bland to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1775 Oct. 29</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e282">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[Theodorick Bland] to the Reverend Jacob
               Duché 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1777 Fall]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 AL</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e290">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Theodorick Bland to his wife Martha
               (Dangerfield) "Patsy" Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1777 Nov. 16</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e298">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mayor General [Baron] von Riesedel to
               Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779 May 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 LS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e306">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robert Dobson to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779 June 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e314">
        <did>
          <unittitle>General Specht to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1779 Oct</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e323">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Colonel Armand (Marquis de la Roulerie
               Tuffin) to [Theodorick Bland?] 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d. [ca.
               1780-1781?]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e331">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Reed to [Committe of Congress,
               including Theodorick Bland] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1791 Jan. 9]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e339">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John Page to [Theodorick Bland?] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781 Jan. 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e347">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Theodorick Bland to St. George Tucker (in
               cipher) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782 May 20</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e353">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edmund Randolph to [Theodorick Bland?] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782 July 19</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e359">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edmund Randolph to Theodorick Bland 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1782 Sept. 20</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e365">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Fragment of a Petition to the British 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1781 June 7 July;
               1858</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Circulated in Prince George County in 1781 by
               Archibald Robertson, with Explanatory Notes by Edmund
               Ruffin, and Ruffin's Grandson Edmund Ruffin (1858)</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e376">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Lampoon, apparently in response to Archibald
               Robertson's Petition 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1781]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e384">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of a Court Martial in Prince
               George's County 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1785 Nov. 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e392">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Booklet 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1785-1788</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>re Militia of Prince George County including ALS
               Theodorick Bland to Lieutenant Colonel Muir, Muster
               Roll, and Minutes of the Board</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e403">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Electioneering Squibs (Lampoons) by Opposing
               Candidates in Prince George County 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1787 May; 1787 June 12;
               1858</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Edmund Ruffin and [?] Muir, with explanatory notes by
               Ruffin's grandson, Edmund Ruffin (1858)</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e415">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Unidentified Drawing 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e423">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ben McCullough to Colonel David Randon,
               introducing Edmund Ruffin 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Feb. 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e431">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Charles F. Osbourne to Edmund Ruffin 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 Dec. 2</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e439">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Edmund Ruffin 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861
               March-Dec</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>16 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e447">
        <did>
          <unittitle>R.M.T. Hunter to Edmund Ruffin 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861 Oct. 8</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e455">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Captain John Scott to Edmund Ruffin,
               enclosing copy of a report made to General Holmes re:
               The First Battle of Manasses 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 Feb 11</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e461">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Edmund Ruffin; ALS Edmund Ruffin
               to Ona Reid 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>19 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e469">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Edmund Ruffin 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1863</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>17 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e477">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Edmund Ruffin with Charles
               Campbell; ALS Edmund Ruffin to C.J. Memminger; Letters
               to Edmund Ruffin, and Edmund Ruffin, Jr. 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>6 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e485">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Edmund Ruffin; Notice of a meeting
               to help the citizens of Charleston</unittitle>
          <physdesc>7 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e491">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Note by Edmund Ruffin re: his burial and
               reputation (draft?) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1865?]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e500">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thomas Jefferson to Theodorick Bland (in
               Thomas Jefferson Papers, Vault) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1780 July 28</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e508">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photograph of Edmund Ruffin (in Prints) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
