<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02218">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02218::A Guide to the Mary Stone Naijon Letters)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02218.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02218::A Guide to the Mary Stone
             Naijon Letters)//EN" "viu02218.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Mary Stone Naijon Letters, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1986</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Naijon, Mary Stone, Letters 
            <num type="collectionnumber">8809-k</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">20 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Alicia Pearia, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3/19/02</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-19" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 19, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02218::A Guide to the
            Mary Stone Naijon Letters)//EN" "viu02218.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Mary Stone Naijon Letters, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1986</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">8809-k</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Mary Stone Naijon Letters, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1927-1986</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">8809-k</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collecton
         consists of fifty-five letters.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Mary Stone Naijon Letters, 1927-1986, Accession #8809-k
            , Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were given to the Library by Mrs. Fillmore
            (Elizabeth) Norfleet, Charlottesville, Virginia, on March
            25, 1993.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of fifty-five letters, ca.
         1927-1986, chiefly from Mary (Mealand) Stone Naijon
         (1890-1984), Paris, France, to her life-long friend, Fillmore
         Norfleet. Mary Naijon was an American born in Cleveland, Ohio,
         who first married Walter [Stone ?] in the United States. After
         a divorce, she moved to Paris, France in 1924, where she
         taught school to young children. In 1934, she married Andre
         Naijon (d. 1974) and became totally a Frenchwoman, never
         returning to the United States in her later years. Also
         present is a fourteen page typed round robin letter by Mrs.
         Naijon with autograph emendations describing her experiences
         in France during World War II including her internment at
         Vittel, France, by the Germans.</p>
      <p>Topics in her letters to the Norfleets include: a
         description of her culinary and visual experiences on her trip
         to Rouen, France (1927 Oct 29); her encouragement to Fillmore
         to continue his writing and her advice concerning love and
         marriage based on her own early life with Walter [Stone ?]
         (1928 Jan 21); a reference to her round robin letter about
         World War II and her internment at Vittel, sent after her
         liberation reaching them years later (1948 Feb [21 ?]);
         comments about Frances P. Keyes' book Came A Cavalier and her
         thanks for Fillmore's book on St. Memin (1948 May 17);
         political upheaval in France, a lack of things to purchase at
         the market, and shortages in electricity (1949 Dec 16); the
         grim food situation in England and the need for any used
         clothing in France (1951 May 17); the arrival of two of her
         brothers in Europe, Dick in London, and Arthur (1891 ?- ) in
         Paris (1951 Sep 25); and the sale of several of her children's
         songs to Silver Burdett and Ginn &amp; Company.</p>
      <p>Additional topics include: the illness of her brother Dick
         ([1905 ?]-1958) with cancer, his return to Lyme, Connecticut,
         and subsequent death (1957 Nov 29; 1958 Apr 2); the unfair
         criticism of Paris by American visitors (1958 Jul 4); her
         serious illness from September 20 until the date of the letter
         (1967 Jan 27); the death of Andre Naijon (1974 Oct 5); a
         political bombing in the building across from hers in Paris,
         changes in Parisian architecture and the increase in crimes by
         teen-agers in France (1976 Jan 1; Dec 20); more about changes
         in Parisian architecture and neighborhoods (1977 Oct 12); her
         dislike of Julien Green and comments by the French who resent
         his entry into the Academie Francaise (1978 Jan 13; 1984 Jan
         13); mention of the Naijon mustard industry in Dijon (1978 Mar
         15); the worsening of crime in France with Mary a victim of
         attacks and robberies (1978 May 8; 1982 Jan 18); her disgust
         with Francois Mitterrand and French politics (1982 Apr 8); and
         her distrust of Ronald Reagan (1981 Jul 25; 1984 Jan 1).</p>
      <p>Other letters in the collection include a letter from Mary
         Naijon's niece Ruth Mealand Swartz to Elizabeth Norfleet about
         the death of Mary Naijon (1986 Aug 24) and a letter from
         [Madame ?] Lapeyroux, Poitiers, concerning the bad conditions
         in France after World War II (1947 Sep 17). Another letter
         from [Madame Lapeyroux ?], Poitiers, assures the Norfleets
         that they will be happy to have them visit during their tour
         of Europe, mentions the Norfleets' visit to Greece during the
         trouble with Turkey, and promises that Pierre will write them
         (1974 Jul 31).</p>
      <p>In her fourteen page letter describing her experiences
         during World War II (ca. 1946 ?), Mary Naijon mentions the
         following:</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Page One</emph>- when war broke out Mary
         Naijon was at Cosne; describes the mobilization of horses and
         of her husband Andre and his brother, Pierre; Andre stationed
         at Nevers as quartermaster, not in active service as he served
         in World War I; at New Year's, Andre sent back to Paris to his
         office because they made war materiel; left for Cosne when the
         Germans entered France [1940 June] 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Two</emph>- describes the exodus from
         Paris; mentions the presence of a fifth column in France; the
         movement of French troops to the Loire River where they were
         to make a stand against the Germans; the bridges over the
         Loire River all blown up 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Three</emph>- German bombers strafing
         the refugees on the roads and on the trains; the death of her
         friend Madame Fernand Dubois; adventures on the way to
         Clermont-Ferrand searching for food and places to stay 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Four</emph>- the Naijons made it only
         as far as Correze; the town of Meymac paid 10 francs a day to
         refugees without funds; France occupied by August 1940; line
         of demarcation was at Bourges, not far from Cosne; saw a line
         of French prisoners herded through the streets to barracks 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Five</emph>- the Naijons returned to
         their Paris home; Mary had to sign in at the police station
         every week as an American citizen - her French naturalization
         papers had not come through yet; the Germans came for her on
         September 24, 1942, along with other American women, they were
         taken to the palarium at the "Jardin D'acclimatation" (the
         zoo); where they called themselves the Monkey House Women 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Six</emph>- stayed at the zoo for
         four days until they were taken to the Pantin railroad station
         to travel to their internment at Vittel; French train men
         helped send messages to their families 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Seven</emph>- collected all the
         discarded "lard" and sausages given to them by the Germans for
         later use; taken to hotels at the Casino in the Park at
         Vittel; first received English Red Cross boxes, then American
         Red Cross boxes six weeks later; describes her quarters 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Eight</emph>- American, Russian and
         English Jews put into another hotel; prisoners had movies, a
         library, and packages from home; Jews with illegal passports
         were deported and some committed suicide; many English women
         imprisoned for five years had mental breakdowns; depended on
         Red Cross boxes to supplement the single simple meal a day
         granted by the Germans 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Nine</emph>- heard of the liberation
         of Paris and saw the exodus of the Germans from France;
         Germans stopped people and forced them from their bicycles;
         first liberation of the Vittel camp short-lived; spies and
         collaborators arrested; Vittel located in the Belfort
         Corridor; next day, the Germans returned to the camp with
         cannon and tanks 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Ten</emph>- knew the battle of Nancy
         was going on; the camp had shrapnel falling all over the
         hotels; then both the French and American armies entered
         Vittel which was liberated for good [September 12, 1944] 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Eleven</emph>- the hospital now
         filled with wounded soldiers; Mary visited the town of Vittel;
         had a surprise visit from her American nephew [Jay Brigeman ?]
         not seen since he was a boy; left Vittel on September 29, 1944
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Twelve</emph>- saw Troyes completely
         destroyed by bombing on the way home; made it to Paris at
         last; went to the Cite Universitaire to the provisional
         hospital; was reunited with Andre; France in famine conditions
         when liberated 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Thirteen</emph>- Andre in poor
         physical condition due to the years of little provisions and
         lack of fuel and electricity 
         <lb/><emph render="bold">Page Fourteen</emph>- contains a list of
         American friends who should receive this round robin
         letter</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
