<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03132">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03132::A Guide to the John H. Hunter Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03132.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03132::A Guide to the John H.
             Hunter Papers)//EN" "viu03132.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Hunter
            Papers</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Hunter, John H., Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">166</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Mark Hayek, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9/04/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03132::A Guide to the
            John H. Hunter Papers)//EN" "viu03132.xml" converted from
            EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the John H. Hunter
         Papers</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">166</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>John H. Hunter Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1842-1888</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">166</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of 135 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>John H. Hunter Papers, Accession #166, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The material in this collection was loaned to Alderman
            Library by Beirne Lay of Charlottesville, Virginia, on
            October 22, 1938.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are 135 items in the collection ranging from 1842 to
         1888, comprising the papers of John Harrison Hunter (ca.1830-
         ), a physician who practiced medicine in the South from 1855
         until at least the 1880s, serving as a surgeon for the
         Confederate Army during the Civil War. Nearly all of the
         papers are 1861-1865 official correspondence on his medical
         duties, with numerous requisitions, orders, and communiques
         between himself and the Surgeon General's Office in Richmond,
         which provide much information on the conduct of military
         hospitals under adverse circumstances, and create an oblique
         view of southern life during the war.</p>
      <p>Hunter was born in 1830 in Martinsburg [present-day West
         Virginia] to an upper-middle class family. Both his father and
         maternal grandfather had been doctors and he was related to
         the Tuckers of Virginia, being a cousin of J[ohn] R[andolph]
         Tucker (1812-1883). He enlisted in the army when he was
         eighteen, and served in the Mexican War. He was stationed in
         Buena Vista, first as a private soldier in the First Company
         of the Virginia Foot Volunteers, and then in February 1848 as
         a sergeant in the Quarter Master Corps.</p>
      <p>In 1852 he was in California, but sometime in late 1852 or
         early 1853 he returned east and entered the Medical School of
         the University of Maryland in Baltimore. He graduated and
         passed his boards in March 1855. Although he was soon
         practicing in Kanawha County, present-day West Virginia, at
         some point in the late 1850s he moved to Arkansas and settled
         in the town of Pocahontas in Randolph County.</p>
      <p>In late 1859, in the light of John Brown's abortive raid on
         Harper's Ferry, Hunter and other residents formed themselves
         into a militia company called the "Randolph Guards." In
         December of that year the Governor of Arkansas chose Hunter to
         captain a militia company of light infantry called the
         "Randolph Riflemen." By December 1860 Hunter had also been
         named captain of a militia patrol group in a neighboring
         town.</p>
      <p>After war broke out, Hunter was ordered to report to the
         Arkansas Volunteers, presumably as an infantry officer. He
         brought his young family back east, and was quickly
         transferred to a Virginia company. He saw action at the Battle
         of First Manassas on July 21 1861 under General Thomas
         "Stonewall" Jackson. On the battlefield he rendered medical
         aid to the wounded and, apparently upon reflection, decided
         that he could do more good as a physician than as a combatant.
         He applied to join the Physicians Corps and was commissioned
         as an Assistant Surgeon at the end of July 1861.</p>
      <p>In early September, Hunter received orders to establish a
         convalescent hospital in a house at Warm Springs, Virginia.
         For the next three months he hired nurses and cooks, tended to
         the sick, and completed the copious amounts of paperwork
         demanded by the Surgeon General's Office. In December 1861 he
         was appointed to inspect and inventory hospital property at
         the three small hospitals in Warm, Hot, and Healing Springs.
         They were apparently being closed.</p>
      <p>On January 19, 1862, Hunter received orders to immediately
         establish a hospital at Romney [present-day West Virginia]. He
         was told to prepare to receive many ill and wounded. On March
         11 General Jackson's brigade left Winchester and headed south.
         Hunter was re-assigned to Jackson's Forty-second Regiment of
         Virginia Volunteers as a field surgeon. He joined them at
         Strasburg and traveled with them throughout the famed Valley
         Campaign of March-May 1862. During this time he received his
         commission as a full surgeon in the Phyicians Corps.</p>
      <p>In June, Jackson was ordered to bring his troops to aid in
         Richmond's defense. Hunter's correspondence indicates that he
         was at Mechanicsville in June and Richmond in July. In August,
         after the Seven Days Battles had saved Richmond, Jackson's
         troops were sent northwest toward Culpeper County. On August
         9, Hunter was wounded at the Battle of Cedar Mountain, shot in
         the foot while administering first aid on the field. His
         recovery was slow; he was nursed primarily by an uncle in
         Richmond and was on furlough for a year.</p>
      <p>By the time he was re-assigned to duty in a hospital in
         Montgomery County, Virginia, in September 1863, his wife
         Sophie and four small children had become refugees. He moved
         them to Blacksburg, six miles from Montgomery Springs where
         the hospital was located. Although he was an assistant to the
         Chief Surgeon J. L. Woodville, he often served as the acting
         surgeon-in-charge during Woodville's absences. Animosity
         developed between the two, and, combined with his chronic
         disabled state from the foot wound, which rendered him unable
         to walk to town to visit his family, Hunter seemed at that
         time a disheartened man. He requested transfer twice, and was
         finally ordered to Bristol, Tennessee, to chair the Medical
         Examining Board for Conscripts in early May 1864. He remained
         there for several months and moved his family to Bristol.</p>
      <p>On December 14, 1864, Union General Stoneman and his men
         surprised Bristol and easily captured the town and its guards.
         All of the officers (including physicians) were captured and
         paroled, promising on their honor to travel to Knoxville for
         internment. Hunter, however, was too disabled to walk the
         distance and was allowed to remain behind with his family
         until the situation could be honorably resolved. This occurred
         when the Union and Confederate governments jointly determined
         that the parole was invalid, particularly for members of the
         Physicians' Corps, and the surgeons could return to duty with
         honor unimpaired.</p>
      <p>In early February 1865, Hunter was sent to chair the
         Medical Examining Board in Montgomery, Alabama, and on
         February 14 he boarded a train for Alabama. His journey was
         cut short, however, by General Sherman's march across South
         Carolina, and Hunter remained where he had been halted in
         North Carolina and was placed in charge of the Officers'
         Hospital in Raleigh, North Carolina, in late March. At the end
         of April the Union authorities now in command placed him in
         charge of the Confederate sick in Greensboro, North Carolina.
         On May 11, Hunter was at last relieved from duty; he
         immediately fell ill and did not leave for home until June 6.
         Hunter's war ended on June 16, when he took the new oath of
         allegience in Richmond and returned to private life.</p>
      <p>Hunter next appears in 1876, living and practicing medicine
         in Berkeley County, West Virginia. From 1876 to 1879 he was a
         member of the West Virginia Volunteer Militia. In 1880 he also
         became an examining physician for the Valley Mutual Life
         Insurance Company. His certificate from the State Board of
         Health is dated August 9, 1881, and in September 1881 he was
         one of three doctors appointed to the local board of health.
         Hunter had obviously become one of the area's more respected
         citizens, and was appointed a trustee of the town of Berkeley
         Springs in 1885.</p>
      <p>This collection contributes to the social history of the
         Civil War by presenting a non-combatant view of the war from a
         mid-echelon participant. Although as an officer and an
         educated man Hunter ought to have enjoyed a certain amount of
         power, he is nevertheless powerless to effect circumstances
         concerning his patients, family, or himself. The sense of
         personal and professional frustration appears in the
         correspondence towards the end of 1861, and gradually deepens
         to a sense of futility and despair. The collection is also
         useful for the light it sheds on the gradual disintegration of
         power and order within the Confederate war machine through its
         illustration of the collapse of structure within the field
         medical corps (although the Surgeon General's office churns
         out memoranda until the end). This, of course, parallels the
         disintegration of order in the military and civilian spheres
         as well.</p>
      <p>The collection is arranged chronologically and consists of
         varied official papers: requisitions and receipts for
         supplies, lists of patients, orders, commissions, memoranda;
         and military and personal correspondence between Hunter and
         officers and friends.</p>
      <p>Of particular value are the letters commending Hunter's
         behavior at the Battle of First Manassas and recommending him
         for a position in the Medical Corps (July 30, August 1,4,5,14,
         1861). These are evidence of the courtliness and code of honor
         held by the gentry in the antebellum period. Also of interest
         are a letter ordering him to establish a hospital in Romney
         (January 19, 1862) and correspondence between Hunter and
         Surgeon General Moore over the number of disabled soldiers
         Hunter was discharging from service (July 28, 1862).</p>
      <p>The correspondence concerning Hunter's request for a
         transfer because of personnel and health problems (March and
         April, 1864) and the correspondence over Hunter's capture and
         parole by General Stoneman in Bristol, Tennessee (December
         1864 and January 1865) particularly illustrate the waning
         fortunes of the Confederate cause and its followers. Also
         included in the collection is an 1864 memorandum from
         Jefferson Davis to Adjutant General Samuel Cooper.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
