<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01362">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01362::A Guide to the John Horn Saw Mill Letters)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01362.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01362::A Guide to the John Horn
             Saw Mill Letters)//EN" "viu01362.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the John Horn Saw Mill Letters 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.1852-1876</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Horn, John 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11289</num></subtitle><author>Special Collections Staff</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">24kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Leonard Sadosky, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.1852-1876</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01362::A Guide to the
            John Horn Saw Mill Letters)//EN" "viu01362.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the John Horn Saw Mill Letters 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.1852-1876</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession number">11289</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Letters 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         ca.1852-1876</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11289</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">There are four
         ledgers with loose financial papers.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>John Horn Saw Mill Papers, 1852-1876, Accession #11289,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These ledgers were purchased by the Library from
            Heartwood Books of Charlottesville, Virginia, on January
            27, 1997.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Papers of the Davis and Horn and related families
         (Accession #378) provide other information on the Horn,
         Firebaugh, and Anderson families. Jacob Horn had three
         children: John; Mary M., who married Robert B. Anderson; and,
         Rebecca, who married Benjamin F. Firebaugh. John Horn was the
         administrator of the estate of his brother-in-law, Robert B.
         Anderson; Anderson was the executor of the estate of Isaac
         Bryan.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are four ledgers with loose financial papers, ca.
         1852-1876, pertaining to the John Horn Saw Mill of Rockbridge
         Baths, Virginia. The ledgers list a variety of services and
         materials associated with the saw mill, including: sawing and
         making items such as pine, log gum, hickory logs, rabbets,
         plants, weatherboarding, poplar, posts, joist, fencing, white
         oak, bedsteads, plank wagon beds, laths, strips, walnut plank,
         smokehouse roof, cedar posts, shoestuff logs, drawboards logs,
         boulster stuff, houndstuff, window and door frames, portico
         sills, handrailing, shingles, and garden railing. Each ledger
         contains an index to the names listed in the accounts.</p>
      <p>Ledger #1 contains accounts for November 1853 through April
         1860. Names listed in the index include: Adams, Anderson,
         Bryan, Buchanan, Davis, Dickson, Firebaugh, Jordan, McCown,
         Perry, Randolph, Snider, Sterett, Taylor, and Whitmore. In
         addition to the accounts, there are records of work schedules
         and methods of payment in exchange for services rendered,
         including those for George Conner, James C. Snider, and Samuel
         Fulwider. There are also accounts for bushels of ears of corn
         (page 32), twist of tobacco (page 35), and bag thrash [of
         corn] (page 36).</p>
      <p>Ledger #2 contains accounts for April 1857 through December
         1861. Names listed in the index include: Adams, Anderson,
         Bryan, Buchanan, Cox, Davis, Horn, Howardsville Turnpike
         Company, Elliot, Firebaugh, Fulwider, Jordan, Mohler, McCown,
         McCurdy, Perry, Selby, Snider, Sterett, Taylor, Welch, West,
         and Wilson. In addition to the accounts, there are records of
         work schedules and methods of payment in exchange for services
         rendered. Jacob and Frederick Snider performed such services
         as working at the icehouse, making shingles, mowing,
         harvesting, thrashing and shucking corn, hauling rocks, and
         hauling hay. Samuel Fulwider settled his account by performing
         such services as hoeing and shucking corn, harvesting, cutting
         and putting up oats and hay, thrashing wheat, and hauling wood
         and rocks. H. A. Wilson settled his account by performing such
         services as sawing plaster, hauling logs, planting corn,
         harvesting, hauling grain, putting up oats and hay, plowing
         "Penoly," thrashing, seeding, and chopping wood. There are
         also several accounts with women: Mrs. Elizabeth H. Snider
         account (pages 14 and 34) for calico, cotton, stockings,
         shoes, and dress; Miss Betty West account (page 25) for goods,
         shoes, calico which she worked off through harvest; Miss
         Margaret Wiseman account (page 35); and, Mrs. Mary E.
         Buddlemyer account (page 35). There is an account for "School
         House Lumber" on page 26. The end of the ledger contains
         comments on weather and harvesting.</p>
      <p>Ledger #3 contains accounts for January 1862 through
         October 1867. Names listed in the index include: Australia
         Furnace, Rockford Bridge, Bethesda Sabbath School, Firebaugh,
         Fulwider, Mohler, McCown, Perry, Snider, Sterett, Taylor, and
         West. In addition to the accounts, there are records of work
         schedules and methods of payment in exchange for services
         rendered. Samuel and James Fulwider settled their accounts by
         performing such services as planting corn and wheat, hauling
         hay and oats, picking apples, and providing barrels of corn.
         Mrs. Elizabeth H. Snider settled her account by weaving cotton
         and providing cuts of woolen yarn and bunches of cotton.
         Andrew Snider settled his account by performing such services
         as planting corn, plowing, hauling wood, clipping sheep, and
         cutting wheat. On pages 9 and 11, there are accounts for work
         on the Rockford Bridge, September - November 1862; and, on
         page 14, there is a comment on the bridge at Rockbridge Baths,
         February 1863 - March 1864. There is a comment on the feeding
         of Lieutenant Sancy's horse, which was left by Sergeant Knapp
         to be kept one month, on October 28, 1863 (page 12). The
         Bethesda Sabbath School is mentioned on page 11 and at the end
         of the ledger. Miscellaneous comments are at the end of the
         ledger: weather December 31, 1867 - January 1, 1868; grain
         accounts for 1863 and 1865; records of killing a small beef,
         two wild hogs, and pork, and of providing deerskin and beef
         hides, October 1863 - January 1864; prices for articles
         purchased in Lynchburg, May 17, 1863; miscellaneous records of
         planting, harvesting, and cutting; comment on finishing the
         Rockford Bridge on November 5, 1862; comment that the
         Jefferson Davis Legion of Southern Troops came to Cove Run
         Camp on March 26, 1863; and, comment that the Rockford Bridge
         went off March 4, 1865 and that it stood for two years and
         five months.</p>
      <p>Ledger #4 contains accounts for January 1868 through
         December 1876. Names listed in the index include: Adams,
         Anderson, Brown, Bryan, Cochran, Cox, Davis, Firebaugh, Horn,
         Jordan, Kerrs Creek Township, Little, Mohler, McCown, McCurdy,
         Nutty, Perry, Snider, Sterett, Taylor, and Wilson. In addition
         to the accounts, there are records of work schedules and
         methods of payment in exchange for services rendered. Various
         members of the Snider family settled their accounts by
         performing services: Frederick Snider by sawing and thrashing;
         Andrew Snider by hauling and chopping logs, mowing, building
         plank fence, sawing, working at the apple house, clipping
         sheep, and mowing and putting up hay; George Snider by hauling
         logs and plank, mowing, hauling hay, plowing and hauling corn,
         working on the dam, working at the saw mill, making tar,
         thrashing, making cider and molasses, chopping and hauling
         wood, and, working at the steam mill. There are also numerous
         accounts for John Nutty with work schedules and methods of
         payment for services rendered and for rent at "Penoly." Nutty
         performed such services as thrashing, working in the dam,
         planting corn, shucking and hauling corn, chopping and hauling
         wood, making shingles, building fence, hauling hay and wheat,
         harvesting wheat, mowing, sawing shingles, hauling rocks and
         logs, mowing, and picking apples. There is an account for
         William Cochran Coloured (page 48). The end of the ledger
         holds notes on Bethesda Parsonage concerning a series of
         meetings held by Rev. C. M. Howard from September 3 - 27, 1874
         and a sacramental meeting held on October 18, 1874. There are
         also weather comments for February 7 and April 17, 1875. There
         is a note concerning Confederate money received from James W.
         Brown, administrator of Margaret Brown, for Horn's three
         children, Lizzy, Mary, and Emerson, on January 16, 1863,
         signed by John Horn. At the end is also a commentary on a
         great flood of September 28, 1870 and a comment on the weather
         for December 23, 1870. Weather and harvesting comments
         follow.</p>
      <p>Business papers removed from the ledgers consist chiefly of
         accounts and accounts settled. From ledger #2 are items of
         note: an account, October 31, 1853, for Mary Tripinger, for
         calico, cotton, gingham, and cashmere gloves; a list of
         appletrees in rows named Fallow Water, Bellflour, Johnstons,
         and Paradise, March 1859; and, a note to "Miss Kittie"
         containing the names and addresses of three women -- Isidore
         Anderson, Lizzie S. Rule, and Virginia I. Anderson. From
         ledger #3 are items of note: an account, February - December
         1861, of John Horn with Andrew Cox [blacksmith]; an account,
         November 15, 1867 - February 8, 1868, of John Horn with S. L.
         McDowell, dealer in groceries, dry goods, and hardware;
         Rockford Bridge Committee receipts for October 1, 1868; and, a
         resolution pertaining to Bethesda Sunday School. From ledger
         #4 are items of note: 1890 Tax for John Horn to the treasurer
         of Rockbridge County; and, a letter, June 25, 1890, from Ida
         Horn to "Clara" discussing the arrangements for the numerous
         boarders coming to the mountains for the summer.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e192">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Boxed Ledgers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e196">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Ledger #2 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1857 Apr - 1861
                  Dec</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e202">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Ledger #4 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868 Jan - 1876
                  Dec</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e208">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Ledger business papers
                  removed 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 -
                  1890</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e214">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Oversize Ledgers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e218">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Ledger #1 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Nov - 1860
                  Apr</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries" id="d1e224">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Horn Saw Mill Ledger #3 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862 Jan - 1867
                  Oct</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
