<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04079">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04079::A Guide to the World War II Letters of Joseph J. Jania)//EN" "viu04079.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the World War II Letters of Joseph J. Jania </titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Jania, Joseph J., Letters 
                    <num type="collectionnumber">13832</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the World War II Letters of Joseph J. Jania </titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">13832</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">World War II Letters of Joseph J. Jania
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">13832</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">70 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector"/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p> There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>World War II Letters of Joseph J. Jania, Accession #13832, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The letters were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Charles Apfelbaum, 2007 Feb.27.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of seventy letters, July 23-October 12, 1944, of Joseph J.
                Jania to his wife [Florence?] in Chicago, Illinois, while he was stationed at Fort
                Belvoir, Virginia. Jania describes his life and daily activities at Fort Belvoir
                while he was a member of Student Company H, S.S.R. Jania was enrolled in the Map
                Reproduction Course, Engineer School. He had previously been stationed at Camp
                Gruber, Oklahoma, before his transfer.</p>
      <p>According to their website about historic Belvoir, "In March 1941, the Engineer
                Replacement Training Center facility began to provide basic military engineer
                training to draftees. Originally, the ERTC program was designed as a 12 week course,
                but its duration was shortened to eight weeks early in 1942, when the demand for
                troops escalated dramatically after Pearl Harbor. A similar curriculum was offered
                at the ERTCs at Fort Leonard Wood in Missouri and later at Camp Abbot in Oregon.
                Recruits were schooled in reconnaissance, unit coordination, road and obstacle
                construction, and demolition. After mid-1942, Belvoir began training engineer
                specialists in operating construction machinery, carpentry, drafting, and surveying.
                Instruction also was offered for such non-engineering specialties as truck driving,
                cooking, and baking. As the war progressed and new weapons were developed,
                specialized courses in weapons operation were added to the curriculum. Engineers
                learned about tanks and their uses, flamethrowers, and anti-aircraft guns. By the
                end of the war in 1945, the ERTC at Fort Belvoir had trained roughly 147,000
                engineer troops (http://www.belvoir.army.mil/default.asp).</p>
      <p>Activities mentioned in the first folder of Jania's letters include: learning to read
                maps (July 26); plans to sneak out and see Mt. Vernon (July 30 and 31); taking
                photographs both speed action and stills (August 1, 3); difficulties with arranging
                wife visitations (August 5); lists his fellow students, most experts in lithography,
                plate making or photography (August 6); and his progress in learning photography
                (August 8).</p>
      <p>Topics in the second folder of letters include: work on the copy camera (August 14,
                16); receipt of rifles (August 16); wife has a job now (August 19); worries about
                tuberculosis (August 20); believes that most of the units have moved out of Camp
                McCoy, where he had been previously (August 21); after four weeks of study, he finds
                out that Map Reproduction 65 [his group] has the best marks (August 22); and he
                misses the Polka dances with her (August 23).</p>
      <p>Third folder subjects include his plans on going to see Washington, D.C. on the
                weekend and a comment about Eleanor Roosevelt that she should stay home and send all
                the money she spends traveling around to soldiers' wives so they could visit their
                husbands (August 26); discusses his trip to Washington, D.C. which did not impress
                him (August 27); learning to do lay-out jobs and hints for a chocolate cake (August
                29); studying plate [graining] (August 30-31); rumors that his company will move out
                the first week of October and go to either Texas or Indiana (September 5); he is
                impressed with her knowledge of the presses (September 6); and he has received
                pointers from a professional photographer on how to take the best nude pictures
                (September 9).</p>
      <p>The topics in folder four include: gratitude for the nice dictionary sent by her
                parents; being in charge of one of the press groups; and news of the organization
                moving to Fort Riley, Kansas, soon after September15, 1944, reporting to his company
                upon completion of his course (September 11); did really well on his process plate
                making test (September 12); interest in the Harris Press school (September 15);
                feels like he is becoming a very good pressman (September 16); prices for beer,
                milk, and other items (September 17); and the news that Jania was chosen as one of
                the top five honor students to attend a special dance in Washington, D.C. (September
                23).</p>
      <p>The subjects in the fifth folder include: his visit to Master Sergeant King's home
                for extra information on lithography (September 24, 1st letter); his recollection of meeting her in September 1937
                (September 24, 2nd letter); working out in the field
                today, wearing leggings and gas mask at all times (September 25); working on a
                special letterhead for himself and wife (September 26); preparations for and
                attendance at the special Wave dance in Washington, D.C. (September 27-28); receipt
                of a twelve day delay-en-route permission when they travel from Fort Belvoir to Fort
                Riley, although he will have to pay to travel from St. Louis to Chicago (October 2);
                Sergeant King going overseas and he had asked Jania and Diedrich to join his new
                outfit (October 3); will live outdoors for three days under battle conditions and
                eating K rations and describes his appetite for food (October 7); all of the map
                reproduction guys marched to church on their last Sunday at Fort Belvoir and then
                played ping pong with the chaplain (October [8?]); and describes his final test
                (October 11).</p>
    </bioghist>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
