<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01602">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01602::A Guide to the Letters of Adolph Morbio)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01602.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01602::A Guide to the Letters of
             Adolph Morbio)//EN" "viu01602.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of Adolph Morbio 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1919</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Morbio, Adolph Letters, 1917-1919 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10875-ab</num></subtitle><author>Special Collections Staff</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">31 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Sue Cuthbertson, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8/14/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01602::A Guide to the
            Letters of Adolph Morbio)//EN" "viu01602.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of Adolph Morbio 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1919</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Joseph M. Bruccoli Great War Collection 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10875-ab</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>The Letters of Adolph Morbio 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1917-1919</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10875-ab</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">132
         items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains a carbon
         letterbook kept by Adolph Morbio while stationed at the Second
         Engineer Officer Training Camp, Vancouver Barracks,
         Washington, Sept. 6, 1917-Nov. 27, 1917, and carbon copies of
         letters, 1917-1919, describing his service in
         France.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Adolph Morbio, Letters, 1917-1919, in the Joseph M.
            Bruccoli Great War Collection, Accession #10875-ab, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the University of
            Virginia Library from Charles Apfelbaum, Rare Books and
            Collections, Valley Stream, New York, on September 24,
            1994.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Morbio was a graduate of the California School of
         Mechanical Arts (1908) and a Mechanical Engineering graduate
         of Cornell University (1913), with a Certificate in Electrical
         Engineering. After graduation, he worked for the Engineering
         Department of the Panama-Pacific Exposition for a year, and
         then went to work for the Great Western Power Company for two
         years in charge of Industrial and Domestic Electric Heating
         Department for the San Francisco District. At the time Morbio
         entered the service, he was in business for himself in
         building construction.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The earliest part of this collection consists of a
         handwritten carbon letterbook kept by Adolph Morbio, a member
         of Company "B", 115th Engineers, Pioneer Regiment, while
         stationed at the Second Engineer Officer Training Camp,
         Vancouver Barracks, Washington, from September 6, 1917, until
         the camp closed on November 27, 1917. Morbio had transferred
         to Vancouver from Camp Kearny, located about seventeen miles
         from San Diego, California, and begins his correspondence with
         a description of the camp and its routine to his sister on
         September 6.</p>
      <p>The letters in the letterbook are chiefly written to his
         family and friends but do include a few letters concerning
         bills and business affairs. All of the letters emphasize the
         rigorous and tight training schedule of the camp created to
         produce engineering officers capable of serving with the
         Infantry on the front lines or as staff officers depending on
         the need.</p>
      <p>Subjects in the letterbook include: a typical schedule, the
         probability of being assigned to an Infantry Regiment,
         vaccinations, and his regret that his brother, Carlo Morbio,
         is going with a machine gun company (Sep 9); his lack of free
         time (Sep 9); his experiences in drilling his men, the hikes
         and training (Sep 13); list of the seventeen volumes he has to
         master for his formal exams to become an officer and his fears
         in drilling his company (Sep 15); he holds the provisional
         commission of a West Point cadet (Sep 16); his progress in
         training, his difficulty with the semaphore classes, and the
         practice skirmish which was extremely physically demanding
         (Sep 22); the soldiers feel ignored by the people of Portland
         and Vancouver (Sep 25); Portland finally furnishes some
         entertainment for the soldiers at the Hotel Multnomah (Sep 30
         &amp; Oct 3); his study of mapping, infantry drill, and his
         experiences drilling his company (Oct 7); new work of making
         brush mats for the walls of trenches, drilling on the Columbia
         River in pontoon boats, and cutting brush with large Bowie
         knives (Oct 9); learning knots and hitches for bridge
         construction, his participation in the mock battle near a
         cornfield, involving the capture of barns, wood piles, etc.
         without prior explanation to the farmers (Oct 14); comments
         concerning army regulations, "Army Regulations is quite a
         volume and we have gone over it quite thoroughly. It
         prescribes and prohibits everything that everybody in the Army
         has been able to think of since the time of George Washington"
         (Oct 18); his work at the shooting range (Nov 5, 6, &amp; 7);
         a dance in Portland and his stay at the hotel (Nov 11); and
         news that the Vancouver Barracks are to close on November 27th
         when he will come home on leave for a few days (Nov 14).</p>
      <p>The rest of the collection consists of about 115 carbon
         copies (with some duplication), 1917-1919, of Morbio's letters
         to family and friends just prior to his departure overseas and
         during his tour of duty supervising the construction of
         electrical installations at Tours, France. Subjects in these
         letters include: the purchase of a Corona typewriter for
         Christmas to take with him overseas and his visit to the
         residential areas of Los Angeles (1917 Dec 25); and his
         explanation that the 115th Regiment of Engineers is a National
         Guard Unit of Pioneer Troops that goes ahead to build advance
         railroad lines and other preliminary work, his present work as
         the 2nd Platoon Leader, his scare concerning a soldier who
         experienced an epileptic seizure while under his command in
         the desert where they were attempting to assemble a railroad
         trestle, and the location of Camp Kearny about 17 miles from
         San Diego on a flat plain in the desert (1917 Dec 31).</p>
      <p>Morbio begins his letters of 1918 with the news that he has
         contracted the German measles and must remain in isolation for
         two weeks at the Base Hospital (Jan 2 &amp; 5); describes a
         brief "escape" from hospital quarantine to La Jolla without
         leave (Jan 6); includes "Beating the Submarines" (1918 Jan)
         which describes his trip overseas from New York to England on 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Philadelphia</title>, one of the
         American Line ships, and Boat Number 351 of the American
         Transport Service, departing on January 27th according to a
         later letter (May 22); his assignment with the Office of the
         Chief Engineer, Service of the Rear, A.E.F., France (Feb 17);
         mentions his lack of assignment and his congenial
         circumstances (Feb 24); reports that he has been ill, does not
         find French women attractive at close range, and mentions that
         the Americans are doing valuable civilian work as well as war
         preparation, such as operating street cars (Mar 4); has
         finally received mail from home and is busy with electrical
         work which consists of "getting power, designing, installing,
         and purchasing materials for wiring, and installing electrical
         apparatus" (Mar 7); and describes his earlier stay at the
         English and French "Rest Camps" and the trip over to France
         (Mar 10).</p>
      <p>Subjects in additional letters include: the promotion of
         his brother Carlo S. Morbio, U.S.N.A., 166th Depot Brigade,
         10th Battalion, 37th Company, Camp Lewis, American Lake,
         Washington, to 1st Lt. (Carlo had attended the 1st Training
         Camp at the Presidio), the inferiority of French cement which
         causes delays in the work, the good work of the Y.M.C.A. in
         France, and includes two poems about life in the Great War,
         "Recollections A.E.F." and "The Service of the Rear" (Mar 19);
         his new work being in charge of all electrical work in a
         factory (Mar 24); the name of his department changed to
         Department of Construction and Forestry, Service of Supplies
         (Mar 29 &amp; Apr 14); urges his mother not to worry about the
         affairs of the store until after the war (Apr 16); furnishes a
         detailed description of the floating bathhouse at the [Loire
         River] where they bath periodically (Apr 22); a letter to
         Major Van Zile details Morbio's educational and practical
         experience (May 5); his "Mother's Day" letter sent express by
         the government (May 6); describes his work in detail and the
         need for liberal use of improvisation to get the job done (May
         10 &amp; 25); now is allowed to tell his family that he is in
         Tours, France (May 18); and gives his opinion concerning the
         various types of cars in use for war work, the best being the
         Cadillac, the huge demand for more electricity, and the
         superior hospitals now being built for the wounded (May
         24).</p>
      <p>Other topics include: his description of the increase in
         work with the second offensive under way and his methods of
         avoiding red tape and getting results (Jun 10); his visit to a
         French chateau near the Cher River at Tours, hearing the
         Cavalry Band playing for nearly 2,500 employees (French women)
         on Saturday at one of the places where he was installing
         electrical systems (Jun 23); the combined celebration with the
         French of July 4th &amp; 14th and a few social events with
         French families (Jul 4); his visit to the Chateau of Chinon
         (Jul 8); his visit to Paris during Bastille Day, the new
         offensive apparently going well, sugar seems to be the only
         commodity lacking in Paris, description of the extent of his
         work building electric power plants in Tours, the necessity of
         swiping materials from plumbers and the steam men, avoiding
         red tape, and building without taking time to design (Jul 19,
         22, &amp; 28); furnishes an itinerary of his trip overseas
         back in January, arriving in Liverpool six months ago on
         February 4, reaching Havre on February 7, and describes his
         various assignments since his arrival in Europe when Tours
         became the General Headquarters of the whole Service of
         Supplies and continued to grow, gives his impressions of Major
         General Langfitt, Chief Engineer as a guest for lunch (with no
         warning!), and his present work on a P.O.W. camp electric
         transmission line to accommodate the influx of German
         prisoners (Aug 4); Morbio has almost completed his 11th
         installation and is ready to begin work on three more jobs,
         most of his men were physically unfit for duty or wounded, his
         appreciation for the work of the men at the front, and the
         success of the American offensive at [St. Mihiel ?] (Sep 7
         &amp; 15); description of the wedding of Carlo Morbio by Frank
         R. Wehe (Sep 17); his promotion to Captain a few days ago (Oct
         20); his new job at Headquarters, Section Engineer, Gievres
         (Loire-et-Cher) near Romorantin (Nov 10); description of the
         American Intermediate Salvage Depot at St. Pierre des Corps,
         near Tours, one of his big electrical jobs, describing in
         detail the procedure of sorting the salvage material for
         reclamation, such as clothing and shoes, and a discussion of
         the chances he had to take to meet the urgent need for more
         electricity (Nov 24); his general disappointment with France
         as a country and the marital difficulties of his sister
         married to a Frenchman (1918 Dec 16; 1919 Jan 5 &amp; 12); his
         impressions of President Woodrow Wilson visit to Paris (Dec
         20); and the monotony of life now that the war is over and the
         death of his former roommate's wife on Christmas Eve (Dec
         29).</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
