<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04039">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04039::A Guide to the Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, 1928-1954)//EN" "viu04039.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1954</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">McCasland, S. Vernon, Additional Papers of
<num type="collectionnumber">12755
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by jbo3d, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/10/09</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1954</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">12755
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1954
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">12755
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">The collection consists of about 329 items. (two Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot.)
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Additional Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, Accession #12755, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The papers were the gift of Miss Roy Land, 1989, March 10.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Selby Vernon McCasland (1896-1970), the John B. Cary Memorial Professor of Religion at the University of Virginia, was from Comanche, Texas where he attended Hardin-Simmons College (A.B. 1918) and the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary (Th.B. 1922). He was awarded the A.M. in 1924 and the Ph.D. in 1926, both from the University of Chicago. He also studied at Universities in Germany from 1926 to 1927. Prior to his arrival at the University of Virginia, he taught at Abilene Christian College, Goucher College, and the American School of Oriental Research in Jerusalem. 
</p>
      <p>He married Louise Gaston in 1928 and they had two children. McCasland enjoyed great popularity among his students at the University, and he was deeply involved in University life. The YMCA in particular came under his direction periodically and benefited greatly from his enthusiasm and dedication. His academic interests included Biblical scholarship and philosophy of religion. He was a member of the Disciples of Christ Church and various learned societies. His death in 1970 came just three years after his retirement from the University faculty. He taught religion at the University of Virginia from 1939 to 1967. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The Papers of S. Vernon McCasland, Professor of Religion at the University of Virginia, contain theology lectures, and information from the Young Men Christian's Association at the University of Virginia, including Board of Director correspondence, minutes, finances, insurance, notes on the history of the University of Virginia, and leases and repairs for Dawson's Row from 1920 to 1965. The correspondence includes a letter from Daniel L. Gibbes to President Colgate Darden about the YMCA sponsoring the State Wesley Foundation Conference, if it was to be held as a meeting of Christian College Students and not as an interracial meeting. 
</p>
      <p>There are also notebooks containing accounts, travel notes, archaeology notes, a photo album of University of Virginia students and faculty and a scrapbook containing clippings about the Scopes trial with Clarence Darrow and William Jennings Bryan, an editorial about the trial by George Bernard Shaw, clippings about various events of the day including the gangster shootings of Angelo Genna, and a clipping about President and Mrs. Calvin Coolidge, Jr. Also in the scrapbook are programs for sermons of S. V. McCasland in 1924 and a program for the farewell address of [his father,] James Murl McCasland at Johnstown Colorado in 1925. The scrapbook has several signatures including Warren P. Blodgett, Harold H. Titua; Arthur L. Dickinson; E W Jones; W. E. Garrsion; E. M. Stunnard; Frank S. Ware; and Earl J. Sechler; and a clipping about the funeral service for University of Chicago President Ernest DeWitt Burton. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e138">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Theology lectures of Selby Vernon McCasland on <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Problems of Happiness and The Christian View of Sin, Grace and Salvation.</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1964
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
          <physdesc>6 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included with the lectures are three programs for McCaslands' lectures for the University of Virginia Christian Association at Madison Hall and a news clipping about them.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e155">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Board of Directors
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1964
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
          <physdesc>45 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included are University of Virginia YMCA Board of Directors minutes, lease agreements, nominations, biographical sketches, and general information about seminars and activities. Correspondents include S. A. Mitchell, George B. Zehmer, Raymond S. Edmundson, Daniel L. Gibbes, Jr., Vincent Shea, Edward E. Younger, T. Graham Hereford, Francis H. Fife, B. F. D. Runk, Lawrence R. Quarles, Ralph W. Cherry, Donald M. McKay, the Reverend Peter Braun, S. H. O'Grince, Edward R. Slaughter, Charles E. Moran, Jr., Charles W. Smith, Marvin B. Perry, Jr., Harold Colvin, F. Rogers-Jones, and John P. MacCallum.
</p>
          <p>There is also a letter from Daniel L. Gibbes to President Colgate Darden about the YMCA sponsoring the State Wesley Foundation Conference, if it was held as a meeting of Christian College Students and not as an interracial meeting.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e171">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA: #3 and #4 Dawson's Row 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
          <physdesc>54 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are letters, bills, receipts, and rental agreements pertaining to the YMCA properties, number three and number four Dawson's Row. Some of the correspondents are Vincent Shea, C. R. West, Mr. and Mrs. Howard Turner, Mrs. C. H. Kauffman, S. Vernon McCasland,Daniel L. Gibbes and T. Graham Hereford.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e185">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Finance Committee Correspondence 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1958
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
          <physdesc>72 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include University of President Colgate W. Darden, Jr., James F. Minor, Carrie B. Deane, Trust Accountant, The Peoples National Bank; Francis H. Fife, Trust Investment Officer, The Peoples National Bank; Cornelia D. Nuckols, The Peoples National Bank; Vincent Shea, Comptroller, University of Virginia YMCA; James Harry Michael, Jr.; Charles K. Woltz; Oscar B. Wooldridge, Jr., Mrs. Mary Hudson Hayward; Mr. Jay F. Waters; Richard R. Fletcher; Myron S. Miller; Jack Dalton, Mrs. Ralph Miller; Leander McCormick, George B. Zehmer, D. Clark Hyde, W. F. Souder, Wyatt C. Wood, and B. F. D. Runk. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e199">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Finance Committee Documents 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1958
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
          <physdesc>74 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>By-laws, financial statements and lease for Madison Hall. Included is a letter from President Colgate Darden concerning a $2500.00 annual rent for Madison Hall.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e213">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Correspondence-Financial Insurance
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1950
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
          <physdesc>30 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondents include Francis H. Fife, The Peoples National Bank; Vincent Shea, comptroller, University of Virginia YMCA; James F. Minor, Minor-Duke Mutual; W. F. Souder, Hanckel-Citizens Insurance Corporation; Wyatt C. Wood, Virginia Insurance rating Bureau; Carrie B. Deane, The Peoples National Bank; S. Vernon McCasland. The correspondence is about insurance policies for properties such as Madison Hall.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e227">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA - General File 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955-1957 
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
          <physdesc>16 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting minutes, annual report and budget information; Handwritten notes for the University Handbook; Biographical sketches of other ministers; and printed information such as a church program from the University Chapel, brochures on the University YMCA and a program for the Boy's Club Banquet.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Notes on the History of the University YMCA 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
</container>
          <physdesc>3 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are handwritten notes on the plans and history of the University of Virginia YMCA including proposed by-laws.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Program Committee Records
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1965
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
</container>
          <physdesc>3 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e266">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA Property Committee Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1965
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
</container>
          <physdesc>4 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e278">
        <did>
          <unittitle>University of Virginia YMCA - Contact with Oscar B. Woodridge, Jr. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946-1949
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
</container>
          <physdesc>5 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e289">
        <did>
          <unittitle>YMCA - Printed Matter 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
</container>
          <physdesc>8 items.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e300">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Scrapbook
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920-1925
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>News clippings about Clarence Darrow and William Jennings Bryan during the Scopes evolution trial; editorial by George Bernard Shaw about the trial; Programs for sermons of Evangelist S. V. McCasland ,1924 and program for the farewell address of James Murl McCasland at Johnstown Colorado 1925; More news clippings and articlesle about President and Mrs. Coolidge; article about gangster shooting of Angelo Genna; Several signatures including Warren P. Blodgett, Harold H. Titua; Arthur L. Dickinson; E W Jones; W. E. Garrsion; E. M. Stunnard; Frank S. Ware; and Earl J. Sechler; and a news clipping about the funeral service for University of Chicago President Ernest DeWitt Burton.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e314">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Grade Book [Goucher College]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e325">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Article titled, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="doublequote" xlink:href="">Crediting Bible Study in the Schools</title> by W. M. Forrest from the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Normal Bulletin</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e342">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal of accounts, expenses and family history
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="file" id="d1e353">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal with notes on archaeology
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937-1939
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e364">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Journal with notes on travels
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e375">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photo Album
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e386">
        <did>
          <unittitle>German Notebook
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="box" type="box">2
</container>
          <physdesc>1 item.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
