<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03360">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03360::A Guide to the Papers of Robert Watson Claiborne)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03360.xml" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03360::A Guide to the Papers of
             Robert Watson Claiborne)//EN" "viu03360.xml</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert Watson
            Claiborne 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1966</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Claiborne, Robert Watson, Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">4572-a</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2012 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Mark Hayek, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/07/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03360::A Guide to the
            Papers of Robert Watson Claiborne)//EN" "viu03360.xml
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">February 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert Watson Claiborne 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1966</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Libraryt 
         <num type="Accession Number">4572-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2012
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Robert Watson Claiborne 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1934-1966</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">4572-a</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 9600 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Robert Watson Claiborne, Accession #4572-a,
            Special Collections, University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The papers were a gift of Virginia (McKenney) Claiborne,
            wife of Robert Watson Claiborne, of Richmond, Virginia, in
            May 1976 through Mrs. Ralph T. Catterall and Mrs. D. M.
            Lemmon, also of Richmond. The papers are an addition to the
            papers of Dr. John Herbert Claiborne (1828-1905), accession
            no. 4572, given by Mrs. Claiborne in 1953.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Robert Watson Claiborne was born in Petersburg, Virginia,
         in 1888, the son of Dr. John Herbert Claiborne and Annie
         (Watson) Claiborne. He graduated from the University of
         Virginia in 1909 with a B.A., and received an M.A. from
         Princeton and a LL.B. from Columbia University School of Law.
         He served as a captain in the Marine Corps in World War I. In
         1918, he married Virginia Spotswood McKenney of Petersburg,
         Virginia and they had two children, Robert W. Claiborne, Jr.,
         (Bob) born 1919, and a daughter, Clara, born 1923. Virginia
         (McKenney) Claiborne was director of the Valentine Museum in
         Richmond until 1957.</p>
      <p>Claiborne taught at various boys' schools in the east, such
         as Groton (Massachusetts) School, where he was head of the
         English Department in 1910-1911. From about 1918 to 1926, he
         practiced law in Richmond, Virginia, New York, and England,
         and was connected with several law firms and corporations, his
         specialty being international and admiralty law and Latin
         American affairs. He was also active in musical activities,
         including radio programs and teaching music in the late
         1920's.</p>
      <p>In April 1934, Claiborne sailed to the Virgin Islands,
         where he practiced law and began a business preserving fruits
         in rum. His son Robert and a former pupil, James Robertson,
         accompanied him, while his wife and daughter remained in
         Virginia on a permanent basis. While in the Virgin Islands,
         Claiborne became active in local political and civic affairs.
         He successfully represented the Virgin Islands Teachers
         Association in a suffrage case, in which women won equal
         rights in the Virgin Islands.</p>
      <p>In July 1936, after investigating the feasibility of a
         preserved fruit business in Puerto Rico, he sold his business
         in the Virgin Islands, and moved to Puerto Rico that fall,
         settling near Mayaguez, a city on the Northwest part of the
         island. He set up a farm business, practiced law, and became
         involved in Puerto Rico's political and economic life,
         particularly in labor activities. In October 1938, Claiborne
         was appointed regional attorney and acting territorial
         representative in Puerto Rico of the Wage and Hour Division of
         the U.S. Department of Labor, becoming the first administrator
         in Puerto Rico under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938.</p>
      <p>Claiborne's term in office was brief and controversial. He
         was viewed as a liberal reformer and was popular with labor
         leaders but his attempts to strictly enforce the Wage and Hour
         Law made him unpopular with some business and political
         interests, in the needlework, sugar, and tobacco industries in
         particular. A March 14, 1939, letter from Elmer F. Andrews,
         adminstrator of the Wage and Hour Division in Washington,
         informed Claiborne that his "resignation" had been accepted.
         Claiborne contended that he had never resigned, and that a
         personal letter of March 2, 1939, had been misinterpreted in
         order to remove him from office. He claimed that many
         officials favored business interests, and pressure from these
         interests had resulted in his removal.</p>
      <p>During his term in office, Claiborne's activities included
         the investigation of employee and union complaints of
         violations, interpreting the meaning of the law to employers
         and employees, speaking to meetings of labor groups, and
         corresponding about general policy and about specific
         cases.</p>
      <p>The suit by the Eastern Sugar Associates against Claiborne
         and a group of employees, begun in February 1939, sought to
         prohibit them from enforcing the Wage and Hour Law and was the
         first suit filed against the law. The suit sought a judgement
         that the employees in the sugar industry were engaged in
         agricultural work, and therefore exempt from the law. Also at
         this time, there was an attempt in Congress to exempt Puerto
         Rico from the Fair Labor Standards Act through the Norton
         Amendment. This was fought by labor unions and others, such as
         Representative Vito Marcantonio of New York. In February and
         March 1939, the economist Isador Lobin was in Puerot Rico to
         investigate conditions.</p>
      <p>By the end of March 1939, Claiborne had become discouraged
         about the possibility of enforcing the law; there were many
         violators who were not punished and who had an unfair
         advantage over companies who did observe the minimum wage law.
         He felt that the government was lagging in bringing companies
         to court. At the end of March, after his "resignation,"
         Claiborne formed a law partnership with Gutierrez Franqui and
         Ramos Antonini, to handle labor cases first through mediation
         and through the courts if necessary. Claiborne hoped that
         through private legal action, unions and employees could force
         enforcement of the law. Many of the firm's cases were won, but
         at the same time, during the summer and fall of 1939,
         Claiborne heard rumors attempting to discredit him and his
         character, and of a move by employers to disbar him, which he
         claimed were intended to hold up or stop suits against
         employers. He felt, as he had in the Virgin Islands in his
         suffrage fight, that he was fighting a "machine."</p>
      <p>The Ades case, a suit filed in July 1939 by employees, with
         Claiborne as their lawyer, against the Ades brothers company,
         resulted in allegations against Claiborne and an investigation
         of his personal conduct in 1940. At issue was the authority of
         Claiborne to represent his plaintiffs, and the propriety of
         his professional conduct in the possible use of information
         gained while in his government later in his private practice.
         There were also allegations that in his correspondence with
         industrialists, he had sold the workers out in a conspiracy.
         Claiborne charged that there were no specific charges against
         him, that witnesses against him had been bribed, signatures
         forged, and that Judge Robert Cooper had been fed false
         information and irrelevant evidence. By the end of February
         1940, Claiborne was given a choice by Judge Cooper: he could
         resign from the bar or be disbarred. Upon refusing, he was
         then told that he could resign from the labor cases he was
         representing, which he also refused to do. In February 1940,
         Judge Cooper then gave the case to Rafael De La Haba, a
         lawyer, to investigate and report on. In July 1940, Claiborne
         was suspended from the practice of law for a period of a year,
         beginning December 1, 1940, or earlier if his cases were
         finished. Claiborne appealed the suspension, but in May 1941,
         the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in Boston denied his
         appeal.</p>
      <p>After 1940-1941, Claiborne became even more discouraged
         about improving labor conditions and he concentrated his
         efforts on his farm, Hacienda Santa Rita. On this abandoned
         coffee farm in the mountains above Mayaguez and near Maricao,
         he began a series of agricultural experiments to develop a
         cash crop to replace coffee, which was no longer profitable in
         the area. He raised animals such as goats and chickens, and
         grew fruits, vegetables and flowers. He helped train and
         educate young men who worked on the farm, and when he died on
         August 6, 1966 of hypoglycemia, the farm was left as a trust,
         run by two of these young men.</p>
      <p>During the 1940's, 1950's, and 1960's, Claiborne made the
         acquaintance of many interesting individuals who came to visit
         him at his farm and with whom he corresponded, such as Nathan
         Leopold (of Leopold and Loeb fame); some Communists such as
         Richard Levins, Mary Craig Speed, Jane Speed, and husband
         Cesar Andrea, and government officials, university professors,
         lawyers, farmers, business men and others mentioned in the
         description of the papers. Also, especially in the early
         1940's and early 1950's Claiborne's letters reflect an
         atmosphere of suspicion and indicate that he felt he was often
         being investigated for radical activities, possibly partially
         due to confusing Claiborne with his son of the same name.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The papers of Robert Watson Claiborne from 1934 to 1966
         contain chiefly correspondence while Claiborne was a lawyer,
         government official, and experimental farmer in the Virgin
         Islands (1934-1936) and Puerto Rico (1936-1966). There is also
         a small amount of other material such as miscellaneous
         financial papers, memorabilia, photographs, circulars, press
         releases, newsclippings, and a speech and legal document
         relating to a 1936 Virgin Islands suffrage case. Claiborne was
         involved in political, economic and agricultural affairs, and
         was particularly interested in labor activities in Puerto
         Rico. He was acting territorial representative and regional
         attorney in Puerto Rico for the Wage and Hour Division of the
         U.S. Department of Labor from November 1938 to March 1939.</p>
      <p>The correspondence is chiefly composed of long, detailed,
         opinionated letters from Claiborne to his wife, Virginia
         (McKenney) Claiborne, who was usually in Richmond, Virginia.
         The letters provide a diary-like account of his activities,
         and often concern personal matters, especially his health,
         financial and legal matters. They also contain his views on
         politics, labor activities, living conditions, and social life
         in the Virgin Islands and Puerto Rico. He often enclosed his
         correspondence with others in letters to his wife, and there
         is a particularly large amount of Claiborne's official
         correspondence while in the Wage and Hour post which helps
         illuminate the relationship between Puerto Rico and Washington
         during the New Deal.</p>
      <p>Claiborne (nicknamed "Parjo") corresponded with his wife,
         (nicknamed "Mana" or "Bala"), with their son "Bob" and
         daughter-in-law Adrienne, their daughter Clara, Claiborne's
         mother, Mrs. John Herbert Claiborne, family-friend James
         Robertson ("Jimmie"), and lawyer and advisor Arnold Knauth.
         Some of Virginia (McKenney) Claiborne's correspondence with
         others on behalf of Claiborne, usually in financial and legal
         matters, is included, such as a few letters to and from
         Senator Harry F. Byrd in 1942, 1943, and 1950.</p>
      <p>In addition to personal and family correspondence, there is
         correspondence of Claiborne on political, economic,
         agricultural, and labor matters with U.S. and Puerto Rican
         government officials, labor leaders, industrialists, lawyers,
         politicians, agriculturalists, and others active in Virgin
         Islands and Puerto Rican affairs. There is occasional
         correspondence with Virgin Islands government officials during
         1934-1936, including one or two letters from Governors
         Lawrence Cramer and Paul M. Pearson.</p>
      <p>Individuals active in Puerto Rican affairs who have
         substantial amounts of correspondence with Claiborne include
         Ruby A. Black, ("R"), a Washington newspaperwoman, unofficial
         lobbyist, and friend of Luis Munoz Martin; Vito Marcantonio
         ("Marc"), a representative in congress from New York; Earl
         Parker Hanson, writer, consultant and government official; and
         Walter McK. Jones, a writer (all on the Committee for Fair
         Play to Puerto Rico). Also, George Warrek, professor of
         English at the University of Puerto Rico and Paul Schumm, a
         visiting planner. U.S. Government officials with whom
         Claiborne corresponded, especially during his term in office,
         include A. Cecil Snyder, U.S. Attorney for San Juan; Elmer F.
         Andrews, Administrator of the Wage and Hour Division; Arthur
         L. Fletcher, Assistant Administrator; Paul Sifton, Deputy
         Administrator; and John Babe, Wage and Hour Attorney. There is
         often correspondence with officials of the U.S. Department of
         Agriculture, especially the USDA Agricultural Research
         Administration, Office of Experimental Stations in Puerto
         Rico.</p>
      <p>Peurto Rican officials with whom Claiborne often
         correspondend include Ramon Colon Torres, secretary of Puerto
         Rico's Department of Agriculture and Commerce, and Luis Rives
         Santos, secretary of agriculture. There are a few letters to
         and from Luis Munoz Marin, Governor, and his staff, and from
         his wife Muna Lee Munoz. Puerto Rican political and labor
         leaders include Alberto E. Sanchez and Miguel Angel Garcia
         Mendez. Claiborne also corresponded with industrialists Samuel
         Schweitzer, President of the Puerto Rico Needlework
         Association, Auguste Schwab, and Nathan Cohen. There is some
         correspondence to, from and about Communists in Puerto Rico,
         including Richard Levins, Mary Craig Speed, Jane Speed, and
         husband Caesar Andrea. Other acquaintances and individuals
         with only one or two items of correspondence are not included
         here. These individuals range from Nathan Leopold (of Leopold
         and Loeb fame) to Craig Claiborne the food writer, and David
         Dubinsky, the labor leader.</p>
      <p>Some of the correspondence is in Spanish. A few letters
         have had parts cut out, especially those from the early 1940's
         when war-time censors cut out occasional words. Occasionally,
         Mrs. Claiborne visited Claiborne in the Virgin Islands or
         Puerto Rico, causing gaps in the correspondence. Mrs.
         Claiborne often changed the dates on Claiborne's letters,
         which were not always correct.</p>
      <p>In addition to the correspondence, there is a small amount
         of other material, filed at the end, which includes a speech
         and legal documents relating to the Virgin Islands suffrage
         case Claiborne represented in 1936; some miscellaneous
         financial papers, memorabilia, and photographs; press
         releases, statements, circulars, and newsletters, primarily
         relating to Puerto Rican labor matters, ca. 1939; and
         newspaper clippings from 1934-1965, mostly from Puerto Rican
         newspapers. Many of the circulars and newsclippings are in
         Spanish.</p>
      <p>Of interest is a letter in Box 26, 1979 March 23, from Robert Claiborne, Jr. to Edmund Berkeley, Curator of Manuscripts, in which Claiborne asserts that "the factual statements in the letters [his fathers's] are by no means reliable."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Organization</head>
      <p>The correspondence is filed chronologically. It is followed
         by the speech and legal document relative to the Virgin
         Islands suffrage case, miscellaneous financial papers,
         memorabilia, press releases, circulars and clippings described
         above, which are in rough chronological order under each type
         of material.</p>
      <p>The papers were originally packaged in a reverse
         chronological order, in which correspondence and
         non-correspondence were mixed.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e231">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934 April-1935
               July</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          <physdesc>9 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935 August-1936
               October</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e251">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1936 November-1937
               August</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">3</container>
          <physdesc>9 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e261">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937 September-1939
               February</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">4</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e271">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939 March-1940
               April</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">5</container>
          <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e281">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940 May-1941
               December</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">6</container>
          <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e291">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942 January-1944
               May</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">7</container>
          <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e301">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944 June-1946
               May</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">8</container>
          <physdesc>11 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e311">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946 June-1947
               December</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">9</container>
          <physdesc>11 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e321">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948 January-1949
               March</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">10</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e332">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949 April-1949
               September</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">11</container>
          <physdesc>8 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e342">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949 October-1950
               April</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">12</container>
          <physdesc>9 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e352">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950 May-1951
               July</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">13</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e362">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951 August-1952
               May</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">14</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e372">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952 June-1953
               March</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">15</container>
          <physdesc>9 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e382">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953 April -
               November</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">16</container>
          <physdesc>8 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e392">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953 December-1954
               August</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">17</container>
          <physdesc>8 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e402">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954 September-1955
               June</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">18</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e412">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955 July-1956
               August</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">19</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e422">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956 September-1957
               December</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">20</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e432">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958 January-1959
               June</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">21</container>
          <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e443">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959 July-1960
               October</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">22</container>
          <physdesc>11 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e453">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960 November-1961
               December</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">23</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e463">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 January-1963
               July</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">24</container>
          <physdesc>11 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e473">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1963 August-1964
               December</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">25</container>
          <physdesc>11 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e483">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965 March-1966 August, 1979 March 23, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
          <physdesc>10 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e493">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Virgin Islands Suffrage Case: Speech and
               legal document by Claiborne 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1936</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e501">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous financial papers, memorabilia,
               and photographs 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1935-1961,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e509">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Press releases, Statements, Circulars and
               Newsletters primarily relating to labor matters in
               Puerto Rico in 1939 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939, 1961,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e517">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newspaper clippings 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
               1934-1936</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e525">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newspaper clippings 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1938-1939</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
          <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e535">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newspaper clippings: English translations of
               some articles in Spanish 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939 February-March</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e544">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newspaper clippings 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1940-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e552">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newspaper clippings 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1955-1965,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">26</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
