<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01495">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01495::Dr. Charles Fox Papers, 1943-1945)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01495.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01495::Dr. Charles Fox Papers,
             1943-1945)//EN" "viu01495.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Dr. Charles Fox Papers 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1945</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Fox, Dr. Charles, Papers, 1943-1945 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11073</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">23 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Robert Ingram, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 18, 2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01495::Dr. Charles Fox
            Papers, 1943-1945)//EN" "viu01495.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-03-01" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Mar 01, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Dr. Charles Fox Papers 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1945</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11073</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Dr. Charles Fox Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1943-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11073</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">There are 160 items
         in this collection (1 Hollinger box).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Dr. Charles Fox Papers, 1943-1945, Accession #11073,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the Library from Charles
            Apfelbaum, Valley Stream, New York, on January 4, 1993.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 160 items, 1943-1945,
         chiefly the letters from Captain Charles G. Fox, Jr.,
         originally of Shawyer's Mill, Virginia, to his wife Claudyne
         [Worley ?] Fox, while serving in the Medical Corps in the
         United States, Great Britain, France, Germany, Belgium, and
         the Netherlands. Charles Fox, Jr., took his final medical
         exams at Carlisle, Pennsylvania, during September 1943 and
         looked forward to his own medical practice at the end of the
         war. These deeply personal letters illustrate clearly how much
         World War II affected the personal lives of many American
         families, especially the "war marriages" that occurred during
         those uncertain years. Charles G. Fox, Jr. ([1915 ?] - ?) and
         Claudyne [Worley ?] were married on October 27, 1942, and Fox
         requested not to be called to active duty prior to August 15,
         1943, because they were expecting their first child, Charlyne,
         at the end of July. Their second child, Gary, was born on
         March 5, 1945, while Charles Fox was serving in the 320th
         Medical Battalion in Europe. Many of his letters mention his
         pain at being separated from his growing family and new wife
         at the beginning of their life together. Others discuss all
         the everyday difficulties with communication, money, repairs,
         business matters, payments, etc. that occurred because
         families were separated during wartime.</p>
      <p>Other correspondents include: Lt. George M. Pride to
         Claudyne Fox (1944 May 21 &amp; 1945 Apr 13); Claudyne's
         sister-in-law, Madge Worley, Queensland, Australia, to
         Claudyne, about her marriage to Wilbert Worley and her desire
         to meet the other sisters, Virginia and Lucille (1944 Sep 10);
         Wilbert P. Worley, 91st Repl. Battalion, to his sister
         Virginia, about his new wife (1944 Nov 9); a friend, Janice O.
         Evans, to Claudyne (1944 Nov 16); cousin Mamie Gibson to
         Claudyne (1945 Feb 4); a Christmas card, 1944, from Mr. &amp;
         Mrs. T.J. Higginbotham to Claudyne; Charlie Fox to his
         sister-in-law, Virginia, about the birth of his son (1945 Mar
         16); and a telegram from Virginia to Charlie notifying him
         about his wife's ruptured disk (1945 Sep 25).</p>
      <p>The letters from Charlie to Claudyne began in July 1944
         when he left for his post with Company "C" 320th Medical
         Battalion, Indiantown Gap, Military Reservation, Pennsylvania,
         on July 22, 1944, and Claudyne and her daughter Charlyne,
         returned to Richmond, Virginia. Fox left the Boston harbor on
         August 6, 1944, on the Mariposa, a former luxury liner,
         reached the coast of Scotland on the twelfth, and stopped at
         Liverpool. He then traveled across England to Winchester by
         train.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">LETTERS OF 1944</emph><lb/><lb/>Topics of discussion in Charlie Fox's 1944 letters
         include: his departure for active duty (Jul 22); the
         uncertainty of their lives and his inability to make plans
         during the war (Aug 2); life on board the ship crossing to
         England (Aug 6-12); in England, a discussion about
         communication, a woman's role as mother, officers frequently
         breaking censorship rules (Aug 16); an English pub (Aug 17);
         the movie Gone With the Wind (Aug 22); the prevalence of
         veneral disease in the armed forces and marital cheating (Aug
         25); and the absence of coca-cola in England and pubs crowded
         with soldiers drinking warm beer (Aug 27).</p>
      <p>Additional subjects include: the types of English cars (Sep
         1); a tour of London, visit to officer's club, English trains
         and taxis (Sep 4); the thefts of valuable items from the
         officer's shipping box (Sep 5); in France (Sep 9); complaints
         that the French pick up most of the souvenirs of the war,
         mentioning a French boy with a complete American uniform
         driving cows out of the pasture to prevent soldiers from
         milking them, a description of his bath out of a heated helmet
         full of water interrupted by the appearance of two French
         women, his discomfort at standing around with soap all over
         his body in his overcoat until they left the area, and general
         difficulties with cleanliness and baths (Sep 15); French
         locals asking him for minor medical treatment (Sep 19);
         finding bed springs which Fox liberated from an abandoned
         German camp and brought back to the dispensary (Sep 20-21);
         and dinner at a French officer's home, trouble communicating
         with the French and medical practice on the French (Sep
         26).</p>
      <p>Other topics are: his request for a 6 volt auto radio or
         headphones for a crystal radio (Oct 4); food sent to soldiers
         from home often wasted (Oct 6); the improvised operating
         light, the unfaithfulness of some of the soldiers on the
         battlefield in his battalion, and the hunger of the men for
         letters from home (Oct 20); his work as a military censor (Oct
         24); his memories of their wedding two years ago (Oct 27); a
         list of places he has visited in France, and comments about
         French women and culture [1944 Oct ?]; mention of the
         presidential election and belief that Franklin D. Roosevelt
         will win again (Nov 7); new living quarters in a small
         Catholic hospital taken over by the U.S. Army (Nov 10); a
         mention that he was with "Blood and Guts" Patton in the U.S.
         Third Army during the Battle of Metz, Germany (Nov 16); a
         discussion of the various places he has lived during the war,
         the numerous casualties from Metz, and his photographs taken
         on captured German film (Nov 27); listening to a German radio
         station with his crystal set and a mention of General George
         S. Patton's (1885-1945) ivory-handled 45 caliber pistols (Dec
         11); crossing the Saar River, the casualties, mentally
         affected soldiers, laundry done for the first time in two
         months, dressing up like a pirate and assembling musical
         instruments for an impromptu concert to help keep up the
         morale of the men (Dec 15); Patton's Christmas card to all of
         the soldiers in the Third Army, continuous artillery shelling
         (Dec 24); and a reference to the Battle of the Bulge and the
         detrimental effect of the German counter-offensive on his
         morale (Dec 26).</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">LETTERS OF 1945</emph><lb/><lb/>Subjects in these letters include: helping themselves to
         the coal in the basements of the buildings because all the
         civilians have left the town they are in (Jan 8); return to
         France for a rest, the halting of the German offensive and the
         mention of the Soviets on the Eastern Front (Jan 12); movies
         and a description of a U.S.O. show (Jan 16); the rapid advance
         of the Soviets against the Germans (Jan 21); Fox now in
         Belgium, the Soviets now only 95 miles from Berlin (Jan 31);
         Fox was with the 95th [Infantry ?] Battalion when it took Metz
         and Saarlantern (Feb 3); mentions windmills while in Holland
         (Feb 18); and complains about the amount of junk shipped to
         soldiers from home which takes up room for supplies and
         ammunition (Feb 22).</p>
      <p>Other subjects include: the radio report of the crossing of
         the Rhine by the 1st Army in force (Mar 9); the birth of his
         son Gary and mention that he was with the 9th Army, 95th
         Infantry Division, in the final phase of the Rhineland Battle,
         driving with the Second Armored Division to the Rhine River in
         the Duisberg area (Mar 14); his transfer to "A" Company (Mar
         16); a description of a concert by Lilly Pons (1904- 1976)
         with her husband Andre Kostelanetz (1901-1980) (Mar 18); a
         three day pass to Brussells and his stay at a hotel made into
         a leave center for American officers, and the prices of wine
         and women in Brussells (Mar 24); unable to write because he
         was with the 9th Army which cut off 150,000 German troops from
         the Ruhr Valley (Apr 4); the massive surrender by Germans,
         many marching to the rear lines unguarded, mention of
         liberated Jews used by the Germans as slave labor and their
         fear of a German return to the city (Apr 5); his work on a
         light plant that could be towed on a trailer behind an
         ambulance or jeep (Apr 11); the 9th Army only seventy miles
         from Berlin (Apr 12); a ride for 200 miles to check on about a
         dozen captured German hospitals staffed by German doctors as
         prisoners kept to take of the German wounded (Apr 18); and the
         rumor that the British controlled Bremen except for the dock
         area, improvement in the time it takes for him to receive
         mail, and the worn-out condition of his clothing after two
         years (Apr 26).</p>
      <p>Other items mentioned include: the seeming reluctance of
         the French prisoners to leave their German captivity, a
         reference to the deaths of F.D. Roosevelt and Benito
         Mussolini, and rumors about the death of Adolph Hitler (May
         1); his joy at the news of V-E Day beginning on May 8th and
         disappointment that he could not celebrate with his wife in
         the United States, and his appropriation of a German house in
         Werl, Germany for his quarters (May 7-8); warning to his wife
         not to expect a rapid return home as it will take some time to
         ship 5 or 6 million men overseas (May 9); an explanation of
         the point system to determine who goes home first, and a visit
         to the [Berlin ?] Zoo (May 10); busy day doing physical
         examinations on American soldiers to see if any deserved a
         medical discharge, and his concern over the fraternization of
         American soldiers with German women (May 12); his itinerary
         when he left the Boston harbor for Europe (May 13); presently
         in Recklehausen near Essen, close to the Rhine; at Easter he
         was at the Wesel River and participated in the movement to
         seal off the Ruhr pocket (May 16); the general uncertainty
         about whether his battalion will stay to occupy Germany, go
         home or go on to fight the Japanese, mentioned in each letter
         written since Germany's surrender (May 19); observations of
         three court-martials for fraternizations with German women
         which all resulted in acquittals, complaints about people who
         try to produce various ailments so they can go home and avoid
         the Japanese theater (May 20); his German souvenirs (May 22);
         according to The Stars and Stripes, his battalion will be
         coming home in June and his remaining letters speak mainly of
         his longing to be home with his family (May 24-June 12); on
         the coast of France waiting for a ship to sail for the United
         States (Jun 17); last letter from France (Jun 19); and in
         Mississippi after a leave at home, hopes the Japanese will
         surrender soon after the atomic bomb attacks (Aug 10).</p>
      <p>Miscellaneous material includes: Fox's request not to be
         called to active duty until the birth of his first child
         (1943); his authorization for the purchase of war savings
         bonds (Aug 1943); special order #53 granting leave for three
         days effective on June 25, 1944, Headquarters 320th Medical
         Battalion; and Army Service Forces, Third Service Command,
         Fort George C. Meade, Maryland, Special Orders # 214 (1945 Aug
         2).</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
