<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu00603">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu00603::A Guide to the Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia, )//EN" "viu00603.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Cabell, Joseph Carrington, Papers Relating the the Founding of the University of Virginia
<num type="collectionnumber">2791, 2791-a, 2791-b
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2006 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Stephanie Brooks, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">9/6/2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">2791, 2791-a, 2791-b
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">2791, 2791-a, 2791-b
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia, Accession #2791, 2791-a, 2791-b, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased from Mrs. Raymond Orf, Bremo Recess, 1972 July 25.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Joseph Carrington Cabell, 1778-1856, was an early adherent to Jefferson's party and well-traveled for his day--having completed a tour of Europe November 1802-May 1806--Cabell had opportunities to serve in the administrations of Presidents Madison and Monroe. He declined even to run for a congressional seat, preferring Richmond to Washington. He served for decades in the Virginia General Assembly not because he was incapable of attaining a higher station, but because his service there well-positioned him to advance his two great interests, the University of Virginia and the James River &amp; Kanawha Canal. 
</p>
      <p>Thomas Jefferson recruited Cabell's aid in the earliest stages of planning for the University of Virginia. Jefferson first raised the issue with his friend in a letter of 5 January 1815, and Cabell thereafter served as the University's most faithful advocate in the state legislature. He was the prime mover first behind the incorporation of Central College in 1817 and second behind the selection of Central College as the official state university in 1819. In that year, Cabell joined Jefferson, his best friend John Hartwell Cocke, and several other of the Commonwealth's most distinguished citizens on the University's first Board of Visitors. When Cabell's energy faded and he considered resigning his post in the state legislature, Jefferson begged his friend in the strongest possible terms not to abandon his post as the institution's most capable friend in Richmond. "Nature will not give you a second life wherein to atone for the omissions of this. Pray then, dear and very dear sir, do not think of deserting us," he pined in January 1821. Cabell found some hidden reserve of energy and served the University of Virginia longer than any of its original founders, as a Board member until his death in 1856 and as a member of the General Assembly until 1835.
</p>
      <p>In addition to his remarkable contributions to the University, Cabell spearheaded the drive for internal improvements in the state of Virginia. He doggedly pursued his goal of connecting the James and Kanawha Rivers, thereby linking the Chesapeake watershed and the Mississippi River, and demonstrated perseverance and political acumen that even his opponents admired. Editor of the Richmond Whig, John Hampden Pleasants, marveled in 1842 at Cabell's ability to keep the project afloat despite the disapprobation of a majority of his fellow citizens. "To keep this majority passive, and not merely passive, but to impel them into active co-operation," he wrote, "argues a great knowledge of mankind, and a great talent for influencing them."
</p>
      <p>Cabell died at his Nelson County estate, "Edgewood," in February of 1856, survived by his wife of forty-nine years, Mary Walker Carter Cabell. Cabell left no children to mourn his passing, but the Faculty and Visitors of the University each passed resolutions honoring him. His grateful successors on the Board further commemorated his sacrifices on their behalf by naming the University's new academic center Cabell Hall in 1895.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists primarily of Joseph Carrington Cabell's letters to Thomas Jefferson, 1810-1826, concerning the founding of the University of Virginia; the collection also includes Cabell's copies of the University of Virginia Board of Visitors' minutes and his memoranda concerning passages of Jefferson correspondence omitted from Nathaniel Francis Cabell's Early history of the University of Virginia, as contained in the letters of Thomas Jefferson and Joseph C. Cabell, hitherto unpublished (Richmond, Va. : J. W. Randolph, 1856.)
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e133">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810 July 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 2-5.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Unwillingness to enter into an agreement with Judge Cooper regarding collection of minerals. His knowledge only that of an amateur. His collection lent to William and Mary and to [Louis H.?] Girardin.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e147">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 January 12.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 6.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defense of T. J.'s rights against the petition of the Rivanna Company. References to [Philip P.?] Barbour and [Chapman] Johnson.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e161">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 February 17.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 7-8.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Services by Cabell, [P. P.?] Barbour, and [Chapman] Johnson in the Virginia legislature in defense of T. J.'s rights against the bill petitioned by the Rivanna Company. Action in the Senate and House of Delegates. Use of T. J.'s canal by the company and exemption of T. J.'s and his customer's produce from tools were involved.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e175">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 November 29.
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 10-12.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bill concerning T. J. and the Rivanna River Co. will pass the Virginia Assembly. Disagrees with T. J. on the length of the charter. Prefers Jean Baptiste Say's book on political economy to Adam Smith's. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e189">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 December 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 12-13.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Books forwarded through General Moore. Reelection of Governor Barbour expected despite discontent throughout the state. Consultation with Charles Everett and Jesse W. Garth relative to the petition of the Rivanna River Co. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e203">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 January 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 16-18.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Expresses limited approval of a state banking system. Voted for chartering Bank of Virginia. Restriction of the residence of a member of the House of Representatives to the district from which he was elected. Bill respecting the Rivanna River Company. Reasons for the division of state into wards. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e217">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 February 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 21-23.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Assembly's action on residence requirements for Congressmen. Passage of the Rivanna River Company bill in form agreed upon by T. J. and [Dabney] Minor. Bill to charter bank at Wheeling.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e231">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Carysbrook, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 March 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 24.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Return of T. J.'s letters on banking and finance which have been shown to William C. Rives, [John?] Tucker, Thomas Ritchie, and [John H.] Cocke.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e245">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 September 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 24-27.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Preparations for defense of Richmond against the British. Lack of money in treasury at Washington and Richmond. Loans from Bank of Virginia and from the Farmers' Bank to the state. Stopping of specie payment in these banks. Suggests Colonel Nicholas as next governor.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e259">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 October 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 32.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Issuing of state certificates to bolster public credit. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e274">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814 December 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 32-35.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Tracy's work on political economy. Possible solutions of the problems of financing the state government: loan from the Farmer's Bank; issuance of treasury notes by the state; or a private loan by citizens. Thomas Mann Randolph's petition to open the falls near Milton and charge tolls on traffic conflicts with the Rivanna River Charter. References to Charles Yancey and William Wood. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e288">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Albemarle Academy, Central College, Visitor's Minutes.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1814-1826.  
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
</container>
          <physdesc>AD. #2791
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e299">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Minutes of the Trustees of Albemarle Academy 1814-1817, the Board of Visitors of Central College 1817-1819, and the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia 1819-1826.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1817-1826
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:13
</container>
          <physdesc>AD. MS. Vol. 65 pp., 6 pp., 2 pp. #2791-a
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Copies of the minutes belonging to Joseph Carrington Cabell. Some of the notes date from 1814, with the minutes of the Trustees of Albemarle Academy. The notes for 1826 March 4 and 5 (2 pp.) have interlineations in T. J.'s hand. (See "Bibliography of Unprinted Official Records" in sixth Annual Report of the Archivist, Univ. of Va., 1935-36). 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e313">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 March 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:14
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 38-41.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Petition regarding the setting up of an academy in Albemarle County; possible effect on the College of William and Mary. Hopes it will induce such men as Jean Baptiste Say to reside in Virginia. Disposition of his slaves from Corotoman taken by the British. References to Dr. [Charles?] Carr, Peter Carr, Admiral Cockburn, John A. Smith, Destutt de Tracy, David Watson, and Charles Yancey.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e327">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 January 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:15
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 43-45.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Expects no opposition to Mr. Miller's petition. Some resistance to the bill for establishing Central College. Questioning of powers given the professors to imprison students. Possibility of a school for the deaf and dumb, taught by a Mr. Braidwood, to be attached to the college. Recommends enlisting the cooperation of Chapman Johnson, William G. Poindexter, Edward Watts and John W. Green of the Senate. References to [Peter] Carr, [Thomas W.] Maury, and [Charles] Yancey. [1387]
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e341">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 January 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:16
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 45-47.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Objections to the Central College bill. Papers in Captain Miller's case with respect to the Reed estate. Copy of the bill to prevent obstructions in the navigable watercourses of Virginia. Appropriations for Literary Fund and for endowment of a professorship for teaching the deaf and dumb. Dr. Smith asks recommendation of a textbook on the principles of government for use at William and Mary. References to Chapman Johnson, John Locke, Jean Jacques Rousseau, Jean Baptiste Say, and Charles Yancey. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e355">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1816 January 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:17
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 50-51; B of R VI 58 (MS. in DLC); Adams II 66-67.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Requests permission to publish T. J.'s letter to Peter Carr regarding the establishment of Central College. Possible locations: Charlottesville, Staunton, or Lexington. Move to shift seat of government to Staunton. References to [Charles F.] Mercer. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e369">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 February 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:18
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 56.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of bill for Central College, Mr. Miller's bill, and the bill respecting navigable waters. Reference to [John W.] Green. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e383">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 February 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:19
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 57-60.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of Captain Miller's bill and of bill respecting navigable water; rejection of lottery bill to purchase Triplett Estis' property. Possible appropriation of U. S. surplus to Literary Fund. Modifications in Central College Bill respecting powers of college proctor, glebe lands, and the Literary Fund. Translation of Jean Baptiste Say's Traité d'economie politique. Mentions William Cabell, John W. Green, Chapman Johnson, Thomas W. Maury, and Wilson C. Nicholas. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e397">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 February 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:20
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 60-61.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Publication of T. J.'s letter to Peter Carr. Appropriation of Virginia's U. S. Government stock to education. Presbyterians in Lexington and Scotch-Irish in Staunton will object to Albemarle as site for university since they hope to move seat of government to Staunton. Washington College at Lexington the bantling of the Federalists. Trouble with Colonel Monroe about caucus for an electoral ticket. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and [Charles F.] Mercer. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e411">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 July 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:21
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 62-65.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Maine's method of preparing hawthorne hedges is best. References to James Henderson, Isaac Newton, Dobson's Encyclopedia, and Lord Karmes' translation of Say's Traité d'economie politique. Implementation of General Assembly act requiring an accurate map of each county. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e426">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1816 August 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:22
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 6769.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Superiority of thorn hedges. Surveying for the map authorized by the Assembly (Herman Boye's A Map of the State of Virginia). Advisability of a convention to amend the Virginia Constitution, favored by westerners desiring to place the pecuniary burdens of government on the easterners and by Federalist bank stockholders wishing to charter fifteen banks. Books by Montesquieu, Destutt de Tracy, and Say as textbooks at William and Mary. References to Philip Doddridge, Mr. Meriwether, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and John Augustine Smith. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e440">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1817 January 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:23
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 71-73.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cabell to oppose the petition to which T. J. is opposed, and attend to Count Barziza's petition. Translation of Say's Traité d'economie politique. Copy of a banking bill enclosed. Failure to increase the Literary Fund as recommended by the governor. Col. [Samuel?] Taylor author of petition from Port Royal. Appointment of Cabell as a Visitor of Central College. Difficulty in obtaining money for colleges. Possible site for the University in Staunton. References to Thomas W. Maury.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e454">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 February 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:24
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 73-74.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rejection of Count Barziza's petition. Is attending to Turnpike Bill. Hewing down of mammoth bank bill. References to Thomas W. Maury, [Joseph] Milligan (bookseller), William C. Rives, Tracy's Political Economy, and Archibald Thweatt. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e468">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 February 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:25
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 74.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Report on Turnpike Bill, bill to call a convention, bill to equalize senatorial districts (modeled after bill reported by T. J., Pendleton, and Wythe in 1779), and the University Bill. Mentions Archibald Thweatt and Charles Yancey. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e482">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 March 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:26
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 75.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Sends Maine's recipe for preparation of haws found in Brown's Rural Affairs. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e496">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Bremo, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1817 April 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:27
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 75-76.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Inability to attend meeting of the Board of Visitors of Central College. References to Bedford and Goochland counties, Enniscorthy, John Hartwell Cocke, James Madison, and David Watson.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e510">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 August 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:28
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 76-78.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Catalog of English books sold by Barrois at Paris. Subscriptions to Central College from Albemarle, Amherst, Campbell, Lancaster, Northumberland, Richmond, and Westmoreland counties. Death of Cabell's mother. Comments of T. J.'s manuscript on meteorological subjects. References to William Brent, George Cabell, John Camm, Hill Carter, Sterling Claiborne, Ellyson Currie, Thomas Eubanks, David S. Garland, Spottswood Garland, William J. Lewis, James Madison, Roderick McCullock, William Pope, Robert Rives, Mr. Ritchie, Henry St. George Tucker, Robert Walker, and Edmund Winston.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e524">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Charlottesville, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 October 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:29
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 81.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Delay in arriving at Board of Visitors meeting due to the meeting of the Association for an Agricultural Society. References to John Hartwell Cocke, James Madison, James Monroe, Judge [Archibald?] Stewart, and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e538">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 October 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:30
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 82-83.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Plan for schools and colleges throughout the state of Virginia. Copy of membership list of Cincinnati left at Monticello. John Wayles Eppes endeavoring to secure subscribers at Buckingham Court House. Advises delay on the report to the Agricultural Society. Mentions John Hartwell Cocke, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and Arthur Young's Annals.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e552">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 December 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:31
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 85-87.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Subscriptions to Central College from [Henry St. George?] Tucker and John Coalter. Plan for primary schools throughout the state. Opposition to Central College from Federalists, bigots, members of the Society of Cincinnati, and from friends of Washington College at Lexington. William and Mary people are liberal. References to Judge Brooke, John W. Green, Armistead Holmes, Chapman Johnson, and Edward Watts.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e566">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Robert G. Scott, Chairman of the Committee of Schools and Colleges. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 December 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:32
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. Draft. 5 pp. Endorsed by T. J. [Copy sent to T. J.]. #2791-a. Enclosed in [1511]. Printed: Cabell 94-96.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Jefferson's ideas regarding the bill providing for the establishment of primary schools, academies, colleges, and a university. Discussion of whether education should be compulsory. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e581">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 December 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:33
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 6 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 89-94.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Opposition by members of the Society of Cincinnati to Central College, preferring to give funds to Washington College. Presbyterians oppose because T. J. is an infidel. Opposition in the Assembly to setting up a system of public education in Virginia. Encloses copy of letter sent to Robert Scott, Chairman of Committee for Schools and Colleges [1504]. Site for the University. Report on the Literary Fund. References to Francis T. Brooke, William Cabell, John Coalter, Thomas Cooper, Mr. Garrett, Chapman Johnson, Wilson C. Nicholas, [Alfred H.?] Powell, Spencer Roane, Henry Tucker, and Edward Watts. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e595">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:34
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Enclosure: C. Tompkins, ALS. 2 pp. Partly printed: Cabell 99-101.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Encloses letter from Major Christopher Tompkins regarding the price of bricklaying for Central College. Essay in the Enquirer by Mr. Giles. Prospects not good for the general education bill. Receipt of the papers of Poinsot des Essarts. Information regarding subscriptions to Central College from William Brent, Mr. Currie, and Creed Taylor. References to Wilson C. Nicholas, James P. Preston, Mr. Brown (bricklayer), and Mr. Night (bricklayer). 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e609">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:35
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Enclosure: Creed Taylor ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by Cabell. Partly printed: Cabell 108-110.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Search regarding land will be carried out for T. J. in the Register's Office. Copy of the Report of the Visitors circulated in the Assembly. Copy of T. J.'s letters regarding primary schools given to Robert Scott, Chairman of the Committee on Schools and Colleges. Motion to move the capital. Opposition to Central College by the Washington College people. Recommends that William Brent, John T. Brooke, John Hartwell Cocke, and George Poindexter run for the Assembly. Bank loan being negotiated. Recommends annuity from the Literary Fund as best income for Central College. Encloses note from Chancellor Creed Taylor regarding T. J.'s proposed system of public education. References to Jesse W. Garth, James Madison, Robert Mallory, Dabney Minor, and James Monroe. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e623">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:36
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 111.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Disappointment in the bill reported by the Committee of Schools and Colleges. Visitors will be personally responsible for a bank loan to Central College. Movement of seat of government from Richmond to the West postponed.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e637">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to John Brockenbrough.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:37
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  [Copy sent by Cabell to T. J.] Printed: Cabell 114-115.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>To the President of the Bank of Virginia, covering reports by the Visitors of Central College, given to enable the bank to judge the merits of a loan sought in anticipation of subscriptions. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e651">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John Brockenbrough, Richmond, to Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:38
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Deposited by Philip B. Campbell. Printed: Cabell 115-116.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Agreeing to lend money to Central College for 60 days with renewal of notes possible. Originally enclosed in Cabell to Jefferson, 1818 February 1.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e665">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:39
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 112-113.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Fears failure of general education bill for Virginia. Requests T. J. to draw bill for annuity from Literary Fund for endowment of professorships. Inquires with regard to Des Essarts' land patents. References to Robert Scott, Samuel Taylor, and [George J.] Davison. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e679">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:40
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 113-114.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Loan offered by John Brockenbrough, President of the Bank of Virginia, better than can be obtained from Benjamin Hatcher of the Farmer's Bank. Necessity for the Visitors to sign the notes as individuals. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e693">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:41
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 1 16-1 18.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Inquiries regarding Poinsot des Essarts' land patents. Back-country opposition to T. J.'s general education bill. Opposition to Central College from friends of Lexington and Staunton. Recommends selection of men such as General [John George] Jackson in the Northwest of Virginia and William Burwell from the Southwest. References to Mr. Johnson, General Kosciuszko, and Peter Carr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e707">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:42
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 119-121.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>T. J.'s letter published in the Enquirer to help the general education bill, omitting T. J.'s estimate of the large amount of money necessary. Reference to William Cabell, Wilson C. Nicholas, and Lewis Somers (i.e., Summers).
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e721">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:43
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 121-122.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Introducing Lewis Summers of Kanawha County. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e736">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:44
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 122123.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Enquiries regarding Poinsot des Essarts' land. Failure of T. J.'s general education bill, with only a small appropriation for education of the poor, due to interests from Lexington and Staunton and to the Presbyterians, aided by a junto from the middle country delegation (Charles Yancey, Thomas Miller, Robert Mallory, and Charles Everett). Possibility of an appropriation for Central College. References to Francis T. Brooke, Dabney Carr, John W. Green, Thomas Hill, and Chapman Johnson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e750">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:45
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 125-126.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bill providing for education of poor, an appropriation for the University, and the setting up of the Rockfish Gap Commission passed the Senate. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e764">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 February 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:46
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 127.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of the Rockfish Gap Bill. Asks T. J. to serve as a commissioner. Appointments in the hands of the president and directors of the Literary Fund, three fifths of whom are from beyond the mountains. Urges immediate work on buildings of Central College because of opposition from Federalists, Presbyterian clergy, and the entire back country. Mentions James Madison. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e778">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Fluvanna County, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1818 March 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:47
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 129.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Selection of members of the Rockfish Gap Commission. Visit to Monticello. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e792">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 March 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:48
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 130-132.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Rivalry between Washington College, Rockbridge College, and Central College as to the site for the University. Offer by a Mr. Robinson of Lexington to leave his estate to the University if located there. Requests T. J. to urge Wilson J. Cary, John Hartwell Cocke, Randolph Harrison, and Washington Trueheart to serve in House of Delegates as friends of Central College. References to John Wayles Eppes.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e806">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, at Mrs. Tinsley's, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 March 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:49
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 132.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Lending Jefferson a copy of the Oxford and Cambridge guide. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e820">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 July 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:50
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 132-133.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Sends by his brother William the signatures of Central College subscribers in Nelson County, agreeing to the conveyance of the property of Central College to the Commonwealth of Virginia, if the University of Virginia is located on the site of the college. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e834">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 October 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:51
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 133-134.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>  Invitation to Warminster; urges him not to tax his health. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e848">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Enniscorthy, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 November 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:52
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 134-135.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Illness prevents visit to Monticello. Rockfish Gap Report. Reason why he cannot make the trip to Europe for the college. Possibility he may run for the House of Representatives. Information regarding the hill for locating the University. Mentions [Samuel] Carr, Isaac Coles, William F. Gordon, Spencer Roane, Francis T. Brooke. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e862">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 December 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:53
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 137-138.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Progress of the Rockfish Gap Report in the General Assembly. Attitudes of the William and Mary and Lexington interests. Cabell's health. References to Samuel Carr, William F. Gordon, Samuel Taylor, and Philip R. Thompson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e876">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 December 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:54
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 138-139.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Progress of the bill to decide the site of the University. Prospects of Central College. Report of T. J.'s authorship of the bill gives appearance of dictation. References to Linn Banks, Samuel Taylor, and Robert T. Thompson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e891">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 December 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:55
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 139-140.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Central College fixed as the site of the University in the bill reported to the House of Delegates. Combination of western delegates opposed to Central College. Publication of T. J.'s calculation of the center of population based on census of 1810. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and William Cabell. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e905">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1818 December 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:56
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 141.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Senator Davidson [Davison?] of Clarksburg in favor of Central College. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e919">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 December 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:57
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 141-144.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Delay of the University bill. Opposition from friends of William and Marv, who demand $5000 per annum for William and Mary as price of their concurrence, from those who wish education left to individual enterprise, and from those who wish Literary Fund devoted to the poor. Various methods of calculating the center of population. References to the Edinburgh Review, William S. Archer, James Hunter, Chapman Johnson, Francis Preston, Adam Smith, Dugald Stewart, and Colonel Tatham. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e933">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 January 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:58
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 146-149.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cabell's labors in the General Assembly on behalf of the University Bill. T. J.'s health. References to John Brockenbrough, Chancellor John W. Green, Thomas C. Holmes, W. C. Nicholas, Mr. Pannel, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., Spencer Roane, Mr. Slaughter, John Taliaferro, Samuel Taylor, Chancellor [Creed] Taylor, and Philip Thompson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e947">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 January 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:59
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 149-152.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>University Bill passes the House of Delegates with Central College fixed as the site. Various methods of determining the center of population favor Central College. Cabell's recent illness. References to Briscoe G. Baldwin, Dabney Carr, Armistead Holmes, and James Hunter. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e961">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 January 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:60
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 152-153.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Progress of the University Bill in the Senate. Bill to connect the eastern and western waters. Cabell's ill-health. References to Judge John Coalter, George Hay, Armistead Holmes, Chapman Johnson, Alfred Powell, John Taliaferro, and Philip Thompson.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e975">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 January 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:61
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 153.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of the University Bill. Cabell's illness. References to John Coalter, Chapman Johnson, and Edward Watts. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e989">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 February 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:62
</container>
          <physdesc>LS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed by Cabell 155-159, misdated as of 4 December.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Advises against moving now for the derelict portion of the School Fund. Copy of reports on the navigation of the James and on connection of eastern and western waters. Sketch of services rendered by the following friends of the University: William Brockenbrough, William H. Brodnax, Francis T. Brooke, Samuel Carr, John Coalter, [Francis W.?] Gilmer (author of essays signed "a Virginian"), John W. Green, George Hay, Armistead Holmes, Garrett Minor, Wilson C. Nicholas, George Nicholson, Mr. Pannel, the Rev. Mr. Rice (author of essay signed "Crito"), Mr. Ritchie, Judge Spencer Roane, James Robertson, JF., Mr. Scott, Captain Slaughter, Mr. Stannard, John Taliaferro, Chancellor [Creed] Taylor, Philip Thompson. Mentions also William S. Archer, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and James Madison. (Thirteen lines made illegible, probably prior to publication of N. F. Cabell's book). 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1003">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 February 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:63
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Also includes: J. Brown to Thomas Jefferson.  1819 February 8.  ALS.  2 pp.   Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 159-161.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Revenue of the Literary Fund not equal to appropriations. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1017">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 February 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:64
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Endorsed by T. J. Printed: Cabell 161-163.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Appointment of James Breckenridge, Joseph Cabell, John Hartwell Cocke, Chapman Johnson, James Madison, and Robert B. Taylor as Visitors of the University of Virginia. Cabell's health. Untrue report that Cabell is to go to Europe to seek professors. Advises delay in opening the University until sufficient buildings are ready. References to Samuel Taylor, Armistead Holmes, [Samuel] Carr, and Henry St. George Tucker. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1031">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 February 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:65
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 165-167.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting of the Board of Visitors of University; appointment of Dr. Cooper one of great delicacy and importance; recommends delay in opening until several eminent professors are secured. Difficulties in securing adequate funds from the Assembly. References to James Breckenridge, John Hartwell Cocke, Isaac Coles, James Madison, Robert B. Taylor, and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1046">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 March 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:66
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 170-172.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>State funds for the University. The Literary Fund. Professorship offered to Thomas Cooper. References to John Hartwell Cocke, Isaac Coles, Alexander Garrett, James Madison, and James P. Preston. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1060">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 March 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:67
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 173-174.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Advertisement for workmen for the University inserted in the Enquirer. Alexander Garrett's draft on Literary Fund will be honored. Importance of securing Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough as proctor. Cabell's health improved. Mentions Mary Cabell, Mr. Montcarel, and Wilson C. Nicholas. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1074">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 April 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:68
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 174-176.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Recommends A. S. Brockenbrough as Proctor. Despite admiration for T. J.'s plans for the pavilions and lawn, recommends different style for hotels and ranges. Provision for lecture rooms in separate buildings from pavilions. Fire at Monticello. Reference to John Hartwell Cocke.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1088">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Bremo, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 November 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:69
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 177.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Returns copy of plan of Poplar Forest. Financial requirements prevent his moving to the neighborhood of the University at the present time. T. J.'s illness.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1102">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:70
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 180-181.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University from Literary Fund and elsewhere. Health of his wife, Mary. Reference to Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1116">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1820 February 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:71
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 181-182
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Attempts to obtain money for the University from the Assembly. References to William and Mary, Burwell Bassett, James Breckenridge, James Dickinson, George Hay, and Chapman Johnson.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1130">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 February 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:72
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 182-183.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Encloses bill just passed regarding funds for the University. References to James Breckenridge, William F. Gordon, and Chapman Johnson.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1144">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Charlottesville, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 October 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:73
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 183.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Verification of Alexander Garrett's account.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1158">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 December 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:74
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 189-190.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Attack on Governor Randolph's character. Money from the Assembly for University. Requests fuller accounts by Bursar, Mr. Garrett. References to James Breckenridge, Mary Cabell, Chapman Johnson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1172">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 December 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:75
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 190-192.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Resolution giving grants to William and Mary, Hampton-Sidney, Washington College, New London Academy, and the University will defeat the claims of the University on the Literary Fund. Attitude of James Breckenridge, John Bowyer, John Coalter, George W. Crump, Philip Doddridge, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, Mr. [Richard] Morris, Thomas Miller, Isaac Otey, Jr., Judge Spencer Roane, Mr. [William?] Taylor, and David Watson. Alexander Garrett's account for the University. Comments on Governor Randolph's message.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1186">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 January 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:76
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Endorsed by T. J. Printed: Cabell 194-195.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Doctrine that all colleges receiving funds should be under the control of the legislature. References to William and Mary, Mr. Bassett, Samuel Blackburn, Philip Doddridge, David S. Garland, Thomas Griffin, Chapman Johnson, Thomas Miller, [James?] Smith, Richard Venable, and Henry E. Watkins. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1201">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 January 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:77
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 196-197.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Little prospect of gaining additional funds for the University. References to Mr. Broadnax, [Richard?] Morris, and [Samuel] Taylor. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1215">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 January 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:78
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 197-199.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Plans to leave public life at end of present session. References to James Breckenridge, [Nathaniel?] Claiborne, John Hartwell Cocke, Chapman Johnson, and James P. Preston. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1229">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 February 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:79
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 203-204.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Agrees to be a candidate for Assembly again. Funds for the University. References to Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, Chapman Johnson, and William Selden. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1243">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 February 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:80
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 204-206.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Funds for the University. Passage of James River Bill by House of Delegates. References to William Archer, James Breckenridge, William Brodnax, Armistead Currie, David S. Garland, Chapman Johnson, Robert Mallory, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., Samuel Taylor, and Robert B. Taylor. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1257">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 February 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:81
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 206.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. References to Samuel Blackburn, [Nathaniel?] Claiborne, and David S. Garland.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1271">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 February 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:82
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 208-209.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of bill providing funds for the University. Mentions Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, John Bowyer, William B. Chamberlayne, George W. Crump, Armistead Currie, William F. Gordon, James Hunter, Chapman Johnson, George Loyall, Richard Morris, Mr. Stephenson, and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1285">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 March 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:83
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 210-212.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Advises building no more buildings than those for which there is money in hand. Urges Jefferson to use his influence in the election of friends of the University. References to James Breckenridge, William H. Brodnax, Samuel Taylor, Littleton Tazewell, and Mr. Watts. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1299">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 April 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:84
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 212.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Reasons for inability to attend meeting of the Board of Visitors. Note sent by [Valentine?] Southall. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1313">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Henrico County, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 April 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:85
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 212-214.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cabell's illness. Requests information regarding last meeting of the Board of Visitors. Success of Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, David S. Garland, Mr. Maury of Buckingham, and Joseph Shelton in the recent election. Funds for the University. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1327">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 August 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:86
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 215-216.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cabell's illness. Request for complete statement of all University accounts for the next General Assembly. Attacks on the University by the Presbyterians of Hampton-Sydney and the Episcopalians of William and Mary. Washington College to receive Robinson's estate. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1341">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 August 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:87
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 217-218.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p> Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Cabell's health. Reference to Mary Cabell. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 November 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:88
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 222-223.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Absence from the meeting of the Board of Visitors due to illness. Advisability of finishing all University buildings. University finances. References to Chapman Johnson and Dr. [John A.] Smith of Williamsburg. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1370">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 January 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:89
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 229231.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Reasons for Thomas Griffin's resolution. Opposition from the clergy. References to William and Mary, Hampden-Sydney, Chapman Johnson, Bishop [Richard Channing] Moore, Richard Morris, Rev. Mr. Rice, and Henry E. Watkins. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1384">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 January 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:90
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 231-237.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Advises conciliation of the clergy who are uneasy because of the predominance of the Socinians at Cambridge (Harvard), the appointment of Thomas Cooper in South Carolina, and the discovery that George Ticknor and Nathaniel Bowditch are Unitarians. References to Chapman Johnson and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1398">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 January 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:91
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 238-239.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Estimate of revenue from the Literary Fund. References to John Bowyer, Chapman Johnson, and Charles Fenton Mercer. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1412">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1822 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:92
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 240-241.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. The Kentucky Mission. States' Rights. References to Samuel Blackburn, Thomas Griffin, Chapman Johnson, and Richard Morris. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1426">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:93
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 242-244.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. The Literary Fund. References to James Breckenridge, [Charles?] Cocke, Chapman Johnson, Thomas Miller, and Richard Morris. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1440">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 February 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:94
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 244-245.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. References to John Bowyer, Chapman Johnson, Richard Morris, Samuel Taylor, and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1454">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 March 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:95
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 7 pp Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed (in part): Cabell 245-251.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Failure to pass various bills to provide funds for the University. Reports of extravagance in construction of the buildings. Attack on the Literary Fund based on the waste of the Primary School Fund. References to Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough, Samuel Blackburn, John Bowyer, Mr. Clay, Thomas Griffin, Chapman Johnson, Richard Morris, and David Watson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1468">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1822 March 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:96
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 251-254.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Funds for the University. Convinced that all buildings should be completed to give favorable impression. Incidental effects of the move to shift the capital from Richmond to Staunton. Attitude of the Federalist Party. References to Wilson J. Cary, George Crump, Thomas Griffin, Chapman Johnson, James Madison, and John Tyler. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1482">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 October 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:97
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Endorsed by T. J. Printed: Cabell 254-255.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Illness prevents attendance at the Board of Visitors meeting. Auditing of the University's accounts by Martin Dawson. References to John Hartwell Cocke. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1496">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 December 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:98
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed Cabell 255-257.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Literary Fund finances very unfavorable. Cabell's health improved. Glad T. J.'s wound improving. References to Wilson J. Cary, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, Chapman Johnson, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., [William Cabell] Rives, and Judge St. George Tucker. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1511">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 December 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:99
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 257-259.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cost of building the library estimated by James Dinsmore. Funds for the University. Purchase of books and apparatus. Settlement of the Proctor's accounts. References to John Bowyer, Alexander Garrett, William F. Gordon, James Hunter, George Loyall, and [William Cabell] Rives. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1525">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 December 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:100
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 263-265.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Cost of the library. Error in the Proctor's accounts. References to Briscoe G. Baldwin, John Bowyer, Wilson J. Cary, John Hartwell Cocke, Peter M. Daniel, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, Chapman Johnson, Daniel Sheffey, Allen Taylor, and Henry E. Watkins. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1539">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 January 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:101
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 265-266.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. University's popularity shown in elections in Mecklenburg, Lunenburg, Brunswick, Greenville, Henrico, Norfolk, and Essex counties. References to Mr. Clopton, James Hunter, Arthur Lee, and Addison Powell. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1553">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 January 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:102
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 268-270.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University and for colleges and primary schools throughout the state. Question of moving the capital from Richmond. References to Hampden-Sydney College, William F. Gordon, [William Cabell] Rives, and Samuel Taylor. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1567">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:103
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 272-273.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Loan bill for the University secure. Mr. Brockenbrough's accounts. References to Philip Doddridge and Thomas Griffin. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1581">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:104
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 274.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of the University Bill. References to William F. Gordon, Chapman Johnson, and George Loyall.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1595">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:105
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 274-277.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>No attention paid to James Oldham's charges against Arthur Brockenbrough. Chapman Johnson's failure to attend meetings of Board of Visitors. University finances. Application from Dr. Tones, formerly of the College of William and Mary, for the chemistry chair at the University of Virginia. References to Briscoe Baldwin, John Bowyer, Philip Doddridge, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, George Loyall, Daniel Sheffey, Allen Taylor, and Joseph Watkins. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1609">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 277-278.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Law regarding seats on the Board of Visitors. Contracts for the library should be for a definite amount. References to Chapman Johnson and John Augustine Smith. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1623">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 March 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 280-282.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Contracts for the library. Funds for the purchase of books and apparatus. References to John Hartwell Cocke and Chapman Johnson. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1637">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 June 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Another copy: 3 pp. File draft. Endorsed by Cabell. Cabell Papers.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Requesting T. J.'s advice on plan of jail for Nelson County. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1651">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 July 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. 
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Thanking T. J. for his aid in planning the Nelson County jail. References to Mr. Crawford, Mr. Peck, and William Philips. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1666">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 August 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 5 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Enclosure: AD. 2 pp.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Deposited by Philip B. Campbell.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Selection of the site of the Nelson County jail. Details of its plan. References to Arthur Brockenbrough, William Cosby, Mr. Crawford, Mr. Nelson, John Perry, William Phillips. Enclosure: memorandum of the contract made 29 July 1823 between Robert Rives, Joseph C. Cabell, and Thomas Massie, Jr., for the court of Nelson County, and William B. Phillips, who agrees to build the jail. Contract refers to Jefferson's plan. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1680">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 October 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 282-283.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Coffey's and Roscoe's books on prisons. Unable to find the Oxford and Cambridge Guide. New purchase of land will make it necessary to withdraw from the Senate.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1694">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 November 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 284.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Personal affairs delay his attending Assembly meetings. Returns Roscoe's work on prisons. University bill to be pushed by James Breckenridge and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1708">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 December 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 285.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Bill to remove the University debt. References to Colonel Boyd, William F. Gordon, James Pleasants, and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1722">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 December 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 286.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. References to Thomas Miller and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1736">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 January 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 287-288.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University. Purchase of books. Reference to Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1750">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 January 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 288-290.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of the University bill. Funds for purchase of library and apparatus. Recommending Claude Crozet as professor of mathematics and Dabney Carr as professor of law. Mentions Alexander Garrett. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1764">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 February 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 293-294.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Logrolling attempt: University bill and the bill to recharter the Farmer's Bank. References to James Breckenridge, Alexander Garrett, William F. Gordon, and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1778">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 March 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 294-296.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University from the debt due Virginia from the Federal government. Francis Walker Gilmer's scheme of professorships. References to James Barbour, William F. Gordon, [George?] Hay, Chapman Johnson, James Madison, and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1792">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 March 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 296-299.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Complete victory of the friends of the University in the Assembly. Downfall of William and Mary seems certain. Suggests hiring of certain of the William and Mary faculty: John A. Smith, Mr. Campbell, James B. Rogers, and James Semple. References to John Bowyer, James Breckenridge, Alexander Garrett, William F. Gordon, Chapman Johnson, George Loyall, James Madison, and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1806">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Washington, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 April 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 299-301.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Attempt to get recognition of the University's claim to money owed Virginia by the United States. Monroe's recommendation of [James G.?] Percival and [John] Torrey for the University faculty. References to James Barbour, William H. Crawford, Chapman Johnson, and William Wirt. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1821">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell. Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 April 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 301-302.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Returning a horse loaned by T. J. Reference to Col. John Coles and to Mr. Maclure.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1835">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Bremo, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 April 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 303-304.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Agreeing to the engagement of the anatomical professor from Europe. Pleased to see the number of foreign professors is to be limited. Note by John Hartwell Cocke: "I concur with Mr. Cabell in the above." 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1849">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1824 May 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 305-308.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Attitude of the University toward the possible removal of the College of William and Mary from Williamsburg to Richmond. Views on the subject held by William Armistead, Colonel Bassett, Chancellor Brown, [John B.?] Clopton, Dr. Charles Everett, N. Faulcon, Dr. Galt of Williamsburg, [James M.?] Garrett, Thomas Griffin, Mr. Johnson of Williamsburg, George Loyall, Thomas Macon, Bishop Moore, Hugh Nelson, Mr. Nicholas, Brazure W. Pryor, Archibald Ritchie, Judge James Semple, Mr. Scott, John W. Sourell, L. W. Tazewell, and John Tyler. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1863">
        <did>
          <unittitle>James Madison, Montpellier, to Thomas Jefferson.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 May 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19
</container>
          <physdesc>L. 1 pp. Copy by J. C. Cabell.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 313; B of R IV 53 (MS. in DLC).
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Urging that the friends of the University of Virginia be passive in regard to the removal of William and Mary from Williamsburg to Richmond, Petersburg, or the western part of the state. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1877">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1824 June 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 314-315.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Illness of Mrs. [St. George] Tucker prevents his visiting T. J. at Monticello and the Madisons at Montpellier. Removal of William and Mary to Richmond.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1891">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 December 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:21
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 316-318.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cabell's business at Corotoman. Assembly politics with respect to the bill to move the College of William and Mary to Richmond and funds for the University. References to George Blaettermann, Francis T. Brooke, John Bowyer, William Brockenbrough, John Coalter, James M. Garnett, George Hay, Chapman Johnson, Mr. Leigh, Judge Marshall, James Madison, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and Robert B. Taylor. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1905">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 December 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:22
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 318-320.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Decision to vote against the bill to remove William and Mary to Richmond. Medical education at the University. References to Chapman Johnson and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1919">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 December 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:23
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 324-327.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Differences of opinion between Jefferson and Madison regarding the removal of the College of William and Mary to Richmond. Funds for the University. References to John Bowyer, Judge Dabney Carr, Francis W. Gilmer, William F. Gordon, George Loyall, Mr. Nicholas, James Pleasants, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., James Semple, John A. Smith, George Tucker, and John Tyler. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1933">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 January 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:24
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 328-329.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letter from George Tucker regarding a teaching position at the University. Application from Mr. Kidd for the position of professor of ethics. Bill for removal of William and Mary to Richmond to be rejected. Funds for the University. References to James Barbour, William F. Gordon, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., James Madison, and Judge James Semple. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1947">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 January 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:25
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 332-333.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Request that T. J. prepare a bill to prevent removal of William and Mary College to Richmond. Clergy, Richmond, and the Federalists all united in favor of removal. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1961">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 January 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:26
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 336.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Removal of William and Mary to Richmond. Articles in the Whig on the funds of William and Mary and the decision of the Court of Appeals in the case of Bracken and the College. References to Alexander Garrett and John A. Smith.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1976">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 January 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:27
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 336-337.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>News of Ship Competitor. Requests authorities to support the division of William and Mary's money. Mentions Dartmouth College case. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e1990">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:28
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 337-338.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Publication of a letter from T. J. to help prevent removal of the College of William and Mary to Richmond. Consideration of Francis W. Gilmer and Chancellor [St. George] Tucker for the law chair at the University. Suggests the professor of law be also given a small chancery district. References to Servant Jones and Richard Morris. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2004">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 February 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:29
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 341-342.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defeat of plan to remove William and Mary to Richmond. Plan for a general education system.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2018">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:30
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 343-345.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Defeat of the bill to remove William and Mary to Richmond. Delay in arrival of the University faculty. T. J.'s resolutions relative to primary schools. Expresses disapproval of a constitutional convention for Virginia. Opposition to Cabell in his senatorial district. References to John Bowyer, Judge Francis T. Brooke, Col. Benjamin Cabell, John Hartwell Cocke, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, George Loyall, and Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2032">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1825 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:31
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 346.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Funds for the University from interest claim of the Commonwealth of Virginia. References to George Loyall and Littleton W. Tazewell. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2046">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 February 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:32
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 346-347.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Arrival of the University faculty. Meeting of the Board of Visitors. References to Chapman Johnson, Francis Gilmer, George Loyall, and John Hartwell Cocke. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2060">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 February 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:33
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 347.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>aculty positions offered to [Henry St. George?] Tucker and to George Tucker. References to Judge John Coalter and [St. George] Tucker. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2074">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Norfolk, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 May 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:34
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 351.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Approves purchase of John M. Perry's land for the University. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2088">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Norfolk, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 May 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:35
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 353-354.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Approves choice of William A. G. Dade for the law chair. Splendid prospects for the University. Greetings from Mr. Maclure in Paris. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2102">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 December 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:36
</container>
          <physdesc> ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 357-358.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Death of his brother-in-law, Dr. Carter, prevents his attendance at Board of Visitors' meeting. New regulations at the University. References to John Hartwell Cocke, Thomas Cooper, Chapman Johnson, George Loyall, and [George] Tucker. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2116">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 January 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:37
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 360361.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Conference between George Loyall, Chapman Johnson, and Cabell regarding delay in the appointment of a law professor. Action regarding the William and Mary Bill. Conference regarding T. J.'s debts. References to Judge Francis T. Brooke, Judge Dabney Carr, Judge John Coalter, Judge John W. Green, and John T. Lemare. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2131">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1826 February 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:38
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 362.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Meeting of T. J.'s friends in support of the lottery. David S. Garland's bill for educational funds. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2145">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 February 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:39
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Partly printed: Cabell 367-369.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>T. J.'s plan for location of colleges throughout the state better than that of David S. Garland. Motion made by George Loyall regarding T. J.'s lottery. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2159">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 February 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:40
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 370-372.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Action in the Assembly with regard to T. J.'s lottery. Bill to establish colleges throughout the state. References to James Madison, Chapman Johnson, and Hampden-Sydney College. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2173">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 February 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:41
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 374-375.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>  T. J.'s lottery bill. Bill to establish colleges throughout the state. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2187">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 February 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:42
</container>
          <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J.  Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson.  Printed: Cabell 375-376.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Passage of T. J.'s lottery bill, with list of the votes of the senators. Bill for establishment of colleges throughout the state. Reference to Samuel Taylor. 
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2201">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors of the University of Virginia, at their meeting in October 1826. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 October 2-7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:43
</container>
          <physdesc> AD.  16 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2212">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors of the University of Virginia at their meeting in December 1826.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1826 December 4-16
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:44
</container>
          <physdesc> AD.  21 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2223">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Rector and Visitors. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 July 10-19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:45
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  14 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2234">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 July 10- July 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:46
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  12 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2245">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Board of Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 October 1- October 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:47
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  9 pp. #2791-a. 
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2256">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 July 14- July 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:48
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  12 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2268">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 July 14- July 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:49
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  14pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2279">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 July 12- July 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:50
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  21 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2290">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 July 11-July 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:51
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  16 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2301">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 July 12- July 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:52
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  20 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2312">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 September 3- September 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:53
</container>
          <physdesc>AD. 9 pp.   #2791-a. 
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2323">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 July 15- July 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:54
</container>
          <physdesc>AD. 19 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2334">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 July 2- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:55
</container>
          <physdesc>AD. 21 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2345">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceeding of the Visitors. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 August 11- August 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:56
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  12 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 July 3- July 4 and 1837 August 17- August 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:57
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2367">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 July 3- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:58
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  12pp. #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2378">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 October 2, 1839 November 16, 1839 April 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:59
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  6pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2390">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 July 4- July 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:60
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  16pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2401">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 November 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:61
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  14 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2412">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 March 22, July 1- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:62
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  8pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2423">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 July 4- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:63
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  7 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2434">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 July 4- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:64
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  8 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2445">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 April 23- April 24, 1845 July 2- July 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:65
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  12 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2456">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 January 20- January 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:66
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  9 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2467">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 June 25- June 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:67
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  10 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2478">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 June 27-June 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:68
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  11 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2489">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors. 
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 June 25- June 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:69
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  13 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2500">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 June 25- June 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:70
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  23 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2512">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 October 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:71
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  3 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2523">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 October 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:72
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  6 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2534">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 June 28- June 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:73
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  6 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2545">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 September 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:74
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2556">
        <did>
          <unittitle> Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 June 26- June 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:75
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  11 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2567">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 June 25- June 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:76
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  26 pp.  #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2578">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 September 1- September 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:77
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  9 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2589">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Proceedings of the Visitors.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854 June 26- June 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:78
</container>
          <physdesc>AD.  24 pp.  #2791-a.  
</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e2600">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Memoranda of Joseph C. Cabell.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[185-?].  
</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:79
</container>
          <physdesc>ADs, 9 items. #2791-a.
</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Concerning passages of Jefferson correspondence omitted from Nathaniel Francis Cabell's Early history of the University of Virginia, as contained in the letters of Thomas Jefferson and Joseph C. Cabell, hitherto unpublished (Richmond, Va.: J. W. Randolph, 1856.)
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
