<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03875">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03875::Papers of Edward Jameson)//EN" "viu03875.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward Jameson <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1862-1871</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Jameson, Edward, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">12123
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6/3/2005 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward Jameson <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1862-1871</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">12123
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Edward Jameson
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1862-1871
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">12123
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Edward Jameson, Accession #12123, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Terry N. Layton, Long Grove, Illinois, on December 6, 2001.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of the papers of Edward Jameson, a soldier in the 4th Battery of the Massachusetts Volunteers of the Federal Army, 47 items, ca. 1862-1871. The letters are addressed to his brother,
James Jameson, who resides in South Reading, Massachusetts. Most of the letters are written while Edward is stationed in Louisiana during the Civil War.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">First Folder: 7 letters from 1862</title><lb/> January 31, 1862, Ship Island, Mississippi, says "doing quite well," "very healthy place," Rebel steamer came to Island under flag of truce,
wanted to possess an English ship seized in Mobile Bay; wonders if it a pretext to check condition of Ship Island; food good, not much going on, gives praise for General John Wolcott Phelps.
</p>
      <p>June 8, 1862, Camp Parapet, Louisiana, writes that New Orleans is becoming "quite a Union City," mentions a small skirmish at Baton Rouge with a Union repulse, thinks Union will soon attack Vicksburg, hears of
General Nathaniel Prentiss Banks' defeat in Virginia; wants brother to send Northern newspapers and knowledge of land, crops and trade from home in Massachusetts, predicts war will end by end of July, thinks he
will be paid a small amount soon.
</p>
      <p>June 22, 1862, Camp Parapet, Louisiana, says enjoyed recent "expedition," not scared by shelling, describes town of Madisonville and encounters no troops when arrives; reports Maine troops secure roads leading
out of town, they begin heading up the river to Covington (20 miles), but only go two miles and return to Madisonville, next day steam to Lake Pontchartrain.
</p>
      <p>July 4, 1862, Camp Parapet, recalls fun he and brother had on previous year, thinks at Vicksburg gunboats and ironclads should carry out attack, comments on how well New Orleans is defended, reports a large
steamer has arrived from Memphis, predicts Vicksburg and Richmond will fall very soon, comments on General George Brinton McClellan and other generals. September 25, 1862, Camp Williams near New Orleans, says he
expected to go to Fort Pike but the order was countermanded, laments fighting in District of Columbia, hears William [Human] has died and describes him as a "patriotic, honorable man," knows five men who have died
but thinks it a "great consolation to loved ones that they perished for such a glorious cause...." October 10, 1862, Camp Williams near New Orleans, mentions heavy losses on both sides at Antietam and doesn't
understand how the South got across the Potomac so easily, says the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Emancipation Proclamation</title> won't amount to anything because Lincoln does not have the power at present and nothing
can happen until he does, thinks that if the President were now to issue new call for soldiers would have as many as he could handle, a Captain [Kensel] went upriver under a flag of truce with prisoners to
exchange but was fired upon with the result that fifteen Rebels were killed; October 20, 1862, Camp Williams near New Orleans, says he is leaving for Fort Pike soon and is glad to depart as camp "was a very sickly
place." Thinks the war could have been carried out much better-"so much corruption in high places"-thinks war should be over by now but they are not getting anywhere, seems some don't care how long the war lasts,
especially those who supply soldiers, is glad to hear brother is going to buy new horse and urges him to save all the money he sends home and not to worry about paying back.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Second Folder: 13 letters from 1863</title><lb/> January 29, 1863, New Orleans, received a box with everything in it he wanted, doesn't like how war is being conducted as it seems each is
striving to be more popular than the one above, out for their own advancement and not the good of the country, says the "country is now plunged in debt and the whole south is not worth one half the lives that have
perished in this war." March 8, 1863, Baton Rouge, first calm Sunday in awhile with time to themselves the city is peaceful, very dead, only soldiers as "war makes sad havoc with a place," says Congress is trying
to push through a conscription bill, which he says is an "unlawful scheme," and is a "little homesick."
</p>
      <p>March 11, 1863, Baton Rouge, hears of a small skirmish ten miles away yesterday, predicts a tough fight at Fort Hudson, says he only wishes to do his duty honorably, has seen many "chicken out" and appear sick
at prospect of battle, but he is confident in battle now because a competent captain's handling of the battery; says if he is killed "not to worry about sending his body home," but is in high spirits and doesn't
expect to die.
</p>
      <p>April 28, 1863, Baton Rouge, received five letters and some papers recently with mail irregular, General Nathaniel Prentiss Banks has gone to Western Louisiana and is doing well against Rebels; reports say the
South has gunboats and is building more at Shreveport, but he feels they could successfully cut off Texas from the rest of the South. Also reports his forces have taken a salt mine in the lake with very good salt
which is very important to Southern forces, North has not been able to take Charleston, but hope ironclads will keep working at it.
</p>
      <p>May 13, 1863, Baton Rouge, May 19, 1863, Baton Rouge, reports he is in good health, says his battery is under Major General [Sugurst] and that Fort Hudson was bombed the previous day, causing the buildings in
Baton Rouge to tremble, many key generals' forces are nearby, expecting "stirring times before long," discusses his hopes for promotion and requests that papers, suspenders, tobacco, etc., be sent to him. July 13,
1863, Baton Rouge, reports he has just returned from (Plains), where he has been doing rear guard duty for a month, with 300 to 400 Southern cavalry attacking them at Springfield Landing, but none of his battery
was injured.
</p>
      <p>August 30, 1863, Baton Rouge, worried about James' possibility of being drafted but learns he is exempted because of a foot injury, reports fighting at Donaldsonville, with 150 Northern soldiers dying, but
Southerners retreated very fast and he expects reinforcements. September 18, 1863, Baton Rouge, has sent home $40 and will send $5 more soon, wants to know how his (James) new home looks, thinks markets around New
Orleans cannot compare to the "old Quincy Market," but he really likes the "coffee stands."
</p>
      <p>November 21, 1863, New Iberia, Louisiana, says Union cavalry captured 156 Southern cavalry with guns and horses, with Rebels around New Iberia all mounted and fast moving, is glad to hear that the Maine
Governor has been reelected, thinks Louisiana would have much more "Union sentiment" were it not for Southern soldiers, some papers say he will be out by next September, but he doubts it. December 13, 1863, New
Iberia, Louisiana, feels many signing up in Maine because of "large bounty" paid and that it is unfair that old veterans never get anything but monthly pay, doesn't think they need a draft but that volunteers are
enough. December 20, 1863, New Iberia, Louisiana, glad to hear James is able to meet mortgage payment, little going on but has "great quarters," is glad to hear Ulysses Grant is doing well.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Third Folder: 12 letters from 1864</title><lb/> January 2, 1864, New Iberia, Louisiana, reports many are reenlisting, but he doesn't expect to, says that there are many prisoners to
exchange-those that the North return to the South are in tip-top shape, but "our Northern men are in rags and are treated badly by the Southerners." January 12, 1864, Franklin, Louisiana, very cold, freezing rain
and snow, has reenlisted and got a bounty ($325 in State Treasury at 5%), also expects a 30-day furlough and is looking forward to a good time with brother at home. January 20, 1864, Franklin, Louisiana discusses
his failure to receive promotion to a commissioned officer but thinks his turn will come next.
</p>
      <p>April 10, 1864, New Orleans, Louisiana, says he took steamer from Boston to New York (following furlough) and got on another steamer with other regiments from New England and New York headed for New Orleans, a
trip that took ten days and two hours, thinks the "sunny south" would please any man if it had good government and a good society. May 2, 1864, New Orleans, talks briefly about battle at Red River-extra hard
fought with Southerners losing heavily. July 30, 1864, New Orleans, nothing much going on and hopes for marching orders because he is tired of New Orleans, would rather be on a march than in a city, says New
Orleans is an expensive place, says restaurants are bad and if someone would start a New England restaurant would make a fortune.
</p>
      <p>August 11, 1864, New Orleans, Louisiana, hasn't heard from James in a long while. But thinks it is possibly due to his involvement in the boat business, doesn't think James is obliged to stay in business with
partner with whom he doesn't agree and suggest he find another occupation, says not to worry about money James owes him, expects memo will be spread soon in Boston of Admiral David Glasgow Farragut's successful
attack on the Rebel navy and defense of Mobile, says he lost heavily but captured the whole Rebel team from Tennessee with 800 men, 26 guns, 1000 stand of arms, stores in abundance, and forced the Rebels to
evacuate Fort Powell, where they found 18 guns in good condition, making 44 guns in all.
</p>
      <p>August 18, 1864, New Orleans, Louisiana, expects draft is "all absorbing" question now in Massachusetts, The Governor of New York, Horatio Seymour, has protested the injustice of the allocation of state quotas,
with New York State having to furnish nearly 700 men to each Congressional District, more than Massachusetts, says General Edward Richard Sprigg Canby got his troops away from New Orleans in good shape. (They
embarked at the levee and went up the river, tied up somewhere along the bank and during the night went down the river past the city and away to Mobile.) Thinks Fort Morgan will "have to give up." Also says he
doesn't want to stay in New Orleans but "someone has to defend the place." Reports a large Rebel force still in Western Louisiana.
</p>
      <p>September 18, 1864, describes his job as an adjutant, thinks he will be sent into the field before long and is anxious to go, is taking great interest in the coming election September 5 to vote to ratify the
constitution of Louisiana-a new one formed by the present legislature of Union senators and representatives. November 6, 1864, Morganza Bend, Louisiana, has a new tent, describes the dimensions and construction in
detail, saying it has a chimney and a fireplace and is raised three feet high, "giving our nigger a chance to sleep underneath," have had much rain and snow and think some men would lose their shoes if they
traveled 200 yards.
</p>
      <p>December 24, Memphis, Tennessee, wants James to raise $300 necessary to bring Charlie (brother) home as he has been ill and looks bad in his photograph, says he will repay James and states the terms so if he
dies, his bounty and monthly pay will cover about $300.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Fourth Folder: 14 letters from 1865</title><lb/> January 6, 1865, Kennerville, Louisiana, left Memphis at 1 o'clock January 2 and arrived at New Orleans at 4 o'clock, no one permitted to go
ashore, stayed on the levee, steamed 14 miles to Kennerville, a place of a dozen houses. General Benjamin Henry Grierson went with them and a large force of the cavalry on the 28th and marched on to Germantown,
left Germantown at 2 P.M. and arrived at Memphis about 8:30 P.M. the same day. February 7, 1865, are moving on to Mobile, says he would rather be in the field than laying around camp, feels that on a march he is
"soldiering and doing something for his country."
</p>
      <p>February 23, 1865, Dauphin's Island, Alabama, has received orders to reduce baggage and thinks they will go on a long march soon, when he gets paid he will get eight months and two bounties of $350 each, has
plenty of clothing, health excellent and spirits good. March [7] 1865, Dauphin's Island, Alabama, still has not received eight months pay, but reports officers are worse off than men because they are expected to
pay for everything, muses about Charlie feeling bad because he was brought home, says his Corps commander is Major George Gordon Granger, and his Division commander is Brigadier General James Clifford Veatch.
</p>
      <p>April 15, 1865, Blakely, Alabama, is writing for transfer to Mobile, discusses terms of business of tin plate and sheet iron markers he and a friend intend to go into in New Orleans. April 16, 1865, Mobile,
Alabama, arrived last night from Blakely and face the Rebels-however, received joyful intelligence that General Robert E. Lee has surrendered the Confederate forces to the U.S. and that after a certain date,
whoever fires on the American flag shall be treated as an outlaw. April 25, 1865, Spring Hill, Alabama, describes the capture of Mobile and all its works-over 5,000 prisoners, more than 300 pieces of artillery,
vast quantities of ordnance, over 21,000 pounds of Brookes rifles, and 12 battle flags.
</p>
      <p>June 7, 1865, Mobile, Alabama, discusses being passed over for promotion and his mortification after three and a half years of service. June 21, 1865, Mobile, Alabama, hears they may not be discharged until
later part of next fall, war is over and there is not the "least bit of excitement except morning drill, talks of looking over some of the incidents of the Grand Reviews of the Army of the Potomac and of General
William Tecumseh Sherman's. It was thought that the first looked more jaunty and showed greater discipline, but the Army of General William Tecumseh Sherman was a fine looking body of men so far as height and
size." Thinks two Eastern regiments will do harder fighting than three Western-that they will march farther and not straggle so much and be more orderly in every way, thinks the "Army of the Potomac has done the
hardest fighting in the war and has come out with perfect soldiers."
</p>
      <p>July 11, 1865, Houston, Texas, tells of travels from Galveston to Houston. August 14, 1865, Houston, Texas, doesn't think Texas is more sickly than any other Southern state, although diarrhea, fever and ague
are the diseases most to be guarded against, thinks he may be mustered out soon, everyone seems to be homebound, September 4, 1865, Houston, Texas, discusses a Captain [Trall] who he says intends to remain in the
service although he didn't think much of him as a soldier, tells his brother to try to sell their farm, but not at a sacrifice as he understands things are prosperous in that area now. October 15, 1865, was
mustered out yesterday, had to make seven copies of "muster out rolls", explains details of mustering out process, plans to return home "up the river" by Cairo, Illinois, and would like James to repay him if he
can.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">4 letters from 1866</title><lb/> January 14, New Orleans, business not good the past week because of rain, expenses very heavy, discusses his indebtedness to James and other business
matters. February 18, 1866, thinks business is doing well now. March 15, 1866, New Orleans, discusses Southerners attitudes after the war, saying that those most prominent in the rebellion are striving to obtain
an honest livelihood and have little to say, papers exaggerating, mentions that in Mississippi lately some Northern men had from 20 to 25 mules stolen and "their persons threatened," but these outrages were
committed by outlaws; thinks North is wrong to try to keep Southern representatives out of Congress, that government has no right to tax a people without representation, and adds "I think Andy Jackson to be
perfectly right in many things lately done by him."
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Other letters from 1865-1871</title><lb/> This collection also includes three letters, one from E.H. Jameson to his sister, Sarah; another to James Jameson from Thomas H. Jameson, and a
third from William Wardwell to James Jameson. They are excerpted below:
</p>
      <p>Oxford, Mississippi, December 3, 1865, William Wardwell to James Jameson, writes about business matters, discusses abolitionists and matters concerning both their families and how they survived the war.
Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, April 15 (n.y.) to Sister Sarah from Edward H. Jameson, describes the people of Birmingham-Dutch, Welch, Irish and English-and their living conditions in coal mining areas, describes coal
mining procedures, plans to go see and oil well and a salt well and says he plans to go down a coal mine, where he expects to see "hundreds of white rats with pink eyes." Chicago, July 6, 1871, to brother James
from Thomas H. in which he describes his trip to Niagara Falls.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
