<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01601">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01601::Civil War Letters of Wallace James and His Wife, 1864)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01601.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01601::Civil War Letters of
             Wallace James and His Wife, 1864)//EN"
             "viu01601.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Civil War Letters of Wallace
            James and His Wife, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">James, Wallace, and his wife, Civil War
            Letters, 1864 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10874</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">23 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01601::Civil War
            Letters of Wallace James and His Wife, 1864)//EN"
            "viu01601.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Civil War Letters of Wallace James
         and His Wife, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10874</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Civil War Letters of Wallace James and His Wife 
         <unitdate label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1864</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10874</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of two letters.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Civil War Letters of Wallace James and His Wife, 1864,
            Accession # 10874, Special Collections Dept., University of
            Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were purchased by the Library from Theme
            Prints, Ltd., of Bayside, New York, on September 25,
            1989.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>These two 1864 letters were written by an Ohio Union
         soldier, Wallace James, and his unidentified wife. 
         <emph render="underline">Complete typescripts are included at
         the conclusion of this summary</emph>.</p>
      <p>Wallace James' letter of Monday, June 13, 1864, was written
         while he was stationed at Martinsburg, West Virginia. He
         declares his delight at receiving letters from his wife and
         describes Martinsburg weather as very cold but as having
         peaches and strawberries in abundance for he and his fellow
         Union soldiers. Local residents are characterized as being
         loyal to the Union cause and the ladies in the area treat
         Union soldiers well. As he was composing his letter a group of
         four refugee women with a combined total of twenty children
         passed his tent. He concludes with the hope that God would
         preserve his wife's health and encloses a ring (not present)
         for her that he had made while in camp and promises to send
         two more after they are finished; he says they are not worth
         anything but hoped they would please her.</p>
      <p>Mrs. James' letter is the more interesting of the two and
         was written on June 23-24, 1864, in New Madison, Darke County,
         Ohio. She confessed to having "the blues rather bad" until the
         arrival of two of Wallace's letters of June 19th and 20th, and
         mentions her activities (washing and ironing) and their
         [infant?] daughter, Getta. The first half of this letter ends
         with "i will quit for the present i have got to go wash and
         iron to morrow and it is after 9 now."</p>
      <p>Her letter resumes on Friday evening, June 24, 1864, at
         seven o'clock, with the observation that New Madison wives are
         becoming very uneasy, especially in regards to news of the
         capture of [Union General David] Hunter's supplies [by
         Confederate General Jubal Early, near Lynchburg]; a neighbor
         was concerned because she (the neighbor) had had no word from
         her husband in three weeks. Mrs. James contends that the war
         would last as long as there were men available and admits that
         even if Wallace were to come home he would probably be
         drafted. She also discusses her husband's lumber business and
         suggests that he hire a man to supervise it during his
         absence; certain customers were apparently helping themselves
         when she was not present at the shop. She ends her letter
         because of the baby's crying but expressed a willingness to
         write another sheet if she had the chance.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Transcripts</head>
      <p>Martins Burg Monday June the 13 1864</p>
      <p>Dear wife it is with pleasure that i take pen in hand to
         answer yours of the eight which came to hand on the eleventh i
         was on picket at the time and did not get in til yesterday at
         [noon?] then i was so tired and sleepy that I Cold not rite i
         slep every [night], since and i feel fine this morning i was
         happy to here from you and that you was well i hope that these
         lines may finde you in good health as it leaves me it is ?
         great satisfaction to me to reade your leaters [letters] if
         has bin very ? since the rest left and it is a pleasure to all
         of the boys to here from home we hae not herde from the boys
         since they left we loock for them in three or four dayes they
         have bin gon nine dayes it may be that we shal go some places
         i think we will stay here we had a very harde storm laste
         thirsday [morning?] it [threw?] down some of our tents and it
         has bin very Coold every since then this is a butiful morining
         yet Cold it is Cold here every nite and every [week?] ? in the
         day time every thing seams to ? , smooth here as fare as i
         know have slep so mulch that i hardley Can rite at all I
         forgot to say that i got one dolar in the the last i received
         and i have received two papers from you they were very
         acceptable to me they was oolde yet they Came from home i had
         thought of going to Church in town uesterday if i had bin in
         Campe the boyes that had the measels is all merley (?) well i
         shold like to stay in the hospitte if the time did not seame
         so longe i am happy to here that Cary is of good boy and tryes
         to help his mom i hope that he will be good that will be happy
         ? to me you had to Clean House I was in hopse that you wold
         leave it alone til I Came back I am afrade that i will make
         you sick i hope not since you have don it if we shold stay
         here til our time is out we can have plenty of peaches they
         are as big now as some i got last year when ripe they treas
         [trees] is very ful strawberys is ripe here i have sean plenty
         of them the ladies in this place tended on our boyes very well
         tho some of them was from Ohio yet there is a magority here
         loyal people i Canot loock one the rebels here with any good
         fealing tho i thinke they are they best of the to those at
         home there is at greate many refuges that Comes thro here and
         they mostly go to Ohio we have some good times with them they
         say tho they never will [never?] ? ? it is harde to tel what
         they ? i shal send a ring in this leter that i made for ? of ?
         rate with my wife i have a [two?] more they are not finished
         yet I shall send when i Can they are not worth any thing yet I
         th[ought?] if i made them they would pleas you they have just
         bin some refuges past here there was four women and that hade
         some twenty Children it loocked harde i shal have to Close
         this leter to get it in the ofice before the male [mail] goes
         oute and I will have to [drill?] rite when you Can May god
         persurve [preserve] your life is my prayer</p>
      <p>from your loving husband</p>
      <p>until death Wallace James</p>
      <p>June the 23 [1864]</p>
      <p>[New Madison, Darke Co.] Ohio</p>
      <p>Dearest husband i seat my self to answer yours of the 19
         and 20 that came to hand this evening you better believe i was
         hapy to get a letter for i had the blues rather bad to day i
         was shure that you was sick i had thought maybe that you was
         out on picket i would like to see you very much but i supose i
         must wait till the time comes for us to meet i feel very
         thankful that i got a letter to night i thank you my dear and
         good kind husband for ?ing us soon as you could may heaven
         bless you and protect you is my prayer this morning i was
         dressing Gretta and she put her litle arms up around my neck
         and kissed me and turned away i was wondered if she ever
         thought of and while i was thinking she turned around and said
         i wish you would come home i wish she could see you some place
         and see if she would know you it is very warm to night i have
         got the door open and windows it has not rained yet i am fraid
         that it will not rain soon anoughf [enough] to do any good
         Eliza sent word by John Jacobs for me to come down o[n]
         saturday i dont know wether i will go or not if i should go i
         will stop at a oaths and go over to henerys it will not cost
         me any mone [money] henery was here to night he wanted me to
         go down with him but i did not like to take the baby through
         the hot sun i was fraid it would make her and me both sick
         some how i dont want to go i have not more than 3 dolars and
         [a] half when i come back i will send you that other dolar i
         will ask mat snodgrass for that 40 ccts [cents] i am fared
         [afraid] that you will think i have bin exstravagent but i
         have not got only what i needed i went to the store and got
         some muslin they say that we will pay 50 cts a yard for calico
         before 2 months i got Getta a pair of shoes will i wont tell
         you what all i have got i have got it all set down well i will
         quit for the present i have got to go wash and iron to morrow
         and it is after 9 now</p>
      <p>freday evening 7 o clock June the 24</p>
      <p>Dear husband i have just receved another letter from you i
         was hoping to here from you again but i am sorry that you have
         to stand gard so much and i am all so sory that the boys have
         not got back their wives are geting very oneasey [uneasy?] a
         bout them it is rumored that some of hunters suplys was taken 
         <emph render="super">1</emph>i have not herd the particulars
         yet [emma?] northrop is very on easey [uneasy] i know that she
         must feele very bad for i dont know what i should do if i had
         not herd from you for 3 weeks i dont beleive this war will end
         as long as there is a man to fight i feel all most [almost]
         out of hart [heart] if you do come home it will only be to be
         drafted or be called out again right a way it[?] could ? a
         good deal to night if i had the chance but the baby is not
         very well and she is very cross i have washed and i roned
         [ironed] to day and cleaned up the sellar and i have a good
         deal to do if i go down to ? to morrow but if the baby gets
         any worse i will not got it is reported that ira macelannen is
         sent home dead i do not know wether it is so or not i think
         that you ought to have got some man to tended to your lumber
         and your things that you had partly made if you should have
         bad luck i dont Know what you had and never has a good call[?]
         of business in the shop and if [any?] body wants any small
         peace [piece] of lumber they Know where to go and get it if i
         hapen to see them they will tell what they wanted ? only knows
         how much is taken when i am gone well i must quit for now for
         the baby is cring [crying] ? to kill(?) if i go to paris 
         <emph render="super">2</emph>you will not get your letter as
         usall [usual] for i wiil not be at home on monday so dont be
         on easey [uneasy] i could write with a good will another sheet
         if i had the chance but you dont now [know] how hard it is
         sometimes to get to rite I dont espect you [will read them?] i
         dont have time to read them over</p>
      <p><emph render="super">1</emph>On June 23, 1864 Confederate
         General Jubal Early's forces captured part of Union General
         David Hunter's supplies as Hunter retreated from Lynchburg
         toward the Valley.</p>
      <p><emph render="super">2</emph>A town in Stark County.</p>
      <p>[END OF LETTER]</p>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
