<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02094">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02094::A Guide to the Papers of the Carpenter and White Families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02094.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02094::A Guide to the Papers of
             the Carpenter and White Families)//EN"
             "viu02094.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Carpenter and
            White Families, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1965</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Carpenter and White Families, Papers of
            <num type="collectionnumber">11613</num></subtitle><author>Robin D. Wear, October 31, 2001</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">29 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Lottie Baker, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2/04/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-19" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 19, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02094::A Guide to the
            Papers of the Carpenter and White Families)//EN"
            "viu02094.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Carpenter and White
         Families, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836-1965</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11613</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Robin D. Wear, October 31, 2001</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Carpenter and White Families, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1836-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11613</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 280 items, including personal correspondence,
         financial and legal papers, and genealogical data.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of the Carpenter and White Families, Accession #
            11613, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was a gift to the Library by Ms. Billie
            Lewis Barnes of 1705 Solomon Road, Charlottesville, Va.
            22901 on April 10, 2000.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 280 items, ca. 1836-1965,
         primarily personal correspondence of Frances Ann (White) and
         Alfred Carpenter. There are also financial and legal papers of
         the Carpenters and their children, Amanda, Stephen Alfred, and
         William L. Carpenter. Other material includes genealogical
         data on the Carpenter, White, Teel and related Anderson,
         Ellis, and Johnson families.</p>
      <p>Financial and legal papers, 1844-1876, of Alfred Carpenter
         include various accounts for the sale of cotton (1863),
         tobacco (1858), and oats, wheat and tobacco (1876); and, tax
         in kind estimates and assessments of agricultural products
         (1864) and bacon (1865), including one oversize (1865). There
         is an account of visits by William H. Pitts to "woman Betsy"
         and "boy Jack" for medicine and quinine, and to his wife for
         venesection. Legal papers include an appointment of a Court of
         Enquiry and Appeal (1847), an appointment as surveyor of roads
         (1864), and an Amnesty Oath signed by Alfred Carpenter. Other
         items of interest include settlement receipts on the estate of
         John Carpenter (1853, 1855) and a receipt for the exchange of
         a black mare heavy in foal (1862). There are miscellaneous
         accounts of Frances Ann (White) Carpenter and her children as
         well as a few miscellaneous accounts pertaining to John A.
         Brown and Fielding and Dabney Sprouse.</p>
      <p>Letters of Amanda Carpenter include a letter, March 16,
         n.y., to her brothers referring to their being anxious to join
         the army and letters, November-December 1880, concerning the
         love affair of Amanda and Captain John A. Jones.</p>
      <p>Letters between Frances Ann (White) and Alfred Carpenter
         range from December 1842 to September 1844. The main themes
         discussed between Frances and Alfred are their relationship,
         engagement, and marriage. Alfred's letters are usually lengthy
         and detailed, covering various subjects. Alfred writes chiefly
         from the Post Office in Richmond where he works, commenting on
         the work occasionally. A December 10, 1842 letter indicates
         that they have been busy since the meeting of legislation with
         a great deal of extra work and comments on the Democrats
         having everything in their own hands, hoping they will set an
         example by making this a short session, not hanging on until
         corn planting time according to custom. A December 28, 1842
         letter mentions news of a mail mishap in the canal involving
         the driver, horse and mail.</p>
      <p>There are various topics and comments of note or interest
         in the letters between Frances and Alfred. January 1843:
         everything going on "just as Parson [Samuel] Miller had never
         predicted the end of the world in April 1843"; revival
         commencing at the Methodist Church; eloquent discourse
         delivered by Reverend John Johns (1796-1876); exhibit of the
         "Mermaid" at the Exchange; temperance folks holding numerous
         meetings; weddings being quite in fashion; and, an expected
         revival and protracted meeting. February 1843: the "Orphan's
         fair" at the Exchange. March 1843: description of the wedding
         of Amanda M. Anderson and Benjamin F. Peters. April 1843:
         Richmond area flood and the suspension of navigation on the
         canal; revival at the Baptist churches with Elder Knapp
         holding forth every night, many turning from darkness unto
         light, and being the last warning to the "Sinners of
         Richmond." May 1843: Episcopal convention and several fairs
         being in preparation; a Mr. Pierre being baptized in the
         Campbellite faith. June 1843: the death of Fanny's aunt and
         inquiries as to the care of her little boy; the "General
         Baptist Association" in Richmond; new Methodist church being
         dedicated; the arrival of President John Tyler (1790-1862)
         accompanied by Postmaster General Charles Anderson Wickliffe
         (1788-1869), his attendance of worship at the Monumental, and
         his being a spry widower and probable candidate for matrimony;
         setting a wedding date; Reverend Moffitt expected at the new
         Methodist Church early July; her preference for the country
         and his for the city; their marriage not being romantic as
         "such never turn out well, when romance ceases love will too."
         July 1843: Alfred's birthday; plans for the 4th of July by the
         military companies and the teetotalers and oddfellows;
         opposition to her marriage and reservations about marrying
         someone not so close to home; and, Garnett Piper's wedding on
         the 27th. September and October 1843: the course of true love.
         November and December 1843: wedding being cancelled by Fanny
         and her family due to malicious rumors circulating about
         Alfred and poor no account relations in Greene, and the
         resolution upon realization that the reports were false.
         January and February 1844: previous engagement renewed,
         marriage arrangements, and marriage on February 20th. August
         1844: news from North Garden - father ill with rheumatism or
         shingles, local death from consumption; Richmond news -
         citizens with time and money have gone to the country or
         springs while the merchants have gone north for their fall
         purchases; and a humorous story about a lady who lost her
         bustle in the street; camp meeting in Chesterfield.</p>
      <p>There are personal letters, 1844-1869, to Alfred Carpenter
         from family and friends. There is a letter, April 13, 1844,
         from S. L. Moore of Locust Grove who is mortified to hear that
         she acted so imprudently, giving the appearance of being
         overly friendly, while in Richmond and that it caused an
         improper opinion of her. A letter, May 14, 1844, from John B.
         Carpenter to his brother, says that his father requests his
         presence at the sale and comments that "the Negroes will sell
         very high." On February 4, 1869, D. F. Slaughter negatively
         describes an event that took place on Christmas eve in
         Harrisonburg, writing that there was no official excursion, it
         was a badly managed and mangled affair with no time notice for
         the farmers to prepare for attendance without neglect and
         injury to his crops. This may refer to tobacco farmers during
         reconstruction. An August 18, n.y. letter from S. A. Webb,
         Glenmore, concerns Carpenter's school being broken up, his
         boarders leaving, and his delay in paying debts.</p>
      <p>There are various topics and comments of note or interest
         in the letters to Frances (White) Carpenter. A letter of
         November 1, 1842 gives a humorous account of the infare of
         Julia A. J. Elsom and William Brown the evening following
         their marriage. Letters of October and November 1842 offer
         lengthy and detailed and often witty descriptions of the
         revival at North Garden. On October 25th, Susan A. Durrett,
         North Garden, writes about the different converts and moaners.
         On November 9, John M. Carr, Garlands, discusses the great
         revival amongst the Methodist and the great number who have
         professed religion and joined the church. He also mentions the
         infare and fandango of the Browns and gives a discourse on
         love and marriage and his feelings for his loved one, Sally
         Brown. There is a November 9 letter from Pat Haskell,
         University of Virginia, his just having "returned from the
         North Garden, otherwise Holy land..." where nearly everyone
         was converted; he shares amusing stories of the revival and
         gives a very comical narrative of the revival. On November 16,
         S. L. Woods, Apple Grove, gives a lighthearted view of the
         revival and everybody getting religion and shares a humorous
         story about him mistaking another woman for his wife at the
         revival. January 1843 letters discuss relatives possibly being
         descendants of Miles Cary and claims on the Cary estate and
         encourage Fannie to accept Alfred Carpenter's attention. On
         August 1, 1843, Pat Haskell writes from Memphis, Tennessee
         about deer and bear being plentiful for hunting and Colonel
         Virginius Leake's hound dog, Caleb. A November 18, 1843 letter
         from Benjamin C. Burnete, Bowling Green, discusses the
         character of Pat Haskell. There is a very spiritual letter,
         September 2, 1844, praising Fannie for being born again and
         getting religion. On August 24, 1861, there is a letter from
         Alfred in Lewisburg giving news of some of the soldiers and
         recent skirmishes. On April 21, 1862, Sallie writes from
         Ridgway, Albemarle that she wishes she could do something for
         the comfort of the soldiers; she expresses sympathy for the
         soldiers and their hardships. A letter, May 20, 1863, from
         Richard Carson Triplett, laments the loss of Stonewall Jackson
         as irreparable and favorably comments on General Ambrose
         Powell Hill being in charge of his corps. Triplett also writes
         on December 3, 1865 from Round Hill that he joined Colonel
         [John Singleton] Mosby where he remained until February 18,
         1864 when he was captured and taken to the 'Old Capitol' for
         four months and then to Fort Delaware for the remainder of the
         war. Triplett also comments on the surrender of the South,
         loss of "Negro labor" and the death of Dr. Martin of
         Albemarle. There is a letter, March 15, 1866, from Fannie's
         nephew, Allensville, Kentucky, discussing his dry goods and
         groceries store and business. There are two letters, 1879 and
         1880, from Louis T. Hanckel, Charlottesville attorney,
         concerning some property of the Carpenters.</p>
      <p>There are also letters to Frances Carpenter from her
         relatives, chiefly concerning personal and local news. Two
         letters, November 1842, from cousins relate more lively
         comments about the revival held in North Garden and the
         wedding and post-party of William Brown. There is also a
         letter, July 1, 1844, concerning another revival held in North
         Garden, which relates some of the stories of the
         participants.</p>
      <p>There are a few miscellaneous items such as poetry, notes,
         a recipe, an advertisement, social cards, and an oversize silk
         printing of "President Jackson's Farewell Address to the
         People of the United States."</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
