<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03130">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03130::Charles Fenton Mercer Letters)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03130.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03130::Charles Fenton Mercer
             Letters)//EN" "viu03130.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Charles Fenton Mercer
            Letters</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Mercer, Charles Fenton, Letters 
            <num type="collectionnumber">1471-b</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Katherine Schumann, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09/04/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03130::Charles Fenton
            Mercer Letters)//EN" "viu03130.xml" converted from EAD 1.0
            to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Charles Fenton Mercer
         Papers</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">1471-b</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Charles Fenton Mercer Letters 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1810-1856</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">1471-b</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ten items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Charles Fenton Mercer Letters, Accession #1471-b ,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This material was purchased by the Library from Jerry
            Showalter -- Bookseller of Ivy, Virginia, on April 22,
            1997.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>There are ten items, chiefly letters, 1810-1856, from
         Charles Fenton Mercer (1778-1858) of Leesburg, Virginia, to
         John Janney and Richard H. Henderson, both of Leesburg, Loudon
         County, Virginia. Correspondence, 1836-1855, with Henderson
         and Janney pertains to a dispute with Peter and Nathan Skinner
         over a boundary line. Letters of October 1856 to Janney
         provide a discussion of the political and historical unrest
         during that time.</p>
      <p>Charles Fenton Mercer was born in Fredericksburg, Virginia,
         on June 16, 1778, the son of James and Eleanor (Dick) Mercer.
         He graduated from the College of New Jersey (now Princeton
         University) in 1797, and did his postgraduate in law from
         1797-1800. He was admitted to the Virginia Bar in 1802 and was
         a member of the Virginia House of Delegates from 1810-1817. He
         was an advocate for increased banking capital of Virginia, the
         colonization of free United States African-Americans in
         Africa, and the building of roads and canals. He served as
         lieutenant colonel of a Virginia regiment and as major in
         command of Norfolk, Virginia during the War of 1812; he was
         appointed inspector general in 1814, aide-de-camp to Governor
         James Barbour, and brigadier general in command of the 2nd
         Virginia Brigade. He was a member of the United States House
         of Representatives from Virginia from 1817 to December 1839,
         during which time he served on the committee on canals and
         roads and the committee on the District of Columbia, and gave
         a speech, 1819, attacking Andrew Jackson's maneuvers in the
         Seminole War. He was the first president of the Chesapeake and
         Ohio Canal Company, 1828-1833, and a member of the Virginia
         Constitutional Convention, 1829-1830. He advocated male
         suffrage, the popular election of important officers, and
         equal representation. Mercer died on May 4, 1858, in Howard,
         Virginia, and is buried in Union Cemetery, Leesburg,
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>There are six letters, 1810-1856, from Charles Fenton
         Mercer to John Janney and others. There is a letter, November
         18, 1810, to an unknown recipient, which refers to a claim on
         the estate of Matthew Harrison. A letter, February 21, 1820,
         from the House of Representatives, to Addison H. Clark,
         Occoquan, Virginia, provides assurance "that every attention
         shall be given to this petition of the poor old soldier which
         I can render --" and further explains that the number of
         pensioners is so great that a prejudice exists against further
         extension of the pension lists. He comments that the Missouri
         question occupies the time of the congress and that most other
         business will be delayed until another session. A letter,
         January 29, 1839, from Washington, D. C. to John Janney,
         Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, discusses Mercer's suit
         against Peter and Nathan Skinner for the establishment of a
         boundary line between their lands which affects several acres,
         commenting on the patents and the survey and relating that Mr.
         Harrison is the counsel for the Skinners. The following
         letter, May 16, 1841, from Boston, Massachusetts, to Janney,
         reveals that the boundary dispute has been referred to
         arbitration and mentions Theodore S[tanford] Garnett. In his
         letter of October 6, 1856, from "The Healing Springs," Hot
         Springs, Virginia, to Janney, Mercer mentions his plans to go
         to Clarksburg, Virginia, where he has some affairs to settle,
         lands to sell, and debts to collect; comments on Janney's name
         and speech being in the newspaper; mentions the speeches of
         [Henry Alexander] Wise (1806-1876) and others; comments that
         although he is pleased to see the movement at Wheeling [West
         Virginia] he does "sincerely and deeply sympathize with my
         slave holding friends..."; states that he is no advocate for
         slavery and discusses further his beliefs and views toward
         slavery and emancipation, mentioning the latter in
         relationship to apportionment of representation; comments on
         the possible effects if John Charles Fremont (1813-1890)
         should be elected president over James Buchanan (1791-1868);
         and, discusses the impending civil war between the Confederacy
         and the Union. In the following letter, October 23, 1856, from
         "The Healing Springs," Mercer discusses his thoughts on an
         address from the county to the United States reviewing the
         state of Virginia and the Union; refers to the incidents which
         led to "the call of a convention to amend our constitution of
         state government and the very large and respectable assembly
         which gave birth to the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal"; comments
         on the madmen and South Carolina statesmen "who desire to
         establish the seat of a new Confederacy at Columbia and to
         make Charleston the great emporium of the South"; and, further
         comments that they "would dissolve the union now as they would
         have done to defeat a protective tariff..."</p>
      <p>There are four letters and documents, 1836-1855, of Charles
         Fenton Mercer and Richard H. Henderson, which pertain to the
         dispute over a boundary between Mercer and Peter and Nathan
         Skinner. On March 15, 1836, Mercer writes from Washington, D.
         C. to Henderson, Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia,
         concerning the suit against the Skinners, enclosing a copy of
         the original patent and a copy of the deed used by the
         Skinners (not with the letter). There is a letter of November
         8, 1836 concerning the issuance of a writ against Peter and
         Nathan Skinner to buy the title to the piece of land and the
         writ, November 22, 1836, to the sheriff of Loudoun County
         commanding Nathan Skinner and Peter Skinner to render unto
         Charles F. Mercer one tenement containing sixteen acres of
         land... There is a draft, [June 1855], of a similar document
         which includes references to the survey lines and contains
         notes on the verso dating February 1838 to June 1855.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
