<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01831">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01831::A Guide to the Journal of a Trip to California, 1849)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01831.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01831::A Guide to the Journal of
             a Trip to California, 1849)//EN" "viu01831.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Journal of a Trip to
            California, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Journal of a Trip to California, 1849 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10494</num></subtitle><author>Sharon Defibaugh, 2001 March 6</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2013 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">25 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/12/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01831::A Guide to the
            Journal of a Trip to California, 1849)//EN" "viu01831.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Journal of a Trip to California, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10494</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2013</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Sharon Defibaugh, 2001 March 6</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Journal of a Trip to California, 
         <unitdate label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10494</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of two items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains two diaries, probably by F.W. Brooks, describing a gold rush
         journey to California from May to August 1849. There is also a typed transcription by Richard L. Rieck</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>F.W. Brooks, Journal of a Trip to California, 1849
            April-August, Accession #10494, Special Collections,
            University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the University of Virginia
            Library by Albert N. Barnes of the Mariner's Museum,
            Newport News, Virginia, on March 4, 1982.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of two diaries, a condensed
         original in pencil and a later copy in ink with fuller
         details, both describing the same trip across the prairie to
         the gold fields of California, May 5 to August 15, 1849,
         probably by F.W. Brooks, an agent of Francis J.C. Peesley.</p>
      <p>The penciled account is preceded by a copy of instructions
         in ink from Peesley to Brooks written at Burlington, Iowa, and
         dated April 7, 1849, concerning arrangements for exchanging
         mail until his arrival in the gold fields, "I shall write you
         at New Helvetia, Suter's place and probably to his care. If
         the party do[es] not winter at San Francisco you will have
         letters addressed me at that place by last of December so that
         I can easily find you on my arrival."</p>
      <p>He urges him to write at every opportunity after he leaves
         Fort Laramie, and "as soon as you arrive in Sacramento if you
         cannot get letters immediately forward from New Helvetia you
         must take measures to get your letters to San Francisco as I
         shall wait until 1st January to hear from you but not longer."
         The volume in ink includes an additional entry for April 2 and
         a summary of the entire trip at the end of the volume not
         present in the penciled version.</p>
      <p>The writer begins his diary at his crossing of the Missouri
         River at Iowa Point on May 5, 1849, by ferry after having
         joined Captain Hindley's party. On May 7, he found supplies of
         bacon, beans, and flour left behind by a previous party. They
         passed by a funeral for one of the St. Louis Company who died
         of smallpox (May 9); scarcely avoided a stampede (May10)
         forded the Big Blue River (May 11); since leaving the Missouri
         River, they have passed four new graves of emigrants and have
         heard rumors of trouble in the Burlington Boys Camp a day
         behind them (May 12); now his party consists of 21 wagons and
         60 men (May 15); saw several antelope, but were unable to kill
         them; opportunity to send letters back to St. Joseph (May
         16-17); describes the circumstances of Mr. Shield?s homicide
         of his traveling companion, Mr. Harris, a blacksmith from
         Burlington and convicted rapist, for insulting his wife (May
         19); describes Fort Kearney and a trading post near Grand
         Island on the Platte River (May 19); mentions the visit of a
         band of Sioux Indians returning from their chase of Pawnees
         (May 20); saw and killed his first buffalo (May 22); camped in
         the Platte Bottom unable to make a fire because the buffalo
         chips were soaked (May 25) and continued along the Platte
         River (May 26-31).</p>
      <p>They next camped at Scotts Bluff, Nebraska near the
         Robidoux blacksmith shop and trading post (June 2); were
         joined by Captain McCulloch's company from Missouri and the
         captains decided to make cottonwood canoes to take themselves
         over the Platte River and avoid waiting for the ferry, almost
         losing several men in the swift current; these were saved by
         some men from Captain Hay's Ohio Company behind them (June
         11); an argument broke out with another team to the rear of
         the Ohio Company over use of the boats in crossing the river,
         showing a keen sense of competition in reaching the gold
         fields ahead of others (June 11); and they left the Platte
         River (June 13).</p>
      <p>Camping along the Sweetwater River (June 14); the second
         lightening of the wagons commences, including box goods, a keg
         of powder, and flour, and throwing away spare tools, "our long
         drive, teams failing and the necessity of keeping our position
         compel it our only means of saving ourselves alive" (June 17);
         they pass the Big Sandy River and Green River (June 22-23),
         ferrying the wagons over the Green River (June 24- 25); George
         and Reuben Worrell are sick with a bowel complaint (June 27);
         and found a large encampment of Shoshones (June 28).</p>
      <p>He then describes the hot springs near the Bear River in
         Wyoming (July 2-3); reaching Fort Hall near Portneuf, Idaho
         (July 4); American Falls (July 6); rumors of plentiful gold
         ahead, "every male has left Oregon" (July 7); Goose Creek,
         Idaho (July 10); description of hot and cold springs (July
         12-13); difficulties because the [Mary's River?] area very dry
         and dusty at this time (July 19-26); some other teams made a
         side trip to the Salt Lake region in Utah to exchange their
         worn out cattle for fresh ones with the Mormons; some Indians
         have shot cattle in the train ahead of them; and laments there
         is no water or grass for their animals (July 27-28); preacher
         Brace from Mercer County, Illinois, preached them a sermon;
         the writer discusses the loss of cattle and human illness from
         drinking bad water in the "Mary's River Sink" area; and
         expresses happiness at reaching the Salmon Trout River (July
         29-31).</p>
      <p>They are finally in timber country (August 5); saw the
         Donner party cabins with bones strewn around the buildings at
         Donner Pass, California (August 7); arrived at summit of the
         Sierra Mountains in good time but the road was very steep and
         winding; passed Truckee Lake, California (August 8); in good
         timber area (August 10); talk with the first miners they have
         run across on the journey (August 12); have arrived in the
         gold digging area, about thirty-five miles from Johnson's
         (August 14); and all hands help build a log warehouse for
         storage (August 15).</p>
      <p>At the end of the penciled volume are accounts for
         provisions and equipment, some dated in April, presumably
         before the trip began. The conclusion of the account in ink
         summarizes the journey. They had traveled about 1,950 miles
         from the Missouri River in 98 days, with an ox train of twenty
         wagons. One wagon left for the Oregon Road and one old wagon
         was left at the Hot Springs. They actually only traveled for
         80 of the 98 days, so averaged about 25 miles per day along
         with driving their cattle. He also discusses all the
         fallacious rumors about the reputation of their leader,
         Captain Hindley and finishes with his advice for those
         contemplating the trip across the prairie.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
