<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01713">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01713::Papers of Jackson Davis, 1910-1947)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01713.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01713::Papers of Jackson Davis,
             1910-1947)//EN" "viu01713.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Jackson Davis, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1910-1947</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Davis, Jackson, Papers, 1910-1947 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3072-b</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">63 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09/04/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002, May 22</date>
        <item>Added links to electronic texts of travel
            diaries</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01713::Papers of
            Jackson Davis, 1910-1947)//EN" "viu01713.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Jackson Davis, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1910-1947</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3072-b</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Jackson Davis 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1910-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3072-b</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         contains ca. 100 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Jackson Davis Papers, 1910-1947, Accession # 3072-b,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection of material related to Jackson Davis,
            and his work on education in the South, was made a gift to
            the Library by Sally Guy Brown and Helen Langhorne of
            Alexandria, Virginia, on February 11, 1999.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form</head>
        <p>Both the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/browse-mixed-new.chris?id=Dav1911&amp;data=/texts/english/davis&amp;tag=public">1911</extref>and the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/browse-mixed-new.chris?id=Dav1913&amp;data=/texts/english/davis&amp;tag=public">1913</extref>travel diaries
            are available as electronic texts.</p>
      </altformavail>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 100 items, 1911-1999,
         pertaining to Jackson Davis and his work with the General
         Education Board, the State Board of Education, and education
         in Africa. Included are letters, typescripts, papers,
         photographs, printed, and travel journals.</p>
      <p>General Education Board papers include a 1942 statement
         concerning automobile travel and the use of gasoline by Davis
         as associate director of the General Education Board and a
         1946 address by Davis given at the unveiling of the bust of
         Booker T. Washington. There is also an undated fragment of a
         letter discussing the missionaries in Africa and various
         places, including the Belgian Congo; Las Palmas, Canary
         Islands; and, Treetown, Sierra Leone. There are statements,
         ca. 1940, on counties in Alabama.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1942-1945, from Jackson Davis discuss activities
         in South America and Africa. A letter of October 27, 1942,
         from Bogota, Colombia, mentions activities and gives brief
         descriptions of Bogota and Lima, Peru. A November 8, 1944
         letter, from Lagos, Nigeria, mentions Dr. [John] Bugher's
         study of the jungle type of yellow fever and plans to go to
         the Belgian Congo. A letter of November 19, 1944, from
         Leopoldville, Congo Belge, mentions activities; plans to
         travel to Stanleyville; the death of [John Stewart] Bryan and
         the reelection of [Franklin Delano] Roosevelt; and, describes
         Leopoldville and its situation on Stanley Pool. A December 4,
         1944 letter, from Leopoldville, concerns mission, medical, and
         educational work in the heart of Africa, including villages
         and towns of Stanleyville, Yakusu, and Kindu.</p>
      <p>News from Africa letters from Jackson Davis discuss
         activities in Africa on an official basis. Letters of November
         11 and December 12, 1944, from Leopoldville, Congo Belge,
         discuss war-time conditions in Liberia and at Achimata
         College; activities and meetings with various people,
         including African-American journalist [Thomas White] Young
         (1908-1967), officials at Achimata College, John Bugher, and
         the United States Vice Consul. The latter letter discusses
         visits to Kisantu, Sona Bata, and Kimpese in regard to
         educational, medical, and agricultural facilities and
         programs; visits to Stanleyville, Yakusu, Ineac (the
         government's main Agricultural Experimental Station), Tunda,
         and Wembo Nyama. A January 7, 1945 letter, from Zaria,
         Nigeria, discusses visits to Duala, Bangwa, Baffousam, N'Diki,
         Dshang, Abeokuta, Ibadan, and Zaria. A letter of January 25,
         1945, from Lagos, Nigeria, discusses visits to Zaria, Kano,
         Arochuku (Scottish Mission), Akwa Training School; several
         native rulers; and, refers to the influence of pagan customs
         and the Moslem system of "Purdah."</p>
      <p>There are also letters of condolence to Robert D. Calkins,
         Associate Director of the General Education Board, from
         various college presidents and officials and missionary
         councils. Correspondents include P. Tulane Atkinson, Harry
         Clemons, Virginius Dabney, Spright Dowell, Joseph Dupuy
         Eggleston, Francis Pendleton Gaines, Ivey F[oreman] Lewis, E.
         G. McGehee, Jr., Fred T. Mitchell, John Davison Rockefeller,
         Jr., Anson Phelps Stokes, E. G. Swem, and Dean Acheson.</p>
      <p>There are photographs, 1940-1943, of Jackson Davis; General
         Education Board members; Jackson Davis Elementary School;
         Davis grave markers; natives in Africa; Davis with Charles E.
         Diehl and Sir William Beveridge; and others.</p>
      <p>Travel journals, 1911 and 1913, kept by Jackson Davis,
         chiefly describe his tours and activities through towns in
         Virginia and North Carolina and discuss the education of
         African-Americans. Entries of January 1 to June 7, 1911
         consist of minimal personal entries. During mid-June, Davis
         travels to the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute and
         St. Paul's School in Petersburg; Hampton Institute and the
         Trade School and Dow Science Building; and the University of
         Virginia summer school registration. He discusses the
         significance of training mind and will through hand. A visit
         to Hampton [Institute] Summer School provides a discussion on
         building an African-American school outside of Hampton. During
         June 23-26, Davis attends conferences in Montreat, North
         Carolina. He mentions students in "Negro Life classes";
         comments on John Little's method of teaching
         African-Americans; describes his view of the climb of
         "Graybeard" with Charles Edward Stowe (1850-1934); and,
         mentions work on the Committee on Negro Association with
         George Foster Peabody (1852-1938), Samuel Chiles Mitchell
         (1864-1948), John Little, and [Willis Duke] Weatherford (1875-
         ). From June 27 to July 4, Davis is in Charlottesville,
         meeting with [Hollis Burke] Frissel (1851-1917), [Charles
         Gilmore] Maphis (1865-1938), K[ary] C[admus] Davis
         (1867-1936), [Charles William] Kent (1860-1917), and [Bruce
         Ryburn] Payne (1874-1937). He refers to Frissell's comments on
         improving the economic conditions of African-Americans and
         Kent's suggestion that there should be "negro trustees for the
         colored schools." He also provides a quote concerning Thomas
         Jefferson's scheme for the education of the people of Virginia
         and describes the pageant of the Virginia Delegation. On July
         5-6, Davis visited Virginia Union University in Richmond,
         meeting with its president [George Rice] Hovey (1860-1943) and
         [Algernon Bertrand] Chandler, Jr. (1870-1928). He refers to
         Hovey's comments on "the idea of 
         <emph render="italic">higher work</emph>." On July 7-8, Davis
         met with Colonel [Samuel Harden] Church (1858-1943); he refers
         to the Virginia Plan and other improvement plans and the
         improvement of summer school each year. On July 18, there is
         the Rural Life Conference in Charlottesville; comments are
         made on topics covered by [Hollis Burke] Frissell, Caroline P.
         Davis, Edwin Mims (1872-1959), and [Bruce Ryburn] Payne and on
         his own speech on "The Negro in Country Life." Davis' next
         visits were to Hampton, where he met with [Joseph Dupuy]
         Eggleston (1867-1953) and attended the Negro Conference;
         Harrisonburg, and Manassas, where he met with 
         <persname normal="Leslie">L[eslie]</persname><persname normal="Pinckney">P[inckney]</persname>Hill
         (1880-1960), discussing personnel and tuition. During July 26
         to 29, Davis went to St. Louis, Missouri to speak to the
         National Association of Teachers "in colored schools." He
         describes the land from Cincinnati to St. Louis, refers to
         feelings of discrimination in the distribution of funds and to
         comments made by T. C. Walker, 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="Manuel">M[anuel]</persname>Gandy (1870- ),
         and others. In early August, Davis writes about the
         Superintendents' Conference in Farmville, and later discussing
         comments made by Eggleston on the work of examiners and their
         role in having measures enacted by the State Board of
         Education. On August 23-24, he is with the Appomattox
         Association in session Baptist Church and discusses schools
         and colleges doing great work but that county funds are being
         drained. In late August, Davis visits various family vegetable
         gardens in Halifax County, commenting on the vegetables,
         cultivation, and canning. On September 2, Davis had a
         conference with [Charles Gilmore] Maphis and others in regard
         to colored schools; he lists the points agreed upon and
         mentions Julia Ferguson and Josephine Pride. On September 7,
         Davis met in Richmond with [Willis Duke] Weatherford, John
         Stewart Bryan (1871-1944), and R. M. Smith. There were visits
         to homes, vegetable gardens, and tobacco fields in Nottoway
         County; he comments that African-Americans are more prosperous
         here. During September, he also made visits to homes, farms,
         and schoolhouses in Dixondale and Gloucester. There are
         statistics on property owned by African-Americans, criminal
         records, and lists of Baptists churches and preachers in
         Centralia, Chesterfield County. Late September, in South
         Boston, canned goods were being set up for the canning exhibit
         at Suggs and Jones Store; and, in Cumberland, there was an
         exhibit of tomatoes and canned goods by African-Americans.
         During October, Davis visited schools in Hampton, Elizabeth
         City County, Brunswick County, Henrico, and Caroline County.
         There are negative comments about conditions in Brunswick
         County, including children being infected with hookworm and
         lands being neglected. In Charlottesville, there was a
         conference with B. C. Caldwell, Johnson, Everett, Shelton, and
         Josephine Pride. On October 16, Davis visited Virginia
         Randolph and discusses briefly her plan of industrial work.
         Following a visit to Caroline County, he mentions Bowling
         Green Industrial Academy, Mattie Holmes, Virginia Union
         University in Richmond, [George Rice] Hovey, and colored
         churches. In Petersburg, he attended sessions of the Colored
         Bible Study Institute and mentions Lottie Jefferson and the
         canning exhibit. From October 23-27, Davis was in Gloucester,
         and comments extensively on a Mr. Folkes, a minister, born to
         a colored wet nurse; comments on visits to schools (white and
         colored) and a meeting of teachers. Topics discussed in the
         meeting were health, morality, home improvement, economic
         improvement, industrial work, and rural development. From
         November 4-9, Davis was in Hampton, where he had conferences
         with Wallace Buttrick (1853-1926), Wickliffe Rose (1862-1931),
         [Joseph Dupuy] Eggleston, and [Hollis Burke Frissell]. He
         mentions several points, including Colonel Church's
         resignation and the poor condition of Union State School as
         well as speaking on school and farm demonstration. While in
         Burkeville November 10-14, Davis mentions Reaumur Coleman
         Stearnes (1866-1945) and his philosophic address. In Honaker,
         November 17-18, Davis met at Honaker School with principal H.
         C. Williams and mentions Dorothy Mitchell, the Russell County
         Teachers Association, Fugate, the need for trained teachers,
         and Mr. Swain, principal of Agricultural High School in
         Lebanon. On November 22, he mentions Farmers' Warehouse,
         tobacco acreage and sales, prosperous farmers growing tobacco,
         the Farmers Cooperative Guano Company, and a visit to
         Blackstone Colored High School. On November 22, in Richmond,
         he mentions Health Day, Arthur Wright, Chester Colored School,
         Lottie Jefferson, and a meeting of the State Board. Notes from
         November 28-30 discuss the Education Conference, the meeting
         of the Executive Committee Cooperative of the Education
         Association, a proposal to ask the Southern Education Board
         for a larger amount this year, and DeJarnett's Colored League.
         He also comments on addresses by [Joseph Dupuy] Eggleston and
         Miss Jessie Fields of Page County, Iowa on rural schools.
         During December, Davis traveled to Williamsburg, Kenbridge,
         Richmond, and Hampton. On December 11, he comments on Miss
         [E.G.] Agnew's idea of combining home and garden work with the
         school curriculum and on the discussion of the Board of
         Examiners. There is a memorandum including a list of books
         read near the end of the journal.</p>
      <p>Davis' 1913 travel journal includes entries discussing his
         visits to schools and counties in Virginia from January
         through October. On January 3, he visited Caroline County,
         where he met Superintendent John Washington; he describes the
         Dawn school building. On January 10, in Williamsburg, he
         discusses a meeting of teachers in five peninsula counties for
         the purpose of organizing a school fair. While in the office,
         Davis refers to various people and topics: [Reaumur Coleman]
         Stearnes, [Wallace] Buttrick; [Charles Gilmore] Maphis, [ ]
         Robinson, and [James Hardy] Dillard (1856-1940); an offer of
         the position of secretary and his decision to stay with
         current work; the need for field men; a meeting on
         arrangements for the Conference of Education in the South next
         April; [Joseph Leonard] Jarman's (1867-1947) comments on
         Virginia Military Institute; and, plans for Health Day. From
         January 15-17, he visited Hampton, Dinwiddie, and Prince
         Edward County, and mentions a visit to Shellbanks with Dr.
         Phenix, the condition of schools in Dinwiddie, meeting P.
         Tulane Atkinson at Farmville, and the condition of schools in
         Felden. In Hampton, February 1-3, Davis discusses the
         Founder's Day Exercises and meeting all colored supervisors
         and demonstrators on one side and white supervisors in front;
         he mentions Rhea Scott, Margaret McCane, Sue Cleaton, Lottie
         Jefferson, E. G. Agnew, Virginia Randolph, and Norah Bocock.
         During mid-February, he mentions visits to Henrico Industrial
         School, Greenwood Mountain Road School, Pole Road Industrial
         School; needing two women in Hampton to help John B. Pierce
         supervise the canning; and, a meeting of colored teachers at
         Centralia, Chesterfield County. On March 4-5, he mentions
         visits in Goochland to the Court House, Miller Colored School,
         and Beaver Dam Colored School; meeting in Henrico with J.L.
         Sibley, supervisor of Negro Rural Schools in Alabama; a visit
         to Jeter School and Industrial School; and, meeting Virginia
         Randolph. On March 6, he describes visits to rural schools in
         Middlesex, and mentions Saluda High School, the Exhibit of
         Colored Schools, Sibley's lecture on work in the Philippines,
         and a proposition for a central school. On March 9, there is
         mention of the work of industrial teachers and demonstrators.
         Jackson Davis made no entries from March 10 to May 31, with
         the exception of a reference to the purchase of lot 4 in the
         block of Ginter Park on May 22. During June, there are
         references to plans for supervisors in Hampton; the Disputanta
         High School graduation; speaking at "Colored Chatauqna" at
         Front Royal; industrial work in Front Royal schools;
         [reverends] J. B. Dinkins and M. E. Church; and, the annual
         celebration of the Alumni Association in Williamsburg. During
         early July, there are references to St. Paul's Summer School;
         school and farm demonstration work; Thyne Institute in Chase
         City; White Normal; and, the disreputable conditions of "The
         Ridge," a slum near Boydton. On July 11, Davis mentions people
         working toward certification at Virginia Union University and
         Estelle B. Wingo studying to be supervisor for Amelia County.
         On July 15-16, there are references to the Rural Life
         Conferences and Horticultural Society meeting at the
         University [of Virginia]. Visits to Manassas and Madison
         follow; summer school inspections, a meeting of stockholders
         of Robinson Cove Orchard, and Normal [Institute] are
         mentioned. Davis also comments on Miss Caroline Preston Davis
         revealing that the Civic Club paid the salary of the science
         teachers at the Negro School in Charlottesville and that she
         had obtained a black teacher a job as a maid at the Summer
         Institute at the University of Virginia so the woman could
         observe a class there. There are scattered notes from July 19
         to September 18. In later September, he visited Newport News,
         Hampton, and Williamsburg. On September 24, he discusses the
         meeting of trustees of Nelson districts of York and Warwick
         counties and the agreements to hire a supervising industrial
         teachers for the colored schools and to remodel "Rising Sun"
         School. September 25-28, he mentions Cumberland topics: C. W.
         Dickinson, Jr. selling eggs; Hamilton School; Tar Wallet Club;
         Matilda Moseley and Kate M. Barter; and, a meeting of white
         and colored teachers. There are scattered notes from September
         29 to October 22. In York County, October 23, he mentions
         "Rising Sun" graded school, Thomas Lackey, and a visit to the
         schools. Following the journal entries is a memorandum, "Books
         Read during Year."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e220">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110217040449/http%3A//etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/browse-mixed-new.chris?id=Dav1911&amp;data=/texts/english/davis&amp;tag=public">Travel Diary</extref>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e232">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110217040509/http%3A//etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/browse-mixed-new.chris?id=Dav1913&amp;data=/texts/english/davis&amp;tag=public">Travel Diary</extref>
            <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e244">
        <did>
          <unittitle>
            <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Jackson Davis and the Lost
                  World of Jim Crow Education</title>
          </unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          <physdesc>2 copies</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e255">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Future in Europe" (Notes by Dr. Alan Gregg
               on his recent trip in Europe) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e263">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Genealogical Data on the Ancestors and
               Descendants of Jackson Davis 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1998-1999</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e271">
        <did>
          <unittitle>General Education Board 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1940-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e279">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Journal of Our Trip to Europe: A Series of
               Letters to Helen M. Davis..." by Jackson Davis 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e287">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Jackson Davis 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1942-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e295">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Jackson Davis: News from Africa 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1944-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e303">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters of Condolence for death of Jackson
               Davis 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e312">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Observations and Impressions of South
               America" by Jackson Davis 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e320">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photographs of Jackson Davis and others 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1943,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e328">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed re Jackson Davis 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1911-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e334">
        <did>
          <unittitle>"Statement on Social Medicine" by Alan Gregg 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e342">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Travel Journal of Corinne Mansfield Davis 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e350">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Travel Journal kept by Jackson Davis as state
               agent for Negro schools for the State Board of Education
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e358">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Travel Journal kept by Jackson Davis as state
               agent for Negro schools for the State Board of Education
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e366">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Leather brief case personalized "Jackson
               Davis, Richmond, Va." 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e372">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Travel Diary 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1911</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e380">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Travel Diary 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e388">
        <did>
          <unittitle>2 copies Lost World 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
