<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02958">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02958::British Abolition Movement Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02958.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02958::British Abolition Movement
             Papers)//EN" "viu02958.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the British Abolition Movement
            Papers 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821-1887</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">British Abolition Movement Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3846</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Ann Southwell, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July 2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02958::British
            Abolition Movement Papers)//EN" "viu02958.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the British Abolition Movement Papers 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821-1887</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3846</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>British Abolition Movement Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1821-1887</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3846</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">60 items</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>British Abolition Movement Papers, Accession #3846,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Stuart W. Jackson of Gloucester, Virginia</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The papers contain documents, letters, broadsides and
         miscellaneous material relating to the abolition of the slave
         trade and the anti-slavery movement in Great Britain and
         America. A few of the letters were kept by the compiler for
         their autograph value (Duke of Wellington, Disraeli) but have
         no discernible connection to the abolition movement.</p>
      <p>
Correspondence and documents relate to the anti-slavery movement in America and to the abolition of slavery in Africa and South America, 1821-1887.</p>
      <p>
Much of the correspondence consists of letters written to Thomas Denman, Margaret Denman Cropper, and Henry William Macaulay on English efforts to abolish the international slave trade.</p>
      <p>
Of interest are letters from Sierra Leone residents seeking employment or making other requests of Henry William Macaulay or William Wilberforce.</p>
      <p>
Items of United States interest include a letter from Thomas Clarkson on slave-holding clergy in the South and letters from Frederick Douglass to Margaret Cropper on the anti-slavery cause, the aid of the Liverpool Society, gifts from Mrs. Cropper, and the destitution of escaped slaves.</p>
      <p>
There are also a few letters from Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry William Macaulay on family matters and a request for documents from the 1690s.</p>
      <p>
Miscellaneous letters include one from a gunner on the "Scylla," captured and imprisoned by the Carlists, and one from Robert Cecil on winning over the Roman Catholics of Ireland.</p>
      <p>
The papers also contain a few letters collected by the compiler for their autograph value and having nothing to do with abolition. These include two letters from the Duke of Wellington on a railway from Warrington to Liverpool, social notes from Disraeli and Bulwer-Lytton, a letter forwarding orchids from Robert H. Schomburgk, a letter from George Biddell Airy on a magnetic disturbance on an iron ship, a letter from John Taylor Coleridge conveying family news, and an envelope addressed in 1871 by one of the last survivors of Waterloo.</p>
      <p>
Miscellaneous items include broadsides from the Sierra Leone Turf Club and one regarding a regatta, and an invitation to the coronation of William IV.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The letters were originally in a bound volume, grouped
         roughly by type of material and by correspondent but otherwise
         in no discernible order. The original arrangement has been
         maintained.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e149">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letter, Henry John Temple Palmerston to Henry
               William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 Oct 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Refers to letter of the 17th to Macaulay by Sir
               George Shee and the submission of Macaulay's name for
               the vacant Situation of His Majesty's Commissioner of
               Arbitration at Sierra Leone. Informs Macaulay that His
               Majesty's government requires abstaining from any
               commercial pursuits while holding Office in the Mixed
               Commission due to the incompatibility of the positions
               of Merchant and Commissioner of Arbitration.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e160">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Appointment by King William IV 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Feb 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ADS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Appointment declaring Henry William Macaulay as
               Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as
               Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a treaty with
               Spain for the abolition of the slave trade concluded
               1817 Sep 23. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be performed
               as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and
               Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by Spain, among
               others. Signed by Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington,
               as Foreign Secretary.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e171">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Appointment by King William IV 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Feb 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>6 p. ADS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Appointment declaring Henry William Macaulay as
               Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as
               Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a convention
               with Brazil on the abolition of the slave trade
               concluded 1826 Nov 23. This convention adopted several
               articles and provisions of the treaties made by King
               George III with the King of Portugal on 1815 Jan 22 and
               1817 Jul 28. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be performed
               as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and
               Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by Brazil, among
               others. Signed by Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington,
               as Foreign Secretary.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e182">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Appointment by King William IV 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Feb 25</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>5 p. ADS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Appointment Appointment declaring Henry William
               Macaulay as Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as
               Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a treaty with
               the Netherlands for the abolition of the slave trade
               concluded 1818 May 4. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be
               performed as a mixed commission with the Commissary
               Judge and Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by each
               of the five nations participating. Signed by Arthur
               Wellesley, Duke of Wellington, as Foreign Secretary.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e193">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Commission by Queen Victoria 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 Sep 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>5 p. ADS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Commission declaring Henry William Macaulay as
               Commissioner and Charles Pettingal as Arbitrator
               pursuant to a treaty with Portugal concluded 1842 Jul 3.
               Macaulay and Pettingal's work is to be performed as a
               mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and
               Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by both nations.
               Signed by George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of Aberdeen.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e204">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of Aberdeen to
               Her Majesty's Commissioners in Boa Vista 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 Sep 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Aberdeen writes to the Commissioners, enclosing a
               copy of correspondence relating to the Portuguese
               Government's intention of authorizing the Board of
               Superintendence of liberated Negroes at Boa Vista to
               distribute captured Negroes in any part of the Cape
               Verde Islands.</p>
        </arrangement>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e215">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Stratford Canning of Redcliffe to Her
               Majesty's Commissioners at Boa Vista 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 Nov 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Canning writes to the Commissioners, enclosing copies
               of correspondence with the Portuguese Government on the
               subject of the disposal of Negroes found on board of
               slave vessels captured by Portuguese Cruizers and
               condemned by the Mixed Court of which they are members.
               With enclosed obituary of Lord Shaftesbury.</p>
        </arrangement>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e226">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury to
               Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Nov 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Shaftesbury writes to Cropper regretting that he
               cannot adopt her previously proposed attitude towards
               immediate abolition. He proposes that admitting rather
               than denying the difficulties of immediate abolition
               will help abate hostility.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e237">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury to
               Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 Nov 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Shaftesbury writes to Cropper concerning two separate
               addresses circulating to be sent to London. He expresses
               joy over the activity in Liverpool in support of a
               universal goal. He suggests that Cropper and others in
               Liverpool continue to obtain signatures for their
               address while he and the London Committee do the same
               there. He explains that upon completion the two lists
               will be combined along with an explanation of
               differences in wording between the addresses and
               requests that Cropper not send anything to London until
               all lists can be combined in a "Single Cargo." Together
               with an undated [1888] newsclipping eulogy on the life
               of Lord Shaftesbury.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e248">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Fragment, unsigned, relating to Henry William
               Macaulay's position as commissary judge. 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. AN</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e257">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Maria Maxfield to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 Nov</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Maxfield, Sierra Leone, requests the loan of half a
               dozen knives and forks and the use of some liquor on the
               occasion of her wedding the following day.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e268">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George Freeman to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Feb 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Freeman writes to Macaulay inquiring about any
               possible vacancies (vagence) in Macaulay's department
               and humbly requests consideration for any such
               positions</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e279">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Petition of John Samuel and related note 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Jan 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Samuel petitions the successor of his master's estate
               for employment. He emphasizes his experience as a mason,
               but requests any available positions, including those of
               messenger or interpreter of Portuguese. A note at the
               bottom of the petition describes Samuel as a mason who
               arrived in Sierra Leone in Maxwell's time. Samuel was
               previously a steward on a slave ship that was taken by
               the Amelia frigate.</p>
        </arrangement>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e290">
        <did>
          <unittitle>John F. Spooler to William Wilberforce 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Apr 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Spooler, Freetown, Sierra Leone, refers to a
               conversation with Mr. Cole in which he was informed to
               speak to Wilberforce regarding a possible position in a
               school for boys. He also requests any other position
               that it is in Wilberforce's power to give.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e301">
        <did>
          <unittitle>James Carbinthy to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 Sep 23</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Carbinthy, London, informs Macaulay that his clothing
               consists of shoes, two shirts given to him by her
               Ladyship, and two pairs of stockings left to him by
               Macaulay. He explains that he is writing on the subject
               because he does not wish to trouble his captain about
               the matter, but that in general he is being well
               treated. He also explains that he wrote to his father
               about the matter but received no reply.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e312">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Hannibal Marks to Captain Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Apr 29</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Marks, the gunner of the Scylla, writes to Captain
               Denman while a prisoner with the boat's crew in the
               hands of the Carlists. He ensures the captain that he
               was never treated better and that the captain that took
               him was very kind. He also describes a trip by Denman's
               orders that resulted in their capture.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e323">
        <did>
          <unittitle>A. Marshall to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 Nov</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Marshall, Sierra Leone, apologizes to Macaulay that
               he is unable to come down as requested. He explains that
               his wound has not healed and that he is unable to stand
               upon it. He says that he will come once the wound is
               healed and begs for Macaulay's patience.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e334">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thomas Clarkson to "My Lord" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Mar 17</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Clarkson, Playford Hall near Ipswich, writes
               regarding the practice of slavery in America and his
               efforts to change opinion in the United States. He
               informs the recipient that the clergy of the South are
               not only slaveholders themselves and mistreat their
               slaves but that they defend the practice in the pulpit.
               He states that this defense of slavery has spread to the
               North and that overall, seven-tenths of the clergy in
               America do not consider slavery a sin. Clarkson was
               requested to use his influence to try and change the
               opinions of the clergy and, after deliberation due to
               his age, acquiesced. His writing on the subject was
               printed and sent to the United States, where 100,000
               copies were to be made. [A letter to the clergy of
               various denominations, and to the slave-holding
               planters, in the southern parts of the United States of
               America] He sends a copy of his work to the recipient
               for review and to assess its likely effectiveness
               altering the clergy's position. Together with a
               newspaper clipping describing a memorial in memory of
               Clarkson.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e345">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Frederick Douglass to Mrs. Edward Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858 Mar 8</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. AL</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In a third person letter, Douglass, Rochester, N.Y.,
               acknowledges Mrs. Cropper's letter dated January 8th and
               requests that the parcel for Mrs. Douglass be forwarded
               to Rochester, New York. Also expresses thanks to Mrs.
               Cropper for her past and continued interest and support
               of the abolitionist movement. Together with a newspaper
               clipping, 1907 October 4, from The Daily Telegraph,
               reviewing Booker T. Washington's biography of
               Douglass.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e356">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Frederick Douglass to Mrs. E. Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1859 May 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Douglass, Rochester, N.Y., thanks Cropper for the
               Liverpool Antislavery Society donation towards the
               publication of his antislavery papers. He reports on the
               progress of the antislavery cause in the U.S. and the
               nature of the movement compared with ten years earlier.
               Specifically, he describes more action being taken by
               individuals than by organizations. He stresses the
               importance of constantly reminding the people about the
               movement in order to sway their opinions. He credits
               assistance from abroad with helping by allowing him to
               work more efficiently and by giving him influence among
               his people because he is not asking them for financial
               support. He also discusses the destitute situation of
               many slaves who have escaped to Canada and a plan to
               furnish escaping slaves with tools as they pass
               through.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e367">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Broadsides : Sierra Leone Turf Club Races and
               a Regatta 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 Dec 2,
               n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 broadsides</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Broadside setting the date for the Sierra Leone Turf
               Club races and outlining rules for riders, horses,
               schedule, as well as detailing prizes. Partial broadside
               of regulations for a regatta to be held Feb 7-9.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e379">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed invitation from Hannah Cuthbert to
               Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 May 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Cuthbert, Freetown, Sierra Leone,invites Macaulay to
               luncheon at 3 o'clock in honor of the marriage of her
               daughter Miss N. Barnett to Mr. A. O'Conner.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e390">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed funeral notice for Henry Fleet sent
               to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 May 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p.</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Wesleyan Missionaries Thomas Dove, Henry Badger
               and Thomas Edwards [Sierra Leone?] inform Mr. Macaulay
               of the death of the Reverend Henry Fleet. Funeral
               arrangements are outlined.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e401">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robert Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury, to
               Thomas Denman, Baron Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18?? Oct 5</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Salisbury thanks Denman for the enclosure and hopes
               the unnamed task is not as formidable as people
               imagine.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e412">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robert Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury, to
               Thomas Denman, Baron Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881 Mar 17</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Salisbury thanks Denman for his letters. He states
               his belief that the Roman Catholics of Ireland could
               have been won over "for in other countries they do not
               usually take the side of insurrection, but fears that
               the opportunity has been lost for at least the
               present.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e423">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Frank J. Mebbs to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 21</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Mebbs, Kingston [Jamaica?], thanks Cropper for her
               letter. He tells her of how he has been busy in the
               office lately, and therefore has not gotten as much work
               done on his book as he would like. He states agreement
               with Cropper's opinion of Harry and concern for his
               future. He turns down Cropper's offer of payment for
               embroideries because of existing obligations to her, and
               offers to complete them free of charge. He refers to a
               loan expected from Mr. Cropper that was not received,
               and asks for any amount available to be sent.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e434">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[ ? ] to Thomas Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 May 2</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Promises to visit Denman's
               protégé in Pall Mall, but
               expresses hesitation about any assistance he can offer
               due to a lack of buyers. He expresses his desire to
               visit on the same day as Parr, because of his renewed
               vigor, but regrets that he is busy on that day, and
               therefore suggests that he will come on the 19th to
               celebrate Denman's election.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e445">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Wilberforce to Henry William Macaulay
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">182[?] Dec 24</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilberforce, Uxbridge Common, informs Macaulay that
               he forwarded two letters to him that morning, but did
               not address them fully and tells Macaulay to inquire
               about them at the Post Office. Sends well wishes to the
               Cropper family. With newsclipping from The Daily News,
               1907 June 10, regarding the sale of Battersea Rise
               House, Wilberforce's London home.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e456">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Duke of Wellington to Major Wilson 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 Aug 31</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In a third person letter Wellington thanks Wilson for
               his letter of the 30th, promises to express an opinion
               on the Warrington and Newton Railroad as soon as
               evidence is printed, and asks that Wilson not take the
               trouble of calling on him.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e467">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Alexander Fergusson, Joseph Chabinthy, and
               Thomas Williams to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 Oct 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Fergusson, Chabinthy and Williams, Freetown, Sierre
               Leone, ask Macaulay to baptize them because they were
               told it was a necessity and that having read the Bible
               is nothing without it. Letter is docketed "Specimen
               letter from the boys wishing to be baptized."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e478">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire,
               to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[?]9 Sep 19</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. AL</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Spencer invites Mr. and Mrs. Cropper to dinner and to
               stay at Lismore Castle. Signature cut away.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e489">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J. Fowell Buxton to Thomas Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Mar 18</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Buxton, Brewery, Spitalsfields, congratulates Denman
               on his son's involvement in the "(I hope) fatal blow
               which has been struck at the Slave Trade on that part of
               the coast." He expresses joy that the achievement was
               done by the son of a "faithful friend of the Negro" when
               others had not been sympathetic to the cause.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e501">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry
               Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[48?] May 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Macaulay thanks Mrs. Macaulay for the present of a
               chair that belonged to her late husband and a likeness
               of him.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e512">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire to
               Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856 Mar 13</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Devonshire deeply regrets that he cannot comply with
               Cropper's request, and expresses his inability to do
               so.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e523">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry
               William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 May 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry William
               Macaulay Macaulay thanks his sister-in-law for her
               promise of an engraving as a memorial to his brother. He
               mentions that he did not see Macaulay's children's
               picture at the Exhibition of the Royal Academy as he had
               expected. He also sends his love to Selina</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e534">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Benjamin Collins Brodie to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Aug 14</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Brodie informs Cropper that the place was not sold,
               but bought in at L27000. He explains the difficulty of
               selling on account and promises to update her if he
               hears anything more. Also invites the Croppers to look
               at the property at Broome.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e545">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Frederick Douglass to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858 Sep 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Douglass thanks Cropper for her previously sent gifts
               which had only reached Douglass a few days prior.
               Cropper sent a scarf to Mrs. Douglass and a volume of
               Dr. Livingston's Travels in Africa to Douglass. Douglass
               expresses gratitude for Cropper's interest in the cause,
               and also mentions that he is writing on the anniversary
               of his escape from slavery</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e556">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Henry William Macaulay to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Sep 15</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Macaulay thanks Cropper for her kindness towards his
               sister Selina and for her letter of the 29th of August
               and one dictated by Selina. He wishes to inquire further
               about one passage of her letter.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e567">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire to
               Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] Oct 3</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Devonshire apologizes for his late reply to Cropper's
               letter in favor of an unnamed workman. Promises that
               upon his return to Chatsworth he will take some green
               from a now locked cupboard and send them on to the
               workman, provided that he is given a name and
               address.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e578">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Catherine Marsh to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] May 19</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Marsh thanks Cropper for her invitation, but declines
               because she is busy until she leaves for Scotland. Also
               encloses a speech in case Cropper has not read it
               already.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e589">
        <did>
          <unittitle>H. C. Hamilton to Henry William Macaulay 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Hamilton, Congotown, requests that Macaulay give him
               any available position on one of Her Majesty's
               ships.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e600">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Invitation 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1830]</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Printed invitation to The Coronation of Their Most
               Sacred Majesties made out to His Majesty's Attorney
               General. Entry at the West Door.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e611">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Hugh Charles Clifford to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Clifford hopes to be able to dine with Cropper on
               Friday the 13th if nothing comes up in the House of
               Lords to detain him.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e623">
        <did>
          <unittitle>J[ohn?] MacGregor to "Dear Madam" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Wednesday</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>MacGregor accepts an invitation to dinner on
               Friday.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e634">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[Thomas Babington Macaulay] to Margaret
               Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853 Aug 24</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Partial Partial letter to Cropper inquiring about
               papers in a collection. Asks about Lord _____'s M.S.S.
               as well as any documents pertaining to 1689, 1690 and
               1691, probably for his book on "The history of England
               from the accession of James II." Mentions that letters
               relating to Lord Cromwell's time are not of much
               use.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e645">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Envelopes to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] May 13 and n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Partial envelopes addressed to Margaret Cropper</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e656">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George Biddell Airy to Charles Parker 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 Oct 28</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Biddell is in Liverpool and will attempt to call on
               Parker as soon as he is able. Mentions that the purpose
               of his visit is to examine an iron ship belonging to W.
               Cairns to try and correct a magnetic disturbance. Also
               notes that he saw Dr. and Mrs. [Thomas Stewart?] Traill
               and their daughter at Greenwich.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e667">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire,
               to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] Apr 30</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Devonshire reports that he has been sick with
               bronchitis for over a week and is unable to assist.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e678">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Henry William Macaulay to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855 Aug 16</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Macaulay reports finding her letter among other
               papers with its seal unbroken. He attempts to ease her
               worries over a young man who is not an energetic worker,
               but mentions that the problem should be corrected. He
               also sends his love to Edward and the children.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e689">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Beaconsfield [Benjamin Disraeli] to Miss [?] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[?] Jul 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Beaconsfield thanks his correspondent for a gift [of
               grapes?] and invites her to call any time after
               five.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e700">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Richard Wellesley to The Lord Chief Justice
               [Thomas Denman] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 Nov 22</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wellesley confirms his Lordship and the Provost of
               Eton's visit at 3 o'clock that day. He also reports that
               his health is much improved and that his doctors promise
               him a "new Lease on Life."</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e711">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Sir John Taylor Coleridge to Thomas Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 Aug 6</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>4 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Coleridge inquires about Denman, and asks to be sent
               news from someone other than Denman himself. He
               discusses Denman's giving up his work as a judge, and
               the effect his workload may have had upon his health.
               Discusses his future son-in-law and preparations for the
               wedding. Reports on his latest circuit and on winning a
               shilling on a point in the Highway Act. Includes a
               passage in Greek. Also mentions that Lady Coleridge
               sends kind regards to Lady Denman.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e722">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[John?] Russell, Lord Russell to "My Dear
               Lord" [Thomas Denman] 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Mar 11</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Russell congratulates Denman on the conduct of his
               son on the Coast of Africa and discusses the effect of
               Joseph Denman's actions on the African chiefs and the
               slave trade in the Gallinas.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e733">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Envelope and fragment to Major Wilson at the
               United Service Club 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e742">
        <did>
          <unittitle>[?] to "My Dear Sir" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Oct 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondent notes that an order in Council is about
               to be opened upon the subject of slavery. It is
               necessary that the recipient take some action
               [publication?] so the order can proceed without
               delay.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e753">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton to Lord Denman 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1884 Nov 6</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Earl and Lady Lytton thank Denman for his
               congratulations.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e764">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Envelope addressed to "The Lord Denman" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1871</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Pencil note on envelope reads "From Captain [?] one
               of the few survivors of Waterloo--Peninsular War
               1871"</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e775">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Robert H. Schomburgk to Charles Parker 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 Jun 1</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Schomburgk forwards Forwards a box of plants for his
               Grace the Duke of Bedford after returning from the
               Interior. Apologizes for giving Parker the trouble of
               receiving and forwarding packages, and explains that Sir
               William Hooker instructed him to do so. Also asks that
               the box be forwarded as soon as possible because it
               contains orchids.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e786">
        <did>
          <unittitle>William Wilberforce to R.H. Davis 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[20?] Nov 27</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 p. ALS</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Wilberforce Informs Davis that Lord Calthorpe is
               coming to visit Wilberforce and may arrive the next
               night on his way to Warwicke. Explains that they may go
               together to Blaise Castle and asks if he may show Davis'
               "horrid statement" to Calthorpe. He stresses that
               Calthorpe is highly principled and may be relied upon
               for secrecy, but Wilberforce requires Davis' permission
               before sharing the information. Wilberforce discusses
               the lack of feeling and principle evident in the conduct
               attributed to the Queen. During his writing, Wilberforce
               was called away and he hurriedly signs the letter.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e797">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Duke of Wellington to Major Wilson 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[?] Dec 2</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 p. AL</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In a third person letter Wellington thanks Wilson,
               but informs him that he must decline to interfere with
               the proposed bill for making a railway from Warrington
               to Liverpool.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e808">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Envelope addressed to Margaret Cropper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 May 19</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
