<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01571">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01571::Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries and Photoprints, 1855-1863)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01571.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01571::Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries
             and Photoprints, 1855-1863)//EN" "viu01571.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries and
            Photoprints, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1863</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Tayloe, Sally Betts, Diaries and
            Photoprints, 1855-1863 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10936</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">20 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">08/08/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01571::Sally Betts
            Tayloe Diaries and Photoprints, 1855-1863)//EN"
            "viu01571.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries and
         Photoprints, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1863</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10936</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries and Photoprints 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1855-1863</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10936</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of two manuscript volumes as well as three
         photographs.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Sally Betts Tayloe Diaries and Photoprints, 1855-1863,
            Accession # 10936, Special Collections Dept., University of
            Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These two manuscript volumes were purchased from Book
            Press by the Rare Book Division of the Special Collections
            Department of the Library on April 4, 1990.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>These two manuscript volumes, a travel journal covering
         September 6-October 10, 1855 and a diary dating July
         7-December 12, 1856, were kept by Sally Betts Tayloe of
         Washington, North Carolina. The last few pages of the travel
         journal contain poetry about the Potomac and expenses for
         1862-1863. Both volumes contain much personal thought
         concerning the activities mentioned. Much of the writing gives
         a good view of the social life of a young single woman and her
         friends. In addition, there are three photographs of Annie
         Roulhac Sims.</p>
      <p>The travel journal is a narrative of Sally's northeastern
         tour of the United States from September 6-October 10, 1855,
         with her travelling companions Colonel Roulhac and his
         daughter Annie, and was apparently written the following
         autumn (according to the September 3, 1856 entry in her
         diary). As the travel journal was not written until a year
         later, some of the places visited are slightly out of
         sequence. Several days of the week and dates are also
         inconsistent. On September 6, 1855, they left Raleigh, North
         Carolina, travelling to Weldon, and then on to Petersburg and
         Richmond, Virginia, taking a steamboat across Aquiner Creek.
         Daylight on September 7 found them in Washington, D. C., where
         they rode the omnibus to view the White House, the Capitol,
         and the Smithsonian Institute. They spent the day in
         Baltimore, Maryland touring shops, then left for Havre de
         Grace, where they travelled by boat across the Susquehanna
         River to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, arriving at the Girade
         [Girard?] House. On September 9, they attended St. Mark's
         Church before walking through Public Square and taking a boat
         to Camden and Burlington, New Jersey. A terrible accident a
         few days previously in Burlington and its effect on the city's
         inhabitants is mentioned. They changed boats in Jersey City
         and went on to New York City where they checked into the St.
         Nicholas, noting its grandeur. The next few days found them
         touring Broadway--shopping, visiting Becks, Taylors Saloon,
         Metropolitan Theatre [Opera House?] for "Rachel," and Wallacks
         Theatre for "The Game of Love." On September 15, they boarded
         "Alyda," the most elegant boat on the Hudson River. She
         describes the beauty of the river, mentioning places of
         interest at Hastings-on-Hudson and Tarrytown, such as the
         Pallisades and Sunnyside, the home of Washington Irving, and
         West Point. They stayed several days near West Point,
         socializing with the cadets ("brass buttons") and touring the
         monument to General Tadeusz (Andrzej Bonzwentura) Kosciusko
         and the monument to soldiers who perished in battle. They left
         on September 17, riding along the Hudson River to Albany, New
         York, which she describes as beautiful scenery. In Albany,
         they stayed one night at the Delavan House [named for reformer
         Edward Cornelius Delavan?], where her southern notions were
         shocked by all the "white waiting girls being under the
         control of one great negro man." They spent September 18 in
         Saratoga, New York, where they visited Congress Hall [Park]
         and drank from the [Spencer Trask Memorial Foundation] spring.
         Upon leaving Saratoga on September 19, they travelled to
         Schenectady and on to Buffalo that night. During the next few
         days they toured Buffalo, which she calls the "City of
         Churches," walking through the principal streets and viewing
         the city from the observatory. They took a boat on Lake Erie
         [and Lake Ontario] seeing the Old Fort [Niagara] and Niagara
         falls, and stopping to see the museum and gardens. On
         September 21, they crossed the suspension bridge between the
         American and Canadian falls, driving to Goat Island to view
         the falls. That evening they proceeded to Ogdensberg where
         they took the steamboat "Jenny Lind" on Lake Ontario; at
         daylight they switched to a smaller boat to ascend the rapids
         of the St. Lawrence River toward Montreal, Quebec, Canada. On
         September 23, there is a description of High Mass at
         Montreal's Cathedral and the celebration of the "Immaculate
         Conception" starting at St. Peter's Church and proceeding
         through St. Catherine's street. The following day they
         travelled down Lake Champlain-- there is a description along
         with a brief history of a battle during 1812. They stayed in
         Rutland, Vermont overnight, travelling to Boston,
         Massachusetts on September 25. They arrived at the elegant
         [Paul] Revere House which is described. Their sight-seeing
         tour brought them to the Bunker Hill Monument in Charlestown;
         The Boston Common and Faneuil Hall [known as "Cradle of
         Liberty"] in Boston; and, Mt. Auburn Cemetery and Harvard
         University in Cambridge. September 28 brings them to
         Connecticut, seeing the Charter Oak Memorial and the residence
         of Mrs. [Lydia Howard Huntley] Sigourney in Hartford and the
         residence of P[hineas] T[aylor] Barnum in Bridgeport, before
         reaching New Haven, and visiting Yale University. The next
         day, they took a carriage to East Rock Park where they saw New
         Haven, West Haven, and Long Island from the outlook; and
         toured the college buildings. On October 1, they left for New
         York where they stayed at the St. Nicholas. While there, they
         went to Broadway and to the Broadway Theatre to see the actor
         [Edward Loomis] Davenport. On October 5, they took a horse and
         carriage ride on the banks of the Hudson River, noting the
         place where the volunteer companies do target shooting; rode
         to High Bridge on the west side of New York City; and, on
         their return, saw the Convent of the Sacred Hearts and
         Chrysler Palace. Their remaining few days in New York were
         spent seeing more sights. On October 8, they stopped at
         "Brady's daguerrean gallery" to have a daguerreotype taken,
         went to Dusseldorf Gallery to admire the paintings of modern
         art (discussion of the gallery), visited [James] Boyle's
         studio, and later went to the Broadway Theatre to see the
         renowned tragedian [Edwin] Forrest in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Hamlet</title>. The following two days
         were concerned with a visit to the "Spirit Rappers" and
         included is a discussion of their visit with a medium. Sally
         ends by stating that they returned through New Jersey,
         Pennsylvania, Maryland, and Virginia, arriving home on October
         12, 1855.</p>
      <p>Sally kept a diary from July 7-December 12, 1856 chiefly
         while staying at "Mt. Airy," Isle of Portsmouth, North
         Carolina. According to her, she began this journal since her
         last entry of September 1855. The diary includes much on the
         social activities of Sally and her friends, especially Annie
         Roulhac and Sallie Bond, and her family. Throughout the diary
         she discusses their near daily horseback riding, "surf
         bathing" in the Atlantic Ocean, serenading and other forms of
         entertainment, visits to "Gipsy Camp," reading novels, and
         other social activities. On July 9, she mentions the arrival
         of the steamers "Pamlico" and "Astoria." On July 12, she is
         excited that her pony "Kenning Kirkland Kent Ruffin..." left
         Washington and can be expected shortly. On August 22, she
         writes about reading aloud to her cousin from Washington
         Irving's 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Wolfert's Roost</title>. News of the
         sale of "Magnolia," the Roulhac family home in Raleigh, came
         on August 23. Near the end of September, plans are made to
         return home; and, on October 3, she is home in Washington,
         North Carolina after three months. She mentions the hard times
         and the merchants being discouraged. From October 31-December
         12, she stayed at Liberty Hall, where Sallie Bond got married
         on November 25. On December 12, she left Liberty Hall and was
         met by the horse and buggy in Williamston which carried her
         home to Washington, North Carolina.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
