<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01665">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01665::Ewing Family Papers, 1806-1926)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01665.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01665::Ewing Family Papers,
             1806-1926)//EN" "viu01665.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Ewing Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806-1926</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Ewing Family Papers, 1806-1926 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10799</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">20 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">08/21/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01665::Ewing Family
            Papers, 1806-1926)//EN" "viu01665.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Ewing Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806-1926</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10799</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Ewing Family Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1806-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10799</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         contains about 250 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Ewing Family papers,1806-1926, Accession # 10799,
            Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These papers were purchased by the Library from Franklin
            Gilliam Rare Books of Charlottesville, Virginia.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of the personal correspondence of
         the Ewing families of Rockbridge County, Virginia, and Kanawha
         County, West Virginia, and contains about 250 items (1
         Hollinger box), 1806-1904, 1926, and undated. Also present are
         four photographs of Dr. William P. Ewing of Kanawha County,
         West Virginia, and various papers pertaining to his medical
         practice, and papers concerning William M. Ewing of Rockbridge
         County and his attendance at Washington College, Lexington,
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>The correspondence naturally falls into several distinct
         groups. The first group of letters, 1806-1810, are those of
         Drusilla Tate, her fiance Rev. John D. Ewing, and other
         suitors and friends, including C.H. Chambers, James C.
         Willson, Matthew D. Willson, H.W. Houston, and C.H. Sevier,
         which are mainly concerned with matters of courtship and
         social life.</p>
      <p>Topics of note among these are: a fourth of July
         celebration (1806 Jul 11); a description of poor whites and
         black slaves in Albemarle and Buckingham Counties (1806 Nov
         20); the sentiments of a young man about slavery (1807 Jun 3);
         and a fire in Fredericksburg which destroyed about a hundred
         houses (1807 Oct 17).</p>
      <p>The next group of correspondence, 1837-1855, pertains to
         Dr. Philander D. Ewing, son of Rev. John D. Ewing and
         [Drusilla Tate Ewing ?], who studied medicine at Jefferson
         Medical College in Philadelphia and emigrated from Virginia to
         the West to pursue his career. Dr. Ewing moved to Canton,
         Mississippi in 1838, where in addition to practicing medicine,
         he became a member of the Mississippi State Legislature about
         1846. Because of poor health he returned to Fancy Hill,
         Rockbridge County, Virginia in 185[3 ?].</p>
      <p>In this correspondence are letters of introduction and
         recommendation furnished to Philander by friends of the family
         to help him become established as a physician. These were
         written by William H. Letcher, William H. Caruthers, Robert R.
         Barton, Charles Williams, and Jack M. Ruff, to family and
         acquaintances in Texas, Alabama, Mississippi, and Louisiana.
         Two were written to General Samuel Houston of Texas (1837 Oct
         8 &amp; 14).</p>
      <p>Letters of special note include: John Martin Elder's
         discussion of a scheme to divert 500,000 acres of state land
         in Mississippi from its original purpose and exchange it for
         Planter Bank bonds and warning that it will precipitate
         speculation (1846 Jan 25); a discussion of a petition before
         the Mississippi state legislature concerning the estate of
         W.A. Cottingham, one of the legatees of Amos Lott's will who
         died before reaching the age of twenty-one (1846 Jan 28); the
         "Briscoe Bill" amendment before the Mississippi Senate having
         to do with limiting the number of years a creditor could sue a
         citizen of Mississippi and preventing the introduction of such
         judgments as evidence in Mississippi courts after three years
         where previously creditors had up to twenty years to make a
         claim (1846 Feb 7 &amp; 11); the "Torry Bill" which dealt with
         the bankrupt and insolvent banks of Mississippi by combining
         the principles of the bankruptcy and insolvency laws (1846 Feb
         18); the complaints of a practicing attorney of Westville,
         Mississippi about the uncultivated females in the state who
         lived the lives of "drudges" (1847 Nov 15); a description of a
         yellow fever epidemic in New Orleans, Louisiana, and
         Mississippi, mentioning the Singleton family and their slaves
         which the writer says will financially ruin Singleton, and
         also the mention of business with Choctaw and soldier's scrip
         (1853 Aug 23); a visit to the healing springs at Cooper's
         Well, Mississippi, and a discussion of the dangers of the
         Know-Nothing Party for the South, local Mississippi politics,
         and news of the progress of the Canton and Jackson Railroad
         (1855 Jul 12); the advance of the Know-Nothing Party in
         Camden, Mississippi and the work of the "old" Democrats
         against its progress (1855 Aug 31); political barbeques (1855
         Sep 1); and yellow fever in Canton, Mississippi (1855 Oct 1
         &amp; 8).</p>
      <p>The next group of letters are generally to John Tate Ewing
         of Lisbon, Bedford County and Fancy Hill, Rockbridge County,
         the grandson of Rev. John D. Ewing. Many of the letters from
         1869-1871 are from his brother Will, who attended Washington
         College, Lexington, Virginia.</p>
      <p>Letters of note among these are: a description of social
         life during the Civil War (1864 Jan 8); a letter from Lt. W.C.
         Howard, Cobb Legion Cavalry, Young's Brigade, Butler's
         Division, Hampton's Corps, Army of Tennessee, describing an
         engagement with [Hugh Judson ?] Kilpatrick, commander of
         General William T. Sherman's cavalry, near Goldsboro, North
         Carolina, and other news of General Sherman's Carolina
         Campaign (1865 Mar 25); an attempt to find employment with the
         Venezuelan Land Company because jobs were unavailable in
         Virginia (1866 Mar 8); and Will Ewing's discussion of the
         local society and his teaching experiences in Charleston, West
         Virginia, and the fight with the "Radicals" over public
         education in Charleston (1871 Jan 29 &amp; Mar 3).</p>
      <p>The family of Dr. W.P. Ewing and Annie P. Ewing moved to
         Charleston, West Virginia in 1871. Two sons, Henry and Will,
         emigrated from West Virginia to the West and engaged in
         mining, teaching, and other activities beginning about 1875.
         Their letters back home to Kanawha County form the next set of
         letters.</p>
      <p>These include: a description of the Comanche County, Texas
         area, avoiding Indians, hunting buffalo, fervent but aberrant
         forms of religion, and women dipping snuff (1875 May 11 &amp;
         Nov 22); the social life in Texas, a decision to take up
         bounty hunting, and talk of the flood of Southern immigrants
         into Texas (1876 Jan 30); work on the Transcontinental
         Railroad, Paris, Texas, and various other employments (1876
         Jul 24); plans to take a wagon of bacon to Arizona by way of
         Ft. Worth, Ft. Choncho, El Paso, and through Mexico to avoid
         the Apaches, and to continue prospecting for gold and silver
         (1877 Mar 17); a description of Arizona (1878 Feb 22); a
         description of muscal and Spanish soap weed plants, and the
         Chinese immigrants in the Sacramento Valley of California
         (1878 Aug 11); and the failure of the Hackberry Mining
         Company, Arizona, and the subsequent argument over payment of
         the miners resulting in sixteen deaths (1879 Mar 13).</p>
      <p>The last group of letters primarily concerns the family of
         Fannie Ewing Scott, a daughter of Dr. W.P. and Annie P. Ewing,
         who married M.W. Scott prior to 1894 and moved to California.
         Among these are several pertaining to the prevention of
         cruelty to animals (1894 Nov 30; 1895 Apr 22; and 1897 May 1
         &amp; 19) and references to the genealogy of the Ewing family
         (1895 Feb 1).</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
