<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03139">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03139::Clark Family Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03139.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03139::Clark Family Papers)//EN"
             "viu03139.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Clark Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925-1993</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Clark, Family Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10396-B</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Katherine Schumann, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">09/04/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03139::Clark Family
            Papers)//EN" "viu03139.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002
            by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Clark Family Papers 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925-1993</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10396-B</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Clark Family Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1925-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10396-B</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of 26 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Clark Family Papers, Accession #10396-B , Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Clark Family Papers were placed on loan in the
            Library by Ervin and Lorraine Jordan of Charlottesville,
            Virginia, on April 13, 1993.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Mary C. Stanley was born on January 11, 1901 to Barley and
         Alberta ("Bertie") Clark (her siblings included George,
         William, Gertrude and Violet), and was educated in
         Charlottesville public schools. She moved to Waterbury,
         Connecticut, and resided there until 1948. She returned to
         Charlottesville and operated a beauty shop at her home on 319
         10 and a half Street, N. W., Charlottesville, circa 1950-1988.
         She was married to Hubert Stanley, and appears in
         miscellaneous published sources and documents as Mary E.
         Clark; Mary E. Cooper; Mary J. Williams; Mary E. Williams;
         Mary E. Stanley; and Mary C. Stanley. In various city
         directories she is listed as: 1950 Mary J. Williams, operator
         of Apex Beauty Shop 1951-52 Mary E. Williams 1953 Mrs. Mary
         Williams 1955 Mrs. Mary Williams beauty shop 1957 Mrs. Mary E.
         Williams beauty shop 1961 Mrs. Mary W. Stanley beauty shop
         &amp; Hubert Stanley 1972 Mrs. Mary W. Stanley beauty shop
         1988 Mary C. Stanley beauty shop 1989 George Clark (brother),
         retired Her mother, Bertie Clark, is listed at same address,
         1931-1954, as a laundress and widow of Barley Clark.</p>
      <p>Mary was a member of Zion Union Baptist Church and served
         on its Usher Board, Deaconess Board, and Flower Committee. She
         was a Past Daughter Ruler of the Elks, Blue Ridge Temple #67
         [Daughters of the Improved, Benevolent, Protective Order of
         Elks of The World]; a member the Seamstress Arts and Crafts
         Club, Charlottesville, and the Democratic Party for which she
         frequently volunteered as a city poll worker. Mary died on
         April 17, 1991 at a Charlottesville nursing home after an
         extended illness and was buried at Oakwood Cemetery</p>
      <p>Items pertaining to Mary C. Stanley include a January 2,
         1931 diploma from the Simplex College of Beauty and Culture
         and Hairdressing [signed by Rosamond Stewart and mentions an
         instructor named Mme. M. Mitnaul or Mitraul] awarded to Mary
         E. Cooper, perhaps one of the first diplomas awarded by this
         school (a typescript of this document is appended to this
         guide); a March 17, 1985 illustrated program, Anniversary
         Service Celebrating the 90th Year of the Zion Union Baptist
         Church/Preston Avenue/Charlottesville, Virginia, containing a
         brief history of this Charlottesville black church (founded in
         March 1865), with photographs of and advertisements by
         contemporary African-American individuals and organizations;
         and a funeral program, "Service of Triumph for Mary C.
         Stanley."</p>
      <p>Other items pertain to her Elks activities: a 1925 bronze
         badge, "26th Annual Convention/I. B. O. E. of W." [Improved,
         Benevolent, Protective Order of Elks of The World]. The I.B.O.
         W.'s the Grand Lodge Session was held in Richmond, Virginia,
         at the Rayo Theater, August 25-29, 1925. Also present is a
         1957 Constitution and By-Laws of the Grand and Subordinate
         Temples/Grand Temple/Daughters of I. B. O. E. of The World
         [cover bearing as inscription "Dt. Mary C. Stanley/Blue Ridge
         Temple"; and the 1975 program for the Virginia State
         Association I. B. O. E. of W., 52nd Annual Session, May 24,
         25, 26, 27, 28, 1975, Headquarters Daughters/Howard Johnson's
         Motor Lodge/13th and West Main Streets; Headquarters
         Brothers/Rivanna Lodge #195/115 2nd St., N.
         W./Charlottesville, Virginia"--Mary Stanley is listed on page
         two as co- member of the Housing Committee and on the Patron
         List (her name is misspelled).</p>
      <p>George Albert Clark was born in Albemarle County, Virginia,
         on June 15, 1910, to Bartholomew and Alberta Perkins Clark,
         and attended county schools. He lived and worked as a
         chauffeur in New Rochelle, New York, where he meet and married
         Anna Clark, who predeceased him shortly after World War II.
         George spent his winters in Florida and briefly resided in
         Aberdeen, Maryland. During World War II he served in the
         United States Army. Several years later, as his health began
         to fail, he returned to Charlottesville (the 1989 city
         directory describes him as retired and residing at his
         sister's home on 319 10.5 Street) and cared for his sister
         Mary until her death in 1991. For many years he was employed
         by Eljo's (a Charlottesville clothier) as a parking lot
         attendant. He was a member of Zion Union Baptist Church and
         died on December 28, 1992.</p>
      <p>George's items pertain to his military service. Among these
         is a May 1945 V-Mail letter from fellow Private Thomas Burns,
         Seine, France, describing his (Burns's) visit to Rouen while
         on leave and his good times with members of the Women's
         Auxiliary Corps (WAC); a typescript is appended to this guide.
         Also present is an incomplete copy of the November 9, 1945
         issue of "The Bell News" consisting of page 4 of a
         mimeographed sheet of a transport ship for returning American
         soldiers en route to New York; it describes world and ship's
         news.</p>
      <p>The majority of his military items consists of army
         decorations and insignia, including two metal dog tags on a
         chain: "George Clark/32864457 T43 44/A/P" and "George
         Clark/32864457/T434/A/Mrs. A Clark/21 Morris St/New Rochelle
         NY/P." There is a row of three U. S. Army ribbons (in order of
         precedence): Good Conduct Ribbon--red ribbon of alternating
         red/white bars; American Campaign Ribbon--ribbon of light
         blue, white, black, red [faded orange], white, light blue,
         dark blue, white, red [faded orange], light blue, white, red
         [faded orange], black, white, light blue; blue indicating the
         Americas, black and white, Germany; red and white, Japan;
         European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Ribbon--with
         Arrowhead (indicating participation in an initial assault
         landing) and three bronze stars, indicating participation in
         three campaigns or operations; ribbon of brown, green, white,
         red, green, dark blue, white, red, green, white, black, white,
         brown; green indicates Europe; green, white, and red, Italy;
         black and white, Germany; brown, Africa.</p>
      <p>Collar pins, shoulder and sleeve patches include: a
         gold-color eagle with wings jutting beyond circle--Present War
         Service button (all armed forces), indicates wearer was
         discharged from armed forces subsequent to September 8, 1939
         or was a member of same as of July 23, 1943; gold-color eagle
         with wings jutting beyond circle; same design as above,
         superimposed on a green shoulder patch (Present War Service?);
         two double- white chevrons above "T" (Technician Fifth Grade);
         five gold War Service bars on a green patch (worn on left
         sleeve)--one for each 6 month's overseas service indicating 30
         months [2 and a half years]; gold-color collar button
         depicting a castle (Corps of Engineers); gold-color collar
         button depicting a ship's steering wheel, a shield and a
         winged wheel (Transportation Corps); "U. S." gold-color collar
         button (worn by enlisted personnel); Army Qualification badge,
         silver and blue enamel with flintlock and wreath (Combat
         Infantryman Badge); black "A" on green patch (First Army);
         and, a golden eagle gripping a submachine gun superimposed
         over an anchor against a blue field (Army Personnel Assigned
         to Amphibian Units, signifies collaboration of air, sea, and
         ground forces in amphibious warfare). His funeral program,
         "Homecoming Celebration for George Albert Clark," is also
         present.</p>
      <p>There are three miscellaneous items, two of which it is
         unclear as to whom they belonged: a ca. 1959 souvenir china
         plate ["photograph plate"], "Future Home For The
         Needy--Richmond, Virginia/Purchased by Virginia State Baptist
         Deacon's Convention and Women's Auxiliary, Inc." (design mark
         "Taylor SMITH Taylor/U.S.A./858/Fotoware/Preston-Hopkinson
         Co./Appomattox, Virginia"). The building depicted is the
         Baptist Home For The Needy, 2000 Lakeview Avenue, Richmond,
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>The second miscellaneous item is a May 3, 1985 program "A
         Night To Remember": Alpha Kappa Alpha Debutante Ball,
         Charlottesville Hilton; sponsored by the Eta Phi Omega chapter
         (Charlottesville-University of Virginia). It is illustrated
         with photographs and biographical sketches of the debutantes;
         includes patrons lists, acknowledgements and congratulations
         of African-American organizations including various black
         University of Virginia faculty and administrators.</p>
      <p>The final miscellaneous item is a February 1993
         advertisement by The Settlers announcing the sale of "the
         personal property of the late Mary Stanley and her brother
         George Clark."</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of 26 items, 1925-1993, papers and
         miscellaneous related materials pertaining to the civic,
         social, and professional activities of two members of a
         Charlottesville, Virginia, African- American family: Mary C.
         Stanley (1901-1991), a beautician, and her brother, George
         Albert Clark (1910-1992), a World War II veteran. Items
         include Mary's beautician diploma and relevant materials
         regarding her membership in Blue Ridge Temple #67 [Daughters
         of the Improved, Benevolent, Protective Order of Elks of The
         World]; George's military ribbons, insignia, and a letter to
         him from a fellow soldier while stationed in France, May 1945;
         and, a photographic china plate: "Future Home For The
         Needy--Richmond, Virginia."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e201">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Mary. C. Stanley items 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1925-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>5 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e209">
        <did>
          <unittitle>George Albert Clark items 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945,
               1992</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>17 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e217">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985,
               1993</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e225">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Souvenir china plate: "Future Home For The
               Needy--Richmond, Virginia" 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1959</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e233">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Diploma, Simplex College, Mary E. Cooper 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931 Jan 2</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physloc>Oversize box</physloc>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
