<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01247">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01247::Papers of the Wohlbrück and Related Burgess families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01247.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01247::Papers of the
             Wohlbrück and Related Burgess families)//EN"
             "viu01247.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the
            Wohlbrück and Related Burgess
            families</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Wohlbrück and Related
            Burgess Families Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11461</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2000 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="filesize">19 Kb.</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word. Date of source: 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01247::Papers of the
            Wohlbrück and Related Burgess families)//EN"
            "viu01247.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Wohlbrück
         and Related Burgess families</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession number">11461</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">{Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library}</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Wohlbrück and Related
         Burgess Families 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1889-1901</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11461</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">ca. 60 letters and
         2 photographs.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>The collection is without restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of the Wohlbrück and Related Burgess
            Families, Accession # , Special Collections Dept.,
            University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The collection was purchased from K. Dietrich,
            Stockbridge, Mass. in December 1998 and January 1999.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists letters, chiefly to Marie
         (Wohlbrück) Burgess from her siblings, Dora
         [Theodora], Kittie, Gertrude, and Theodore C.
         Wohlbrück from Charlottesville, Virginia and Bound
         Brook, Elizabeth, and Newark, New Jersey. The letters discuss
         family matters and economic hardships. There are also two
         photographs, 1889, of Marie (Wohlbrück)
         Burgess.</p>
      <p>There are several letters from siblings in Charlottesville,
         Virginia, to Marie (Wohlbrück) Burgess. Letters of
         September and October 1890 mention Marie's upcoming marriage
         to Charles A. Burgess and the conflict between Marie and her
         mother and stepfather, Charles Mays. While living in
         Charlottesville, Dora, Gertrude and Theodore write about the
         family, trying to get work, and business being poor. On March
         20, 1893, Theodore discusses the economic hardships and
         inquires of machine shops. On August 22, 1893, Dora writes of
         taking boarders this fall and Kittie keeping a confectionary
         store in New Jersey. In letters of January 14 and March 14,
         1894, Gertrude refers to business as being dull and trying to
         get work in the knitting mill. On August 27, 1894, Dora writes
         that Gertrude is now working in the knitting mill and that
         Theodore is working in a butcher's shop. In a letter of May
         31, 1896, Theodore mentions the poor economic conditions. An
         undated letter, May 13, from Bettie Adams of Charlottesville,
         discusses living and cultivating land in the Charlottesville
         area and offers assistance for Charles and Marie Burgess' move
         to Charlottesville.</p>
      <p>There are two letters, October 17 and 18, 1895, from
         Charles A. Burgess to his wife, Marie (Wohlbrück)
         Burgess, from Roanoke and Lynchburg, Virginia, while searching
         for work. He discusses the possibility of a position running
         the pumping machinery in a blast furnace, conditions in the
         cities of Roanoke and Lynchburg, the difficulties in finding
         work, the dissolution of the General Custer Council, and the
         possibility of going to Richmond to look for work.</p>
      <p>There are several letters during 1890 from Kittie [Mrs.
         Charles Mitchell] in Plainfield, New Jersey, discussing
         personal and family matters, including the conflict between
         Marie and her mother. There is a January 1892 letter
         concerning revival meetings held by an evangelist and the New
         Year's ball at Madison Square Garden. Letters of 1894 from
         Kittie in Elizabeth, New Jersey discuss Dora's need for
         assistance in leaving home and the feeling that their mother
         has little love for her children (February 24); building going
         on in Elizabeth, including a large four story brick factory
         (May 9); and, business being dull and being settled in a new
         place (December 30). Letters from Dora in 1894 are from Bound
         Brook, New Jersey, and discuss earning wages for doing washing
         and ironing, liking Virginia better than New Jersey (November
         8); the conflict between Marie and their mother (November 28);
         and, plans to stay with Marie after Mrs. Smith finds a
         replacement for her (December 15). On January 6, 1895, friend
         Gertrude writes about being busy as a dressmaker and belonging
         to a lodge called the Daughters of Liberty. There are several
         letters, 1895, from Dora while in Elizabeth and Newark,
         discussing personal and family news. On March 2, she refers to
         Kittie's husband, Charlie Mitchell, as a brute; and, on May
         29, she mentions problems between Kittie and Charlie
         concerning their daughter, Belle. On March 22, she mentions
         Kittie being in a new place and going to see plays, including
         "The Derby Winner" and "Kellar, the Great Magician." Letters
         of April 10 and May 12 discuss working in a store downtown in
         the bakery and confectionary and later at Bamberger's, a large
         dry goods store, seeing the play "Uncle Tom's Cabin," and
         having further conflicts with their mother. On August 1, 1895,
         Dora is still working at Bamberger's but wishes to work for a
         lady who has a division of girls who travel with expenses paid
         and receive a commission on each book sold. On December 26,
         1895, Dora writes that she is one of about 160 people laid off
         at Bamberger's. A letter of December 26, 1895, from Theodore,
         berates their sister Kittie's actions concerning men and her
         not living with her husband. On February 19, 1896, Dora writes
         that she has begun work in Hahne &amp; Company, a large store
         in Newark; she also mentions a fire and flood in Bound Brook.
         A letter of December 15, 1896 mentions the possibility of
         getting Charles Burgess a job in a family business.</p>
      <p>There are also several letters from Anne Mitchell, Kittie's
         mother-in-law, to Marie (Wohlbrück) Burgess. On
         April 2, 1892, she reveals personal news about Kittie
         (Wohlbrück) and Charles Mitchell. In a letter of
         December 25, 1893, she mentions her husband being out of work,
         her making some money by sewing, and the family all living
         together. Letters of March 20 and April 23, 1897, refer to
         Dora's new husband and to [her son], Fred, who is working as a
         paper hanger and painter. There is also a letter, December 25,
         1901, from Royer C. Strickland in Charlotte, North Carolina,
         to C[harles] A. Burgess, concerning living arrangements in
         Charlotte.</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
