<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu00376">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu00376:: Papers of Charles Brockden Brown, 1769-1922)//EN" "viu00376.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Charles Brockden Brown, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1769-1922</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Brown, Charles Brockden, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">6349, etc.
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/2/2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Charles Brockden Brown, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1769-1922</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">6349, etc.
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Papers of Charles Brockden Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1769-1922
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">6349, etc.
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">This collections consists of ca. 43 items.
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Charles Brockden Brown, Accession #6349, etc., Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>6349 and 6349-a were deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on April 16, 1960, and made gifts on December 30, 1966.  6349-b was a gift of Roger E. Stoddards on November 10, 1972.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Charles Brockden Brown was born to a Quaker family in Philadelphia on 17 January 1771. His father was a merchant, descended from a family whose Quaker roots can be traced to the seventeenth century. His maternal ancestors, the Armitts, shared a similar heritage. The family business failed, although Brown's father managed to support his large family, probably through establishing new business activities in real estate.</p>
      <p>From about the age of eleven to sixteen, Brown studied under the tutelage of Robert Proud at the Friends Latin School in Philadelphia, and after leaving it he went to work in the Philadelphia law office of Alexander Wilcocks, without having attended college. The legal profession seems to have held little attraction for Brown, but he formed deep friendships at this time, particularly with William Wood Wilkins and Joseph Bringhurst, both of whom shared Brown's literary interests. The three of them were active in the Belles Lettres Club of Philadelphia, which was formed in 1786 and lasted until 1793. When Wilkins, who had gone on to complete his legal education, died in 1795, Brown lost his closest tie to the profession of law. By then Brown had already declined to complete his own education as a lawyer, and the reason for this decision implies much about him as a writer.</p>
      <p>Brown had begun experimenting with the writing of literature even while he studied law. In 1789 a handful of his essays, "The Rhapsodist," were published in Columbian Magazine in Philadelphia, and, after abandoning the law a few years later, he dabbled in poetry and fiction. In 1797 he finished a novel called "Sky-Walk." Although he never published it and the manuscript has been lost, parts of it appeared in <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Edgar Huntly.</title> However, in 1798, he began having his work published at a remarkable pace. During this year, he brought out a portion of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Arthur Mervyn,</title> which appeared in the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Weekly Magazine</title> (Philadelphia), as well as two complete works, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Wieland</title> and <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Alcuin.</title></p>
      <p>In 1801 Brown had two more novels published, Clara Howard and Jane Talbot. Relative to his previous novels, both these works are less imaginative in their plot structures, and both rely more heavily on the epistolary form. Additionally, neither one employs the kind of bizarre devices, such as ventriloquism or sleepwalking, that Brown had used heavily in earlier fiction.</p>
      <p>From 1803 to 1805 Brown also published serially in the Literary Magazine "Memoirs of Carwin the Biloquist." The textual history of this uncompleted story is complex, but apparently the bulk of it was written in 1798 while Wieland was in the process of publication. With additional segments probably written when Brown needed material for the Literary Magazine, the text of "Memoirs of Carwin the Biloquist" appeared during 1803 through March 1805.</p>
      <p>The year 1803 saw Brown expending his energies in writings other than fiction. In addition to beginning his association with the Literary Magazine and American Register, Brown departed from Quaker pacifism to write a pamphlet urging the taking of the Louisiana territory, by force if necessary, and opposing Jefferson's policies, which led to the territory's purchase. Brown seems to have achieved popularity in the writing of pamphlets that eluded him as a novelist. His work An Address to the Government of the United States, on the Cession of Louisiana to the French was quickly reprinted, although in a shortened version. Soon after, Brown published a second pamphlet, which like the first attacked Jefferson's policies toward the Louisiana territory.</p>
      <p>Toward the end of 1807, Brown introduced a new periodical to replace the Literary Magazine. The journal was entitled the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">American Register, or General Repository of History, Politics, and Science,</title> and Brown edited five volumes. Although the pages of this journal included literary topics, such as poetry (including Brown's own) and reviews of British and American literature, the main emphasis now reflected Brown's political and historical interests. Essentially, the <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Register</title> was what its name implied. It kept a record of laws and state papers, but it also gave written accounts of contemporary events, such as a report on the duel between Hamilton and Burr. If most of Brown's remaining literary efforts were devoted to the publication of this journal and the writing of his "Geography," he still had time for one more political pamphlet, a document published in 1809, entitled <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">An Address to the Congress of the United States, on the Utility and Justice of Restrictions upon Foreign Commerce.</title> This publication reflects Brown's continuing interest in public affairs as his career moved toward its end. Once more, his political position placed him in confrontation with Jefferson, this time on the issue of the embargo that had been placed in an attempt to deal with the war then in progress between England and France. Brown, as did many people with mercantile interests, adamantly opposed the embargo.</p>
      <p>Brown died in 1810 and was buried in Philadelphia, in the Friends Burial Ground.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection consists chiefly of research material assembled by Daniel E. Kennedy for his projected biography of Brown.  These include his commentary on William Dunlap's "Life of Charles Brockden Brown" and miscellaneous notes and annotations on Brown; manuscript copies of other material related to Brown particularly a copy of an article from "Littell's Living Age," 1844, and a copy of Brown's death notice; and a resolution by the Friends of Philadelphia concerning Brown's expulsion for marriage to a non-member by a "hireling minister."</p>
      <p>The collection also contains three letters from Brown to William Wood Wilkins and one letter from Wilkins about their friendship, 1790-1793, and a letter to his brother James Brown about Wilkins's death, 1795; a postscript on a 1798 letter from Maria Templeton to Maria NIcholson mentioning yellow fever in Philadelphia; letters to lawyers William P. Beers and John Elihu Hall on literary matters, 1800, 1806; a letter to Mary Linn urging her to cultivate her mind, 1802; and a letter to John B. Romeyn on family matters after the death of his father-in-law, 1808.</p>
      <p>In addition there are four letters to his widow Elizabeth, 1812 and n.d. from her brother-in-law William Keese on a financial matter, her son William Linn Brown on a trip to England and a friend Eliza Kane on social matters.</p>
      <p>Miscellaneous papers include diplomas of John Blair Linn, 1795-1897 and William Linn Brown, 1821; a bond signed by Elizabeth Linn Brown, 1810; inventories and appraisals of the estates of Charles Brockden Brown, 1810, and Elihu Hubbard Smith, 1799; three receipts to Charles Brockden Brown and Charles Brockden Brown, Jr., 1806, 1821, 1830; the will of Elizabeth Armitt, 1798; a passport of William Linn Brown signed by James Buchanan, 1846; a newsclipping regarding William Linn Brown, 1846; and photographs of  the [tombstone?] of Charles Brockden Brown.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is divided into three series: Series I: Literary Manuscripts; Series II: Correspondence; and Series III: Miscellaneous Papers of the Brown and Linn Families.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e177">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Literary Manuscripts
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e181">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript commentary concerning William Dunlap's <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Life of Charles Brockden Brown</title> by Daniel E. Kennedy, mounted with pages from Dunlap in a ledger in a scrapbook format,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d. [20th c]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
		</container>
            <physdesc>Volume One, pages 1-105, indexed.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e195">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript commentary concerning William Dunlap's Life of Charles Brockden Brown by Daniel E. Kennedy, mounted with pages from Dunlap in a ledger in a scrapbook format,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d. [20th c]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
		</container>
            <physdesc>Volume Two, pages 105-390, indexed.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e206">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript volume, "The Verses of Charles Brockden Brown studied in metre" by Daniel Edwards Kennedy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1922
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e215">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript copy of an article on Charles Brockden Brown from <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Littell's Living Age,</title> Volume 2, 1844, copied by Daniel E. Kennedy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d. [20th c.]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1a
		</container>
            <physdesc>8 pages stapled within home-made covers.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e229">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript copy of a review of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Memoirs of Charles Brockden Brown,</title> which first appeared in the London <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Monthly Review</title> October 1822, copied by Daniel E. Kennedy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d. [20th c.]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2
		</container>
            <physdesc>24 pages stapled within home-made covers.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e246">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Manuscript Notice of the Death of Charles Brockden Brown of a consumption in Philadelphia,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810 Feb
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3
		</container>
            <physdesc>1 page
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e257">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous notes about Charles Brockden Brown by D[aniel] E. Kennedy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e266">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Ossian's Address to the Moon" (print version) by Charles Brockden Brown, with annotations by Daniel E. Kennedy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e275">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Poem "To the Memory of the late Dr. John B. Linn," "by a young lady" of Philadelphia,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1804
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6
		</container>
            <physdesc>AMs, 4 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e286">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Resolution by the Friends of Philadelphia (Quakers) concerning the Expulsion of Charles Brockden Brown from their membership because of his marriage to a non-member by a "hireling minister,"
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1805 Feb 20
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8
		</container>
            <physdesc>AMs, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e297">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Correspondence
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e301">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Ross to Charles Brown, brother of Charles Brockden Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1769 Sep. 19
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8a
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He writes concerning business matters between the two men. He also asks Brown to help their friend, Mr. Craig, if possible.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e315">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[ca. 1790?]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:9
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 6 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He declares his pleasure at receiving letters from his friend, and explains that it is much easier for him to express his feelings in a letter than in person, "my pen is the best interpretation of my sentiments." He also says about his friendship with Wilkins, "Of what importance was this name to me eighteen months ago! And now, next to the idea of myself, it occupies, in partnership with that of another person, my whole attention."
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e329">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1790-1795?]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:10
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He compares and contrasts love and friendship, saying "without a friend I am miserable." Thanks Wilkins for his kind treatment during his visit to him "while on the banks of the Delaware [River]." "I intended to stay but a single day, and to have resided at Woodbury, but when I arrived at that place and found you absent, I could not resist the inclination to see you."
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e343">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1792-1793?]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:11
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 8 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Brown assures his friend that he is much interested in Wilkins activities in Trenton and that he should not apologize for the subject of his letter. Also tells Wilkins that his own father praised his conduct when he last saw him alone and approved of his son.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e357">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Wood Wilkins to Charles Brockden Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[ante 1795 Feb 15]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:12
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He apologizes for offending Brown's sensibilities, and hopes to spend more time with him in pleasant companionship.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e371">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to his brother, James Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1795 Apr 19
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:13
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Brown writes to his brother in Edenton, North Carolina, about their brother Joseph leaving them, the death of his friend, William Wood Wilkins, and its effect upon his chances in the legal profession, "It is his death that hath prevented me from fulfilling your expectations and obliged me to defer my admission till the succeeding term."
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e385">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Postscript by Charles Brockden Brown on the second page of a letter from Maria Templeton to Maria Nicholson, while in [New York?],
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798 [Aug?]
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:14
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He promises to send the entire work of <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Wieland</title> to her in a few days and says that yellow fever has so far stayed away from Pine Street, although he has lost two friends, Drs. Sayer and Cooper, in Philadelphia.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e402">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to William P. Beers, a lawyer of Albany, New York,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1800 Feb 12
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:15
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He asks Beers to examine a paper that he is sending him and hopes that he will find it worthy of his subscription and thanks him for the copy of one of his speeches.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e416">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to Mary Linn, sister of his future wife,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1802 Jan 9
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:16
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Sends a little volume for her to write in and urges her to cultivate her mind by reading and reflection.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e430">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to John E[lihu] Hall, a lawyer of [Baltimore?], including an original poem by Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806 Nov 21
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:17
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Brown discusses the use of the word <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Adversaria</title> which was the title of Hall's contributions to his publication, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Literary Magazine and American Register,</title> and discusses his plans for a new semi-annual literary magazine, a change made at the suggestion of his publisher, C. and A. Conrad, Philadelphia. He urges his friend to marry and includes a poem as part of his letter about marriage for Hall's benefit.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e451">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Charles Brockden Brown to John B. Romeyn,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1808 Jan 18
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:18
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He discusses the impact of the death of his father-in-law, William Linn, upon the unmarried younger members of his family. He was especially concerned about Linn's son, William, who was to be educated for the pulpit. Brown asks for advice from Romeyn about whether William Linn might be interested in the mercantile life and requests any help he could render in finding a place for him with some respected merchant in Albany.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e465">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Keese to his sister-in-law, Elizabeth L. Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812 Feb 19
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>He encloses a draft for $100.00 as the last quarter's allowance for Henry and mentions a remittance of $75.00 which he sent last week. He asks that Mary acknowledge the receipt of the two sums when she writes to him.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e479">
          <did>
            <unittitle>James Ogilvie, Savannah, Georgia, to Tart Esquires, possibly a law firm, Charleston, South Carolina,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1813] Apr 23
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:19a
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 4 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Ogilvie spends the first half of the letter disputing the claims of a Mr. Johnson to the status of "permanent celebrity" and the second half discussing the possibility of writing the memoirs of Charles Brockden Brown. He asks that they try to procure subscriptions for a Brown biography in Charleston.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e493">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William Linn Brown, Capes of Delaware, to his mother, Elizabeth L. Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:20
		</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>William writes that all is confusion on the vessel and will be until they are cleanly out to sea at daylight. Warns her that she will not likely hear from him until they arrive at Liverpool and mentions his Uncle James [Brown?] in England.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e507">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Eliza Kane to Mrs. Brown and Miss Linn,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:21
		</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Inviting them to tea.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e521">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mr. Kane to Miss Linn,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:22
		</container>
            <physdesc>AN, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Inviting her for a ride.
		</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e535">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Miscellaneous Papers of the Brown and Linn Families
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e539">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Bond signed by Elizabeth Linn Brown, Elijah Brown, Armitt Brown, and James Robertson,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810 Apr 10
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:23
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e548">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Calligraphic samples done by Charles Brockden Brown, Jr. as a boy,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">18[?] Jun 6, n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
		</physloc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e557">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certificate of Membership issued to William Linn Brown, son of Charles Brockden Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 Feb 6
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:24
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e566">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diploma of John Blair Linn from Columbia College,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1795 May 16.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
		</physloc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diploma of John Blair Linn from Concordia College,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1797 May 13.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
		</physloc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e584">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Diploma of William Linn Brown from Nazareth Hall,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 Jun 6
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:25
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e593">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Inventory and Appraisement of the Personal Estate of Charles Brockden Brown, late of the City of Philadelphia,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810 May 19.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
		</physloc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e602">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Additional Inventory of the Estate of Charles Brockden Brown,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1810 Jun 6
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:26
		</container>
            <physdesc>ADS, 1 page.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e613">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Inventory of the Estate of Dr. Elihu Hubbard Smith, Physician of New York City,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799 Jun 1
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:27
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e622">
          <did>
            <unittitle>News clipping announcing that William Linn Brown of Pennsylvania was admitted to practice before the U.S. Supreme Court,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 Jan 23
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:28
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e632">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Passport of William Linn Brown, signed by James Buchanan,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 Apr 26.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
		</physloc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e641">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of the Tombstone or Memorial Stone of Charles Brockden Brown and Unidentified Building, with negatives,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:29
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e650">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Receipt for Charles Brockden Brown's Subscription to <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dr. Ree's New Cyclopedia,</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1806 Nov 11
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:30
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e662">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Receipts issued to Charles Brockden Brown, Jr. from the Library Company of Philadelphia for payment of his dues
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821, 1830
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:31
		</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e671">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Will of Elizabeth Armitt, grandmother of Charles Brockden Brown, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
		<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798 May 16
		</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:32
		</container>
            <physdesc>ADS, 3 pages.
		</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
