<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01834">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01834::A Guide to the Sitwell Family Papers, 1948, 1963-1995)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01834.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01834::A Guide to the Sitwell
             Family Papers, 1948, 1963-1995)//EN"
             "viu01834.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Sitwell Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948, 1963-1995</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Sitwell Family, Papers, 1948, 1963-1995
            <num type="collectionnumber">10480-i</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">27 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">11/12/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01834::A Guide to the
            Sitwell Family Papers, 1948, 1963-1995)//EN" "viu01834.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Sitwell Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948, 1963-1995</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10480-i</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Sitwell Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948,
         1963-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10480-i</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection is
         comprised of ca. 500 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection of "Sitwelliana"
         compiled by Arthur P. Bean, Jr., includes Bean's
         correspondence with Sitwell collectors and scholars, book and
         manuscript dealers and the University of Virginia Library;
         business papers related to his purchases; printed material and
         a postcard photograph of Edith Sitwell.</abstract>
      <origination label="Collector">Arthur Parsons Bean,
         Jr.</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Sitwell Family Papers, 1948, 1963-1995, Accession #
            10480-i, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the Library on November 8,
            1995 by Arthur P. Bean, Jr. of Washington, D. C. through
            the Rare Book Division of the Special Collections
            Department.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection of "Sitwelliana" consists of ca. 500 items,
         1948(1963-1995), created and compiled by Arthur Parsons Bean,
         Jr. of Washington, D. C. Included are correspondence of Bean
         with individuals, book and manuscript sellers, and the
         University of Virginia Library; business papers concerning the
         purchase of his Sitwell collection; printed material; and, a
         photograph.</p>
      <p>The Business Papers include invoices and cancelled checks
         for various book and manuscript sellers, including Bernard
         Quaritch Ltd., Bertram Rota Ltd., Booked Up, Dalian Books,
         Kenneth W. Rendell, Inc., North Shore Books Ltd., Pharos
         Books, Robert Loren Link, Booksellers, and others.
         Correspondence with representatives of the various book and
         manuscript sellers describe Sitwelliana for sale and include
         list prices. There is a letter, June 22, 1978, from Larry
         McMurtry of Booked Up, Washington, D. C. to Bean, discussing
         the appraisal of Bean's "extensive collection of the works of
         Edith, Osbert, and Sacheverell Sitwell."</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1971-1978, from Frank Magro of Florence,
         Italy to Bean discussing various subjects. A letter of July
         30, 1971 discusses the Music Festival Tour, operas performed
         in London and Rome, and the Sitwell manuscripts in Texas. In a
         letter of May 15, 1972, Magro mentions an American family (Jim
         and Carole Howe's) living in the [Sitwell] castle; discusses
         the fate of the castle including Reresby Sitwell's possible
         plans; mentions being the literary executor of Osbert Sitwell
         and having an interest in Bean's collecting of manuscripts and
         letters of the Sitwells; relates an account his recent trip to
         Honolulu and the Pacific side of the United States, Canada,
         and Mexico as well as the Panama Canal, Jamaica, Nassau, and
         Bermuda; and, mentions the Dramatic Publishing Company.
         Letters of December 30, 1977 and August 12, 1978 mention the
         Sitwell exhibit in the Rare Book Department at the University
         of Virginia Library, his writing a statement as Sir Osbert
         Sitwell's literary executor for the keepsake, and University
         of Virginia's Henry J. and Mildred K. Abraham's visit to
         Florence.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1982-1989, between Bean and Paul W.
         Motter of San Francisco, California. A letter of February 7,
         1983 discusses briefly a failure in the negotiations to
         publish "The Death of Venus," poems of Dame Edith Sitwell. A
         letter of May 31, 1986 discusses Motter's Edith Sitwell
         collection being on exhibit at the Gleeson Library at the
         University of San Francisco in the fall of 1987 and the
         collecting of Sitwelliana, and includes a list of wanted
         Sitwell items. In a (copy of) a letter, June 10, 1986, Bean
         describes the preparations and planning for the exhibit at the
         University of Virginia Library, discusses the collecting of
         Sitwelliana, mentions Neil Ritchie as the collector of
         Sitwelliana in Florence, and comments on Motter's 'wanted'
         list. Letters of June 16 and August 30, 1986 discuss various
         collections of Sitwelliana and the upcoming exhibit at the
         Gleeson Library, mentioning the assistance of various persons,
         including Neil Ritchie, James Purdy, Allanah Harper, Mildred
         Abraham, Rosamund Strode, Beulah Roth, Rollie McKenna, Norman
         Parkensen, Dame Peggy Ashcroft, Michael Kennedy, John Freeman,
         and Lawrence Whistler. A note of [June 1987] mentions going to
         a luncheon and performance with Francis Sitwell. There are
         also copies of the keepsake and the catalog for the Dame Edith
         Sitwell Centennial exhibit at the Gleeson Library, and a
         postcard containing a photograph of Edith Sitwell.</p>
      <p>There are numerous letters, 1985-1993, from Neil Ritchie of
         Florence, Italy, written to Bean as a "fellow collector of
         Sitwelliana." Letters from December 1985 to August 1986
         discuss in detail Ritchie's work on the revision and update of
         the bibliography of Sacheverell Sitwell's writings, previously
         compiled by Richard Fifoot. Letters of September and November
         1986 discuss Ritchie's visit to the United States,
         particularly visits to archives containing Sitwelliana,
         including the University of Virginia, Austin, Texas, Yale,
         Harvard, and Boston University. Letters of March and April
         1987 discuss Ritchie's visit to England and meetings with
         Sacheverell Sitwell and Francis and Susanna Sitwell. Ritchie's
         letter of October 29, 1987 includes a advertisement on his 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Sacheverell Sitwell: An Annotated and
         Descriptive Bibliography 1916-1986</title>. Letters throughout
         1988 continue to discuss in detail the collecting of
         Sitwelliana and mention several persons including Sacheverell
         Sitwell (and his death on October 1, 1988), Reresby Sitwell,
         Francis and Susanna Sitwell, Paul W. Motter, and Mildred
         Abraham. Letters throughout 1989 also discuss the collecting
         of Sitwelliana and mention the possibility of Sir Osbert
         Sitwell exhibitits in 1992, and mention various persons
         including Reresby Sitwell, Francis Sitwell, and Henry and
         Mildred Abraham. In 1990, the letters continue to discuss the
         collecting of Sitwelliana, often specifying items for sale,
         and discuss a bibliophiles' conference in Wurzburg including a
         visit to the library of Otto Schafer at Schweinfurt and to
         Udine for a Lombard exhibition. A note of December 2, 1990
         discusses the decision of Paul W. Motter to sell his Sitwell
         collection. In addition to discussions of collecting
         Sitwelliana, letters of 1991 describe Ritchie's trip to South
         Africa and Namibia (March 19) and mention a visit by George
         Sitwell, Francis' elder son (May 20) and a collection of
         Graham Greene-Edith Sitwell correspondence at Georgetown. On
         May 31, 1992, Ritchie mentions his South African expedition
         and the Sitwell castle and a visit by "an Australian Facade
         maniac" and Frank Magro; and, on November 22, 1992, he relates
         his plans to move to the mild climate of South Africa. Letters
         of February 9 and July 26, 1993 discuss life in South Africa,
         mention the National Library and the University of Cape Town
         Library, refer to Sarah Bradford's biography of Sacheverell
         Sitwell, and inquire of Mildred Abraham.</p>
      <p>Correspondence, 1981-1993, with the Sitwells contain
         chiefly letters of Francis Sitwell to Bean, and discuss
         various topics. A letter of February 1, 1981 mentions the
         death of his mother and a visit by his father, Sacheverell
         Sitwell, to his friend Artur Rubenstein, the pianist. On
         September 1, 1981, he mentions a visit from Henry and Mildred
         Abraham and the health of his father. A letter of August 9,
         1982 mentions a visit to Los Angeles where he saw a
         performance of Dorin McGough's play, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dame Edith,</title>on Edith Sitwell's
         life, and his return to England because of his father's
         emergency surgery. Letters of August and November 1986 discuss
         Bean's collecting of Sitwelliana, and mention a gala
         performance of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Facade</title>in the gardens of Carlyle
         Square on October 14th, in aid of a musical charity, the Park
         Lane Group, of which Sitwell is chairman. There is a touching
         letter, November 2, 1988, from Reresby Sitwell, Renishaw Hall,
         Derbyshire, to Bean, following the death of his father,
         Sacheverell Sitwell, discussing his father and his life,
         especially the latter years. A letter of January 7, 1993
         refers to Bean's "marvellous selection of the Sitwell family's
         books" and offers a copy of the paperback reprint of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Roumanian Journey.</title></p>
      <p>Correspondence, 1948(1973-1995) with the University of
         Virginia chiefly discusses Bean's gifts of Sitwelliana to the
         Rare Book and Manuscripts Departments and later the Special
         Collections Department of the University of Virginia Library,
         and also exhibitions of the Sitwell collection at the
         University. There is a letter, May 4, 1948, from John Cook
         Wyllie, Curator of Rare Books, to Bean as winner in the
         "Student Collectors' Competition, along with the list of books
         submitted and a newspaper article concerning the annual book
         collector's contest. Correspondents include William H. Runge,
         Curator of Rare Books (1973); Julius P. Barclay, Curator of
         Rare Books (1977-1989); Mildred K. Abraham, General Services
         Librarian, Librarian for Readers' Services, and Research
         Librarian (1977- 1992); Frank L. Hereford, Jr., President of
         the University (June 30, 1980; March 23, 1981; February 10,
         1983); Edmund Berkeley, Jr., Curator of Manuscripts
         (1981-1989); and, Kathryn Morgan, Curator of Rare Books
         (1992-1995). There are also signed deeds of gifts, descriptive
         lists of gifts, and appraisals of Bean's gifts by Harold E.
         Graves and Franklin Gilliam. Included is a photograph,
         December 3, 1978, taken by Ed Roseberry, of Francis T. S. and
         Susanna Sitwell, Mildred Abraham, and Arthur P. Bean, Jr. at
         the opening of the Sitwell exhibit in the Rare Book Department
         in Alderman Library at the University.</p>
      <p>There are also miscellaneous and printed items, 1985-1992,
         on the Sitwells: "...From the Personal Library of Pavel
         Tchelitchew," "20th Century Consort" (April 23, 1988); "Sir
         Sacheverell Sitwell at Weston Hall: A Conversation" by Duncan
         Fallowell in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Encounter</title>(May 1988); "Facades"
         reviews in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Lyric Studio</title>(June - July 1988);
         and, "Memoir: A Day at the St. Regis with Dame Edith" by
         Perdita Schaffner in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The American Scholar</title>(Winter
         1991) with letter to and from Schaffner.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e213">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Business Papers of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. with
               Book/Manuscript Sellers 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1963-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e221">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and
               Book/Manuscript Sellers 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1963-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e229">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and
               Frank Magro 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1971-1978</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e235">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and
               Paul W. Motter 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1982-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e241">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and
               Neil Ritchie 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1985-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e247">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and the
               Sitwells 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1981-1993</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e253">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence of Arthur P. Bean, Jr. and the
               University of Virginia Library 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1948
               (1973-1995)</unitdate></unittitle>
          <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e261">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Printed re the Sitwells 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1985-1992</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
