<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03864">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03864::Autographs of Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen)//EN" "viu03864.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Autographs of Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.1810-1885</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen, Autographs
<num type="collectionnumber">2010
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">6/1/2005</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Autographs of Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1810-1885</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">2010
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Autographs of Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1810-1885
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">2010
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Autographs of Civil War Officers and U.S. Statesmen, Accession #2010, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The collection was purchased from William F. Kelleher, of Grantwood, New Jersey on September 7, 1944.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 80 items, ca. 1810-1885, of Civil War officers and U.S. statesmen. The correspondence and documents have been chiefly compiled for their autograph value, but numerous letters
also concern military tactics during the Civil War, and political matters.
</p>
      <p>Autographs, 1810, 1830s-1840s, contain letters from Pascoe Grenfel; General Lewis Cass; John Parker Hale; Braxton Bragg; Philip Francis Thomas; and Charles Clark.
</p>
      <p>Letters of interest include: April 24, 1833, George McDuffie, Cherry Hill, South Carolina, mentioning his speech on the Force bill; May 8, 1834, Henry Laurence Pinckney, Washington, D.C., discussing
nullification and the deposit question; September 18, 1843, Dan Weisiger Adams, Jackson, Mississippi, requesting financial aid for an upcoming case against him in Warren County Circuit Court and discussing
Mississippi politics; May 18, 1844, Ward Hunt, Washington, D.C., to Don A. Cushman, discussing the efforts of Whigs to publish and mail communications meant to enlighten the people and counteract efforts of
opponents, explaining the necessity of gaining funds throughout the country for the Whig cause.
</p>
      <p>Autographs, 1850s, include letters from William Morris Meredith; Albert Gallatin Brown; Roger Atkinson Pryor; Daniel Stevens Dickinson; John Minor Botts; William Matthew Fenton; Henry Flagg French; William
Bigler; John Parker Hale; Robert Augustus Toombs; John Jones McRae; Isaac Toucey; and Samuel Deanes.
</p>
      <p>Letters of interest include: January 3, 1853, Walker Brooke, Washington, D.C., with lists of addresses of ex-governors and former members of Congress; August 28, 1856, S.D. [Watkins], Freeport, concerning
political controversy in the country and the election of 1856; December 8, 1859, Lewis Penn Withers Balch, Newport, Rhode Island, writing of the threat of war with the south and events at Harper's Ferry.
</p>
      <p>Autographs, 1860s, include letters and military documents and telegrams from Francis Preston Blair; George T. Swann; Thaddeus Stevens; Benjamin Gratz Brown; John Esten Cooke; Francis Wilkinson Pickens; Richard
Napoleon Batchelder; Walter Cauthen Cutting (military pass); Benjamin Franklin Butler (autograph) and John Schuyler Crosby.
</p>
      <p>Letters of interest include: February 11, 1860, John L. Morgan, Camp Floyd, Utah, to A.R. Boteler, concerning the disposition of troops in Utah and the great influence on war of Mormon church; January 8 &amp;
9, 1861, David Flavel Jamison to Brig. Gen. [James] Simons, on troops movement in Charleston, countermanding an order for embarkation of troops on the Marion; June 7, 1861, Samuel Taylor Glover, St. Louis,
Missouri, inquiring about steps taken by the Missouri Legislature to preserve the Union, including vigilante committees, enrollment of Union soldiers, etc; February 26, 1862, Col. Benjamin James Lea, to Brig. Gen.
Daniel Ruggles, listing the numbers of men and regiments in his command; June 13, 1862, Major General Edward A. Palfrey, C.S.A. Headquarters, Jackson, Mississippi, to Brigadier General Daniel Ruggles, discussing
supply movements.
</p>
      <p>Other items of interest include: June 27, 1864, special orders signed by John Archer Coke for a free Negro to report as a shoemaker; August 29, 1865, document detailing 100 bales of cotton hauled away from
Vicksburg plantation signed by Thomas C. Jones and George K. Birchett; August 31, 1868, to Lt. Gen. William Tecumseh Sherman, a bill for six rooms and fuel for August and acknowledgement with payment by check of
W.T. Sherman.
</p>
      <p>Autographs, 1870s, include letters from Stewart Lyndon Woodford; Richard W. Johnson; Thurlow Weed; Emmons Clark, John Wood; Benjamin Harvey Hill; Hiram Casey Young; James Edmund Bailey; Isham Green Harris and
Haywood Yancey Riddle; Otho Robards Singleton; Fernando Wood and John Wood.
</p>
      <p>Letters of interest include: May 8, 1872, Edward Alfred Pollard, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Roberts Brothers, Publishers-Boston, concerning the completion of the book <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Lost Curse</title>
as a follow up to the book <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Lost Cause</title>, and dealing with the condition and progress of African-Americans since emancipation; December 5, 1873, Edward Swift, Newport Barracks, to
Major General William Worth Belknap, containing a long discussion about his experiences in the Mexican War and how they relate to the situation in Cuba; May 7, 1879, Major General Irvin McDowell, San Francisco,
broadside, regarding his impressions of the Fitz-John Porter case.
</p>
      <p>Autographs, 1880s, include letters from John Henninger Reagan; William Paris Chilton; Joseph Eggleston Johnston; Samuel West Peel to Benjam Perley Poore; William Ruffin Cox; William Hayne Perry; and Benjamin
Franklin Butler.
</p>
      <p>Undated autographs are from Simon Cameron; Andrew Johnson, Winfield Scott; Alexander Stewart Webb; M.C. Yancey; Stephen Arnold Douglas, Varina Jefferson Davis, Ambrose E. Burnside, and Roscoe Conkling.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
