<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01624">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01624::Philip R. Fendall, Jr. Correspondence, 1813-1841 (1813-1817))//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01624.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01624::Philip R. Fendall, Jr.
             Correspondence, 1813-1841 (1813-1817))//EN"
             "viu01624.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Philip R. Fendall, Jr.
            Correspondence, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1841 (1813-1817)</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Fendall, Philip R., Jr.,
            Correspondence, 1813-1841 (1813-1817) 
            <num type="collectionnumber">10851-a</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">20 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Danielle Culpepper, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">08/16/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01624::Philip R.
            Fendall, Jr. Correspondence, 1813-1841 (1813-1817))//EN"
            "viu01624.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Philip R. Fendall, Jr.
         Correspondence, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1841 (1813-1817)</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">10851-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Philip R. Fendall, Jr. Correspondence 
         <unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813-1841
         (1813-1817)</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">10851-a</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of 27 letters.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Philip R. Fendall, Jr. Correspondence, 1813-1841
            (1813-1817), Accession # 10851-a, Special Collections
            Dept., University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville,
            Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This collection was purchased by the Library from
            Timothy H. Bakken, Halvor Americana, of Clarendon Hills,
            Illinois, on October 27, 1989.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Philip Ricard Fendall, Jr., a native of Alexandria,
         attended the College of New Jersey at Princeton from November
         1813 until his graduation in August 1815, and was admitted to
         the bar in Alexandria ca. 1820. He was a prominent lawyer as
         well as a political and literary writer. He later moved to
         Washington, D.C. where he filled the office of District
         Attorney of the District of Columbia from 1841-1845 and
         1849-1853, during the administrations of John Tyler, Zachary
         Taylor, and Millard Fillmore. For years, he was considered one
         of the most competent advocates of the capital.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection of correspondence, 1813-1817, 1830, and
         1841, consists of 27 letters, chiefly from Philip R. Fendall,
         Jr. (1794-1868) while a student at the College of New Jersey
         (now Princeton) and residing at Nassau Hall, Princeton, New
         Jersey. There are 22 letters to his mother, Mary, and his
         sister, Lucy Eleanor, in Alexandria, Virginia, and five
         letters to Fendall from Peter Hoffman Cruse (1795-1832),
         Oliver Norris, Edmund Lee, Jr., Josiah Stoddard Johnston
         (1784-1833), and Albert Gallatin Brown (1813-1880).</p>
      <p>The letters from Princeton reveal glimpses of Philip's
         personality, activities, and plans during this time, and
         provide an overall view of college life. In general, he
         discusses his entrance into college, expenses, studies,
         examinations, professors, fellow students, college life,
         religious matters, and various other personal and political
         affairs.</p>
      <p>During a visit to the northeast, Philip discusses his stay
         in Baltimore, Maryland with his friend, Charles Oliver, and
         his father, Robert Oliver, "the wealthiest, the most
         influential &amp; liberal man in Baltimore" (May 31, 1813). In
         November, he has made the trip north to begin college, and
         writes about his trip describing his fellow passenger, Dr.
         [John Syng] Dorsey (1783-1818), the nephew of Dr. [Philip
         Syng] Physick (1768-1837), describes Dr. [Ashbel] Green
         (1762-1848), discusses the books he needs, and mentions that
         there is a delay in the opening of the school (November 9,
         1813). He writes of his matriculation into college, on
         November 13, 1813, as well as the good fortune of having made
         the acquaintance of John Wurts (1792-1861) at the Tavern and
         being introduced to his brother whom he chose as his roommate,
         and includes college expenses and a list of books needed. His
         December 17, 1813 letter consists of a lengthy explanation of
         the college's two student literary institutions, the Whig and
         Cliosophic societies, and reveals his choice to join the
         Cliosophic Society. In his discussion of the societies, he
         writes about John Wurts and [Charles Pettit] McIlvaine
         (1799-1873) and their society ties. He writes again following
         preparation for quarterly examinations, admitting his
         enjoyment of religous studies even though it improbable that
         he will become a parson, discussing the parliamentary contest
         between [Richard] Stockton (1764-1828) and [Charles Jared]
         Ingersoll (1782-1862), and inquiring about his bills (January
         31, 1814). In a February 17, 1814 letter to his sister, he
         criticizes and instructs at great length on "the mechanical
         part" of her letter. During the time to follow, his letters
         are concerned more with religious concerns. In his May 20,
         1814 letter, he discusses Dr. Green's attendance at the
         Presbyterian convention and his hopes to benefit their church;
         and, makes observations on European affairs, including the
         Allied armies taking Paris, Napoleon Bonaparte, and the
         intended reduction of the French empire. On August 3, 1814, he
         describes a "remarkable circumstance" that occurred in the
         village where William Thornton committed suicide. His
         September 10, 1814 letter mentions the prospect of his
         literary distinction being favorable and discloses persons
         receiving first honor, including [John Blair] Dabney
         (1795-1868) from Virginia and [Charles Pettit] McIlvaine from
         New Jersey. In answer to news from his sister, he writes on
         January 14, 1815, expressing his shock at the deaths of Mr.
         [Richard] Brent (1757-1814 Dec 30), Judge [Nicholas] Fitzhugh
         (1763-1814 Dec 31) and the latter's son, Burditt (1795-1814
         Dec 26). His further concern for religious matters is evident
         in his letter of January 25, 1815, where he discusses "one of
         the most extraordinary revivals of religion..." at great
         length and attributes it to the conversion and explicit
         profession of [ ] Newbold of Philadelphia and mentions his own
         intention to devote his life to the Episcopalian ministry.
         Apparently his intentions were misunderstood by his mother,
         whom he writes on February 13, 1815, explaining that his
         intentions are not to become a preacher or minister, and
         giving a lengthy discussion of religion. His May 25, 1815
         letter reveals that the religious state of the college is
         highly gratifying. By summer 1815, he has nearly decided to
         embrace the study of theology and has come to the conclusion
         that knowledge should not be confined to a particular
         profession but rather should embrace the whole circle of
         science, and writes a discussion of his "future professional
         destination" to his mother on June 17, 1815. He also discusses
         Dr. Green's disapproval of the commencement ball and his
         subsequent contribution for the purpose of "erecting an
         establishment for instructing the poor children in religious
         knowledge." Letters from July and August 1815 are largely
         concerned with commencement and examinations, which are
         comprised of twenty-three branches of science (August 14,
         1815).</p>
      <p>In addition to Philip's letters home, there are five
         letters to him from friends. Peter H. Cruse writes from
         Alexandria, Virginia, on January 24, 1814, revealing his
         constant study of law, his mortification over Philip's
         decision not to become a fellow member of the Whig Society,
         and his pleasure at Philip's preference for Baltimore over
         Philadelphia. Oliver Norris writes from Alexandria, Virginia,
         on March 7, 1815, concerning religious concerns, particularly
         the revival of religion at the college, various denominations
         of Christians in the eastern United States, and the Episcopal
         Church in Virginia. Edmund Lee, Jr. writes from Princeton, on
         August 26, 1817, concerning Dr. Green's demands prior to
         commencement. There are also two letters, 1830 and 1841.
         Included is an interesting letter, November 30, 1830, from
         Josiah S. Johnston in Philadelphia, referring to the early
         events of Henry Clay's bid for the presidency in 1832 and the
         advantage of the National Convention for Clay, and mentioning
         the trouble in the current administration of Andrew Jackson.
         In his letter of April 4, 1841, Albert Gallatin Brown writes
         from Jackson, Mississippi, having just completed his first
         term as a U. S. Congressman, referring to affairs in that
         state as continuing to be in "a gloomy condition."</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
