<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02228">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02228::A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02228.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02228::A Guide to the Papers of
             the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families)//EN"
             "viu02228.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and
            Related Gilmour and Pollock Families 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1695(1755-1944)1981</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock
            Families, Papers of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">8409-a,-b,-c</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">144 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Alicia Pearia, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3/26/02</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-19" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 19, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02228::A Guide to the
            Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock
            Families)//EN" "viu02228.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related
         Gilmour and Pollock Families, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1695(1755-1944)1981</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">8409-a, -b, -c</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and
         Pollock Families, 
         <unitdate type="bulk" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1695(1755-1944)1981</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">8409-a, -b, -c</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 2750 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock
            Families, Accession #8409-a,-b,-c , Special Collections
            Dept., University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville,
            Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Accession #8409-a was purchased by the Library on April
            23, 1990 from Jerry N. Showalter, Bookseller, of Ivy,
            Virginia. The collection was previously on deposit in the
            Southern Historical Collection at the University of North
            Carolina. Subsequent accessions #8409-b and #8409-c were
            purchased by the Library on June 24, 1991 and August 3,
            1992, from Timothy Bakken, of Halvor Americana, Clarendon
            Hills, Illinois.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>John Janney, born November 8, 1798, was the son of Elisha
         and Mary (Gibson) Janney of Loudoun County. Janney played a
         large part in the development of Loudoun County, and was one
         of the leading attorneys in Virginia. He married Alcinda
         "Alice" S. Marmaduke on January 26, 1826, and became a citizen
         of Leesburg where he made his home for the remainder of his
         life. Although he did not take a very active part in politics,
         he was so well regarded by his fellow Whigs that he was
         drafted on several important occasions. He was a member of the
         Virginia Assembly as delegate from Loudoun County, and was a
         Whig elector in the presidential campaign of 1844. Janney was
         known for the eloquence with which he expressed the principles
         of his political party. He was elected a delegate to the
         Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1850, and, in 1860, a adelegate to the Secession Convention of 1861, then
         being elected by the Union men as president of the Convention.
         Janney opposed secession, however he accepted the adoption of
         the ordinance of secession when it was passed in April 1861.
         He continued to be an important influence on Virginia politics
         until his death on January 5, 1872.</p>
      <p>Robert Stevenson Janney, born September 22, 1915, was the
         son of Abram David Pollock and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney. He
         received his education from Princeton University and was
         awarded the New York Herald Prize for his thesis on "Foreign
         Policy of the United States 1930-37." From August 1937 to
         spring 1938 he took a trip around the world, sailing around
         Europe, India and Asia. In 1937 he made 2nd lieutenant R. O.
         T. C. in the United States Field Artillery, and in July 1941
         transferred to the Army Air Force and became 1st lieutenant.
         He trained at bases in Georgia, Louisiana, Alabama and South
         Carolina. He received his wings at Moody Field, Valdosta,
         Georgia in July 1942. Following intensive training in Light
         Bomb Group, he was made Captain, and in January 1943, he flew
         the South Atlantic and took part in the North Africa Campaign.
         In Italy he was with the 27th Fighter Bomber Group 12th Army
         Air Force as Group Operations Officer. During February to July
         1943 he flew missions over Casablanca, Oran, Algiers and
         Tunis; from July until August 1943, he was stationed on Malta
         and then in Sicily. He was promoted to Major in November 1943.
         He was killed on a mission over Cecina, Italy on January 16,
         1944. He received the Air Medal with three oak clusters and
         the Purple Heart award.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of ca. 2750 items,
         1695(1755-1944)1981, pertaining to the Janney and related
         Gilmour and Pollock families, and includes personal
         correspondence, political correspondence and papers including
         broadsides, financial and legal papers, genealogical material,
         and photographs. Persons represented include John Janney
         (1798-1872); Robert Stevenson Janney (1915-1944); Abraham
         David Pollock and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour (1886- ); Charles
         Phillips Janney (1839-1925); Lilias Janney (1874- ); Thomas
         Gordon Janney (1870- ); Abram David Pollock and Lucy
         (Stevenson) Janney; and, various members of the Gilmour,
         Janney and Pollock families.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Papers of John Janney</emph><lb/>The papers of John Janney include biographical material,
         personal correspondence, political correspondence and papers,
         and financial and legal papers.</p>
      <p>There are Civil War correspondence and papers of John
         Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney. There is a
         pass, June 5, 1861, for James C. Janney to go through the
         lines at Harper's Ferry. On August 22, 1861, John Janney,
         Leesburg, writes to [Joseph Eggleston] Johnston (1807-1891),
         Manassas Junction, about the illness of his servant "George"
         who drove his team to the Junction, offers fifty acres of hay,
         and requests that his horses with the artillery be returned.
         There is a list dated August-September 1861 of "Sick Soldiers
         nursed by Mrs. John P. Smart and Mrs. John Janney." On
         September 10, 1861, Arthur L. Rogers, Loudoun Artillery,
         writes concerning the appraisement of Janney's horses and the
         need for horses in service. On October 25, 1862, wife of
         William Barksdale (1821-1863), 
         <persname normal="Narcissa L. Smith Barksdale">N[arcissa] L. [(Smith)]
         Barksdale</persname> (d. 1875), Oakwood, near Columbus, Mississippi,
         writes to Alcinda Janney, reminiscing over her visit to
         Leesburg, and wishing she was able to avenge the wrongdoings
         done to Mr. Janney. She also describes the trip from Orange
         Court House to Huntsville, Alabama to Corinth and Columbus,
         Mississippi, mentioning the starving and sick soldiers
         encountered; and, mentions that Bayou Lara, Louisiana was
         burnt, that the sugar crop is large in Louisiana, that there
         were several marriages and births in camps, and that she has
         heard little news of her husband. There is a pass, November 1,
         1862, Headquarters, Whipple's Division, 12th Army Corps,
         Hillsborough, Virginia, for James and Robert Janney to Berlin,
         Maryland, and return with their brother Charles. On August 4,
         1865, Joseph [Eggleston] Segar (1804-1880), Washington,
         requests Janney's views as to the general sentiment in regard
         to the result of the late civil conflict and mentions
         President [Andrew] Johnson (1808-1875). In his letter of
         August 7, 1865 to Segar, Janney comments on the action of the
         military authority to nullify the election. There is another
         letter, April 1866, from Mrs. 
         <persname normal="Narcissa L. Smith Barksdale">N[arcissa] L. [(Smith)]
         Barksdale</persname>. Columbus, Mississippi, to [Alcinda Janney], wishing
         to see her friends in Leesburg, mentioning her
         African-American servants, Matilda and John, hoping that her
         sons, 
         <persname normal="Ethelbert">Ethel[bert]</persname>(1859-1892)
         and Willie [William] (1856-1877), may become such men as their
         father, and mentioning acquaintances, Lieutenant and Captain
         Tucker, of the St. George Tucker family. Mrs. Barksdale refers
         to the death of her husband, William Barksdale, writing "My
         life has been one long day of sorrow since I left Virginia,
         and the sun of my life set at Gettysburg" and the problems in
         bringing his remains home.</p>
      <p>There are two Civil War memorandums: "Events of the War,"
         August-September 1862 and "War Memo" June-July 1863, by
         Alcinda S. (Marmaduke) Janney. "Events of the War" begins with
         the explanation that Leesburg was first taken possession of by
         the Federal forces under the command of [John White] Geary on
         the 8th of March following the evacuation by the Confederate
         troops under General [Ambrose Powell] Hill, General [Richard]
         Griffith, Colonel [Winfield Scott] Featherston, and Colonel
         [William] Barksdale. In August, several Leesburg residents
         were arrested, including John Janney, N. Braden, Rev. Nourse,
         and Armistead Vandeventer. Mrs. Janney mentions Yankee
         soldiers entering the drugstore and peoples' homes looking for
         food and Colonel Geary requesting a room. She writes that the
         main body of troops occupied the town and a portion encamped
         on the "Morven" estate. Referring to March again, she writes
         that upon evacuation, General Hill gave orders to burn wheat
         stacks along Point of Rocks, Maryland, the finest mill on the
         Potomac, and a fine depot in the suburbs. In August, Leesburg
         and the surrounding area is left under Federal rule but the
         blockade was raised. The formation of a "Home Guard" disturbed
         the relative quiet, when they began to confiscate goods and
         arms from stores and raiding the houses of secessionists. She
         relates that a company of Southern cavalry arrived for the
         first time since March and were involved in some skirmishes
         with the enemy, that they met with General [William] Barksdale
         and Captain Doherty, and that the Southern troop left for
         Maryland. The "War Memo" relates the outrages committed by the
         Yankee troops and the conflicting news and rumors heard by
         civilians concerning the progress of the war. The June 28th
         entry finds Confederate troops on their farm procuring two old
         carriage horses and other necessities, causing an estimated
         loss of $2000 to $2500, according to [servant] "George"; the
         two old carriage horses were apparently returned at the
         insistence of "an old colored free woman." The June 29th entry
         mentions the Eleventh Corps under General [Oliver Otis] Howard
         being encamped on the portion of the Janney farm taken care of
         by [Thomas] Havener and committing outrages and that "they
         spoke of their deeds being justifiable because Mr. J was the
         President of the Va. Convention..." She writes of stories
         heard about various officers and their activities, including
         [Alexander Peter] Stewart, [Richard Stoddert] Ewell, [James]
         Longstreet, 
         <persname normal="Ambrose">A[mbrose]</persname><persname normal="Powell">P[owell]</persname>Hill, and Robert
         E. Lee. She also mentions various places where fighting
         supposedly is taking place, including Point of Rocks,
         Maryland, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, Vicksburg, Mississippi,
         and Charleston, South Carolina. The July 25th - 29th entries
         relate to civilian activity; mentioned are that persons are
         being allowed to travel safely to Washington and Baltimore
         without papers and the "murder" of a civilian named Mathews on
         the river near Whitesford.</p>
      <p>The financial and legal papers of John Janney consist of
         correspondence, memorandums of agreement and other legal
         documents, and accounts and bills of sale pertaining to
         Janney's legal practice and his farm operation. Among the
         papers, 1832-1839, are: license to practice law in Virginia
         (December 24, 1829); correspondence about claims against the
         deceased Solomon Parsons (January 24, 1832 and September 10,
         1834); opinion on the wills of John and Mary Hawling, with
         copies of the wills (1832); papers on Brown vs. Taylor (ca.
         1832-1847); and, letter from John Sinclair, Mountsville,
         relating the courses and lengths of the lines and descriptions
         of the corners in dispute between Charles Fenton Mercer and
         the Skinners (January 20, 1837). Among the papers, 1841-1848,
         are: an account of Amos Janney and Edmund Jennings (June 8,
         1841); memorandum of agreement between Alexander Kilgam and
         Aquila Janney re a tract of land in Loudoun County (December
         20, 1844); and, a circular letter announcing the establishment
         of the firm N. E. Janney and Company in the china, glass, and
         earthenware business (April 1, 1848). There is also
         correspondence from the period of 1841-1848. On October 10,
         1841, Barrow [Frere ?], Cottage Farm, Aldie, Loudoun County,
         writes concerning financial obligations with a postscript on
         "an improved implement for cleaning the roads." There are
         letters, July 20 &amp; 22, 1846, from Benjamin B. Davis,
         Salem, Ohio, to Samuel M. Janney, Springdale, Loudoun County,
         with copies of documents, concerning the legacy of Rebecca
         (McArtor) Murphy from Mahlon McArtor. On May 24, 1847, Abbott
         Lawrence (1792-1855), Boston, writes to John [Strother]
         Pendleton (1802-1868), Culpeper, that the machine shop at
         Lowell is full, with 600 persons at work, and that a new
         machine shop will be opening in the new town of Lawrence, and
         praises the young men from Virginia working in the machine
         shop. On October 23, 1847, Benjamin Hawley, Salem, Ohio,
         writes to Samuel M. Janney, Springdale, Loudoun County, on
         behalf of Rebecca (McArtor) Murphy. There is a letter, October
         11, 1847, from John Sinclair concerning a land dispute between
         Edward P. Upton and Jonathan Beard. Among the papers,
         1850-1859, are: bill of sale for a "negro woman 
         <persname normal="Harriett">H[arriett ?]</persname>Jackson"
         and "to warrant her to be a slave for life" from William H.
         Gallagher, Morrow, Ohio, to John Janney; answer of Common
         Council in Council of Alexandria vs. William Wheeler (August
         13, 1850); and, Abraham heirs certificates (January 1853).
         There is an agreement, September 30, 1850, between John Janney
         and Thomas Havener to hire the latter as a farmer on land
         owned by Janney in Loudoun County, describing the conditions.
         There are also a memorandum of agreement and accompanying
         papers, 1851-1862, between Robert Beverley and Charles C.
         Turner. There are documents, November - December 1859, giving
         power of attorney to John Morgan from Jane Morgan and others
         in the suit relating to the Hutchison estate. Among the
         papers, 1860-1870, are: papers re the Hutchison estate (April
         - August 1860); notes re Confederate States of America vs.
         Joshua Pancoast estate (July 1861); bond to John Janney from
         Hogan estate (December 30, 1861); and, receipts to Charles
         Phillips Janney from John Janney on account for the purchase
         of his law library (January 13 and December 18, 1869). Other
         items include United States Internal Revenue Service Licenses
         granted to John Janney of Leesburg, Loudoun County to carry on
         the business or occupation of lawyer (December 19, 1864 and
         July 10, 1866). There is also a letter, June 1, 1866, from
         John R. Watkins, Baltimore, concerning a suit against Matilda
         W. Fitzhugh of Loudoun County, in which he claims that he left
         $1600 in Federal money upon his capture by the Federal Army,
         which was spent by the Fitzhugh family.</p>
      <p>There are financial and legal papers, 1853-1869, relating
         to the Alexandria, Loudoun and Hampshire Railroad Company. On
         January 19, 1853, John Janney , Leesburg, writes to Charles B.
         Ball, discussing his week's service on horseback with Captain
         George L. Green, engineer, making a general examination of the
         country from Alexandria to Harpers-Ferry, mentioning various
         places visited in determining the route to be established. On
         June 27th, Lewis McHenry, Office Alexandria, Loudoun and
         Hampshire Rail Road Company, writes re securing subscriptions
         to finance the construction of the road to Washington. There
         is a proposal, March 25, 1854, from Miller &amp; Schuyler to
         build and equip the Railroad Company's road, exclusive of the
         cost of engineering and right of way, from Alexandria to its
         western terminus at Westernport or Piedmont. On December 22,
         1854, Lewis McHenry of the Railroad Company, writes enclosing
         comparisons of cost to company as estimates by contractors'
         bids. There are numerous stock receipts, 1855-1860. On
         February 27, 1857, Sidney G. Miller, Alexandria, writes
         detailing his proposal for the entire construction and
         equipment of the Railroad Company's road from the depot at
         Alexandria to the depot at Wineberten. There are documents
         establishing the appointment of John Janney as director on
         behalf of the Board of Public Works in the Alexandria, Loudoun
         and Hampshire Railroad Company (December 20, 1860 and January
         3, 1867). There is also a proposition, March 9, 1869, with a
         view to the further extension of the Railroad Company's
         road.</p>
      <p>There are financial and legal papers, 1796-1842, dealing
         with the business of the Mutual Assurance Society. There are
         Declarations for Assurance for dwelling houses and other
         buildings in Leesburg, Loudoun County for Samuel Hough (June
         1796), Lee Durham (November 1803), John Drish (January 1804),
         and Joseph Smith (May 1805). There is a Revaluation of
         Buildings declared for Assurance by Joseph Smith, signed by
         James Rawlings (September 26, 1816). Dated October 21, 1825 is
         a list of debts due to the Mutual Assurance Society "against
         fire on buildings of the State of Virginia for ensurance of
         buildings...," signed by James Rawlings. Papers of 1825 relate
         to a claim against John and Elizabeth Potter. There is a
         Revaluation of Building formerly declared for Assurance by
         Samuel Murray, signed by John Rutherford (October 18,
         1827).</p>
      <p>The personal correspondence of John Janney and Alcinda
         "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney refer chiefly to family news but
         does contain some political references. On December 5, 1831,
         Alice Janney, Hillsborough, expresses her feelings on the
         death of her twenty-three year old daughter, Cornelia, and
         includes a poem dedicated to her daughter. There are two
         letters, April 23 and May 11, 1841, from S. H. Williams,
         Cumberland, Maryland, concerning family news, including the
         last days and death of their child Alice. Letters from John
         Janney and Alice Janney dated September 19, October 1 and
         November 3, 1848 refer to the illness of Nathaniel Ellicott
         Janney and the family's efforts to take him home before his
         death. They describe the family's journey on the steamer
         "Alice" on the Ohio River, the last days and subsequent death
         of Nathaniel Janney with his wife, Sarah [Ann Irwin] Janney,
         and other family by his side; and, mention the arrival of
         Robert H. Miller, husband of Anna [Janney Miller]. On April
         24, 1851, John Janney, Richmond, writes to Alice Janney
         referring to mixed basis representation and the numerous
         politicians speaking their opinions on the subject. An April
         25, 1854 letter from George Adre, Greenwood, discusses the
         fire that destroyed his house. On April 23, 1861, John Janney,
         Richmond, writes Alice Janney that there may be trouble in
         Washington, Richmond is full of troops, and that General
         Robert E. Lee was introduced in the House. There is a letter,
         [April 1861], from John Janney, Alexandria, to Alice Janney,
         with the news that Tennessee has been electing members of
         convention and that he is to be president of the Convention in
         Richmond. He also mentions the books, The Children of the
         Abbey and Evelina [or, The History of a Young Lady's Entrance
         into the World]. There is a letter, August 16, 1871, from 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="William">W[illiam]</persname><persname normal="Mallet">M[allet]</persname>(1832-1912), The
         Rawley Springs, Rockingham County, Virginia, to John Janney,
         discussing the springs with "An Analysis of The Rawley Springs
         in Rockingham County, Va..." printed on the verso. There are
         two letters, September 30 and October 10, 1880, from Thamsin
         Janney, Lincoln, Virginia, to Alice Janney, sending medication
         and giving directions for their use.</p>
      <p>The political papers of John Janney are rich in discussions
         of the principles and activities of the Whig party,
         presidential elections, prominent politicians, and other
         aspects of Virginia and national politics from the 1830's
         until the 1860's.</p>
      <p>There are certifications, November 1836, that a
         presidential and vice-presidential election was held in the
         counties of Loudoun, Fairfax and Fauquier. In a letter of
         March 26, 1838, Henry Clay (1777-1852) writes to Janney
         concerning the speech of John 
         <persname normal="Caldwell">C[aldwell]</persname>Calhoun
         (1782-1850) which was brought to the attention of the Senate
         by Daniel Webster (1782-1852), Calhoun voting against the
         engrossment of the Sub-Treasury Bill, and hopes that the
         measure will be defeated in the House. Letters and documents
         of April 9 &amp; 21 and May 1, 1838, concern Janney's
         appointment to represent the state of Virginia at all meetings
         of the stockholders of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company
         in the absence of Charles 
         <persname normal="James">J[ames]</persname>Faulkner.</p>
      <p>During 1840 there are numerous invitations to Janney to
         either attend or speak at meetings, conventions and festivals
         in support of William Henry Harrison and John Tyler and the
         Whig party. A circular letter of May 30, 1840 from Clarksburg,
         invites the recipient to attend a convention of delegates "to
         aid the great cause of Reform in promoting the Election of
         General William Henry Harrison and John Tyler." There is a
         letter, June 11, 1840, from Samuel Chilton, Warrenton, written
         on behalf of the Central Whig Committee of Vigilance of
         Fauquier County; and, a letter, June 16, 1840, from G.
         Cuthbert Powell, Middleburg, concerning preparations for a
         large assemblage of people in July. A circular letter of July
         13, 1840 from Wheeling, invites the recipient to attend a
         convention in that city to "aid the cause of Harrison, Tyler
         and Reform" to be held by the Whigs of the states of Virginia,
         Pennsylvania and Ohio. A circular letter of August 24, 1840
         from Martinsburg invites the recipient to attend a public
         festival in the good cause of Harrison and Reform to be held
         by the Whigs of Berkeley County on September 10th. On August
         27, 1840, Charles 
         <persname normal="James">J[ames]</persname>Faulkner
         (1806-1884), Martinsburg, writes concerning his attendance at
         the event on September 10th. On August 29, 1840, 
         <persname normal="Philip">P[hilip]</persname><persname normal="Ricard">R[icard]</persname>Fendall
         (1794-1868), Washington, inquires about William Henry
         Harrison's and Martin Van Buren's militia plans. A circular
         letter of September 1, 1840 from Richmond, invites the
         recipient to attend the Whig State Convention to be held on
         October 5th. There is a letter, September 21, 1840, from the
         sub-committee of arrangements for the Whig State Convention to
         be held on October 5th, concerning the proposed arrangement to
         have a meeting of the several electors of the district on the
         day before the convention in order to form a college to select
         a president and secretary whose names will be announced by one
         of the electors. A circular letter of September 22, 1840
         states the resolutions adopted at the September 17th meeting
         of the Democratic Whig Club of Norfolk concerning the plans of
         the Grand Whig Encampment on the Plains of York Town to be
         held on October 19th. There are certifications, November 1840,
         that a presidential and vice-presidential election was held in
         the counties of Loudoun and Fairfax.</p>
      <p>There is a heartfelt letter, July 4, 1843, from Janney,
         Philadelphia, regretfully declining an invitation to unite
         with his fellow Whigs in that city, adding a sentiment on the
         "Cradle of American Liberty." During 1844 there are numerous
         invitations to attend or speak at meetings, conventions and
         festivals in support of Henry Clay and the Whig party. An
         interesting letter of February 22, 1844, from 
         <persname normal="Jeremiah">J[eremiah]</persname>Morton
         (1799-1898), "Moreland," Fluvanna County, discusses William
         ["Extra Billy"] Smith (1797-1887), 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="Strode">S[trode]</persname>Barbour
         (1790-1855), and his own speech on the subjects of the public
         debt and the bank and tariff question. On February 27, 1844,
         R. T. Daniel of Richmond writes as chairman of the Whig
         Central State Committee, to the Whig Electors in the state,
         making some suggestions on the gain of monies in order to
         publish and circulate the "Whig Address" and "Facts from the
         Record" and the registering of all Whig voters for the spring
         and fall elections by the appointment of an executive
         committee. A circular letter of March 9, 1844, "Young Men's
         Whig National Convention of Ratification. To the Young Whigs
         of the United States," serves as an invitation for a
         convention to be held on May 2nd in Baltimore. On March 9,
         1844, Wyndham Robertson (1803-1888), Fluvanna County, comments
         at great length on an editorial in the Whig on March 5th and
         other articles which apparently misrepresented his own remarks
         and those actions passed in the Committee, and also mentions
         [Willoughby ?] Newton (1802- 1874), [John Caldwell] Calhoun,
         and [Daniel] Webster. A circular letter of July 8, 1844,
         Clarksburg, is an invitation to a Whig convention to be held
         on August 21st. A circular letter of July 1844 is an
         invitation to a Whig Barbecue on July 25th, along with the
         Whig Convention. On July 19, 1844, Willis Green (1783-1845 ?),
         Washington, writes putting forth suggestions for "the
         prominent active Whigs of the State" to "unite upon some plan
         to act in concert throughout the state," similar to the plan
         adopted by the Whigs of Ohio which involves dividing the state
         into districts. A circular letter of July 22, 1844,
         Winchester, is an invitation for a "Grand District Mass
         Meeting" to be held on August 22nd "for the purpose of
         proclaiming and enforcing the principles and designs of the
         Whig party." A circular letter of July 24, 1844, Charlestown,
         Jefferson County, is an invitation for a mass meeting or
         county convention for "advocates of the Whig Cause and
         Principles." Letters of 1844 continue to discuss the Whig
         party as well as the Loco- Focos. A circular letter of August
         12, 1844 is an invitation for a Convention in the Whig City of
         Wheeling to be held on September 12th. A circular letter of
         August 28, 1844, Cumberland, Maryland, is an invitation for a
         mass meeting to be held on September 17th. On September 10,
         1844, James 
         <persname normal="French">F[rench]</persname>Strother
         (1811-1860), Rappahannock, writes concerning a meeting of the
         Whig party to be held in October. A circular letter of
         September 10, 1844, Williamsburg, is an invitation for a
         Convention at York Town on October 10th to support Henry Clay.
         On September 11, 1844, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart
         (1807-1891), Staunton, writes about upcoming plans including
         being present on October 1st when the Federal Court meets in
         order to make his arrangements for the continuance of his
         causes and traveling to New York in early October to attend
         the commencement of the proceedings of the Institute, and
         thereby regretfully declining a visit to Loudoun County. A
         circular letter of September 12, 1844, Martinsburg, is an
         invitation to address a Mass Meeting on October 10th "in
         defence of the great principles of our Party." A circular
         letter of September 20, 1844, Rockville (Montgomery County,
         Maryland) is an invitation to a Mass Meeting on September
         30th. On September 23, 1844, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart,
         Staunton, writes again declining a visit to Loudoun County
         because of previous engagements and commenting on the people
         of Loudoun as being "the most enlightened &amp; virtuous in
         Virginia." A letter from Warrenton on October 3, 1844 mentions
         the Loco- Focos meeting. William Cabell Rives (17932-1868),
         Castle Hill, writes on October 7, 1844 that he is unable to
         attend the gathering of the Whigs in Loudoun County due to ill
         health. On October 7, 1844, James 
         <persname normal="French">F[rench]</persname>Strother,
         Rappahannock, writes concerning meetings of the Whig party.
         There are certifications, November 6-11, 1844, that
         presidential elections were held in the counties of
         Rappahannock, Loudoun, Fauquier, Fairfax and Culpeper. There
         is an interesting letter of November 28, 1844, from John 
         <persname normal="Strother">S[trother]</persname>Pendleton
         (1802-1868), "Redwood," Culpeper, which mentions a
         conversation with Samuel Chilton about his being a candidate
         for re-election to the Congress, inquires of Janney whether he
         would accept such a nomination, and comments that public
         sentiment seems to be leaning toward Janney or himself.
         Pendleton's letter also includes a lengthy discussion of the
         future nomination and matters of consideration. There are also
         letters from Pendleton on December 9 and 10, 1844 concerning
         similar matters. On December 10, 1844, Janney writes to
         Pendleton concerning his inquiries on the next Congressional
         election and declining any nomination for himself, stating his
         views regarding this. Pendleton answers on December 16, 1844,
         commenting on Janney's letter, discussing how men in the
         public are sometimes urged to become a candidate, relating his
         regard for Janney and his own unwillingness to pursue the
         nomination if Janney were willing to, mentioning
         considerations of support from various counties, and referring
         to circumstances which would make a congressional term
         desirable to him. On December 28, 1844, J. C. Gibson,
         Culpeper, writes a lengthy, heartfelt political letter
         concerning Whigs, the Texas Whigs, Virginia, and elections and
         further wishes to solicit Janney's name as a candidate for
         this district in the ensuing election for Congress.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1845 continue to solicit John Janney
         as a congressional candidate. Janney answers Gibson on January
         4, 1845, declining the candidacy and giving his reasons. On
         February 20, 1845, H. A. White and R. W. Payne, Warrenton,
         wish to solicit Janny's name as a candidate to represent the
         Whig party in the 9th Congressional District of Virginia while
         claiming to understand his repugnance to become a candidate
         but urging him to change his mind; they discuss the Whigs and
         the Texas Whigs. Letters of March 1st and 3rd from Janney
         decline the candidacy and explain his reasons. There is a
         letter dated [ ] 28, 1845, from 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="Hill">H[ill]</persname>Carter to William B.
         Tyler which mentions the Whigs and John Janney.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1846 chiefly concern the question of
         holding a Convention of Virginia and the Tariff. On February
         4, 1846, there is a letter from Asa Rogers, Richmond,
         reporting that the Convention question is now under discussion
         in the House of Delegates and that prominent men are giving
         speeches [in the House] including [Joel?] Leftwich (1759-1846)
         of Wythe, leader of the western people; mentioning that
         [Zachary] Taylor is leaning toward the "extreme west";
         referring to representation by whole population for districts
         as opposed to "white basis"; mentioning the state west of the
         Blue Ridge and discussing the division of the state. On
         February 11, 1846, Janney answers Rogers, writing that he is
         unable to determine public sentiment regarding the subject of
         a convention and that he feels that the public attention may
         be drawn to foreign rather than domestic relations. He relates
         that he is in favor of organizing a convention based upon the
         "mixed basis" and not upon the "white basis" and says that
         some of Taylor's people favor the "white basis" and are "under
         the impression that the additional political power is given to
         the east because of the taxation upon slaves alone, and not on
         account of taxation upon property in the mass." Janney also
         mentions that the speech of 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="Strother">S[trother]</persname>Pendleton is
         being generally well received. John 
         <persname normal="Strother">S[trother]</persname>Pendleton,
         Washington, writes on February 24, 1846, requesting Janney's
         notes on the Tariff subject as he is about to examine the
         subject, and relating that the news from Europe is good
         through the prospect of peace attributed to the manner in
         which [James K.] Polk has managed the business. On March 2,
         1846, Janney sends his references on the Tariff subject and a
         copy of the "Fair Proposition" by A. H. H. Stuart, questions
         the intelligence of striking down the protective policy and
         the possible reactions from foreign government, and comments
         on various reports and expresses his views on the Tariff
         question. There are letters of introduction, ca. June-July
         1846 for Janney, explaining his inquiries into public or
         common schools, especially in regard to the plan of Free
         schools. Among the 1847 political papers is a letter, December
         19, 1847, from John 
         <persname normal="Strother">S[trother]</persname>Pendleton,
         Washington, to Harrison Gray Otis (1765-1848) and Thomas 
         <persname normal="Handasyd">H[andasyd]</persname>Perkins
         (1764- 1865), introducing Janney. There are also extracts,
         [1847], from General [Zachary] Taylor's letters, August to
         September 1847, concerning his candidacy for the
         presidency.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1848 discuss the nomination of Zachary
         Taylor for the presidency and the Whig party. There is a
         letter of introduction, January 19, 1848, for Janney from
         Abbott Lawrence (1792- 1855), Boston, to the residents of
         Lowell. There are resolutions adopted by the Loudoun Whig
         meeting on February 14, 1848. On March 3, 1848, John Janney
         writes to John 
         <persname normal="Minor">M[inor]</persname>Botts (1802-1869),
         Washington, concerning the nomination of General Zachary
         Taylor for the presidency. A circular letter of July 14, 1848,
         Alexandria, urges action to place Virginia among the Whig
         States of the Union and includes Virginia election returns for
         1844 and 1840. A letter, August 7, 1848, from John Janney to
         John 
         <persname normal="Minor">M[inor]</persname>Botts, Washington,
         concerns their positions on the nomination of Taylor. Botts
         writes on August 23, 1848, concerning his position on the
         nomination of Taylor and his belief that [Martin] Van Buren
         will take many more Whigs in the New England states. On
         December 20, 1848, Janney writes to B. W. Harrison, having
         examined the resolutions of the General Assembly of Virginia
         which were adopted on March 8, 1847. He discusses the issue of
         slavery and its relationship to Mexico and the new territory,
         mentioning the Missouri Compromise and the Wilmot Proviso, and
         the ramifications on the border states and southern states if
         the Union dissolves.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1849 further discuss the issue of
         slavery and the new territories. There are letters, February
         1849, urging Janney to take the nomination for a seat in the
         State Senate; there is a letter from Janney to "Fellow
         Citizens" declining to be a candidate. In a letter of February
         28, 1849, Robert E. Peyton, Gordonsdale, inquires whether or
         not Congress has a right to pass a law prohibiting slavery in
         the territories acquired from Mexico and whether or not
         Congress has a right to emancipate slaves in the District or
         forbid slave trade. In his letter of March 4, 1849, Janney
         comments on Peyton's letter, believing that it would be a
         misuse of power for Congress to prohibit slavery in California
         and New Mexico, claiming to oppose the Wilmot Proviso, stating
         that people authorized by a state constitution have the power
         to regulate slavery in their territory, believing that
         Congress has no right to abolish slavery or to forbid slave
         trade in the District of Columbia, and relating the possible
         effects on the District of Columbia if Maryland and Virginia
         ever became non-slaveholding states. On April 17, 1849, John 
         <persname normal="Strother">S[trother]</persname>Pendleton,
         Fredericksburg, writes on his progress as a candidate for
         Congress. Political papers of 1850 relate to the Virginia
         Constitutional Convention of 1850-1851. There are drafts of
         resolutions, February 22, 1850, by the citizens of Loudoun
         County. There is a letter, July 26, 1850, from John Janney "To
         the People of Loudoun County." A document dated October 1850
         to February 1851 includes minutes of the proceedings, the plan
         proposed, and resolutions for the Committee on the Judiciary
         of the Convention.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1851-1852 discuss the new constitution
         and representation based different methods. On May 30, 1851, 
         <persname normal="Richard">R[ichard]</persname><persname normal="William">W[illiam]</persname>N. Noland
         (1821- ), Albemarle County, inquires about and comments on the
         defeat of the "mixed basis" in the convention. On May 31,
         1851, Janney answers Noland, giving his views on
         representation and the best method of protecting the east,
         which he believes is with a "suffrage basis," and commenting
         on [James French] Strother's motion regarding the vote. 
         <persname normal="Richard">R[ichard]</persname><persname normal="Cassius">C[assius]</persname><persname normal="Lee">L[ee]</persname>Moncure (1805-1882),
         Fredericksburg, writes on June 23, 1851, concerning the
         establishment of district courts, having an independent
         judiciary, the mode of electing appellate judges, and
         improvements needed in the jury trial in relation to the new
         constitution. On December 5, 1851, Janney writes to his fellow
         citizens about his nomination for the office of senate and
         expressing his opinions on certain matters, including the new
         constitution and representation by "mixed basis" and "white
         basis." There are letters, April 2 and 4, 1852, from John W.
         Tyler, Warrenton, concerning his election as judge of his
         judicial circuit.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1857-1858 relate to the public land
         question, politics in general, and the University of Virginia.
         On March 28, 1857, George 
         <persname normal="Eyster">E[yster]</persname>Senseney, editor,
         Winchester Republican, refers to the public land question and
         the injustice in regard to the dispositions of the common
         domain, comments on [Charles James] Faulkner taking both sides
         of the land question in order to help his election, and
         requests to offer his name as a candidate for Congress. On
         April 3, 1857, Janney writes to Senseney, declining to be a
         candidate and commenting on the Constitutional Convention of
         Virginia 1850-1851. There is an interesting letter, April 29,
         1858, from 
         <persname normal="Valentine">V[alentine]</persname><persname normal="Wood">W[ood]</persname>Southall ( -1861),
         Charlottesville, concerning the University of Virginia. He
         comments disfavorably on the University since "the reign of
         Democratic terror commenced in Va," claims that the entire
         visitors board and faculty appear to have been selected
         because of their political opinions, mentions his disdain for
         Governor [Joseph] Johnson (1785-1877), refers to the political
         clique of "Calhoun abstractionists, fire eaters, &amp;
         disunionists," mentions the visit to the University by [ ]
         Davis and the discourteous reception which apparently led to
         the loss of a bill proposing an appropriation to the
         University, comments passionately on the deplorable state of
         public affairs, state and federal, refers to [James Buchanan
         (1791-1868)] "chief magistrate who seems but little removed
         from lunacy," and touches on other political topics. On May
         22, 1848, Southall writes about his dissatisfaction with the
         course of the Richmond Whig and its involvement in the subject
         of a revival of the African slave trade.</p>
      <p>Political letters and papers of 1860-1862 relate to the
         Union, the Constitution, and the Convention of Virginia. There
         are drafts concerning the presidential election and the
         organization of the Union Party in Loudoun County (October
         1860). There are resolutions to be laid before a meeting of
         the citizens of Loudoun County concerning issues relating to
         the Union and the Constitution, especially the fugitive slave
         laws and slavery in the new territories (November-December
         1860). There is a draft of Loudoun County resolutions
         concerning the imminent danger to the Constitution of the
         United States and the Union (1860). There is an 1861 Electoral
         Ticket for Jefferson Davis as President and Alexander H.
         Stephens as Vice-President for the Confederacy. On February
         23, 1861, [ ] Huey, Philadelphia, writes to Janney, who is
         presiding over the Virginia Convention, advising that Virginia
         must stay in the Union at all costs, expressing his belief
         that a majority of both houses of Congress and the Supreme
         Court will be in favor of the South, and inquiring as to what
         can be gained by secession that is not already secured in the
         Union. There is a copy of the March 20, 1861 Congressional
         Record "Our First Grave Constitutional Crisis 1861; Speech of
         Hon. Dale Alford." On April 18, 1861, 
         <persname normal="John">J[ohn]</persname><persname normal="Jordan">J[ordan]</persname>Crittendon
         (1787-1863), Frankfort, Kentucky, writes concerning the
         Resolution of the Convention of Virginia in appreciation of
         Crittendon's efforts in the Senate. A lengthy letter, April
         18, 1861, from Charles Cocke, Huntley, Nelson County,
         questions the outcome of the Convention of Virginia. Cocke
         writes a passionate political outpouring on the effects of
         "dissolution of the Union," including "the terrors of a civil
         strife" and "the subversion of the noblest form of
         Government." He claims that the Convention "laid down the
         principle that secession for cause, is justifiable"; comments
         on South Carolina's reasons for seceding; scoffs at the
         advocates of secession -- 
         <persname normal="James">J[ames]</persname><persname normal="Murray">M[urray]</persname>Mason (1798-
         1871), 
         <persname normal="Robert">R[obert]</persname><persname normal="Mercer">M[ercer]</persname><persname normal="Taliaferro">T[aliaferro]</persname>Hunter
         (1809-1887), [William] "Extra Billy" [Smith] (1797-1887), 
         <persname normal="Shelton">S[helton]</persname><persname normal="Farrar">F[arrar]</persname>Leake
         (1812-1884), and 
         <persname normal="Roger Atkinson">R[oger Atkinson
         ?]</persname>Pryor (1828-1919); comments on several leaders as
         good men, including John Janney, William [Cabell] Rives, and
         others; and, comments that if the "rebel states had stood
         their ground, [Abraham] Lincoln would have been in a minority
         in both Houses of Congress..." There are two letters, April 28
         and May 1, 1861, from 
         <persname normal="William Cabell Rives">W[illiam] C[abell] Rives</persname>,
         "Castle Hill," Cobham, concerning political matters. The former
         letter from Rives relays the content of two conversations with
         the vice-president of the Confederate States, [Alexander
         Hamilton] Stephens; reveals that he is pleased with "the calm
         &amp; dispassionate tone of his mind, &amp; the frankness
         &amp; sincerity with which he expressed his views"; and,
         claims that Stephens is anxious for a peaceable separation.
         The latter letter concerns Rives' appointment as one of the
         delegates to the Congress at Montgomery, and encloses a letter
         to be laid before the Convention as follows: expressing his
         acknowledgments for the honor of being elected as one of the
         Delegates of Virginia to the Congress of the Confederate
         States and regretfully declines acceptance because of his
         delicate health. Rives writes a heartfelt, patriotic letter in
         support of the Commonwealth and its decision of secession. A
         letter of May 3, 1861 from George 
         <persname normal="William">W[illiam]</persname>Summers (1804-
         1868), Kanawha Courthouse, concerns the progress of the
         Convention of Virginia; inquires about the status of Virginia
         as a Confederate State, and the possibility of a peaceable
         separation with the South acting only in defense; and, states
         the conditions in his region. On May 5, 1861, Rives writes in
         deference to the wishes and opinions expressed by Janney and
         A. H. H. Stuart that he has decided "to undertake the mission
         to Montgomery," and refers to Janney's address to General
         [Robert E.] Lee upon his appointment to the chief command of
         our military forces. A letter of June 14, 1861, from Rives
         concerns his acceptance of the duties of the appointment
         conferred upon him by the Convention. There is an August 1861
         document of the property of John Janney impressed for the use
         of the Confederate states. There is a letter [1861] "To the
         People of Loudoun" revealing thoughts on Virginia and the
         Union and the question of secession and the organization of
         the Convention of Virginia. On June 9, 1862, 
         <persname normal="Francis">F[rancis]</persname><persname normal="Harrison">H[arrison]</persname>Pierpoint
         (1814-1899), Wheeling, West Virginia, writing as provisional
         governor, indicates his desire to restore peace and order in
         Loudoun and the adjoining counties and warns that he intends
         to protect the Union men and their property, threatening to
         send away the secessionists at any sign of trouble.</p>
      <p>Political letters of 1865-1868 are chiefly between Janney
         and Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart and concern the possibility
         of the reunion of Virginia and West Virginia. There is an
         October 11, 1865 document, "The Voter's Oath," signed by John
         Janney. On March 9, 1866, Alexander 
         <persname normal="Hugh">H[ugh]</persname><persname normal="Holmes">H[olmes]</persname>Stuart
         (1807-1891), Staunton, writes concerning his election as one
         of the commissioners to West Virginia, referring to the
         resolutions directing them to communicate with the government
         legislature of West Virginia, and indicating that a
         postponement would be best witih the commissioners meeting in
         Richmond some two or three weeks from now to confer with each
         other and with Governor [Francis Harrison] Pierpont. On March
         28, 1866, Stuart encloses a copy of a letter dated March 21st
         from Governor [Arthur Ingram] Boreman (1823-1896), Wheeling,
         West Virginia, concerning the resolutions adopted by the
         General Assembly of Virginia on the subjects of a reunion of
         the states of Virginia and West Virginia, the settlement of
         the public debt, and a division of the public property of
         Virginia as existed prior to the separation. There is a
         letter, June 19, 1866, from 
         <persname normal="Joshua">J[oshua]</persname>Francis Fisher
         (1807-1873), concerning his pamphlet ["Concessions and
         Compromises" ?] before the meeting of the South Carolina
         Convention, which showed his feelings and principles at the
         beginning of their troubles. On February 26, 1867, Stuart
         discusses their resignations and the prospect of delaying them
         until the new legislature meets and provides his impressions
         on the current political situation. A letter, June 28, 1867,
         from William Cabell Rives refers to the Trustees of the
         Peabody Fund appointment of Dr. [Barnas] Sears (1802-1880) as
         their general agent. On February 24, 1868, John Janney writes
         to R. T. Daniel concerning a political address, indicating a
         change to be made on the statement about the Convention of
         Virginia that ratified the Constitution of the United States,
         and mentioning [Robert Mercer Taliaferro] Hunter. On December
         25, 1868, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart writes that reports
         indicate that something must be done "to save Virginia from
         ruin," and mentions [John Brown] Baldwin (1820-1873), [John]
         Echols (1823-1896), and [ ] Sheffey, who request Janney's
         presence at a meeting in Richmond. A March 20, 1870 letter
         from Charles B. Ball, Richmond, to George N. Owing concerns
         his chances for the judgship. There are several undated
         political items, including a petition "To the Senate of the
         United States of America," by the citizens and voters of
         Philadelphia, requesting an alteration to the Constitution
         concerning representation as related to slave property. There
         are also notes: "Reasons for voting against re-eligibility in
         committee," "Subject of Guarantees" on basis and re-
         eligibility of government, and on amendments to the
         Constitution, chiefly regarding representation.</p>
      <p>There are transcripts of letters, February - April 1861,
         from John Janney to his wife, Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke)
         Janney while he is in attendance at the Convention of Virginia
         in Richmond. Although the letters are of a personal nature,
         Janney does relate his opinions and other information-- some
         confidential--about the Convention and its progress.</p>
      <p>Among John Janney's papers are correspondence and financial
         and legal papers of Solomon Parsons. There are letters,
         1810-1813, from Solomon Parsons to his wife, Harriett E.
         Parsons. On April 11, 1813, Parsons mentions Admiral [John
         Borlase] Warren (1753-1822) and his fleet being at the mouth
         of the Potomac River and refers to his insolence in sending
         his compliments to their fort. On July 19, 1813, Parsons
         writes that he believes that the British will come up as far
         as Dumfries or opposite Occoquan for water before making their
         escape back, that the town is nearly all soldiers, that he
         does not know what his part will be yet, and that more troops
         are arriving. There are letters on October 12 and December 21,
         1821, to Henry Gunnell concerning the John Coffey estate and
         its appraisal. On September 10, 1816, Jacob Parsons,
         Gloucester, writes about the failure of the tanning business,
         looking for a new livelihood, and commerce and the fisheries
         being depressed. There is a letter, February 30, 1828, from
         Gloucester, referring to the attendance of parties and balls,
         family news, religious matters, and cousin John [Janney].
         There is a June 20, 1829 letter from Baldwin Bradford,
         Warrenton, to Parsons, concerning an enclosed letter dictated
         and marked by an African-American woman, Nancy Jackson,
         requesting another African-American woman, Patsy Johnson, to
         give ten dollars to Solomon Parsons after her death. It notes
         that Samuel Johnson, husband of Patsy Johnson, is a free black
         man who lives with Bradford. The enclosure, February 9, 1829,
         [Nancy Jackson] to "Dear Master" states her intentions.
         Letters of July 14 and July 18, 1829 between Parsons and
         Thomas W. Hewitt concern the John Coffey estate and an inquiry
         into the sale of the slaves and whether or not they brought as
         much as they were worth. There is a letter, July 25, 1829,
         from 
         <persname normal="Mordecai">Mord[ecai]</persname>Miller,
         Alexandria, in which he advises one Sibblefield not to give up
         the rifles to the government. On September 13, 1829, Jacob
         Parsons, Gloucester, writes to his brother, commenting on
         their having similar views on religious subjects yet such
         differing views on political and commercial topics. On
         September 24, 1829, 
         <persname normal="Anthony">A[nthony]</persname>P. Gover,
         Alexandria, refers to foreign affairs, mentioning the
         Russo-Turkish war and the Russians playing havoc with the
         Turks and to domestic affairs, mentioning "John Eaton, and the
         chaste and enlightened cabinet" of Andrew Jackson and the
         changes to be made in the Custom House offices. Letters of
         September 24 and October 4, 1829, from John R. Pierpoint,
         Alexandria, concern the books, James Fenimore Cooper's Works
         and Ivanhoe [by Sir Walter Scott]. Gover also writes on
         December 17, 1829, about the speculation in wharf property and
         the establishment of a foundry and a new ferry in Alexandria.
         There are interesting letters, October - November 1829, from
         Fanny B. B. Wilson, "Happy Retreat," Occoquan, to her brother,
         Solomon Parsons, as a widow with several small children
         attempting to settle the estate of her late husband, Richard
         Wilson. She discusses options for making a living such as
         working part of the farm; the Sheriff calling for a fee bill
         and taxes and taking her horse, which she hired out for money
         to buy bread, when she could not pay; the tenant on the
         Lindsay farm not paying rent; and problems with settling the
         estate and its outstanding debts. She also lists the names of
         her six children. Letters of January 12 and March 3, 1830,
         from J. D. Parsons, Charleston, South Carolina, to his brother
         chiefly concern business and mention brother Samuel losing his
         office, his own business being in much confusion, the
         bankruptcy of a former commercial debtor and ensuing financial
         problems, and mercantile, agricultural and mechanical
         operations, and the improvement in business by March. On
         January 17, 1830, Jacob Parsons, Gloucester, writes about a
         shipment of a keg of mackerel and there being no sale for fish
         except mackerel; he also "hopes that Congress will do
         something toward removing the shackles from commerce" and
         gives his views on how to maintain a healthy commerce. A
         letter of February 1, 1830 discusses business progress at
         Occoquan, mentioning John Morgan selling a great many goods,
         the factory being in full operation, some thirty good looking
         and well-dressed girls being well broken in to the business,
         several houses being built, and the village needing a tailor
         and a shoemaker. He also mentions freight voyages to St.
         Thomas, Brazil, and St. Domingo and the effect of the
         Temperance Society around Alexandria. A letter of March 17,
         1830, from Thomas Love, Lebanon, [Ohio], gives a description
         of the geography of Fairfield, Ohio and surrounding land and
         waterways; and, mentions various newspapers published in Ohio,
         the Message from the President [Andrew Jackson], and the
         tuition at Oxford College, Butler County, Ohio. On March 19,
         1830, 
         <persname normal="Anthony">A[nthony]</persname>P. Gover,
         Alexandria, writes concerning the stir at their town election
         for councilmen in relation to taxation; the canal dispute and
         building the road causing much corporate debt; news of local
         business, including the crockery business of a local, and a
         foundry and spinning machine maker and the establishment of a
         ferry on the wharfs. A letter of April 11, 1830 mentions
         family and local news of Alexandria, John R. Pierpoint being
         their only boarder, Samuel M. Janney moving to Occoquan, and
         the house being rented to [Samuel] Carusi, the music and
         dancing master. A letter of May 13, 1830, from Gover reports
         the progress on the [Alexandria] canal and refers to the
         magnitude of the undulation and the wonderful locks. There is
         another letter, June 15, 1830, from Fanny B. B. Wilson,
         reporting that she has still not received money or property
         from the estate because of the lack of an administrator and
         that she is sending the majority of her children to school.
         The financial and legal papers of Solomon Parsons refer to the
         John Coffey estate (February 11, 1807 and January 24, 1827);
         the farm called "Chantilly" in Fairfax County (September 1,
         1818); smith shop accounts, 1821-1823; and, accounts between
         Solomon Parsons and 
         <persname normal="Anthony">A[nthony]</persname>P. Gover.</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Papers of Robert Stevenson Janney</emph><lb/>There are letters, 1924-1943, from Robert Stevenson
         Janney to his parents, Abram David Pollock and Lucy
         (Stevenson) Janney, during his childhood and youth and later
         during his service in Europe during World War II. On March 5,
         1938, he writes from San Francisco, California, following
         visits to Tokyo and Yokohama, Japan and to Honolulu and Oahu,
         Hawaii and the voyages between places. He mentions sailing
         with Taylor Statten and his wife who were on their way home
         from India where they had been travelling and observing Y. M.
         C. A. work. On December 8, 1941, while training at Maxwell
         Field Replacement Center, Montgomery, Alabama, he writes
         concerning the attitudes of the men receiving the news of the
         war [the attack on Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, on December 7th], the
         duplicity of the Japanese government, the immediate effect of
         guards being doubled or tripled and wearing uniform at all
         times, and his friends in the 17th Squadron now in Manila.
         Letters of February 1 &amp; 23 and March 7, 1943, "Some Where
         in North Africa" mention the climate; the quarters and meals
         being satisfactory; continuing preparations for training;
         encouraging news from the Russian front; amusement in the form
         of movies, a traveling French vaudeville show, and card games;
         doing some flying; spending all their times on the base; Arab
         farms and shepherds nearby; and foods for soldiers.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1925-1936, to his aunts, Lilias Janney
         and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, concerning his studies,
         activities and school sports while a student at Princeton
         University (1934-1936) and a visit to the resort Grandmere in
         the district of Quebec and playing golf (October 8, 1935).
         There are letters, 1937-1943, from Janney to his aunts during
         his youth and later during his service in Europe during World
         War II. Letters from September 1937 to February 1938 detail
         his visit to various countries in Europe and to Japan. A
         September 10, 1937 letter from London, England mentions visits
         to the British Museum, Houses of Parliament, Tower of London,
         Madam Tussaud's, St. Paul's, London School of Economics,
         Oxford University, and Bodleian Library; attending a Russian
         ballet; and, hearing [George] Campbell Morgan (1863- ) preach
         at Westminster Chapel. An October 12, 1937 letter from Tours,
         France describes visits to the Chateau of Chenonceaux, the
         Chateau of Ambiose, and the interior of a wine-making
         establishment; mentions visits to Paris, the Louve, the
         Exposition, the opera (Rigoletto, Carmen, and Fidelio),
         Versailles, Church of the Madeleline, Arc de Triomphe, the
         Invaides Palaces, Notre Dame, Church of the Sacre Coeur,
         Gardens of Luxembourg, Napoleon's tomb, and the Eiffel Tower. A postcard dated November 16, 1937 from Vienna,
         Austria, concerns a stay in Munich, Germany which ended
         with a Nazi festival with the presence of German officials,
         including Adolf Hitler; and visits to Oberammergau and the
         Bavarian Alps. A postcard dated December 9, 1937 from Naples,
         Italy mentions visits to Capri via Sorrento and the Blue
         Grotto and Pompeii and Vesuvius. A postcard [1937] from
         Florence, Italy mentions staying in Venice for five days and
         visits to the ancient ruins of Fiesole and an exhibit of
         Italian thirteenth and fourteenth century art. On December 12,
         1937, Janney writes from Nice, France, a lengthy letter giving
         details of activities and descriptions of places visited while
         in Europe up to this date. He mentions his traveling
         companions from Princeton, Boardman Jones of St. Louis and
         Bradford Cochran of Plainfield, New Jersey. Places visited in
         Germany included Oberammergau, where they saw the wood
         carvers' shops and the theatre where the Passion Play is
         performed; Linderhof, a rococo palace built by Kind Ludwig II of
         Bavaria; beautiful scenery in Bavarian countryside; and, the
         top of Germany's highest mountain, the Zugspitze. They took a
         train trip to Innsbruck and Vienna, Austria, where they
         visited the Crown Jewels, Imperial Palace, Habsburg crypt, an
         art gallery, Rigoletto, an exhibition at the Spanish Riding
         School, a military museum, and the "Blue Danube." He comments
         on his impressions of South Germany and of Vienna. He details
         his visits to places in the Italian cities of Venice,
         Florence, Rome, and Naples. Places mentioned include: Doge's
         Palace, the Lido, Academia Art Gallery, Church of San
         Zacharia, Cathedral of San Marco, Church of Santa Maria della
         Salute, and, a glass-blowing establishment (Venice); Uffizzi
         Gallery, Church of Santa Croce, Church of San Miniato, Pitti
         Gallery, a Giotto exhibition, the Cathedral, and, the ruins of
         Fiesole (Florence); the ruins of the forum and coliseum, the
         Baths of Diocletian and Caracalla, the Catacombs, National
         Museum, St. Peter's, Apian Way, Capucina Monastery, Vatican
         Museum, Sistine Chapel, and Mostra Augustina (Rome); and,
         Pompeii and Mt. Vesuvius, Capri, and Sorrento (Naples). On
         January 25, 1938, onboard ship toward Japan, Janney writes
         about his voyage on the S. S. Potsdam from Genoa, Italy to
         Manila with stops at Port Said, Egypt; Colombo, Ceylon; and
         Singapore, Manila. He gives a brief description of volcano
         eruptions at Stromboli and the straits of Messina in Italy.
         In Singapore, Malaysia, he made visits to botanical gardens,
         docks and native quarters. He describes Johore and life there
         and mentions meeting interesting peoples in Manila, including
         an Englishman named Hearn. A postcard dated February 1, 1938
         from Kyoto, Nippon [Japan] mentions visits to shrines and
         palaces in Kyoto and Nara. On March 6, 1938, he writes from
         San Francisco, California about his tour of San Francisco and
         surrounding country, with visits to Berkeley, Oakland, the
         University of California, Mt. Tamalpais, Muir Woods, and
         Chinatown. He mentions hearing Reverend [Charles Rosenbury]
         Erdman (1866-1960) of Princeton, New Jersey preach. There is a
         description of Honolulu, Hawaii and mention of his activities.
         He mentions the voyage on the Empress of Japan from Yokohama
         with interesting people, including Taylor Statten and his
         wife, returning from India to observe Y. M. C. A. work; the
         kindness of the Japanese people; visits to Kobe, Kyoto, Nara,
         and Tokyo, and, meeting the Hepners, Lutheran missionaries
         from Virginia. Letters from March - June 1940 concern work
         with the Japan Reference Library.</p>
      <p>Robert Stevenson Janney sent letters to his aunts from
         October 1941 to December 1943 while training and serving in
         the United States Army Air Corp. Letters of October 25 and
         November 3, 1941 are written while training with the 89th Bomb
         Squadron at Savannah Air Base and mention his application for
         flying school being favorably received, General [George
         Catlett] Marshall (1880-1959), plans to go to flying school at
         Maxwell Field in Montgomery, Alabama, and the beautiful
         gardens owned by the Henry family. On November 24, 1941, he
         writes from the Air Corps Replacement Center, Maxwell Field
         about his activities, including plans to take flying training
         with seventy other officers; being in the preliminary period
         designed to give the men their foundation in discipline, drill
         and general army routine; living arrangements; and, having
         dinner where at the Baldwin's where Beverley Randolph Tucker
         of Richmond was a guest. Letters of December 22, 1941 and
         January 8 and February 17, 1942, written from the Hawthorne
         School of Aeronautics, mention living arrangements, the
         routine of army life, his flying progress and first solo ride
         and acrobatic maneuvers, and the final party at the local
         cadet club. He writes from Basic Flying School at Shaw Field,
         Sumter, South Carolina on February 23 and March 16, 1942,
         mentioning the new facility; their program being full with
         classes in the morning and flying the afternoon; a new type of
         plane more complicated, faster and more powerful; restrictions
         on discussions of training; and, a dance for the cadets in
         Hartsville. Letters of May 3 and June 6, 1942, written from
         Moody Field, Valdosta, Georgia, mention the trip from Sumter
         to Valdosta; advanced planes; having an x-card for gas
         rationing; Cecil Thompson of the First Presbyterian Church;
         bad weather delaying flying; doing some night flying, local
         and cross-country, in addition to regular day time flying and
         ground school; and a weekend trip to Montgomery, Alabama. On
         July 19, 1942, Janney writes while with the 465th Bomb Squad
         at Key Field, Meridian, Mississippi, mentioning that they are
         learning to fly a new type of plane, the Douglas Boston bomber
         (DB-7), which is fast and maneuverable and chiefly used
         against ground forces and that they are being readied for
         combat duty. Janney was with the 465th Bomb Squadron until
         December 1942. On September 21, 1942 he writes that the
         maneuvers were a valuable experience and that they took place
         along the Sabine River, the boundary between Louisiana and
         Texas and that they used the A-20-B. Postcards, September to
         November 1942, from bases in Louisiana, mention his new
         position as squadron operations officer, scheduling flights,
         the 27th Bomb Group doing maneuvers in the region, living
         quarters, athletic facilities, flying facilities, and night
         flying. On December 27, 1942, Janney writes while with the
         27th Bomb Group at Harding Field, Baton Rouge, Louisiana,
         stating that training is proceeding at an increased rate and
         that he was presented with a Swiss wristwatch from the men in
         his squadron upon his retirement as their commanding officer.
         In a letter of January 18, 1943, en route to North Africa, Air
         Base, Natal, Brazil, he describes a quaint town of about
         200,000, with the natives a mixture of Portugese, Indian and
         African-American strains. On March 21, 1943, with the 27th
         Bomb Group, somewhere in North Africa, he writes about their
         recreation of volleyball and baseball; the Arabs and French in
         the area; a diet of eggs, oranges and tangerines; Bill
         Clifford of Loudoun County being there; and, good living
         conditions. On April 15, 1943, with the 47th Bomb Group,
         somewhere in North Africa, he writes about his transfer to
         another organization, with other fellow pilots from the old
         group and describes a visit to Algiers. On May 24 and June 20,
         1943, with the 84th Bomb Squadron, 47th Bomb Group, he writes
         about seeing many prisoners on his trips to the battle area;
         some places being torn up and strewn with equipment while some
         fields are under cultivation; land mines left by the Germans;
         his new living arrangements; Walter Janney, Jr. being around;
         and, the squadrons being reviewed by a high British official.
         There is V-mail dating from July through December 1943 which
         mention living in a British Officers' quarters and a visit to
         Constantine, Algeria where Bastille Day was celebrated with
         parades and patriotic ceremonies (July 25, 1943); being at a
         British base and the British putting to use what they learned
         about managing in the field (August 4, 1943); visits to Mt.
         Etna, Catania and other places as well as Syracuse, Augusta
         and the straits of Messina and the inhabitants of Sicily,
         Italy (September 5, 1943); a visit to the Isle of Capri
         (October 4, 1943); and, a visit to Naples, Italy (November 1,
         1943).</p>
      <p><emph render="bold">Correspondence and Papers of the Gilmour,
         Janney and Pollock families</emph><lb/>Papers of the Gilmour, Janney and Pollock families
         include correspondence and papers of members of these families
         of Loudoun County. Folders are arranged in groups by specific
         individuals or couples: Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and
         Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour (1886- ); Abram David Pollock
         Janney (1880- ) and Lucy (Stevenson) Janney; Charles Phillips
         Janney (1839-1925) and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney ( -1908);
         John Janney, Jr. (1878-1967); Lilias Janney (1874- );
         Nathaniel Ellicott Janney (1813-1848); Thomas Gordon Janney
         (1870- ); and, Lily Pollock.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1897-1946, to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and
         Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour cover a variety of topics. On June
         19, 1897, John R. Sampson, principal, Pantops Academy,
         Charlottesville, to writes A. D. P. Gilmour concerning his
         favorable decision to hire Gilmour for a vacancy in the
         mathematical department. There is an essay, October 27, 1898,
         describing "The Island of Canna" and "The Cave at Eigg" in
         Scotland. On October 3, 1939, Carrie Lena Moffett refers to
         her visit to Shanghai, China, mentioning news of the Moffetts
         and others, the hospital and the Refugee Hospital in Shanghai,
         the need for Chinese technicians in Kiangyin, and Ruth Worth
         teaching technicians at the Refugee Hospital. On December 30,
         1939, Peter Mao, Boys' Department, Y. M. C. A., Shanghai,
         writes concerning missionary and education work in Kiangyin
         and a celebration in honor of three of their missionaries,
         Lacy L. Little, Andrew Allison, and Kathryne L. Thompson. On
         January 30, 1940, Charles W. Worth, Hangchow Christian
         College, Hangchow, Che., China, writes about the uncertain and
         confusing political situation, the effects of the Treaty
         lapse, poverty throughout the occupied areas, and the amount
         of relief work. Letters, 1844, from 
         <persname normal="William">W[illiam]</persname><persname normal="Hammond">H[ammond]</persname>Milton (1868- )
         and Virginia Lee Milton touch upon his early ministry,
         [Archibald Joseph] Cronin's The Keys of the Kingdom and Evelyn
         Underhill's Worship, and, the death of the Gilmour's nephew
         [Robert Stevenson Janney]. On July 10, 1944, 
         <persname normal="Joseph Graegoire">J[oseph
         Gr&amp;#10599;oire]</persname>de Roulhac Hamilton (1878-1961),
         The Library, University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill,
         encloses a brochure on the University's "A National Southern
         Collection" and refers to the Pollock diary. A letter of May
         28, 1946, from Brooks Palmer (1900?- 1974) of New York, refers
         to Daniel Monroe, a Massachusetts clock maker.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1908-1965, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, chiefly
         pertain to news of family and friends in Leesburg, Virginia.
         Letters of 1935 refer mostly to her engagement to A. D. P.
         Gilmour. Other items of interest are mentioned. There are
         letters (May 16, 1934; October 14, 1935, March 2 &amp; 17,
         1936; and, January 22, 1955) from Reverend James Shannon
         Montgomery, Minister of the Leesburg Presbyterian Church,
         chiefly concerning church matters and news of Leesburg and its
         inhabitants. In 1934, Montgomery also mentions a visit to
         Westfield, New Jersey and Princeton, a meeting with William K.
         McKinney and his request for him to talk to Robert [Stevenson
         Janney] about his interest in the ministry, and describes the
         reunion held at Princeton. In 1955, Montgomery writes from a
         retirement community, Olds Hall, Daytona Beach, Florida, that
         he is still opposed to the Church Union movement, and about
         religious insights, the division of the Presbytery of St.
         Johns, and the rapid increase of the Florida population. There
         is a letter, January 4, 1935, from Lily 
         <persname normal="Heth Davis">H[eth Davis]</persname>Dabney
         (1875-1973) at the University of Virginia. There are letters,
         January 1935, from 
         <persname normal="William">W[illiam]</persname>Sinclair Bowen
         (1867-1951), Cleveland, Ohio and Rachel [McMasters] 
         <persname normal="Miller">M[iller]</persname>Hunt (1882-1963),
         Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, about her engagement. There are
         letters (January 9, 1935; [post 1943] August 7) from Edward
         Griffith Dodson (1884-1969), Clerk, Virginia House of
         Delegates, concerning personal matters. On January 17, 1935,
         Harrison Williams (1873-1953 ?), Washington, D. C., writes as
         president of the Thomas Balch Library concerning her
         resignation of the chairmanship of the Grounds Committee and
         the work so far accomplished. There is a letter, February 8,
         1935, from Daisy 
         <persname normal="Haywood">H[aywood]</persname>Moseley (1892-
         ) of Glen Ridge, New Jersey. There is a letter, February 13,
         1935, from Hugh Chaplin (1887-1973) of New York mentioning a
         Chinese meal with a group of old Chinese friends. On March 14,
         1935, Cazenove 
         <persname normal="Gardner">G[ardner]</persname>Lee, Jr.,
         Washington, D. C., writes about the progress at "Stratford"
         and about the Lee Society. There are two letters (March 25 and
         May 8, 1935) from former University of Virginia student,
         Edmund 
         <persname normal="Jennings">J[ennings]</persname>Lee (1877- ),
         Rector, Chatham Hall, Chatham, Virginia, concerning personal
         matters and mentioning his wife, Lucy. There is a letter, Mary
         24, 1935, from "Josey" in Hwai-an, Ku, China, concerning
         mission work and religious and educational work in that area.
         A September 23, 1935 letter from "Betty" in Jersey, Channel
         Islands, mentions the feeling of war in Europe, especially
         Italy, and a visit to London, and describes Jersey and its
         inhabitants. There is a December 22, 1935 letter from
         Constance Cary Harrison of "Belvoir," Fauquier County. Other
         letters of interest to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour are from Ada
         H. Wright, a missionary in Japan and Australia. Letters of
         January 7 &amp; 17, 1935, from Kumamoto, Ki_shi_, S. Japan,
         mention mission work for local people, a visit to the
         Government Leper Asylum, St. Timothy's Church in Tokyo, work
         with the lepers in the Loo Choo Islands and at the Government
         Leper Asylum and describes a Christmas celebration. A letter
         from the same place on February 16, 1935 mentions the
         engagement and an addition to their hospital. A letter,
         February 2, 1944, from Wright in Guildford, Perth, Western
         Australia, mentions an auxiliary for the Mission to Lepers in
         Perth. A letter, August 17, 1939, from "Jessie" at Golf Hotel,
         Woodhall Spa., [England], contains a description of the
         village of Woodhall, and mentions the King and Queen of
         England [King George VI and Queen Elizabeth] touring America,
         offering "Rosemont" for housing evacuated children, and
         Germany blindly following Hitler. On May 20, 1941, Robert E.
         Peyton, Jr., Richmond, writes concerning the negative effect
         of the war in Europe on the prosperity of apple orchards in
         Virginia. There are also letters from the summer of 1944
         expressing sympathy over the death of the Gilmour's nephew,
         Robert Stevenson Janney. There are letters (September 1,
         October 11, 1958; December 28, 1960; and, December 18, 1961)
         from Stewart Couper of Midlothian and Angus, Scotland,
         concerning religion, church matters, and conditions and life
         in Scotland. An undated letter, February 20, from Hetty
         Harrison, Hay-Adams House, Washington, D. C. discusses
         gardening and several Virginia nurseries, and mentions
         Constance Cary Harrison. An undated letter, March 22, from
         "cousin Lily" in Paris, France, mentions travel around Nice
         and Paris, France, and gives her opinion of Paris.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1929-1964, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her
         brother, John Janney, Jr., touch upon legal, political, and
         religious concerns as well as events in Pioche, Nevada.
         Letters of March 22 and April 5,1935, on "American Society of
         Practical Economists" letterhead, mention Janney being one of
         the speakers at a meeting of the Foreign Policy Association
         and comment on the financial depression in the county and on
         the Congressmen from North Carolina "playing in with the
         international bankers by letting them manage currencies..."
         The latter one comments at length on senators and congressmen
         from North Carolina being blind to "this monetary situation"
         and thus not "lending any substantial cooperation to any
         effort in the Congress to save this great nation from its
         present tragic plight..." and mentions control of the value of
         the properties of this nation, the manipulation of private
         banking interests, and other national financial interests. A
         March 15, 1936 letter discusses Jewish and Christian sermons
         in his area and comments on the modern revisions to the
         sermons. On May 8, 1936, Janney is "On Board Steamship"
         traveling through a canal. A letter of October 6, 1950 relays
         personal and legal news. On Febraury 20, 1958, Janney mentions
         Governor [J. Lindsay] Almond's speech [on segregation] and
         comments on the conditions in Virginia. Letters of January 9
         and February 15, 1959 comments at length on "Massive
         Resistance" in Virginia as well as on Governor Almond usurping
         the rights of the legislature. On April 29, 1959, Janney
         writes that he has much work since he took on the job of
         Virginia political deficiencies. A November 9, 1959 letter
         discusses an agreement on the family farm and a controversy
         with the bank and the life tenant. There is a copy of a
         letter, December 13, 1962, from Janney to George S.
         Montgomery, concerning a Pioche, Nevada court case involving
         Dolman and Company and its effect on the Pioche Mines Company.
         A July 7, 1964 letter on "Pioche Mines Consolidates, Inc."
         letterhead also discusses the Dolman-Lee case as well as other
         legal work.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1908-1940, n.d., to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour
         from her sister, Lilias Janney, chiefly discuss family and
         friends and events in Leesburg, Virginia. On February 1, 1908,
         she writes from Los Angeles, California concerning visits to
         Los Angeles and Pasadena, mentioning the actions taken in
         locating a room and meeting a woman who is a Christian
         Scientist and a practitioner. On April 21, 1916, she writes
         from Yokohama, Japan, discussing her trip to Kamakura, with a
         visit to a "Tea House" and to the home of [Inazao] Nitobae
         (1862-1933) and his wife [Mary Patterson Elkinton] Nitobae,
         and comments on a procession of the Emperor and Empress and
         their court. Letters of June 1929 refer to the death of Leon
         Fry while schooling a horse, her nephew, Robert [Stevenson
         Janney] going to Camp [Ahmeck, Algonquin Park], Ontario, and
         Cary Langhorne entertaining the Garden Club. One letter in
         June is from "The Monticello," Charlottesville, where she has
         visited "Monticello," Michie Tavern, Farmington Country Club,
         and the University of Virginia. A letter, ca. January 1935,
         from the Acorn Club, Philadelphia, describes the attendance of
         Anne [Janney's] recital at the Hotel Barclay ballroom and
         includes a newspaper clipping. Letters of February 21 and 27,
         1935, from Plainfield, New Jersey, mention a Bokara man who
         sells rugs, including Persians and Orientals and a visit with
         her nephew, Robert [Stevenson Janney], at Princeton University
         and to Westminster School. In a letter, ca. February 1935, she
         writes about her visit to New York and hearing [Ignaz]
         Friedman (1882-1948) who, she feels, is in the same class as
         [Ignace Jan] Paderewski (1860-1941) and going to the
         Metropolitan Museum. A letter of April 29, 1935 mentions 
         <persname normal="Cazenove Gardner">Caz[enove
         Gardner]</persname>Lee. On June 17, 1935, she writes news of
         the Garden Club, mentioning the medal given to [John Davison]
         Rockefeller (1874-1960) for the Williamsburg Palace gardens.
         On June 20, 1935, she mentions the Massanetta Festival in July
         and being chairman of the "Open Air" Music Committee. A
         September 20, 1935 letter gives news of Robert Heston who has
         been cooking at a Catholic institution and a riding club. A
         September 28, 1935 letter refers to the management of family
         property rented to the Gallehers and the possible offer to
         sale to them. On November 26, 1935, she mentions meeting Mrs.
         [John Stewart ?] Battle [Mary Jane (Lipscomb) Battle ?] at a
         tea. A letter, ca. January 1936, mentions the death of "Harry"
         [Henry B. Rust]. From January 21 until February 12, 1936,
         Lilias writes from Hamilton, Bermuda. She discusses her
         arrival in the unique and beautiful town of Hamilton;
         activities including the service for the King at the
         Cathedral, a visit to Warwick Parish Church; activities with
         the Pattons; a train trip to Somerset; [Henry] Van Dyke
         (1852-1933) and his "poetic spirit"; guest houses and shopping
         and plans to go sailing. Letters of March and April 1936
         discuss life in Leesburg. There are numerous undated letters
         from Lilias Janney. In a February 5th letter, she mentions
         seeing Mary of Scotland with Helen Hayes (1900-1993) as Mary.
         In a May 5th letter, she mentions having tea at the Pattons,
         stating that "Old Mrs. Patton is quite the Grande Dame...Mr.
         &amp; Mrs. George Patton being quite important people here. He
         is in Parliament &amp; her niece married Lord Kitchener's
         nephew &amp; they own an island."</p>
      <p>Letters, 1929-1938, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her
         sister-in-law, Lucy (Stevenson) Janney relate news of family.
         On January 13, 1935, Baltimore, she relates news of her son
         Robert [Stevenson Janney] and his education and work and her
         own work [weaving], making socks, sweaters and fishnet
         scarves. A letter of October 7, 1935 gives news of Robert at
         Princeton University. In a letter of March 6, 1938, The St.
         Francis, Union Square, San Francisco, she writes about hearing
         a sermon of 
         <persname normal="Charles Rosenbury Erdman">C[harles] R[osenbury] Erdman</persname>
         (1866-1960) of Princeton Seminary at the Calvary Presbyterian
         Church and relates Robert's visits to the surrounding
         areas.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1929-1944, to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from her
         brother, Thomas Gordon Janney, are chiefly written from his
         home in Chicago, Illinois. On June 20, 1929, he inquires about
         her European trip and mentions a Chicago horse, "Reigh Count,"
         the second place runner in the Ascot Gold Cup. In a letter of
         April 17, 1934, he is busy with the spring season adjustments
         of coke prices and codes and labor studies. A letter of June
         20, 1934 explains in detail how to connect an indoor aerial up
         to the radio. On September 19, 1934, he inquires about a Mr.
         Eisenhard and whether or not he is Jewish, commenting that
         "they are so prominent now in administration circles that it
         is no doubt an honor to entertain one." He also mentions
         "Willie" Metzger, who sees the wisdom of being very stern with
         those criminals who drive when intoxicated, and Shirley
         Temple. A letter of November 17, 1934 relates news of the
         apple business. On January 31, 1935, he gives advice to their
         sister, Lilias, as general manager of a building. A March 19,
         1934 letter relates that "everything is still strained &amp;
         disturbed in business circles &amp; outlook anything but
         reassuring." On June 10, 1935, Gordon reminisces about
         Wilkesboro near the headwaters of the Yadkin River which was
         the terminus of his first job -- the survey and construction
         of a railroad from Winston-Salem to Wilkesboro. He also refers
         to the Supreme Court decision putting the National Recovery
         Administration (N.R.A.) where it belongs and how it will
         help business if the good features can be retained. On June
         27, 1935, he mentions the visit of M'Cready Sykes (1869-1952)
         who spoke admiringly of Robert [Stevenson Janney]. A letter of
         September 25, 1935, he has come east to Leesburg on business
         brought about by the threat of the coal strike; he mentions a
         visit to Spa-Valley and Crozet over arrangements for apple
         storage. A January 27, 1936 letter discusses the death of
         "Harry" [Henry B. Rust] (1872-1935) and the funeral held at
         Calvary Episcopal Church and includes an obituary, also
         mentioning his parents Ida Lee and Armistead T. Rust. Also
         mentioned are the Spa-Valley outlook not being as good as New
         York and export prices being so low that little fruit is
         moving. On March 23, 1936, he gives news of cases of influenza
         and pneumonia and prevalent floods. In a letter of August 9,
         1944, Gordon mentions there is not enough rain to save the
         corn crops in the area.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1898-1946, to Abram David Pollock Janney and Lucy
         (Stevenson) Janney cover a variety of topics. There is a
         gossipy letter, October 7, 1898, from Berina Gilmour, to A. D.
         P. Janney, Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, discussing
         mutual male acquaintances that are V.M.I. cadets. On October
         13, 1898, Charles P. Janney, Leesburg, writes to his son
         concerning his promotion to First Sergeant and encouraging his
         studies. On January 4 &amp; 23, 1899, Janney writes to his son
         at V. M. I. concerning the news that General Shipp has
         dismissed the entire First Class as a disciplinary action and
         actions taken in regard to the First Class and giving advice
         on daily study to prepare for examinations. On February 25,
         1900, Nancy Lee Janney, Leesburg, writes to her brother with a
         description of the wedding of "Lalla" and other local news. A
         letter, March 20, 1925, from Harris 
         <persname normal="Elliott Kirk">E[lliott]Kirk </persname>(1872-
         1953), Minister, Franklin Street Presbyterian Church,
         Baltimore, expresses sympathy over the death of Charles
         Phillips Janney. There is a Christmas greeting, 1926, from
         Anne (Morson) and Francis Lee Stuart (1866-1935). On January
         12, 1927, Thomas Gordon Janney, Chicago, discusses his illness
         due to the extraction of a wisdom tooth and mentions Turn of
         the Century [first volume of Our Times, the United States,
         1900-1925] by Mark Sullivan (1874-1952). A February 15, 1928
         letter from Nancy Lee Janney discusses her activities in
         Sicily and Taormina, Italy. A March 14, 1928 letter from
         Lilias Janney discusses activities in Florence, Italy,
         including a drive to Il Miniato and the Cascine, and future
         plans for visits to the Riviera, Nice, Milan, Venice, and
         Paris. A May 7, [1928] letter discusses activities in Paris
         and touring the countryside. A May 13, 1928 letter mentions
         the purchase of red copper water bottles in Vienna. On June
         17, 1928, Edinburgh, Scotland, Lilias discusses her activities
         in London, including seeing the King [George V] and Queen
         [Mary] and Princess Mary and the Prince of Wales at the Trophy
         of the Colours, watching the procession from St. James Park.
         On December 7th and 18th , Harris E. Kirk sends church
         memorabilia about Robert Stevenson Janney.</p>
      <p>Correspondence and papers, 1852-1923, of Charles Phillips
         Janney consists of letters to and from Janney, financial and
         legal papers, and miscellaneous papers. Letters from Janney
         discuss politics and legal and personal matters. On September
         17, 1878, he writes to "Dear Charlie" providing support in his
         determination "to abandon the use of drink..."; that the
         temperance movement in Loudoun County has assumed formidable
         proportions; suggesting that he connects himself with the
         order here; and that he will consider a partnership after the
         experiment proceeds for a year. There is a letter [1884 or
         1892] "To The Honorable Grover Cleveland President Elect"
         requesting that he consider John Randolph Tucker (1823-1897)
         for Attorney General and praising the character and
         professionalism of Tucker. A letter to the editor, September
         3, 1901, concerns those who desire him to represent them in
         the State Senate and his decline of the offer. Letters of
         March 22, 1922 and October 4, 1923 concern Janney family
         properties, "Leeton Forest" and King Street property. On
         December 31, 1917, in a letter to Albert Shaw (1857-1947),
         Janney comments on President Woodrow Wilson as being a real
         leader to the American people. There is an undated letter [ca.
         1921] concerning the presentation of an Arbor Vitae tree to
         Hampden-Sydney College on behalf of Lois I. (Kimsey) Marshall,
         wife of Thomas R. Marshall, the recent Vice-President of the
         United States. On September 17, 1923, Janney writes to Henry
         J. Nichols, recalling an incident as a child in Hillsboro
         during the Presidential Campaign of 1844, mentioning his
         father, James Craik Janney (1804-1878) and Lewis McKenzie
         (1810- 1895), and a conveyance returning from a Whig meeting
         in Maryland.</p>
      <p>There are also letters, 1865-1923, to Charles Phillips
         Janney and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney from family, friends
         and professional contacts. On July 26, 1865, H. B. Miller,
         Culpeper County, reports that only secessionists are in the
         political field for the elections for county officers and that
         the Union men are still hated. On January 20, 1866, Samuel
         McPherson Janney (1801-1880), Washington, D. C., a Unionist
         during the war, reports on efforts to be indemnified for
         losses sustained by the family during the Civil War; mentions
         consulting several prominent statesmen, including [Henry
         Bowen] Anthony (1815-1884), [Daniel] Clark (1809-1891), 
         <persname normal="Columbus">C[olumbus]</persname>Delano
         (1809-1896), Charles Edward Phelps (1833-1908), [Noah Haynes]
         Swayne (1804-1884), and [Edwin Hanson] Webster (1829-1893). A
         letter of February 18, 1868, from D. W. Taylor, Alexandria,
         concerns Miss Fannie Pollock, whom he judges as "a true woman"
         and believes that she "has good ideas as to what should
         constitute a true woman"; and, contains a discussion of
         relationships between men and women and how their opinions on
         certain subjects may vary. There is a letter, January 22,
         1884, from James S. Porter, pastor, about the Gum Spring
         Methodist Church at Gainesville. On June 23, 1897, M. O.
         Hawkins, "Hanover Construction Company/Builders of the
         Montgomery Division of the Mobile &amp; Ohio Railroad,"
         Tuscaloosa, Alabama, writes concerning the hiring of an
         assistant engineer and his request for John [Janney] and the
         railroad company building 200 miles through Alabama. Letters,
         March 28, 1921 and January 16, 1922, concerning the Janney
         family and land patents are from Fairfax Harrison (1869-1938)
         and Richard Mott Janney. There are two letters, October 9
         &amp; 16, 1923, from James E. Galleher and W. Cary Galleher,
         Jr. of Richmond concerning the purchase of the King Street
         property in Leesburg.</p>
      <p>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from William Edward Dodd
         (1869-1940) concern the purchase, 1912-1913, and management,
         1916-1925, of Middlebrook Farm, Round Hill, Virginia. A
         September 24, 1914 letter concerns the contract with Houghton
         Mifflin Company for Dodd's History of the United States.
         Letters from 1914-1916 concern the settlement of the Laura B.
         V. Gray land. On February 26 and April 28, 1916, Dodd at the
         University of Chicago, comments on events in Europe,
         mentioning the fight around Verdun and German ambitions, the
         cost to the French in holding back the Germans from Verdun,
         and the presence of Russians in France.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1916-1924, to Charles Phillips Janney from Nancy
         Lee (Janney) Gilmour chiefly detail her visit to the Far East
         in 1918. In letters of January 27 and 31,1916, she writes from
         Philadelphia, Pennsylvania concerning people met and her
         activities, including a luncheon with the Arts Club, attending
         the Opera, a ball at the Ritz-Carlton and a Shakespeare party.
         On April 20, 1918, she writes onboard the S. S. Korea Maru
         about people onboard and the activities, including
         shuffleboard, bridge, and checkers. A May 26, 1918 letter
         describes travel in Korea, relating that they left Tokyo,
         Japan on an express train to Shimonoseki, Japan and viewed the
         countryside of Japan, passing Fuji, inlets of the sea, and
         cultivated lands. While traveling through Korea, they went
         through mountainous country, cultivated lands and wild
         countryside. On May 30, 1918, from Peking, China, Nancy
         discusses the breakdown of their train engine and the
         resultant delay at the station, after having crossed
         Manchuria. She mentions the station being full of Chinese
         soldiers walking up and down and a couple returning from
         Petrograd, where they had been through the Revolution. She also
         describes a tour of Peking, including Rickshaw, the Legation
         Quarter, and the Gate of the Tartar. In a letter of June 13,
         1918, from Kyoto, Japan, she describes a trip from Seoul,
         Korea to Pusan, Korea, across the Sea of Japan, to
         Shimonoseki, Japan, and across the lake. She mentions the
         people on the train, including Bishop [Beverley Dandridge]
         Tucker (1846-1930), and notes the different expressions on the
         faces of the Christian Japanese. On June 20, 1918, from Tokyo,
         Japan, she discusses the visit of Prince Arthur to the
         Emperor. On August 18, 1918, Nancy is returning to the United
         States on the S. S. Kamo Maru with other members of her
         mission; she describes the ship and discusses people onboard.
         She also relates the tale of the Furgusons, missionaries from
         the west of China who were attacked by Chinese pirates. In a
         letter dated May 6, 1922, Norfolk, Virginia, she mentions the
         import of servants. There are two letters, February 12 and
         March 8, 1923, from Chicago, Illinois, discussing Bible School
         and various activities and people. Nancy writes a letter from
         Boston, Massachusetts, on the day of the death of Woodrow
         Wilson, February 3, 1924, expressing "It is sad to feel that
         the great leader-- at last is gaining his peace." On February
         7, 1924, from Cambridge, Massachusetts, she mentions the
         funeral of Woodrow Wilson.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1908, to Charles Phillips Janney from Lilias
         Janney and Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney, are chiefly from
         Pasadena, California where Nannie Lee Janney is convalescing.
         Letters of February 6 &amp; 8, 1908 give a description of the
         neighborhoods and the city of Pasadena and mentions activities
         such as seeing a Minstrel show, going to Redondo Beach, and
         driving to "Oak Knoll" and "Venice." Letters from Lilias
         during late February through late March discuss the failing
         health of her mother, Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney. On April
         19, 1916, Lilias writes from Tokyo, Japan, mentioning visits
         to the Tokyo Electric Car Station, Imperial University,
         cottage of Armistead and Margaret [at the University ?], the
         T. K. K. ships, the Embassy, Imperial Theatre, and "Cherry
         Blossom" Sunday at the park, as well as other activities and
         people.</p>
      <p>Correspondence, 1896-1899, of John Janney, Jr. cover a
         variety of subjects. A letter of February 29, 1896, from his
         mother, Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney, to Janney at Virginia
         Military Institute, give encouragement to keep up his studies,
         news of the health of Marshall and Harry [Henry B.] Rust, and
         news of family and friends. On April 7, 1896, his sister
         Lilias mentions going to the Yale concert and ball. On
         February 19, 1897, his aunt, Lily [Pollock], "Leeton Forest"
         supplies remedies for indigestion and sore throat. A letter of
         March 3, 1897 from his brother, Thomas Gordon Janney, suggests
         gargling with witch hazel for his sore throat and mentions a
         fifty per cent salary increase at the Baltimore and Ohio
         Railroad Company. Letters from his father, Charles Phillips
         Janney, enclose a pass, duly extended (January 1, 1897);
         discuss available teaching positions at the College of South
         Carolina, the Fishburn School, in Clarksville, Tennessee, and
         at Gambier (March 9, 1897); and, give news that Colonel Isaac
         Saunders, principal of the Danville Military Institute, always
         secures a West Point Army graduate (March 27, 1897). There are
         two letters, September 17 &amp; 18, 1898, from John Janney,
         Jr. at the University of Virginia, to his mother, Nannie Lee
         (Pollock) Janney, mentioning a lecture on International Law by
         [Raleigh Colston] Minor (1869-1923), his matriculation for
         courses in Philosophy and Law, hearing Bishop [Alfred Magill]
         Randolph (1836- 1918) at the University Chapel, and attending
         the Y.M.C.A. reception.</p>
      <p>Political papers, 1932 and 1959-1960, of John Janney, Jr.
         include a government document, 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Payment of Adjusted-Compensation
         Certificates</title>, 1932; a 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Pioche Record</title>editorial
         concerning Virginia and Massive Resistance (February 5, 1959);
         Janney's comments on Virginia and Massive Resistance (February
         18, 1959); a 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Congressional Record</title>re the
         question of forced racial integration (September 5, 1959);
         and, newspaper clipping re "Declaration of Principles of
         Virginia Voters" with a photograph of Janney (January 25,
         1960).</p>
      <p>Letters, 1834-1848, from Nathaniel E. Janney in St. Louis,
         Missouri, to James C. Janney, discuss family and financial
         affairs. On February 13, 1834, Janney writes concerning the
         accounts of distress in the money market in the northern
         cities and throughout the country, the memorials signed by
         citizens to restore the deposits [Federal funds on deposit in
         the United States Bank and distributed to state banks by
         President Andrew Jackson], and the failure of numerous New
         York businesses, and gives advice on holding onto flour as
         prices are minimal and offers financial support. A letter of
         January 8, 1837, discusses their brother, Aquila Janney, and
         gives the opinion that he is best suited for farming and
         mentions opportunities for work. A letter of May 17, 1837,
         discusses Elisha [Janney] and his improvement in health after
         using the Manchester Mineral Springs, inquires about the
         building of the mill and mentions financial gains. On June 22,
         1842, Janney discusses the city's money affairs being in the
         worst possible condition and merchants scarcely being able to
         meet their liabilities. On July 17, 1847, he writes concerning
         "Israel" and whether or not he will return and expecting to
         hear from him concerning his whereabouts, the name of his
         master, and the price to be paid. He also mentions "Armistead"
         having the objective to solicit aid to purchase his own
         freedom offered by his master. A letter of October 9, 1848
         mentions the death of Nathaniel E. Janney.</p>
      <p>Letters, 1837-1840, from Nathaniel E. Janney to Mary Janney
         chiefly cover personal topics. On March 12, 1837, he expresses
         thoughts of ending his bachelorhood and getting married,
         mentions Aquila [Janney] and that Elisha [Janney] has learned
         his business efficiently. On July 16, 1839, he writes upon
         hearing of the news of the death of his brother, Charles
         [Phillips Janney], expressing feelings of grief and also
         relief for his release from suffering. He also mentions a
         visit from Robert [H. Miller] and gives advice to James
         [Janney] on the purchase of wheat. A letter of September 6,
         1840 mentions Sarah [Janney] going to Manchester [Mineral
         Springs] for health reasons, his being confined to work as his
         two assistants are absent, alternate rains and sunshine
         yielding the farmers a large return, and business affairs.
         Janney also writes that he trusts that they shall see elected
         "the 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">old farmer of North Bend</title>to the
         Presidency" [William Henry Harrison] (1773-1841).</p>
      <p>Letters, 1886-1920, to Thomas Gordon Janney, are chiefly
         from family members. On October 28, 1886, Charles Phillips
         Janney writes to his son, inquiring of his studies and
         mentioning the Circuit Court case Hixson vs. Nixon. Letters,
         April - May 1918, from Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour, discuss her
         trip to Japan and China. On April 22nd she mentions a visit to
         the Golden Gate Bridge in San Francisco, California, onboard
         activities, and people onboard including Dutch, Russians and
         diplomatic servicemen. On May 1st she mentions a visit to
         Honolulu, Hawaii, activities onboard including deck tennis,
         shuffleboard, knitting and reading, celebrating her birthday,
         and the stunning costumes at the fancy ball from Bolivia,
         Spain, and Paris. On May 13th she mentions activities
         in Japan, meeting Japanese dignitaries and other, and being
         guests at the Embassy. On May 24th, on the Tokyo-Shimonoseki
         Special, Daily Train de Luxe, she describes scenery from the
         train, mentions Colonel Robertson, military attache at the
         British Embassy in Peking, China.</p>
      <p>Financial and legal papers, 1695(1755-1873)1906, of the
         Janney family and others include indentures and other legal
         documents. There is a document, March 31, 1695, assigning
         Jacob Janney to be the lawful attorney of his father Thomas
         Janney. Documents of 1757 relate to bonds between Joseph Yates
         and Mahlon Janney. A document of July 6, 1780 relates to
         Fairfax titles. There is the last will and testament, December
         8, 1801, of William Darke of Berkeley County. There are
         indentures of trust, May 2, 1817, between members of the
         Janney, Osburn and Pursel families concerning a debt to
         Valentine Pursel and his heirs. There is an indenture, April
         3, 1824, between Elisha and Mary Janney and John Janney. A
         deed, February 10, 1873, concerns property in Loudoun County
         near the village of Purcellville, and is between members of
         the Nichols and Janney families.</p>
      <p>Miscellaneous correspondence, 1858-1944, n.d., of the
         Janney and Pollock families cover several topics. There is an
         interesting letter, September 5, [1858], from Thomas Gordon
         Pollock (1838-1863) while a student at the University of
         Virginia. He mentions taking four classes of law and being in
         his old room at 21 West Lawn. He mentions [Elisha Boyd]
         Faulkner (1841- ) being there and relates a story about him.
         He discusses the changes at the University including "an
         elegant new Hotel built at the end of the Eastern Range with a
         dining hall..." and describes the new eating arrangements. He
         also mentions Douglas [French] Forrest (1837- ) taking junior
         classes of law and being pleased with [James Philemon]
         Holcombe's (1820-1873) lectures on mercantile law. A letter,
         February 12, 1908, from Lilias Janney in Pasadena, California,
         describes the part of town with shops, with all kinds of
         Indian curios, rugs, baskets, etc. and beautiful China. A
         letter, Thursday evening [ca. 1908], from George D.
         Montgomery, Los Angeles, California, to Lilias Janney,
         mentions a visit to Redondo Beach, Hermosa Beach, Playa del
         Rey, Venice and Santa Monica and discusses arrangements for
         Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney to stay in Pasadena. There is
         another letter, April 22, 1916, from Lilias Janney in
         Yokohama, Japan, mentioning a visit to a mission boarding
         school, describing the living arrangements of the girls at the
         school, and describing a recital arranged for her in the
         chapel. A letter of January 17, 1936, from the Friends of the
         Library of the University of North Carolina discusses the
         "Southern Collection" of the library.</p>
      <p>Other items in this collection include genealogical and
         historical data, photographs, travel brochures, bound volumes
         including a photograph album, scrapbook and travel journals.
         There is also a framed photograph of Robert Stevenson
         Janney.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e523">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Papers of John Janney (1798-1872)</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e527">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Biographical data on John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1890-1938</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e535">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Civil War Correspondence and Papers of
                  John Janney and Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1861-1866</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e543">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1824-1870</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <physdesc>4 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e553">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1853-1869</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re the Alexandria, Loudon, and Hampshire Railroad
                  Company</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e564">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1796-1842</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re the Mutual Assurance Society</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e575">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1809-1859</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Thompson &amp; Chinn (deceased) vs.
                  Beveridge</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e586">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1805-1847</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Washington vs. Lovett</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e597">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorials and Tributes to John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1872-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e605">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Personal Correspondence of John Janney and
                  Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1834-1884</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e613">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Political Correspondence and Papers of
                  John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1829-1839</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e622">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Political Correspondence and Papers of
                  John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1840-1858</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <physdesc>16 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e632">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Political Correspondence and Papers of
                  John Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1870,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e642">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcripts of Letters from John Janney to
                  Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861
                  Feb-Apr</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e650">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence of Soloman Parsons
                  [belonging to John Janney' 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1810-1830</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e660">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of Solomon
                  Parsons [belonging to John Janney] 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1807-1830</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e668">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Papers of Robert Stevenson Janney</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e672">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Biographical data on Robert Stevenson
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e680">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters concerning Robert Stevenson Janney
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1933-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e688">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters from Robert Stevenson Janney to
                  Abraham David Pollock Janney and Lucy (Stevenson)
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1924-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e696">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters from Robert Stevenson Janney to
                  Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1925-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e706">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1915-1930</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e714">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney from
                  Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1940-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e722">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Robert Stevenson Janney from
                  Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1928-1929</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e730">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mementos 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Robert Stevenson Janney</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e741">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorial and Tributes to Robert Stevenson
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1944-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e749">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certificates awarded to Robert Stevenson
                  Janney by the Royal Life Saving Society 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928, 1930</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="OS Box" type="Oversize">
                  M-22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e758">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certification of the Purple Heart Award to
                  Robert Stevenson Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944 Jun 21</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="OS Box" type="Oversize">
                  M-22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e766">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence and Papers of the Gilmour,
               Janney, and Pollock Families</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e770">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour
                  and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1897-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e778">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour
                  and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from his children 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e788">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour
                  and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from family 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1899-1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e796">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Abraham David Pollock Gilmour
                  and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1935</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re their marriage</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e807">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1908-1934</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e817">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935 Jan</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>4 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re her engagement</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e830">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935
                  Feb-Dec</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>4 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e840">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1936-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e850">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e860">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  John Janney, Jr. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1929-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e869">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1908-1929</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e877">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>3 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e887">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1936-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e897">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>4 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e907">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Lucy (Stevenson) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1929-1938</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e915">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour from
                  Thomas Gordon Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1929-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e925">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers of Abraham David
                  Pollock Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934-1941,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e933">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers of Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1922-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Garden Clubs</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e944">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Abram David Pollock Janney and
                  Lucy (Stevenson) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1898-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e952">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters from Charles Phillips Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1870-1923</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e960">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney and
                  Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1865-1923</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e969">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from
                  William Edward Dodd, and related 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1912-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e977">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from
                  Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1916-1924</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e985">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from
                  Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908, 1916</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e993">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Charles Phillips Janney from
                  Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1907-1908,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1001">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney
                  from Charles Phillips Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1868-1869</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1011">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers of Charles Phillips Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1852-1922</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1019">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence of John Janney, Jr. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1896-1899</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1027">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Political Papers of John Janney, Jr. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1932,
                  1959-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1035">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1915-1951</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1043">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney from "Bessie" 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1051">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney from family 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913-1936,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1060">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney from Nancy Lee
                  (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1918-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1070">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney from Thomas
                  Gordon Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1921-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1078">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lilias Janney and Nancy Lee
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1923-1935</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1086">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters from Nathaniel E. Janney to James
                  C. Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1834-1848</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1094">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters from Nathaniel E. Janney to Mary
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837-1840</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1102">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Thomas Gordon Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1886-1920</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1110">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Lily Pollock 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1908-1910,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1118">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers of the Janney
                  familiy and others 
                  <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1696(1755-1873)1906</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1126">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Correspondence of the Janney
                  and Pollock families 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1858-1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1136">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Address Book kept by Nancy Lee (Janney)
                  Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1941-1958</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1146">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Business Woman's Circle Meetings Minutes
                  kept by Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1939-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1157">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Gunston Hall Address Book kept by Nancy
                  Lee Janney, along with a brochure 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1903-1904,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1167">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Gunston Hall "Memoir Book" kept by Nancy
                  Lee Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1903-1904</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1177">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Memorandum Book kept by Charles Phillips
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1187">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album kept by Nancy Lee
                  (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1900-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Loose photographs removed from oversize
                  photograph album</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1197">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Travel Joural to Europe and Bermuda kept
                  by Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1928-1955</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1207">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Travel Journals to Japan and China kept by
                  Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1918</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>2 bound volumes</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1217">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph Album kept by Nancy Lee Gilmour
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1900-1905</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="OS Box" type="Oversize">
                  P-22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1225">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Passport for 
                  <persname normal="Abraham David Pollock">A[braham]
                  D[avid] P[ollock]</persname>Gilmour 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1913 May 5</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="OS Box" type="Oversize">
                  M-22</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e1236">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Papers re the Gilmour, Janney, and Pollack
               families</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1240">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogical data on the Janney and
                  Pollock families 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1888-1938</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1248">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogical data on the Janney family 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825-1966,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1258">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogical data on the Janney family 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904, 1939</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>Printed</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1268">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Genealogical data on the Janney family
                  compiled by Melvin Lee Steadman, Jr. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1968,
                  1981</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1276">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Historical data on Loudoun County,
                  Virginia and related 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879-1958,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1284">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1873-1953,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1292">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Organizational Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1907-1960</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1300">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Abraham David Pollock
                  Gilmour and Nancy Lee (Janney) Gilmour 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1884-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1308">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Abraham David Pollock
                  Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1885,
                  1900-1901</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1316">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Charles Phillips Janney and
                  Nannie Lee (Pollock) Janney 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1868</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1325">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Charles Phillips Janney and
                  family 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1879-1931,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1335">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Lilias Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1876-1896</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1343">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Robert Stevenson Janney 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1916-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1353">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of the Janney and Pollock
                  family members and others 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1887-1958,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
            <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1363">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of the Janney and Pollock
                  family members: Potraits 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1880-1897,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1371">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of the Janney and Pollack
                  family members and servants 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1863-1878,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1379">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Leesburg and Loudoun County
                  Residences 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1890-1957,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1387">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Religious and Church-related Material 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1928-1944,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1395">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Travel Brochures and other Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1929,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re travel in Eurasia and the United States</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1406">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Travel Brochures and other Papers 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1928-1936</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re travel in the United Kingdom</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1417">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1943-1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
            <physdesc>Bound volume; 2 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>re Robert Stevenson Janney</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1431">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Framed Photograph of Major Robert
                  Stevenson Janney of the United States Army Air Force 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="OS Box" type="Oversize">
                  R-11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
