<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04090">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04090::A Guide to the Papers of Thomas A. Mason)//EN" "viu04090.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Thomas A. Mason</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Mason, Thomas A., Papers 
                    <num type="collectionnumber">14859</num></subtitle><author>Processed by Special Collections Dept. staff; machine-readable finding aid
                    created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library </publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University
                    of Virginia. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Thomas A. Mason</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">14859</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Thomas A. Mason
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">14859</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Extent"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Thomas A. Mason, #14859, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisitions Information</head>
        <p>These papers were given to Special Collections by Thomas A. Mason, Indianapolis, Indiana, on October 9, 2009.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Thomas A. Mason was a Michigan native, who received his bachelor's degree in history
                from Kenyon College and his master's degree and doctorate from the University of
                Virginia. Formerly acting director and associate editor of 
The Papers of James Madison at the University of Virginia, he also was
                an assistant professor of history at Pembroke State University. He is currently project director of The Papers of Lew and Susan Wallace and an adjunct faculty member at Indiana University.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection chiefly consists of the correspondence files of Thomas A. Mason,
                formerly one of the editors of The Papers of James Madison at the University of Virginia, 1958-2009, ca. 1,952 items
                (4 Hollinger boxes; 1.5 linear feet). Sometimes the correspondence files also
                contain additional materials about the correspondent, such as magazine and news
                clippings, obituaries, newsletters, and brochures.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The original alphabetical order by name of correspondent of the collection has been
                maintained.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined" altrender="table">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="d1e121" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-2009</unitdate> Correspondence-Ab-Ad,
                            including: William Wright Abbot, University of Virginia History
                            Professor; Henry Abraham, University of Virginia Professor of Government
                            and Foreign Affairs; and Winthrop Lindsay Adams, University of Utah
                            History Professor.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e131" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-2005</unitdate> Correspondence-Al-As,
                            including: C. Knight Aldrich, University of Virginia professor of
                            Medicine; Michael Van Cleave Alexander, Virginia Tech History Professor;
                            Harry Lee Arnest III, graduate of the University of Virginia
                            Architecture School and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; and Robert
                            Ashton, University of East Anglia School of English and American Studies
                            Professor.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e143" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-2006</unitdate> Correspondence-Ba,
                            including: Lance G. Banning, University of Kentucky History Professor;
                            Madeleine Barry, English medical editor; Juxon Barton, English historian
                            and correspondent; and Joan Baxter, former Secretary of University of
                            Virginia Architecture School.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e153" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971-2003</unitdate> Correspondence-Be,
                            including: Sarah Beth Bearss, Editor at the Virginia Historical Society
                            and Library of Virginia in Richmond; Francis Lewis Berkeley, Jr.,
                            Professor Emeritus at University of Virginia and University Archivist;
                            Ronald Stanley Berman, Professor of English at Kenyon College and
                            Chairman of the National Endowment for the Humanities; and Mary Hall
                            Betts, Hostess of the Rotunda at University of Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e165" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1998</unitdate> Correspondence-Bl-Bu,
                            including: Mary Scott Parker Blake, Director of the Martha Jefferson
                            House in Charlottesville; Joseph Norwood Bosserman, Dean of the School
                            of Architecture at University of Virginia; Robin Bredin, teacher at
                            Woodberry Forest School; Hugh J. Brent, 1974 University of Virginia
                            Alumnus; Mildred Conrey Brown, Resident of Scottsville; and Frank Gerard
                            Burke, Acting Archivist of the United States.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e177" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1999</unitdate> Correspondence-(Dominic)
                            Nghiep Cong Bui, Pembroke State University Assistant
                            Librarian.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e185" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-2006</unitdate> Correspondence-C,
                            including: Adelaine Callery, Michigan correspondent; John Canaday,
                            University of Virginia Assistant Professor of Art and art critic for the
                                <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Times</title>; Charles Carlton,
                            North Carolina State University History Professor; Robert Girard
                            Carroon, Historiographer for Episcopal Diocese of Connecticut; Philander
                            D. Chase, Editor of the University of Virginia Papers of George
                            Washington; Douglas E. Clanin, Editor for the Indiana Historical
                            Society; Sandra Sangeser Clark, Director of the Michigan Historical
                            Center; Charles Frederick Williams Coker, Head of Reference and Reader
                            Service Section in the Manuscripts Division at the Library of Congress;
                            John Crisp Coleman, Assistant Professor of English at University of
                            Virginia; Elizabeth Collier, English correspondent; Dennis M. Conrad,
                            Editor of the Papers of Nathanael Greene and Editor at the Naval
                            Historical Center; Lawrence D. Cress, associate Dean of Arts and
                            Sciences at Willamette University; and Robert Dougherty Cross,
                            University of Virginia Dean of the Faculty of Arts and
                            Sciences.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e208" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-2008</unitdate> Correspondence-D,
                            including: Cullom Davis, Editor of the Legal Papers of Abraham Lincoln;
                            Edgar Glenn Davis, Vice President of Eli Lilly and Company in
                            Indianapolis; Harry James Dell, History Professor at University of
                            Virginia; Mary Sudman Donovan, Adjunct Professor of History at Hunter
                            College; Ruth E. Dorrel, Editor for the Indiana Historical Society;
                            Lindsay Gordon Dorrier, Commonwealth's Attorney; William S. Dudley,
                            Editor at the Naval Historical Center and James Raynor Dunton,
                            Washington Publisher.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e222" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980-2008</unitdate> Correspondence-E-F,
                            including: David K. Eliades, History professor at the University of
                            North Carolina at Pembroke; John Leslie Finucane, Employee at the Naval
                            Air Warfare Center; Florence Fleischman, Staff Liaison for Congressmen
                            J. Kenneth Robinson and D. French Slaughter; Gerald P. Fogarty,
                            Professor of the History of Christianity at University of Virginia;
                            Emmett Brown Ford, Employee at the Office of Sponsored Programs at
                            University of Virginia; and Anne Freudenberg, Curator of the Barrett
                            Collection.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e236" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1988</unitdate> Correspondence and Papers
                            Related to-John Francis Flynn, Artist and Professor at Pembroke State
                            University.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e244" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-2004</unitdate> Correspondence and Papers
                            Related to-Peter M. Foley, Lawyer.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e251" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1995</unitdate> Friday Club, Student Dining
                            Club at University of Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e258" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-2008</unitdate> Correspondence-G,
                            including: Muriel Kemp Ganser, Librarian at Lehigh University, Iowa
                            State University, Bennington College, and more; James Gilreath, American
                            History Specialist at the Library of Congress; Renée Gonse,
                            English correspondent; and John Henry Greller, Vice President for
                            Development at Northwestern College.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e269" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1999</unitdate> Correspondence-Ha,
                            including: Hattie P. Hall, correspondent; Charles Louis Hamilton,
                            Assistant Professor of History at Kenyon College and Administrator at
                            Simon Fraser University; William Henry Harbaugh, Professor of American
                            History at University of Virginia; Charles Montreville Harris, Professor
                            at Duquesne University and Editor of the Papers of William Thornton; and
                            John Hattendorf, Kenyon College graduate and American Naval
                            Historian.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e282" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1995</unitdate> Correspondence-Martin
                            Joseph Havran, Professor of History at University of
                            Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e290" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1996-2002</unitdate> Correspondence-Martin
                            Joseph Havran, Professor of History at University of
                            Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e298" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-2001</unitdate> Correspondence-Ho,
                            including: Eugene Pendleton Hogan, Author of fiction and nonfiction and
                            resident of Charlottesville; David Holmes, Professor of Religious
                            Studies and the College of William and Mary; Davyd Foard Hood,
                            University of Virginia Architecture graduate; Alan Hornstein,
                            Proffesseur at the Ecole Nationale Supérieure des
                            Télécommunications in Paris, France; and Hampton P.
                            Howell, Jr, stockbroker and resident of Charlottesville.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e311" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-2005</unitdate> Correspondence-I-Ll,
                            including: Alfonso Lynn Ivey III, Richmond correspondent,; David
                            Jackson, Delta airlines employee and resident of Isle of Palms, South
                            Carolina; Bernice Jones, Bermuda correspondent; Mary Veronica Kuebel,
                            PhD History; Charles Latham, teacher at the Episcopal Academy in
                            Philadelphia; Emma Lents, Employee at Indiana Historical Society;
                            Alexander Lind, Banker and Historian; Janet Linde, Archivist at
                            University of Virginia and in New York; Samuel Thames Lloyd III,
                            clergyman and Dean of Washington National Cathedral; and Marguerite
                            Lloyd, University of Virginia graduate.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e326" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-2003</unitdate> Correspondence-Lo-Lu,
                            including: Roger W. Lockyer, English Historian; Sir Gilbert Longden,
                            English Member of Parliament; and Sister Julien Hill Lucy, French
                            nun.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e335" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980-2002</unitdate> Correspondence-Ma,
                            including: Dumas Malone, American author of biography on Thomas
                            Jefferson; Sally D. Mason, Editor of the Omohundro Institute of Early
                            American History and Culture; Eleanor G. May, Professor of Business
                            Administration at University of Virginia; and Margaret McClure MacLeod
                            Mayo, Professor of History at University of Virginia and a resident of
                            Charlottesville.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e347" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980-2002</unitdate> Madison, Papers of James -
                            History of the Project</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e354" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Madisons of Montpelier</title>- Manuscript
                            Exhibition, Captions and keepsake</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e362" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1981-1987</unitdate> Madison, James-<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Dictionary of American Biography</title>
                            article</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e370" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962-2005</unitdate> Correspondence-Mc-Me,
                            including: J. Borden McCloskey, Proprietor of the Alcoholic Beverage
                            Commission in Red Springs, north Carolina; Shirley Ann Snyder McCord,
                            Editor at the Indiana Historical Society; Frances McCoughtry, Resident
                            of Attica, Indiana and Ypsilanti, Michigan; James Sears McGee, Professor
                            of the University of California, Santa Barbara; Judith Quintas McMullen,
                            Editor at the Indiana Historical Society; John M. McNeary, Proprietor of
                            a tree service company in Charlotte, North Carolina; Ernest C. Mead,
                            Professor of Music at University of Virginia; Kenneth Meisel-Weisskopf,
                            Swiss correspondent; and Arthur Mejia, San Francisco
                            correspondent.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e386" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973- 1997</unitdate> Correspondence-Mi- No,
                            including: Joseph C. T. Miller, Professor of History at University of
                            Virginia; William Lee Miller, Scholar in Ethics and Institutions at the
                            Miller Center of Public Affairs at University of Virginia; Samuel Holt
                            Monk, Professor of English at the University of Minnesota; Walter
                            Bedford Moore, Assistant Professor of Humanities at University of
                            Virginia; Peter Myles, English clergyman and correspondent; Louis John
                            Nigro, U.S. Ambassador to Chad; and Elizabeth Copeland Norfleet,
                            Author.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e400" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970- 2002</unitdate> Correspondence-O-P, including:
                            David Olyphant, Executive Director of the English-Speaking Union in New
                            York; Olof Palme, Prime Minister of Sweden; William Brown Patterson,
                            Professor of History at the University of the South; Elizabeth Pigg,
                            Federal computer expert; James Playfair, English physician; and Patricia
                            Power, Australian teacher.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e411" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1998</unitdate> Correspondence-R-Ro,
                            including: Michael Ramos, Lawyer; W. Ramsey Richardson, Clergyman;
                            Andrew Richmond, Editor of Papers of Philander Chase; Jefferson D.
                            Robinson III, Alumni Director at Kenyon College; Marie-Louise Roget,
                            visiting Professor of French at University of Virginia; and Henry G.
                            Roseveare, Professor of History at King's College in London.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e422" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1996-2002</unitdate> Correspondence-Robert
                            Allen Rutland, Editor of Papers of James Madison at University of
                            Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e430" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1995</unitdate> Correspondence-Robert
                            Allen Rutland, Editor of Papers of James Madison at University of
                            Virginia.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e438" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984-2009</unitdate> Correspondence-S-Sc,
                            including: Thomas R. Sant, Lawyer and Kenyon College graduate; Hans
                            Schmitt, Professor of History at University of Virginia; and William
                            Remsen Schultz.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:3</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e447" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-2003</unitdate> Correspondence-Se-Sha,
                            including: Edward Carl Wolfram von Selzam, German Diplomat; David A.
                            Shannon, Provost at University of Virginia; and Ronald Sharp, Professor
                            of English at Kenyon College.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e456" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-2008</unitdate> Correspondence-She-So,
                            including: Chester Price Shelly, Michigan Accountant and godfather of
                            Thomas Mason; Charlotte J. Shelton, Charlottesville stockbroker; Joan
                            Shivel, Williamsburg, Virginia correspondent; Edward F. Shotter, English
                            clergyman and correspondent; Richard Stuart Simons, Indiana Historian;
                            Jerry N. Showalter, bookseller; Susan Slade, Indianapolis architectural
                            historian; Lewis M. Slater, Lawyer in Detroit; and Earl Phillip
                            Sourwine, Indianapolis banker.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e469" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-2004</unitdate> Correspondence-St-Ti,
                            including: Victor Andrew Stock, English clergyman and correspondent;
                            Anton J. Streiff, Administrator at Carnegie Mellon University; Peter
                            Taylor, J. Garland Teasley, Clergyman and correspondent; Edward Riggs
                            Telling III, Lawyer in Rockford, Illinois; Alexander C. von Thelen,
                            Harriet Gayle Thornbrough, Executive Secretary of the Indiana Historical
                            Society; and Marie Leslie Shackelford Tise, librarian in
                            Delaware.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:6</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e482" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982-2005</unitdate> Correspondence-Tu-V,
                            including: Eve Turnball, Hostess of the Rotunda at University of
                            Virginia; Dory Twitchell (see also Montpelier), Administer at
                            Montpelier; Nicholas Tyacke, Professor of History at the University
                            College, London; Irene Ashworth Valentine, Charlottesville resident and
                            correspondent; and John Stanley Vishneski, Chicago Lawyer.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e493" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958, 1972-2003</unitdate> Correspondence-W,
                            including: Joseph Addison Warren; Michigan Lawyer; James B. Watson,
                            London small-press printer; William Stone Weedon, Chairman of the
                            Philosophy Department at University of Virginia; Minor Tompkins
                            Weisiger, librarian at the Library of Virginia; Herman B. Wells,
                            Chancellor at Indiana University; Michael L. Westfall, Hospital
                            Administrator and Board member of Historical Organizations in Indiana;
                            Sir. John Wheeler-Bennett, Historical Adviser for the Royal Archives;
                            and Michael Cunningham Williams, Washington Lawyer.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">4:8</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
