<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu01377">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01377::Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letters from Liberia)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu01377.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01377::Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas
             Letters from Liberia)//EN" "viu01377.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letters
            from Liberia 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820-1836</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letters from
            Liberia, 1820-1836 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11180</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2001 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Conditions of Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">19 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by B. Tsering Yeshi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">05/01/2001</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-18" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 18, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu01377::Mars &amp;
            Jesse Lucas Letters from Liberia)//EN" "viu01377.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letter from
         Liberia 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820-1836</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11180</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letters from Liberia 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1820-1836</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11180</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of eight electrostatic copies of letters.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Mars &amp; Jesse Lucas Letters from Liberia, Accession
            #11180, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>These letters were given to the University of Virginia
            Library by Richard T. Mann, Purcellville, Virginia, on May
            4, 1995.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of eight electrostatic copies of
         letters, 1822, 1830-1831, and 1836, between the Heaton Family,
         Loudoun County, Virginia, and Mars and Jesse Lucas,
         emancipated slaves living in Liberia, Africa. The earliest
         letter, September 7, 1822, is from James Heaton to [William
         Allebone ?] which refers to the Missouri Compromise, "It is
         gratifying to think that the situation of our beloved country
         has altered so much for the better since the date of your
         letter. The Missouri question settled, and that black cloud
         which hung so portentously over our political horizon -
         threatening to prostrate our liberties and to involve us in
         civil war &amp; bloodshed, has been dissipated by the calm
         still voice of reason &amp; that attachment of all parties to
         the Union which has saved in many trying &amp; critical
         situations. May a similar question never be revived, but may
         it sleep forever!" James Heaton also mentions two young
         doctors, Dr. Eackes, [Loudoun County ?] and Dr. William
         Taylor, Culpeper County, who had left him and commenced their
         medical practice, and his two sons, Albert and Townsend, both
         engaged in the study of medicine. Heaton plans on sending his
         sons to the Philadelphia Medical School although much "noise"
         had been made about the new school in Baltimore.</p>
      <p>The rest of the correspondence (six letters) is from Jesse
         and Mars Lucas, emancipated slaves living in Liberia, to two
         brothers Albert and Townsend Heaton, near Leesburg, Loudoun
         County, Virginia, except for a copy of one letter from Albert
         Heaton to Jesse and Mars, April 29, 1830, full of advice and
         hopes for their success in Liberia, and referring to the evils
         of slavery, "You have felt and witnessed the degradation of
         your colour in this country whether slaves or the free people
         of colour, the latter tho they have no masters and are free
         yet they are only so in name...".</p>
      <p>Jesse Lucas writes from Caldwell, where he lives on the
         [Saint Paul ?] River, about the voyage to Liberia where he saw
         a whale, sharks, and a flying fish, describes various plants
         in Liberia including the very useful [cassava ?], mentions
         that there are plenty of wild cattle, deer and goats, offers
         to send a pet monkey, and asks them to send apples, tobacco,
         flour, and a quantity of cheap handkerchiefs to trade with the
         natives (1830 Mar 10).</p>
      <p>Mars Lucas, Caldwell, Liberia, also describes the voyage of
         the fifty-eight immigrants, who all arrived in good health,
         from Hampton Roads to Liberia. Thankful for his emancipation,
         Mars describes the land as fertile and describes the fruits
         and vegetables in the land, believes the natives are not given
         to industry but care only about hunting and fishing, and
         tobacco and rum. The land is eight miles from Monrovia, the
         capital, which has two forts (one with ten guns and one with
         four guns) and two Methodist churches and one Baptist (1830
         Mar 12). Mars goes on in another letter, June 19, 1830, to
         report that he was recovering from a severe attack of fever
         but Jesse's wife had died, mentions trade articles such as
         tobacco, ivory, and beads, and that he is to go to Milburg by
         order of Governor Mecklin. He also discusses the difficulties
         of the colony, "I am much deceived with this country the
         reports, is all a lie, merely to encourage people to come to
         this country. Times is very hard, out here, everything is very
         dear and not to be had."</p>
      <p>Jesse Lucas writes about the loss of two of his children
         and his need for tobacco and nails (1831 Feb 2). Another
         letter from Jesse and Mars Lucas mentions the loss of Jesse's
         children, Susan and Henry, the allotment of their land which
         they are now living on, the scarcity of silver and the high
         cost of everything, such as pork at eighteen dollars a barrel
         and flour for ten to twelve dollars a barrel, and the presence
         of leopards and large snakes (1831 [Dec] 29).</p>
      <p>In the last letter to the Heatons, April 24, 1836, Jesse
         and Mars Lucas write about surviving a native attack on the
         American settlement at [Basso ?] where he and his brother were
         captured at the saw pit and taken to a native town. They were
         later freed and Mars went back and fought in a war against the
         natives. Many of their tools, saws, axes, pots, and clothes
         were lost in the attack. Jesse has been remarried to an
         American woman and has a son, Alexander Lucas. Meat is very
         difficult to secure and when they get meat it is usually
         monkeys and an animal similar to a rat. They ask them to send
         a barrel of flour and will send a barrel of rice in return; he
         also asks his brother to send him a couple of good hounds.
         Circumstances are so difficult for the colony in Liberia that
         he writes, "We both thought we were slaves when we were in
         that country but we never knew what slavery was until we came
         to this country, &amp; that is the cry with every living man
         in the colony."</p>
    </scopecontent>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
