<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03023">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03023::Papers of Rosalie Caden Evans)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu03023.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03023::Papers of Rosalie Caden
             Evans)//EN" "viu03023.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>Papers of Rosalie Caden Evans, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1860-1950</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Evans, Rosalie Caden, Papers of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">2895</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ##38.5 Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by niyi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">8/13/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03023::Papers of
            Rosalie Caden Evans)//EN" "viu03023.xml" converted from EAD
            1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-03-02" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Mar 02, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Rosalie Caden Evans, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1950</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">2895</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Rosalie Caden Evans 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1860-1950</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">2895</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">The papers of
         Rosalie Caden Evans contain ca. 3850 items (9 Hollinger boxes,
         ca. 3.8 linear feet) and consist largely of personal
         correspondence, financial records, legal papers, and journals
         dating from ca. 1860-1950 (with some items dating from the
         mid-sixteenth century and to the 1960s).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Papers of Rosalie Caden Evans, Accession #2895, Special
            Collections Dept., University of Virginia Library,
            Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Rosalie Evans collection was presented to the
            University of Virginia library in several installments,
            beginning on March 15, 1948. It was a gift of C. Edmonds
            Allen, III of New York City.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The papers of Rosalie Caden Evans contain ca. 3850 items (9
         Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.8 linear feet) and consist largely of
         personal correspondence, financial records, legal papers, and
         journals dating from ca. 1860-1950 (with some items dating
         from the mid-sixteenth century and to the 1960s). Included in
         this collection is material pertaining to Evans' attempts from
         1918 to 1924 to regain control of her hacienda, San Pedro
         Coxtocan, which was under threat of expropriation by the
         Mexican government and seizure by local agrarians. The
         collection also contains records of the extensive legal battle
         for ownership of the hacienda which arose after Evans was
         murdered by agrarian revolutionaries in 1924. These legal
         papers are mostly those of her sister, Daisy Caden Pettus, who
         acted as executrix of the Evans estate. Also included are
         typescripts and correspondence concerning the 1926 publication
         of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>by the Bobbs-Merrill Company. The original
         letters and journals from which this volume was compiled are
         to be found within the Evans collection. Other papers of
         interest include those of George Camp, who acted as overseer
         of San Pedro Coxtocan both before and after Evans' death, and
         those of Juan Strathaus, a young German employee of the
         hacienda who was critically wounded while defending Evans at
         the time of her murder. The collection also contains some
         short works of fiction by Rosalie Evans, two research papers
         (1965 and 1986) on the political and legal ramifications of
         the expropriation and assassination, and several photographs
         and newspaper clippings dealing with Rosalie Evans and her
         struggle to maintain her rights to San Pedro Coxtocan.</p>
      <p>Evans was born Rosalie Emma Caden in Galveston, Texas in
         1877. A sickly child, she nonetheless valued learning and was
         an avid reader and fine artist in pen-and-ink. Childhood
         correspondence is mostly between Evans and her sister,
         Florence, with whom she was particularly close. In 1896,
         Rosalie made her first trip to Mexico, where she met Harry
         Evans, an Englishman who was then manager of the Puebla Bank
         of London and Mexico. In 1898, she married Evans in Virginia
         and returned with him to Puebla. The two spent much of their
         time with Rosalie's sister, Florence, who had also married and
         settled in Mexico.</p>
      <p>When, in 1904, Florence died, Harry Evans resigned from the
         presidency of the Bank of London and Mexico and purchased San
         Pedro Coxtocan, a sixteenth century hacienda located within
         fifty miles of Mexico City. Mr. Evans hoped that the project
         of restoring the neglected 166-hectare estate would improve
         Rosalie's spirits after the death of her sister. The couple
         soon became dedicated to the restoration of the property, and
         their improvements, including an irrigation system and repairs
         to the buildings, greatly increased the value of the hacienda.
         They lived at San Pedro Coxtocan until 1910, when political
         unrest due to the fall of the Diaz regime forced them to quit
         their property and move to Mexico City, where they remained
         for three years. Further political uprisings forced the couple
         to leave Mexico altogether, abandoning all of their assets and
         interests in the country.</p>
      <p>For the next four years, Mr. and Mrs. Evans travelled in
         America and Europe, often writing letters to Rosalie's sister
         Daisy Pettus, until financial troubles compelled them to
         attempt to regain control of San Pedro Coxtocan. The hacienda
         was under threat of expropriation by the Mexican government
         and its fields and buildings were being used by local farmers.
         The situation required Evans' presence in Mexico City, so
         Rosalie remained with family in the United States while Harry
         travelled south to negotiate with the Mexican government. On
         his second trip to Mexico City, in November of 1917, Harry
         Evans suddenly became ill and died before Rosalie could reach
         Mexico. There existed some suspicion that Evans was poisoned
         by parties hostile to his ownership of San Pedro Coxtocan, but
         this claim was never firmly established.</p>
      <p>Rosalie's letters and journal entries from this period
         illustrate her great grief at the loss of her husband, but
         they also indicate her faith in spiritualism and the
         afterlife. Early journal entries chronicle her attempts to
         communicate with Harry's ghost through meditation, consulting
         with mediums, spirit-writing, and the use of a Ouija board.
         Most records of these attempts were edited out of the
         published account 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>. Evans' journal entries from the time of her
         husband's death take the form of nightly letters to him,
         relating the day's events, but also telling of her endeavors
         to contact him and asking for his spiritual intercession in
         her daily life. These journals are to be found among the bound
         volumes at the end of the collection.</p>
      <p>A little over a month after Harry's death, Evans resolved
         to travel to Mexico to continue his attempts to re-establish
         ownership of the hacienda San Pedro Coxtocan. She left her
         sister's home in Charleston, South Carolina, in early January,
         1918. Correspondence from this time until her death in August,
         1924 consists mainly of letters from Rosalie to her sister,
         Daisy Caden Pettus, describing her struggle to maintain her
         rights to the property. These are the letters which Pettus
         published (in greatly condensed format) in 1926. They express
         Evans' powerful commitment to regaining the hacienda, a cause
         she considered to be sacred to her husband's memory, and
         detail her negotiations with the Mexican government, American
         and British embassies in Mexico City, and local agrarian
         leaders from the villages surrounding San Pedro Coxtocan.</p>
      <p>A dynamic woman, Evans wrote that she "always seemed to win
         out in a personal interview" in which matters could be
         discussed rationally; however, she was recorded to have
         resorted to riding out into her fields, waving a pistol and
         cracking her whip, in order to drive off agrarian invaders.
         This was a time of great tension between Rosalie Evans as a
         landowner and the native members of the agrarian movement,
         between Evans as a female and the male-dominated culture in
         which she found herself, and between Evans as a foriegner and
         the nationalistic forces in the Mexican government. Violence
         erupted several times over the six years that Evans remained
         in Mexico; her fields were regularly seized, her workers
         attacked, her water supply diverted, and her buildings burned.
         Evans' letters paint a vivid picture of life at San Pedro
         Coxtocan during this turbulent period. Her struggle to
         maintain her property rights was one of frustration and
         hardship. Conversely, it also served as a time of great
         personal development for Evans as a woman forced to rely only
         on her strength of character in order to prevail.</p>
      <p>In early August 1924, as she was travelling by buggy to her
         hacienda, Rosalie Evans was ambushed and shot by a group of
         agrarians who hoped that, on her death, the ownership of her
         property would revert to local villages. Her driver, Juan
         Strathaus, was seriously injured in this attack. He survived,
         however, and was able to draft several statements concerning
         the circumstances of Evans' murder. These statements, along
         with other letters and records concerning Strathaus, his role
         in legal proceedings concerning the Evans case, and his
         financial situation after being crippled, are grouped together
         and filed with the financial and legal papers of this
         collection.</p>
      <p>After Evans' death, the struggle to establish control of
         San Pedro Coxtocan was taken up by her sister, Daisy Caden
         Pettus, who was named executrix of the Evans estate. Her
         attempts to claim the hacienda developed into a protracted
         legal battle with the Mexican government which was not
         resolved until the late 1940s, when the Evans land was awarded
         to the local villages of Tianguismanalco, San Mateo, Santa
         Maria, and Tepeyacac. A small cash settlement, reportedly far
         less than the market value of the hacienda, was paid to the
         estate of Rosalie Evans by the Mexican government. The records
         of lawyers associated with the case are filed among the
         financial and legal papers of the collection and consist
         mostly of the correspondence of attorney Francis Price, who
         worked in the interest of the Evans estate both in America and
         in Mexico. Other lawyers employed by Mrs. Pettus include Hugh
         Sinkler, Thomas G. Corcoran, and Salvador M. Cancino.</p>
      <p>Also among the financial and legal records in the Evans
         collection are the papers of George Camp, a Texan who was
         briefly in the employ of Rosalie Evans and who was later hired
         by Daisy Pettus to act as administrator of the hacienda San
         Pedro Coxtocan following Evans' murder. These papers include
         general payrolls and financial records, and correspondence
         concerning the political climate around the hacienda, along
         with reports on the condition of crops, buildings, and
         property. Also included are Camp's letters to farming supply
         companies and records of his attempts to cut and sell timber
         on the Evans/Pettus property. Camp, identified as "Dashiel" in
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>, was ultimately fired by Daisy Pettus for his
         mismanagement and disregard for her interests, and also
         because she felt that he desired personal ownership of San
         Pedro Coxtocan. He had been previously dismissed by Rosalie
         Evans due in large part to the blood-thirstiness with which he
         defended her hacienda and because of his unwanted sexual
         advances. Financial records and payrolls for the period
         1920-1925, before Camp's term as administrator, are grouped
         separately among the financial and legal papers under the
         subheading "Accounts of Hacienda San Pedro Coxtocan." As
         financial reports during Camp's tenure were often made to Mrs.
         Pettus and her lawyers, accounts from 1926 on are filed with
         the general financial and legal papers.</p>
      <p>Papers dealing with the 1926 publication of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>have been separated into two folders and are
         located in Box 8. These papers consist mostly of
         correspondence between Daisy Pettus and the Bobbs-Merrill
         Company concerning the terms of their agreement and editorial
         decisions regarding what should be omitted from the published
         letters. Also included in the collection are three wire- bound
         volumes of Evans letters readied for publication. These
         typescripts are NOT exact copies of the letters from Rosalie
         Evans to Daisy Pettus found in the correspondence series of
         this collection. Rather, they reflect the editing and
         omissions decided upon by Pettus and the Bobbs-Merrill
         Company.</p>
      <p>Photographs and newspaper clippings relevant to the Evans
         case have been separated into two folders in Box 7. They
         include pictures which were used as illustrations in 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>along with other photographs of Mr. and Mrs.
         Evans, George Camp, Evans' employees, and views of the
         hacienda. Articles from both American and Mexican newspapers
         are among the clippings in the collection. They date from
         approximately 1924 to 1927, and cover Evans' attempts to hold
         her property against the Mexican government and the agrarian
         movement, her subsequent murder, and the legal case which
         Daisy Pettus pursued after Evans' death.</p>
      <p>Also included in this collection are two research papers
         which deal with the Evans case. The first, a thesis entitled
         "Mexican Agrarian Reform in the United States," was written by
         C. E. Allen III while a student at Washington and Lee
         University in 1965. The second essay, called "Rosalie Evans
         and the Expropriation of San Pedro Coxtocan," was written by
         S. M. Volkersz, an undergraduate at the University of
         Virginia, in 1986. (Also of interest, although not a part of
         the Evans collection, is a 1990 master's thesis, "Agrarian
         Politics, Violence, and the Struggle for Social Control in
         Puebla from 1918 to 1927: The Case of Rosalie Evans," by C. P.
         Dussaud (UVA). This thesis is part of the University of
         Virginia library holdings.)</p>
      <p>Two short, undated works of fiction, both imaginative
         adventure stories by Rosalie Evans, are included in the
         collection. "Antonio," an autograph manuscript, is a fantasy
         story about a mouse, and the typescript "A Vision of Mitla" is
         a love story with an Aztec flavor.</p>
      <p>Finally, a folder contains oversized material in the Evans
         collection. This includes three maps of the hacienda San Pedro
         Coxtocan and its environs and a plan of the irrigation system
         used on the hacienda. Also included are an oversized Mexican
         legal document concerning the estate of Rosalie Evans, and an
         1853 certificate of American citizenship belonging to Thomas
         Caden, Rosalie's father.</p>
      <p>The Evans collection exists as a valuable resource, not
         only for the light it sheds on the political situation in
         Mexico in the early part of this century, but also as an
         intimate portrait of a woman whose personal convictions caused
         her to lead an extraordinary life.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Various additions to the Rosalie Caden Evans papers have
         been reorganized and interfiled in the main accession, #2895.
         The papers are organized into two main series, Correspondence
         and Financial and Legal Papers, in which documents are
         organized chronologically in Boxes 1 through 6. Documents
         concerning Juan Strathaus and the accounts of the Evans
         hacienda are to be found at the end of the Financial and Legal
         series. Photographs, newsclippings, and original fiction and
         essays are located in Box 7, while Box 8 contains documents
         concerning the publication of 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
         Mexico</title>. Finally, a series of bound volumes, including
         the journals of Rosalie Evans, is to be found in Box 9.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e229">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e233">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1923 May</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
            <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e243">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1923 Jun - 1926,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>6 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e253">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e257">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1559-1924</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
            <physdesc>6 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e267">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925-1926 Feb</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
            <physdesc>13 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e277">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1926 Mar - 1938</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
            <physdesc>14 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e287">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1939-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
            <physdesc>8 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e297">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1967, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
            <physdesc>12 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e307">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers: Juan Strathaus
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1917-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e315">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Financial and Legal Papers: Accounts of
                  Hacienda San Pedro Coxtocan 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
            <physdesc>4 folders</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e325">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certificate of United States Citizenship,
                  Thomas Caden 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1853</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e333">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Plan of Irrigation Systems, Haciendas San
                  Pedro Coxtocan, Santa Maria, and San Mateo 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1920</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e341">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mexican Legal Document re: Evans Estate 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e350">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Blueprint Map of Hacienda San Pedro
                  Coxtocan 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e358">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Blueprint Map of Hacienda San Pedro
                  Coxtocan and Annexes 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e366">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Hacienda Santa Maria Coxtocan 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Oversize" type="Oversize">
                  Folder</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e374">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Photographs 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1920s</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e382">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Fiction by Rosalie Evans 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e390">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Newsclippings re: Evans Case 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1924-1927</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e398">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Thesis: "Mexican Agrarian Reform in the
               United States," C. E. Allen III, Washington and Lee
               University 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e406">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Essay: "Rosalie Evans and the Expropriation
               of San Pedro Coxtocan," S. M. Volkersz, University of
               Virginia 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e414">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Drafts and Correspondence re: Publication of 
               <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The Rosalie Evans Letters from
               Mexico</title>(1926) 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1947, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
          <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e427">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound Volumes: Typescripts of Letters,
               Rosalie Evans to Daisy Caden Pettus, 1918-1924 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1926</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
          <physdesc>3 volumes</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e437">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound Volume: Notes re: Caden Estate 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1901-1902</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">9</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="item" id="d1e446">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Bound Volumes: Journals of Rosalie Caden
               Evans 
               <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1886-1920</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">9</container>
          <physdesc>12 volumes</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
