<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu04070">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu04070::A Guide to the Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. Collection)//EN" "viu04070.xml"
        </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. Papers</titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Hereford, Frank Loucks, Jr., Papers
                    <num type="collectionnumber">12764-a</num></subtitle><author>Processed by Special Collections Dept. staff; machine-readable finding aid
                    created AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2011 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by AEL Data Digitization and Digital Curation Services [Date of source: <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language>English.</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Frank Loucks Hereford Jr. Papers</titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession number">12764-a</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Frank Loucks Hereford Jr. Collection
                <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">12764-a</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Extent"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <origination label="Collector"/>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. Papers, #12764-a, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquistion Information</head>
        <p>The collection was transferred from the Office of the Vice-President and Provost
                    to Special Collections Library on August 12, 1981.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist id="biogFull">
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Frank Loucks Hereford Jr. was born in Lake Charles, Louisiana on July 18, 1923. He
                received a B. A. at the University of Virginia in 1943 and a Ph.D. in Physics at the
                University in 1947. While an undergraduate, he wrote a sports column for the
                University newspaper, <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">College Topics.</title> He was a
                research scientist in the United States Navy from 1942 to 1945. During the war years
                he worked on research for the Manhattan Project under Dr. Jesse Beams, who called
                him "one of the best all around physicists with whom I have ever been associated."
                He worked for the Bartol Research Foundation at Swarthmore College in Pennsylvania
                from 1947 to 1949. He married Ann Lane in 1948 and became an Associate Professor of
                Physics at the University of Virginia in 1949, rising to full professor in 1952, and
                Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences in 1962. He was named the Robert C.
                Taylor Professor of Physics in 1966 and was promoted to Provost of the University,
                the chief academic officer after the President. Also in 1966 he received the Thomas
                Jefferson Award in recognition of his extensive services in teaching, research and
                administration. In 1970 he was Provost and Vice-President, being the first occupant
                of this position. Throughout his career, Mr. Hereford was noted as an able teacher
                and an articulate advocate of improving the quality of education at the University.
                He guided and planned for the growth of the University and formulated plans for the
                admission of women to the College of Arts and Sciences. He was visiting professor at
                the University of St. Andrews, Scotland from 1971 to 1972. He was inaugurated as the
                fifth president of the University of Virginia in 1974. He was the recipient of the
                Raven Award in 1983, the Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award in 1985, as well as the IMP
                Society Distinguished Faculty Award in the same year. He was a member of many honor
                societies including Phi Beta Kappa, Omicron Delta Kappa, Alpha Tau Omega, Raven
                Society, Sigma XI, and Fellow of American Physical Society. He was on the Board of
                Directors of the Virginia National Bank, Belfield School; St. Anne's School;
                Woodberry Forest School; The Mariners Museum and Gould, Inc. He was the
                author of numerous publications and was an avid sportsman, enjoying hunting and
                tennis as well as spectator sports.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>The collection consists of the personal papers (1973-1985) of the University
                of Virginia's fifth president, Frank Loucks Hereford, Jr. The collection is 708
                items, 3 Hollinger Boxes and 1.25 linear feet. Included in the collection is
                personal correspondence of President Hereford, which is mostly thank you letters,
                including one to the Seven Society and a resolution from the Board of Visitors in
                his honor.</p>
      <p>There is some correspondence about conflicts of interest policies as President of the
                University. There is also information about Carrs Hill. Of particular interest in
                the correspondence, is a letter from John A. Gill to the president that is filled
                with racism against African Americans and Jews at the University of Virginia and
                Farmington Hunt Club. The letter was written to President Hereford after the
                president had made a statement in favor of more diversity at the University and
                Farmington.</p>
      <p>There is also information about President Hereford's inauguration in 1974 and his
                resignation after eleven years in 1984, as well as Board of Visitors meeting
                minutes. There are also original speeches of the President from 1973 to 1985,
                including materials that he used to prepare his speeches. Included with the
                University of Virginia related speech materials are articles about the history of
                the University and correspondence between President Hereford and former alumni who
                reminisced about the early days at the University. There are also "Remarks by Walter
                Dexter Whitehead and a typescript of a "Papraphrased Conversation between Hereford
                and Richard M. Brandt." In the University of Virginia miscellaneous there is a poem
                by Raymond C. Bice written for President Hereford's birthday. Correspondents of the
                President include Governor Mills E. Godwin, Jr.; Thomas J. Michie, Jr.; Francis L.
                Berkeley, Jr.; Walter Muir Whitehill; J. C. Smiddy; Frank S. Walker; Edgar and
                Eleanor Shannon, Jr.; Thomas A. Graves; Dumas Malone; Joseph H. McConnell; Charles
                L. Brown; and Gilbert "Gilly" J. Sullivan.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each
                folder.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 id="d1e168" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974; 1979; 1983</unitdate> Correspondence about Carr's
                            Hill</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1</container>
          <physdesc>14 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are thank you letters for gifts to Carr's Hill, information about
                            items on loan, and budget information on entertaining</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e180" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1984</unitdate> Correspondence about
                            Conflicts of Interest</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2</container>
          <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included are policies on conflict of interest and correspondence from
                            President Hereford clarifying that he was not profiting from his son's
                            businesses while they provided service to the University. There are also
                            letters to Myron E. Tremain and Bernard J. Haggerty about resigning from
                            the board of Virginia National Bank due to conflicts of interest.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e195" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974 October 9</unitdate> John A. Gill to Frank
                            Hereford</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3</container>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There is a letter from John A. Gill with very strong and discriminating
                            language against Negroes and Jews attending the University of Virginia
                            and Farmington Hunt Club. Gill was upset that President Hereford had
                            made a statement about changing the policies at Farmington to include
                            all people and Gill was begging Hereford to stand against this "liberal"
                            position.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e211" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1975; 1976</unitdate> Correspondence of
                            Frank Hereford</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4</container>
          <physdesc>69 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included is Hereford's letter of resignation as professor of physics,
                            notes for his Board of Visitors infoview, and letters of congratulations
                            from Hereford to Mills E. Godwin, Jr. and Thomas J. Michie, Jr. on their
                            successful elections. Hereford also corresponded with Walter Muir
                            Whitehill, and Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. about plans for the Rotunda.
                            There are also newspaper clippings about President Hereford's
                            inauguration. Other correspondents include J. C. Smiddy, Frank S.
                            Walker, Edgar F. Shannon, Jr., and Thomas A. Graves.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e229" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1981</unitdate> Correspondence of Frank
                            Hereford</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5</container>
          <physdesc>76 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included is a letter to Associate Justice of the U. S. Supreme Court,
                            Lewis J. Powell, Jr. about a hunting trip. There are mostly thank you
                            letters from the President and his wife. There is also a letter to
                            Hereford from the Board of Visitors about receiving a salary increase.
                            There are also letters about the death of his daughter, Molly, in a
                            tragic car accident, including a letter from Paul Gaston.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e245" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982-1984</unitdate> Correspondence of Frank
                            Hereford</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6</container>
          <physdesc>96 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are mostly friendly inquiries and thank you letters. Included are
                            letters about receiving the 1983 Raven Award. Correspondents include
                            Robert M. Gooch, Gilbert J. Sullivan, and William H. Fishback.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e258" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate> Correspondence of Frank
                            Hereford</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7</container>
          <physdesc>13 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are thank you letters from Hereford for an evening held for him at
                            Carr's Hill and a thank you letter to the Seven Society. Included is a
                            resolution from the Board of Visitors honoring Hereford. There are also
                            nominations for him to serve on the National Science board.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e272" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Miscellaneous notes</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8</container>
          <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Handwritten notes by President Hereford which seem to make up a checklist
                            of items needing his attention</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e283" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Miscellaneous physics
                            paper</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9</container>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e291" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984-1985</unitdate> Resignation</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10</container>
          <physdesc>10 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are newspaper clippings, Board of Visitors meeting minutes, and
                            correspondence about President Hereford's resignation after eleven years
                            as president, including letters from Dumas Malone, Eleanor Shannon,
                            Joseph H. McConnell, Charles L. Brown, and Thomas A. Graves.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e304" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Resume</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11</container>
          <physdesc>11 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Included are several vitas of President Hereford as well as visa
                            applications to Japan</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e315" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977-1982</unitdate> Rotunda</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12</container>
          <physdesc>2 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There is information about names for the Rotunda Blocks. There is also
                            information about the Pep Band performing at the Rotunda for the Lawn
                            Society Banquet.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e327" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n. d.</unitdate> Speech list</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:1</container>
          <physdesc>1 item</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There is a list of speeches made by President Hereford</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e337" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:2</container>
          <physdesc>19 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Richmond Rotary Club; Arthur J. Morris Law Library;
                            Faculty Wives; Chamber of Commerce; Diabetes-Endocrinology Center; Forum
                            club; Inaugural address; Graduate Business School Sponsors; New Faculty
                            Members; Entering Students; Resident Staff; Jaycees; Commencement
                            Address for Florida Institute of Technology; Woodberry Forest;
                            Hampden-Sydney College; Associates of the University Library; and Clinch
                            Valley.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e353" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:3</container>
          <physdesc>24 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Virginia Club of Washington; Entering Students; Southern
                            Surgical Association; Center for Oceans Law &amp; Policy; New Faculty
                            Members; Governor and Budget Advisory Committee; Dedication of the
                            Darden School; Resident Staff; Charlottesville Rotary Club; Virginia
                            Bankers Association; Final Exercises; Service Award Ceremony; Law Day
                            Luncheon; Dr. Wade Hampton Frost Professorship; Founders Day; Thomas
                            Jefferson Society Alumni; Board of Managers of Alumni Association;
                            Associates of the Library; Notes for the Crystallographers; Federal
                            Executive Institute Seminar; Association of Virginia Colleges Annual
                            Meeting; and Chairs Dinner.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e372" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:4</container>
          <physdesc>19 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include School of Education; State of the University; Fall
                            Convocation; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Resident Staff;
                            Conferring Law Degrees; Final Exercises; Rotunda Dedication; Founders
                            Day; 1926 Graduates; Omicron Delta Kappa; and Alumni</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e385" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:5</container>
          <physdesc>17 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Medical Alumni Board; Fall Convocation; Lawn Society;
                            Introduction of Governor Godwin; New Faculty Members; Resident Staff;
                            1952 Class Reunion; Final Exercises; Chairs Dinner; Thomas Jefferson
                            Society; Founders Day; Alumni; Omicron Delta Kappa; Medical Advisory
                            Committee; and Entering Students</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e399" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:6</container>
          <physdesc>20 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Congressional Delegation; Federal Executive Institute;
                            Winchester Rotary Club; New Faculty Members; Entering Students; Local
                            Government Officers; Final Exercises; Alumni Awards Dinner; Founders
                            Day; Omicron Delta Kappa; Faculty Bicentennial Speaker Series about
                            Women; Thomas Jefferson Society; Norfolk Rotary Club; Panama Canal
                            Treaties Symposium; Appropriations Committee of the House of Delegates;
                            Fall Convocation and Lawn Society</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e415" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1980</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">2:7</container>
          <physdesc>36 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include New York Alumni; Lynchburg Alumni; Philadelphia Alumni;
                            Alumni Awards Dinner; Dedication of Sponsors Hall; Fall Convocation; New
                            Faculty Members; Entering Students; New Student Convocation; Resident
                            Staff; Local Government Officials Conference; Final Exercises; Sidney S.
                            Negus Memorial Symposium; Dumas Malone Ceremony; Dedication of Walter L.
                            Brown; Law Class Reunion Dinner (Senator Edward Kennedy) Thomas
                            Jefferson Society; Founders Day; Chairs Dinner; Easters; Faculty
                            Bicentennial Speaker Series; Dedication of Shannon Garden; Parents Day;
                            Alumni State of the University; Medical Alumni Association; and General
                            Professional Advisory Committee.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e434" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1981-1982</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:1</container>
          <physdesc>38 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Parent's Committee; Alumni Homecoming; Fall Convocation;
                            Darden Convocation; New Student Convocation; Founders Day; New Faculty
                            Members; Student Aid Foundation; Resident Staff; Science Engineering and
                            Applied Sciences Conferring Degrees; State of the University Address;
                            Thomas Jefferson Society; University Union; Prospects For Higher
                            Education; Medical Alumni Advisory Committee; W. Ralph Singleton; Local
                            Government Officials Conference; Final Exercises; Columbia Alumni;
                            Charleston Alumni; Memphis Alumni; Charlottesville Rotary Club; and the
                            Clemons Library Dedication.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e452" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1984</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:2</container>
          <physdesc>25 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches include Parents Day; Fall Convocation; New Faculty Members;
                            Entering Students; Darden School Sponsors; New Student Convocation;
                            Final Exercises; Thomas Jefferson Society; Omicron Delta Kappa; Founders
                            Day; Baltimore Area Campaign Kick-Off; Roanoke Area Campaign Kick-Off;
                            Wilmington Area Kick-Off; New York Area Campaign Kick-Off; Lynchburg
                            Campaign Kick-Off; Chattanooga Alumni; Atlanta Alumni; Houston Alumni;
                            New Orleans Alumni; Maryland Alumni; Budget Requests; SCHE Conference;
                            Groundbreaking of Replacement Hospital; Introduction of John Casteen;
                            and Lawn Advisory Board.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e470" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate> Speeches</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:3</container>
          <physdesc>4 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Speeches were addressed to the UVA Women Faculty; Founders Day attendees;
                            Clifton Waller Barrett Dinner guests, and Final Exercises</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e481" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1973</unitdate> Speeches Before Hereford was President</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:4</container>
          <physdesc>13 items</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e488" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1925-1979; n. d.</unitdate> Speech
                            material</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:5</container>
          <physdesc>57 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There are articles, and reference materials for speeches. The material is
                            divided into different subject areas such as earlier alumni speeches;
                            enrollment; financial information; historical facts; honor system;
                            medical school; miscellaneous; and public vs. private Institutions.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e502" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1893; 1921-1922; 1965-1984; n.
                                d.</unitdate> Speech material: UVA related materials</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:6</container>
          <physdesc>32 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There is information pertaining to the history of the University of
                            Virginia that Hereford used in his speeches. Included are photocopies
                            from Philip Bruce's, "History of the University of Virginia," an article
                            by John Hammond Moore, "Morgan Robinson Preservation of the Traditions
                            of the University of Virginia," an article, "Another Peppercorn for Mr.
                            Jefferson," and an article from the Magazine of Albemarle County
                            History, "Lafayette in Albemarle." There are copies of Board of Visitors
                            minutes from 1909; a report from the UVA Faculty Committee denying the
                            admission of Women (1893;) "Remarks by Walter Dexter Whitehead, Dean of
                            the Faculty of Arts and Science" (1971 December 14); "Remarks by Mills
                            Godwin" at President Hereford's inauguration; and a typescript
                            manuscript of a "Paraphrased Conversation between Richard M. Brandt and
                            President Hereford (April 19,1973)</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 id="d1e525" level="file">
        <did>
          <unittitle><unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1984; n. d.</unitdate> University of
                            Virginia miscellaneous</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">3:7</container>
          <physdesc>10 items</physdesc>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>There is a poem by Raymond C. Bice written for President Hereford's
                            birthday; poems by Frank L. Hereford, Jr., endowment figures, Virginia
                            Freedom for Information legislation, and lists of tenured faculty and
                            members of the standing committees of the Board of Visitors.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
