<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02999">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02999::Venable, Minor, Wilson and Related Families)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu02999.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02999::Venable, Minor, Wilson and
             Related Families)//EN" "viu02999.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Venable, Minor, Wilson and
            Related Families, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822(1875-1946) 1990 and n.d.</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Venable, Minor, Wilson, and Related
            Families 
            <num type="collectionnumber">3750-d</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2013 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ##36.5 Kilobytes]</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by niyi, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">7/31/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-20" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 20, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02999::Venable, Minor,
            Wilson and Related Families)//EN" "viu02999.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Venable, Minor, Wilson and Related
         Families, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 (1875-1946) 1990</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">3750-d</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2013</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections Department</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Venable, Minor, Wilson and Related Families 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 (1875-1946)
         1990</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">3750-d</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of ca. 210 items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Venable, Minor, Wilson and Related Families, Accession
            #3750-d, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia
            Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>This material was given to the Library by Walter
            Klingman of Houston, Texas on June 19, 1996.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection pertains to the Venable, Minor, Wilson and
         related families. Included are correspondence, papers,
         photographs, artwork, memorabilia, and bound volumes. The
         majority of the collection consists of letters addressed to
         Anne C. J. Minor, daughter of Natalie Embra (Venable) and
         Raleigh Colston Minor, and wife of Walter O. Klingman. There
         are also letters to other members of the Venable and Minor
         families.</p>
      <p>There are several letters addressed to Charles Scott
         Venable (1827-1900) and Raleigh Colston Minor (1869-1923)
         among the correspondence of the Venable and Minor families.
         There are two letters, July 21, 1875 and October 24, 1895,
         from 
         <persname normal="Thomas">T[homas]</persname><persname normal="Francis">F[rancis]</persname>Bayard
         (1828-1898) to Charles 
         <persname normal="Scott">S[cott]</persname>Venable. In 1875,
         he mentions Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's poem "Morituri
         Salutamus"; discusses national politics and finances; and,
         comments that "men of conscience and convictions" have always
         had problems of adaptation. In 1895, from the Embassy of the
         United States in London, he mentions [ ] Price receiving the
         Waterloo medal and Lord [Welseley] being the new commander-in-
         chief; comments on the Venezuelan matter (the boundary dispute
         between Venezuela and Great Britain) and the journalists'
         coverage which seems to create sensation; comments on 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Life of General Thomas
         Pinckney</title>by his grandson (Rev. Charles Cotesworth
         Pinckney) and that "it is a pity the South does not take care
         of the history of it's men... On February 7, 1896, 
         <persname normal="Walter">W[alter]</persname><persname normal="Heron">H[eron]</persname>Taylor (1838-1916)
         writes to Charles 
         <persname normal="Scott">S[cott]</persname>Venable, commenting
         on [James] Longstreet (1821-1904) and his book [ 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">From Manassas to Appomattox; Memoirs of
         the Civil War in America</title>]. On April 11, 1918, Charles
         Henderson writes from Camp Lee, Virginia, to Raleigh 
         <persname normal="Colston">C[olston]</persname>Minor, while
         serving in the 320th Regiment in its Headquarters Company. He
         describes his duties while at the Depot Brigade and the
         organization of each regiment's Headquarters Company; relates
         news that he will probably be assigned to the Signal Platoon;
         writes that he saw "William" and other friends at O. S. C.
         where there was little work; and, comments that "Easter Week
         makes me fear for the sanity of the present student body" [at
         the University of Virginia] and that there seems to be a lack
         of steadying influences.</p>
      <p>There are letters, 1915-1927, to Anne C. J. Minor from
         various family members and friends. On November 7, 1915,
         [Robert Kent] Gooch (1893- ) writes from Christ Church,
         Oxford, commenting on the great variety of people riding
         bicycles and the beauty of the colleges and describing some of
         the war scenery in France. On February 24, 1917, Edmund Minor
         Wilson (1895-1972) of the 111th Field Artillery mentions the
         parade with twenty-eight thousand men; comments on Anne
         Minor's education, being a bridesmaid, and corresponding with
         French soldiers; and, writes about activities which include
         having inspections and grooming horses. Raleigh Colston Minor
         at the University of Virginia writes his daughter on June 15,
         1918, with news of [C.] Venable [Minor], Thomas Barringer,
         Arthur [Barksdale] Kinsolving, and Isabel Perkinson. There are
         postcards, September-December 1918, from French and American
         soldiers, including 
         <persname normal="Armistead">A[rmistead]</persname><persname normal="Mason">M[ason]</persname>Dobie (1881- ). A
         March 27, 1919 letter from "Minor," Camp Meade, Baltimore,
         finds him back from France and expecting to be discharged. It
         also mentions needing volunteers for the victory loan and news
         of Charles Henderson. On May 9, 1924, Thomas Manning writes
         from the Columbia Country Club, Chevy Chase, Maryland, a
         humorous letter mentioning the orchestra playing a tune "Will
         Spearmint Keep Its Flavor on the Bedpost Overnight?" There are
         two letters, June 7 and December 18, 1925, and a postcard from
         Port-au-Prince, Haiti discussing the weather, activities and
         daily life in Haiti, native Haitians, and its being
         undeveloped. There are postcards, June-July 1925, from Italy
         and France, mentioning cabarets and other shows, including 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Rose Marie</title>. A June 7, 1927
         letter from Milton C. Elliott concerns the Law Class of 1902
         presenting the University of Virginia with a portrait of her
         father, Raleigh Colston Minor.</p>
      <p>There are also letters, 1928-1931, to Anne C. J. Minor from
         family and friends. Letters from July 1928 are from "Harrison"
         and "Billy" on an overseas voyage and visit to various places
         in Europe, apparently with a group of University of Virginia
         students. Persons mentioned on the trip include: 'Mike'
         [Morton Morris] Pinckney, 'Sunny' [Russell Lee] Post, Jouett
         [Ross] Todd (1903-1967), "Harry" [Henry Kennedy] Benham,
         'Andy' Anderson, "Bill" [William Hamilton] Roper, "Jim" [James
         Miller] McCready, "Tom" Winston, "Jack" [John Samuel]
         Poindexter, Howard [Weaver] McCall, Jr., and Garrison Elder.
         These letters discuss activities and plans on the voyage,
         seeing the play 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Bachelor Father</title>in New York,
         plans to see John Stewart Bryan (1871-1944) in London,
         activities and travel in Switzerland, living quarters and
         inhabitants in Hotel Malherbe, travel around England's
         Devonshire, London, and Shakespeare country, and activities in
         Paris, France. There is also a postcard, Sep 1928, from
         Karlovy Vary, Czechoslovakia. There are also letters, May 30
         and August 19, 1929, from "Janie" in Paris, France, relating
         plans for an exploration trip to Heidelburg and Cologne,
         Germany, Brussell, Belgium, and the coast of Normany, France;
         discussing activities and a typical school day in Toul, France
         and future travel plans; and, commenting on 
         <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">All's Quiet on the Western
         Front</title>and "the utter futility of war." There are also
         postcards, late 1920s, from Canada, Mexico, London, and Costa
         Rica. A letter, ca. July 1928, from "Ted" [Edmund George]
         Laird from Paris, France, discusses travel activities in Great
         Britain, the beach of Dinard, Notre Dame, the Louvre, and St.
         Denis, France.</p>
      <p>There are several letters, 1918-1919, to Anne C. J. Minor
         from Fred A. Broomall of the 6th U. S. Engineers stationed in
         France and Germany. While in France, May 1918 - November 1918,
         Broomall mentions being with the British Expeditionary Forces
         but attached to the Australian Imperial Force and later with
         the American troops, the official status of the unit at the
         University of Virginia, Thomas Smedley Butler of the Marines,
         the war developing into one of movement instead of one of
         position, and harvest season in France with crops worked
         mostly by French soldiers and peasant women. Broomall also
         discusses fighting with the infantry, the regiment's capture
         of prisoners and important ground, the armistice being signed,
         going forward again but with no shells or machine guns,
         expecting to be part of the Army of Occupation, and the
         feelings of the allies. During February 1920, Broomall is
         assigned to Ochtendung, German with the Army of Occupation,
         where he writes concerning activities in the Claire Chesnes in
         the Argonne Meuse region, action near Malancourt (Esnes), and
         his progress in the war since December 20, 1917. The
         activities of the U. S. Engineers include erecting barracks at
         Haute Sa&amp;#56442;&amp;#56684; building steel bridges,
         destroying the big Engineer dump at Chaulnes, building bridges
         over the Somne Canal, joining the 3rd Division or the Marne
         Division, bridging the Vesle River at Tismes, taking over the
         road from Montzeville to Malancourt, relieving the 79th
         Division, crossing into Luxemburg, and reaching the area near
         Coblenz. Current activities include athletics and military
         competitions such as horse shows and rifle teams, and being in
         charge of the regimental mounted section. In May 1919,
         Broomall is still in Germany on detached service and writes
         that they took over some road work from the 318th Engineers,
         6th Division. He comments on returning soldiers to the United
         States and the parades of welcome and the 6th U. S. Engineers
         wishing to take their colors up Pennsylvania Avenue as a D. C.
         regiment. He also describes the scenery of mountains,
         vineyards, gardens and potato fields, and the daily life of
         German children.</p>
      <p>Among the letters, 1940-1946, to Anne C. J. (Minor) and
         Walter O. Klingman are several from her brother, C. Venable
         Minor. A November 8, 1940 letter and its attachments concerns
         a legal matter involving an African-American, Robert Ellis, in
         the employ of the Klingmans in New York. On January 21, 1943,
         Minor writes a verbose and witty letter concerning his trip to
         Washington, D. C. to procure a position in the service and the
         obstacles encountered. He describes at length his contact with
         various officers in different branches of the service and
         other officials, including 
         <persname normal="Edward">Ed[ward]</persname>[R.] Stettinius
         (1900- 1949), [T. Munford] "Munny" Boyd, and [James] Hardy
         Dillard, and, visits to the Judge Advocate General's Office,
         the Pentagon Building, Lend- Lease, the Marine Recruiting
         Office, and Selective Service Headquarters. He also mentions
         teaching Virginia Procedure and Contracts in the University of
         Virginia Law School and the arrival of [Mary] "Polly"
         [Southall Venable] Barclay Dulaney [Mrs. Robert Leroy
         Dulaney]. On May 3, 1943, Minor discusses the Aircraft Warning
         Services, Mrs. Dulaney, 'Radar' in the Marine Corps, his
         difficulty in being commissioned into service, and his
         position with the archaic office known as Examiner of Records.
         A June 24, 1943 letter from Minor expresses concern for their
         ailing mother, [Natalie Embra (Venable) Minor] and requests
         that all of her children and grandchildren attend her birthday
         celebration on July the 15th; discusses further obstacles with
         being commissioned into service; and, mentions servants Annie,
         Blondie, and Isaiah. A letter, December 1, 1944, from Dr.
         Charles Scott Venable, San Antonio, Texas, to Walter O.
         Klingman, requests that he give serious consideration to
         moving to San Antonio following his release from service in
         order to assist the only neuropsychiatrist at the medical
         center. A July 28, 1945 letter from Charles E. Thompson
         concerns swords sent from Belgium and France. On September 12,
         1945, Minor writes a brotherly letter expressing his affection
         following an apparent misunderstanding in which he also
         mentions the death of Murray [Mason] McGuire (1872-1845) and
         news of his wife Clara [Winston Cabell] McGuire, and news of
         the release of "Staige" and Walter [Klingman] from the Army. A
         letter dated December 21 from Julius Barclay in London
         includes information on the illustrated book Coaching Days of
         England.</p>
      <p>Letters, ca. 1870s, to Mary L. Minor from Nannie C. Minor,
         chiefly relate to personal and family matters and various
         cloths or materials for making garments and also mention cases
         of the measles among the children, the death of young "Cooke,"
         Lizzie Maury, Bertha Rives, and Jeannie Colston.</p>
      <p>There are other papers and printed materials relating to
         the families. The biographical and genealogical data contains
         information, in the form of Bible records, sketches, and
         newspaper articles, on the Colston family (1785-1822),
         Elizabeth McDowell Benton (1794-1854), Elizabeth (Henry)
         Russell (1749-1825), and the Venable, Wilson, Minor and
         related families. The material for educational institutions
         include: catalogue (1896) for Hampden-Sidney, a poem (1921) by
         Moncure Lyne, "The Centennial of the University of Virginia,"
         flyer (1925) for a celebration of the Episcopal High School of
         Virginia, and an anonymous card from the Seven Society with
         its symbol. Among the medal and memorabilia are an IMP charm,
         a Republican National Convention medal and ribbon (1904), and
         a medal for the dedication of the Stonewall Jackson statue
         (1891). The miscellaneous material includes a sketch on John
         S. Skinner's visit to Albemarle in 1820, auctions (1988) for
         "Midmont" and Michie Tavern, postcards for the Edgar Allan Poe
         Shrine, art work, and a Valentine Day's card.</p>
      <p>There are photographs of members of the Minor, Venable, and
         Wilson families. Persons included are: John Barbee Minor, John
         <persname normal="Barbee">B[arbee]</persname>Minor, Jr.,
         Raleigh Colston Minor, Charles Scott Venable, Mary Minor,
         Susan Colston (Minor) Wilson, Mattie Minor, Nannie Jacquelin
         Minor, [Mary] Cantey (McDowell) Minor, Natalie Embra
         (Venable)</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e240">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e244">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Correspondence of the Venable and Minor
                  families 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1875-1927,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e252">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1915-1924</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e260">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1925-1927</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e268">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1928-1931</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e276">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. Minor from Fred A.
                  Broomall 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1918-1919</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e284">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. (Minor) and Walter
                  O. Klingman 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1940-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e292">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Anne C. J. (Minor) and Walter
                  O. Klingman 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1946,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e300">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters to Mary L. Minor from Nannie C.
                  Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca.
                  1870s</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e308">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Topical</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e312">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Biographical and Genealogical Data 
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822-1930,
                n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edge Hill School certificates for Nannie Minor 
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1886-1887,
                n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>       
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e320">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Educational Institutions 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1896-1925</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e328">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Medals and Memorabilia 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1891-1924,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e336">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1988,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e344">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Pastel Drawing of the Rotunda by [ ] 
                  <persname normal="Venable">V[enable]</persname><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e355">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Minor and Venable family
                  members: John Barbee Minor; John Barbee Minor, Jr.;
                  Raleigh Colston Minor; and Charles Scott Venable 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1882,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e363">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Minor and Venable family
                  members, and others 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">(1899-1921)1990,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e371">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of Minor and Wilson family
                  members 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">ca. 1900,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e379">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Recipes and Household Hints, in a bound
                  volume belonging to Mrs. John Barbee Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1881,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e387">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Recipes and Household Hints, removed from
                  the bound volume belonging to Mrs. John Barbee Minor 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860-1896,
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e396">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Transcripts of letters from Betsy Ambler
                  Carrington to Ann Ambler Fisher, 1796-1823 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e404">
          <did>
            <unittitle><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Holy Bible</title>given to
                  Thomas M. and Eliza J. Colston by Father Rawleigh
                  Colston on May 16, 1822 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1822</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e415">
          <did>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Mini-Tray
                  107</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e419">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ambrotypes and Daguerreotypes of Minor
                  family members. Ambrotype of [Raleigh Colston Minor
                  ?]. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Mini-Tray
                  107</container>
            <physdesc>[in one envelope and three
                  boxes]</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e429">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs of McDowell and Venable family
                  members: James McDowell; Mary Cantey (McDowell)
                  Venable; Charles Scott Venable; and, Thomas Francis
                  Bayard 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Oversize Box
                  P-17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e437">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Yellow Journal</title>
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924, 1926,
                     1929</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Oversize Box
                  P-17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e449">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Poster of "Confederate Commanders"
                  [damaged -- several tears] 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Oversize Tray
                  58</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
