<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03976">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03976::Papers of Henry Clay)//EN" "viu03976.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798-1934, n.d.</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Clay, Henry, Papers
<num type="collectionnumber"> : Multiple numbers
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2015 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Paul Pugliese, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1/19/2006</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798-1934, n.d.</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num>Multiple numbers
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2015
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798-1934, n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">Multiple numbers
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">ca. 271 items
</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xtf="http://cdlib.org/xtf">See the 
            <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Henry Clay, Various Accessions, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was acquired by gift, purchase, and loan, ca. 1900-present. See individual accessions for detailed information.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Henry Clay was an American statesman whose masterly compromises on sectional issues helped pacify and preserve the nation during the troubled decades preceding the Civil War. In a long career in public service,
he was a Kentucky legislator, a U.S. Congressman (1811-1814, 1815-1821, 1823-1825) and speaker of the House of Representatives (1811-1814, 1815-1819, 1823-1825), Secretary of State, and several times a Senator
(1806-1807, 1810-11, 1831-1842, 1849-1852). Clay was a major promoter of the Missouri Compromise (1820), the compromise tariff of 1833 (ending the Nullification crisis), and the Compromise of 1850, all efforts to
balance the rights of free and slave states. Clay was twice the unsuccessful Whig candidate for president (1832, 1844). An excellent orator in an age that esteemed oratory, Clay was a charismatic leading statesman
of his period. He was impetuous by nature, on occasion rash in action, and sometimes selfish and arrogant as a Whig Party leader. Abraham Lincoln and William H. Seward later agreed that his selfishness had been
detrimental to the Whigs. Clay's championship of Latin American freedom strengthened the prestige of the United States in that part of the world and laid the foundations for Pan-Americanism. As a Whig leader, he
played an important role in establishing the two-party system that was so essential to the country's political stability. A gradualist, believing that change should come slowly, and a genius in the art of
compromise, he did much to hold the Union together in the four decades before the Civil War. And his devotion to tariffs and internal improvements furnished a basis for the domestic program that kept the
Republican Party in power in the years after the war and encouraged the nation's economic growth.
</p>
      <p>Henry Clay was born in Hanover County, Virginia on April 12, 1777, the seventh of nine children. His father, John Clay, was a former Baptist minister turned farmer. He died in 1781, and 10 years later Elizabeth
married Capt. Henry Watkins and moved to Richmond. In 1792 the couple moved to Kentucky, but Henry remained in Richmond as a deputy clerk in the high court of chancery. There he acted as amanuensis to Chancellor
George Wythe, who advised him to study law. Clay read law under the direction of Wythe and Attorney General Robert Brooke and, after a brief period of preparation, was admitted to the bar in 1797.
</p>
      <p>Clay was introduced to Richmond society and quickly acquired self-assurance there. However, he looked beyond Richmond for a place to practice law. Kentucky, where land suits were many, was a paradise for
lawyers, and Clay made his way there in the winter of 1797-1798, settling in Lexington, then a town of some 1,600 inhabitants.
</p>
      <p>Clay found the early West congenial. He established a law practice, which flourished, and made friends who shared his political views. On April 11, 1799, he married Lucretia Hart, youngest daughter of Col.
Thomas Hart, a wealthy merchant and land speculator. By 1805 Clay had acquired considerable property, as his profession brought him into close contact with the landed proprietors and the nascent industrial
interests of the growing West.
</p>
      <p>A Jeffersonian-Republican by conviction and education, Clay took an interest in politics almost from his arrival in Kentucky. He urged democratization of the state's constitution and a gradual emancipation of
slaves. Outspoken on national issues, too, he opposed the Alien and Sedition Acts, championed the Kentucky Resolutions, and campaigned for his party in 1800. In 1803 he was elected to the state legislature, where
he sponsored internal improvements and defended a banking venture upon which his friends and relatives had embarked. In 1806, as counsel for Aaron Burr, he obtained that adventurer's exoneration by a grand jury in
Frankfort, Ky., which refused to indict Burr on a charge of fomenting an expedition against Mexico. The defense of Burr on this occasion did Clay's reputation no harm, for Burr was then well thought of in Kentucky
and Clay had undertaken the case only upon Burr's most solemn pledge of innocence. Clay never forgave Burr for his duplicity. (This early hearing is not to be confused with Burr's trial for treason and acquittal
in Richmond, Va., in August 1807, in which Clay took no part.) In 1806, Clay went to the United States Senate to fill an unexpired term. His constituents sent him to the Kentucky legislature in 1807, where he was
elected speaker of the House of Representatives.
</p>
      <p>A duel with a Federalist opponent, Humphrey Marshall, in which Clay was slightly wounded, added to his popularity. He was easily reelected to the legislature in 1809 and was chosen by that body to fill another
unexpired term in the U. S. Senate, commencing in February 1810. There he stood for protection and declared himself an ardent expansionist. He opposed the recharter of the Bank of the United States in 1811, a
stand that was popular with the speculators and state banking interests of Kentucky. On returning home, he was elected to Congress, and when that body convened on Nov. 4, 1811, he was chosen Speaker of the House
of Representatives.
</p>
      <p>As Speaker, Clay increased the power of the office and strengthened his own political position. In doing so, he played a prominent part in inciting the War of 1812. One of the Indian-hating, land-hungry "War
Hawks," Clay appointed expansionists to important committee posts and by his speeches fomented the rising war fever. He sought vigorous prosecution of the war with Britain and at its close was one of the five
American members of the peace commission that concluded a status quo ante bellum peace, the Treaty of Ghent. He returned home by way of England, where he helped to conclude a commercial treaty. When Congress
reconvened in December 1815, he was reelected Speaker.
</p>
      <p>Ambitious, impetuous, and eloquent, Clay proceeded in the years following the War of 1812 to develop what became known as his "American System." Domestic improvements at national expense, a protective tariff, a
national bank, and finally cooperation with the South American patriots to enhance the U. S. position of leadership in the Western Hemisphere constituted the essence of his plan. Its development, he believed,
would bring the United States "to that height to which God and nature had destined it."
</p>
      <p>This program was carried out in part. The national bank was reinstated, and the protective tariff became law in 1816. But Clay's plans for internal improvements at national expense were thwarted by the
constitutional scruples of Presidents James Madison and James Monroe, and his demand for early recognition of the South American republics was countered by John C. Calhoun and John Quincy Adams, influential
members of Monroe's cabinet. Furthermore, Clay earned Andrew Jackson's enmity by bitterly censuring him for his conduct in the Florida expedition of 1818, and he sorely tried Monroe's patience by a policy of
carping criticism, which arose out of disappointment at not having been made Secretary of State in 1817. These shortcomings and limitations were more than offset, however, by his brilliant handling of the Missouri
Compromise, which earned him the title of the "Great Pacificator."
</p>
      <p>During the 1820's, Clay became more and more closely identified with the nation's economic upper class. His Kentucky estate, Ashland, and other property gave him a tax assessment of over $72,000 in 1831. His
views on financial matters during the panic of 1819 classed him with the creditor, anti-relief interests. His legal practice identified him closely with the privileged classes. All this boded ill for his political
ambition.
</p>
      <p>Clay sought the presidency in 1824, as did Andrew Jackson, John Quincy Adams, and William Harris Crawford, another member of Monroe's cabinet. Clay had the great disadvantage of running against another
contestant from the West, Jackson. The latter emerged from the contest with more electoral votes than anyone else, but since no candidate had a majority the election was to be decided in the House of
Representatives. Clay, who had run fourth, was no longer a candidate, but his influence as Speaker of the House for Adams was decisive. Adams made Clay Secretary of State, and Jackson and his friends promptly
raised the cry of "Bargain and Sale."
</p>
      <p>Before the election in the House, Adams and Clay in private conversations had disclosed to one another a fundamental harmony of views on public questions. There probably was a general understanding that Clay
was to receive some kind of recognition for his support. That the "bargain" went further than this is doubtful, but the charge of "Bargain and Sale" persisted. Clay never ceased his efforts to demonstrate the
purity of his motives in the 1824 election, and in 1826 he fought a bloodless duel with Sen. John Randolph of Virginia over the issue.
</p>
      <p>As Secretary of State, Clay sought to broaden U. S. trade and extend American influence in the Western Hemisphere through participation in the Panama Congress of 1826. But the American delegates to Panama, who
had to await confirmation from a reluctant Senate, arrived too late, and the role of the United States was ineffectual.
</p>
      <p>The political opposition to Clay's Pan-American policy was evidence of the crystallization of parties that took place during Adams' administration. Adams and Clay led the National Republicans, who summoned all
believers in protection and internal improvements to join their ranks. The opposition, led by Jackson, Calhoun, and Crawford, was a heterogeneous collection of men and principles; but it could claim with some
reason that the Clay-Adams party had inherited the mantle of conservative Federalism and that its own standard was the emblem of a revitalized Jeffersonianism which would cater to small farmers, workingmen, and
the debtor class. "Democracy" was its battle cry and General Jackson, the hero of New Orleans, its candidate.
</p>
      <p>In 1828, Adams went down to defeat before Jackson, and the latter's uneasy coalition took over. Clay was despondent, but his ardent imagination soon began picturing his own elevation to the presidency in 1832.
He denounced Jackson's use of the spoils of office and the veto power, and he championed internal improvements and protection. He returned to the Senate in 1831 and that same year was nominated for the presidency
by the National Republicans. Jackson was renominated by what was coming to be known as the Democratic party.
</p>
      <p>Clay's bid for election was based partly upon the assumption that the West was as eager for internal improvements as it was for cheap lands, and that the South would accept protection if it were labeled
"incidental." He was wrong on both counts. A further error was his decision to apply for a recharter for the Bank of the United States. The bank was unpopular, and the bill for its recharter was promptly vetoed by
Jackson in a ringing appeal to class hatred and sectional jealousy. The electorate responded with emphasis in 1832, Clay receiving 49 electoral votes to Jackson's 219.
</p>
      <p>Defeat did not quench Clay's ardor for public service. He was the guiding spirit in the passage of the Compromise Tariff of 1833, which put an end both to South Carolina's nullification of the tariffs of 1828
and 1832 and to Jackson's threats to use force against that state. The Compromise of 1833 added to Clay's reputation as a compromiser of sectional issues.
</p>
      <p>During Jackson's second term the Whig party, an amorphous combination of elements predominantly conservative in tone and nationalistic in outlook, came into being as the successor to the National Republicans.
Clay was its logical leader, and from his position in the Senate he strove to marshal the Whig forces in generally fruitless attacks upon Jackson's fiscal policies. The Kentuckian was anxious to obtain
renomination for the presidency in 1836, but the Whigs chose instead to follow the futile strategy of running several regional candidates against Martin Van Buren, Jackson's choice as his successor.
</p>
      <p>Reelected to the Senate in 1837, Clay once more led the assault upon Democratic measures, especially against Van Buren's independent treasury bill and against a proposed democratization of the government's land
policy. The first effort wholly and the second partly failed, but they placed Clay more firmly than ever on the side of the vested interests.
</p>
      <p>In regard to the growing problem of slavery, Clay also displayed his conservatism. Despite a genuine moral repugnance to slavery, as a Kentucky slaveholder he was himself involved in the "peculiar institution."
He had always espoused colonization of the blacks, a harmless, because impractical, remedy for slavery. He hated abolitionism, believing it to be a force that was dividing the sections and leading toward civil
war. While upholding the right of petition, he declared that abolitionist petitions should be rejected. He took a moderate position on the proposed annexation of Texas in the late 1830's. In these ways he tried to
forestall the controversy over slavery and at the same time retain his popularity in both North and South.
</p>
      <p>Clay had hoped to be Van Buren's opponent in 1840, but Thurlow Weed, Whig boss of New York state, and other northern Whig politicians wanted a new candidate. To Clay's disappointment, the choice of the Whigs
fell upon Gen. William Henry Harrison. The convention then chose John Tyler of Virginia, a supposed admirer of Clay and popular with the southern Whigs, as the vice presidential candidate. Clay supported this
ticket, though laying down a program for action that showed his conviction that the leadership of the party still belonged to him.
</p>
      <p>Dissension among the Whigs followed Harrison's death on April 4, 1841. Tyler was an anti-bank, anti-internal improvements, low-tariff Southerner who had no desire to promote the American System or to allow Clay
to usurp his prerogatives as the presidential leader of the Whig party. The Kentuckian was determined that he should lead and Tyler should follow. Under the circumstances, it was inevitable that Clay's program of
a national bank, a higher tariff, and the distribution of land sales to the states should meet a cold reception at the White House. Tyler vetoed two bank bills sponsored by Clay, and a bitter intra- party conflict
developed. Out of this Clay emerged as the leader of the Whigs. He resigned from the Senate early in 1842 to chart his course for 1844.
</p>
      <p>There was no significant challenge to Clay's nomination for the presidency in 1844, but a successful campaign was by no means assured. The question of the annexation of Texas was assuming great importance. In
his famous "Raleigh letter" of April 27, 1844, Clay came out against annexation "at the present time"; a similar letter by Van Buren (collusion has always been suspected but never proved) appeared on the same day.
The intent of the letters was to prevent Texas from becoming a campaign issue, but Van Buren's letter cost him the Democratic nomination, which went to expansionist James K. Polk.
</p>
      <p>Clay was nominated on May 1, and the Whigs conducted a spirited campaign. Texas was the issue. The Democrats declared that Clay was opposed to annexation, and under the weight of this charge his Southern
support began slipping away. Clay sought to explain his stand in the so-called Alabama letters, but in the North these letters produced a fatal drift of antislavery men from the Whig ranks. Polk was elected, and
Clay gloomily retired to Ashland. There he remained, deeply disturbed by the growth of the sectional conflict over slavery and by the Mexican War, of which he thoroughly disapproved and in which his son, Henry
Clay, Jr., was killed.
</p>
      <p>Clay wanted the Whig nomination again in 1848, but influential leaders in the party, both North and South, stood opposed. General Zachary Taylor, of Mexican War fame, was nominated by the Whigs in June 1848.
Clay bowed to the will of the convention, but throughout Taylor's successful campaign he remained in retirement at Ashland.
</p>
      <p>Clay returned to the Senate in 1849 to serve again in a time of crisis and division. The cession of California and the Southwest by Mexico at the end of the Mexican War had greatly heightened tension over
slavery. Northern opinion demanded the exclusion of slavery from the new territories, and in the South a secessionist movement of formidable proportions developed. Clay believed that if the Union were to be saved,
a great effort at compromise must be made. He formulated his plans, obtained Daniel Webster's promise of support, and at the close of January 1850 began his campaign.
</p>
      <p>In a series of resolutions, Clay discussed the principal questions agitating the country. His most important proposals were the admission of California as a free state, a more rigid fugitive slave law, and
provision that the new territories south of 36-degrees 30' should be organized without restriction as to slavery. During the spring and summer of 1850 he fought strenuously for this compromise. His plan, known as
the Compromise of 1850, became law after Clay had gone to Newport, R. I., for a rest. Its immediate passage owed much to Stephen A. Douglas and the Democrats in Congress; but to Clay must go the credit for its
conception and for arousing public opinion favorable to the measure.
</p>
      <p>Clay was not to live much longer after the passage of the compromise. He spent the summer of 1851 at Ashland, where he made his will, providing for the disposition of his estate and the freeing of his slaves.
Though dying of tuberculosis, he returned to Washington that fall and answered to the first Senate roll call. Thereafter he was closely confined to his room in the National Hotel, where he died on the morning of
June 29, 1852.
</p>
      <p>Clay was a conservative, and his appeal was essentially to the upper middle class. He sought by his American System to link East and West together under his leadership without alienating the South, but opposing
sectional interests stood in his way. The protective tariff could not be made into an advantageous issue for a national party. The West preferred cheap lands to a general distribution of land revenues. The South
had no more liking for internal improvements than for raising tariff rates.
</p>
      <p>Clay failed to achieve the presidency because of his mistakes of judgment and the machinations of professional politicians such as Thurlow Weed. But his services to his country in foreign affairs and in
effecting compromises at times of national crisis-especially the Compromise of 1850, which history considers his crowning achievement-give him high rank among American statesmen.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of 265 items, consisting chiefly of letters and documents by and to Henry Clay. The collection also includes prints and photographs of Clay. Correspondents include:
</p>
      <p>
Correspondents include: John Agg, James Barbour, Nicholas Biddle, James Brown, Jacob Burnet, Matthew Carey, Langdon Cheves, James F. Conover, Susan Wheeler Decatur, Horace Greeley, Jabez D. Hammond, Thomas Jefferson, John L. Lawrence, Benjamin Watkins Leigh, James Madison, Brantz Mayer, James Monroe, James M. Morris, Hezekiah Niles, Peter B. Porter, Robert Selden Rose, Richard Rush, Nathan Sargent, Samuel Smith, Joseph Story, Alexander H.H. Stuart, Littleton Dennis Teackle, William Thornton, John P. Todd, William Tompkins, Nicholas P. Trist, John Tyler, Joseph Vance, James Watson Webb, Daniel Webster, Conway D. Whittle.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The collection is organized in two series: Series I: Correspondence and Documents and Series II: Prints and Photographs. Both series are arranged chronologically.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e198">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Correspondence and Documents
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e202">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal document, signed by Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1798 September 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:1
</container>
            <physdesc>DS, 1 p.; partially printed. #3261.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Lexington District, Fayette County, [Kentucky]. A complaint by John Thomas against Greenberry Riggs for payment of eighty pounds.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e216">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal document
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1799
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ADS, 1 p.; docketed. #3261.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Woodford County, [Kentucky]. Complaint by Elijah Pepper against John Harris for the death of a horse, caused by Harris's "two negro slaves."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e230">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to "Sir"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1811 February 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2180.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies that he is not able to give a more satisfactory account of the judgment against Chambers; owing to a blunder committed by the sheriff, the money has not been collected. Clay will write again and
expects the money "to be made in five or six months." He closes by asking for the return of his letter in which Mr. Grine [?] is mentioned as he has no recollection of that name.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e244">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, House of Representatives, to "Dear Major"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812 February 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:4
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #4206.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes in reference to a suit brought against Major by Mr. West. Clay states that he and Mr. [Martin D.] Hardin and Mr. [Robert] Wickliffe were equal partners in the process. Clay reminds Major that he
recommended compromising with Mr. West, but Major chose instead to urge on "the controversy." Clay mentions that the appointment of officers in the new army will keep the House busy for several weeks. He closes by
saying that [William T.] Barry and [William] Worseley are in Washington and Worseley is leaving for Philadelphia today.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e258">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, House of Representatives, to Scott, Trotter &amp; Co., Philadelphia
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:5
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2908.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that he has paid the bill drawn on him by Mr. [John] Hart; in order to do so Clay has written a draft against Scott, Trotter &amp; Co. and hopes it will be honored. He encloses Mr. Hart's bill [not
present].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e272">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Randolph, reply to Henry Clay's letter in the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">National Intelligencer
</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1812 July 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:6
</container>
            <physdesc>D, 3 pp.; printed. Original in Papers of John Randolph of Roanoke. #1883.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Randolph responds to Clay's letter of June 18, 1812 concerning "a late transaction in the House of Representatives."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e289">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to Richard Parrott &amp; Co., Georgetown, D.C.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 September 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:7
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Kentucky, Sept. 6. #2933-g.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay states that he has drawn $4000 to pay Mr. John Hart $3661.54 for sugar and barrels; the cost of transporting the sugar to Petersburg will be covered by the difference. The sugar was sent from Lexington to
Limestone in care of Mr. Sam. January, who will forward it to Mr. James Adams of Petersburg.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e303">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to "Sir"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1813 December 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:8
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; lower right corner (ca. 5 x 3 cm.) torn away; "Amies" watermark. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes to [James Madison] urging the appointment of John Fowler as postmaster of Lexington, Kentucky. Clay states that Fowler "appears to me to have claims to the office, in his early migration to
Kentucky, in his integrity, in his capacity, and in his invariable adherence to republican principles, what I had supposed would have been at once recognized by Mr. Granger."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e317">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to "Dr. Genl."
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 January 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:9
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; silked. #2933.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes concerning payment of a debt and mentions Col. Nicholas, Beale, Maj. Morrison and Gilmour. Clay then discusses at length his objections to a "treaty stipulation in favor of the India trade."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e331">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, London, to John P. Todd, Paris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 March 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:10
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2933-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay scolds Todd for not writing and says he has not had "a line from any one at Paris since I left it." Clay is anxious to know how [James A.?] Bayard is and wishes to return to the United States. He has met
Lord Castlereagh, but would be glad if Todd joined him in London. Clay expects a ship from New London to arrive in Portsmouth in sixteen days but does not know what news it will bring. He sees Lord Gambier
tomorrow and hopes to visit Windsor.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e346">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Birmingham, [England] to John P. Todd
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1815] July 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:11
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Birmingham, 1815 July 7; mounted beneath engraving of Clay. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that he left London on Tuesday [July 4, 1815] and arrived in Birmingham on July 6. Mr. [Albert] Gallatin was to leave London the same day but Clay presumes Gallatin "in my rear." He notes "we signed
the treaty the day before I departed." Clay is eager to leave for the United States and tells Todd "Be you ready, for like Patrick Coutts, when dying, I wait for no man."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e360">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Woodford, to [Martin D. Hardin]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 October 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:12
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #2908.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes to Hardin, Secretary of State of Kentucky, regarding his right to hold his seat in House of Representatives. "Having signed a Commercial convention with Great Britain on the 3d of July last, under a
Commission from the President, it has become questionable whether my seat as a Representative, the right to which commenced on the 4th day of the preceding March, has not thereby become vacated." Clay regrets that
he must call the Governor's [Isaac Shelby] attention to the matter and suggests that if an election must be called it should be soon, perhaps "a fortnight's notice might suffice."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e374">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1815 November 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:13
</container>
            <physdesc>AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.26. #1729.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Smith writes that the sale of Clay's "yarns" left $5114.31 to his credit on his bond of $375. If Clay will send Smith "yarns of the quality of those sold by S. S. &amp; B." [Samuel Smith and James A. Buchanan]
Smith will either allow Clay twelve cents per pound against the balance due, or will sell them free of commission for Clay's account.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e388">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to William Thornton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1817 December 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:14
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that he has purchased 2000 acres of land on the Wabash for two dollars per acre; he believes that "considering the progress of population and improvement" it will soon be worth fifteen or twenty
dollars per acre. Clay understands that the Wabash, "which I think the fairest branch of the Ohio, has been exceedingly healthy this fall &amp; summer." Clay mentions that Thornton's friend Martin Birbeck is
settled not far from the Wabash. He concludes with a postscript: "I have a cordial dislike to appearing in the news papers &amp; of course do not expect to be put there, in this instance."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e402">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to [John W. Hunt]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 January 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:15
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #9030.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay inquires about land values in Lexington, [Kentucky] and says that he must sell some property to meet financial obligations. Clay asks Hunt be his agent in the sale. He concludes by saying "[w]e have been 4
days, and will probably be twice as many more, in discussing Jackson's conduct of the Seminole War."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e416">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Charles Tait , Elbert, Georgia
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 June 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:16
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; docketed; silked; mounted beneath a blue "Blood's Penny Post" stamp bearing Clay's likeness. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks Tait to assist him "if it be practicable, to effect my reimbursement" of $325 advanced to Mrs. Rebecca Willisson. Mrs. Willisson "had a claim to some negroes in this state" and "brought a suit to
recover them." Clay, "with more gallantry than prudence" agreed to stand security for the costs. He includes a copy of the receipt (made by John Spears, administrator for Jacob Spears) for the funds he advanced
and says he "will be greatly obliged by any exertions you may make to get me the amount." Clay concludes by mentioning he has just heard of the capture of Pensacola. He presumes the action "is without authority;
for if it has been, in pursuance of instructions, the Constitutional provision is a dead letter which confides to Congress the power of declaring War."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e430">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 June 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:17
</container>
            <physdesc>AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.66. #1729.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Smith writes that he owes Col. [James] Morrison $1000 in taxes and has "taken the liberty to draw on you in his favor for that amount at 60 days sight."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e444">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to "Dr. Sir" [Samuel Elliot, Jr.?]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 August 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:18
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; docketed on verso; mounted. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has transmitted to Mr. Dougherty a note for $4000 to be applied to his note at "your bank." He encloses a check for $1000 [not present] to cover reminder of the debt.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e458">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to Mr. [John F.] Watson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 August 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:19
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Being in Frankfort last week" Clay checked on the status of the suit of Edith Ross against David Barbour. He found that it was dismissed "several years ago for the want of security for costs." This was during
Clay's absence. He believes that the suit can be renewed and suggests either George M. Bibb or Robert Wickliffe as "suitable counsel" since "I do not myself now practice the law."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e472">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Deposition of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1818 October 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:20
</container>
            <physdesc>DS, 1 p.; witnessed and signed by Matthew Elder[?], Justice of the Peace, Fayette County. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The deposition concerns the sale of a slave by William Ellis to Elizabeth Gorney [?].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e486">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 July 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:21
</container>
            <physdesc>AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.76. #1729.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Smith writes that he is in a "miserable situation" and is "under the necessity of drawing on you to pay Col. [James] Morrison" $500 for taxes. Smith states he has "no other means of payment" and begs Clay "to
honour the bill." Smith's firm (Smith and Buchanan) failed following a run on the Baltimore branch of the Bank of the United States.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e501">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to [Benjamin] Watkins Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 December 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:22
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks Leigh for advice on a legal question concerning the validity of the sale of John Clay's (his father) plantation, Euphraim, in Henrico County, Virginia. Clay mentions Richard Chapman, Henry Watkins and
Richard Cocke.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e515">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to [Benjamin Watkins Leigh]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 December 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:23
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; silked; "M &amp; K N York" watermark. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay received Leigh's letter and has written to Hanover "to obtain a copy of the act of renunciation" which his mother made regarding provisions in John Clay's will.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e529">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819 December 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:24
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received a copy of his "mother's renunciation of the benefit of the provisions for her contained in my father's will" concerning the plantation Euphraim. Clay wishes to proceed with the action to recover the land and has asked Edmund W. Rootes to call on Leigh to "take under your direction the measures necessary for the successful prosecution." Clay then discusses the remaining heirs of John Clay and asks Leigh to advise if it is better to prosecute the case in the name of all three or two only.  Clay prefers the case to be carried forward in Federal court. 
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e543">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 January 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:25
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received a copy of his "mother's renunciation of the benefit of the provisions for her contained in my father's will" concerning the plantation Euphraim. Clay wishes to proceed with the action to recover the land and has asked Edmund W. Rootes to call on Leigh to "take under your direction the measures necessary for the successful prosecution." Clay then discusses the remaining heirs of John Clay and asks Leigh to advise if it is better to prosecute the case in the name of all three or two only.  Clay prefers the case to be carried forward in Federal court. 
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e557">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 March 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:26
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks if it is necessary "to sue out letters of Administration, upon the Estate of my deceased brother, to maintain the Ejectment for Euphraim?" He repeats his question of January 20, 1820 concerning the possibility of obtaining administration without actually being present in Henrico County. 
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e571">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 April 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:27
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is informed by Col. [James] Morrison that he administered the estate of Clay's brother, George, in Richmond. Clay has requested Col. [Thomas] Tinsley of Hanover to work with Leigh in preparing the suit.  He concludes by asking about the schedules of the court.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e585">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 May 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:28
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has sent Leigh's opinion to his brother Porter, who "is more interested than I am in the Ejectment." Clay concludes by asking Leigh to ask [Edmund W.] Rootes to record the deed from John [Clay] to Porter [Clay].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e599">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Chillicothe, to M[aurice] Langhorne
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1820 September 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:29
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay received Langhorne's letter and "immediately addressed a letter to Col. [George?] Gibson" on Langhorne's behalf. Clay had hoped to see Langhorne on his journey back to Kentucky but "an unexpected summons from Mr. [Thomas] Wilson, Cashier of the Bank of the U.S." means Clay must now travel by way of Cincinnati. Clay concludes by stating that "subsequent reflection" has confirmed the opinion he previously gave Langhorne concerning the Bank of Limestone.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e613">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. M. Beckley, Lexington
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 February 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:30
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #10012.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that Capt. Fowler should retain the office of postmaster, but "he is greatly in arrears to Government" and "unless he makes some satisfactory arrangement very soon" he "will be deprived of it."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e627">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Frankfort, to Thomas Dougherty
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1821 December 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:31
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1109.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses a check for $1300 [not present] to pay off the note coming due later in the month. Clay is "very anxious that the amount of Mr. Scott's note should be received and applied to the discharge of
mine" and asks Dougherty "not to let him know that I have made an arrangement predicated on his default." Clay comments that the Kentucky legislature is still in session. The legislature is considering "sending me
as one of two commissioners to treat with Virginia and to appear before that Ct. about the Occupying Claimant law." Clay concludes by mentioning that the "next Presidency" is being discussed in the papers and
Dougherty "may confidently believe in an entire union of the West in favor of some Western candidate."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e641">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Langdon Cheves, Philadelphia
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 January 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:32
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed. #2933-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces Sam. Q. Richardson of Cincinnati to Cheves. Richardson wishes to "hold a conversation with you in respect to the revival of the Off. of Dt. &amp; Dt."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e656">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Richard Morris, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 February 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:33
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington City, February 27. #38-79.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes to communicate the result of an enquiry he was requested to make at the Department of the Treasury by Dr. Morris. Clay was unable to go to the Treasury in person but sent a note to Mr. Pleasanton.
Because of Mr. Pinckney's "regretted death" the business of the House of Representatives was suspended and Clay was able to visit the Treasury. He encloses a note for Dr. Morris [not present] and states that he
will be happy "to serve him in this affair, if in my power." Clay notes that the Virginia House of Delegates has finally dispatched with "its part of the 'Kentucky Question.'" Clay is glad the House of Delegates
"abstained from the expression of any opinion on our laws, as it did not feel itself justified in acceding to either of our propositions." Clay concludes with regards for Mrs. Cock [?] and Mrs. Kempe.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e670">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to B[enjamin] W[atkins] Leigh, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 March 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:34
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington City March 8. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay congratulates Leigh on being appointed a Commissioner to Kentucky and suggests he travel by stage from Richmond, through Washington, to Wheeling and then on to Frankfort. Clay concludes by stating that
[Philip Norborne] Nicholas "is at my elbow, desires to be presented to you, and asks the favor of you to take care of him in the Ct. of Appeals until Wednesday, when he will be there." In postscript, Clay notes
that Leigh will come through Lexington and asks him to "[c]ome to my house, sans ceremonies otherwise I may not know of your being in town."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e684">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Philadelphia, to Thomas Dougherty
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 April 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:35
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. Negative Photostat; original at Pequot Library Association, Southport, Conn. #2933-e.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has been detained for three days by "indisposition" which "has absolutely confined me to my room." He has written to General [Montfort?] Stokes, requesting Stokes to pay Dougherty $115. Clay asks Dougherty
to send him details of the "arrangement you made with Commodore Rogers [sic] [John Rodgers] about the Carriage."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e698">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ohio River, to Genl. Peter B. Porter
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 April 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:36
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 4 pp. #5593.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay regrets that he did not see Porter on his return from Virginia in Washington City as Clay wished to consult "with you on a subject of great interest to me
personally." Clay believes there is no viable candidate for the presidential election to follow James Monroe's second term from either New York or Pennsylvania. He notes that "in the South, there are springing up
several candidates, my juniors in years and in terms of our respective service." Clay writes that his friends see nothing to "restrain them from bringing forward my name" as "[i]t is assumed that the Western
States from Ohio to the Gulph [sic] of Mexico will be firmly and ardently united in my support." New York should ally with the western states in the election since "by lending its support, either to New England or
to the South, it will not advance its pretensions one inch." Clay asks Porter if he "could not find time to employ your excellent pen in illustrating and enforcing those views of general and State policy which
ought to determine the judgment of New York, and which we think obviously indicate the expediency of her looking Westwardly?"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e712">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Richard Rush
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 July 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:37
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #8991.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks for Rush's assistance concerning a bill passed in Congress regarding the Messrs. Streshlys[?].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e726">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Cincinnati, to Jacob Burnet
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 August 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:38
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #5363.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay had hoped to meet Burnet in Cincinnati, but Burnet's absence prevented him from doing so. Clay outlines the "dispute which exists between the States of
Kentucky and Virginia" and explains that it will be resolved by "six commissioners, selected from States other than Virginia and Kentucky, which is to meet at the City of Washington on the last Monday of January
next." Clay asks if "it would suit your convenience and inclination to attend, if the State of Kentucky should appoint you" as a commissioner?
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e740">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 August 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:39
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; file draft, endorsed by T.J. Photocopy. Original in Thomas Jefferson Papers. Edgehill-Randolph Papers. #1397, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Jefferson asks Clay to represent him in Kentucky in a lawsuit. The "misfortunes of the late Colo. Wilson Carey [sic] Nicholas" will have a negative effect on both Jefferson and his grandson, Thomas Jefferson
Randolph as they are "bound to the bank of the US. in Richmd." for $20,000. Thomas Deye Owings of Kentucky was indebted to Nicholas for ten thousand pounds and Jefferson asks Clay "to have suit brought on it
immediately in the Federal district court of Kentucky."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e754">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to Jacob Burnet
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 October 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:40
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; docketed. #5363.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Burnet's letter of September 18 and states he is sorry that Burnet is "disinclined to serve as one of the Commissioners." Clay says that Burnet's concern about having formed an opinion on one
of the matters to come before the commission should not prevent him from serving. Clay says that Burnet's opinions "are similar to those which have probably been made upon the minds of all the eminent Citizens of
our Country. And if they are to be considered a valid objection, who shall we be able to prevail upon to serve?" Burnet's "want of acquaintance with the subjects of controversy" likewise should not prevent him
from serving. Since the "Citizens of the States immediately concerned" are prohibited from serving on the commission, citizens of other states must make up the commission. Clay urges Burnet to reconsider and asks
for his reply as soon as possible.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e768">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 October 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:41
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has not received any letters from Leigh since he returned to Richmond. Clay encloses a copy of his "report to the Legislature of the two agreements which we have entered into for our two States" [not
present]. He comments on the recent Kentucky elections and mentions that "little has been said and nothing will be done" concerning the "attack" made against Judge [James] Clarke. Clay asks Leigh to tell [Thomas]
"Ritchie that after having done so much, by the able and ingenious publications in his paper, against the Judiciary, to kindle the spirit which has existed in this quarter, it is a little unkind, on his part, to
treat his deluded followers so roughly as he has recently done."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e782">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Frankfort, to Benj.[amin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 November 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:42
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that the Kentucky General Assembly has "unconditionally ratified the Conventions." He mentions that Jacob Burnet of Cincinnati and Hugh L. White of Tennessee will probably be appointed as
commissioners. Mr. [John] Rowan will probably be appointed Clay's co-counsel. Mr. [George M.] Bibb "declines offering."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e796">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 November 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:43
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay confirms that Jacob Burnet and Hugh L. White were appointed as commissioners. Clay and John Rowan were appointed as agents.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e811">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Fr.[ancis] Johnson, Washington City, to Benjamin W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1822 December 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:44
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Johnson confirms the appointments of Jacob Burnet, Hugh L. White, Clay, and John Rowan.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e825">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:45
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay had "a conversation with the Chief Justice yesterday" and believes that the Supreme Court will not issue its ruling until "it has seen that the Legislature of Virginia will take no step towards an
accommodation of the differences with Kentucky." Clay does not thing the "General Assembly of K.[entucky] would consent to strike out the clause of guarranty." He says that "both you and I ought to be now
satisfied that popular assemblies are not happily organized for the consideration &amp; just decision of those delicate &amp; difficult matters which form the subject of treaties between State and State."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e839">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Philip N. Nicholas, Richmond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:46
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1921-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses "the desired letter for Mr. Ambler" [not present] and states that he "felt at a loss to whom to write at Paris, but concluded that a letter to Mr. [Albert] Gallatin would be of most service."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e853">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Nicholas Biddle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 February 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:47
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed by Biddle; mounted; "JW Hatman Turkey Mill 1822" watermark. #3102.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay received Biddle's two letters dated February 24 and "immediately caused an enquiry to be made for Mr. [Jesse?] Hunt. Hunt "had taken his departure four or five days ago." If Clay had had the transcripts "a
week ago his arrest might have been effected." Clay hopes "no difficulty" will occur with the arrangement made with [John J.] Marshall. Clay will remain in Washington another eight or ten days and plans to make a
short visit to Philadelphia.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e867">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 October 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:48
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; docketed by Leigh. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses a deposition [not present] "to prove the facts you directed to be established in relation to my deceased brother Geo." Clay mentions Henry W. Watkins, Henry Perrin and Samuel Perrin of Virginia in
connection with the lawsuit concerning Clay's father's estate. "A Mr. Chapman of Hanover and Col. N. Wilkinson of Henrico" were his father's executors. Clay asks if the death of Col. Morrison will have any effect
on the "Ejectment." Clay is "greatly obliged" by Leigh's enquiries about his health; after seeing Dr. [John] Adams [of Richmond, Va.], Clay has improved and has "strong hopes" to regain his health completely. He
mentions that he has received a copy of Ephraim May Cunningham's pamphlet Correspondence between the Hon. John Adams ... and the late Wm. Cunningham. Clay states that it "sheds no new light upon the character of
the father or son." It seems likely to Clay that John Quincy Adams will be elected President as the "probabilities appear to me to be greatly in his favor." Clay notes that Genl. [Andrew] Jackson has been elected
to the Senate. Clay understands "that the General has altered essentially his course of personal conduct; and has become extremely gentle, affable &amp; conciliatory" and asks what Leigh would "think of receiving
from him a sincere and cordial shake of the hand?"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e881">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Nicholas Biddle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1823 December 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:49
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; docketed by Biddle, date received Dec. 8, 1823. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is indebted to "the Bank [of the United States] at the Lexington office" and has been "struggling to obtain the means to liquidate the whole debt." Clay was owed $10,000 by the Bank of Kentucky, which
offered him "my choice of notes out of its bill box in Lexington." Clay selected notes and turned them over to Mr. [James] Harper "to be offered to your Board at Lexington as
<emph render="underline">collateral security
</emph> only." Harper informed Clay "that the measure adopted by the Bank of K. has produced considerable excitement with the makers of the notes." Clay asks Biddle to "lay the matter before your Board in the hope
that it will make the requisite order to receive the notes." Clay includes a list of the notes he wishes to assign to the Bank of the United States [not present].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e898">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Robert R. Henry, Albany, New York
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 January 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:50
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. Endorsed by Henry. #3472.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Henry's letter "in relation to certain alleged malpractices of officers of Government." Clay replies that "if they exist in the degree and extent to which you suppose they ought to be
seriously investigated and the proper remedy applied." He "can only present to the House over which I have the honor to preside any petition which shall be respectfully couched, and transmitted to me for
presentation."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e912">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond, Virginia.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 July 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:51
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. Endorsed by Leigh. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Leigh for "communicating the very satisfactory result of the action for Euphraim" and asks Leigh to have Mr. [Garland] Tinsley or Col. [Lawson] Burfoot to arrange "to rent out the property for this
year." Clay then discusses the "occupying claimant laws" in some detail and concludes with greetings to Mrs. Leigh and Mrs. [John] Wickham.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e926">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond, Virginia.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1824 December 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:52
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; docketed by [Leigh?] on blank leaf, now detached. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Leigh's request "to know the state of Kentucky politics." Clay is "sorry to be obliged to tell you that I derive very little satisfaction from the contemplation of them." Clay briefly discusses
the Relief and Anti-Relief parties and the possible abolition of the Kentucky Court of Appeals. He encloses a check for $50 for prosecution of his suit regarding Euphraim.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e940">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Littleton Dennis Teackle, Annapolis, Maryland
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 January 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:53
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2388.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay responds to the "bill" Teackle sent him [not present] and does not think the "project it proposes" will succeed. Clay states that the "emission of paper, founded upon any other basis than that of specie
cannot...under any conceivable circumstances, be attended with success." He notes that "[o]ur paper bank in Kentucky [Bank of the Commonwealth] has so far disappointed the hopes of the public that every body is
tired of it and desirous to get back, as soon as we can, to a specie circulation."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e954">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Strong
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 March 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:54
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; printed biography of Clay from unidentified source laid down on address leaf. #2933-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay tells Strong "in confidence" that since Mr. Clinton has declined to accept the "English Mission," it has been offered to Mr. R.[ufus] King. Clay states that King's "weight of character, the estimate in
which he is held both here and in England, his residence, and the place of his nativity, so deeply concerned in fixing our N.E. boundary" will be "sufficient considerations for his appointment." Clay has directed
a copy of his [March 26, 1825] address to his constituents to be sent to Strong.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e969">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to General [Joseph Vance]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 April 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:55
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; mounted on board. #4602-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Vance for his recent letter and states that the "information which it communicates is very gratifying." Vance's friend Josiah Baldwin "has been provided for as you wished." Clay says that he does
"not find my new office a bed of roses. I work from 12 to 14 hours per day."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e983">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal document, signed by Henry Clay as Secretary of State
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 April 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:56
</container>
            <physdesc>DS, 1 p.; partially printed. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Document asserting that Richard Peters is and was "a Judge of the United States for the District of Pennsylvania" and that R.C. Weightman, a witness for Robert S. Garnett and Olympia Garnett is and was the
mayor of Washington, D.C.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e997">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Wheeling, to James Barbour, Washington
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 May 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:57
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-144.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay will, in one hour, "be on a steam boat for Kentucky." He was "received with enthusiasm on this side of the mountains," and "every species of kind and considerate attention have manifested the good feelings
which prevail respecting" him. He mentions that Lafayette was "at Lexington on the 16th" and "is expected here in four or five days. The steamboat, on which he ascended the Ohio, sank below Louisville in the
night, to the great personal hazard of the passengers, but without any loss of life." Clay asks Barbour to "make my respectful compliments to the President and our Colleagues."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1011">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Matthew Carey, Philadelphia
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 June 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:58
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed by Carey; postmarked Lexington Jun. 7. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Carey's letter containing "the Copies of your papers containing an examination of the later British doctrines as have been unfolded by Mr. [William] Huskisson, in their new policy." Clay has
"put your valuable papers in a course of distribution."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1025">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to J[ohn] E. Hall
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1825 September 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:59
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. With engraving of Clay from unidentified source mounted beneath his signature. #5825.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Hall for his letter informing Clay of Hall's intent to "to continue the life of Lafayette, began [sic] by Mr. Waln." Clay does not wish to make any changes to his address of December 10, 1824, which
Hall wishes to include in the book.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1039">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 May 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:60
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay "shall send you in a few days, a long instruction on the subject of our claims" against France. Approximately one-half of the letter consists of instructions to Brown. "On American politics" Clay is
confident that Mr. [John Quincy] Adams will be re-elected and "that we shall have a most embittered contest, uncomfortable in all respects; and that the struggle in Kentucky will be hot and sharp." Clay mentions
"[o]ur affair at Rio Janiero [sic]" and says it is "not likely to lead to any serious consequences." He mentions that the Clays are more comfortable by their "removal to Decatur's house." He encloses two volumes
of his speeches, one for Brown and one to be "neatly bound and presented in my name to Genl. La Fayette." His daughter Anne is unable to spend the summer since she is "in a family way."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1053">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Lexington, to Col. G[eorge] Thompson, Pleasantfield, Mercer [County, Ky.]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 July 13;
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize.
</physloc>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #7100.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay returns Mr. [Claiborne W.?] Gooch's letter [not present] and states that it has "several errors respecting me." Clay states that he did not refuse to serve in "Mr. [James] Monroe's Cabinet, because Mr.
[John Quincy] Adams was a member of it."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1067">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to H[ezekiah] Niles
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 November 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:61
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2933-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Niles' letter with "Copies of the Address in behalf of the Harrisburg Convention" and has no doubt he will "find in it an able exposition of facts and views in support of the American System."
Clay mentions Mr. Markeley and Mr. Buchanan.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1081">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. S[tephen] Decatur (Susan Wheeler)
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1827 November 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:62
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1087.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Mrs. Decatur for her letter and urges her to attend a "diplomatic dinner on friday next." She "would promote greatly the happiness" of her friends and herself "by occasionally mixing in our
circles."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1095">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 May 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:63
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay expresses concern over the accounts of "Mrs. Brown's health." Clay re-states his opinion that "Mr. Adams will be re-elected"; his opinion "excludes for our calculation Pennsa. Virginia and the other
Southern States, which I think cannot be relied on for Mr. Adams, although there are hopes of the two States mentioned and North Carolina." Clay mentions money owed to Brown, the Louisiana treaty with France and
treaties with "Prussia and the Hanse towns." Clay states that there "is no present danger of any rupture with G. Britain about our N. Eastern boundary. It is to be arbitrated." He concludes by asking Brown to
purchase gloves for Mrs. Clay.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1109">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 May 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:64
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. Imperfect; large portions of text wanting; silked.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>#38-144.Letter of appointment as ambassador to the United Kingdom.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1124">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 May 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:65
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; portion of text and address leaf torn away; docketed by Barbour. #38-144.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces Mr. Gerard H. Coster of New York, who will be traveling to Europe "for the purpose of amusement and instruction."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1138">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 June 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:66
</container>
            <physdesc>DS, 1 p. Printed. #2908.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Printed circular, transmitting 110 copies "of the Laws of the last session of Congress" to the Governor of Mississippi.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1152">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Cuckooville, to Murray Morris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 September 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:67
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #38-79.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay had intended to visit Morris on his "return from the Springs to Washington," but "had some how confounded your residence and Louisa Courthouse, which I supposed were situated within a short distance of
each other." Clay asks Murray to visit him in Washington and asks if he was "serious about purchasing my grey horses."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1166">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Madison
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 October 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:68
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; negative photostat. #2933-e.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay has heard "through a respected channel" that "it would conduce greatly to the comfort of Mrs. Randolph [Martha Jefferson Randolph], the daughter of Mr.
Jefferson, if her son in law, Mr. Trist [Nicholas P. Trist] were appointed to some Clerkship in one of the Departments here." Clay can provide a position for Trist if he were assured that "Mr. Trist possesses the
requisite qualifications."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1180">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 October 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:69
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS. 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #911.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on the health of Mrs. Brown and hopes that "her judicious retirement to the delightful gardens of Versailles may restore her health." He comments at length on the presidential election. Elections
in Maryland and Delaware have just closed, and the election in Kentucky was close. Still, Clay believes Adams will carry Kentucky and "he should also received 20 votes in N. York." He mentions that "the violence
in the South is pretty much limited to So. Carolina &amp; Georgia. It derives no countenance and will obtain no support in Virginia, which is rapidly becoming a Tariff state." Clay authorizes Brown to compensate
"Mr. B." [W. Armand Barnet] "who acted as Secretary." He mentions that the "King of the Netherlands has been selected" to arbitrate the border dispute between the United States and Great Britain. He closes by
stating that the "country is generally prosperous. Kentucky is becoming quite so. Virginia and some of the Southern States are exceptions."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1194">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. J.[ames] M. Morris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 October 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:70
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-79.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Morris's "manager arrived this morning and is preparing to start with the horses." Clay describes the horses as a "most serviceable pair." He invites Morris and his wife to visit in Washington and jokingly
addresses Morris's concerns that "Mrs. M. may be infected by political heresies."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1208">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nicholas P. Trist, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 [November 29]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:71
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 4 pp.; docketed "Dec. 1828." #1727.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Trist understands that Clay may have an incorrect understanding of his recent connection with the pro-Jackson Charlottesville, Va. Virginia Advocate. In a lengthy statement, Trist attempts to correct the
misunderstanding and notes that he had reluctantly accepted a position as editor mainly because of the salary involved.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1222">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1828 December 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:72
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; silked. #38-144.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay tells Barbour that "General Jackson is elected by a majority of more than two thirds of the Electors. We were beaten in all the doubtful States, without exception... The President has borne his reverse
with much philosophic composure and our friends, generally, are less affected than I feared they would be." Clay mentions that there is "vague speculation as to the intentions of the President elect. His own
friends even do not appear to know what they are." He says that the current session of Congress has been very quiet and the "Jackson party will probably remain quiet for the present." He mentions the Senate's
delay in confirming Mr. Hughs as ambassador to the Netherlands and Mr. [John Jordan] Crittenden to the Supreme Court. Clay closes by saying he will "return to Kentucky upon the close of the present administration,
and whether I shall take any part in public affairs hereafter, I shall then decide."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1236">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to "My dear friend"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 January 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:73
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3888.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay proposes a visit "if I thought you would receive me."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1250">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. J.[ames] M. Morris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 January 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:74
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #39-79.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Morris for the gift of "a dozen bacon hams" and states they "fully sustained the antient and renowned character of Virginia hams." He closes by expressing Mrs. Clay's desire to have the directions
used for preparing the hams.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1264">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas Law
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 May 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:75
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. #2801.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay discusses a land title case in Kentucky and refers Law to Mr. [George W.] Bibb. Clay then talks about the "picture of public affairs at Washington." He states that the "smoak of the cannon, fired in
exultation of the Election of President Jackson, has hardly yet vanished. Mortification and pride prevent many from expressing their regrets and disappointments, on account of their having supported him." Clay
states "many have taken the first step towards weaning themselves from their infuriated attachment, and returning to common Sense." He concludes that Law has done well to retire from Washington "to enjoy the
tranquil scenes of rural life, in spite of all the wickedness, violence, and hypocrisy which at present disgrace the Metropolis."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1279">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 November 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:76
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 25. #4475.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on Conover's idea of starting a new newspaper in Cincinnati. Clay points out that no newspaper can "permanently succeed which does not abstain from any violation of public decorum in its
discussions, make truth its guide, and avoid personality" and that no place "in the Western Country is so important for diffusing intelligence to the people as Cincinnati." Clay says he will subscribe to Conover's
newspaper but cannot invest in it. He hopes there will be no "competition or collision" between Conover and Charles Hammond.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1293">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to E.C. Berry
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1829 November 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:77
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #2933-c.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes to Berry, Auditor of Public Accounts, Vandalia, Illinois, to confirm that his "lands in your State have been placed in a situation free from danger of being sold for taxes." He asks if his
arrangement to pay land taxes from a previous overpayment is still in effect.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1307">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 May 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:78
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on Conover's newspaper and states that although it "has not been patronized to the extent you expected" in Kentucky, when the paper is more generally known, Conover will not be disappointed. Clay
mentions the possibility of a "Northern trip" but has rejected the idea lest his motive be questioned. He states that the "information which reaches me from all quarters but especially from Washington City, as to
my future prospects, is in a high degree encouraging." He does not know what "effect will be produced by the recent movements at Harrisburg and Albany" but says that "those movements are mere stratagems of Mr. V.
Buren" [Martin Van Buren]. Clay goes on to discuss Van Buren's "notorious embicility and incompetency, as well as his maladministration." Clay mentions Judge John McLean. He concludes by discussing the recent
Jefferson Day dinner in Washington, which "indicates the course of attack on the Tariff and Internal Improvements."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1321">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 May 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:79
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Conover for his letter and says that while he has "entertained thoughts of a Northern trip," he is now "disinclined" to make such a trip.  He says that the "information which reaches me from all quarters ... as to my future prospects, is in a high degree encouraging." Clay mentions Martin Van Buren's "strategems" against John C. Calhoun. Clay states that he has never wronged Judge John McLean and, along with other friends of John Quincy Adams, regrets the Judge's "course during the late Admin." He discusses the tariff and internal improvements and says "it is fortunate that we now know the plan of the Campaign of our opponents, and we ought now to prepare ours to defeat it." Clay states, possibly in reference to the Maysville veto, that "the sacrifice of our American System is to propitiate G. Britain as well as the South."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1335">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to George W. Featherstonhaugh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 May 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:80
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 24. #2933-d.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Featherstonhaugh for his letter and mentions that he spent "some very pleasant days" in New Orleans with Stephen Van Rensselaer. He finds "great benefit as well as amusement in my agricultural
pursuits" and "shall be ready very soon to renounce for ever the strife and the cares of public life." Clay states that the election of "Genl. Jackson ought to be regarded as an exception from the general good
sense with which the American people have conducted their affairs." Clay concludes by sending "warmest regards and my best wishes for his happiness and prosperity" to Baron Paul de Krudener.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1349">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John C. Wright
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 May 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:81
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jun.1. #5903.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on Wright's plan to run for the House of Representatives from Ohio and says that "it would be very gratifying to friends of our cause." Clay states that the "general results of the present Session
of Congress are highly favorable to our cause." He mentions Samuel A. Foot and John Holmes. There is a brief discussion of the tariff and Clay concludes by speculating on whether or not the "President has approved
the Maysville [Road] appropriation."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1363">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 June 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:82
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay suggests that the Constitution be amended to allow "a bare majority of all the Members elected to each house of Congress, instead of two thirds of a quorum...to pass a bill returned by the President." He
also discusses "the Indian bill" which he says "threatens to bring a foul and lasting stain upon the good faith, humanity and character of the nation." He concludes by asking Conover to consult with Charles
Hammond and Isaiah Thomas.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1377">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 August 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:83
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug. 18. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has sent to William Greene "a Sketch of my Speech delivered at Cincinnati" and refers Conover to Daniel Drake concerning its possible publication. Clay concludes by saying the "news from Indiana, Illinois
and, Missouri...is highly encouraging."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1391">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 October 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:84
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf and Clay's seal; postmarked Lexington. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay expresses "lively interest" in the success of the Cincinnati American. He says that the Kentucky Convention will be held on December 9th in Frankfort. Clay suggests that Conover prepare a "subscription
paper" to be circulated at the Convention. Clay comments on the Ohio and Pennsylvania elections and closes with the question "Who is your Senator?"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1405">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830 December 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:85
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 14. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand following salutation. Clay refers to Lawrence's letter of the 2nd and says that he does not disapprove of the measures Lawrence referred to. Rather, he is "perfectly persuaded that
without some such defeat awaits us in N. York at least in 1832." He mentions that the Kentucky Convention met and the proceedings "were marked by harmony and vigor." Barton [?] was not put forward as a candidate
and the Benton candidate was defeated. The legislature has not elected a Senator because "some half dozen of our friends have persuaded themselves or been persuaded by others that they are pledged, on the
particular question of a Senator to work for one of the Jackson party." Clay closes by saying he is leaving for New Orleans on "private affairs exclusively."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1419">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, New Orleans, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 March 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:86
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked New Orleans, Mar.7. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay states that he believes "we shall be able to rescue the Government from the dangers which are impending over it." He considers "the election of any
particular individual to the Chief Magistracy so perfectly a consideration of secondary and subordinate consequence, compared to the great and patriotic object of preserving all that is valuable in our
institutions that I am entirely ready to surrender my pretensions, whatever they may be, to any one who can unite our friends and hold out a more encouraging prospect of success." He closes saying he will leave
New Orleans "in the course of the week" and regrets that he feels unable to make a campaign visit to New York.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1434">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John L. Lawrence, New York, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 March 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:87
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; with attached address leaf. #6683.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Lawrence writes in response to Clay's letter of March 7 and says in regard to "your frank declaration of willingness to yield your own pretensions in favor of others, I must be equally frank in Saying, that to
your numerous friends, here Such an avowal, publickly made, would not be acceptable." He goes on to say that "our friends look with great anxiety to the next election in your State" and that there are some
"expectations of a Jackson triumph in that quarter." Lawrence closes by discussing "an attack" against Robert W. Wickliffe in relation to his affairs with Robert Scott.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1448">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 April 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:88
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay reports that he arrived in Lexington from New Orleans on April 6 and comments on the weather and the health of family members. He has learned from Mr. Senator [Josiah S.] Johnson that "Mr. Calhoun will be
a candidate for the Presidency, and that he will probably obtain the vote of S. Carolina, No. Carolina and Virginia." Clay has "not yet seen evidence sufficient to convince me of its correctness."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1462">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jabez D. Hammond
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 April 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:89
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Apr.15. #2529.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses letters of introduction [not present]. He says that he regrets to learn of the "impracticability of Union among opponents of the Administration in New York. On that union I am well assured depends
the vote of the State." He concludes by commenting on Andrew Jackson's declining support and says should "Mr. Calhoun be a Candidate it will prejudice the General."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1476">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 April 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:90
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Apr. 15. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Lawrence's letter of March 29. Clay says that his willingness to retire from the Presidential race "was dictated by a thorough conviction of the evils brought and likely to be brought upon the
Nation" by Jackson's "misrule; and an anxious desire to avert them from my Country. It was not dictated by any unwillingness on my part to encounter the perils of a canvass, nor fears as to its successful
termination." He also says that his offer to step aside was not "prompted by any belief of my own that another's name could be advantageously substituted to mine." He closes with a postscript, asking Lawrence to
share this letter with M.[atthew] L. Davis.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1490">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John Agg
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 May 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:91
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. #1761.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay explains that Agg's recent letter was delayed. He comments on the upcoming elections and says that "whether we regard the goodness of the American System, or the present flattering prospects of its final
triumph, by the overthrow of the existing feeble corrupt and incompetent Administration, the friends of that system have every motive for renewed and energetic assertion. He is sorry to hear of the financial
difficulties of the Washington
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Daily National
</title> newspaper since "it has been decidedly the leading paper in supporting the principles of the Opposition." Clay concludes by stating that there is "every reason to count upon a most signal triumph at out
approaching Elections in August."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1507">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to H.[ezekiah] Niles
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 June 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:92
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay responds to Niles's proposal to move the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Niles' Register
</title> from Baltimore to New York. He says the move would be favorable and its "means of information and circulation would be greatly multiplied." In closing, Clay mentions the illness of Abraham H. Schenck and
sends condolences to his brother Peter H. Schenck.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1524">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Richard Smith
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 June 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:93
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jun.31. #10751.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Smith's letter in which a check for $121.51 was enclosed [not present]. Clay mentions a claim to dower and says that since he knows nothing of the "doweress" he "cannot judge the terms of a
compromise."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1538">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Capt. John Meany
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 June 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:94
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is unwilling "to hazard any conjecture" about the approaching elections but "will say that we shall be more than ever mortified if our friends do not return a large majority to the Legislature and to
Congress."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1552">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 August 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:95
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; with text on attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.5. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes extensively about the "Antimasonic excitement," which he says "is likely to be troublesome." He has determined "not to mix myself in that controversy" and will not "make some declaration adverse to
Masonry" as he has been urged to do. He "cannot admit the propriety of blending either Masonry or Anti Masonry with Federal Politics. What has the General Govt. to do with either? What part of the Constitution
authorizes it to discountenance either? It has no more power to put down either than it has to interfere with any of the literary, benevolent or religious associations of the Country." Clay states that he does
"not think we ought to be diverted by Anti Masonry" in the attempt to oust the Jackson administration. He closes by mentioning Charles Hammond and discussing the Baltimore Convention.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1566">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 August 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:96
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Brown's letter of July 29th, which reached him "during my absence at the Olympian Springs." He comments on Mrs. Clay's health, the health of Brown's niece, and Brown's health. Clay thinks
Brown's "advice, in respect to public life is good," and that if he "could devise a proper and honorable mode, of withdrawing my name from public notice, I would instantly do it." Clay reports that the recent
elections in Kentucky resulted "in a majority for the Jackson party in Congress, and a majority to the opposition in the Legislature-a drawn battle." Clay mentions that he is planning to place his "son James in
some Counting House at Philadelphia" and asks if Brown can assist him with any of his "mercantile acquaintances." He closes by stating that his "crops are fine, especially our great Staple, Corn. I am pleased with
the occupation, and the prospect of the profits of farming; but Mrs. Clay's repugnance to the cares of a Country life may induce us, possibly, to go to town."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1580">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 August 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:97
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; with separate address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.28. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay acknowledges that "several of my prominent friends at Cincinnati were extremely discouraged by the issue of our Congressional elections, and were entertaining the project of substituting some other name to
mine, as a Candidate for the Presidency." Clay states that he "should most cordially agree to such an arrangement, and even urge it, if such a substitute can be found with the approbation of our friends
generally." He discusses the strengths needed by a candidate and says that "I am not an impartial if competent person to make this enquiry." He comments on the suggestion of John Marshall as a candidate and says
he would be "delighted" to see Marshall as President instead of Jackson. He concludes that the party would be well served by waiting to see how events develop and says "we should not despair, certainly not of the
Republic, if we do of our Candidate."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1595">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 October 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:98
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Oct.12. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on the "Anti Masonic nomination" of William Wirt which "has excited as much surprise at Lexington and with me as it has done at Cincinnati." Clay quotes from a letter from Josiah S. Johnston about
the "Anti Masonic Convention" in Philadelphia, at which Wirt was nominated. Clay states that the National Republican Party should forbear "to attach Anti Masonry or Mr. Wirt" because the convention "may think it
is politic to nominate him" and "it is prudent to the leave the door open to his party and him to unite with us."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1609">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 November 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:99
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Nov. 18, amended to Nov. 19. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says that he accepted a Senate seat only "from a sense of public duty and in conformity with the almost unanimous wishes of my friends. I go to my post however with not anticipations of pleasure from
occupying it." Clay concludes by saying that if William Wirt and "Jackson should be the only Candidates, there will, I believe be concentration, but it will be on Jackson."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1623">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1831 December 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:100
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay expresses regret for Brown's injuries and recommends postponement of his trip to New Orleans. Clay states that John Sergeant's nomination by the National Republican Party for Vice President "is thought
here to have been the best that could have been made." Clay has seen John C. Calhoun "several times, but have had no political conversation with him." Clay does not believe Calhoun will be a candidate for the
Presidency. If Andrew Jackson approves a bill to recharter the Bank of the United States, Clay says "it has been suggested that [Littleton W.] Tazewell will be brought out as the Southern Candidate for President."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1637">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Herring
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 January 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:101
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #6273.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>In response to Herring's inquiry, Clay states that "one of the best portraits of me" was made by the late Matthew Harris Jouett of Kentucky; Clay believes the portrait is "somewhere in the City of N. York" and
formerly in the possession of Joseph Delaplaine. Clay has no portrait of himself in Washington which he can send to Herring.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1651">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Christian Hager, Woodford County, Versailles, Ky. to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 March 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:102
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #8557.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Hager asks Clay to see General [Walter] Jones and make some inquiry of him" concerning a lawsuit to be argued before the Court of Chancery next June. Hager states that "I hope you will be our next President it
appears to me that Jacksons friends are many of them geting more Cooler what the[y] have been." Hager asks Clay to write about the status of the lawsuit and concludes with a postscript mentioning the unusually
cold weather.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1665">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 March 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:103
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.29; with two receipts (each 1 p.) dated 1831 April 8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on Brown's health and tells him he is wise to abandon his trip to New Orleans. Clay reports that James Erwin was robbed in New Orleans of promissory notes worth $20,000. He concludes by declining
an invitation to visit Philadelphia saying "whenever I go from my abode, I become a State prisoner, and I love liberty in name but more in fact."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1679">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Gen. W.[alter] Jones
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 April 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:104
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf. #8557.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Jones for his note and the "excellent cheese" from Mr. Palmer. Clay encloses a letter from Mr. Hager [see 1832 March 17, above] and asks Jones for any information which Clay will then communicate to
Hager.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1693">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Brantz Mayer
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 June 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:105
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jun.17. #4990.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Mayer's request for information to compile a biography of Daniel Boone. Clay "never personally knew Boone. When in 1797 I migrated to Kentucky, he had gone further West." Clay suggests that
Mayer obtain the series of articles on the early history of Kentucky by John Bradford published in the Lexington
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Kentucky Gazette.
</title> He also mentions Gilbert Imlay's
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">A topographical description of the western territory of North America
</title> and Humphrey Marshall's
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">The history of Kentucky.
</title> "Neither of them is well written. The first is rare, and I really do not know where it can be procured. Imlay also wrote a bad novel, the title of which I do not recollect. Marshall's history may be
easily obtained in K. possibly in some of the Atlantic book stores." Clay suggests that the "best repository of materials for your work is the family of Boone."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1716">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 June 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:106
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jul.3. #4475.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on the formation of an "Electoral ticket" by the "Anti Masonic party" in Ohio. He says there is much confidence that Pennsylvania will not support Jackson. He mentions the Tariff Bill and the Land
Bill in the Senate and closes by saying he thinks Congress will not adjourn before the 16th.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1730">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 September 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:107
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Sep. 6. #5828.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on the defeat of Richard A. Buckner which he says "was very mortifying" as it "resulted entirely from religious prejudices." He states that the "other elections terminated very favorably" and the
National Republicans have a majority in both houses of the Kentucky legislature. Clay comments on elections in Ohio, Indiana, Louisiana, Missouri and New York.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1744">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 September 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:108
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with separate address leaf; docketed. #4475-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay extends regrets for Conover's "private affliction" and mentions the death of his mother-in-law, Susannah Gray Hart. He says that the "defeat of our Governor [Richard A. Buckner] was mortifying" but the
other results of the election were gratifying. Clay comments on the division between the Anti Masons and National Republicans in Ohio. He continues to believe "that Jackson will be defeated" and regrets the
"perseverance" of Judge John McLean in continuing to hope that he would be selected as a Presidential candidate.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1759">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Robert S. Rose
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 September 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:109
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1761.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Rose for his letter of recommendation for General Holsteen but regrets he does "not know of any place in this quarter, at present, which would be acceptable to him." Clay mentions that the
University of Kentucky "has been laboring under difficulties from the loss by fire of the principal building." Clay mentions that he "had an opportunity of passing a short time in Virginia with Mr. [James] Madison
and Govr. [James] Barbour. Mr. Madison is feeble in health but his mind and memory are perfectly sound." Clay concludes by saying he is glad to hear that New York is withdrawing support from Andrew Jackson.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1773">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Daniel Webster to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 October 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:109A
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #6078-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
Webster says that the early returns from Pennsylvania were encouraging, but the later returns did not sustain the first impression.  Webster says they were "thrown badly back by Ohio." But for that, Webster would "have had strong hopes of Maine &amp; some hopes of N. Hamp." He believes that "the anti-Jackson ticket" will prevail in New York.  Webster asks for news of Missouri and closes with regards to Mrs. Clay.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1787">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 October 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:110
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on a case Brown is appealing to the U.S. Supreme Court and promises to "take care of the case there for you." He mentions that his son Henry has married Julia Prather of Louisville. Clay attended
the wedding and returned "slightly indisposed with an ordinary complaint." Because cholera has broken out in Louisville, Clay says "you may probably hear that I caught the pestilence, and have been long since dead
and buried. You are authorized to contradict, most positively, such a report if you should hear it." Clay mentions the illness of Anne Clay Erwin's youngest child. He mentions the Kentucky elections and hopes that
"the State will on friday week choose Anti Jackson Electors." Clay closes by suggesting that Brown abandon his plans for a trip to New Orleans "considering the prevalence of the Yellow fever there, with the
prospect of its being followed by the Cholera."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1801">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John J. Crittenden
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1832 November 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:111
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments that Crittenden's "views, in regard to your wishes on the subject of a service in the Senate, correspond with your character." Clay had planned to depart for Washington around Christmas "but the
dread of a winters journey and the present good prospects of weather have induced me to proceed immediately."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1815">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to John L. Gilliland
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 January 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:112
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Jan.16. #4602.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Gilliland for the "box containing the Specimens of your pressed glass ware. He tells Gilliland that the policy of tariff protection is "now in imminent danger," and that "the people alone can now
save it." He concludes by saying he does not believe the recent election demonstrated popular opposition to public policy.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1829">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. Morris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 March 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:113
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.4. #38-79.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks [James Maury] Morris if he wishes to sell his lot on Poydras Street in New Orleans and, if so, at what price.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1843">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Augustus E. Cohen
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 March 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:114
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.7. #1761.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Cohen's letter and discusses the Compromise Tariff bill. He concludes by saying he does "not regard myself as a regular practitioner of the Law" and therefore, would not be able to have Cohen
study under him.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1857">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.[ichard] H.[enry] Wilde
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 April 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:115
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand following salutation. Clay discusses the Compromise Tariff bill and says that a "large section of the Jackson party, headed by Mr. V. Buren, will attempt either to impress the
North with the belief that its interest were injuriously affected...or the South with the opinion that its interests were not sufficiently attended to." He then tells Wilde that "the danger you apprehend from a
surplus Revenue will not be realized." Clay says that "passage of the Land Bill would have afforded further security, and I think most desirable security, against the extraordinary inconvenience of a superabundant
exchequer." Clay will introduce a new land bill in the next session of Congress. Clay states that the "prospects of a renewal of the Charter of the U. States bank have decidedly improved" and he does "not despair
of its being accomplished." Clay concludes by discussing the possibility of the emancipation of slaves in the British West Indies and says that the "danger is perhaps not sufficiently near or great to justify any
interference from us." He says that slavery "lies at the bottom of many of the evils under which the Southern Atlantic States are suffering" and though Wilde has Constitutional grounds to protest "against the
slightest interference of the Genl. Government with the institution of Slavery or the condition of its unfortunate subjects, it is perfectly manifest, I think, that you will have soon to alter materially the
character of their labor. You will either have to find new products for it, or new markets for its present products."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1871">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Morris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 May 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:116
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 21. #2483-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay will tell his friends of Morris' determination to sell his New Orleans lots at auction. In the lengthy postscript, Clay says that if "others have found pleasure in contemplating the political condition of
our Country, for the last few years, it is more than you and I have."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1885">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 July 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:117
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Jul.8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay mentions that a "few stragling cases of Cholera" continue in Lexington and that several families have lost slaves to the disease. Clay's son and daughter-in-law are expecting a child this month. The
possibility of the emancipation of slaves in the British West Indies "will exert a moral influence on that institution in the U. States; but I do not apprehend any immediate effects from it" and does not believe
emancipation will happen in the United States "in our time." Clay predicts that Southern slave owners will be "more sensitive to the slightest disturbance of the question." Northerners are "probably interested in
the continuance of Southern slavery."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1899">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 September 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:118
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has heard from Dr. Nathaniel Chapman of Brown's "severe attack" but hopes his health is better now. He and Mrs. Clay will leave Lexington and "proceed directly to you in Philadelphia" as soon as Anne Clay
Erwin "is confined, which is expected in eight or ten days."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1914">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Baltimore, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 October 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:119
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Oct. 8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay will be joined in Baltimore by Mrs. Clay, John Morrison Clay and Henry C. Duralde "the day after tomorrow." Clay is glad to hear that Brown's health is "almost entirely re-established." Clay concludes by
announcing that his daughter "was delivered of a Son on the morning of the 2d. inst."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1928">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to S.[amuel] Fleet
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 December 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:120
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Dec.5. #2933-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Fleet for sending him "specimens of Sisal Hemp" and adds "they look well, but I am not sufficiently acquainted with its properties, culture or produce to determine whether it could be advantageously
introduced into our agriculture." Clay compliments Fleet on his editorship of the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New York Farmer,
</title> regrets that he is too busy to write for Fleet and asks how he can pay for a subscription.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1945">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 December 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:121
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Dec.11. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is anxious to hear from Brown. The Clays have "taken a small furnished house in the rear of Gadsby's." Clay says there is an apparent majority in the House of Representatives for and in the Senate against
the Jackson administration.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1959">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1833 December 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">1:122
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-114.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay "met with Judge Bullard" of Louisiana and "had a conversation with him about your Florida slaves." Bullard "says that unless there is an unusual proportion of very young and old among them, they are worth
$500 each; that the blacksmith if a tolerably good one and not old, is worth $1500-the rough carpenter $1200, women $500 each. Bullard will offer $20,000 for the slaves. Clay says Bullard would be glad to reach an
arrangement with Barbour, "putting in 1250 acres of first rate Red River land at valuation (he has been offered $10 per acre) and the slaves at valuation, and working the whole together." Bullard says such an
arrangement would produce 300 bales of cotton per year. Clay says that though cotton "has fallen to thirteen cents" he believes Barbour can count on $500 apiece for the slaves.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1973">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to George Watterson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 May 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:1
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay acknowledges Watterson's election as an honorary member of the Columbian Horticultural Society of the District of Columbia.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e1987">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to John S. Wellford, John Coalter, John Tayloe Lomax
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 May 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay declines an invitation to attend the "Whig Celebration" in Fredericksburg, Va. Considerations of public duty have compelled him also to decline an invitation to a similar function in Alexandria, Va.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2001">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[ellamy] Storer
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 August 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Aug.26. #2148.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is eager to hear the election results from Ohio. He says "the Jackson party has been annihilated" in Kentucky. He concludes with a discussion of the charter of the Bank of the United States.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2015">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 August 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:4
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Aug.26. #1395.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks Leigh to "investigate thoroughly at Richmond the subject of Scrip-warrants and come back to the Senate with such information as will enable us...to secure the Government against frauds." Clay says
that the result of "our recent Elections " in Kentucky "put us at ease" and says that Whigs in Indiana, Illinois and Missouri also did well. Clay then asks if "any thing can be more stupid than the course of Duff
Green?" Clay says he is convinced Green's true purpose is "to affect the election of Mr. V. Buren." Clay closes with a comment on the precarious nature of his wife's health.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, to Hamilton Smith 
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 September 6 
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:4
            </container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington [Sep.?] 9; docketed; Barrow. #5421.
            </physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Smith's query "regarding my opinion whether the manufacturing business, and especially that of cottn may be expected to revive." 
              Clay say that much depends on "certain great elections at hand in Penna [Pennsylvania] and elsewhere."  If these elections are favorable to the 
              current administration, Clay says "we may expect for some time to come a continuance of the derangement of the currency, exchange, etc. with all train 
              of consequences."   
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2029">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1834 October 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:5
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks for the address of Mr. Johnson for a neighbor who wishes to write to him. Clay states that "Ohio has acquitted herself nobly. [James] Findlay is supposed to be elected by several thousand, and four or
five Jackson members of the H. of R. have been made to yield their places to Whigs."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2043">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Senate Chamber, to H.[enry] Shaw
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 February 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:6
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; with ALS, H.W. Shaw, New York, to Dear Baldwin, 1875 June 15. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay expresses confidence in Shaw's "continued friendship." He adds that he regrets "extremely to hear of the distractions which you describe as prevailing among the Whigs in Massachusetts &amp; sincerely hope
that they may be finally brought to harmonize together." The letter from Shaw (written below Clay's letter) to Baldwin transmits the letter as a gift for his "extensive and valuable collection of autograph
letters."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2057">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. Mayard C. Meade
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1835 December 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:7
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1769.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received Mrs. Meade's letter with the papers she sent for Judge Parker. He has given the papers to Parker who will review them after which "he will present them to the Senate, and move their reference
to a Committee. We have talked of that on Foreign Relations."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>[Henry Clay] to John Wickham
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 January 23
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:7a
            </container>
            <physdesc>AN, 1 p.; signature excised. #15753.
            </physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces Mr. Bainbridge of Kentucky.
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2072">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to John Harvie
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:8
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2196.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces Richard D. Cutts, "the son of a particular friend of mine, and the nephew of Mrs. Madison and Mrs. Todd."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2086">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Senate Chamber, to A.[lfred] Beckley
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 May 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:9
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington May 10. #10012.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says that he will "be happy to furnish you with any Durham Cattle, or other stock in my possession which you may want." He suggests Beckley come to Ashland and select the stock himself. Clay closes by
saying that he has "been a long time in public life, and think I may shortly retire without being liable to any reproach for leaving it."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2100">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Conway D. Whittle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1836 August 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:10
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.8. #7973.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay acknowledges Whittle's letter of July 13th and says he would have answered it sooner if he "could have communicated the information you wish to possess." Clay wrote to "Col. Edm. H. Taylor" who is "well
informed in regard to lands and persons situated where your land lies." Col. Taylor's enclosed response [not present] indicates he is not familiar with Whittle's land and Clay suggests that Whittle "open a
correspondence" with Taylor.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2114">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] W. Stow
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 April 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:11
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay comments on Stow's health and sends wishes for "a speedy and effectual recovery." Clay then discusses the institution of slavery and says it "is an institution of which our Country would be most happily
rid of, if it were practicable." "In spite of the delusions of those who are directly interested in its preservation, and of the rash and impolitic interference of those who have no direct interest and no right to
interfere about it, undoubtedly it is fraught with great mischiefs to both races, to say nothing of the injustice which it inflicts upon one of them." Separation of the races, "by first Colonizing the free blacks
and afterwards with the consent of the Slave States, the class of slaves," is the only practical solution. Clay then comments on the country's "Commercial embarrassment" and mentions a reduction in the price of
cotton. "The measures of Government have beyond all doubt contributed largely to produce the present calamitous state of affairs."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2128">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Alexander Hamilton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 May 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:12
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #2583.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Hamilton for the "Caricature" that he sent. Clay will make a statement in Congress about the "present unhappy state of our Country." Mr. [Daniel] Webster and his family left Lexington yesterday
after a week-long visit. Clay concludes with a postscript stating that he has "heard that suspension of Specie payments by the Banks in the West is general, without a single exception."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2142">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.[obert] P.[erkins] Letcher
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 August 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:13
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.7, overwritten as 8. #5039.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay declines Letcher's invitation "to take the excursion to Lancaster" since he is leaving for Washington shortly. He would like to see Letcher at Ashland to let him know "what has been done, and is doing,
about bringing me out as a Candidate." Clay has "given no consent for the use of my name; and shall hesitate much before I do."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2156">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to W.[illiam] O. Niles
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 September 27
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:14
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #3758.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Niles' note and tells him "that not one step is yet taken towards the preparation of the Speech, which I pronounced on Monday."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2170">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to M.[atthew] L. Davis
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1837 October 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:15
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #4925.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Davis for his letter "communicating the arrangements which have been made, in the City of New York, for the approaching Election to the Legislature." Clay would like to know the results. He states
that the "opposition in the West is firm, increasing and unconquerable" and that "Ohio has fulfilled our hopes."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2184">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Saml. I. Peters
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 January 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:16
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay states that "it is not my general habit to acknowledge Pamphlets" that are sent to him but he cannot "deny myself the pleasure of expressing my thanks" for the pamphlet by the Chamber of Commerce of New
Orleans sent by Peters.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2198">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to John Agg
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 May 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:17
</container>
            <physdesc>LS, 1 p.; in an unidentified hand, signed by Clay; ghost of another ALS on verso. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Agg for his note and says that he has "nothing whatever to do" with the "new paper" Agg mentions. Clay says that "our political friends" have long contemplated establishing another paper in
Washington. Clay understands that "Mr. [William D.] Merrick" and "Mr. [Rice] Garland are two of the Committee charged with attending to that business."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2212">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to F.[ortescue] Whittle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 May 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:18
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #7973.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Whittle for his friendly letters. He says that those who "like you and I, have been for a long time deploring the infatuation and delusion which have sustained, so unfortunately, Genl. Jackson in
his reckless course have much reason to rejoice in the prospects of better and brighter times which are opening upon us." Clay hopes to see "our Government once more confided to honest and faithful hands" but
whether he will "be called to the station or not...is a subordinate concern."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2227">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to J.[ohn] M.[iddleton] Clayton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 June 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:19
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; silked. #4948.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Clayton for his letter and says he has "been always proud of the attachment and confidence of your noble State." Clay says that Delaware has exhibited "an encouraging moral spectacle...throughout
all these times of trouble" and that the courage and constancy of Delaware is "worthy of the best days of Greece and Rome." Clay thinks that, "in regard to the next Presidency...[d]ivision is weakness, as Union is
strength." He closes with a comment on the sub-treasury bill, which he hopes will be defeated.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2241">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to M.E. Pointois
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 July 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:20
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces Felix Huston, "Commander of the Texan Armies."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2255">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 August 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:21
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay acknowledges Sargent's letter and says he shares the "feelings excited by the bright and encouraging prospects which have opened on our public affairs." Clay says that they "have not yet overcome all
difficulties; the adversary is in possession of the field." If the elections in New York and Pennsylvania result in Whig success, Clay foresees an end "to the whole controversy." Clay is pleased with Whig
successes in the Kentucky elections but is anxious about the results in Illinois and Missouri.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2269">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to C.C. Baldwin
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 August 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:22
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; negative photostat; location of original unknown. #3417-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay tells Baldwin that in regards to slavery, the tariff and internal improvement, he expressed himself "as fully and as explicitly as language can admit of during the last Session of the Senate of the U.S."
Clay says that the slave states "have
<emph render="underline">exclusive
</emph> power" over the institution; that "Congress has no power touching the institution" and further has "no power to prevent the removal of slaves from one Slave State to another;" and, finally, that Congress
cannot abolish slavery "in the D. of Columbia or in the territories, without a violation of good faith." Clay states that he supports a "bill to distribute among the States the proceeds of the public lands" for
internal improvements. He supports the Bank of the United States "for the benefits of the institution," but is unconcerned about its location. Clay tells Baldwin that he cannot consent to the publication of this
letter. He mentions that the voters of Kentucky have voted down a proposed convention, which was supported "principally by Van Buren men." He tells Baldwin that he is not "a friend to Slavery" and that it is "an
evil." However, Clay believes "it better that Slaves should remain Slaves than be set loose as free men among us." Such Clay says was the belief of "our Revolutionary ancestors." The current defense that "Slavery
is a blessing" is "espoused by the new school in South Carolina." Clay says that if this is true "the more of it the better; and it is immaterial upon that hypothesis, whether the slaves be black or white." Clay
concludes that he is not a candidate for the Presidency and that to speak on the use of the veto by the President would be improper.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2286">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay and Mackenzie Beverly, [Fredericksburg?], to John Minor
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1838 November 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:23
</container>
            <physdesc>L, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Fredericksburg Nov. 20. #3750.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>In Beverly's hand? Beverly and Clay ask Minor to collect the "bond for my smith...take out for fees &amp; forward the amount through the bank." Minor is then asked to provide a pass for Richard "a few days
before xmas" to "come over and see if you can hire him in the next year &amp; have his hire paid quarterly if practical." Richard might require $2.00 "to bring himself home" and Minor is asked to get the amount
from Richard's employer and "see if he is well shod and clothed."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2300">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to G.[eorge] W. Featherstonhaugh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 February 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:24
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf and separate address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Feb. 11.; with typed transcription. #6004.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay assures Featherstonhaugh that he has not said anything to "Mr. [Louis Joseph] Papineau" about British-Canadian relations that he has not said to British officials. Clay said that the United States "would
not interfere, on Canadian account, and never but as a collateral affair, when they might happen to be engaged, on their own proper account, in a contest with G. Britain." Clay says that he is eager "to cultivate
&amp; preserve the most friendly relations" with Great Britain and not to interfere in "the contest between the parent Country &amp; the Colony."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2314">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Horace Greeley
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 February 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:25
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #10751.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay believes that Greeley's proposed pamphlet on the public lands "will be attended with excellent effect." Clay is unable to supply the documents Greeley requested and tells him they have been published in
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Niles' Register.
</title></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2331">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to J.[oseph] R. Ingersoll
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 June 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:26
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Ingersoll for his letter and tells him it "brought me the first authentic intelligence of the Chambersburg Convention." Clay thinks that "Anti-Masonry, however right its votaries may be, can never
become the basis of the politics of this whole Union." Clay expects to leave "next week on an excursion to the Lakes, the Falls of Niagara and Canada, neither of which I have yet seen." He dreads the possibility
of "parade or demonstrations on my account." Clay mentions "Judge Wooley" [Aaron K. Woolley], Horace Binney, John Sergeant, and Josiah Randall.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2345">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 September 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:27
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Leigh for his letter and encloses "two letters from Genl. Harrison" [not present]. Clay says Harrison "counts confidently upon receiving the nomination." Clay then comments extensively on election
prospects in New York, Maryland, Tennessee, and Indiana. Clay says that several of the "new States have rushed prematurely and unwisely" into expensive programs of internal improvements, for which they have had to
borrow funds. The Jackson party, which initially supported the programs "turns round &amp; opposes them, and endeavors to the lay the blame at the door of the Whigs!" Clay closes by asking if any political party
ever existed "which equals it in inconsistency?"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2359">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to William Tompkins
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 October 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:28
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #9521.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay tells Tompkins that he received a letter from "Genl. Harrison" in response to the letter he sent "on my passage through Ohio." Harrison's letter was "written
in the most friendly spirit" and stated that he "had never desired to be thrown into a competition with me, whose election he
<emph render="underline">had
</emph> desired." Harrison's letter "does not say, in terms, that he will abide by the nomination of the Convention, but that is to be inferred from the fervor of the letter." Clay comments on elections in New
York and questions how the "Administration party" has been able to make gains. He says that "the Administration has put its hands, in its desperation, into the public treasury, and taken out hundreds of thousands
of dollars to use in purposes of corruption." Clay says that he fears his prediction that "Jackson ruled by intimidation and V. Buren would by corruption" has come true. Clay comments on the "Staunton Convention"
and hopes it will arouse the people of Virginia "to a due sense of the dangers which encompass them." Clay closes with comments on the elections in Tennessee and voter fraud in Alabama.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2376">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1839 October 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:29
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Oct.26. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Sargent for "communicating the results of the Election in the City and County of Philadelphia. He comments on the elections in Pennsylvania, New York and Massachusetts and says he is "grieved to
witness the divisions among the Whigs." Clay says he would consent to have his name withheld at the "Harrisburg Convention" if doing so would increase the Whig Party's chances of success.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2391">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to John L. Carey
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 January 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:30
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Jan.7. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Carey for sending a copy of the second edition of his pamphlet
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Some thoughts on domestic slavery.
</title> Clay is pleased that Carey also sent copies to "Mr. [Franck] Taylor," a Washington bookseller.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2408">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay and J.J. Crittenden, Washington, to The Honble Secy of War
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 March 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:31
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2290, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay and Crittenden transmit to Joel Roberts Poinsett a letter from the Governor of Kentucky "containing evidence of the application of a quantity of arms belonging to that State to the use of the United States." Clay and Crittenden ask if the arms can be replaced "in a course of administration, without a special act of Congress."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2422">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to William Coffin
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 March 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:32
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar. 28. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Coffin for sending "to Copies of my engraved likeness."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2436">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Mr. Onderdonk
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 April 29
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:33
</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay sends Onderdonk a copy of one of the speeches he requested. Clay notes that the "others are to be found in the periodicals of the day."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2450">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to J.[ohn] M. Clayton
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1840 May 8]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:34
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked May 8. #2933.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is "grieved" to hear of Clayton's accident and says he considers himself "the cause, although the innocent cause of it." If Clay had been well enough to visit Clayton in New Castle it "would not have
happened." Clay hopes to be well enough "to make tomorrow my excursion to Philad." and will visit Clayton while there or on his return to Washington.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2464">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Danl. [Daniel] Gardner
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 July 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:35
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jul.7. #2291, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay apologizes that he lacks the time to respond fully to Gardner's letter. Clay's thoughts "may be found in the Panama instructions" which were published in Niles' Register and the "State Papers of Congress."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2478">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Messrs. McNairy, Hall, Marcy?, Huston, Manlove &amp; Norvell
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 July 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:36
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1761.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks the men for their invitation to visit Nashville on August 17, but says that he is "worn down by the fatigues of an exhausting Session of Congress" and cannot come so soon. He suggests a later visit
in either September or October.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2492">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to S. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 July 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:37
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay introduces G.W. Brown of Charleston, S.C. "who is desirous of viewing the Northern manufactories."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2506">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Charles F. Mayer
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1840 December 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:38
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay tells Mayer that he is well acquainted with "our friend D.[avid] Hoffman" but since Clay has "no expectation of being otherwise connected with the new administration than as a member of the Senate," he is
unable to aid Hoffman.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2520">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to J. Trotter
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 February 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:39
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf. #2908.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses a draft for $2575 [not present] "for collection and to be put to my account in Bank." Clay tells Trotter that before the "recent suspension, and whilst your Bank was paying Specie" he drew a check
for $2000 and sent it to Kentucky. Clay hopes there will be no problem paying the check "in Greens, or lawful currency."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2534">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to [unidentified recipient]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 March 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:40
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; name of recipient clipped out. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks the recipient for the "box containing the Shirts and Stocks" and sends his thanks to "Mrs. P[ ]er?" as well. Clay will deliver the recipient's message to General Harrison when he next sees him and
"would send him one of the shirts but that I know it will not fit him."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2549">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 April 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:41
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf and separate address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington. #4475.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says that "the distressing intelligence of the death of Genl. Harrison" has reached him and that it is "greatly to be deplored, although it does not surprize me much, from what I observed of his habits and
excitement." Clay declines a suggestion to deliver a eulogy for Harrison on the grounds of the "yet feeble state of my strength." Clay is sorry that Conover was unable to obtain an appointment in Washington and
says that he has "no power, not the bestowal of a single office." Clay concludes by stating that "V.P. Tyler will, I presume, not confine the patronage of the Govt. exclusively to any particular class of Whigs."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2563">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jno. [John] L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 April 13
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:42
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Apr.15; silked. #5828-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay shares Conover's "surprize and regret" about William Henry Harrison's death. He states that he has known Vice President Tyler "long and intimately" and that he "has ability quite equal to his predecessor,
is amiable, and I think honest and patriotic. His defect is want of moral firmness." Clay says that he believes the member of the Cabinet should have resigned on Harrison's death.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2577">
          <did>
            <unittitle>John Tyler, Washington, to Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 April 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:43
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 4 pp.; docketed; silked. #2362.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Tyler apologizes for not answering Clay's letter earlier. Tyler says that no one should expect him to bring before Congress "matured plans of public policy connected with deeply interesting and intricate
subjects." Some issues, such as the "repeal of the subtreasury" and "the state of our military defences" require immediate attention. "It will however be for Congress to decide whether other measures shall claim
its attention." Tyler says that his opinions "on the subject of a distribution of the proceeds of the sales of the public lands" were made known three years previous in a report to the Virginia House of Delegates.
He says that the "annual appropriation to harbours and rivers" is "wholly indefensible in any view in which I can regard it." In regards to "a Bank...I would not have it urgd [sic] prematurely-The public mind is
still in a state of great disquietude in regard to it." He tells Clay that "Jackson tore the charter of the old Bank into tatters-and his followers will go forth as agitators and the result of thier [sic]
agitations may prove dissastrous [sic]." Tyler urges Clay to attempt "to frame a Bank as to avoid all constitutional objections" and repeats that he has "no intention to submit any thing to Congress on this
subject to be acted on." Tyler closes by saying his "attention is turned to the removals from office after the manner that you suggest."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2591">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to the Rev. H.[enry] R. Bascom
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 May 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:44
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 10. #6004.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says that he will "take pleasure in mentioning to some of the faculty and trustees of Transylvania Dr. [John James] Reese favorably." Clay thanks Bascom for notifying him of "the complaints which have
reached you against me of neglect in my correspondence. Clay says that if a day "had 48 instead of 24 hours" it would still be too short to answer the hundreds of letters he received in Washington. He generally
did not reply to letters seeking office but hopes that he did not treat any personal letters "with disrespect." Clay closes by telling Bascom of the letter he received from John Tyler; Clay hopes for Tyler's
cooperation and support.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2605">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to O.T. Keeler
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 July 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:45
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2375.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay received Keeler's letter containing "a Memorial in behalf of the passage of a general bankrupt law" and has presented it to the Senate.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2619">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to John R. Thompson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 August 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:46
</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 p. #5718-c.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes to Thompson, a University of Virginia student: "In answer to your enquiry about the word 'locate,' I have to say that whether it be an English word or not, I think it a very good American one."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
<c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Charles Parrow 
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 August 15
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:46a
            </container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #7661.
            </physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes concerning legislation in the current session of the United States Congress and predicts failure for the bill to establish the 
              Bank of the United States "which is in the hands of the President, and which is believed he will veto."
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>   
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2633">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Col. [James Watson] Webb
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1842, ca. January 26]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:47
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #5694.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes, possibly in reply to Webb's letter of January 21, 1842, and thanks him for his suggestions. Clay says it "has not been found practicable to delay acting on the repeal of the Bankrupt law." If the
repeal is defeated, it will most likely be because of a tie vote.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2647">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Col. [James Watson] Webb
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 January 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:48
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #5694.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of page. Clay asks Webb or Charles King "to render me an act of justice." Henry Wise has dragged Clay's name "in the unfortunate affair of poor [Jonathan] Cilley" and has
"totally misrepresented any agency of mine in it." Clay says that on the day of the duel, Charles King consulted him "as to the practicability of arresting it." Clay says that he suggested notifying the police and
recommended that King go to Charles F. Mercer and Francis Scott Key for that purpose. Unfortunately, the police "mistook the road, on which the parties left the City." This is the fact that Clay wishes "to be
brought out by one or both of you; and in such suitable manner as may be deemed most proper."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2661">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Col. J[ames]. W[atson]. Webb
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 February 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:49
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp. docketed. #5694.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay has received Webb's letter and forwarded the enclosures to the editor of the Washington
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Daily National Intelligencer.
</title> Clay distributed Webb's prospectuses for the New York
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Courier
</title> to a member of the House of Representatives who will canvas for names. Clay says that he has "not made up my mind to consent to the use of my name" as a candidate for the Presidency. The only reason that
would make him consent would be "a clear manifestation that my services were desired by a majority of my Country men." Clay says there is not a single Senator "in the Whig ranks, who is not well disposed towards
the Whig party, and who is not exempt from all tincture of Tylerism."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2681">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Papers regarding Henry Clay's connection with the Jonathan Cilley-William J. Graves duel of 1838.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:50
</container>
            <physdesc>6 items. #2540.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>
              <list type="simple">
                <item>Statement of Charles King, New York, 1842 Feb. 4 (ADS, 4 pp.)
</item>
                <item>Statement of Reverdy Johnson, Baltimore, 1842 Feb. 7 (ADS, 4 pp.; with modern transcription in unidentified hand.)
</item>
                <item>William Jordan Graves to Henry Clay, 1842 Feb. 16 (ALS, 5 pp.)
</item>
                <item>Paper wrapper with note "Original papers published in Natl. Intell. Feb 25, 1842"
</item>
                <item>"Henry Clay on dueling," (printed; reproduces text of Samuel Wood to Henry Clay, 1838 Mar. 8 and Henry Clay to Samuel Wood, 1838 Mar. 23, both re the duel.)
</item>
                <item>Printed biography of Jonathan Cilley removed from unidentified source
</item>
              </list>
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2709">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Jon. A. Tenney
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 March 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:51
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2180.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay tells Tenney that although he generally declines requests for autographs, he is making an exception because of the "friendly sentiments towards me, conveyed in you letter."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2724">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to [unidentified recipient]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 May 26
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:52
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1113.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay responds to a request to inform the recipient when he left the United States on the mission to conclude the Treaty of Ghent.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2738">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 May 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:53
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Jun.1. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Sargent for the "Copy of my Valedictory so handsomely printed on Satin." He asks about President Tyler and whether the relationship between him and the Whigs is improved. Clay mentions the "affair"
between Edward Stanly and Henry A. Wise. He concludes by mentioning that "Mr. Van Buren" left a few days ago and Clay found him "interesting often &amp; some times amusing." Clay mentions the reception in
Lexington given to "the little magician" [i.e. Van Buren] and says he doubts "whether he has had one so imposing any where since he left home."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2752">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan. Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 July 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:54
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jul. 31. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Sargent for his recent letter and mentions John D. Langhorne. Clay says he is "glad the N.E. question is settled, altho' the terms are curious enough." He wonders what President Tyler "will do with
the Tariff, and, if he veto it, what Congress will then do." Clay says Kentucky is blessed with abundant crops and he is "making extensive preparations to Water rot hemp."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2766">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas W. Duffield, Jr.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 September 6
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:55
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Sep. 6. #6306.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Duffield for a copy of an address he had delivered to the literary club of Oxford, Pa. Clay suggests that the club members might usefully debate such topics as the presidential veto, free trade vs.
tariff protections or the establishment of a Bank of the United States. Clay says that such debates "might be made highly instrumental in propagating truth &amp; dispelling error."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2780">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A. M. January
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842 September 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:56
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #11159.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay will travel to Cincinnati by the Maysville route and will write January "next week informing you, if I can, who will accompany me."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2794">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin Watkins Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 March 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:57
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; postmarked Lexington Mar. 18. #1463.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay describes his "Southern jaunt," from which he has just returned. If he should be selected as the candidate of the Whigs for the presidency he believes the vote of Kentucky "is no more certain than that of
Louisiana." Clay believes that both Mississippi and Alabama will vote Whig, though "a bitter schism exists on the bank question in Alabama, and on repudiation in Mississippi...and in both on the Presidency." Clay
tells Leigh that he "heartily concurs" with the address of the Whig convention in Virginia to the people. He states that the "brief notice with which Mr. Tyler is treated in the address was wise." Clay says there
is an omission in the address that he regrets; that is, "Executive power &amp; the veto." He closes with regard to Chapman Johnson, Francis T. Brooke, Robert Stanard and Julia Wickam Leigh.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2808">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B[enjamin]. W.[atkins] Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 June 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:58
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached partial address leaf. #1463.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay states that he wrote Leigh several weeks ago in reply to Leigh's letter asking "into the origin of Mr. Wise's alienation and his present enmity" towards Clay. Since Clay has had no reply he wonders if his
letter miscarried. Clay says he is "surprized and gratified" by the Virginia election results and is confident of success in Tennessee and Indiana. Clay closes with a postscript in which he states that he is
"informed from N. York that some of the Intriguers of 1839 are again engaged in active machinations."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2822">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N[athan]. Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 September 2
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:59
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Sep. 3. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Sargent for his letter and tells him to ask Mr. [Josiah] Randall to show him Clay's letter that suggests "a plan of organization." Clay is pleased with Sargent's account of prospects in Pennsylvania
and says if the "Whigs and Anti Masons can carry the Legislature at the ensuing election, the whole Nation will resound with joy."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2836">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to N[athan]. Sargent
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 September 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:60
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Sep. 20. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Sargent for his letter and says that he has been indisposed with "the Tyler Grippe." He is pleased with Sargent's report of Pennsylvania's prospects. Clay says that "[w]e shall think about a
Com[mitt]ee" though he will be away from home from December until May.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2850">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jno.[John] L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 October 5
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:61
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; with envelope, postmarked Lexington, Sep. 11. #5828.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay thanks Lawrence for his letter. He says that he cannot speak in favor of Daniel Webster as candidate for Vice President. Clay says that before Webster "could
be properly even considered, he ought to give some public and unequivocal testimony of adherence to the Whig cause." Clay says that "under no circumstances, in my opinion, ought Mr. Webster's name to be used as a
Candidate for the V.P." Clay concludes by stating that the "treachery of Mr. Tyler ought to inspire the greatest caution with the Whig party."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2864">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas H. Baird
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 November 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:62
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached partial blank leaf. #6236.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay says that if he did not know of Baird's "fidelity and attachment" he would have been "mortified" at Baird's recent letter. Clay is surprised that "any doubt
should be entertained of my devotion to the policy of cherishing our manufactures, or that any impression should be made upon a friend by a perversion of my meaning, by an enemy...." Clay then presents a lengthy
explanation of his stand on revenue, tariff and the government's debt. He concludes by saying that he would have to "pile letter upon letter until they reached a Mountain height, if I were to write to correct
every perversion of my meaning and misrepresentation of me that are made."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2879">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A[aron]. B[alderston]. Quimby
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 November 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:63
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Nov. 9. #2338.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Quimby for his letter and the copy of his letter to Mr. Clayton [not present]. Clay does not think it wise to attack the "two gentlemen mentioned in your letter" since it is not necessary to the
success of the Whig cause.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2907">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to "Gentlemen"
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1843 December 12
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:64
            </container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Dec. 13. #3920.
            </physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is honored by the invitation to visit Wilmington, N.C. He hopes he will be able to visit en route to Raleigh, N.C. but "[d]istance of time and place prevents a positive decision at present." A list of
              twelve names (Alex. Anderson, Edwd. B. Dudley, Thomas F. Davis, Alex. Macrae, W.C. Lord, John Potts Brown, A.J. De Rosset, James F. McKee, P.K. Dickinson, James S. Green, John McKae and Wm. A Wright) in an
              unidentified hand follows Clay's signature.
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02> 
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2893">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Legal brief in the case of Joseph Ray
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1843]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:65
</container>
            <physdesc>AD, 7 pp. on 2 sheets, in Clay's hand. #2467, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay's brief for the suit of Joseph Ray, consul at Pernambuco, Brazil, 1816-1817, against the Brazilian government, mentions John C. Calhoun and Henry A. Wise.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>

        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2921">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Macon, [Ga.], to "Gentlemen"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 March 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:66
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 3 pp.; with attached address leaf. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to members of the National Clay Club. He states that it "is to be inferred from your letter" that there are "differences among my Philadelphia friends" and urges them to "unite in a spirit of
mutual concession and conciliation, as a band of brothers in the great struggle which is before us."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2935">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Henry White
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 June 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:67
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Jun.15. #5718-e.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks White for his letter and says he is "rejoiced to hear that the merchants of Phila. are animated by such liberal and patriotic zeal. Clay says that regardless of what "we may think of the nominations
of our opponents, it is always wisest, in politics as well as War, Never to despise an enemy but to go to work as if Napoleon or Wellington were in the field. If we act in that way, and according to that maxim, we
shall drive our opponent out of the Union to find refuge in Texas." Clay closes by saying he will be happy to serve White "with the Planter of Louisiana."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2949">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin]. W[atkins]. Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 July 3
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:68
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay encloses copies [not present] of his "famous letters to Mr. [Francis P.] Blair" and says that he does not object to Leigh's "shewing them to any person you
please." Clay does not want them published without his consent. He says that he is "a little ashamed of ever having been on terms of such intimacy with so great a scoundrel as I now believe Blair to be." Clay
closes by saying he is "now
<emph render="underline">considering
</emph> whether I shall not attack the Jackson party."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2966">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Conway D. Whittle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 July 8
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:69
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #7973.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says "military land in Missouri is liable to forfeiture for the non payment of taxes." Clay suggests that White's "immediate attention to the subject is advisable if you have any military lands in
Missouri."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2980">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to B[enjamin]. W[atkins]. Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 July 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:70
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay is "vexed with applications, chiefly from Virginia" to allow the publication of his Francis P. Blair letters. Clay has no objection "to any gentleman of either party reading the letters" but has not yet
decided to publish the letters. He has two objections, "one of which is the violation of the confidence due to private correspondence, and the other is the allusion to an infirmity of Mr. [John Quincy] Adams."
Clay has not "received all the proof I expect to establish 'bargain intrigue &amp; corruption,' upon [Andrew] Jackson and his friends. He closes with comments on the political situation in Tennessee, Virginia,
South Carolina and Kentucky.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e2994">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Geo[rge]. M. Davis
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 August 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:71
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Sep. 2. #2802, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay is somewhat disappointed in the election results in Illinois. He declines to make a public statement "on the subjects of the Naturalization Laws and the Native
American party." He sends Davis an issue of the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Lexington Reporter
</title> [not present] "which comprehends abundant matter defending me against the charge of liberality to foreigners."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3011">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Henry White
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 September 19
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:72
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Sep. 20. #1649.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks White for his letter and hopes that the success of the "Commercial Committee" will "correspond with its good intentions." Clay says "our intelligence concerning" the 1844 gubernatorial election in
Pennsylvania "is somewhat conflicting." He mentions the Whig committee in Washington organized by Garrett Davis and Willis Green. Clay closes by saying he will be happy to serve White's "house with the sugar
planters in Louisiana" if he is able.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3025">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A. Webster, Secretary of the Clay Club of Plainfield, to the President of the Clay and Frelinghuysen Club of New Brunswick
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 September 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:73
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed; postmarked Sep. 24 Plainfield N.J; on blue paper illustrated with portraits of Clay and Frelinghuysen, with the caption "Huzza! Huzza! the Country's risin.'" #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Webster writes concerning the organization of a mammoth mass meeting to be held on September 26 in support of Clay's candidacy.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3040">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin Watkins Leigh
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1844 September 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:74
</container>
            <physdesc>LS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. #1403.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has been "much urged by Mr. [John] Pleasants and other friends in Virginia, to allow the publication of my [Francis P.] Blair letters." Clay says his "opinion from the first has been, that their
publication, so far from injury would benefit me in respect to the charge of bargain." If Leigh and others in Virginia think publication will help, Clay has no objections. He asks that if the letters are published
"it would perhaps be best to say, that it was done by friends of Mr. Clay upon their own responsibility...Credit should be claimed for me, which I think I deserve for abstaining from the publication on account of
the private playful and familiar character of the letters, although the evidence which they contain in regard to the public charge, is really beneficial to me." Clay discusses the public accessibility of the
letters over the years and states that the contents do not differ substantially from his letter to his constituents in March 1824. Clay closes by stating that this letter "has been written by an amanuensis upon my
dictation, although I am happy to tell you, that my health is now excellent and never was better."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3054">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Campaign ribbon for the Clay-Frelinghuysen campaign
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[ca. 1844]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:75
</container>
            <physdesc>ca. 23 x 7 cm. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Silk[?] ribbon, with portrait of Clay and text: Henry Clay / The people's choice / The pride of America / Freylinghuysen
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3068">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Joseph Story
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 February 9
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:76
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay states that he is not surprised that Story is considering stepping down from the Supreme Court. Clay says that Story's "friends would rejoice if you could reconcile it to your feelings to continue; but
most certainly, after what you have said to me, the question should be left to your exclusive judgment."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3082">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland to Peter Cromwell, Fishkill Landing, N.Y.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 February 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:77
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Feb. 16. #3121.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay thanks Cromwell for his letter and the "friendly sentiments" it contained about the "late Presidential election." Clay says he entertains "many serious
apprehensions" about the future and hopes that the American people "will perceive impending dangers and guard against them."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3096">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Mr. [Henry L.] Ellsworth
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 March 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:78
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses a letter [not present] from "two of the most enterprising and reputable citizens of Louisville" concerning an experiment to produce "an efficient Hempbrake."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3110">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland to John L. Lawrence, New York
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 April 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:79
</container>
            <physdesc>LS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with cover. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" above salutation. Clay thanks Lawrence for his recent letter and mentions that he has received a Baltimore newspaper "containing what occurred in the British House of Commons on the Oregon subject."
Clay has long believed that difficulties "would arise out of the headlong course of our Government in respect to Oregon, at the very moment when a negotiation is in progress with Great Britain." Clay believes it
"premature" to settle the Pacific coast and maintain defences "at a time when we have quite enough to defend the coasts of the Atlantic Ocean and the Gulph of Mexico." Clay says that he is apprehensive "that we
are shortly to have war with both England and Mexico. The party in power has not the moral courage to do right." Clay fears that Great Britain will, because of the annexation of Texas, see "dangers to all her
American possessions ahead" and possibly craft an alliance with Mexico. Such an alliance would be "capable of inflicting much mischief, especially on the Pacific." Clay believes "that there is a strong possibility
of war." He asks Lawrence to send him a full report of Lord Russell's speech if possible. Clay closes with a postscript stating, "I have dictated the above to an amanuensis."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3124">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay and James B. Clay to Thomas Grubbs
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 August 1
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:80
</container>
            <physdesc>ADS, 1 p. #4925.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Promissory note for $350 at 6% interest.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3138">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to [Henry] C. [Westervelt]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 September 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:81
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with address cut from leaf or cover; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Sep. 21. #3193.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Westervelt for his letter "communicating the desire of Mr. [William] Fischerman to make and present me a pair of boots, and for that purpose, to obtain from me an old boot or some other adequate
measure of the leg and foot which he kindly desires to cover." Clay fears that the old boot, "if I were to send one, might never reach its destination. It would be an inconvenient customer to the P.[ost] Office
department...and if sent through any other, it might, by mistake, get upon some other leg &amp; foot, and lead its strange companion a dance." Clay encloses [not present] a "paper measure of my leg and foot, taken
by a plain but worthy boot and shoemaker in Lexn." who is, like Mr./ Fischerman "a foreigner" and "a good whig." A note below Clay's signature in an unidentified hand states "The boots were made in an elegent
[sic] &amp; comfortable manner under my superintedance [sic], with the hair (undressed inside) and were as a beautiful a specimen of the Mechanic art as I remember to have seen. Mr. Clay recd them &amp; expressed
his kind acknowledgements to Mr. Fisherman [sic] personally."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3152">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Benjamin Belch
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 November 20
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:82
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Nov. 21. #2180.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay received Balch's letter "transmitting a plan of the National Life Insurance Company of Massachusetts." He appreciates the offer to be appointed president, but cannot "reconcile it to my sense of propriety
to accept the appointment."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3166">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Messrs. David S. Brown, Henry White, A.I. Lewis, William Reynolds, Ch. Gibbons, Charles W. Churchman, and John E. Kean
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1845 December 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:83
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached blank leaf; Barrow. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks the subscribers for the presentation by White of a letter and book "entitled, 'A testimonial of gratitude and affection to Henry Clay.'" He says that it is impossible "to find language of sufficient
force and strength to express to you the emotions of gratitude and thankfulness excited in my breast by this precious and affecting testimonial." He is "also charged by Mrs. Clay" to present her thanks "to the
Ladies and Gentlemen who have had the goodness to send her a Casket of rich jewels." He closes with warm thanks and acknowledgement to White for "performing a long journey, at a most inclement season, to fulfill
the commission entrusted to him."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3180">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Certificate of Membership in the American Colonization Society
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 March 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:84
</container>
            <physdesc>DS, 1 p.; signed by Henry Clay. #5718.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Printed certificate, for Mrs. Emmeline Rockwell.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3195">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Nathan Sargent,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 April 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:85
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with detached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Apr. 28. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has returned to Ashland after an absence of four months and found Sargent's letter of March 13. He comments on the divisions in Congress and says that if Congress should "finally disagree, and leave the
Oregon question where it has been so many years, I for one shall not regard it as National misfortune." Clay says he has not been "and am not now, without fears for the peace of the Country." He closes by stating
that "it would be altogether premature, and highly indiscreet and impolitic for the Whig party to make any movement whatever, in favor of any body, in respect to the next Presidential election."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3209">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Mr. and Mrs. Maury
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 May
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:86
</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 p.; photocopy, location of original unknown. #931.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"With the best wishes for Mrs. Maury and the warmest regards for Mr. W. Maury"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3223">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John Wood, Jr., Hardins Tavern, Albemarle County, Va.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 September 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:87
            </container>
            <physloc>Oversize.
</physloc>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Sep. 10. #10433.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay writes that he received Wood's friendly letter and assures him that he "never supposed that the act of wantonness, to which I called your attention, was performed by any respectable person of your
community." Because of his high regard for the community, Clay "thought it due to it to transmit to you the means of discovering and exposing the guilty individual." Clay closes with warm thanks for Wood's
friendship.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3237">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Geo[rge] McClellan
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 September 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:88
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received McClellan's letter "communicating the death of my Grandson Martin Duralde." Clay thanks McClellan for his attentions and asks him to have his grandson's body buried "in a private and decent
manner, marking the spot of the interment, so that it may be known." He asks for Duralde's "cloathes, watch, papers and other effects" to be packed and shipped to him. Clay closes saying "ruthless death, has
deprived me of Six affectionate daughters, all that I ever had, and has now commenced his work of destruction, with my descendents, in the second generation."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3251">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Arthur Wells
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1846 November 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:89
</container>
            <physdesc>LS, 1 p. #5718-c.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>In unidentified hand. Clay sends "congratulations on the recent triumph of the Whigs and it adds to my pleasure that their success has been achieved on great and vital principles of policy." He hopes that if
"the Whigs are hereafter wise...there is much reason to hope that the administration of our General Government may be again brought back to a just comprehension and a faithful support of sound principles of
National policy."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3265">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Geo[rge] Stone
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 May 15
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:90
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2575.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Stone for his "friendly letter of condolence, on the occasion of the death of my beloved son, at the battle of Buena Vista." He hopes that God will help him "ultimately to bear, with becoming
resignation, the infliction which His providence has permitted."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3279">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to W.R. Prince
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 May 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:91
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1665.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Prince for his offer to "send me next fall any tree or plant which I might select from you rich and ample collection." Clay has "as many rare shrubs plants and trees as I care about" but would be
grateful if Prince would send "a half dozen choice Firs."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3293">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Richard Henry Wilde
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 June 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:92
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #2290, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay discusses financial matters and a case to be heard by the Supreme Court.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3307">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to J.D.G. Quirk
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 July 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:93
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; photocopy; location of original unknown.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Quirk for sending the "locket and breastpin" containing locks of Clay's son's hair. Clay says these items will be "more highly prized by us 'than rubies and diamonds.'" Clay also thanks Quirk for
procuring the "splendid Coffin."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3321">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, W. Sulphur S., to P.[hilip] R. Fendall,
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 July 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:94
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2180.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay regrets he was unable to see Fendall "after you were so kind as to proceed to Balto. to meet me." He asks Fendall to thank Joseph Gales for his invitation, but will be unable to accept since it is "not a
part of my arrangements to pass by the metropolis."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3335">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, White S. Springs
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 July 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:95
</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 p. #38-115.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay responds to the request for an autograph from the unidentified daughter of "an admirer."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3350">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Cape May, to Messrs. Carter, Hargrave, Cochran, Magruder, Watson, Southall and Timberlake
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 August 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:96
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf and separate letter cover postmarked Philadelphia, Aug. 19. #5711.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks the representatives of the "Commte. of Citizens of Albemarle" for their invitation to visit Charlottesville. Clay regrets that he could not attend but his travel arrangements were already fixed. The object of the "journey, moreover, was to escape from daily scenes, which constantly reminded me of a heavy domestic affliction." He closes with warm regards and thanks for their "generous sympathy."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3364">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Cape May, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 August 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:97
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Lawrence for "tendering the hospitality of your roof, of which I should have been very happy to avail myself, if I had visited N.Y."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3378">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Cape Island, to Messrs. Henry White and A.I. Lewis
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 August 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:98
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks White and Lewis for their invitation "to partake of a public dinner" in Philadelphia on his journey to the east coast. He declines the invitation since "it would be entirely incompatible with the
state of my feelings."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3392">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.P. Letcher
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1847 December 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:99
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #2933-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay asks if Letcher will be going to Washington as Clay is "called there by business."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3406">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Harriette McIlhaney
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 February 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:100
</container>
            <physdesc>AN, 1 p.; with portion of cover laid down. #5806.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay sends [a lock of his hair?] [not present] and thanks Miss McIhaney for the gift for Mrs. Clay.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to William F. Wickham
              <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 February 22
              </unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:100a
            </container>
            <physdesc>AN. #15753.
            </physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay declines an invitation to visit.
            </p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>    
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3420">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to W.[illiam] E.[rigena] Robinson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 March 4
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:101
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses the autographs he promised [not present]. He has not seen the issue of
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Philadelphia Daily News
</title> mentioned by Robinson. Clay will leave for New York "Tuesday next" and shudders "in contemplation at the scenes which I shall have to pass."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3437">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.D. Haslett
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 April 14
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:102
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #6004.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay sends the requested lock of hair [not present] and regrets that "it is not something more worthy of your acceptance."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3451">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 June 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:103
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Jun 17. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay states that the "action of the Whig Convention did not take me altogether by surprize, although I was greatly surprized at some of the incidents attending it." He
mentions his astonishment "at the course of the Ohio delegation." He says it is his "inclination, and perhaps my duty, quietly to submit to the decision of the Convention,
<emph render="underline">so far as I am personally concerned
</emph> . Beyond that I feel under no obligation to go." Clay says that Zachary Taylor would not have withdrawn his name were Clay nominated. Clay says "Genl. Taylor professes to be a Whig in name, but disclaims
all obligations to carry our Whig principles and measures. In that respect his case differs entirely from that of Genl [William Henry] Harrison." Clay has no advice to offer his friends. He desires "all the
information I can get about the Convention, its secret movements and springs." Clay closes with warm regards and mentions Abraham R. Lawrence and Charles S. Morehead.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3468">
          <did>
            <unittitle>George Benskin Poindexter to the Proprietors of the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Richmond Whig
</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1848 June 25
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">2:104
</container>
            <physdesc>ADLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with attached address leaf. #2784-h.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Poindexter submits an article praising Henry Clay for publication in the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Whig.
</title></p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3488">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, New Orleans, to A. [Pierse]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 February 16
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:1
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; Barrow; large section torn from upper center, affecting first five lines of text. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Pierse for his recent letters and sympathizes with the illness that kept Pierse from attending the Whig convention in Philadelphia. Clay says that the "President elect will not find himself at
Washington on a bed of roses." The most important issue is the "Free soil question" which, if it should "remain unadjusted during his administration, I fear it will widen the existing breach between the South and
North." Clay says that he is not surprised that Pierse wishes to go to California. "To those whose age and condition in life admit of their going there, the Country offers great inducements and attractions." Clay
does not know if a governor will be appointed for California and is "unwilling to make any recommendation for that office."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3502">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas B. Stevenson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 June 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:2
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp.; photocopy, location of original unknown. #2222.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Stevenson for his letters and sends condolences on the death of Dr. Ennis Combs. He says that as far as he remembers, Thomas Hart Benton "was pleased with and approved all that was done to admit
Missouri into the Union. And if he ever reproached me with my agency in the matter, I have forgotten it." Clay says he would "deplore the event of the Administration being thrown into the minority in the H. of R.
It would be bad for them, bad for the Whig party and bad for the Country." He is apprehensive that Kentucky will not elect additional Whigs in the next election. Clay comments on the political situation in Ohio
and says that Pierse's "conjectures are correct in regard to the President's feelings towards me." Clay closes by saying the cholera "still lingers with us" but he has "lost no one."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3517">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Newport, to James V. Earle
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 August 21
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:3
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to Earle and says he has "no expectation of being in Boston prior to my return home."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3531">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to Miss Jewell
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1849 December 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:4
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #5601.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay replies to a request for an autograph.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3545">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington to Conway D. Whittle, Union Level Post Office, Va
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 January 31
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:5
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with enclosure AD, 1 p., n.d.; with envelope, postmarked Washington, D.C. Feb. 1. #7973.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay encloses a draft of petition requested by Whittle. He apologizes that his "engagements will not allow" him "to attend to it ought to be" and suggests "any of the Virginia members in either house will do so
with pleasure." The pension concerns a pension owed to [Whittle's father?].
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3559">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to J. Morrison Harris
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 May 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:6
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Harris for his letter informing Clay of his unanimous appointment as an honorary member of the Maryland Historical Society.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3573">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to, Washington, [Francis T.] Brooke
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 June 11
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:7
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #6273.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Brooke for his invitation to visit St. Julien (near Fredericksburg, Va.) but "cannot now abandon my post, we are in the midst of the Slavery contest, and I can get no discharge until is has
terminated."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3587">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Newport, to Mr. [Daniel] Webster
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 August 22
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:8
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. #2933.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay has received a letter from Millard Fillmore "in which he kindly expressed his willingness, that my son James [Brown Clay] might give the finishing stroke to the negotiation which he had conducted at
Lisbon, by concluding a suitable convention, and that you had concurred in that arrangement." Clay says that his son left Lisbon on July 18 and encloses a letter from him dated July 17 [not present] that gives his
itinerary. Clay says he does not know if his son "would like to return to Lisbon, which would be somewhat awkward, as under his instructions, he has closed his mission there, and new Credentials might be
necessary." Clay says that he will "be entirely content with any decision you make." He closes by saying he has enclosed a letter from his son [not present] to show "what serious consequences sometimes result from
the free conversations between Members of Congress, and foreign members."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3601">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] H.H. Stuart
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 November 7
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:9
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #345.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Confidential" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay thanks Stuart for his recent letter. He says the information he had received that Attorney General John J. Crittenden had "prevented the appointment" of
William H. Russell "to an Indian Agency" was from Dr. William M. Gwin. Clay says if there are "well founded objections to Col. Russells appointment" he does not wish it to be made. Clay is pleased with the
appointment of [James S.?] Crutchfield. Clay suggests that Secretary of the Treasury Thomas Corwin "make full enquiries" about William L. Hodge in New Orleans and Philadelphia before appointing him as Assistant.
Clay says Hodge is "in bad odor" in both cities "and his appointment will prejudice the Administration in both those Cities."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3615">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] H.H. Stuart
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 November 18
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:10
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #345.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay sends a letter from Senator George W. Jones of Iowa [not present] concerning the appointment of a post master and says "[a]lthough he is a democrat, I have a
great respect and regard for him and entertain great confidence in him." Clay is sorry the William Gilliam "was not appointed to the land office in Iowa City owing, as I understood, to the interference of Mr.
[Fitz Henry] Warren."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3629">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to A.H.H. Stuart
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">[1850 November 19?]
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:11
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p.; with envelope; postmarked Lexington, Ky., Nov. 19. #345.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay recommends William Gilliam "for the office of the Register of the Land Office at Iowa City."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3643">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to Editors of the
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">New Yorker
</title><unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850 December 17
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:12
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #1754-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks the editors for the newspapers he has received from them, but regrets he cannot subscribe, his "object being, rather to lessen than increase the number of papers that I now take."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3660">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Ashland, to James S. Whitney
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1851 April 23
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:13
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3920.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay thanks Whitney for his election as an honorary member of the Jefferson Literary and Historical Society of Philadelphia.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3675">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay, Washington, to [John M. Clay]
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1852 April 30
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:14
</container>
            <physdesc>AL (copy), 1 p.; transcription by M.W. Anderson; location of original unknown. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay sends a bill of sale [not present] for a slave, Bill Burton. He tells his son he is entitled to half the $1500 held by Wright &amp; Price.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3689">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Invitation of the Clayonian Literary Society of Newark, New Jersey, for the 89th anniversary of the birth of Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1866 April 12
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:15
</container>
            <physdesc>D, 1 p., addressed to W.M. Force, Esq. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3700">
          <did>
            <unittitle>M.W. Anderson, Lexington, Kentucky, to W.S. Hunt
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1934 September 24
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:16
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Concerning the purchase of a letter by Henry Clay, 1852 April 30; see transcription above.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3714">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Fragment of a Pro-Whig drama concerning the election of 1836
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:17
</container>
            <physdesc>AMs, [34] pp.; pp. 7-22, 35-50, 61-61 present. #3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3725">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Henry Clay to William C. Johnson
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Monday morning
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:18
</container>
            <physdesc>ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. #5718-c.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Clay says that he kept the letter requested by Johnson "several weeks in my pocket" intending to return it. He is now unable to find the letter and fears he might have "unintentionally destroyed it."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3739">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Lines on hearing a speech from Henry Clay," by Ann Sophia Stephens
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:19
</container>
            <physdesc>AMsS, 1 p.; photocopy; original in Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature. #8532-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3750">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Autograph
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:20
</container>
            <physdesc>ANS, 1 p. #8641-d.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"I am with great respect, your obt. Serv."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e3764">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Photographs and Prints
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3768">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Talbotype of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:21
</container>
            <physdesc>#3417-b.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3779">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carte-de-visite photograph of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:22
</container>
            <physdesc>#7055.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Published by Craft &amp; Ferry Photographers, 132 Bowery, New York."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3793">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Silhouette of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1841 March 10
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:23
</container>
            <physdesc>Photographic copy; location of original unknown. #5231-a.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3804">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1842
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:24
</container>
            <physdesc>#3193.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"I have wished the good opinion of the world but I defy the most malignant of my enemies to show that I have attempted to gain it by any low or groveling acts by any mean or unworthy sacrifice by the violation
of any of the obligations of honor or by a breach of any of the duties which I owed to my country." "Published by H.R. Robinson, Hoboken, New Jersey."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3818">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1854
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:25
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"John M. Butler &amp; Alfred Long" Clay addressing the Senate on the omnibus bill, 1850.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3830">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1856
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:26
</container>
            <physdesc>2 copies. #2908, #8483-c.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Martin &amp; Johnson" Oval portrait within ornamental border, above three vignettes showing, left to right, Clay in the House of Representatives, signing the Treaty of Ghent, and at home with his family.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3844">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:27
</container>
            <physdesc>#3248.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Likeness from a portrait in the possession of his family. Johnson, Fry &amp; Co. Publishers, New York."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3858">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:28
</container>
            <physdesc>2 copies. #10751.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Engd. by W.G. Jackman, from a daguerreotype by Brady. N.Y. D. Appleton &amp; Co."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3872">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:29
</container>
            <physdesc>Detached from unidentified book; text on attached guard sheet: "Henry Clay photogravure after a daguerreotype by Brady." Derivative of image #10751, above.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3883">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:30
</container>
            <physdesc>"Engd. by W.J. Edwards from Dag. by Brady." Within ornamental border, above vignette entitled "Peace negotiations at Ghent." Not the same image as #10751, above.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3895">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:31
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Bureau Engraving &amp; Printing."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3907">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:32
</container>
            <physdesc>4 copies. #2180, #10751.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Daguerreotype by Root. Engraved by A. Sealey"
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3921">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:33
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Engraved by J.B. Longacre from a painting by W.J. Hubard."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3933">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:34
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"C. Fenderich del. Fredk. Halpin, sculp. Ptd. by Neale &amp; Pate."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3945">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:35
</container>
            <physdesc>#2908.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Drawn &amp; engraved from several daguerreotypes by A.H. Ritchie. Likeness principally taken from a fine daguerreotype by Messrs. Page &amp; Beach, proprietors of the Plumbe Daguerrean Gallery, Washington."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3959">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Portrait of Henry Clay
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:36
</container>
            <physdesc>Photographic copy of unidentified print.
</physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3970">
          <did>
            <unittitle>"Henry Clay and his wife"
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:37
</container>
            <physdesc>#9860.
</physdesc>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Engraved by T. Johnson. After a photograph in possession of Louis E. Levy, Esq."
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3984">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Engraving of statue of Henry Clay, New Orleans, La.
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1860 April 28
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <physloc>Oversize; OS Box W-4
</physloc>
            <physdesc>Detached from
<title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="italic" xlink:href="">Harper's Weekly.
</title></physdesc>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e3998">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photograph of statue of Henry Clay by Thomas Ball
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">n.d.
</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">3:38
</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
