<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03859">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03859::Letters of Captain David F. Dobie)//EN" "viu03859.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of Captain David F. Dobie <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1865 </date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Dobie, Captain David F., Letters
<num type="collectionnumber">989
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2005 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from [word], created by [Paul Pugliese], <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">5/26/2005 </date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Letters of Captain David F. Dobie <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1865 </date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">989
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Letters of Captain David F. Dobie
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1865
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">989
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Letters of Captain David F. Dobie, Accession #989, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Fred Rouleau, Kennebunk, Maine on November 12, 1940.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
      <p>Captain David F. Dobie, age 22 years, enrolled August 12, 1862, at Plattsburgh, New York, as a First Lieutenant in Company H of the 118th Regiment; he became a Captain April 30, 1864; was wounded in action
September 28 at Fort Harrison, Virginia; was mustered out with his company June 13, 1865, at Richmond, Virginia.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of forty-eight letters of Captain David F. Dobie, 1862-1865, while serving with the 118th N.Y. Infantry in the Civil War and later as Judge Advocate at brigade headquarters.
</p>
      <p>Other papers of Captain David F. Dobie consisting of general orders, returns, receipts, ordnance invoices, reports of deserters, etc. can be found in the University of Virginia Special Collections under a
separate accession number (1066). There are also letters of Captain Dobie in the New York State Library.
</p>
      <p>The following are excerpts of letters to Hattie Jillson of Watervliet, New York, regarding his military duties as a provost general, court martial advocate and a brigade inspector. They also include comments on
General Tecumseh Sherman's military strategy and the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from 1862</title><lb/>September [?] 1862, Headquarters, 118 Regiment, Camp Relay-describes his departure from Plattsburgh a week ago when he bade her goodbye and his trip with the
regiment to New York, sleeping on the railroad car floor on the way out and on the ground in New York, and from there on to Baltimore, where citizens treated them decently; says one of the men in the regiment on
picket duty captured a "secesh" who is now in jail; rumor in the camp that 500 rebels were about, which caused some of the men to fake illness; describes his tent and says "on the whole we have a good time and
lots of fun;" appear to be headed toward Washington Junction, Maryland.
</p>
      <p>September 20, 1862, Camp Wool, says has been acting counsel for one of the noncommissioned staff at a regimental court martial but doesn't know the outcome; has received her first letter since leaving
Plattsburgh; describes daily routine-5 A.M., roll call; drilling until breakfast; 8 A.M., officers' drill until dinner time; afternoon, study, dress parade and battalion drill; tells her that camp looks good with
streets laid out regularly with ditches on the side; saw about 600 Rebel prisoners taken at Harper's Ferry pass through in the cars and could hardly tell the officers from the men as they were "ragged and dirty
and some without shoes"; says his regiment narrowly missed going to Harper's Ferry as there were not enough railroad cars; a regiment that came later was sent there and captured.
</p>
      <p>September 29, 1862, Camp Wool (name changed from Camp Relay) sends photograph of himself to Hattie taken on trip to Baltimore; says his company will go on picket duty for about a week starting tomorrow; he is
only officer going as others he thinks are faking illness.
</p>
      <p>October 20, 1862, Camp Wool, has returned from picket duty and says most unpleasant part is sleeping in the night air. Last night he left his tent and slept on the ground near the fire and was quite
comfortable-camp life is beginning to become monotonous, but thinks they will be in the same place all winter.
</p>
      <p>November 7, 1862, Camp near Fort Ethan Allen, Virginia, says has been ill, threatened with jaundice; describes an incident in which a drunken picket guard fired a gun at the engineer of a train going through
and hitting him, and thinks that is why the regiment was moved to Virginia (six miles from Washington D.C.), where he thinks they will stay for the winter; says the "G. G.F. &amp; C." (Great Guns, Chills and
Fever) is a great society there; he cannot honor her wish for him to come home soon as his full dress uniform has been slept in so much "it is all played out." Has been snowing heavily and men have received India
rubber blankets, which should make them comfortable; says all they have for fun is getting together, telling stories, smoking, playing Euchre or Old Sledge, but not much drinking, as "stuff is too abominable and
sure death for the men who drink it."
</p>
      <p>November 18, 1862, Fort Ethan Allen, Virginia, mentions that he is officer of guard with comparatively light duties and Captain Bailey is officer of the day; says he is now outside General John Ellis Wool's
department and under General John Joseph Abercrombie; says General Abercrombie thinks they have "the neatest camp in the vicinity."
</p>
      <p>November 27, 1862, Fort Ethan Allen, Virginia, Thanksgiving Day-his first Thanksgiving in camp, which he enjoyed over a good turkey; has been engaged for two days as counsel for a prisoner; says the weather is
mostly cold with ice and snow and "quite a number of the most disagreeable days I ever saw."
</p>
      <p>December 7, 1862, Fort Ethan Allen, Virginia, very cold, two inches of snow, had picket duty very near the house occupied by General Franz Sigel during the second Bull Run battle; describes of two men trying to
desert in Company A of the regiment but who were brought back and are awaiting court martial.
</p>
      <p>December 12, 1862, Fort Ethan Allen, Virginia, describes soldiering as a "lazy life" with winter quarters "anything but agreeable," mostly sitting around and no drilling-guard duty and picketing; mentions that
Captain Smith of Company D has resigned and gone home, the third resignation in the regiment.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from 1863</title><lb/>May 10, 1863, Fort Union near Suffolk, Virginia-should have written sooner, but in difficult position now as have no tables and chairs, having left them behind
in move from Washington; Rebels have left this part of the country now; at first, didn't like moving, but after moving once or twice, it didn't make any difference; when they left Washington, just packed up
everything they could and left all the rest-stoves, lamps, chairs, tables desks, etc.
</p>
      <p>June 7, 1863, Camp near Suffolk, Virginia, four regiments now in his brigade-the 99th New York, 19th Wisconsin, 9th Vermont and his own, under Brigadier General Isaac Jones Wistar; now have tents and are
building arbors in front of them; relies on the New York papers to get news of what is happening anywhere; says "resigning fever has commenced in our regiment," mentions that went out on a long march, ran out of
meat, and shot so many sheep and cattle and ate so much, all men got sick; says he saw an eclipse of the moon.
</p>
      <p>August 24, 1863, Gloucester Point, Va., has been on court martial duty so hasn't yet applied for leave; wants her to come to visit with her father-no hotels, but soldiers give up their tents for visitors and
move in with others; comments on Southerners use of the word "right" as their only adjective, as in "right smart," "right much," and "right far."
</p>
      <p>Included in 1863, is a brief note on September 28 from David Dobie's brother James, advising him that he is about to start for New York and has a good many letters written to ship owners and ship masters there.
</p>
      <p>December 3, 1863, Portsmouth, Virginia, muses about family at home; says he is in "splendid quarters" now, in a confiscated house with gas and modern improvements; mentions he will be 24 years old on January
12.
</p>
      <p>December 19, 1863, Newport News, Virginia, has moved again and quarters not as good-a wall tent, no floor except ground, no stove; hears a rumor that might be sent to Texas; before recent move, several men were
joined in camp by their wives.
</p>
      <p>December 21, 1863, Newport News, Virginia, says he knows tobacco is a dirty habit but uses it to cure corns; is getting more comfortable and has sent for a small stove, now thinks they may stay there all
winter; wishes the rebellion would be over this winter, but thinks "extermination and utter subjugation seem to be the order of the day."
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from 1864 January-June</title><lb/>April 11, 1864, Bowers Hill, Virginia, says "everything in the life of a soldier changes the taste of a man very materially. Home with all its
good qualities becomes the regiment, particularly when a man has no particular spot he can legitimately call home."
</p>
      <p>April 18, 1864, Bowers Hill,Virginia, from the picket line, writes that he moves tomorrow, but doesn't know where or when; details recent movements, including crossing the Nansemond River, marching through a
small village called Chuckatuck, where they confiscated nine or ten horses, six mules and arrested a Rebel soldier; marched back to river and joined the 9th New Jersey. They were followed by one hundred Rebels who
thought they were following 150 Federals, only to discover they were about 900 strong, causing the Rebels to retreat. Next day were sent to Smithfield on [Pague] Creek, where they were sent to hunt for torpedo
boat that attempted to blow up the Minnesota; marched up the creek about three miles, destroyed four small boats, returned to regiment and embarked on transports to steam to Portsmouth-on the way saw the vessel
Atlanta, captured from the Rebels near Savannah; described it as "looking like a roof of a house floating on the water."
</p>
      <p>April 25, 1864, Yorktown, Virginia, readying for approaching campaign; estimates about 30,000 or 40,000 troops there with more coming everyday; splendid weather and expects will be underway in less than five
days.
</p>
      <p>May 3, 1864, Yorktown, Virginia, received orders that night to be ready at 6 A.M. to transfer all camp and garrison equipment to the quartermaster to be ready to march; has been recommended for captain to
replace Captain Bailey, who has resigned; not very comfortable because baggage and all except one change of clothing has been sent to the rear; nights are cold and he is writing in overcoat.
</p>
      <p>May 29, 1864, Chesapeake Hospital, Fort Monroe, Virginia, says escaped from last fight without injury but came down with rheumatism and is hardly able to walk; his rheumatism has moved to his arms and hands and
he is not very strong; has seen men from his regiment; hears rumors about something going on up at the front but doesn't know what; calls his hospital "very fine," was used as a female seminary before the war.
</p>
      <p>June 3, 1864, Chesapeake Hospital, Fort Monroe, Virginia, is still in pain and can't walk, but mostly comfortable; hasn't heard from his regiment and hasn't "The least idea of where it is"; reads the New York
papers everyday; says one Rebel General (William S. Walker) is in the hospital and had an amputation; writes, "there is something singular about amputations made here at the hospital-as a general thing, they do
poorly and a large number of them die, while most of them performed on the field are doing well. There is something strange about it."
</p>
      <p>June 14, 1864, Chesapeake Hospital, Old Point Comfort, still recovering slowly, says hospital is a great place for rumors; hears his brigade passed there last night on the way back up the James River; thinks
General Grant is going to cross over to the South side of the James and continue flank movements around Richmond.
</p>
      <p>June 21, 1864, Chesapeake Hospital, has received his commission as Captain and has applied for discharge from hospital to be mustered in. Dobie says if he can't, he shall resign at once.
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from 1864 July-December</title><lb/>July 9, 1864, Camp near Petersburg, Virginia, back with regiment, mustered in as captain, and two days later was detailed as judge advocate; not
free of rheumatism; Rebels have been shelling their camp; currently entirely without field officers, says "We have seen the rough side of soldiering this season, I assure."
</p>
      <p>July 15, 1864, camp near Petersburg, Virginia, his regiment doing duty in the city of Petersburg four days out of six; he has been detailed on a court martial as Judge Advocate; Rebels only about 3/4 mile away
and shell the woods almost everyday; says he has heard any officer mustered in after June 1 has to stay in three years after that date, but as he was made captain June 8, he doesn't intend to stay beyond his three
year commitment.
</p>
      <p>July 24, 1864, camp near Petersburg, Virginia, describes trenches around Petersburg and their use as protection; tells of "bomb proof" his company has built, have about 225 men for duty; thinks General Robert
E. Lee eventually will come out to fight or evacuate Richmond "the former would certainly end in the latter if General Lee will only try hard enough; the latter would be welcome because with Richmond in our hands
we have gone many a good mile toward our journey's end."
</p>
      <p>August 8, camp near Petersburg, Virginia, still doing duty in the trenches and had another affliction in shape of a flood after about 24 hours of rain; some persons drowned and much property lost; has read
David Copperfield and says he "seems like a very foolish little fellow to me." Hears rumors of moving to Point Lookout, New Berne, N.C. or Washington, D.C.
</p>
      <p>September 1, 1864, camp near Bermuda Hundred, Virginia, comments on the draft up north and talks to an orderly Sergeant, an Irishman who is an excellent drill master who would break in recruits so they "would
land inclined slightly forward with their heels on a line for the rest of their natural life." Comments on having read Dickens' Great Expectations expecting something great all the way through and never found it.
</p>
      <p>September 25, 1864, camp near Bermuda Hundred, Virginia, discusses at length the Chicago convention and says he will not vote for any man even "nominated by such a class of men."
</p>
      <p>October 3, 1864, camp near Chapin's Farm, Virginia, describes a skirmish September 28 when his Division was ordered out and his regiment took the advance; was ordered to take 50 men across the river, drove the
Rebels into the woods about three miles, came to an open field where he was hit in the head and neck, but thinks he will be all right.
</p>
      <p>October 24, 1864, they are now near Fort Harrison-now called Fort Burnhan (after General Hiram Burnham, who was killed inside the fort after it was taken); are living partially underground in a huge hole with
logs over and under and a chimney - "very comfortable." He also makes remarks on the character of General George Brinton McClellan.
</p>
      <p>November 10, 1864, Chapin's Farm, Virginia, the regiment has been in fight in which just half of those present were killed or taken prisoner; 101 reported missing in action, he was not present because of
unfinished court martial business; thinks they are building winter quarters where they are now.
</p>
      <p>November 13, 1864, camp near Chapin's Farm, Virginia, expects to finish court martial and then take Captain Cunningham's place as Acting Assistant Adjutant General of the Brigade.
</p>
      <p>November 25, 1864, Headquarters 2nd Brigade, describes mud in the area and officers participating in Thanksgiving dinner; doesn't expect to go north this winter; talks of the canal at Dutch Gap and says it is
almost completed; says 15,000 pounds of powder were to be placed to blow the canal into existence; asks what she thinks of General Tecumseh Sherman's march to the Atlantic Coast; thinks it will give the Rebellion
such a blow that the war will end immediately.
</p>
      <p>December 10, 1864, Headquarters 2nd Brigade, says 18th Corps has been consolidated with the white troops of the old 10th Corps and from the 24th Corps; he has been returned to duty in the old Brigade and
appointed Provost Marshall on the staff of Colonel Potter; describes his duties and says he anticipates an attack from the enemy.
</p>
      <p>December 24, 1864, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, has only 8 months and a few days remaining to serve and then "goodbye army for me"; describes duties as a Provost Marshall, complains about dinners sent to soldiers
by "good people of the north" and says there is "never enough sent to make much more than a mouthful."
</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from 1865 January-August</title><lb/>January 24, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, says Rebel gunboats came down river yesterday "with evident intention of breaking through our
obstructions and going down to City Point, but went back to Richmond after some shelling."
</p>
      <p>January 28, 1865, bitter cold weather, has been asked if he would like to go recruiting up north for two or three months; hears General William Tecumseh Sherman is really on the move and says the 25th Black
Corps has been sent to reinforce him.
</p>
      <p>February 11, 1865, Headquarters 2nd Brigade, Colonel Nichols has gone back to hospital with lung fever, so thinks his chances of going north for recruiting have diminished; hopes the Peace Commission will come
around all right.
</p>
      <p>February 17, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, hopes Spring campaign doesn't come off; hears Peace Commission has broken up but still is in hopes it will amount to something.
</p>
      <p>February 19, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, comments on "gymnastic exercises" she has been doing and says he is very much in favor because "a good many believers of female character have grown up as dolls
rather than real women" and thinks everything looks well for the war.
</p>
      <p>May 7, 1865, near Manchester, Virginia, says he is mostly "laying around with nothing to do; returned to the battlefield on May 16, 1864, and felt lucky to still be alive; includes a clipping from the New York
Herald describing a bout of drinking mint juleps by officers at his headquarters; tells of a parade on May 5 on Main Street in Richmond to receive the 5th and 2nd Corps of the Army of the Potomac.
</p>
      <p>May 21, 1865, Headquarters 2nd Brigade, says there are many "ifs" in the matter of his resigning. If he stays three more months he can go home with his regiment; reports he is on a commission in Richmond
"trying Negroes for all matter of little offenses and some grave ones. There seems to be a disposition on the part of the people to deal harshly with their former slaves, and there also is also on the part of the
Negroes a very strange idea of freedom-to their minds it means idleness." He wonders what will be done with "old Jeff and his wife's clothes" and says there is considerable difference in their sizes, she being "as
large again as her valiant husband," whom he hopes to see hanged.
</p>
      <p>May 28, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, 3rd Division, reports that he has read in the New York Herald that the officer who does the mustering out will settle accounts; thinks that mustering out will begin
soon.
</p>
      <p>June 4, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, order to muster out has been received in the Brigade and thinks it very likely his will go home this week; describes a very affecting farewell speech given to the
Division by General Charles Devens at a review of the troops. "When he came to say farewell, his expression as to his dislike to say the word and yet the necessity of it brought tears to many of the veterans
around him."
</p>
      <p>June 11, 1865, Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, 3rd Division, Manchester, Virginia, hasn't started for home yet, but thinks General Edward Otho Cresap Ord wants to have one more grand review of the whole corps;
thinks he will start for home in 3 or 4 more days; questions what he will do when out of the service; says most officers say they will do nothing for a month but visit friends; reports Colonel Nichols "has just
been here and says that the regiment has been reported as ready to be mustered out; says he will write "when we leave the sacred soil."
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>The letters of Captain David F. Dobie are in chronological order and are described in the guide chronologically year by year.
</p>
    </arrangement>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
