<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu02102">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02102::A Guide to the Papers of Edward L. Hopewell and Family)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;viu2102.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC
             "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections
             Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02102::A Guide to the Papers of
             Edward L. Hopewell and Family)//EN" "viu2102.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward L. Hopewell
            and Family, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1948</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Hopewell, Edward L. and Family, Papers
            of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">11693</num></subtitle><author>Mitzi Clark, May 2001</author></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
            Virginia Library</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By the Rector
            and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights
            reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">37 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word
         2000, created by Lottie Baker, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2/7/2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-19" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 19, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special
            Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu02102::A Guide to the
            Papers of Edward L. Hopewell and Family)//EN" "viu2102.xml"
            converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-27" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 27, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Edward L. Hopewell and
         Family, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1948</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>The Special Collections Department 
         <num type="Accession Number">11693</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections Department, University of
         Virginia Library</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Mitzi Clark, Special Collections Department, May
               2001</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of
      Virginia Library</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Special Collections, University of Virginia
         Library</repository>
      <unittitle>Papers of Edward L. Hopewell and Family, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1942-1948</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">11693</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">This collection
         consists of 274 letters, 6 postcards, and 1
         telegram.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://search.lib.virginia.edu/terms.html">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Edward L. Hopewell and Hopewell family Papers,
            1942-1948, Accession #11693, Special Collections Dept.,
            University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The Library purchased this collection from Charles
            Apfelbaum of Watchung on October 31, 2000.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Capt. Edward L. Hopewell was a physician attached to a
         medical regiment serving with the U.S. Army in the South
         Pacific during World War ll.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection consists of 191 letters he wrote from posts
         in Panama, Tonga, New Hebrides, Guadalcanal and British Samoa.
         Most of them were to his mother, Mrs. H.T. Hopewell (Rose) and
         his sister Ruth, both of Strasburg, Virginia, and his brother,
         Tilden, and his wife Billie, who were in Alaska while Tilden
         served with the Civil Aeronautics Administration. The
         collection also includes 8 letters from Effie Hopewell,
         Edward's wife, who worked during the war as a nurse in
         Nicaragua; 59 letters to Mrs. Rose Hopewell from Tilden and
         Billie; 13 to Rose and Ruth from friends and relatives, and 3
         miscellaneous letters,6 postcards and 1 telegram.</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters of Captain Edward L.
         Hopewell</title><lb/>Eleven letters from April through August of 1942
         chronicle Hopewell's departure by ship from Indiantown Gap
         Military Reservation in Pennsylvania to his arrival on islands
         in the Pacific. Because of censorship, he can give no names of
         exact locations, but he does describe life aboard ship,
         including an interesting account (May 10) of hazing rituals
         involved in crossing the equator; appearance and habits of
         natives on the lush, tropical islands where his units
         disembark; the boredom and monotony of camp life; and
         diversions such as native feasts and fishing expeditions in
         which he participates (Aug 10-Aug16).</p>
      <p>Nine of Hopewell's letters from September through November
         of 1942 continue with his descriptions on life on the islands,
         the monotony that is broken by mail and news (some of it from
         U.S. stations) on his radio. In letters of November 13 and 18,
         he tells of arrival at a new tropical but less civilized
         location, where he and several others are engaged in setting
         of a makeshift hospital for from ten to 26 patients.</p>
      <p>In December, 1942, Hopewell's seven letters tell of his
         having moved again to a different site, where the natives and
         facilities are more primitive. He still works at a makeshift
         hospital, where some patients have been very ill and where
         much improvisation of medical equipment is required. The
         soldiers are doing their own laundry and most are suffering
         from homesickness as Christmas approaches. He has heard from
         Effie, (Dec. 7) who now is teaching nursing in Spanish as an
         employee of the Rockefeller Foundation in Managua, Nicaragua,
         and seems to be adjusting better to his absence. Christmas
         dinner was two days early because of early arrival of the
         perishable food, but the radio managed to receive some carols
         on Christmas Eve, which heartened them all.</p>
      <p>From January through April of 1943, Hopewell wrote thirteen
         letters, mostly describing life in various positions on the
         island where he is stationed. This life is quite monotonous,
         with the quality of food varying from good to poor,
         entertainment sparse (although on February 28, he notes that
         entertainers Joe E. Brown and Johnny Marvin, made appearances
         there) and heat, mosquitoes and flies almost intolerable. He
         discusses various faults of "V-Mail" use, describes the
         foibles of a friend who is an astrologer, and in a letter of
         March 21, vividly describes for his Mother his first
         engagement in combat and how he was changed by the experience.
         On April 27, he is able to mention that his first station was
         Tonga, where the natives were friendly. Continuing, he writes
         that in his present spot, natives are extremely "ugly" but
         respectful after apparently having suffered horrendous
         treatment by the enemy (now driven out.)</p>
      <p>Fifteen letters (and one decorative postcard) from May
         through August of 1943 detail Hopewell's movement to a new
         address where days are delightful and nights cooler. In fact,
         he writes that he is near civilization where there is a town
         and a "Governor's mansion." He attends several dances at this
         mansion, which he describes as very pretty affairs with white
         women, attractive dresses, orchestras and delicious food.
         (June 6, June 20, July 4). He talks of frequency of air raids
         and descent into underground bomb shelters, and in several
         letters makes numerous comments on the epidemic of malaria and
         treatments, including his own 3-week bout with the disease in
         a hospital in a coconut grove, where he finds ward boys in
         attendance much superior to female nurses (August 12). He is
         bitterly disappointed in the rotation procedure by which he
         and two other medical officers were ignored. In a letter May
         9, he tells his mother he has sent her an enemy skull he found
         on a battlefield and soaked in formaldehyde for two weeks
         before mailing it. The enemy's treatment of its dead, he
         writes, contrasts sharply with the more humane care given by
         Americans.</p>
      <p>In thirteen letters from September through December of
         1943, Hopewell tell of a month's vacation on another
         "beautiful" island and describe a native reception for a "high
         government official" including food, costumes and
         entertainment. He talks of the religious life and churches on
         the island, all of which are either Protestant or Catholic. He
         complains of the irregularity of mail, encloses a printed menu
         of Thanksgiving dinner for the troops and remarks on the
         number of "practical" Christmas gifts he has received. He also
         mentions that he hears there has been some maltreatment of men
         returned from the Pacific because of illness.</p>
      <p>From January to April of 1944, Hopewell writes twelve
         letters. He mentions arriving at his 34th birthday and
         describes a party given for him at a hotel; the general
         improvement of food, movies and mail service from the U.S.,
         talent shows and denial of his request for a transfer to
         hospital duty. On February 16, he writes Aunt Ruth that he and
         his group have been moved to an isolated spot, and in April
         letters, tells of being moved again with "each island growing
         worse."</p>
      <p>In eleven letters from May through July of 1944, Hopewell
         says he now can write that he has been in New Caledonia. A
         long letter of May 21 details complications he has encountered
         concerning obtaining either a promotion, a transfer or leave.
         During this time, he becomes acting regimental surgeon, hears
         of the European invasion, and on July 2, writes of another
         move by ship back to his former APO address.</p>
      <p>Highlights of nine letters from August-September, 1944,
         include a trip on the island in which he stopped at several
         French restaurants and ended with a visit to a Bob Hope show
         (letter of Aug 16) where ten to twelve thousand troops were
         present and he was fortunate to have a fifth row, center aisle
         seat for the hour long show. An Aug 20 letter describes
         arrival of a full time Red Cross girl and plans to build a Red
         Cross recreational facility. He notes that he can now say that
         he formerly was on Emira Island in the St. Matthias group of
         islands, less that 100 miles from the equator. In a Sep 2
         letter, he describes attending a Jack Benny, Carol Landis,
         Larry Adler show ("really good, but not as good as Bob Hope"),
         and mentions concerns with securing narcotics, alcohol and
         poisons. Problems with promotion and rotation may delay his
         return home.</p>
      <p>Eleven letters cover some events in 1945 and three undated
         in the folder appear to be from Hopewell's early days in the
         service. He tells of receiving a Bronze Star recommendation
         and of purchasing a new uniform in expectation of going home
         but is disappointed to learn that instead he is being sent on
         leave to New Zealand. When there, he becomes enamored of the
         island and its people, and in a letter of Feb 14, describes a
         brief tour of the area with Agnes Davis, a Metropolitan Opera
         star traveling with the U.S.O., and two Red Cross girls. The
         group goes through geyser and hot springs country, including
         Rotorua; visits sulfur baths at Lake Taupo, marvels at catches
         of large trout in Lake Taupo, samples a baked trout at dinner
         at an Australian home, and visits caves at Waitomo, where a
         river runs through one and the ceiling is sprinkled with glow
         worms. In an undated letter, he describes the difficulties
         encountered aboard ship in an emergency appendectomy in which
         he participates, and in a letter of April 15, says he has
         learned of President Roosevelt's death. By the letter of April
         22, censorship has been lifted and he has been moved to a
         combat area where he relates his experiences going into a
         Japanese cave where much modern medical equipment has been
         stored.</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters from Effie Hopewell</title><lb/>Eight letters and one postcard from Effie Hopewell,
         Capt. Edward T. Hopewell's wife, are to Mrs. H.T. Hopewell and
         her daughter Ruth in Strasburg, Virginia The letters span the
         years from August, 1942 to January, 1945 and primarily
         describe her activities as a nurse serving in Managua,
         Nicaragua. During this time, she studies Spanish and takes
         many nursing classes to prepare to teach. Her first letter
         August 19, 1942, gives an interesting description of her trip
         from Mexico through Guatemala, where she visits many Indian
         villages, through San Salvador and on to Managua. Her last
         letter of January 2, 1945, tells of her return to her home of
         Augusta, Ga., where she plans to then go on to Strasburg to
         prepare for her husband's return.</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters of Tilden and Billie</title><lb/>1940-1942--In sixteen letters, Tilden and Billie
         describe life in Alaska, where he is an engineer for the Civil
         Aeronautics Administration. In the letters of November, 1940,
         Til tells of his trip to Alaska by both train and ship. He
         sails from Seattle, arrives at Seward, and travels to
         Anchorage, where he travels back and forth from one to the
         other during his service. He describes the beauty of Alaska,
         which he calls "America's last frontier," and the variations
         in the weather. He goes in greater detail in a March 2, 1941
         letter, where he tells of a trip to the Interior on a plane
         equipped with skis where the weather reached 36 degrees below
         zero. He saw a herd of buffalo, helped lay out a defense
         airfield and radio station 13 miles south of Big Delta, and
         visited an Indian village (Nabesna Village) near the Canadian
         border, where soil tests were made to see if the site was
         feasible for a landing site. While there, he was a guest of
         the Chief, and participated in an Indian dance. He makes
         arrangements for Billie to fly to Alaska to join him (Mar 16,
         1941), and on Aug 15, 1941 describes their living arrangements
         in a 1-room log house in Big Delta, where an "airport is
         springing out of the wilderness." On May 12, 1942, Billie
         tells "Mother Hopewell" they now are living in a 14 by 20 foot
         hut in Gulkana, which is humming with International Highway,
         railroad, bridge and airport construction underway. She is the
         only woman in camp. June letters of 1942 from Til and Billie
         tell of a bombing at Dutch Harbor 1,100 miles away from their
         camp and mention that letter censorship has begun. On Aug 23,
         1942, Til writes he has bought a rifle and plans to shoot
         moose. The couple now are living in Big Delta in a regular
         house.</p>
      <p>February-May 1943--eleven letters in which Til writes to
         his mother from Seattle, where he has been positioned from
         Alaska before going to Vancouver, B.C., where he has been
         assigned to duty with the Royal Canadian Air Force. He spends
         two months in Vancouver on a survey team before he goes to
         Seattle in preparation for a return to Anchorage, Alaska as an
         assistant chief of construction section, with a budget of 15
         million.</p>
      <p>June-December 1943--twelve letters from Tilden (one from
         Billie) mostly to Mother and Ruth. Til's letters primarily are
         from Anchorage, Alaska, where he has taken up flying and is
         looking for and has successfully found housing so Billie can
         return after an absence of eight months. On September 30, he
         describes a hunting trip to Farewell, Alaska, where he killed
         a 600-pound grizzly bear, a 100 pound mountain sheep, and a
         1200 pound moose. He also saw caribou and heard the howling of
         wolves. On October 5, he tells of cutting up the meat for
         freezer storage, pointing out that law prohibits selling moose
         meat, but it can be traded for other commodities. On October
         24 he tells more about shooting the grizzly. On November 9,
         Billie writes Mrs. Hopewell describing her long trip to Alaska
         by train and boat.</p>
      <p>1944--twelve letters and one card are from Tildon and
         Billie to Mrs. Hopewell, and one is from Billie to "Aunt
         Lizzie." All but two are from Anchorage, Alaska and describe
         the couple's day to day life there, including their work,
         problems with starting flower gardens, variations in Alaskan
         ivory and a 1500-mile trip Tilden takes through Alaska
         (including Farewell, McGrath, Unalakleet, Moses Point, Nome,
         Kotzebue, Aniak[chak?], Bethel and Iliamna . On November 3,
         Til writes from New York City where he has been transferred
         and where the couple have set up housekeeping in Jackson
         Heights on Long Island.</p>
      <p>1945-1946--Eight letters to Mrs. Hopewell from Til and
         Billie tell of their adjustment to New York City life,
         including "meatless Tuesdays " decreed by Mayor LaGuardia
         (January 12), of Til's business trips to Massachusetts and
         West Virginia, of their personal visits to Billie's mother in
         Washington, D.C., and Til's visit with his own mother in
         Strasburg, Virginia In 1946, Til is transferred to work in
         Torreon, Coachuila, Mexico, and his letters from there and
         from San Luis Potosi tell of the climate, the difficulties
         encountered with working conditions and employees, and life on
         the plazas. He mentions (May 28, from Torreon, Coachuila),
         that he is pleased Effie and Ed, who are reunited in this
         country, have named their baby son after him, and goes on to
         discuss politics by saying "John L. Lewis has gotten this
         country in a mess."</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Letters to Rose and Ruth Hopewell from
         Friends and Family</title><lb/>Thirteen letters are from friends and relatives --one
         from late 1942, and the rest from 1943. Most discuss family
         matters, although two to Ruth--8-13-43 and 8-29-43--are from
         her friend Pete Preston, who is in training in Air Force
         Officer Candidate School in Miami, Fla., and describes some of
         his experiences there. A letter Sep 2, 1943, to Rose from
         Capt. Robert Jerles describes Edward Hopewell's participation
         in the Battle of Guadalcanal where, he writes, "your son did a
         magnificent job." On Nov 13, 1943, Rose's sister May writes
         from Roanoke describing a trip she took to Marianna, Georgia
         to visit her son in service and his living conditions on the
         base. In an undated letter to Rose from Roanoke, May tells of
         a visit home at the same time by four servicemen, all of whom
         grew up together--her son Jack from Australia; one from Italy,
         another from England, and another from North Africa.</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Miscellaneous Letters</title><lb/>There are three miscellaneous letters, two in 1934 which
         deal with a problem involving $5.48 which a neighbor is
         attempting to collect from the estate of Dr. E.T. Hopewell
         (father of Edward) for damage to window panes and draperies in
         his house by Edward when he was practicing casting a fishing
         line.</p>
      <p><title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" render="bold" xlink:href="">Postcards and Telegrams</title><lb/>One telegram is from Edward Hopewell on his Mother's
         birthday. Six postcards, mainly to Rose, are from traveling
         friends and relatives, all from locales in the southeast
         United States. There also in this folder is a booklet for
         "Mendenhall's Chill and Fever Tonic."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>These letters are arranged chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e256">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Edward L. Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1944- April
               1942</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
          <physdesc>9 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e266">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Edward L. Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October
               1944-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          <physdesc>2 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e276">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Effie Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1942-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e284">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Effie Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1942-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e290">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters from Tilden and Billie Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1940-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          <physdesc>5 folders</physdesc>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e300">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Letters to Rose and Ruth Hopewell, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1942-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e308">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Miscellaneous Letters, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1929-1934</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e316">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Postcards and Telegrams, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1941-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
