<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viu03782">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViU">PUBLIC "-//University of Virginia::Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViU::viu03782::Papers of Robert Larimer)//EN" "viu03782.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert Larimer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1861-1865</date></titleproper><subtitle id="sort">Larimer, Robert Papers of
<num type="collectionnumber">38-129
</num></subtitle></titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2004 By the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">[ca. ##29 Kilobytes]
</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from [...], created by niyi, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 11/2/2004</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert Larimer, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1861-1865</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections<lb/>The University of Virginia Library
<num type="Accession Number">38-129
</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/uva-sc.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2004
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/uva-sc_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository">Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of Robert Larimer
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1861-1865
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Accession number">38-129
</unitid>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>See the 
            <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.library.virginia.edu/policies/use-of-materials">
            University of Virginia Library’s use policy.</extref></p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Papers of Robert Larimer, Accession #38-129, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>The papers were a gift to the Library of Mrs. Richard Fell, prior to 1938.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of papers and diaries of Robert Larimer, who was born in Perry County, Ohio, in 1841, and left his farm there to serve in Co. C., 62nd Regiment, Ohio infantry, during the Civil War.
</p>
      <p>The first diary (1862 December 31 to 1863 December 1) describes his service in the Union army; camp life; and the seige of Charleston (1863) including bombardment of Morris Island and the attack on Ft. Wagner;
Springfield rifles' target practice and boat drills; and voting for pro-Union candidates. The second diary (1865 January 1 to December 3) describes the siege of Richmond; the hanging of deserters; reviews by Union
Generals and President Lincoln; capture of Fort Gregg, Va.; the Appomattox Campaign and surrender; visits to Richmond, Va. and duties until mustered out; his captain's mugging; visit to a "photograph gallery", and
purchasing land in Minnesota under the Homestead Law. There are scattered references to freed slaves and African-American troops.
</p>
      <p>The papers also contain military records including discharges, appointments, and special orders; a list, 1865, of contributors to a fund to buy a sword and watch for the captains; three newspaper clippings and
a railroad ticket. Of interest is a treatise "The slaveholders' rebellion" giving detailed accounts from November 10 1860 to January 5 1861, of activities in the South with a conclusion condemning the rebellion on
moral grounds. General John Gibbon is a correspondent.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e128">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Military Papers
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>January 29, 1864 -- Discharge from the U.S. Army as a corporal from Samuel B. Larimer's Co. C, 62nd Reg. Ohio Infantry Volunteers, by reason of reenlisting as a veteran volunteer.
</p>
          <p>March, 1865--Two agreements of members of Co. C.--one to purchase a watch as a gift for presentation to Samuel B. Larimer, ex-captain of Co. C. 62nd Ohio Vols., and another to purchase a sword for Capt. H.K.
Hitchcock.
</p>
          <p>April 9, 1865--General Orders-a commendation from Headquarters, 1st Division, A.C., in the field, signed by Brig. Gen. R.S. Foster, Commander, commending men for achievements April 2 at Appomattox Court House,
where General Lee's armies were shut off.
</p>
          <p>June 13, 1865--a letter from John Gibbon, Maj. Gen Vols., praising 24th Army Corps men in writing "by your discipline, long marches and hard fighting, you have established for yourselves a name second to none
in the army." Newspaper clips concerning the 62nd Ohio regiment
</p>
          <p>August 3, 1865 from Headquarters, Department of Virginia, Richmond--special orders consolidating the 62nd and 67th Ohio Volunteers--signed Maj. Gen. Alfred Howe Terry
</p>
          <p>November 1, 1865--a certificate appointing Robert Larimer a First Sergeant in Co. F of the 67th Regiment of the Ohio Volunteer Infantry.
</p>
          <p>December 7, 1865--Discharge papers for Robert Larimer from Co. F, 67th Regiment, Ohio Infantry Volunteers.
</p>
          <p>A handwritten treatise entitled " The Slaveholders' Rebellion" giving detailed accounts from Nov 10, 1860-January 5, 1861, of activities in the South leading up to the Civil War--also a paper condemning the
rebellion on moral grounds.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="d1e149">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Diaries
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e153">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1862-1863
</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The diary covers the dates December 31, 1862 through March, 1863. Entries primarily detail Larimer's travels sailing from Norfolk to Moorhead Station, then by train to New Bern, N.C, on by ship to Beaufort,
S.C. and then on to St. Helena Island 2 miles north of Hilton Head, where he disembarked and stayed throughout February. He remains on St Helena throughout March and in April, is back on ship to where the 62nd
Regiment camps on Folly Island; mentions some activity around Fort Sumter, with the Rebels located on Morris Island; some fire as the Rebels try to resurrect the sunken ironclad [Keokuk] April 16, 1863.
</p>
            <p> In May, 1863, Larimer describes the building of defenses and fatigue duty. June, 1863, sees some sea action, including spotting a Rebel ship that has gone aground; some shelling by the Rebels. July 10-11,
1863, describes action of Union gunboats keeping up steady fire on Morris Island in Charleston Harbor; some infantry storm the fort July 18 with heavy losses. July 19, Union wounded returned by boats to Hilton
Head and Beaufort following the attack; describes losses of storming party as 1,500 killed, wounded or missing; reports that in 62nd Regiment, 155 were killed wounded or missing, and in his Co. C, 19 killed,
wounded or missing; shelling continues and ironclads engage in activities.
</p>
            <p> In August 1863, he tells of constant shelling, much sickness in camp. August 22, steady fire all day on Fort Sumter with a boat bringing a flag of truce at night; August 23, 1863, the whole ironclad fleet
operating at daybreak--a slackening of fire in the evening; August 27, 1863, steady fire all day, his regiment in front in entrenchments.
</p>
            <p> September 2, 1863, ironclads bombard Forts Gregg and Wagner with Rebel works heavily damaged and guns silenced; September 7-enemy forces evacuate Forts Gregg and Wagner on Charleston's Morris Island. U.S.
forces occupy Forts Wagner and Gregg. September 8, the ironclad fleet attacks Sullivan Island batteries with success. September 20, Federal forces shell Fort Johnson and Castle Pinckney
</p>
            <p> In October 1863, Larimer receives news of fighting at Chattanooga; every day, slow fire of Rebels on Union works at Cummings Point; October 29, regiment marches to south end of Folly Island where it pitches
tents. November, 1863, drills and usual routine. December 1, 1863, regiment moves to Hilton Head Island.
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item" id="d1e173">
          <did>
            <unittitle>
              <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1865
</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>On January 1, 1865, Larimer is encamped in front of Richmond, with rebel camps in view. January 25, mentions that three Rebel ironclads attempt to pass the Federal fleet and go down river but are attacked; one
sunk, two run ashore and abandoned. February 14, receives news of capture of Charleston, S.C. February 17, reports that two men from the 2nd Division were hung in front of the men for crimes of murder, robbery and
desertion. March 1-11,1865, entries mention his learning of President Lincoln's inauguration, Sherman's burning of Columbia, S.C. and Jubal Early's defeat by General Phillip Sheridan in the Shenandoah Valley
</p>
            <p> March 12, reports being reviewed that day by Generals Ulysses S. Grant, Edward Otho Cresap Ord, John Gibbons and Robert S. Foster. March 25, troops ordered to get ready to move. March 26, participates in a
review by President Lincoln and his family and General Grant. March 27, receive orders to move; marched all night, crossing the James and Appomattox. March 28, halted at 6:00 a.m. and resumed march at 11:00 a.m.;
column consists of two Divisions, 25th and 26th corps; marched two and one-half miles north of [Hatchers Run ?] and bivouacked for the night. March 29, moved one mile north westward from the line on the left of
the 6th corps, relieving the 2nd corps; detailed for picket duty; hears brisk musketry in the direction of Petersburg. March 30, relieved from picket duty at 11:00 a.m.; tells of skirmishing. March 31, in line at
breastworks all day
</p>
            <p> April 1, quiet on the picket lines; reports battle opens on Petersburg line at 11:00 p.m. and continues all night. April 2, Rebels open fire at 2:00 a.m., but are driven back at daybreak and hemmed in by
Sheridan; 2,200 captured. April 3-15, describes in some detail the troop movements of his division and engagement in the final battles at Petersburg and Appomattox; tells of poor weather conditions; of the march
toward Richmond with a halt near Farmville and an engagement there with the enemy; mentions bivouacking at Appomattox Court House, the attempts to find rations for the captured Rebel troops and difficulties of
managing captured army; notes surrender of General Robert E. Lee at 4:00 p.m. April 9; mentions Abraham Lincoln's assassination. April 16, writes of departure of his unit from Appomattox Station on march to
Richmond.
</p>
            <p> May, 1865, short entries include some brief descriptions of activities while encamped outside of Richmond--inspections, drills and weather. June, some routine camp activities with a mention June 9 of a beating
and robbery outside the camp of Capt. H. K. Hitchcock. July, more routine camp activities with some talk of going home; visits to Richmond; his group leaves camp at the end of the month and goes by boat to City
Point
</p>
            <p> Entries in August and September 1865, mostly tell of movements of individuals, such as transfers, leaves, detachments from service and making mustering out rolls. The last entry is for December 3, 1865, while
Larimer is working on mustering out rolls
</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
