<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vino00085">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00085:: Papers of J. Henry McCoy 1918-1976)//EN" "vino00085.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of J. Henry McCoy, <date>1918-1976</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">McCoy, J. Henry, Papers of
<num type="collectionnumber">1-1B5
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2008 By Rector and Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Cathy Jones, <date>09 January 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English. 
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of J. Henry McCoy, <date>1918-1976</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections
<num type="Collection Number">1-1B5
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2008
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">A Guide to the Papers of J. Henry McCoy
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1918-1976
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">1-1B5
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Size" encodinganalog="300$a">1 Hollinger document case
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">McCoy, J. Henry
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Open to researchers without restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Questions on literary property rights should be directed to the Special Collections Librarian.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Papers of J. Henry McCoy, [Box number], [Folder number], Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, Virginia.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift from J. Henry McCoy on March 16, 1978. 
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Dr. J. Henry McCoy, Jr. attended Norfolk Division of William and Mary (now Old Dominion University) and graduated from Medical College of Virginia. In 1968, he was appointed to the Old Dominion University Board of Visitors. Later McCoy was appointed Vice-Chairman of the Local Board of Tidewater Community College. During the mid 1980's, Dr. McCoy represented the Kempsville Borough on the Virginia Beach City Council. He became Mayor of Virginia Beach in 1984. His term as Mayor ended in 1986. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The papers of J. Henry McCoy date from 1918 to 1976. They document McCoy's professional life as a member of the ODU Board of Visitors and as Vice Chair of Tidewater Community College. This collection contains McCoy's correspondence with Old Dominion College / University and Tidewater Community College, the Commonwealth of Virginia, Virginia-Tidewater Dental Association, Alpha Kappa Psi, the US Congress, and Associated Naval Architects. Included also are generic/organization letters, proposals, job descriptions, program progress reports, meeting minutes, community college general information, and postcards that McCoy collected. McCoy's scrapbook materials include newspaper articles about McCoy's appointment to the Board of Visitors and letters of congratulations on the accomplishment; the hiring and resignation of James L. Bugg's Presidency of Old Dominion University; ODU students' concern over a racist hiring process and other general news about the University.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head><persname encodinganalog="600$a">McCoy, J. Henry</persname>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Universities and colleges</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Community colleges</subject>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Correspondence</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive">29 June 1967-7 May 1976
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:1
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains correspondence with Old Dominion University including several letters related to the Division of Technology Dental Hygiene and Assisting Programs; The Alumni Association; Office of the President; The Mace and Crown; Student Caucus, School of Continuing Studies, and the Board of Visitors. Correspondence with the Commonwealth of Virginia: Governor's Office; Senate; and the House of Delegates. Correspondence also holds letters from Alpha Kappa Psi; The US Congress; and Associated Naval Architects.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive">22 November 1970-25 June 1974
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:2
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains correspondence with Tidewater Community College and others from a variety of cities and companies in Virginia in relation to Tidewater Community College. Specifically: The Virginia Beach Sun; the Virginia Pilot; Virginia Department of Community Colleges; Virginia State Chamber of Commerce; Williams and Tazewell &amp; Associates, Inc.; Dr. Robert J. Kirkman; House of Delegates; House of Representatives; Association of Community College Trustees; Virginia Beach City Public Schools; and Virginia Beach City Clerk.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Old Dominion University Board of Visitors
<unitdate type="inclusive">6 November 1975-21 July 1976
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:3
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Includes generic letters addressed to the BOV members that discuss issues such as: how to select a new president using a search committee; search committee planning and candidates; and a profile of the University's future. Other documents include resumes and an analysis of the 1976 General Assembly.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Meeting of the Executive Committee, ODU Board of Visitors
<unitdate type="inclusive">14 January 1976
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:4
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains papers revolving around the meetings of the Executive Committee beginning in January of 1976. These deal directly with the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors. Discussed are topics related to dates of upcoming meetings; agenda; progress reports; presidency job description; draft letter to the Ambassador of Iran; Meeting minutes; and one letter to McCoy regarding a school of optometry.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Old Dominion University and Intercollegiate Athletics
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:5
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Provides a look into Intercollegiate athletics at Old Dominion University. These pieces illustrate the Four Year Plan for Intercollegiate Athletics developed by the Board of Visitors. This plan was devised in 1974 and devised in 1975. The memos in this series show correspondence between the Board of Visitors and Vice President for Student Affairs, and ODU President's Office. Also included is information about the Eastern College Athletic Conference.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Virginia Community College System
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:6
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Holds information about the Virginia Community College System. In general, the papers include information on policies, procedures, regulations and the curriculum offered by the system.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous ("The Mission of the University", By-laws of the ODU Board of Visitors, In-state tuition application)
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:7
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains one document of Old Dominion University's Mission Statement, Codes or Amendments of the Board of Visitors of Old Dominion, and one Domicile Application.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Postcards from Camp Lee, Virginia
<unitdate type="inclusive">1918
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:8
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains photo-postcards. They include: The School of Arms, Knights of Columbus Hall, Old Dominion College Administration Building and Hughes Hall. There is also a postcard/souvenir folder of Camp Lee with photos of General Headquarters, Popular Place in Camp (Theatre), Officer's Club and its interior, Interior of Bakery, YWCA Hostess House, the Fire Department, Base Hospital, Red Cross Building, and photos of soldiers.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Appointment to Board of Visitors
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:9
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Relates to McCoy's appointment to the Board of Vistors at Old Dominion University. These includes news releases on his induction, letters of congratulations from Old Dominion Board of Visitors, President, and Governor, dinner invitation from Alfred B. Rollins, and other letters thanking him for the acceptance of the position. Also one document shows the oath from the office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
</p>
<p>Also included in this folder are news articles from the Virginia Pilot and Ledger- Star newspapers. Each article presents information on James L. Bugg, a former president of the Old Dominion University. The articles document his beginning as president and ultimate resignation on behalf of the ODU Board of Visitors.
</p>
<p>Additionally this folder contains news releases related to the Leland Peterson affair. Briefly, this refers to the suspected unfair treatment by some of Dr. Peterson, former president of Old Dominion College. His position was called into question after a story was published in the student magazine "The Gadfly." These articles document the students' protests and concerns as well as those of Dr. Peterson, the hearing of the case by The Old Dominion Board, opinions on the case, and editorials.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>President James L. Bugg, Jr.
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:10
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Contains articles concerning news of Old Dominion University in general. It provides information on the activities of students at the university, the programs that the college has approved of and will participate in, graduation speakers, and sports.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Student Protest -- Leland Peterson and the Immaculate Deception
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:11
</container>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Old Dominion University News -- General
<unitdate type="inclusive">1968
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1:12
</container>
</did>
</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>





