<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vino00046">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00046::A Guide to the Papers of Augustus C. Johnson)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vino00046.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old
             Dominion University::Perry Library::Special
             Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00046::A Guide to the
             Papers of Augustus C. Johnson)//EN"
             "vino00046.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Augustus C. Johnson 
            <date>1970-2000</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Johnson, Augustus, C., Papers,
            1970-2000 
            <num type="collectionnumber">MG 71</num></subtitle>
            <author>Mel Frizzell</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By Rector and
            Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">26.5 kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word 97. Machine-readable finding aid created by Kathleen V,
         Smith. Date of source: 
         <date>May, 2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-17">Feb 17, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry
            Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00046::A
            Guide to the Papers of Augustus C. Johnson)//EN"
            "vino00046.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Augustus C. Johnson 
         <date>1970-2000</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections and University Archives
         <num type="Collection Number">MG 71</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion
         University</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         &contact;
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Mel Frizzell</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library,
      Old Dominion University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University </repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">The Papers of Augustus C. Johnson 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1970-2000</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">MG 71</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">One Hollinger
         Document Case.</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>Open to researchers without restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Questions on literary property rights should be directed
            to the Special Collections Librarian.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[Identification of item], Box [insert number], Folder [insert number and title], The Papers of Augustus C. Johnson, Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Norfolk, VA 23529.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Gift of Augustus C. Johnson, July 1999</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Augustus C. Johnson was born in Covington, Kentucky in
         1914. He graduated from Southampton High School in 1930. After
         his father lost his farm, Johnson went to Washington to work
         for the Government Printing Office in 1931. That same year, he
         began taking night classes at George Washington University
         (GWU) and joined the Army National Guard.</p>
         <p>Johnson spent World War II working in a war plant and a
         West Coast shipyard. He also spent a year during the war
         working as a civilian employee for the Army Engineers in the
         Alaskan War Zone.</p>
         <p>After the war, Johnson returned to education. At GWU, he
         taught mathematics and received his Master's degree. In 1948,
         he went on to become an assistant professor of physics at
         Robert College in Istanbul, Turkey. There he met his wife,
         Constantia Hommann, and fathered their daughter, Muriel.</p>
         <p>Johnson spent the next decade working as Research Director
         and Senior Scientist at Booz-Allen Applied Research. He worked
         on arms control, guided missiles, and computer projects, as
         well as a data collection system for NASA. He worked a year
         for Doxiadis Systems Development Corporation as Director of
         Comparative Urban Studies. Johnson then spent another decade
         working for the MITRE Corporation as Solar Energy Group
         Leader. His work included environmental and conservation
         studies, housing and urban development projects, and
         developing government programs in solar energy research and
         development. Later, he served three years working as Chief
         Statistician for the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation,
         where he retired in 1980.</p>
         <p>Johnson began his political work in 1952. He began by doing
         precinct work for the Democratic Party. The following year he
         became a member of the Fairfax County Democratic Committee.
         Later, he became Fairfax County Democratic Chairman. He was
         chairman of the Tenth District Democratic Committee and a
         member of the Virginia State Democratic Committee. In 1962 and
         1964, Johnson ran as the Democratic candidate for Congress
         from the Tenth District. Years later Johnson served on the
         Madison County Democratic Committee. In addition to his work
         in the Democratic Party, Johnson also served on environmental
         and United Nations committees, and the American Civil
         Liberties Union (ACLU).</p>
         <p>Johnson wrote political editorials for the Northern
         Virginia Sun in the early 1970s, and continued expressing his
         political views through letters to the editor in the 1990s. He
         also took his politics to the internet with a Virginia
         political web page in the late 1990s. </p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>This collection consists of editorials written by Augustus
         Johnson for the 
         <title render="italic">Northern Virginia Sun</title> in 1970
         and 1971 and letters to the editor of several papers from 1993
         to 2000.</p>
         <p>Editorials favor the Democratic Party. They relate mainly
         to Northern Virginia politics and to a lesser extent Virginia
         State and national politics. Specific topics include: the
         Northern Virginia Elections; the goals of Fairfax County; a
         proposed prison in Green Spring, Virginia; the two-party
         system; party primaries and conventions; redistricting and
         reapportionment; urban sprawl; reformation of the U.S. House
         of Representatives; the welfare system; a constitutional
         amendment to allow 18-20 year olds to vote; Virginia
         obstructionism; populists and populism; campaign financing;
         and the Byrd machine. Some of the names mentioned in his
         columns are: Harry Byrd; Joel Broyhill; George C. Rawlings,
         Jr.; William S. Hoofnagle; Bill Stanhagen; John Lindsay, Henry
         Howell; Mills Godwin; Harold Ickes; George Kostel; Albert
         Gore; Fred Harris; Audrey Moore; Martha Pennino; Rufus
         Phillips; Joe Alexander; Allen Magazine; Herb Harris; Jim
         Scott; Ginny McEnearney; Warren Barry; Vincent Callahan; Clive
         DuVal; Tuffy Leemans; Linwood Holton; Elwood Clements; William
         Hassan; Paul Beeson; Norris Shealy; Ed Holland; John Melnick;
         Robert Weinberg; Mary Marchall; Dick Chew; G. Harrold
         Carswell; Richard Nixon; Judge Haynsworth; and Lewis
         Powell.</p>
         <p>Letters to the editor promote such political candidates as
         Chuck Robb, Mary Sue Terry, Mark Warner, and Doris Lackey, and
         oppose candidates such as Oliver North, George Allen, and John
         Warner. Other topics include: the federal deficit; Clinton's
         deficit reduction program and tax bill; health care and
         insurance; term limits for congress; special interest money
         and PAC's; Clinton's Welfare Reform Bill; illegal
         contributions to George Allen's campaign; abortion; James
         Gilmore's promise to do away with the automobile property tax;
         the global economy; the 1994 Republican Contract with America;
         the line-item veto; flag burning; opposing use of the
         Confederate flag; campaign reform; gun control laws; and
         democrats and republicans. Other names mentioned in his
         letters are Douglas Wilder; Joe Mann; George Grayson; Franklin
         D. Roosevelt; J. Michael Sharman; Butch Davies; Newt Gingrich;
         Carlton Heston; Kenneth Starr; Michael Eisner of Disney;
         Eugene McCarthy; Thomas M. Davis; Pat Robertson; Jerry
         Falwell; and Andy Young.</p>
         <p>This collection also contains a copy of Johnson's Virginia
         Politics web page updated on February 2, 2000 and biographical
         information on Johnson. His web page includes opinions on
         George W. Bush, George Allen, prayer in schools, national
         debt, Governor Gilmore, Campaign reform, flag burning, the
         First Amendment, the right to bear arms, and Tom Davis.
         Johnson's biographical material includes a short biography,
         milestones in his life, a guide to his personal and political
         papers in the Fairfax County Library, a program to "Celebrate
         Connie &amp; Gus" in June 1998, and an essay about "Breaking
         the Byrd Grip."</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <descgrp type="add">
         <head>Related Materials</head>
         <p>Additional papers regarding Augustus C. Johnson's
         personal, professional, and political life from 1931-1992
         may be found at:</p>
         <p>The Fairfax County Public Library. 12000 Government
         Center Parkway, Suite 324, Fairfax, VA 22035. (703)
         324-3100</p>
      </descgrp>
      <dsc type="in-depth">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <title render="italic">The Northern Virginia
                  Sun,</title>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">September-December
                  1970</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 1</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <title render="italic">The Northern Virginia
                  Sun,</title>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">January-April
                  1971</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 2</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <title render="italic">The Northern Virginia
                  Sun,</title>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">May-August 1971</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 3</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <title render="italic">The Northern Virginia
                  Sun,</title>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">September-December
                  1971</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 4</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Letters to Editors, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">
               1993-1994</unitdate></unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 5</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Letters to Editors, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive">
               1995-2000</unitdate></unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 6</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Web Page (updated February 2,
               2000)</unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 7</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="file">
            <did>
               <unittitle>ACJ Bio</unittitle>
               <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder 8</container>
            </did>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
