<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vino00019">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00019::A Guide to the Papers of Robert M. Rose 1809-1947)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vino00019.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old
             Dominion University::Perry Library::Special
             Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00019::A Guide to the
             Papers of Robert M. Rose 1809-1947)//EN"
             "vino00019.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert M. Rose 
            <date>1809-1947</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Rose, Robert M. 
            <num type="collectionnumber">MG 23</num></subtitle>
            <author>Susan E. Yates</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2001 By Rector and
            Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">34 kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word 97. Machine-readable finding aid created by Tonia
         Graves.</creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-17">Feb 17, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry
            Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00019::A
            Guide to the Papers of Robert M. Rose 1809-1947)//EN"
            "vino00019.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Robert M. Rose 
         <date>1809-1947</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections 
         <num type="Collection Number">MG 23</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion
         University</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2001</date>
         &contact;
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Special Collections Staff</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Perry Library,
      Old Dominion University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University </repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Robert M. Rose 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1809-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">MG 23</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 Hollinger
         Documents Case</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <origination label="Provenance">Gift of Mrs. Carolyn H.
         Tunstall, November 18, 1977</origination>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions on the copying or photocopying
            of the papers. However, copies from the collection may be
            used for publication only with the expressed written
            permission of the University Archivist. Other questions on
            literary property rights should be directed to the
            Archivist.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Publication Rights</head>
            <p>EDIT ME!</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[Identification of item], Robert M. Rose, [Box number],
            [folder number], Special Collections, Perry Library, Old
            Dominion University, Norfolk, Virginia</p>
         </prefercite>
         <custodhist>
            <head>Provenance</head>
            <p>The Papers of Robert M. Rose belonging to the Old
            Dominion University Department of Archives and Manuscripts
            were donated by Mrs. Carolyn H. Tunstall, a former faculty
            member at the University. These papers are part of a larger
            family collection, the bulk of which was given in 1950 to
            the U.S. Naval Academy Museum in Annapolis, Maryland. Prior
            to the date of this former gift, the papers were in the
            possession of George H. Rose, one of the two sons of Dr.
            Robert W. Rose (Series II). Dr. Rose's second son, Robert
            W. Rose, Jr., married the sister of Dr. Robert B. Tunstall
            (Series III). Dr. Tunstall's son Charles, married his
            cousin by this marriage, Jane W. Rose. Mrs. Charles
            Tunstall is represented in Series IV and is the donor of
            the gift to the U.S. Naval Academy Museum. Mrs. Carolyn
            Tunstall, the donor of the gift to the Old Dominion
            University Department of Archives and Manuscripts, is
            married to the nephew of Mrs. Charles Tunstall.</p>
         </custodhist>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Born in the last quarter of the eighteenth century, Robert
         M. Rose was the son of a Norfolk, Virginia family. Apparently
         there was something of the sea tradition in the Rose family.
         There was an uncle, Alexander F. Rose who captained his own
         ship and under whom, Robert's brother Alexander began his
         career in 1830. Much earlier than this, Robert Rose enlisted
         in the U.S. Navy as midshipman on board the USS Independence
         in 1809. While serving on the Independence, Rose attained the
         rank of lieutenant and continued in this capacity in
         subsequent assignments on the USS Columbus and the USS
         Terrier.</p>
         <p>By 1815 Rose had married his wife Mary, a woman also from
         the Norfolk area. As a naval officer, Rose of course was away
         from his family for many months out of the year. Indeed his
         son Robert W. Rose was born in the summer of 1823 while he was
         stationed in Key West with the Terrier. The anxiety caused by
         these extended periods of separation runs throughout Mary's
         letters. Aside from maintaining several rental properties
         belonging to the family, Mary attended to the duties of her
         own household. Periodic outbreaks in the community of diseases
         such as yellow fever were always a source of concern for a
         mother with a young child. There is also some evidence that
         Robert financially supported his brother Alexander while he
         was in school. This went contrary to Mary's way of thinking.
         She felt that Alexander was given too much to study and too
         little honest work.</p>
         <p>Sometime in 1830, Mary and their son Robert began living in
         Portsmouth near Fort Nelson with the family of Lieutenant
         Joseph Smoot. In April of that same year, Rose had been
         promoted to Commander. References in Mary's letters dated
         immediately after this time indicate that Rose had visited
         with his family prior to taking command of the USS Erie.
         Within three months of his new command, Rose contracted yellow
         fever and died at a West India Station on August 27, 1830. The
         last letter in the collection from Mary was written the day
         before her husband's death and is especially poignant as it
         contains the welcome news of their son's recovery from the
         same malady.</p>
         <p>The Papers of Robert M. Rose belonging to the Old Dominion
         University Department of Archives and Manuscripts were donated
         by Mrs. Carolyn H. Tunstall, a former faculty member at the
         University. These papers are part of a larger family
         collection, the bulk of which was given in 1950 to the U.S.
         Naval Academy Museum in Annapolis, Maryland. Prior to the date
         of this former gift, the papers were in the possession of
         George H. Rose, one of the two sons of Dr. Robert W. Rose
         (Series II). Dr. Rose's second son, Robert W. Rose, Jr.,
         married the sister of Dr. Robert B. Tunstall (Series III). Dr.
         Tunstall's son Charles, married his cousin by this marriage,
         Jane W. Rose. Mrs. Charles Tunstall is represented in Series
         IV and is the donor of the gift to the U.S. Naval Academy
         Museum. Mrs. Carolyn Tunstall, the donor of the gift to the
         Old Dominion University Department of Archives and
         Manuscripts, is married to the nephew of Mrs. Charles
         Tunstall.</p>
         <p>The papers in the collection are original holographs with
         the exceptions of folders in Series I: Sub series C. Folders
         24 and 25 are photocopies from the National Archives of
         materials relating to Commander Rose and his wife in the U.S.
         Naval Records of Officers. Folder 26 contains a carbon
         typescript of documents held at the U.S. Naval Academy
         Museum.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>The Papers of Robert M. Rose is a collection of family
         papers including the business records and personal
         correspondence of four Norfolk families in the Rose-Tunstall
         lineage. The papers are arranged according to family into four
         series; however, the focal point of the collection is the
         papers of Commander Robert M. Rose.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Although Series I does not contain correspondence written
         by Robert Rose, there are multiple letters from his wife Mary
         and from several naval and business acquaintances. Those
         letters authored by Mary provide an insight into the Rose
         family, containing personal reminiscences as well as daily
         accounts of household and local affairs. There are, in
         addition, frequent references to the families and ship
         assignments of other naval officers. For example, Mary in her
         letter dated April 12, 1823 (Folder 1), recounts a rather
         grisly newspaper story concerning the pirating of a ship and
         the death of its captain at Campeachy. These and similar
         examples from Norfolk and naval life ca. 1820-1830 may prove
         of interest to the social historian.</p>
         <p>Series II contains the correspondence and business papers
         of Commander Rose's son, Dr. Robert W. Rose. Although there
         are letters from family members and friends,, here as in the
         first series, there is no correspondence actually written by
         Dr. Rose. What could be considered as an exception to this is
         a copy of a legal document written on behalf of Dr. Rose and
         addressed to the 1893 Provisional Congress of the Confederate
         States (Folder 32). The document concerns the loss of six
         runaway slaves for whom Dr. Rose seeks financial redress from
         the Provisional Congress. From the remaining correspondence
         and papers, especially those in Folders 33 and 34, numerous
         genealogical references to the Rose family can be found.</p>
         <p>Series III and IV include the papers of Dr. Robert B.
         Tunstall and his son Mr. Charles M. Tunstall respectively.
         Both of these series may be of little interest to the
         researcher because of their limited scope. Dr. Tunstall's
         papers concern the financial settlement of his estate while
         those of Charles Tunstall and his wife contain memorabilia
         such as World War II ration tickets. The importance of these
         two series to the collection lies in the information they
         provide relative to the connection between the Rose and
         Tunstall families and in establishing the provenance of the
         papers.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <dsc type="combined">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series I">Commander Robert M.
               Rose</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries A">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>April 12, 1823</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     1</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>April 30, 1823</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     2</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>June 14, 1823</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     3</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>June 30, 1823</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     4</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>July 19, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     5</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>August 15, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     6</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Mary Rose 
                     <unitdate>August 25, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     7</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>S. Hambletori (?) 
                     <unitdate>February 19, 1820</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     8</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>James H. Henry 
                     <unitdate>September 21,
                     1815</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     9</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>James H. Henry 
                     <unitdate>November 8, 1817</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     10</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>James H. Henry 
                     <unitdate>September 12,
                     1818</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     10A</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.K. May: n.d. (ca.
                     1813-1820)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     11</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.K. May 
                     <unitdate>February 10, 1820</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     12</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>George W. Stover 
                     <unitdate>October 19, 1818</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     13</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>William P. Taylor: unsigned,
                     n.d.</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     14</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>William P. Taylor 
                     <unitdate>February 14, 1819</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     15</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>M.B.M. (?) 
                     <unitdate>May 8, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     16</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>M.B.M. 
                     <unitdate>June 8, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     17</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>M.B.M. to Lt. Joseph Smoot 
                     <unitdate>July 10, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     18</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>M.B.M. to Lt. Joseph Smoot 
                     <unitdate>August 22, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     19</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>M.B.M. to Lt. Joseph Smoot 
                     <unitdate>October 13, 1830</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     20</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries B">Business
                  Papers</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Certificate of membership, Naphtali
                     Lodge 
                     <unitdate>October 9, 1811</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     21</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Estate of Major Alexander F. Rose 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1817</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     22</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts, six items: (ca.
                     1830)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     23</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries C">
                  Miscellaneous</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>U.S. Naval Records of officers: entries
                     for Rose, (photocopy)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     24</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>U.S. Naval Records of officers: pension
                     file for Mary Rose (photocopy)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     25</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>U.S. Naval Academy Museum: Documents
                     addressed to R.M. Rose and others, typescript
                     (carbon)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     26</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series II">Dr. Robert W.
               Rose</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries A">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.R. Carter: n.d.</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     27</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.R. Carter 
                     <unitdate>December 1, 1856</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     28</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.R. Carter 
                     <unitdate>April 4, 1857</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     29</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>J.R. Carter 
                     <unitdate>July 11, 1857</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     30</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>W. Menkins 
                     <unitdate>March 17, 1818</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     31</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Provisional Congress of the Confederate
                     States from Dr. Rose 
                     <unitdate>May 14, 1863</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     32</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Susan Turner 
                     <unitdate>October 24, 1855</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     33</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Henry Wiekinton(?) 
                     <unitdate>December 21, 1855</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     34</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>John L. Hargrave to Catherine Jamesson 
                     <unitdate>March 22, 1851</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     35</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Signed "your truly attached aunt,
                     M.E.J." to Mollie (Hodge): n.d., return address,
                     56 Library/Savannah</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     36</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries B">Business
                  Papers</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts, bank loans 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">1848 and
                     1865-1867</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     37</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts, Household 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1844-1866</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     38</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts, building and property 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1846-1851</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     39</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Succession and Legacy Returns for Rose
                     Estate 
                     <unitdate>January 9, 1869</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     40</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series III">Dr. Robert B.
               Tunstall</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries A">Business
                  papers</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Check receipts 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1883-1886</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     41</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Promissory notes 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1871-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     42</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Property 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">1881 and
                     1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     43</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts and invoices 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1883</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     44</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts and invoices 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     45</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts and invoices 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1885</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     46</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Receipts and invoices 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1886</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     47</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Stocks and bonds 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">1880 and
                     1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     48</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Taxes 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1883-1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     49</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Deed of land 
                     <unitdate>April 15, 1857</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     50</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Family document appointing Alexander
                     and Richard Tunstall as executors of Dr.
                     Tunstall's estate 
                     <unitdate>April 6, 1883</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     51</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Partial inventory of the Tunstall
                     Estate 
                     <unitdate>April 18, 1883</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     52</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Record of debts paid 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     1883-1887</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     53</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Summary of debts paid 
                     <unitdate>March 19, 1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     54</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Cash on hand statement 
                     <unitdate>April 15, 1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     55</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Richard H. Baker and Son lawyer's
                     statement 
                     <unitdate>October 9, 1884</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     56</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Bank of Commerce Account Book,
                     Alexander and Richard Tunstall (ca.
                     1883)</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     57</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Miscellaneous notes: n.d.</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     58</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series IV">Charles and Jane B.P.
               Tunstall</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries A">
                  Memorabilia</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>World War I War Bond 
                     <unitdate>(encl. April 1,
                     1947)</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     59</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>World War II Ration Book 
                     <unitdate>(Encl. April 12,
                     1944)</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     60</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
               <did>
                  <unittitle label="Subseries B">
                  Miscellaneous</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Assortment of printed calling cards,
                     two with photographs: n.d.</unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     61</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>The Citizen: A Democratic Weekly
                     (printed copy) 
                     <unitdate>December 1, 1944</unitdate></unittitle>
                     <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                     62</container>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
