<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vino00052">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00052::Norfolk 1919 Photograph Collection)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vino00052.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old
             Dominion University::Perry Library::Special
             Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00052::Norfolk 1919
             Photograph Collection)//EN" "vino00052.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Norfolk 1919 Photograph
            Collection</titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Norfolk Photographs, 1919 
            <num type="collectionnumber">MG 69</num></subtitle>
            <author>Peter Stewart &amp; Janice Halecki</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 By Rector and
            Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">29.5 kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word 97. Machine-readable finding aid created by Kathleen V.
         Smith. Date of source: 
         <date>2002</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-17">Feb 17, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry
            Library::Special Collections//TEXT
            (US::ViNO::vino00052::Norfolk 1919 Photograph
            Collection)//EN" "vino00052.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Norfolk 1919 Photograph
         Collection</titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections and University Archives
         <num type="Collection Number">MG 69</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion
         University</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         &contact;
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Peter Stewart &amp; Janice Halecki</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library,
      Old Dominion University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University </repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Norfolk 1919 Photograph Collection 
         <unitdate label="Date">1919</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">MG 69</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">46 photographs in
         one clamshell photo box, 1 linear foot</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <origination label="Collector">The original negatives were
         collected and saved by Mr. Prosser Carnegie and found after
         his death by his daughter Mrs. Gwen C. Scott.</origination>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>The collection is open to researchers without
            restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>Questions about literary property rights should be
            directed to the Special Collections Librarian.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[Identification of item], Box [insert number], Folder [insert number and title], Norfolk 1919 Photograph Collection, Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Norfolk, VA 23529.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>One copy of each of the originals was given to ODU by
            David E. Johnson, Associate Professor of History in the Art
            Department, ODU, November, 1988.</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>(Written by Peter Stewart, 1988)</p>
         <p>The photographs presented here show some of the people and
         businesses of Norfolk, Virginia about one year after war ended
         on the western front in 1918. The anonymous photographer was
         clearly interested in certain kinds of businesses as the
         pictures feature scenes that other observers tended to miss.
         Rather than portraying the political leaders and the finest
         homes in Norfolk, the unknown photographer depicted small shop
         owners and employees, along with a few of their customers. The
         folks portrayed in this fashion look reasonably normal, but
         neither the nation nor Norfolk were experiencing normal times
         when the pictures were taken.</p>
         <p>The Norfolk of 1919 differed considerably from the city of
         the 1980s. Then, as now, there were distinct districts within
         the city, but these varied drastically from any current
         configuration. Between Water Street (now Waterside Drive) and
         the river were warehouses amid steamship and railroad
         terminals. Main Street presented an appearance entirely
         different from that of today. East Main Street, which
         commenced at Granby and ended at the large Union Station
         featured dozens of small shops, many of which appear in the
         collection of photographs. The eleven or twelve blocks
         contained some brothels for which this part of the city became
         notorious, but in 1919 it also held at least twelve lunch
         counters or restaurants, an equal number of tailor shops or
         garment makers, several groceries, shoe stores, and emporiums
         of various descriptions.</p>
         <p>Of the handful of photographs that have been identified,
         all were taken of the small businesses on East Main or nearby
         streets. The Boston Cafe, managed by Hop Sing and Joe Eng,
         stood at 711 East Main while the New York Lunch Room was
         located just a few doors down across the street, at 728.
         Demetrious Feleros, the proprietor of the latter
         establishment, may be the fellow standing behind the lunch
         counter at the New York Lunch Room. The address on one of the
         menus, 1115 East Main, confirms the presence of the Olympic
         Restaurant in the collection while the Maryland Fruit Store
         and Cleopatra's can be identified by the signs on their store
         fronts. The local directory fails to confirm the existence of
         these places in Norfolk or Portsmouth, but Cleopatra's
         neighbor, Brown's which sold breakfasts, stood near the ferry
         slip. Many of these establishments appear quite tiny and of
         questionable longevity.</p>
         <p>The fruit store that also sold candles and cigars, with an
         address of 908 and a half, is listed in the directory on East
         Main. The two gentlemen in the picture are probably Antonio
         and Philip Tagliaveria, the owner and clerk in the store,
         respectively. They both lived on Bermuda Street, a short
         distance to the east of the East Main Street location.</p>
         <p>While few other sites can be definitely identified, almost
         all of the photographs were taken in the East Main Street
         area, especially between Commercial Place and the Union
         Station. The area contained all of the different types of
         businesses portrayed in the collection. One of the other
         restaurants, for example, could be the Savoy. The barber shop
         might be the U.S. Barbershop at 709 East Main and/or the
         Victoria Hotel Barber Shop at 523 East Main. One of the three
         barber shops looks elegant enough to qualify as the Monticello
         Hotel shop on City Hall Avenue, outside the East Main Street
         district. Hofheimer's Shoe Store found at 444 East Main could
         well be one of the shoe stores pictured in the collection.
         W.B. Shafer, Jr., a long time resident of Norfolk, thinks that
         the rather stylish women's dress shop belonged to one Peter
         Smith and stood at the corner of Bank and Main streets. He
         also recognized the Norfolk Harness Shop on Union Street among
         the photographs and believes the bicycle repair shop belonged
         to a gentleman named Councilman, who later made his fortune in
         Detroit.</p>
         <p>At the 400 block East Main passed through Commercial Place
         with its statue of Johnny Reb. Here passengers from the ferry
         from Portsmouth passed on their way to Norfolk's commercial
         center. Some potential customers doubtless went to one of the
         city's well known stores such as Miller, Rhodes and Swartz on
         Commercial Place that advertised as the "largest department
         store" in the city. Or they may have headed to Smith and
         Welton's on Granby, which in 1919 rearranged its interior
         after the Red Cross vacated its 5th floor. Or they may have
         gone to Ames and Brownley, which moved into the Fergus Reid
         building that year.</p>
         <p>One block west of Commercial Place was Roanoke Avenue, the
         location of almost all of Norfolk's produce wholesalers just
         as Church Street contained many of the city's produce
         solicitors. One of the photographs shows such an
         establishment.</p>
         <p>It is hard to visualize now, but grocery stores were all
         over downtown Norfolk in 1919. Pender, the most successful of
         the 400 or so grocers who operated in Norfolk, advertised
         heavily and ran two stores. In the era before chain stores
         became commonplace, every neighborhood in Norfolk, including
         its downtown, possessed individually owned grocery stores,
         which were usually quite small and offered only a comparative
         handful of items for sale. The one chain store in the city,
         Piggly-Wiggly, stood on the corner of Granby and 27th Street,
         well uptown, and quite a novelty in 1919.</p>
         <p>The city market off City Hall Avenue contained several
         stalls where meat, fresh vegetables, and fish could be found.
         In 1919 the local government also managed a municipal grocery
         store at first on Monticello Avenue in back of the public
         market and later at the Red Circle Club on Atlantic Street.
         This outlet handled government surpluses at special prices
         during limited hours.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>This collection is a portfolio of 46 prints, each were
         contact printed from the original 6.5" X 8.5" glass plate
         negative. These photographs were taken in November, 1919 by an
         anonymous photographer. Most of the businesses depicted in the
         photographs appear to have been located in the area of East
         Main Street between Commercial Place and Union Station in
         Norfolk.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <dsc type="in-depth">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Photographs of Norfolk Businesses in 
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers behind the counter in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a shoe repair shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a shoe store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Owner in front of Cleopatra Fruit
                  Store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Men in a pool room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customer in front of Tagliavia
                  Grocery store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in an apothecary
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a bicycle repair
                  shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a cigar shop/soda
                  fountain</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers behind the counter in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a hosiery/shoe
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customer in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a grocery store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a grocery store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a women's
                  clothing store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a men's clothing
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker in a shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a harness repair
                  shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a grocery store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a shoe store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customer in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a lunch room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customer in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a kitchen</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a barber shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker in front of the Maryland Fruit
                  Store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customer in a grocery
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a grocery store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker in front of fruit stand</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Men in a pool hall</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customers in the New York Lunch
                  Room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Men in a cigar store with pool hall and
                  shoeshine stand</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a kitchen</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customer in a pastry/candy shop
                  and soda fountain</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customers in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a large barber
                  shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Worker and customer in a grocery
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customer in a lunch
                  room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers and customers in a barber
                  shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a women's clothing
                  store</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a tailor shop</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Workers in a lunch room</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
