<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vino00022">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00022::A Guide to the Papers of the Hodges Family)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vino00022.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old
             Dominion University::Perry Library::Special
             Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00022::A Guide to the
             Papers of the Hodges Family)//EN" "vino00022.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Hodges Family 
            <date>1754-1979</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Hodges, Family Papers, 1754-1979 
            <num type="collectionnumber">MG 49</num></subtitle>
            <author>Kim Snyder</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
<publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2001 By Rector and
            Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">38 kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft
         Word 97. Machine-readable finding aid created by Tonia
         Graves.</creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-17">Feb 17, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry
            Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00022::A
            Guide to the Papers of the Hodges Family)//EN"
            "vino00022.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of the Hodges Family 
         <date>1754-1979</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections 
         <num type="Collection Number">MG 49</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion
         University</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2001</date>
         &contact;
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Kim Snyder</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Perry Library,
      Old Dominion University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University </repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Hodges Family Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">
         1754-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">MG 49</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1 Hollinger
         Document Case; 1 Oversized Box</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>Collection is open to researchers without
            restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use</head>
            <p>Questions on copyright should be directed to the
            Archivist.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>[Identification of item], Hodges Family Papers, Special
            Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University,
            Norfolk, Virginia.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <acqinfo>
            <head>Acquisition Information</head>
            <p>Gift of Mary Ainsworth Hook, March, 1981</p>
         </acqinfo>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>The Hodges family arrived in America in the first half of
         the seventeenth century. Although early records of the family
         have been lost, it is evident that they settled in the
         Tidewater region almost from the beginning. The history of the
         Hodges family and the history of Portsmouth are closely
         intertwined.</p>
         <p>The oldest available document is the will of William
         Hodges, which was written March 19, 1754. The will indicates
         that William Hodges was a successful planter who owned slaves.
         His will provides the only valid information on his life. Of
         his three sons and four daughters, the only one to be
         mentioned in another family document is Captain John Hodges.
         He married Lydia Thomas July 4, 1760 and died May 12, 1802.
         One of his sons, William Hodges, married Sally Deans, and one
         of their children was John Hodges, the first member of the
         family of whom any considerable record remains.</p>
         <p>John Hodges was born December 31, 1786 and died July 31,
         1855. During the War of 1812 he rose to the rank of Brigadier
         General of the 9th Brigade of the Virginia Militia. He served
         as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates in 1826, and
         was a supervisor in Norfolk County for the election of
         presidential and vice-presidential electors in 1832. In
         addition to these activities, he served an undetermined number
         of years as Postmaster of Portsmouth until his resignation in
         1840.</p>
         <p>General Hodges bought a tract of land on the Western Branch
         of the Elizabeth River, which he called Wildwood. From his
         farm, he operated a ferry, from which the Hodges Ferry section
         of Portsmouth derives its name. He also bought land in
         downtown Portsmouth upon which he built a house that still
         stands on North Street. Hodges married three times. His first
         two wives, Ann Carney (d. 1814) and Louise Harrison (d. 1826)
         both died, Ann childless, and Louise leaving two sons, John H.
         Hodges and William Henry Harrison Hodges. General Hodges'
         third marriage, to Jane Adelaide Gregory in 1828, resulted in
         three children, James Gregory Hodges, Emma Adelaide Hodges,
         and Margaret Jane Hodges.</p>
         <p>No references remain concerning the life of the younger
         John Hodges, except that he married Eliza F. C. Benn in 1842,
         a marriage that produced three children. It is rather strange
         that there is no official notice of his death April 27, 1863,
         since a greater number of letters and other materials survive
         from that period. The other two sons, William Henry Harrison
         and James Gregory, are more fully documented. Their lives
         speak of both the gallantry and the tragedy of the Civil
         War.</p>
         <p>James Gregory Hodges (1828-1863) married Sarah A. F. Wilson
         August 11, 1852, and had two sons, William Wilson Hodges and
         John Nelson Hodges. At the age of twenty-nine he served as
         Portsmouth's first mayor when the city was incorporated in
         1858. The outbreak of the Civil War saw him active in the
         first Tidewater skirmish, which resulted in the burning of the
         Gosport Navy Yard in Portsmouth. Placed in command of the 14th
         Virginia Regiment James found himself at Gettysburg in July,
         1863. During the famed "Pickett's Charge," in which his
         regiment participated, James Gregory Hodges was killed when a
         cannon exploded at his side. The remains of his body were
         never found.</p>
         <p>William Henry Harrison Hodges (1824-1880) married Mary A.
         Griswold May 13, 1856, and had two daughters, Mary Louisa
         Hodges and Susan Green Hodges. He built a house on Middle
         Street across from his father's, still standing today. William
         survived the war, but he did not escape the tragedy of it. As
         cashier of the Merchants and Mechanics Savings Bank of
         Portsmouth, he was supposed to comply with the orders of the
         Union occupation troops under Major General Benjamin Butler.
         William was only one of five men in the town who refused to
         take the loyalty oath to the North, and when he did not obey
         the order to turn over the bank's money to union control, he
         was arrested and imprisoned from February 1864 until after the
         war's end. Through his ordeal he remained steadfast in his
         conviction that obedience to that order would not have been
         consistent with honor.</p>
         <p>William had no sons, James' two sons died childless, and
         from the lack of evidence it appears that the one son of John
         Hodges also left no descendants. Therefore, at the death of
         William Wilson Hodges in 1893, the Hodges' line died out. But
         the memory of their importance to the Portsmouth community
         survives.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>The Hodges Family Papers include documentation of
         generations from 1754 to 1981. Although the Hodges line of
         male descendants ended in 1893, marriages of female
         descendants have brought the Ainsworth, Armistead, Lindsay,
         Hook, and Korty families into direct line with the Hodges.
         Consequently, some of the correspondence, newspaper clippings,
         genealogical information, scrapbook materials, and photographs
         have reference to these other families. Most of the
         collection, however, centers on General John Hodges and two of
         his sons, Colonel James Gregory Hodges and William Henry
         Harrison Hodges.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>The papers are divided into twelve series: correspondence,
         legal documents, financial records, newspaper clippings,
         military papers, publications, genealogical notes,
         certificates, scrapbook, cards, photographs, and
         miscellany.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series I - Correspondence</emph>
         <lb />In the correspondence series, separate folders are
         maintained for General John Hodges, Colonel James Gregory
         Hodges, William Henry Harrison Hodges (2 folders), and Captain
         Andrew Ainsworth. Captain Ainsworth was an Englishman who
         joined the Union forces and served as captain of the port at
         Hampton Roads during the Union occupation. After the Civil War
         he remained in the area and one of his descendants married
         into the Hodges line. There is also one folder of
         miscellaneous correspondence. Especially interesting is a
         letter from James Gregory Hodges to his father, requesting
         marital advice. Also, William Henry Harrison Hodges' letters
         to his wife, Mary Abigail Griswold Hodges, and his requests
         for release from imprisonment provide a direct insight into
         the trials of war for one man. One of the letters to Captain
         Ainsworth from 0. E. Babcock is addressed "Executive Mansion".
         Babcock served in the Grant administration.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series II - Legal Documents</emph>
         <lb />Included in this series are deeds of sale showing how
         General John Hodges acquired Wildwood and other property. Also
         included are wills, statements, a legal claim, and an 1809
         land survey of the Western Branch land that Hodges eventually
         acquired. Items of special interest include a bill of sale for
         slaves and the 1754 will of William Hodges.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series III - Financial Records</emph>
         <lb />This is a small series consisting of receipts, a bill,
         and a promissory note. It should be noted that the Mary Louisa
         Hodges, mentioned on two receipts, could not be the daughter
         of William Henry Harrison Hodges since the dates are before
         her birth. How Mary Louisa Hodges was related to the family is
         unknown.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series IV - Newspaper Clippings</emph>
         <lb />The newspaper clippings include obituaries, weddings,
         anniversaries, and varied articles primarily concerning
         Portsmouth and the Civil War. The articles most pertinent to
         the Hodges family are: an account of the life of James Greqory
         Hodges by his brother-in-law, Judge James F. Crocker, a
         recounting of Portsmouth's incorporation during its 75th
         anniversary, and a 1979 article about the discovered
         gravestones of the Hodges family. Also in this series is a
         copy of the Union occupation force's newspaper, New Regime
         5/30/1864, and maps of the Union campaign against Richmond
         from the Philadelphia Enquirer 6/28/1862 and the New York
         Herald 7/16/1862.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series V - Military Papers</emph>
         <lb />This series consists of a few military communications.
         The most important items are a notice for William Henry
         Harrison Hodges to report to the Provost Marshall's Office,
         and his official prison sentence.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series VI - Publications</emph>
         <lb />Five separate books comprise this series. The Outline of
         Scripture Geography and The Scripture Atlas are the oldest
         publications, both dated 1828. The Communicants' Manual and
         the prayer book were both possessions of Sarah A. F. Wilson
         Hodges, the wife of James Gregory. The Holy Trinity Church
         describes the activities of the church that each generation of
         the Hodges family regularly attended.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series VII - Genealogical Notes</emph>
         <lb />This series is a collection of various notes written by
         family members that give insight into family history. In some
         instances, personal information is revealed that cannot be
         found in any of the other documents.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series VIII - Certificates</emph>
         <lb />Three certificates comprise this series: a marriage
         certificate for William Henry Harrison Hodges and Mary Abigail
         Griswold, and the baptismal certificates for their
         daughters.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series IX - Scrapbook</emph>
         <lb />The original scrapbook remains in the hands of the
         donor, but a photocopy of each page is present in this series.
         Most of the photocopied items are newspaper obituaries and
         articles. The obituaries in this series provide details on
         less prominent members of the Hodges family, as well as a
         solid core of information on the Ainsworths, Armisteads, and
         Lindsays.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series X - Cards</emph>
         <lb />The majority of the items in this series are undated and
         not addressed, although Mary A. Griswold and Susan Hodges are
         noted. Valentines dominate the series.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series XI - Photographs</emph>
         <lb />Most of the items in this series are photographic prints
         of earlier prints, paintings, and daguerreotypes. Included are
         pictures of James Gregory Hodges, William Henry Harrison
         Hodges, Mary Abigail Griswold Hodges, Mary Louisa Hodges
         Armistead, and many other members of the
         Hodges-Ainsworth-Armistead-Lindsay line up to the year 1981.
         Turn-of- the-century photographs of Portsmouth's Confederate
         Monument and Trinity Episcopal Church and a later photograph
         of the house William Henry Harrison Hodges built are also
         included. A photograph of an 1832 letter from Governor John
         Floyd to General John Hodges, informing him of his appointment
         as a superintendent of the election of Presidential electors,
         and one of a ring made by William Henry Harrison while he was
         imprisoned are unique features of this series.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Series XII - Miscellany</emph>
         <lb />Invitations, fragments of letters and envelopes.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <dsc type="in-depth">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series I">Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>General John Hodges</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Colonel James Gregory Hodges</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  2</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>William Henry Harrison Hodges to Mary
                  Abigail Hodges</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  3</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Other Correspondence Concerning William
                  Henry Harrison Hodges</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  4</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Captain Andrew Ainsworth</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  5</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  6</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series II">Legal Documents</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Deeds of Sale 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1825-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  7</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Wills 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1754-1832</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  8</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Notes Concerning Legal Matters</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  9</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Land Survey 
                  <unitdate>1809</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  10</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Claim 
                  <unitdate>1839</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  11</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series III">Financial
               Records</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Receipts 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1815-1858</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  12</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Bill, Promissory Note 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">1843,
                  1846</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  13</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series IV">Newspaper
               Clippings</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Obituaries 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1855-1888</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  14</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Weddings, Anniversaries 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1855-1905</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  15</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Articles 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                  1876-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  16</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Family Matters</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  17</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Battle Map, Philadelphia Enquirer 
                  <unitdate>June 28, 1862</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  18</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Battle Map, New York Herald 
                  <unitdate>July 16, 1862</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  19</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series V">Military Papers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>General Orders, Notices,
                  Passes</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  20</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Prison Sentence for William Henry Harrison
                  Hodges and List of Prisoners at Camp
                  Hamilton</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  21</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series VI">Publications</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Outline of Scripture Geography
                  &amp;Accompanying Atlas by J.E. Worcester 
                  <unitdate>1828</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  22</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>The Communicants' Manual owned by Sarah
                  A.F. Wilson Hodges 
                  <unitdate>1849</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  23</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Prayer book owned by Sarah A.F. Wilson
                  Hodges, ca. 
                  <unitdate>1850</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  24</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>History of Holy Trinity Church by C.
                  Charles Vache 
                  <unitdate>1962</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  25</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series VII">Genealogical
               Notes</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Genealogical Information</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  26</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series VIII">Certificates</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Baptismal Certificates</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  27</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Marriage Certificate for William Henry
                  Harrison Hodges &amp;Mary Abigail Griswold 
                  <unitdate>1856</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  28</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series IX">Scrapbook</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Photocopied pages of newspaper obituaries
                  &amp;articles</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  29</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series X">Cards</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>New Year's Cards</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  30</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Valentines</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  31</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  32</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series XI">Photographs</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter from Governor John Floyd to General
                  John Hodges 
                  <unitdate>1832</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  33</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Children of General John Hodges-William
                  Henry Harrison, James Gregory, and Margaret
                  Jane</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  34</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Mary Abigail Griswold Hodges and ring made
                  for her by William Henry Harrison Hodges</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  35</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Mary Louisa Hodge Armistead</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  36</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Green-Griswold Family</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  37</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Margaret Wall Ainsworth</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  38</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Robert Jefferson Armistead and the
                  Armistead Coat of Arms</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  39</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Ambrose Harvey and Adelaile Charles
                  Lindsay and the Lindsay Coat of Arms</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  40</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Descendants of the
                  Hodges-Ainsworth-Armistead-Lindsay
                  Families</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  41</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Downtown Portsmouth</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  42</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Unidentified Man</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  43</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Lithograph</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  44</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle label="Series XII">Miscellany</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Invitation, Fragments</unittitle>
                  <container type="Box-folder">Box 1, Folder
                  45</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
