<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vino00007">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00007::A Guide to the Papers of A. E. S. Stephens 1949-1961)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vino00007.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViNO">PUBLIC "-//Old
             Dominion University::Perry Library::Special
             Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00007::A Guide to the
             Papers of A. E. S. Stephens 1949-1961)//EN"
             "vino00007.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of A. E. S. Stephens 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1961</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Stephens, A. E. S. 1949-1961 Papers. 
            <num type="collectionnumber">MG 19</num></subtitle>
        <author>Mr. Michael H. Brown</author>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2000 By Rector and
            Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">36 Kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Word 6.0 Machine-readable finding aid
         created by Sandra A. Beehler. [Date of source: 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry
            Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00007::A
            Guide to the Papers of A. E. S. Stephens 1949-1961)//EN"
            "vino00007.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of A. E. S. Stephens, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1961</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>Special Collections and University Archives
         <num type="Collection Number">MG 19</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion
         University</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Special Collections and University Archives Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library,
      Old Dominion University</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Papers of A. E. S. Stephens 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1949-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">MG 19</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">6 Hollinger
         Document Cases; 2.5 linear feet.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open to researchers without
            restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>Questions on literary property rights should be directed
            to the Special Collections Librarian.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>[Identification of item], Box [insert number], Folder [insert number and title], Papers of A. E. S. Stephens, Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Norfolk, VA 23529.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Mrs. Anna Delk Stephens and Mr. Rodham T. Delk
            May 20, 1977</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Allie Edward Stakes Stephens was born November 4, 1900, in
         Wicomico Church, Virginia, the fourth son of J.W.G. Stephens
         and Allie Tyson Beane Stephens. Although Stephens became a
         successful lawyer and a prominent politician, he did not come
         from a family background in either the law or politics. J.W.G.
         Stephens had been a cowboy in the Dakotas before he returned
         to Virginia to open a general merchandise store. Lacking a
         formal education himself, the elder Stephens made sacrifices
         to secure a good education for his children, telling them,
         "Without an education, all the money in the world will just
         make fools out of you."</p>
      <p>A.E.S. Stephens attended public schools in Northumberland
         County, Virginia, and graduated from Wicomico Church High
         School in 1918. During his high school years Stephens was so
         successful as a baseball pitcher that he was asked to try out
         with the Washington Senators. Heeding his father's advice,
         Stephens turned down the offer; however, he maintained a keen
         interest in baseball and excelled in the sport during his
         student years at the College of William and Mary.</p>
      <p>Stephens entered William and Mary in the fall of 1919 and
         was awarded both academic and law degrees upon graduation in
         1923. It was at William and Mary that Stephens received his
         life-long nickname, "Gi". Stephens stood 6'3" in his bare feet
         and his friends claimed he was "lean as a giraffe,." Giraffe
         was pronounced with a long "i" and from this pronunciation
         "Gi" was derived.</p>
      <p>Stephens began practicing law in the Isle of Wight County,
         Virginia, on September 15, 1923. It was in Isle of Wight
         County in 1927 that Stephens experienced a violent initiation
         into politics. An incident occurred in which a fourteen year
         old white girl was allegedly brutally murdered by a black man.
         At a time in Virginia history when lynchings still occurred, a
         mob formed and demanded the death of the defendant. The Isle
         of Wight Commonwealth's Attorney, however, succeeded in
         transporting the black man safely to Petersburg. Stephens was
         asked by angry Isle of Wight residents to run for
         Commonwealth's Attorney as an independent candidate, but
         Stephens made it absolutely clear that he would neither run,
         nor accept the office if elected. Stephens, in fact, won the
         election, but as he had promised he refused to accept the
         office despite the attempted intimidation of the Ku Klux
         Klan.</p>
      <p>Stephens formally began his political career when he was
         elected as a Democrat to the House of Delegates in 1929. He
         served as a Delegate for twelve years. In 1941 Stephens was
         elected to the Virginia Senate where he served until 1952.
         After the death of Lieutenant Governor Lewis Preston Collins
         on September 20, 1952, Stephens announced his candidacy for
         the unexpired portion of Collins' term. His candidacy was
         successful and in November 1953, he was elected to a full
         four-year term. Stephens was re-elected Lieutenant Governor in
         1957, and served in that capacity until his resignation after
         an unsuccessful candidacy for the Governorship in 1961.</p>
      <p>While serving in the General Assembly of Virginia, Stephens
         was the chief patron of the legislation which created the
         Hampton Roads Sanitation Commission. He was interested in
         legislation pertaining to the seafood industry, and while in
         the House of Delegates, he served as a member and chairman of
         the Committee on Fish and Game. His most important
         accomplishments were in public education. Stephens was the
         author and patron of the bill establishing the Denny School
         Commission on which he also served. The recommendations of the
         Denny Commission were instrumental in bringing about
         improvements in public schools in Virginia.</p>
      <p>Throughout his political career, Stephens remained a member
         of the Democratic Party and until the late 1950s he aligned
         himself with the powerful Byrd Organization. Stephens split
         with the Byrd Machine in 1959 when he withdrew his support
         from the Organization's policy of Massive Resistance to public
         school desegregation. Stephens played a critical role in the
         demise of Massive Resistance when he, as presiding officer of
         the Senate, ruled that the Senate could resolve itself into a
         committee of the whole to consider the alternative Perrow Plan
         which conceded a minimum of integration. This parliamentary
         tactic enabled the moderates to bypass the Byrd
         Organization-dominated Education Committee and secured passage
         of the Perrow proposals. By the time Stephens indicated his
         desire to run in the 1961 Democratic primary for Governor of
         Virginia, he was clearly recognized as independent of the Byrd
         Organization. Throughout his primary campaign Stephens asked
         for the votes of the true Virginia Democrats, not those whom
         he accused of using the Democratic label to get elected, and
         then following Republican line on the issues. Attorney General
         Albertis S. Harrison who had the Byrd Organization's support,
         defeated Stephens in the July primary by a vote of 199,519 to
         152,639, and Stephens resigned his position as Lieutenant
         Governor in late 1961. Stephens did not run for State office
         again, but remained an influence in Virginia politics until
         his death.</p>
      <p>Stephens' private life was filled with important and varied
         positions and accomplishments. He married Anna Spratley Delk
         in 1928, and had three children, including the first girl in
         the Stephens family in four generations. Stephens was a
         founder and, at his death, President and a member of the Board
         of the Directors of Historic St. Luke's Restoration. He was a
         member of the Smithfield Ruritan Club, Virginia Bar
         Association and an honorary member of the Smithfield Rotary
         Club, which he twice served as president. He was Town Attorney
         for the Town of Smithfield for many years until his retirement
         on December 3, 1971. Stephens served as a member of the Board
         of Visitors of Old Dominion University from 1968 to 1972.</p>
      <p>He died, after a short illness, at Riverside Hospital,
         Newport News, Virginia on June 9, 1973.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The papers are divided into eight basic series, and are
         arranged in the following order: Correspondence; Photographs;
         Biographical Data; Newspaper Clippings; Campaign Records;
         Speeches; Statements; and Reference Material.</p>
      <p>The Stephens papers are basically centered around his
         unsuccessful campaign for Governor of Virginia from December
         1960, until his loss to Albertis Harrison in the Democratic
         Party primary in July 1961. The papers dealing with the
         campaign period reflect Stephens' stand on various campaign
         issues, and the frustrations of his attempt to win the
         Democratic nomination against the opposition of the Byrd
         organization. The majority of the papers prior to the
         1960-1961 primary race focus on the issue of Massive
         Resistance to racial integration in Virginia schools, and date
         back to the early 1950s. The collection contains neither
         Stephens' private papers, nor the records of his service in
         the Virginia General Assembly, or as Lieutenant Governor.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series I: Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>February, 1949</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>October, 1950</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January, 1951</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1952</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1954</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January-April, 1955</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May-December, 1955</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1956</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1957</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1959</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>March, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>September, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>November 1-15, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>November 16-21, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>November 22-30, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>December 1-7, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>December 8-15, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>December 16-22, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>December 23-31, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  1:20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January 1-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January 16-21, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January 22-31, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>February 1-12, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>February 13-28, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>March 1-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>March 16-20, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>March 21-25, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>March 26-31, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April 1-7, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April 8-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April 16-23, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April 24-30, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  2:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 1-7, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 8-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 16-23, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 24-31, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 1-7, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 8-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 16-30, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 1-11, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 12, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 13-15, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 17, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 18-23, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July 24-31, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>August, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>September-December, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>undated</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  3:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series II: Photographs</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Photographs (undated)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series III: Biographical Data</unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
               4:2</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series IV: Newspaper Clippings</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1954-1959</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Newspaper Clippings 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1959-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series V: Campaign Records 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1960-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
               4:5</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VI: Speeches</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1952</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1953</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1954</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1955</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1956</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1957</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1958</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:12</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1959</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January-June, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July-December, 1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 1-25, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May 26-31, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  4:19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 1-10, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 11-20, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 21-25, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>June 26-30, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>July, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Undated</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:6-9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Speech Outlines 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1954-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  5:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VII: Statements</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Proposed Platform 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 5, 1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:1</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Statements 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March-June,
                  1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Statements 
                  <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">July, 1961 and
                  undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series VIII: Reference Material</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1949-1953</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January-July, 1954</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>August-December, 1954</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1955-1959</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>1960</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>January-March, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>April, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>May-July, 1961</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Undated</unittitle>
            <container label="Box-folder" type="Box-folder">
                  6:12-13</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
