<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/odu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/odu_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vino00069">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViNo">PUBLIC "-//Old Dominion University::Perry Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViNO::vino00069::A Guide to the Papers of Lawrence M. Cox, Sr., )//EN"
"vino00069.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Lawrence M. Cox, Sr., <date>1912-2002</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Cox, Lawrence M., Sr., Papers 
<num type="collectionnumber">MG 38
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Mel Frizzell, Tonia Graves, Jan Halecki, Kathleen Smith
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Old Dominion University
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2004 By Rector and Board of Visitors of Old Dominion University. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">612 kb
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Microsoft Word 97, created by Susan M. Catlett, <date>2004</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Lawrence M. Cox, Sr., <date>1912-2002</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and University Archives
<num type="Collection Number">MG 38
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher> Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2004
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Special Collections and University Archives Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer"> Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository"> Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">A Guide to the Papers of Lawrence M. Cox, Sr.,
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1912-2002
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">235 Hollinger Document Cases, 8 clamshell cases, 17 Oversize Boxes, 1 Poster Tube. 107.7 Linear Feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Open to researchers without restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Questions on literary property rights should be directed to the Special Collections Librarian.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Box [insert number], Folder [insert number and title], The Papers of Lawrence M. Cox, Sr., Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University Libraries, Norfolk, VA 23529.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Original Gift by Lawrence M. Cox, Sr. in May 1979. Final Accession donated by Marvin W. Lee, Sr. in October 2003.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>Lawrence Morgan Cox, Sr. was born March 12, 1912, in Norfolk, Virginia and he was raised in the Larchmont area of Norfolk. He was the second son of William Roland Cox, Sr. and Maude Belote Cox. He had one
brother, William Roland Cox, Jr., and two sisters, Grace and Mary. In 1942, he married Anne Irving Flipper. They had a son, Lawrence Morgan Cox, Jr. Cox and Flipper divorced in 1950. In 1951, Cox married Ethel Mae
Breeden. Cox had one stepdaughter, Mrs. Diane Fecher of Hilton Head Island, South Carolina.
</p>
<p>In 1934, Cox joined the Public Works Administration Housing Division of the U.S. Government as a messenger and statistician. He was promoted in 1937 to Special Assistant to Jacob Crane, Assistant Administrator
of the U.S. Housing Authority, and he served in that position until 1940. During his time in Washington, Cox took undergraduate courses in Public Administration and Business Administration at George Washington
University.
</p>
<p>Cox became Assistant Executive Director of the newly formed Norfolk Housing Authority (now known as the Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority) in 1940. There was regional resistance to the establishment of
the Authority but it was overcome by the support of the U.S. Navy who were short of housing, and by the creation of Merrimac Park set aside for U.S. Navy enlisted men and their families. Cox was named Executive
Director of the Norfolk Housing Authority on April 1, 1941.
</p>
<p>In 1942, Cox became a Bomb Reconnaissance Agent with the Virginia Office of Civilian Defense. Cox was instrumental in the formation of the Virginia Association of Housing Authorities, and served as its
president from 1942-43. When Cox was selected to head the National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials (NAHRO) in 1948, he became the youngest man in NAHRO history to hold that position. While
leading the NAHRO, Cox helped formulate the policies incorporated in the Housing Act of 1949, a landmark document that called for "a decent home and suitable environment for every American family."
</p>
<p>During 1949, Cox spent a great deal of time overseas involved in urban planning and rebuilding. He was a member of the American Delegation to the Economic Commission for Europe's International Conference on
Building Documentation held in Geneva, Switzerland. He traveled in six European countries on a special study assignment for the State Department and the Housing and Home Finance Agency which dealt with housing and
the rebuilding of cities. He also served as a special consultant to the U.S. High Commissioner for Germany and reviewed planning and rebuilding in five German cities. In 1956 and 1957, Cox served the State
Department as part of the International Cooperation Administration's study on housing programs in Peru and as a special consultant to Peru's Presidential Commission on Housing and Land Reform. For his service to
the nation of Peru, he was designated Knight Commander of the Order of Merit of Peru by President Prado. Cox participated in the International Seminar on Urban Renewal at The Hague, Netherlands in 1958. He also
attended the 24th International Congress of Town Planning at Liege, Belgium that same year.
</p>
<p>Even while Cox was serving his country internationally, he did not neglect the needs of Norfolk. Cox was the first city official to publicly support a medical school for Norfolk in a 1959 speech to the Norfolk
Yacht Club. He reiterated his goal of a medical school for Norfolk during his 1961 speech commemorating the opening of the Medical Tower building, the first of four buildings in the Norfolk Medical Complex.
Throughout the 1960's, Cox helped build community support for a medical college in Norfolk, VA. His efforts eventually led to the creation of the Eastern Virginia Medical School (EVMS) in 1973.
</p>
<p>During the 1960s, Mr. Cox lectured extensively at graduate seminars and meetings, both at home and abroad. He addressed the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs at the University of Pittsburgh in
1961. In 1962, he spent a month lecturing at the Graduate School of Ekistics, Athens Technical Institute in Athens, Greece. Also in 1962, Cox lectured at the International School of Social Studies at The Hague,
Netherlands. Cox was also a guest speaker at the American Bar Association's 88th Annual Meeting in Miami, Florida (1965), the University of Cincinnati's Graduate School of Architecture (1967), and the University
of Virginia's Graduate School of Planning (1968).
</p>
<p>Cox continued his role as Executive Director of the Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority (NRHA) until his appointment as Assistant Secretary for Renewal and Housing Assistance of the U.S. Department of
Housing and Urban Development in 1969. He was appointed by President Richard Nixon, and only served in this position until 1970. During this time, he continued as a consultant to urban development, planning, and
housing bodies at the federal, state, and local levels. Cox resigned as Assistant Secretary for Renewal and Housing Assistance in July 1970, amid rumors of misused funds. The allegations were investigated, but Cox
was never charged with any wrongdoing. Cox steadfastly denied that his resignation had anything to do with the rumors. He cited business concerns for his failing land development corporation in Nansemond County as
his reason for leaving.
</p>
<p>More legal troubles ensued in 1973 when Cox was brought before a Grand Jury for keeping interests in private enterprises while working for public interests during his time with NRHA. Between 1964 and 1985, Cox
was an owner of two successful real estate development firms, one of these being Suffolk's Cedar Point, a residential and golf community. However, the Grand Jury found no criminal misconduct by Cox, but did scold
Cox for a breach of ethics.
</p>
<p>In 1973, Lawrence Cox was appointed Counselor to the U.S. Conference of Mayors for policy and legislative matters; and from 1976 to 1982, he served on the Board of Commissioners of the Virginia Housing
Development Authority. Cox also remained actively involved in real estate development from 1964 until the late 1980s.
</p>
<p>In 1990, the Medical College of Hampton Roads and Eastern Virginia Medical School awarded Cox the degree of Doctor of Human Letters, honoris causa. In the early 1990's, he and his wife moved to the Hilton Head
Island Retirement Community. After his retirement, Cox had the opportunity to pursue leisure activities. Cox was an avid golfer and a fisherman. He was interested in history and involved in the Sons of the
American Revolution and the Children of the Confederacy. Cox died on November 7, 2002 on Hilton Island, South Carolina.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection deals primarily with Cox's career at the Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority; the Department of Housing and Urban Development; and as a private real estate counselor.
</p>
<p>These papers document his activities in Washington, D.C. in the early 1930's; in Norfolk from 1940 until 1969; with HUD in 1969 and 1970; and from his home in Suffolk, Norfolk, and Hilton Head Island, in later
years. Additionally, this collection contains personal information on his family, retirement, and hobbies.
</p>
<p>Materials in the archives consist of proposed and enacted legislation at the national and state level; press releases; mailing lists; newsletters; magazines; reports; pamphlets; books; correspondence; newspaper
clippings; awards; achievements; resumes; photos; speeches, and various other materials.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is broken down chronologically by the positions Cox held in his professional career with additional series of personal material, photos, blueprints, and artifacts. Sub-series are organized either
chronologically or alphabetically, as appropriate.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Under Construction">This collection is currently being reprocessed.
</unittitle>
</did>

</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
