<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wm.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wm_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wm_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY zknlva SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/wm/vivadoc.pl?file=viw00189.xml" NDATA html>
]>
<ead id="viw00189">
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
	<eadid mainagencycode="VWM" countrycode="us">PUBLIC "-//College of William and Mary::Earl Gregg Swem Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViW::viw00189:: Robert Saunders Letters, 1829-1867)//EN" "viw00189.xml"</eadid>
	<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
	<titleproper>Inventory of the Robert Saunders Letters <date>1829-1867</date>
	</titleproper>
	<subtitle id="sort">
		Saunders, Robert Letters		<num type="collectionnumber">Mss. Acc. 2007.109</num>
	</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
	<publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</publisher> &address;
	<date type="publication">&copy; 2009 By the College of William and Mary. All rights reserved.</date>
	<p id="usestatement">
		<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use</extref>
	</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
	<creation>Finding aid created by Special Collections Staff, <date>2007</date></creation>
	<langusage>Description is in
		<language langcode="eng">English</language>
	</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
	<titlepage>
		<titleproper>Inventory of the Robert Saunders Letters, <date>1829-1867</date></titleproper>
		<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Special Collections Research Center
			<num type="Accession Number">Mss. Acc. 2007.109</num>
		</subtitle>
		<p id="logostmt">
			<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
		</p>
		<publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</publisher>
		<date type="publication">2009</date> &contact;
		<list type="deflist">
			<defitem>
				<label>Processed By</label>
				<item>Special Collections Staff.</item>
			</defitem>
		</list>
	</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</runner>
<did>
	<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
	<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
		<corpname>Special Collections Research Center</corpname>
</repository>
	<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Robert Saunders Letters	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1829-1867</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid encodinganalog="099" label="Identification:" countrycode="us" repositorycode="VWM">01/Mss. Acc. 2007.109</unitid>
	<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent unit="Items">65.00</extent></physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Materials">
	  The papers are in:
<language langcode="eng">English</language>
	</langmaterial>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">This collection consists of 65 letters written by Robert Saunders of Williamsburg, Virginia to his wife Lucy Burwell Saunders (60 letters) and his daughters Lucy Page Saunders (3 letters) and Roberta P. Saunders (2 letters) from 1829-1867.</abstract>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Saunders, Robert, 1805-1868</persname>
arrangement
	</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information</head>
<!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
	<head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
	<p>Collection is open to all researchers.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540">
	<head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
	<p>Before publishing quotations or excerpts from any materials, permission must be obtained from the Special Collections Research Center, and the holder of the copyright, if not Swem Library.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="510">
	<head>Preferred Citation</head>
	<p>Robert Saunders Letters, Special Collections Research Center, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
	<head>Acquisition Information</head>
	<p>The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 00/00/2007.</p>
</acqinfo>
<!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->
</descgrp>
<!--COLLECTION LEVEL METADATA: -->
<bioghist altrender="Biographical Note" encodinganalog="545"><head>Biographical Note</head>
  <p>Robert Saunders was born 25 January 1805 in Williamsburg, Virginia. He attended the College of William and Mary and the University of Virginia. Saunders served as professor of mathematics at William and Mary from 1833 to 1848 and was president of the college 1847-1848. He was a captain in the Confederate States Army, head of Eastern State Hospital, mayor of Willamsburg, vestryman of Bruton Parish and served in the Virginia State Senate. Saunders married Lucy Burwell Page in 1828 and had, among other children, Roberta Saunders and Robert Page Saunders. He died 11 September 1868. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki:</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
	<head>Scope and Contents</head>
	<p>This collection consists of 65 letters written by Robert Saunders of Williamsburg, Virginia to his wife Lucy Burwell Saunders (60 letters) and his daughters Lucy Page Saunders (3 letters) and Roberta P. Saunders (2 letters) from 1829-1867.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$b">
	<head>Arrangement of Materials</head>
	<p>The correspondence is arranged chronologically.</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
	<head>Additional Information</head>
</descgrp>
<!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS / SUBJECT TERMS -->
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<p>This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.</p>
	<controlaccess>
		<head>Corporate Name:</head>
			<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="local">College of William and Mary--Faculty and Staff</corpname>
	</controlaccess>
	<controlaccess>
		<head>Genre/Form of Material:</head>
			<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Correspondence</genreform>
	</controlaccess>
	<controlaccess>
		<head>Topical Term:</head>
			<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">College of William and Mary--Alumni and Alumnae.</subject>
			<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">College of William and Mary--Presidents.</subject>
			<subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">Confederate States of            America. War Dept.</subject>
			<subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">Williamsburg (Va.)--History--19th century.</subject>
	</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->
<!-- END COLLECTION LEVEL METADATA -->
<!-- BEGIN SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS -->
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Detailed Description of the Collection</head>
<c01 level="file" id="id24290">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">1</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24289">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Hanover c/o Beverley Blair, Richmond,
        <unitdate>16 September 1829</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">1</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Lucy is staying with her sister Margaret (called Peggy).  Expresses wish that his wife and infant daughter Mariana Barbara are in good health.  Reports on the health of his father, her mother, and sister Barbara.  Hopes she has received the gift sent by Mr. Botts for Mariana Barbara.</p>
					    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24291">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Hanover c/o Beverley Blair, Richmond,
        <unitdate>3 October 1829</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">1</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Weather is very warm, concerns over health matters.  Looking forward to being reunited with Lucy and Mariana Barbara. The Empie family and Mrs. Peachy are recovering from the sickness. </p>
					<p>News of Williamsburg. Mrs. Browne and family back in Williamsburg.  Judge (?) is expected soon.  Mr. and Mrs. Campbell have left for Philadelphia.  Mrs. Peachy expecting visit from Mrs. Jane Cary and Mrs. Newsum.  They are to settle in Tennessee.  Mrs. Peachy received letter from Aunt Tucker reporting Mrs. Robertson will visit Aunt Tucker in winter and Mr. and Mrs. Cabell are well. Miss Mary Pryor to marry.  The Coles will attend the wedding  Eliza Waller is ill,  recovering at Dr. Warren's.  Mathew Pierce (my old relation) is very ill and not expected to recover.  Mrs. Dabney Browne and her daughter have been sick but recovering.  Mr. Browne has painted his house and has used bona fide paint, not whitewash. Mr. and Mrs. Edloe arrived in town.  He has read the Devereux and liked it very much.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24313">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">2</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24346">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy c/o Richard Anderson Esq. Richmond,
        <unitdate>28 September 1832</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">2</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Betsy Kennon  our beloved &amp; lovely friend has died due to complications in childbirth.  Very upset.  Expresses sympathy for Captain Kennon. Suggests  Lucy write to him soon. Received the news from Dr. Peachy at the post office. Expresses gratitude that Lucy and the children are well. Encloses $20.  Talks of his father's health as being tolerably well.   The servants have recovered from their sickness.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24347">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Fauquier Springs Hanover,
        <unitdate>30 August 1844</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">2</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Happy she and the children are comfortable at Fauquier Springs.   Expresses  desire to join them, but fears his health won't allow it.  Writes of  a sickness that has taken place much later than usual.  Speaks in unkind terms of the Judge(?). Others at the springs include Mr. Dew, Judge C. &amp; Miss Martha and the boys and Barbara. Expresses  love for his daughters Marianna and Lelia.  Glad to hear that she has gotten thro' her teething.  Mentions the death of Hughella Page.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24348">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Warrenton Springs,
        <unitdate>11 August 1845</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">2</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Writing after a trip to Washington DC.   He mentions cousin Charlotte, Mary Ann, and Peggy.  Explains he accomplished more than anticipated in Washington.  Had dinner with Commodore Warrington.  Attends a reception at  White House.   Introduced to President James K. Polk, Mrs. Polk and Beau Hickman.  Finds Polk to be a very ordinary looking person, of very ordinary manners and  Mrs. Polk   a lady of fine manner.  Spoke to Old Mrs. Madison at  reception for a time and  then backed out of the presence of Royalty &amp; descended among the common herd.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24349">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg,
        <unitdate>2 February 1847</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">2</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Went to St. Paul's in Richmond to hear Bishop John Johns preach.  Disappointed by the appearance of someone else  preaching in place of Johns.  John's appointment (as President of the College of William and Mary)  is much talked about in Richmond.   Would not know what to say to Johns if they met.  Is more and more inclined to leave the college after the next course because of the actions of the Visitors.  Will see Holmes again in reference to the situation at the college.  Lucy is to have Edmund send oysters via Mr. Whitaker.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24350">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24351">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>14 March 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sleepy from a boring sermon given by Dr. Jones.  Jokingly will seek to make such sermons illegal.  Expresses worry about Lelia's cold.  Reminds Lucy of the hereditary weakness of the lungs in his family. Gives his impressions of Senate and role in it.  Letter has literary references to The Arabian Nights.  Went to see Peggy and Mrs. Botts.  They have gone to Cambridge.  Hasn't seen Marianna.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24352">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>28 March 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Nothing accomplished in the  legislature since his absence as he thought.  Was to attend  an astronomy lecture at the Athenaeum but found it  postponed.  Spent evening at the home of  Gustavus Myers  near the Athenaeum.  No regrets about missing  a gentleman's party at Halyburton's.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24353">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>8 April 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Hastily written letter after long,  laborious Senate session. Coming to Williamsburg, Senate business permitting, via Coke's wharf on Saturday.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24354">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg,
        <unitdate>22 April 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Met Senator Mc Sweeney of Wheeling on boat to Richmond. Rode in a hack with Senator and Mrs. Deneale.   Mrs. Senator Deneale  as rough a specimen (he) ever met with.  Busy with Senate work.  No time to meet with Mrs. Cabell.  Mrs. Greene has left Mr. Barton's and has gone to Philadelphia.  Invited to take a  trip to Baltimore by officers of the Fredericksburg Railroad with other Senators.  Will go if he can spare time away from Senate and continue on to Philadelphia to see his friend Robinson and Mrs. G.  Supposes the wedding party has returned to Williamsburg and little lady feels sufficiently married.  Will call on Mr. and Mrs. Henley, Ms. Henley and John A. Henley staying at the American Hotel.  James River flood up to the lower end of  Rocketts due to recent heavy rains causing flooding on the Susquehanna and Potomac also.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24355">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>25 April 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">3</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Everyone is well except Barbara. Concerned about Lucy nursing her to health alone. Barbara's old friends Patty Wilson, or Mrs. Ware, or Mrs. Wise or Mrs. Larke  should help.  Should Barbara complain as to the lack of attention, Lucy is to tell her that he has decided the issue.  Attended church and complains of sleep inducing sermon by Dr. Jones.   He meets Mrs. Stanard and Mrs. Claiborne. Mrs. Stanard  offers  accommodations during the approaching convention.  Will the children come? Where shall they  stay?  Suggests Lucy not come to Richmond on the steamboat Augusta to Port Walthall and rail to Richmond, rather via steamboat Curtis Peck to Richmond.  Talks about present perplexities of the Whigs as to national politics, busy with the Senate.  Death of a member of House of Delegates from Prince George County.  Not heard from Mr. Greene. Presumes Mr. and Mrs. Stevenson have left Williamsburg.  Mr. and Mrs. Peyton Coles are at the Exchange.  Jokes of Mrs. Coles nose which seemedunnecessarily long </p>
					<p>Talks of an unsuccessful attempt to visit Mr. and Mrs. Henley.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24361">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24356">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>28 April 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Mr. Stanard offers invitation of lodging during the upcoming convention and Mrs. Cabell offers to take care of Barbara and Marianna Lelia can stay with Miss Betty Blair. Arrangement  details left to Lucy.  Busy with ordinary business of Senate. Writing letters to politicians about the upcoming presidential elections.  Received a letter from Mrs. Greene.  Mentions the death of John Sergant</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24357">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>6 May 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Coming home to Williamsburg with Mrs. Dunbar.  Requests that Lucy send the carriage to Coke's wharf to pick him up.  Happy that Bob's cold is better.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24358">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>31 May 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Senate holding evening sessions.  Has not had time to see anyone.  Barbara is at Dr. Cabell's. </p>
					<p>Curious as to the results of the recent elections. Who was elected Sheriff of James City County?  Was Bob Shields elected Sheriff of York County?  Judge Clayton won by landslide.  Sends a $10 check, written as part of the letter, and it is removed. Asks that Mr. Vest cash it for her. </p>
					<p>Virginia legislature to adjourn on the 7th.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24359">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>8 June 1852</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Will be coming home via Coke's wharf.  Sally Galt and Lelia Shield  traveling with him. Barbara will not be coming down.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24360">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Williamsburg,
        <unitdate>31 January 1854</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">4</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Will be arriving on Saturday at King's Mill.  Asks that Lucy not meet him there unless it is &quot;perfectly convenient&quot; for her.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24368">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24369">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>3 January 1860</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Cold snap in Richmond. Considerable snow, freezing rain. 15 degree  temperatures. Affection for his grandchildren Ann, Mary , Georgy  and Breckenridge.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24362">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>19 February 1860</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Talks of approaching Party conventions.  Believes the Democrats will choose Stephen Douglas as the candidate at the party convention in Charleston.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24363">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>3 September 1860</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sent hams and shad to Marianna via Ringgold Station.  Peggy is well. Mr. Botts returned to White Sulphur Springs, but didn't see Barbara there. Betty Blair to marry W. Mosely of Buckingham County. Dr. Cabell engaged to Miss Peggy, a music teacher.  Mrs. Caskie, wife of Congressman John Caskie, a debased drunkard and sister of Marmaduke Johnson died.  Rumors she was brutally treated by her husband supported by Dr. Peterkin sermon at funeral.   </p>
					<p>Heard Judge Douglas speak on the Capital square and thinks he made a forcible speech.   Mr. Botts is going to speak in Pittsylvania later in the month.  Hearing that Mr. Gatewood was preaching at St. Paul's, went to worship at St. James.  Heard Dr. Peterkin preach for first time. Disappointed.  Mr. Minnegerode and Mr. Woodbridge taking water in the mountains. Mr. Eyler returning to summer home in Hampton. Mrs. Semple returned to Brooklyn in better health. Little news from Williamsburg. Mr. Thomas Lindsey's son died, Mr. Bunting is better.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24364">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>14 September 1860</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Hopes to leave Williamsburg and be with the family week after next.  Discussion of Bob's school clothes.  Wishes Bob to be decently &amp; abundantly furnished, but fine clothes would beout of place at a country school. Glad Bob is keeping a diary.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24365">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>6 January 1861</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Steamboat taking him to Richmond is decorated with flags in his honor.  Dr. Cabell is married.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24366">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>11 February 1861</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Unreliability of mail due to the condition of the railroad damaged by heavy rains, snow and winds.  Very busy in Richmond.  Bob had difficulty leaving Williamsburg by the York River.   Went up the James the next day. </p>
					<p>Comments on the state of the Union and the Virginia convention to consider secession.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24367">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>27 February 1861</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">5</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Comments about George Washington at Washington's Birthday celebration in Williamsburg.  Not enjoying entertaining members of General Assembly on railroad trip.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24370">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">6</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24371">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Taylorville, Hanover County,
        <unitdate>12 September 1862</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">6</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Writes of the excessive heat  in Williamsburg.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24372">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>16 November 1862</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">6</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Suffering from a hurt.  Responds to Lucy's concerns.  Explains reasons for going to Richmond are to find work to support family.   Thankful  children are helping out.  Never doubted their devotion.   Desperate for work.  Looking for employment within Confederate government. Not optimistic about his prospects.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24373">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24374">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>6 February 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Thinks of his granddaughter Lucy Page  when he sees a  child.  Dreads separation from family. Surmises will get accustomed to it.  Busy at his office.  Shares space with two workers. Call him Professor.   Working  six hours a day.  </p>
					<p>Found room on 3rd St. between Clay and Leigh and board across the street where Williamsburg friends John Hurley Charles Hansford, William Waller and Sydney Smith live.  Asks she address letters to the Ballard House.  Sent a package via Mr. Joynes.  Hopes she received it and likes the calico.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24375">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>9 February 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Asks Lucy write in care of Captain Charles Morris A.Q.M.  in the future.  Hopes she has received  the sewing cotton in his last letter.</p>
					<p>Has taken residence in a boarding house with some Williamsburg friends. Is comfortable considering difficulty of obtaining accommodations and their price.  Not accustomed to work.  Has not had the opportunity to visit anyone.  Hopes to see General Ewell and  Minnegerode tomorrow. </p>
					<p>Visited Drewry's Bluff (Fort Darling) to see Major James Semple.  Boards and inspects the  ironclad  CSS Richmond and  the batteries on the bluff. Meets  Captain Lee, commander of the naval station at the bluff.   Points out he is the brother of General (Robert E.) Lee.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24454">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>15 February 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Raining in Richmond and has a cold.  Only going between his room and the boarding house. Didn't go to church.  Spending time writing letters.  Has sent Bob the permission he desires to go to  church out of ranks.  Daughters are coming to Richmond to see him and stay at Mrs. Clayton's. </p>
					<p>Doesn't see much of other boarders.  Has not been out at night except to get  oysters. Has seen only Mr. Branch, Mr. Custis and Alfred Shield.  Intends to visit acquaintances soon.    </p>
					<p>Misses Lucy, the grandchildren.   Offers regards to Mr. Wilmer and friends.  Writes of the possibility of promotion in his branch of the Treasury.  Robert Taylor trying to find a position for him in his department.  Not optimistic about his prospects.  Mr. Waller has left the department and returned to Williamsburg.   </p>
					<p>Writes of little fight between Confederate cavalry and Yankees on road from Williamsburg in James City County.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24455">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>19 February 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Has seen Lelia and Peggy and was comforted by their visit.  Sending money to Lucy and asks she to write if she needs more.  Received a letter from General  Smith. Bob is acting up and he  has written Bob not to throw away his only chance for a gentleman's education. Writes of the death of Dr. Cabell's mother and  Mr. Hurley.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24456">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>27 February 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">7</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Snow, hail and cold in Richmond.  One of the worst days that (he) has known for several years.  Writes of the disposition of some of the servants.  Little Jim is staying with the Wilmer's.  Saunders is grateful to Wilmer for keeping him. Asks that Wilmer use his judgment as to letting Jim stay with Old Fortune or place him elsewhere.  Does not intend to sell Fanny at this time. She is with Mrs. Hurley.   Old acquaintance in his office  Lucy inquired about is Mr. Gilliam, of  Prince George County,  an older man and member of Minnegerode's  Episcopal church.  Met Mr. Marshall, Kate Edloe's husband. Nothing else to report about Williamsburg.  Has not heard from Bob.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24457">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24458">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,  at Pittsylvania C.H.,
        <unitdate>4 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sending shirts to Lucy for repair via Mr. Johnson.  Provides instructions.  Weather has been bad, but his cold is gone.   Henry Burwell is sick and of some trouble to Lucy and Mr. Wilmer.  Hopes Georgy  is better.  He is clerk  in the 2nd  Auditor department and doing a good job, but  working below his abilities.    Chief clerk would like to promote him.   Would relish a promotion and cares only for the increased salary it will bring.   </p>
					<p>Hears nothing of consequence about Williamsburg except the Yankees have carried the Hofheimer's to Old Point for selling goods in the country.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24459">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania CH,,
        <unitdate>8 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Encloses a check for $25.  Promises to send more.  Disturbed that they can't find fresh provisions and fears they will become scarcer. Prices for board are rising.  Heavy rains and thunderstorms.  Minnegerode received a letter from his daughters. Sending  letter by Gilmer or Semple and will try to send some sugar via Gilmer soon. Mentions Georgy, Breck and darling Lucy Page.  Offers remembrances to Dr. Martin and the Vists.(?).  Mrs. Coleman servants, Bella, Mira and Beverly have run off.  Hopes Lucy doesn't communicate that to their servants.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24460">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>12 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sending 10 pounds of sugar, 10 pounds of rice, some paper, spools of cotton, shoestring, and candy for the grandchildren. Encloses a $25 check.  Went to see Lizzie Ewell.  She wasn't at home.  Weather cold and clear expecting snow or hail.  I have not heard from Bob, have you?</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24461">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>22 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Weather is bad.  Has not gone out, not even to church.   the devil has been permitted to rule the weather for 6 or 7 weeks.  Wrote Bob and received a reply.  He had been suffering from  diphtheria but has recovered entirely. Treated by Dr. Robert Madison of the Institute  who was formerly a student  of the first order.  Upset that Breck is sick and his hearing is affected. </p>
					<p>Gratified to hear of Col. Martin's promotion and marriage. Has seen Mr. Semple.  He would love to visit them, but wants to be firmly established at the Treasury department.  Glad the girls can go to their French School.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24462">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>26 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Snow storm, nearly 12 inches deep, the deepest in 20 or 30 years. Offices are closed.  Sorry to hear that Ann and Mary are sick.  Col Randolph Harrison who told him, according to Mr. George Wise,   that Lelia was very sick. Has not heard the same from Mr. Wilmer. Assumes Wise is mistaken.  John  Gilmer to carry a shirt in need of repair next trip. Sending 4 pairs of summer stockings for darling Lucy Page. Cannot get the eggplant seed she requested...but will keep trying.  Dr Coleman has resigned, gone to Warrenton NC.  Mrs. Tucker intends to return to Williamsburg.  John Barlow lost his wife. his family was in New Kent County.  Has seen Mr. Morecock and  his brother-in-law Captain Taylor.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24463">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>29 March 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">8</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Distressed to hear that Ann and Mary are still sick. Sending 5 pounds of sugar,   some soda, and a few dough nuts for the darling children and a harmonica for Georgy and Breck and a fan for Lucy via Mr. Wilmer.  Not been able to procure the egg plant seed.  Reports no news of consequence from Williamsburg.  Heard a  sermon from Minnegerode and saw  Bishop Johns confirm people at St. Paul's.  I hope you have heard from Bob.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24464">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24466">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>5 April 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Mr.  Patton.  Purchased 31 yards of unbleached cotton (at $1.75/yard) and  will send to Mr. Pollack.  Has little to do in the afternoon and will be pleased to hunt for articles for them.  News from Williamsburg via Mr. W. H. Pierce who has heard it from others.  Pierce is afraid to go into Williamsburg since he sells goods secretly.  Pierce bought a letter from Mr. Sweeney.  Sweeney took 5 mules from the Saunders property. The Yankees stole one, two to Isham for use on the farm, one to Gawian for use on Mrs. Henley's and one to Mrs. Sydney Smith.  </p>
					<p>Isham claims slaves that remain in Williamsburg will wait for their masters'  return and are unhappy at the treatment of the Yankees. Jacob (Mrs. Tucker's servant) has left for Hampton.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24467">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>12 April 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Received the shirts she sent by Mr. Lefebvre.  Will be sending a package back via him to include white cotton for 4 shirts for Bob and a piece of linen.  Met Martha Page. Mr. Sheldon had just come up from Gloucester with news that the Yankees had committed more deprivations in that county.  Met Mrs. Peachy for the first time since leaving Williamsburg.  Presumed that she was unhappy to see him looking well and in health.  Heard that General Wise has gone down to Williamsburg  and was driving the Yankees south.  Presumes that Wise has taken Fort Magruder.  Sees Julia Johns.  Memminger says he sorry about his position and that he could not find something more worthy. Doubts sincerity of remark.  The bread riots were realis war not a bread riot war is merely the pretext for  plunder..</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24543">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>14 April 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Diphtheria epidemic.   Concerned that Lucy is tired caring for the sick especially the servants who don't know how to attend to each other. </p>
					<p>Sending a plate to Lelia as to replace one of Mrs. Lefebvre's broken at the Rectory.  Inventory of what  box he has sent.  An old towel, shirts, small quantity of Passover bread from Mrs. Heller, a doll for Lucy Page, caps for Georgy and Breck, 31 yards of unbleached cotton (at 1.75/yd), shoestrings, 20lbs sugar, 20 lbs of rice, 6lbs coffee (at $3.50 which is cheap! by a dollar,  1lb green tea, ½ lb  black tea and 2 oz of soda,   a tin horn for Georgy  and a whistle for  Breck, candy and $50.  Nothing more specific from General Wise at Williamsburg.  Minnegerode's son James has a warrant as midshipman.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24544">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>26 April 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sending a sample of  fabric ($5.50/yd).  Sent Lelia a box of Beckwith's Pills.  Jim and Cyrus  have been hired at a tobacco factory.  Relieved Wilmer is free  of their support.  Heard accounts of deprivations of  Yankees in Gloucester and of people fleeing.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24545">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>3 May 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Happily hears of Lucy's recovery from Mr. James Semple.  Paid broker $105 for $21 in gold to purchase article for Lucy.  Semple hired out his slave, Jim, in Danville.   Jim had run away once and was with the Yankees. Glad Jim has not the chance to tell other slaves of his escape.  Heard nothing of slaves Molly and Elia.  All their servants in Williamsburg, except Sam, who was hired at the lunatic asylum, are still in place. All slaves at the farm, except Jacob, are still there.  Jacob  enticed away by his wife a servant of Mrs. Tucker. All Mrs. Tuckers' slaves have run off.  Thinks Yankees will abandon the lunatic asylum.  If so, Lee  would make some arrangements for its support.  A battle is near at Fredericksburg (Chancellorsville).  Funeral tomorrow, at St. Paul's, for Channing Price, killed near Fredericksburg.  Does not repine or brood over his affairs.  Would need only to see Lucy  the children and grandchildren to be happy as anyone could be during the war.  The war enrages rather than depresses  him. Strongly  angered, filling him with desire to see the Yankee race exterminated.  Will attempt to get a promoted position when the members of Congress are gone. Believes it will be easier to approach Secretaries at that time.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24546">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>31 May 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">9</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Suffering  with acute diarrhea.  Misses Lucy terribly.  Spent  an evening with General  (Richard Stoddart) Ewell.  Ewell 's been promoted to Lieutenant General a day or two after being married to Mrs. Brown. Ewell has gone to join General Lee's army and take command of Gen Jackson's old command.  Mr. Botts lost his slaves.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24465">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24547">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>7 June 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Recovered from  diarrhea, but many of acquaintances still ill.   Has not heard from Bob.   Has seen Mr. Semple who  offered  regards to the family.  There is nothing new from Williamsburg.</p>
					<p>Has seen Mr. Jonas, Mr. Penick,  Henry and John Dix. Has not been able to get shoes the girls asked for but  the importation of blockade  goods  is expected during the present week.    </p>
					<p>Rumors from Vicksburg are not good news.  Has seen a dispatch from General Johnston, but the information it contains cannot fully be authenticated.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24548">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>12 June 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sending unbleached cotton on Tuesday. Mr. Custis daughters had seen Lucy and Page.  Sent the shoes they asked for.  Has not heard from Bob.  Miss Judith Carter Nelson says  all servants from Shelby are gone had gone except the carriage driver and wife. Has not seen Lizzie Ewell. Has seen  I. Custis and Mrs. Miles Selden.</p>
					<p>Yankee commander has given Dr. Garrett permission to return home.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24549">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>25 June 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Accepted a position as quartermaster of the Pittsylvania District and will be relocated to Danville.  Will stop at Pittsylvania on his way to Danville. Was offered a higher paying position but turned it down to be able to go to Danville and be close to the family.  Eventually he will hold the rank of captain and that will reward him with a higher salary.  Then he can buy from the commissary sugar, bacon, flour, salt, etc and this not for myself, but for my family. at government prices.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24571">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>28 June 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Preparing to leave Richmond to assume duties in the Quartermaster Corps  collecting the tax in kind.  Believes new position will be anything but sedentary, but  rather laborious and require a great deal travel. for a month  Feels ready for the task.  Happy she received  bundle and Mr. Wilmer liked the shirts. Sends regards to Miss Lizzie who he hopes to see again soon.  Will try and get things Lucy requested, but he believes the blankets and the iron things will be difficult to procure.  Has not heard from his daughters and hopes to before he leaves Richmond.  Will not be able to go to Lexington, because he will be too busy organizing a new business not only to (him) but to the whole corps of quartermasters in the same service.&quot;  Expresses regards for his grandchildren Anne and Mary.  Hopes to see them at the Rectory before they leave, and to Georgy, Breck who he'll bring  a spelling book a piece and candy for darling Lucy Page. Unable to see Lizzie Ewell or Colonel and Mrs. Munford.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24572">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at the Rectory to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>12 July 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Salutation to My beloved wife.  Send subsequent letters to Danville. Wants to hear from Bob.  General Pendleton has not been injured.   Mrs. Gilmer lost brother, Col. Henry Carrington, Col. Rawley Martin is wounded and a prisoner, Col. Whittle and James Poindexter are wounded again, Col. Tazewell Patton reportedly killed or wounded.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24573">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Danville to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>30 July 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">10</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Setting up districts in Pittsylvania County for the administration of the collection of the tax in kind.  Has no clerk.  Offered the position of county agent to Mr. Gilmer, but he declined. Then offered it to Mr. Johnson.  Will travel, go to Franklin and Bedford Counties next week to organize them   Lucy is to direct her next letter to Bedford County, in care of Captain Charles Mallory.  News of Pittsylvania Court House relatives and friends at Pittsylvania Court. Colonel Carrington wounded in the hand and captured, Colonel Martin is assumed dead, and Captain James Poindexter and Lt. Hutchins captured.  Colonel Whittle wounded but not taken prisoner, Col. Whittle and Col. Patton, wounded and  imprisoned.  The Poindexter and Carter boys are at home and slightly wounded. </p>
					<p>All are well at the Rectory, darling Lucy Page as sweet  as ever.  News of Williamsburg in a letter from Mr. Sydney Smith.  Mr. Sweeney told him their servants were still all in place &amp; contented.  Old Mr. Pettitt has died according to Dr. Wise.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24574">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24578">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Rectory to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>3 August 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Discusses travel plans. Very busy and doesn't have time to write.  Suggests that several routes from Lexington to Danville and asks that she inform him of her travel plans. Concerned the Bob must get some certificate from Gen(eral) Smith to keep with him until he gets back to Lexington, to avoid possible delay by enrolling officers.  Asks that Lucy not spend any time with Lizzie Nelson who has come all the way from the South  and wants her full attention adding Circumstances force one to be selfish. My mind is as strained as have ever had it, and I cannot support an additional burden.   Reports the death of Colonel Tazewell, the brother of Mrs. John Gilmer and has heard nothing about members of Lucy's family.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24579">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Liberty, Bedford  to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>7 August 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Happy that she will go to Botetourt and will be comfortable there.  Will be traveling all month.   Sent her a check for $100 and hopes she has  received it.  Lelia wrote of the death of  poor Mrs. Munford. He has written to Bob.  Details recent travels and is now staying in Liberty for two or three days with Captain Mallory.  Intends to go to Wytheville when he leaves Liberty, if the Yankees are not about, and then to Carroll, Franklin, Henry and Patrick counties.    Will try to meet Bob at the Rectory.  Asks that she direct her letters to Danville.  Includes a biographical note stating that Captain Mallory, the brother of Dr. Mallory, is from Hampton.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24581">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Henry Court House to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>7 September 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Sent a passport to Mr. Wilmer.  Hopes he has received it.  Rode from Danville to Henry Court House by stage.  Stayed in a fine large room in an old fashioned tavern built of logs.  Is comfortable there as opposed to not being so in his other travels.  Dined with an attorney Mr. Wootten, an old student at the college, and acquaintance.   Wootten helping him with his business.  Will resume his travels to Patrick and Franklin Counties before returning to Danville.  Hopes to be reunited with Lucy before the end of next week.  Has, happily, seen Mrs. Neel and Miss J. Bucktrout, daughters of Mrs. I. Bucktrout  from Williamsburg.  Spoke to Rev. William Lee and he is well.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24583">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Henry Court House to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>11 September 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Finding it difficult traveling from Henry Court House  to Patrick Court House.  There are no horses to be hiredand there is no public conveyance to Patrick Court House from any point on the globe.&quot;  Travel has generally agreed with him and he is entirely well.  Not suffering from gout and neuralgia he has endured in previous years at this time of the season.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24593">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Pittsylvania Court House to his daughter Lucy Page,
        <unitdate>4 November 1863</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">11</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Lucy Page at the home of Mrs. Michie in Staunton.   She has a beaux there, a Dr. Rush. Considers him an entirely respectable young man at his position &amp; and has the reputation of being a very worthy one.  Has traveled more than 1000 miles from end of July to 26 September.  Has used more than 200 stamps on letters relating to official business. Regrets not having written her but uses the large amount of official correspondence as an excuse for not having the time to do so.  Has a fond remembrance of Mrs. Jones, the former Miss Nanny Marshall.   Asks to be remembered to Capt. Bagby although he is not sure that that is his name, but is sure he knows him.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24575">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">12</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24601">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>17 March 1864</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">12</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Is as busy in Richmond as he was previously.  </p>
					<p>Disappointed to hear that Colonel Rawley Martin was not among the exchange prisoners.  Bob has asked for information on how to join the army.  </p>
					<p>Richmond at this time is very disagreeable and every thing is awfully high &amp; things to eat are scarce.   He manages, thanks to his friends.  Mr. James Lyon's house in Richmond has burned to the ground.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24576">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">13</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24607">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House,
        <unitdate>7 March 1865</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">13</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Bob's division is expected to be ordered to Gordonsville. Hopes to see him before he leaves.  Major Baker P. indicates that Bob is well and that Pickett's Division,   was to be reviewed by General Lee.  Colonel Benjamin S. Ewell, has been by to see him.  Expects to join Lucy on Saturday, but travel is uncertain.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24611">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>27 July 1865</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">13</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Informs Lucy that he is well at the home of Charles Waller in Williamsburg.  Traveled from Danville to Richmond, stayed with Mr. Sweeney, then to Williamsburg.  The Waller invitation to lodging was one of many invitations he received.  Has seen many friends and they are well. Has many things on his mind and cannot express them in a hastily written letter.  Saunders Expresses his love for his wife, children and grandchildren and old friends and writes servants very kind.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24623">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House,
        <unitdate>13 August 1865</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">13</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Gilmer for free.  Grateful to him as he didn't have the money to pay for it. Sent the application, along with the regular applications for pardon, to Washington, by way of Richmond where it was signed with a recommendation for acceptance by Governor  Pierpont.  Received  his  property in town without difficulty, but is concerned about York County land holdings.  Anxious that the pardon be accepted and for the complete restoration of  property.  Suspects he will have to go to Washington to see to the matter.  </p>
					<p>Of  Williamsburg he writes  there is nothing doing here, nor is there any prospect, for some time at least for any one to do any thing in any department of human employment to support himself.   Everything is disjointed and in a languishing condition and he would not return to Williamsburg this year if he could get something to do which would barely support life in Pittsylvania or elsewhere for the next year. The families of Colonel Munford,  Dr. Mercer and Dr. Canius (?). are the only one's to return to Williamsburg. </p>
					<p>Envelope addressed to Lucy, care of Mr. J. Clarke, Esq. Danville  attached.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24628">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Washington to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>27 August 1865</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">13</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Had dinner with Peggy and her husband, William Botts in Richmond.  They and their grandchildren are well.  Botts has given him a letter to the President, which he delivered without being able to say much.  Will attempt an interview, but is not hopeful it will occur tomorrow and he may be in Washington a few days before it occurs.  Is as active as a steam printing press and shall not relax (his) efforts until (he ) succeeds in getting (his) property restored or come to a dead halt.  Confident it will be restored.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="file" id="id24577">
<did>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
<c02 level="item" id="id24629">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his daughter Lucy Page at Pittsylvania Court House,
        <unitdate>19 August 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Happy she survived the disagreeable circumstances attending the unusually uncomfortable journey from Richmond to Pittsylvania Court. House.  She is with Miss Sallie and is staying with Miss Mary away from the ennui of Williamsburg.Sends regards to Mr. Whittle and Mr. D. Coles. Judge and Mrs. Gilmer. Indicates great affection for his friends at Pittsylvania Court House.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24630">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>4 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Secured the breast pin Lucy had forgotten.Met Col.Ewell and thanked him for his kindness as to the carriage.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24635">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg  to his daughter, Roberta Page,
        <unitdate>11 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Encloses $5.  Mother leaving for Mr. Botts after arriving at Richmond.  Informs her that she, the Munfords, Custises  and Sherwells are all well.  Prof. Taliaferro and John Henley have died.  Charles Wallers baby died. Prof. Millington a grand old man who is dying gradually.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24636">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Richmond,
        <unitdate>11 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Bob came down from Richmond by steamboat and got a chill.  Administered quinine. Sending the $5 to Roberta Page.  Mr. Keatts, the shoemaker, of Pittsylvania Court House came to visit.  She is at Richmond with granddaughter.   Williamsburg is improved in health. Their immediate friends the Mumfords, Custises and Sherwells are well. Mrs. Maupin has is at the College Hotel. and Mr. Darlington from York County is renting her house.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24637">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House,
        <unitdate>16 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Apparently she is at Pittsylvania with Lucy Page,Peggy.Tells of Bobs chills.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24638">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his daughter Roberta Page,
        <unitdate>25 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>
					<p>Bob returned to Williamsburg with a chill and fever which was treated with quinine and other pills. Will stay with the Pettitts for a couple of days. Pleased that Lucy is in pleasant places,away from the labor of keeping house at a time when labor is to take the places of means,and when there are no servants to depend upon. The unhealthfulness of this region, including the town exceeds anything that I have ever known.  Chills and fever epidemic in Williamsburg.  Asks her not to come back too soon.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="item" id="id24639">
<did>
        <unittitle>Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy,
        <unitdate>30 September 1867</unitdate>,
</unittitle>
		<container label="Folder">14</container>
    </did>
    	<scopecontent>

					<p>Mrs Vest has died suddenly Very sad over it.  Mentions her exuberant spirit, resilient frame and defiance of misfortune. Robert Taylor,steward of the Lunatic asylum and son in law of Mrs Pettis,also has died.Confined to the house with gout.Being treated by Dr. Carmen.Has not been able to prepare the house for Lucys return even though Bob is helping.How much it will cost to bring her back from Richmond.Happy to learn that Dr. Millington is doing better. Expresses good wishes and sentiments,love for his old friend. Conveys great gratitude to Mr. and Mrs. Blankenship for their kindness.</p>
    	</scopecontent>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- END SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS -->
</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- footer.inc.php -->
