<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viw00172">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
    <eadid mainagencycode="US-VWM" countrycode="US">PUBLIC "-//College of William and Mary::Earl Gregg Swem Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViW::viw00172:: Herman Recht Papers, 1943-1946)//EN" "viw00172.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1946</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">
		Recht, Herman		<num type="collectionnumber">Mss. Acc. 2001.31</num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wm_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2009 By the College of William and Mary. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Finding aid created by Benjamin Bromley, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2007</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
		<language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1946</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Special Collections Research Center
			<num type="Accession Number">Mss. Acc. 2001.31</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wm.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/wm_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed By</label>
          <item>Special Collections Staff.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Overview of the Collection</head>
      <repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
        <corpname>Special Collections Research Center</corpname>
      </repository>
      <unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Herman Recht Papers	<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-1946</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099" label="Identification:" countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-VWM">01/Mss. Acc. 2001.31</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a">
        <extent unit="Items">780.00</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Materials">
	  The papers are in:
<language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">This collection is comprised of more than 700 letters written by Herman Recht (1908-1971), a Navy yeoman, from Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946 to his wife, Esther, in Clairton, Pennsylvania. There are no letters from Esther because, as he wrote to her, saving them would make him homesick.
</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator:"><famname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Herman Recht, 1908-1971</famname>
arrangement
	</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <!-- ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>This collection is open to all researchers.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
        <p>Before publishing quotations or excerpts from any materials, permission must be obtained from the Special Collections Research Center, and the holder of the copyright, if not Swem Library.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="510">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Herman Recht Papers, Special Collections Research Center, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 07/04/2001.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <!-- END ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION -->
    </descgrp>
    <!--COLLECTION LEVEL METADATA: -->
    <bioghist altrender="Biographical Note" encodinganalog="545">
      <head>Biographical Note</head>
      <p>He was born in Lviv Ukraine.  Married to Esther who lived in Clairton, Pennsylvania while he was a Navy yeoman at Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946.  Recht had been a lawyer for eight and a half years before joining the Navy. He was Jewish. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: &lt;a href="http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Herman Recht"&gt;http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Herman Recht&lt;/a&gt;.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <head>Scope and Contents</head>
      <p>This collection is comprised of more than 700 letters written by Herman Recht (1908-1971), a Navy yeoman, from Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946 to his wife, Esther, in Clairton, Pennsylvania. There are no letters from Esther because, as he wrote to her, saving them would make him homesick.
</p>
      <p>Recht had been a lawyer for eight and a half years before joining the Navy. He was very well read, and regularly came into Williamsburg to dine at the Williamsburg Lodge and borrow books from and read magazines in the William and Mary library where his interests ran from public affairs to the latest fiction. He often inquires about activities in the Jewish community in Clairton, and is a strong advocate for racial minorities. He is very knowledgeable about classical music. He regularly reads the Pittsburgh Press and inquires about friends and family in Clairton and Pittsburgh.  Gossip about friends from home is included in almost every letter.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$b">
      <head>Arrangement of Materials</head>
      <p>Letters are arranged chronologically.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <!-- CONTROLLED ACCESS / SUBJECT TERMS -->
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <p>This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.</p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Name:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">College of William and Mary</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre/Form of Material:</head>
        <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Correspondence</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Occupation:</head>
        <occupation encodinganalog="656" source="local">United States--Lawyers</occupation>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Topical Term:</head>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">African Americans</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">United States--Jewish History.</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">United States--Social life and customs.</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Williamsburg (Va.)--History.</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="local">World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners of War</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <!-- END CONTROLLED ACCESS TERMS -->
    <!-- END COLLECTION LEVEL METADATA -->
    <!-- BEGIN SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS -->
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Detailed Description of the Collection</head>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23287">
        <head>Series 1: Folders 1-100: 30 October 1943-30 January 1944</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 1-100: 30 October 1943-30 January 1944,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23371">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23288">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 1-10:  30 October 1943-3 November 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 1-10:  30 October 1943-3 November 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>70,000 people at Camp Peary, 1,400 arrive in one day---all clothes stenciled “H.Recht”—gross pay $50; has worked in journalism, law and family furniture store; knows German, French and Yiddish; Address: Herman Recht, A.S., Plat. 1678, Area C-8, Camp Peary, Va.—75% of fellow sailors are married; HR is “almost 35” years old—barracks mates know that he is a lawyer;  refers to request by Marian Anderson that the Daughters of the American Revolution suspend, for her concert,  its segregated seating policy { In 1939 the DAR refused to let her sing in Constitution Hall); a military film shown on the base about “Jugoslavs” was not “unadulterated”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23363">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 11-20:  4 November 1943-15 November 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 11-20:  4 November 1943-15 November 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>He is the only Jew in the barracks—other men are about age 28-38, mostly technicians. Sailors on 12-hour leave go to Williamsburg since they may not make it back from Richmond on time.  Refers to Seabees in Casablanca, Sicily, and Salerno.  He will be promoted from Apprentice Seamen (A.S.) to 2d Class Seaman and maybe to 1st Class Seamen at the end of boot camp. Volunteers for yeoman duty when call made for typists—plays chess—men 35 and older exempted from the obstacle course—regularly visits a rabbi. Tells Esther that he doesn’t save her letters because he doesn’t want to make himself homesick.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23364">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 21-30: 15 November 1943-21 November 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 21-30: 15 November 1943-21 November 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>On yeoman duty for 8 ½ hours but didn’t have more than 15 minutes work. Isn’t allowed to use typewriter to write personal letters during work hours. Laundry must be hung properly—whites on the whites line and blues and other colored items on the blues line; explosion in Yorktown on the 16th. Men chop wood for fuel. Most men have more to offer the war effort than his “less brawny and less combat or-construction skilled brains have to give.” Jobs are frequently shifted; lawyers doing mosquito control, insurance work, and lecturing. Would like time to read and listen to music; reads  L’il Abner comic strip. Peary is  the only boot camp for Seabees in the country. Some Chief Petty Officers aren’t too bright. HR is reading ”The Psychology of the Fighting Man.” Unlike sailors, soldiers can send clothes to a laundry. His promotion to S2C is a “big event.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23365">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 31-40: 22 November 1943-1 December 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 31-40: 22 November 1943-1 December 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Had to shave by razor since electricity is frequently cut off during the day—all 58 pieces of clothing are expected to fit in a white sea bag. Accepted for yeoman training---was sort of interested in storekeeper’s school. He thinks his letters sound dull and asks Esther’s view.  An 18 year-old  Vermonter with a harsh and shrill voice is uncomfortable with the swearing that goes on. He is “getting apt in the use of “fuckin’” this and “fuckin’” that with all the various nuances.”
</p>
              <p>Religious Emphasis Week; heard several talks by Rabbi Philip S. Bernstein, of Rochester, NY relating to Jews in Palestine and Central Europe. A friend at home writes that the new assistant conductor of the New York Philharmonic, “that young Bernstein” is a friend of hers.   Convinced of the evils of organized religion and of the “tommyrot of much of the ritual.”  No cameras allowed—doubts that he could be admitted to officer training due to his defective eyes. A fellow sailor dislikes the Southerners for their prejudices but “they don’t mind sleeping with black gals.” A record 2,150 inductees in one day.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23366">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 41-50: 1 December  1943-10 December 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 41-50: 1 December  1943-10 December 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Rumor that camp will become a prison camp—Boston Symphony programs sound interesting—no shortage of chocolate bars or Rinso. Hopes to read the Old Prophets, good poetry, and Latin and Greek poets and philosophers. He and friends see Peary as being on a vast WPA or CCC  at times . Esther sends food including the coveted bananas, wants her to perfume her next letter with Tabu. Has word that his [furniture?] business is picking up. On 7 December 1943 letter, he writes “2 years after “ [anniversary of Pearl Harbor attack]; hopes he won’t have opportunity to write “3 years after.” The typing and shorthand teacher has a Ph.D. Saw “As Thousands Cheer.” with Lena Horne (”all her gorgeous self”), Mickey Rooney,                                            and Katherine Grayson. Music by Jose Iturbi. Friend had a beer in tavern in colonial building. His wedding anniversary is December 29. Wants to renew his subscription to Free World. H.R&gt; takes the role of an attorney for the accused in mock courts martial. Veterans Administration in Pittsburgh notifies him at home that  he is civil service legible and certified as an attorney and announces a vacancy for a Field Examiner Grade CAP-7 at $2,600 per annum.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23367">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 51-60: 11 December  1943-25 December 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 51-60: 11 December  1943-25 December 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Liberties are 21 hours and 62 hours.; 98 on a spelling test. Rumor that 7,000 women office workers in the District of Columbia have moved from private rooming houses to government dormitories. Describes how life insurance is paid in the event of his death. The new Caruso album got rave reviews morning sky was particularly Wedgwoodian in its blue. Will subscribe to the “Nation” and the “New Republic.” Reading “Philosopher’s Holiday” by Irwin Edman.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23368">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 61-70: 26 December  1943-30 December 1943</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 61-70: 26 December  1943-30 December 1943,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Temporarily assigned to make records of long distance phone calls received. Hopes to hear Ezio Pinza on the radio, His 8th wedding anniversary is December 27.—weather continues “stinkeroo.” Looking forward to whenever the war ends and getting back too civilized living. Fathers have a real interest in the war—they ought to take all available non-fathers first— the young  have what it takes to fight these stupid wars. Live in and for today while maintaining some perspective as to possible future. Number of Seabees began at 99, rose to 3,000 and are now at 262,000. Service men should be allowed  to board trains ahead of all others-they deserve a comfortable ride since they get one so infrequently. Saw “The Lodger” with Merle Oberon, George Sanders and Laird Cregar.—it would frighten children. Post office on the base is heated by wood fires. Pork is now available without ration points. –[Foreshadowing  of D-Day]. Has the feeling that any day there may be a gigantic action and the first waves of men pouring into Europe will result in huge casualty lists. Steel strike is pending—labor shouldn’t strike just because no new contract is signed—wait until the new contract omits retroactive provisions. Labor is giving FDR [Franklin D. Roosevelt] one hell of a thank you. Max Werner making predictions for 1944 in Look magazine says that Germany will have a military and political collapse next year.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23369">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 71-80: 31 December  1943-8 January 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 71-80: 31 December  1943-8 January 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Going to a Burton Holmes film and lecture on Mexico City.  Morale is low due to new liberty policy with a 60 mile limit. French and Norwegian sailors are atationed at Norfolk.  Refers to family “businesses”[a furniture store—Recht’s Furniture, 534 Miller Avenue, Clairton, Pa-- and a grocery store]. Americans are going to be in for terrible shocks soon. Will be hell when invasion gets going. Air bombing won’t  prevent the first-wave men from difficulties. Has read what happened at Salerno, Dieffe, and Tarawa. Russian part of war is much worse. Wife recently saw Gilbert and Sullivan’s “Trial by Jury.” Thinking about applying for officers’ training. Listened to Drew Pearson and Walter Winchell on radio. Greyhound may take over the camp bus lines to Richmond and Washington. Much work is divided among many more men than is necessary. A fellow sailor has a Ph.D. in history and is in charge of one of the small libraries in the camp—he knows several languages but no attention is paid to language qualifications. A colored [his word] company is performing La Traviata in Pittsburgh at end of month with tenor Joseph Lipscomb. The train service from Williamsburg to Richmond is not good,. Chocolate bars are available again. Saw “Destination Tokyo” with Cary Grant. Fellow servicemen amazed at his legal background compared to his rating. He was drafted and has to serve for the duration of the war or the national emergency and 6 months thereafter. Went to a concert in Williamsburg; many  servicemen and civilian women. William and Mary students served as ushers. Liked the Brahms sonata and the Jamaican Rumba. Tries to write his wife at least one letter a day but is concerned that he can’t write a sensible letter in smooth flowing English. Wife will try to get a reservation at the Williamsburg Lodge. She should mention his rating-Seaman 2d Class. Fellow sailor hopes to buy up oil leases at his next duty station and resell them to private oil companies at a great profit.. Plans to see “Cry Havoc” with Margaret Sullivan at the “local.” Heard Claire Primrose in an opera in Richmond. Has visited Mexico.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23370">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 81-90: 9 January 1944-17 January 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 81-90: 9 January 1944-17 January 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Wants a subscription to Time magazine. Concerned that the general American public doesn’t take the war seriously. Reads the American Magazine—February 1944 issue has the beginning of a novel by Franz Werfel. News story about government program for oil development overseas—Alaska, Burma, India, Persia, and Dutch East Indies are possibilities—private oil interest are opposed. Has never been close to his father—mother is deceased. Unpaved roads  have been paved with a hard surface. The Seabees are also in Bougainville in the Solomon Islands. Likes foreign correspondence section of the Christian Science Monitor. Article by Arthur Koestler on war attitudes in the New York Times Magazine. Heard pianist Jose Iturbi in concert. Surprised at the anti-Roosevelt sentiment  at the camp. Annoyed that people make their military heros in public administrators and statesmen. Doesn’t like being called by his full first name.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23372">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 91-100: 17 January 1944-30 January 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 91-100: 17 January 1944-30 January 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">1</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Got in line for phone sat 1:15 pm (46th in line) and reached the phone at 5:15 pm. Clear and sane article on Roosevelt by Eliot Janeway in December 1943 Fortune magazine. Tries to write daily but often feels at a loss as to what to say. Esther’s father owns a store on Burrows Street [ in Pittsburgh.] Several Jewish Seabees—surprised that many are heavy equipment operators. Interested in working in the camp library.  May take a course in conversational Spanish.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23373">
        <head>Series 2: Folders 101-200: 31 January 1944-6 June 1944</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 101-200: 31 January 1944-6 June 1944,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23375">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23374">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 101-110: 31 January 1944-7 February 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 101-110: 31 January 1944-7 February 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Thinks there will be a heightening of United States, British, and Chinese forces against the Japanese. The war will cause terrible scars and the people will continue to be greedy bastards. The cousin of “Louise” teaches music at William and Mary. –Music Department should hold a series of concerts for servicemen. Reading another Irwin Edman book, “Candle in the Dark” and “Yesterday is Dead” by Stuart Cloete. Has the German measles and is in sick bay—first time ever in the hospital. Radio says that journalist,  Raymond Clapper has died in a bomber over the Marshall Islands. Has had ice cream every day since he arrived at the camp. Americans may take Rabaul in Papua New Guinea. Much increase in war bond sales since stories of Japanese atrocities became known.. Harold Ickes has announced that  U.S. will construct a 1,200 mile pipe line from the Persian Gulf to the eastern Mediterranean. Listening to Mahler’s 4th Symphony played by the New York Philharmonic Orchestra. Food isn’t hot and half the time no salt or sugar. Thinks Germany will surrender with the next six months or so. Wishes that music departments at William and Mary and the University of Richmond would create a joint concert series. Hear a broadcast from Mexico City of Elias Breeskin’s group. New cereal –bran with raisins-amazed that both are in a single box. Heard Herbert Marshall and Monty Wooley singing “Mairzy Dotes.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23376">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 111-120: 8 February 1944-16 February 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 111-120: 8 February 1944-16 February 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Got his first issue of the New Leader. Thinks it’s anti-communist but socialist. Oil line from the Persian Gulf to Alexandria will help ships in the Mediterranean area and those coming through the Suez Canal into waters near Burma and India. Western terminus may be Haifa. Reading “The Lone Wolf” – has succumbed to mysteries. Has read one by Raymond Chandler.   Too late to find a “Will You Be My Valentine?” “Why do I need one?—you is my Valentine you is.” Hopes Esther can again spend 5 or 6 days at the Williamsburg Lodge. Read “The Great Impersonator” Heard from Louise’s cousin who teaches music at William and Mary. Hopes to attend a concert with her; Miss [Natalie Jena] Rosenthal. Fellow Seabee is going to IBM School at the camp. “That’s International Business Machines—big and complex things that punch out the card records.” A few hundred men are in the camp brig. New enlarged library. A “shul”, a synagogue for Orthodox and Chasidiim Jews has been built at the camp—the first for the Navy.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23377">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 121-130: 16 February 1944-13 March 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 121-130: 16 February 1944-13 March 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Helps other servicemen with their income tax forms. Esther receives a $50 monthly allowance from the government. Refers to Victory Tax, a wartime income tax. Got his transcripts in case he applies for a commission. He was 12th in a law class of 69. Finds the service is stressful—asks Esther to withhold  some of her remarks about her unhappy lot. Received a letter of recommendation from Dr. [Judson Adams] Crane, Dean of the [University of Pittsburgh] law school. Couldn’t get a room in the Lodge for the Saturday and Sunday of her visit. They will stay in a house on Cary Street, off Jamestown Road; the landlord’s name is Whitacre. Talked to a “negro” from New York about treatment of blacks by whites; New Yorker can’t understand why blacks are not accepted as humans like other people and treated accordingly. He must restrain his temper at times when he would prefer not to and remain quietly satisfied knowing that an ignoramus is that regardless of race or rating. Talked to the Chief Petty Officer in charge of libraries and there may he an opening. Reading “They Shall Not Sleep” by Leland Stowe. Saw Hedy Lamarr in “The Uninvited.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23378">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 131-140: 14 March 1944-27 March 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 131-140: 14 March 1944-27 March 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hopes to move from a yeoman unit to a job in the camp library.  Wants to find out about the difference in amount of leave between working at the library and in the transportation pool.  Got a recommendation letter for his transfer to the library or transportation job from H. Passamaneck, Director of the Young Men’s and Women’s Hebrew Association. Finally gets transferred into the Transportation office.  He finished “They Shall Not Sleep” by Leland Stowe, which talks about the future relations between the US and Russia; there is talk about making the camp into regular navy.  Has gotten his leave approved, and saw the movie “Lady in the Dark;” supposedly will be getting 3,000 people who can’t read or speak English in camp later this week.  Talks about how the postwar period will be something to observe and live through, for many latent prejudices will come out then.  Talks about Jewish services at the Camp, and how they are uninspiring; watched the movie “Purple Heart”; bringing more regular navy to the base. Has been put on special assignment, meaning he does not meet the Navy’s physical standards, as the Navy is now integrating SA men into the entire Navy, not just putting them into the Seabees.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23379">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 141-150: 28 May 1944-5 April 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 141-150: 28 May 1944-5 April 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>First day in Transportation office, had to move to a new barracks.  Goes to the library to read magazines and newspapers; got his liberty schedule.  Talks about Fred Woltman, a newspaper writer, and his change in politics; mentions the Dies Committee.  Hears rumors that all the Seabee men at the camp will be transferred across the country; is reading Pierre Van Paasen’s “The Forgotten Ally”; calls war a “stupid extravaganza.”  Men are starting to get transferred out of Camp Peary by train.  Makes comments about a speech of Churchill that was on the radio, and about the White Paper. Peary is being changed to a “general service camp.”  Talks about Winchell’s response to Dies.  Reads Joe Rosenfarb’s book “Highway to Tokyo.”  Comments on and includes an article about the Supreme Court ruling allowing African-Americans to vote in primaries.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23380">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 151-160: 6 April 1944-13 April 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 151-160: 6 April 1944-13 April 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Finds out that he will not be transferred to another base.  Talks about the upcoming presidential election.  Goes to a Seder meal; talks about rent in Williamsburg, at $8 a week; talks about being a checkers champion.  Saw the documentary “Tunisian Victory.”  Wants to do some reading on public housing, such as work in community centers.  Sees most of the older officers getting transferred out as new recruits are being brought in; there is a shortage of Coca-Cola.  Makes plans for his wife Esther to come down and see him.  Describes his daily routine, and compares it to his home routine.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23381">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 161-170: 14 April 1944-12 May 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 161-170: 14 April 1944-12 May 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Goes to see the movie “Shine On Harvest Moon;” wonders about the new enlargement of the reserve forces.  Finds out that he is a part owner in a furniture business in Clairton, PA; reads an editorial by Henry Wallace, Vice President of the US.  Wants to get on community development when he gets home.  Takes a walk around the campus of William and Mary; watches a newsreel describing Camp Peary as on beautiful Virginia countryside, which the people watching disagreed with vocally; listens to a concert by Vronsky-Babin piano duo; goes to see the movie “Follow the Boys.” Starts speculating that the invasion will come soon, as British censors are becoming more strict.  Describes the sudden transfer order of 15 men from his department.  Goes to a doctor to check his eyes and see if they are good enough for him to become an officer.  Notes that, had he been assigned to the library instead of the transportation department, he likely would have been transferred to another camp by now; been at Camp Peary for six months.  Watches the movie “A Voice in the Wind;” is collecting chewing gum for Esther.  Is thankful for the fact that he has access to books and newspapers, as it allows him to keep a semblance of civilian life and prevent moodiness; wants to take a class in conversational Spanish.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23382">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 171-180: 13 May 1944-20 May 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 171-180: 13 May 1944-20 May 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Is told that his chances at making officer would be better if he were a 2nd or 1st class petty officer; asks for gossip from back home.  Any promotion is stalled for three weeks because the officer he talked to has left for California.  Puts in a request for leave in mid-June, but leaves are still frozen; reading “Release from Nervous Tension,” by Dr. D.H. Fink.  Does not think it sensible for Esther to move down to Williamsburg.  His superior gets transferred out, and replaced with a new boss.  New boss holds a conference with Recht, telling him that both he and his old boss, Wilson, know that he is working under his capabilities, and they will try to transfer him someplace with a better chance for advancement; his new boss is friends with the procurement officer, the one in charge of rerating and taking application for promotions; talks about how some enlisted men were punished for sunning themselves while on duty.  One of the members of Recht’s office gets rerated ahead of him; proposes to reorganize the entire system of filing memoranda.  Would consider Navy work in Europe as a yeoman; talks about the trial of some seditionists.  Is told by his new boss that Esther come down every month, and he will be given time off. Sees the movie “Gaslight” with Ingrid Bergman and Charles Boyer; talks about a contest for Postwar Economic Programs.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23383">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 181-190: 21 May 1944- 28 May 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 181-190: 21 May 1944- 28 May 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Comments on his appreciation of Virginius Dabney and the Richmond Times-Dispatch.  Reads the book “Germany Will Try It Again,” by Schultz.  Sees a Betty Grable movie, with her and other women performing a gun drill; comments about how he is much happier being in the service than merely being a civilian; theorizes about the end of the war and what will come after; talks about a program for former Navy prisoners at the camp.  Still does not know about his rerate; wants to parlay his organization of memoranda into a system for the whole camp.  Gets an article from Esther about the Jews in Palestine.  A book Recht requested, “Better Eyesight without Glasses” comes into the library, so he can try and improve for his officer test; Begins preparing for the takeover of Camp Peary by the regular Navy, on 29 May.  Sees the movie “Story of Dr. Wassel,” with Gary Cooper; thinks about going to see Virginius Dabney give the Commencement address at the College of William and Mary; muses how long the world will be in turmoil unless it becomes better able to handle crises.  Gets a letter from the ACLU asking for donations; gets his index shown to the Lieutenant.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23384">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 191-200: 29 May 1944-6 June 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 191-200: 29 May 1944-6 June 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">2</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Enjoys getting gossip from home.  New changes in liberty schedules and a new Personal Inspection of each department, as part of the switchover into Navy control; talks about the trials the new lieutenant is having in replacing Lt. Wilson.  New lieutenant, Lt. Crockett, wants to help Recht get his commission, even though the Navy is overcrowded with lawyers; sees the movie “Outward Bound.”  Has a conversation with a friend about the current problems, as Recht is his friend’s only intellectual outlet.  One of Recht’s friends from home is assigned to Camp Peary; gets another man added to his department, as well as a new ensign; sees the movie “Between Two Worlds.”  Baby-sits for Lt. Crockett at his house on the York River; as he is taking Recht back to the Barracks, Crockett and Recht talk more about his commissioning.  The new ensign offers to buy the men in the department cokes.  Talks about the invasion of France by the Allies.  Asks Esther about the perception of anti-”negro” sentiment in the Navy, and then explains what he knows about it.  Hears a man in the office suggest that there is anti-”negro” and anti-Semitic feelings in the armed forces, and the best plan would be to send then to Africa and Palestine, but eventually gives up the argument because it is not going anywhere.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23385">
        <head>Series 3: Folders 201-300: 7 June1944- 25 September 1944</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 201-300: 7 June1944- 25 September 1944,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23386">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">3</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23387">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 201-210: 7 June 1944-21 June 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 201-210: 7 June 1944-21 June 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears about the government drilling for oil in Point Barrow, Alaska; sees Life pictures of the war in Europe.  Talks about the fears everyone has now that the invasion has happened.  Details the bus schedule for him coming home on leave.  Talks about how landlords in Williamsburg and Yorktown overcharge the Navy personal because they are only there for a short time; asks Esther about the Clairton swimming pool, which is having race problems.  Talks about the name of the new Camp Peary newspaper, the Peary Scope.  Lt. Crockett sets up an interview between Recht and Lt. Maul, the procurement officer, to talk about his possible commission; makes fun of the other people in his unit for how young they are.  Talks about soldiers caught using black market gas.  Goes on leave to Clairton; lost his bag on the way back, but it was found.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23407">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 211-220: 22 June 1944-29 June 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 211-220: 22 June 1944-29 June 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>All rerates are now subject to regular Navy policies, which include taking an exam.  Finds it harder to readjust to life at Camp Peary this time as opposed to others.  Gets complimented by the Asst. Commander of the base during an inspection of 1,500-1,700 Navy personnel; sees “Going My Way” with Bing Crosby and Barry Fitzgerald, and hears a pianist play.  Lt. Crockett asks him to help write a letter for a man in the department who wants to be discharged because his wife is not feeling well; the Red Cross is checking into requests for leave and discharge because of family members getting ill, because of fake illnesses; the Asst. Commander’s plan to have all the Seabees take tests to become regular Navy soldiers is put on hold when the Commander finds out, without having been consulted.  Has finally finished his backlog of work from over his leave; runs into a group of Italian prisoners of war; talks about the Russian offensive and that state of the German army.  The old assistant commander of the base is reassigned for trying to usurp the power of the commander; doctors and dentists under 38 are being told to enlist or risk being drafted as privates.  Is told by the rerate yeoman that it will be near impossible for him to skip ratings to Y3c.  Talks about the death of one of his friends from home, and how it affected him.  Becomes a semi-official letter writer for his department.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23408">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 221-230: 30 June 1944-4 July 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 221-230: 30 June 1944-4 July 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Includes a pay stub for Recht to the amount of $119.  Calls a show of local talent a display of “hill-billy music;” talks about the nomination of Dewey and Bricker for the Republicans; discusses where the Jews will go after the war, with a possibility being Argentina.  Talks more about Dewey and Bricker, and how, even though he has been back only 9 days, it seems much longer.  The rumor is that Lt. Crockett is to be transferred out of Camp Peary because of his run-in with a Chief that has better connections; Capt. Ware, the commander of the camp, is fed up with the anti-Seabee sentiment among the regular navy officers on the base; talks about a Supreme Court case about 13 “negro” Seabees being declared unfit. 3 “negro”es have been assigned to the repair unit at Peary.  Continues to speculate about the end of the war, talking with his friend Luiz; talks about the difference between Seabees and general service classifications.  Takes care of one of his friends who has had more trouble than he adjusting to the service.  He is completing his semi-annual report on himself; there is more speculation of Crockett being transferred.  Sees the movie “Bathing Beauty,” with Esther Williams.  Talks about the substantial gains in the army with regards to race, in comparison to how strict the military is.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23409">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 231-240: 5 July 1944-11 July 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 231-240: 5 July 1944-11 July 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Explains his pay stub for June; Had a Fourth of July event, which included a band, a chorus, actors playing presidents, a boxing match, and a wrestling match; considers buying some luggage.  A friend of his, Fuss, is trying to get into the psychiatric clinic at Peary, to be a worker; Lt. Crockett is promoted to full Lieutenant; questions the people who thinks war should be ethical and gentlemanly.  Crockett is going to help Recht by filling out his report in a way that emphasizes the areas that Recht is the best at; talks about having to turn in his Seabee uniform for regular navy ones, and the loss of comfortable shoes.  Reading Rex Warner’s “Return of the Traveller[sic];” notes an anger in the literature of this war that was not present in the literature of WWI.  Hears rumors about a friend of his learning Croatian and going to Cairo, and wonders what that means.  Is hoping to get a tan for when Esther comes to visit.  Talks about “robot bombs” being used by the Germans in Europe; questions who to blame for the war; feels that none of the real problems are being solved by the war; talks about the upcoming presidential campaign.  Babysits for Lt. Crockett again; is informed that as of 2 July he has been rerated to S1c.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23410">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 241-250: 11 July 1944-17 July 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 241-250: 11 July 1944-17 July 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Tells Esther that he never intends to return to Williamsburg after he is discharged; discuss how he resents those civilians who do not know what the serviceman has given up by being in the military.  Thinks that the Democrats are going to drop Wallace as FDR’s Vice President; having the African-American soldiers at the Camp has proved not to be a problem.  The newest rumor is that the camp is to be condemned by the medical officers and moved to Ft. Eustis.  Learns that there are no longer waivers on commissions, so his eyes must be correctable to 20/20; learns that Lt. Crockett is being replaced by a new Lt., Lt. Kennedy; visits the College Library.  Finds out that he will not be commissioned anytime soon, because his eyes are too bad.  Talks with one of the camp librarians, learning that many of the political books they used to carry have been removed; sees the movie “The Canterville Mystery;” talks about the mindset of the Germans in using the V-1 rockets; notices Jewish periodicals in the W&amp;M library.  Walks around the campus of William and Mary; resigns himself to his low rate and vows to enjoy the reading that he can get done instead; talks about an interview he read with Santayana.  Says he feels like writing a book about his experience at Peary.  Defends VP Wallace against being a liberal and an unrealistic idealist; dismisses the idea that, if Ester were to come to Williamsburg, she would work at Eastern State Hospital.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23411">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 251-260: 18 July-26 July 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 251-260: 18 July-26 July 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Writes a letter on the back of an old Outgoing Dispatch form; has a going-away dinner for Lt. Crockett.  Is now reading Willard Price’s “Japan’s Islands of Mystery;” talks about the “German Army leaders revolt,” referring to the July 20 plot; talks about the Japanese home situation.  Listens to parts of the Democratic National Convention on the radio; speculates about the relationship between FDR’s interest in the Pope and the US’s official stance towards Loyalist Spain, DeGaulle, and the Italian king.  Hears that Truman has won the Vice Presidency nomination from the Democrats.  Goes to see the movie “The Mask of Dimitrios;” comments on the factors that he thinks led to the nomination of Truman over Wallace.  Talks about registering for classes at the camp, and how most people are using them as a spring-board to being a petty officer; mentions a quote of Churchill saying that the war will be over sooner than previously thought; talks about the possibility of racial problems if the economy goes bad.  Keeps getting in discussions with the boys around the barracks about the “negro matter.”  Hears from Russian writers grumblings about the lack of progress the Allied armies are making in Normandy.  Talks about an oil drought at the camp; talks about the organization of the camp library, and how it is designed to be as uncontroversial as possible.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23412">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 261-270: 26 July-1 August 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 261-270: 26 July-1 August 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Is reading a book that provides a different view on Germany than the tradition ‘racist’ notions; talks about the Russians attacking Lwow, the Polish name for Lviv, which is the hometown of Recht’s parents.  Reads in the College library about race issues in other camps in the US; talks about the amount of federal lawyers that were appointed; wonders about what will happen in Germany at the end of the war.  States that there are good reasons for the Americans hating the Japanese more than the Germans; talks to the new Lt., Lt. Kennedy; complains about the removal of liberal magazines from the PX, but not conservative ones.  Talks about his loneliness at the Camp, and how it is not affecting him too much; talks about 10 new African-Americans that have been received to work on the railroad.  Talks about the racism that some of the white soldiers have towards the new men; intends to read Virginius Dabney’s books.  Reads an editorial by Dabney questioning the reading habits of men in the service; meets with the chief in charge of the Camp library, about the history and future of the said library.  Sees the movie “Storm over Lisbon;” talks with his barracks mates about what should be done to the Germans after the war; talks more about segregation in the camp.  Talks about the Catholic chaplain’s attempt to get Maugham’s book “The Razor’s Edge” out of the camp library for being anti-Catholic.  Mentions a feeling amongst men in service departments that they are not doing enough for the war, unlike the combat units.  Reads about the founding of the American Veterans Committee; talks about people complaining about a lack of consumer goods.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23413">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 271-280: 2 August 1944-7 August 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 271-280: 2 August 1944-7 August 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Meets a German national who works in the library, and describes his beliefs; sees the movie “Memphis Belle;” in a disconnected page 2, talks about the political climate of America.  Hears bad reports of the classes men are taking to prepare for their test for a general service rating; sees “I Love a Soldier.”  Talks about how young all the members of his department are.  Some Waves are coming to Peary, but he does not know who they will be replacing.  Reads a memo that there will be no discrimination in selecting people for advanced schooling; talks about the government’s response to the Philadelphia strike.  If officially transferred from Seabees to general service, along with the rest of the people at the camp.  Starts with physical training for general service; wonders about the problem of some of the men in his department losing their rating when they get checked for general service.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23414">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 281-290: 8 August 1944-17 September 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 281-290: 8 August 1944-17 September 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Sees the movie “Mrs. Skeffington;” is trying to take a more phlegmatic attitude towards Peary, because he expects some day to be transferred, and does not want to get too attached.  Cannot keep up with the first batch of physical training.  Writes about how he hopes Esther trip home from seeing him was good, after a month long gap in letters.  There is a picture of Recht on the letter dated 13 Sept. 1944.  Will try to get Camel cigarettes for people back home.  Gets the edge of a hurricane that is going through the area.  Says that he will get off work for the upcoming Yontif, or holiday days.  Almost gets transferred to another department after 4 people in Repairs department get in trouble for taking a car into Williamsburg and getting in trouble with a corpsman; is trying to get rerated to Y3c; sees the “Gypsy Wildcat.”  Gets in a new batch of seamen from Pennsylvania, who insist on calling Recht “sir.” Talks about the new chain of command under Lt. Kennedy.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23415">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 291-300: 18 September 1944-25 September 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 291-300: 18 September 1944-25 September 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">3</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks about the Rosh Hashanah services at the camp.  Gets a letter from a friend at another camp.  Mentions that the camp football team will be playing its games in the College’s football stadium; has a debate with someone in his office about why they are going to vote for Dewey as opposed to FDR; talks about the differing US and British plans for post-war Italy.  Hears a rumor of Seabees being shipped to California; is trying to get an absentee ballot.  Gets rerated to Y3c.  Sees the movie “Kismet;” relates a story of a soldier whose wife had been told she was pregnant, but actually has a tumor.  There is a new camp 15 minutes of calisthenics, reduced from 45 minutes.  Writes about an unknown pamphlet that appeared in the camp library; talks about the mob of people at the Travis House for dinner after the camp football game; Peary won the football game against a pro team from Washington DC.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23416">
        <head>Series 4: Folders 301-400: 25 September 1944-8 March 1945</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 301-400: 25 September 1944-8 March 1945,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23417">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">4</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23418">
            <head>Subseries 1: </head>
            <did>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears that Lt. Kennedy refereed the football game, and that he was a pro ref and umpire in multiple sports before the service; talks about the German resilience and the German transportation infrastructure; hears rumors of the Allies wanting to force Germany to be an agricultural state after the war; talks about the Republican platform.  Watched the movie “Casanova Brown.”  Talks about a party some of the sailors there had after they found out they were being transferred.  Talks about the Yom Kippur services; makes a point by refusing to cut in line at the mess after not having worked all day because of Yom Kippur.  Sees the movie “Arsenic and Old Lace.”  Hears from Lt. Kennedy that a lot of the men who have been in the department the longest will soon be shipped out.  Is playing a lot of chess; sees the movie “The Master Race;” talks about an Estonian in the Navy.  The library is no longer getting new books in.  Watches an illegal craps game; talks about how some of the families of soldiers had to be moved out of Brown Hall at the College; talks about the Democratic campaigning.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23419">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 311-320: 6 October 1944-12 October 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 311-320: 6 October 1944-12 October 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks jokingly about the impropriety of the liberty yeoman. Has a large convoy to try and help put together.  Goes up to Washington DC for the weekend; talks about broad social and political problems with one of his friends; talks about the captain’s personnel inspection.  Enjoys a dinner with one of his friends in Washington; cannot enjoy the trip fully because he knows he has to go back to the service.  Gets a form from the chief of personnel to fill out about the duties of the key people in his department.  Talks about how he got noticed with his yeoman’s badge on the wrong arm on the train back from DC; talks about an incident between some white soldiers and a “colored” soldier on the same train ride.  Talks about the coffee maker as a navy tradition; talks about the death of Wendell Willkie.  Talks about where the Jews should go after the war.  The chaplain’s car he used to use to get to his office is being reassigned, and so he must walk; considers buying a trench coat; notes that the camp is being emptied of soldiers with longer tenure, and does not think they will be replenished.  Is going to be interviewed by  a man from the Personnel department to evaluate the worth of their duties.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23420">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 321-330: 12 October 1944-15 November 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 321-330: 12 October 1944-15 November 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks to a “colored” soldier about Jim Crow laws on the buses on the camp.  Comments on an author using language in one of his books; talks about “preventive” legal counsel.  Wins the camp checkers tournament.  A kitten somehow gets into the transportation office; the brother of one of his co-workers dies.  Talks about the swing from the south as Democrat to Republican.  Two of the men in his department are reassigned to storekeepers.  Tries to listen to the Boston symphony over the radio; does his laundry, which only requires soaking; mentions Armistice Day, which turned into Veterans Day.  Predictions that 500,000 more men will be inducted into the armed forces are on the radio; one of Recht’s co-workers believes this generation will be permanently mentally scarred; disagrees with a letter that says that almost all the soldiers know what they are fighting for.  Goes and sees the movie “None but the Lonely Heart;” talks about China and its Communist party.  Hears about a book titled “What the Negro Wants”.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23421">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 331-340: 18 November 1944-9 December 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 331-340: 18 November 1944-9 December 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>The office Recht works in is being painted.  Stares at the moon and the stars, and calls it the treat of his evening.  Describes dinner at the camp.  Lt. Kennedy finds out about Recht’s ability to do quick mental addition and has fun with it.  Goes and sees a performance of opera songs, including one from La Boehme.  Is avoiding eating bread and potatoes.  Hears about a telephone operators strike; sees the movie “March of Time”.  Reflects on the war, it being December 7 1944 and therefore the 3 year anniversary of Pearl Harbor.  Sees the movie “Thirty Seconds over Tokyo;” friend Joe tries to get suggestions to keep his son from being sent overseas.  Talks about discharges on account of age; says how if he were to get out now, he would try to get into a business that is making money off of the war.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23422">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 341-350:  10 December 1944-29 December 1944</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 341-350:  10 December 1944-29 December 1944,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks about the lack of people reading real books, as opposed to Readers’ Digest.  One letter includes a newspaper clipping of an article on war diaries.  Describes one of his co-worker’s “moralistic” attitudes; wants to go to Richmond to hear Grace Moore.  Hears about the Christmas liberty that the Captain is giving the camp.  Sees “Sunday Dinner for a Soldier.” Camp is getting many new men in just before Christmas.  Hears rumors that Peary will house German POWs.  Sees “Woman in the Window” and describes more about the movie “30 Seconds over Tokyo”.  Writes about the treatment of US POWs by the Japanese.  Spends time with Esther in Williamsburg, explaining partially the break in letters.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23423">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 351-360: 29 January 1945-3 February 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 351-360: 29 January 1945-3 February 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Reflects on the time that he and Esther spent together, especially the last part in New York.  Sees the movie “Keys of the Kingdom”.  Camp is using some of the war prisoners for work, such as coal deliverers and in the mess hall.  Hears of the possibility of a coal miners strike if their contract is not extended; talks about Esther buying a fur coat, and his misgivings.  Discusses a personal injury case one of his friends in involved with.  Sees the movie “Tomorrow, the World.”  Has a commander ask to get a vehicle to take his dog to the vet.  Talks about the tests required to get a higher rating.  Writes about some men in his depart being court martialed for speeding off the base and hiring out the cars in violation of regulations; hears about other men who have extra cars in the repair area, and who rent them out for weekends, and their serious court-martial; says that a new Captain has taken over the base, and this has caused a flurry of regulations penalties; tells a story of a “negro” soldier who tries to take a rerate exam.  Listens to La Boehme on the radio.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23424">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 361-370: 4 February-9 February 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 361-370: 4 February-9 February 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Sees the movie “The Fighting Lady;” describes the lack of “terrific combat” of the Pacific theater.  Wonders about why the base command shows the sailors movies that make them think about the war some days, and then comedies and such other days. Sees “Practically Yours”.  Reads, for the first time, about what the Nazis are doing to the Jews in Poland.  Lt. Kennedy calls Recht into his office to get a lawyer’s opinion on one of the court martial cases facing someone in their department; asks Esther to send him an apple pie.  Talks about liking Bill Maudlin’s humor and cartoons.  Hears about problems with the German POWs at the base.  Talks about a company that has a contract selling officer uniforms being protected from losses by the Navy.  Talks about the effect of the war on the lives of the people who fight in it.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23425">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 371-380: 9 February 1945-14 February 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 371-380: 9 February 1945-14 February 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Sees the movie “Experiment Perilous”.  Hopes that Esther has “recovered” from his letter of last night; confesses to Esther that he has ‘spring fever’.  Reads remarks by American socialists who have no love for the USSR.  Hears about some sort of scandal with the female editor[Marilyn Kaemmerle] of the William and Mary News[by which he means the campus paper, The Flat Hat];[The scandal was caused by Kaemmerle publishing an editorial in the Flat Hat that supported desegregation of William and Mary.  The Board of Visitors disagreed, and President Pomfret removed her from the editorship.  See subject file “Flat Hat Incident of 1945” and “Marilyn Kaemmerle” for more information]; Tells Esther how mad he got at people making noise during a piano concert. Reading a book by Antoine de Saint-Exupery.  Continues to write about the editor of the William and Mary News.  Hears a rumor that the Camp post office is going to install an X-ray machine to stop people from sending alarm clocks, cigarettes, and other such items; asks soldiers about how they would feel working with Japanese PoWs, and they would not want to.  Gets invited by Kaemmerle to come talk with her at her sorority house, Pi Beta Phi.  Gets a Valentine’s day card from Esther.  Hears about an incident on the camp about a German PoW scratching some swastikas onto a bus being scrapped.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23426">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 381-390: 15 February 1945-25 February 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 381-390: 15 February 1945-25 February 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Describes the office in which he works. Talks about how he usually just chats and drinks coffee while he is supposed to be working.  Hears from Marilyn Kaemmerle that there have been 45 editors in the 33 year history of the Flat Hat so far.  Is reading a book by Anatole France [Jacques Thibault].  Sees the movie “A Tree Grows in Brooklyn.” Debates whether or not to take a plane home after hearing of an accident.  Spends a couple of hours with Marilyn Kaemmerle at her sorority house, and helps sort letters that she has been receiving; talks about the Jewish students at the school with Kaemmerle, along with the continuing reaction to her editorial.  Reads a newspaper article about the treatment of German PoWs by the Russians.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23427">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 391-400: 25 February 1945-8 March 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 391-400: 25 February 1945-8 March 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">4</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Enjoys a walk in Williamsburg and a rest in the Sunken Gardens; explains the new set up of the Flat Hat; goes up to Richmond to go to a B’nai Brith dinner meeting.  Talks about the difference between how enlisted men and officers are treated when they break regulations.  Talks about Time and Newsweek’s depiction of the Marilyn Kaemmerle incident; has another meeting with her and some of her sorority sisters.  Recommends “The Little Prince” to Esther.  Talks about his preparations for his upcoming leave.  Gets new men into the repairs and transportation departments, who have never worked on a gas engine, only diesel ones.  Returns to the camp from leave; gets a small crate of his accumulated mail from his leave; gets his marks from the rerate test.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23428">
        <head>Series 5: Folders 401-500: 9 March 1945-3 June 1945</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 401-500: 9 March 1945-3 June 1945,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23429">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23430">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 401-410: 9 March 1945-13 March 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 401-410: 9 March 1945-13 March 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks with one of the truck dispatchers about freight transportation; hears reports about the bombing of Cologne.  Lists all of the periodicals that he reads; fears the worst for what Germans to do Jewish Allied POWs; while cleaning out the office files he finds some long expired credit cards that Lt. Kennedy just happened to need that day.  Discusses how, even though he was a lawyer in civilian life, he would not care to be a military lawyer; does not like the editorializing comments under some of the captions of Japanese prisoners.  Laments the fact that he can never read all that he wishes to.  Discusses the quality of education in the US with Lt. Sorensen; reads an article that there are too many men in the service doing too little; meets a Jewish girl on the bus; sees two soldiers fight for a chance to give a woman their seat.  Sees a short about Iwo Jima, and how horrible it was there.  Hears the end of some discussion on the “Negro problem,” and joins in the discussion.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23431">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 411-420: 14 March 1945-21 March 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 411-420: 14 March 1945-21 March 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Some of the POWs who work in the mess hall go “on strike” and are replaced; calls Marilyn Kaemmerle and gets an update on her situation.  Sees pictures of the bombing of Dresden; Lt. Kennedy does not mind talking about social problems, but does not see much of a point in them.  Sees the movie “The Unseen;” hears about the return of some German POWs who had escaped; hears about a policy that says the Army will take draftees age 18-21, and the Navy will take draftees 21-38; reads a letter in the newspaper from a Navy sailor who is a William and Mary graduate, who disagrees with the Board of Visitors on the Marilyn Kaemmerle issue.  Talks about how the “loafing” of the men who have just come from the sea is not good for the morale of the camp regulars.  Goes on leave to see Esther in Washington, DC.  On the return trip from Washington, talks with a sailor about the National Gallery.  Hears that one of his friends is in legal trouble for selling meat over the price ceiling; is told about race and segregation trouble at the theater.  Hears from a person at that theater that there had been no problem at all, just rumors; rides with a young African-American soldier on the bus, and hears about his training.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23432">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 421-430: 21 March 1945-25 March 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 421-430: 21 March 1945-25 March 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears about a friend who was transferred from his department for requesting additional leave after his father died; Tries to get a friend who is going back to Pittsburgh to bring back an apple pie from Esther; is angry that there are conditions that make war necessary; has a friend who sees a newsreel of murdered Poles and Jews, and cannot believe that humans could be “guilty of such deeds.” Hears his friends on how the Japanese could be more expected to murder than the Germans, because they are “heathens.”  Is reading the book “Citizen Tom Paine” that takes liberties with history; theorizes that some servicemen are beginning to consider war their profession.  Hears that he has the reputation of being the most avid book reader; hears about another incident involving race on the camp; reads about how the meat famine may just be a creation of the meat packers, not an actual shortage.  Talks with a POW about the situation in Germany.  The Captain makes a separate bus stop for the African-American soldiers, but he makes it close to their separate USO, as they used to have a long walk to get there; mails out more chocolate and cigarettes to people back home; is trying to find information about the African-American actor Ira Alldridge; talks about another racial incident[in a seemingly unconnected letter fragment].  Is curious in hearing about the situation of the Jews in Italy, as compared to Germany.  Draws a map of the garden and the area around the hut he lives in; while playing some classical music, one of the POWs sticks his head in the hut to compliment the music, and Recht notices all the POWs sitting around outside are listening to his music; reads a book studying the lives of Orthodox Jews.  Spends a day in Williamsburg and eats at the Lodge, as he often does; hopes that the war will be over a little sooner than expected.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23433">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 431-440: 26 March 1945-31 March 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 431-440: 26 March 1945-31 March 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Reads a book that talks about Black Mountain College.  Hears rumors of the “imminent possibility of Nazi surrender”; tells Esther about how much money he will get when he gets out of service.  Talks with another soldier about going to Richmond for a Seder meal.  Is confused by a friend ending a letter to him with “Love to Esther.  Anything you want?”; the men living in the hut each contribute a little bit of money to buy flowers for their garden.  Describes to Esther the Passover Seder that he attended.  Comments that the services at camp offer nothing stimulating, so he will not go on a regular basis.  Talks with a man at the Temple in Richmond who owns a clothes plant that makes many of the uniforms for soldiers, along with suits for civilians.  Talks about how the Rabbi at Passover had to quiet down the participants during the service; is polite and civil to the German POWs, but not trusting; hears rumors of the Allied armies making inroads into Germany.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23434">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 441-450:  31 March 1945-4 April 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 441-450:  31 March 1945-4 April 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears a lot of contradictory information regarding China, its Communists, and the KMT; notices how businesses complain about the lack of business when they are actually doing better than ever.  Fragment that talks about Walter White’s book.  Hears about a dance contest for enlisted men, but cannot get down there in time; reads about a French pastor who quotes Pasteur over his door.  Compares what he hears about the treatment of Allied POWs to what he sees the treatment is of the German POWs.  Gives a description of the town of Gottingen from a book he is reading;  has a friend who believes that the Russians will attack Japan as soon as Germany is defeated.  Begins to get a cold wave after the beginning of an early summer.  Tells Esther to tell one of the people he knows, Lt. Boreman, that he is to be a legal officer for the camp.  Sees the movie “Hotel Berlin”; hears that the POWs are allowed a German newspaper from New York City; hears about Nazi leaders escaping through Spain to Argentina.  Reads a book that is a “report on the Negro’s status in World War II,” that has an introduction from Eleanor Roosevelt.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23435">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 451-460: 5 April 1945-10 April 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 451-460: 5 April 1945-10 April 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Reads that Russia will not renew its treaty with Japan and that Japan’s cabinet has fallen.  Makes a visit to Richmond, but returns early; reads a story in the paper about German slave workers brought to Germany from conquered countries.  Hears that the Nazi’s have one of Stalin’s sons as a hostage.  Has to do laundry because of an inspection the next day; talks with a few sailors who are up before the Captain the next day for speeding off the base, and being away without leave.  Two members of the office skip the inspection because they were supposedly out until three a.m. driving people back to Richmond and Hampton, but they in fact never made their second trip and merely slept in.  Hears a story of how every sailor who goes out to sea is given a hammock, but they are only used for covering the bed and sheets to prevent them from getting dirty.  Reads a story about a Rabbi who traveled through all of the war zones and did not hear of any racial or religious prejudice.  Sends Esther an article about segregation in the camp theater.  Talks about how, even with all his talking, it is hard to change the prejudices of people.  Has another discussion with the men in the office about the segregation of the theater.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23436">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 461-470: 11 April 1945-17 April 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 461-470: 11 April 1945-17 April 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Is told that it is not proper for offices and enlisted men to socialize outside of the workplace or in public; hears that Lt. Kennedy used to be a pro football ref before the war.  Recht’s friend from home, Len, is installed as a camp lawyer; goes to a concert at the College.  Hears the news of the death of FDR, and hopes that Truman reveals himself to be more than he fears him to be; feels that the graciousness of FDR will be sorely missed in the negotiations after the war; Kennedy tells a member of the legal department at Peary that Recht was a lawyer, and the lawyer seems interested in stealing Recht for his own department.  Hears that all the men with 2 years of service by Sept 30, 1945 will be shipped out to sea soon.  Gets a “new colored fellow” into the office, the first one for Recht’s department.  Recht decides he does not feel like taking on the busywork of the attorney’s office, would rather stick with his own.  Esther may not be able to come down to the Camp because her mother is ill.  Suggests ways to use the welfare fund money of the camp, such as a tennis court or records.  Confronts a member of the office about not dressing the way the others do, and lying to Lt. Kennedy to get this.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23437">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 471-480: 17 April 1945-22 May 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 471-480: 17 April 1945-22 May 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Watches a news broadcast of Roosevelt’s funeral.  Thinks about telling his fellow sailors about the similarity between racial prejudice and Nazi ideology, but then sees a magazine that already did it.  Enjoys Esther’s visit, even if it was short.  Has so much work he cannot even get off a letter like normal.  Reads about a person from Pittsburgh who is charged a fine of $12,000 for overcharging customers.  Wouldn’t be at all surprised at an Allied landing on the China coast.  One of the other people in his department gets a house that the USO found for him and for his wife to stay.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23438">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 481-490: 22 May 1945-28 May 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 481-490: 22 May 1945-28 May 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Has to go to the mess to see what all the boys were complaining about, and finds the food there to be just fine; Lt. Kennedy’s wife borrows a magazine from Recht that is entirely edited by African-Americans.  Cannot get interested enough to try and get a higher rate, up to a Y2c.  One of his office mates is itching to get his transfer out, and gets out half a day early because Recht covers for him.  Hears that the College is going to put on a swing concert, and thinks about going to that; visits with his friend who is now a lawyer at the Camp, with whom Recht went to law school; Lt. Kennedy sees the first African American officer on the base.  Most of the restaurants in Williamsburg are declared off limits for servicemen because of the unsanitary condition of the kitchens.  One of Recht’s friends from home is assigned to the Pacific theater; talks about Esther’s father’s business; Recht critiques the OPA price minimums.  Gets another African-American into their department, as a driver; gives his impressions of the members of Truman’s cabinet that he has read of.  Recht cannot totally dedicate himself to dieting, as he likes the mashed potatoes too much.  A man who’s been in the Navy 18 months who gets transferred into Recht’s department has been taught to read and write by the Navy since he was drafted; Lt. Kennedy is forced to transfer some men, and picks the ones who went to a show while on duty.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23439">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 491-500: 29 May 1945-3 June 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 491-500: 29 May 1945-3 June 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">5</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Tells the story of one of the men who was forced to transfer by Lt. Kennedy.  Goes to a chorus production that he somewhat enjoys, with mostly African-American singers and songs.  Hears about an African-American author who has written a book about Reconstruction.  Mentions that one of his friends, whose father just died, had been a doctor in the court of the Czar.  Hears that people who have two years service as of December 31, 1945 will be the next group discharged.  Is going to listen on the radio to a program about staying friends with the USSR after the end of the War; hears, from Esther, that the government is cracking down on meat restrictions.  Is planning to have Esther down in Williamsburg for four weeks, starting early August and ending after Rosh Hashanah; describes the work that he did that day.  Sees the movie “Objective Burma;”  seems to be missing on of his jumpers.  Calls Marilyn Kaemmerle again, to check up on her; wants to a say personal goodbye to her before she graduates; the commissary begins rationing meat to 4 oz. per person per day.  Goes reading at the Williamsburg pool, with a lot of College girls there; sees a lot of parents in town for graduation, with only 125 in the class.  Gets a call late at night from another person in his department, asking Recht to cover for him since he is in Richmond; on the phone, Recht can hear much mumbling of female voices.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23440">
        <head>Series 6: Folders 501-600: 4 June 1945 to 5 September 1945</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 501-600: 4 June 1945 to 5 September 1945,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23441">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23442">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 501-510: 4 June 1945-8 June 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 501-510: 4 June 1945-8 June 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Goes to the graduation exercises at the College of William and Mary; gets to say good-bye to Marilyn Kaemmerle.  Is worried that the hard work in Europe is now upon them, since the war itself is over; hears that the Navy discharge age is lowered to 38.  Wonders about the marriage of his friend, Blanche, who is living “a rather complex life these days.”  Recht’s friend Lew has to go to Portsmouth to get glasses, provided by the Navy; sees the movie “Conflict.”  People in his office try to get a frying pan to have eggs in the office; comments about recent articles in a magazine that he subscribes to, dealing with the state of post-war Europe.  Discusses a court-martial that a sailor is under for killing a woman in a car crash.  Has to buy another white jumper because the laundry messed his up, discusses prices of military clothes.  Talks about the array of maps he has on his desk, including one of where American pilots can hit Japan, maps from newspapers, etc.  Is able to iron for the first time in some months; describes his fascination with the smell of coffee, even over the drink itself; sees the movie “Those Endearing Young Charms;”  reads a Bureau of Naval Personnel memo that describes, humorously, the kind of life that Recht leads.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23443">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 511-520: 9 June 1945-15 June 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 511-520: 9 June 1945-15 June 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Reads about the Virginia State Supreme Court upholding a segregation law, as well as a Federal Circuit Court of Appeals case on the same matter; reads reports about what Congress is going to do about conscription after the war ends.  Spends an afternoon in Williamsburg, sitting out near the pool and eating toast and jelly, something he never has in camp.  Hears a story about Kirsten Flagstad, who may or may not have sung for the Nazis in Berlin; reads a comparison of amount of food available for servicemen each year, 220 lbs, as opposed to civilians, 70lbs.  Gives Esther plans for his leave, hopefully a week earlier than expected.  Talks about mailing Jello to their friend Ruthie.  Tells a story about how he heard a noise late at night, and thought it could be prisoners escaping or some sort of thing, but it turns out to be just a short.  Talks about the pet squirrel that they have captured, for which the German prisoners built a cage.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23444">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 521-530: 14 June 1945-26 June 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 521-530: 14 June 1945-26 June 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Enjoys a trip home to see Esther, for about a week.  Has to get to the barber shop to get his hair cut before inspection.  Describes his trip back to the base, on a B&amp;O train, sitting next to a girl who seems prudish, but talks to her about her life as a Cornell student.  Gives a description of what inspection entails.  Lt. Kennedy is getting angry at a sailor for not caring enough, just floating along and waiting to get transferred; hears the newest rules about rerates, saying that everyone must take a general exam as well as a specialist exam; mentions a story from the Pearyscope about a man who was in the Army, discharged, and enlisted in the Navy, and the hardships he has had.  Hears a rumor that Peary is to become the only boot training station east of the Mississippi; notices that a Negro office had been transferred.  Gets free glasses from the Navy; wants to go see programs in PBK Hall related to the Literature, Folk Music, Politics, etc., of Latin America.  Finds out that he is going to be switching jobs with a man whose work Lt. Kennedy does not like.  Sees the movie “Thrill of Romance.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23445">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 531- 540: 26 June 1945-1 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 531- 540: 26 June 1945-1 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks about the income tax for men in the military.  Actually describes his reaction to “Thrill of Romance”; hears that Marilyn Kaemmerle has been taken on as an editorial staff worker for the Freedom House, in New York City.  Starts at his new job, which carries more responsibility, such as giving special liberties, and also has to teach the new person that is taking his old job.  Goes out to dinner at the Capitol; goes and sees a lecture on Colonial Architecture in Latin America at PBK Hall; the Captain of the Camp, Capt. Perry, visits the camp library and is disturbed to find the magazines “PM” and “The New Republic” on the shelves, and that he also does not like having “niggers” in the camp; talks about how he approves of most of the politics of the Southern liberals, but cannot agree with their support of segregation.  Hears that a lot of men are being transferred to Yorktown, and that Peary is receiving “Negro replacements”; hears a talk at William and Mary by Dr. William Schurz, of the Department of State, on the future of Inter-American relations.  He leaves the most controversial issues, like Argentina and Brazil, out of his discussion; compares the treatment of “Brazilian Negroes” and those in the United States; talks with Dr. Schurz about his inability to speak freely, being a member of the State Department.  Receives the “new Negro men” into the department, and begins training them.  Gets a large group of civilians starting boot camp in at Peary; reads a quote by Governor Ellis Arnall of Georgia who says that the people of the South do not agree in “social equality with the Negro.”  Sees a picture of the ship the Queen Mary in Life; is interested in the OPA and FEPC proceedings in Congress; reflects on the “anti-Negro matters.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23446">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 541-550: 2 July 1945- 9 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 541-550: 2 July 1945- 9 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Lt. Kennedy is thinking about having twice monthly office meetings for the men to voice their concerns, as morale has been low the past month.  Gets an electric water fountain in the office; writes a letter drunk.  Talks about the different qualities of lives the he and some of his friends have, officers, rated men, and nonrated men.  Kennedy talks about why his dad was fired from a steel mill: for trying to act independently and not give favor to other steel millers.  Sees a copy of the pamphlet “Guide to Officers or Command of Negro Personnel;” reads an article in PM about the Pittsburgh public schools initiating a policy of teaching interracial and intercultural understanding through adult groups.  Relates a story of a recently inducted sailor who is trying to get home to see his supposedly sick wife, although things seem odd in his story.  There is no longer the “espirit de corps” that categorized the war effort before, but instead it has been replaced with a mere dull routine.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23447">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folders 551-560: 10 July 1945-14 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 551-560: 10 July 1945-14 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Sees that a lot of the area around the hut is much nicer looking, with flowers, but is not sure if the men or the German prisoners did.  Reads a reporter who disagrees with the official remarks that Germany has 75% of its industrial might left; reads an article from Virginius Dabney’s Paper that talks about the “anti-Negro venom spreaders” such as Theodore Bilbo of Mississippi and James Eastland, also of Mississippi.  Is reading Agnes Meyer’s “Journey Thru Chaos,” which he find enlightening.  The camp librarian is replaced with a new man who has to report directly to the Captain of the Camp.  The branch library near the “Negro Barracks” is closed down suddenly.  Few sailors are being assigned to the Atlantic fleet, and the Coast Guard is taking over much of that responsibility.  Sees a deal for new Foreign Service Officers with the State Department, but the age requirement is 21-30 years old.  Lt. Kennedy, and other section chiefs, are getting disgusted with the amount of men being transferred between sections.  Gets Kennedy to help him try to transfer a “young Negro here” who is better trained to work in a different department.  Many people like being at Camp Peary as opposed to being shipped out to sea; also gives just a general account of what he sees as the current mindset of the Seebees at Peary.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23448">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folders 561-570: 14 July 1945- 19 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 561-570: 14 July 1945- 19 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears a story about soldiers who were being shipped out on a train having to wear their dark blue uniforms in the sun, and reflects on the occasional arbitrariness of military orders.  Reads the book The Brick Foxhole; says that soldiers complain about the Williamsburg USO, but says that it is not any better throughout much of the South.  As more men depart the Camp, Recht notices that there is no longer and band and the Captain there to bid farewell to the soldiers.  There has been confusion over if Recht will be allowed out of service on time, since he does not have a birth certificate; theorizes about Russia attacking Japan in a two front attack.  Pokes fun at Esther for keeping all of his letters; sees the movie “Thousand and One Nights.” Lt. Kennedy has not told Recht whether or not he will institute Recht’s recommendation of conferences with the men, to see what the really are feeling; hears a rumor of more civilians being hired at the Camp.  Reads a story in the Post-Gazette about how a Congressman got a passport for a wife to go visit her husband overseas.  Hears that the German prisoners now have the job of cleaning the “heads” and says they have never been so clean; hears that the Navy is bombarding Japanese factories near the coast; includes a poem by Paul Laurence Dunbar.  Buys more war bonds; reads about a Greyhound bus that fell into a river when the bridge collapsed; talks about the value of their record collection.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23449">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 571-580: 19 July 1945-24 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 571-580: 19 July 1945-24 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>The District librarian is coming to visit the Camp library; has to give leave to a sailor whose mother is very sick.  Plans to go see “Bell for Adano” with Lew, but it has not gotten good reviews.  Reads a story in the Richmond paper about a plan for releasing men using a points system, but only people who have had 4 years of duty and will be 41 or older.  Finally sees “Bell for Adano,” and likes it more than the reviews; reflects on whether his letters are more like letters or like “speech-making…and blowing off steam.”  Goes to the Lodge and sits out by the pool, watching a 6 month old baby, before rain forces him inside.  Meets a man from Maine, where Recht and Esther have traveled, and so they talk about places they have both been; men are complaining of getting bitten by flies; has a sailor tell him a story about how the sailor’s uncle sent him a letter saying that the sailor’s wife has been entertaining all sorts of men at their house, however the sailor thinks the uncle is sending these rumors because he wants to go on a date with his wife.  Has an interesting experience of racism in the barber shop, with one barber hiding in the back office instead of cutting hair.  Sees the movie “The Princess and the Bell Hop”; the coffee shop at the Lodge is now using saccharine tablets instead of sugar; hears from Frankie, and former sailor in their group, and that he is on an LST.  Sees a “colored fellow” leading a group of men, both black and white, from induction to the mess hall; theorizes that the Nazi’s learned from the KKK and “other American methods of mistreatment of the Negro.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23450">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 581-590: 24 July 1945-28 July 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 581-590: 24 July 1945-28 July 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks to a Y1c in the ship’s service office, who tells him that there will soon be two sets of barbers to try and prevent similar problems from happening.  Reads Arthur Miller’s Situation Normal…; admits to some of the sailors that he had been a lawyer for 8 and a half years before joining the Navy.  Reads about a white woman from Alexandria, Va, who was arrested for refusing to move from the back of the bus.  Reflects on the defeat of Churchill’s party in the British Parliamentary elections; theorizes on what will happen to the Japanese, and how the Allies will attack them, mainly through more and more powerful air attacks, not a land invasion.  Talks about the price and quality of clothes he can buy and try to send back home.  Talks about playing checkers with a friend in the department; talks about the department picnic, with a “quartet of colored men singing.”  Reads about peace terms, rather than surrender terms, that the Allies send the Japanese; talks with a man who has been working in the camp prison.  Writes about an incident where white sailors followed “several young Negro girls” back to their house, where they were attacked by “Negroes” and also about another incident where a fight broke out about moving to the back of the bus; both of these incidents provoke a debate in Recht’s office; sees the movie “Junior Miss”; talks about one of the men in his office getting into a car crash at the intersection of Duke of Gloucester Street, Boundary Street, and Jamestown Road.  Has some further comments about the fight on the bus; man who crashed the car gets two weeks restriction to base.  Reads an article in Collier’s about the comparative income between races and why governments have failed to equalize it.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23451">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 591-600: 29 July 1945-5 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 591-600: 29 July 1945-5 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">6</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks about tree frogs that have congregated near his sleeping hut, because of all the rain.  Writes in to PM Magazine, sending in some stories about his experience with it on the camp.  Gets new men into his section, who are worse than the ones they are replacing; hears that the enlisted mens’ club is supposed to be finishing renovations soon.  Hears a new order about how men found guilty of being away without leave are to be sent overseas, if physically fit.  Lt. Kennedy shows Recht some pictures of him as an infant and a young child.  Gets mold on his shoes from the amount of moisture in the air.  Gets ready for a visit from Esther.  Talks to the librarian’s wife, who is an ardent Mexican nationalist.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23452">
        <head>Series 7: Folders 601-700: 5 September 1945 to 24 December 1945</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 601-700: 5 September 1945 to 24 December 1945,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23453">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23454">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 601-610: 5 September 1945-12 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 601-610: 5 September 1945-12 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>His friend Lew talks about a book, By the Waters of Babylon, and how he thinks some parts of it are an unfair presentation of the Jews.  Reads in the paper that the Navy will no longer allow sailors to wear civilian clothes when off-duty.  Hears a rumor about the reduction of the amount of points needed to get a discharge; goes to a Billie Holliday concert where “many Negroes” were “specially invited;” hears that a lot of military surplus items are to become available to the public in a matter of weeks.  Lt. Kennedy tells Recht that he is going to start looking for a man to replace him soon, as they both want to get out of the service; reads an article called “Race Relationships in the US.”</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23455">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 611-620: 12 September 1945-15 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 611-620: 12 September 1945-15 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Uses pink paper one day, finding it to be the only thing on hand; the Navy finally recommends to sailors that they buy things at service prices and send them home, which is what sailors have been doing all along; remarks that the old camp soda fountain has been replaced by a sort of jewelry store.  Hears a rumor about the replacement for Lt. Kennedy.  Does not get anything out of the camp religious services.  Finds out the public library is now closed in the evening to give the librarians a break; hears about how the personnel chief is disappointed about the test scores, on the General Classification Test, of the men staying in the Navy after the war ends.  Lt. Kennedy finishes By the Waters of Babylon, and shares his views on it.  A librarian puts up a sign that says “Jim Crow” with an “X” through it, and a “burly Southerner” causes a ruckus about it.  Hears that the Secretary of the Navy is to appear before Congress to discuss demobilization; hears of many men and women having affairs with people all over the camp, including in Recht’s department; talks about living in the same house as Esther’s family.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23456">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945
</p>
              <p>Goes to the dentist.  Researches getting insurance for a business.  Has a Jewish service in the “Chapel of All Faiths,” which has a cross above the door.  Esther gets some interesting ideas from the pink paper Herman sent her a letter upon; is about to get in 13 men to replace the 13 that are being shipped out from his department.  Hears that Camp Peary is to become a general Navy boot camp; hears about yeomen being frozen.  Hears about a group of men, who are not married and whose work is below average, being sent out to sea; goes to Richmond to a synagogue and hears a “hell-raising” sermon; sees the movie “The Southerner,” and thinks highly of it.  Wonders about another trip by Esther down to Williamsburg.  Reflects on having to live on less money than he is used to; has had some discussions with Young, his successor at his old job at the Camp, “about Negroes,” who says that they are not as smart as Whites.  Finishes the novel The Folded Leaf.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23457">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folders 631-640: 20 September 1945-23 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 631-640: 20 September 1945-23 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Talks to a 3rd class Spec. X, who has been in the service 2.5 years, about what he did out of the service and what he has done while in the service; finds out that Esther is pregnant.  Wants to get posters of “The Races of Mankind” from Fisk University for Brille, the librarian, to post in the library; talks about possible child names.  Brille had been talking with Captain Perry’s wife and brought up Recht’s suggestion of distributing the Children’s Bureau pamphlets on Pre-Natal care, which she loved; wonders about using the Children’s Bureau aid for pregnant wives of servicemen; has Esther pick up a Suggested Reading list for him.  Says that most of the men left only want one thing: to go home.  After October 1, will no longer need to wear his white uniforms; researches the possibility of converting GI insurance into normal, private insurance.  All people at the base are temporarily frozen in their current position, and instead of 1000 new recruits coming in, the number has risen to 2600.  Rides to Richmond with Lew, in his newly repaired car.  Is going to take a trip up to Pittsburgh to see Esther at the end of September; hears from Lew that Capt. Perry might want to take the top ten men at Peary, as measured by their service tests, and of which both Lew and Recht are members, and have them give lectures to men being discharged, about how to readjust; hears about a librarian who is a Russian Jew who has lived in Palestine most of his life, and paints, so Recht suggests to Brille that they show his work at the library.  Sends home some towels that are “good enough for private use.”  Hears more scuttle about the points system being changed, but nothing is firm yet; last winter, men packed dirt around the bottom of the Quonset hut Recht lives in to keep the wind from getting underneath.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23458">
            <head>Subseries 5: Folders 641-650: 24 September 1945-28 September 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 641-650: 24 September 1945-28 September 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">5</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Goes and visits a small Jewish deli in Newport News with Lew; visits the Navy Yard and explores Newport News some.  Talks about coming back to Pittsburgh for October 3 through the 9th.  Sees a film about Woodrow Wilson.  Hears that the War Department wants 20 lawyers who speak German to go there for the War Guilt trials, but Recht does not wish to apply; fills up a box with towels, long underwear, jello, chocolate, and other things to send to Esther.  Hears that they are going to reduce the amount of points needed to get out of the Navy to 40 on November 1, at which point Recht will have 40.5, however, the Navy has been slow at processing these men; might cancel next week’s leave for a longer 10 day leave later.  Continues research on insurance companies.  Is considering flying home instead of taking the bus.  Recht’s department has been busy the past few days, partially because of the scheduling to bring in sailors from Williamsburg to watch the Camp play football against Little Creek; complains that the Navy does not recognize the fact that there are men of college training who would like some more intellectual magazines in the library.  Hears about a clothing drive for war-ravages countries and suggests discharged men donate old uniforms.  Gets information from the Children’s Bureau, sends some along to Esther and gives the rest to the library.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23459">
            <head>Subseries 6: Folder 651-660: 28 September 1945- 17 October 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folder 651-660: 28 September 1945- 17 October 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">6</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Reads “A Nation’s Gethsemane” by Powell Spring.  Comments about the “explosive situation” of Zionism in Palestine.  Sees that the PearyScope has been reduced in size, possibly to conserve paper.  Many new sailors are arriving, all dressed in civilian clothes, and they give hope to the older sailors, who can go home as replacements come in; wishes to talk with an acquaintance from home who now publishes a Republican magazine.  Sailors are at the College stadium for the game against Little Creek, but Recht does not want to take the chance of being out in the open without much clothes; hears that many ex-lawyers who joined the service do not want to go back to being lawyers.  His watching being broken gets Recht up and into the office at 6:15 am.  Wants Esther to tell him the reaction when people find out she is pregnant.  Hears that the point requirement will remain 44 until January 1 194[6].  Criticizes the Navy for their policy of releasing men; hears a story about a famous football player, Trippi, released from the Army with 41 points, when 70 are required there.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23460">
            <head>Subseries 7: Folder 661-670: 18 October 1945-24 October 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folder 661-670: 18 October 1945-24 October 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">7</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Theorizes that the reason that they cannot release as many people is because of all the sailors returning from the Pacific and being released first; hears that a show at the Ship’s Company theatre was delayed a half hour so that the CO and his group could finish ice cream sundaes.  Feels that the Navy should pay him and other yeomen more money since they need them so much as to keep them longer than other sailors; talks about expanding a furniture for cash business he used to run.  Talks about his interaction with Martin, a German PoW; talks about how the way to get towards true racial integration is to find the way to have people “want to treat Negroes like any other human being.”  Gets a call in the middle of the night from a man who was supposed to leave at 0005 and the dispatcher read it as 0500.  Talks with Kennedy about the way the demobilization is going.  Thinks about compiling a list of music that would interest “infants and youngsters.”  Has now been in the Navy for 2 years; wonders more about the “freezing” of yeomen; talks about his political affiliations in college.  He and Lew talk with a man named Phillips, who is a Zionist and wants to have more information about Jews and other racial minorities in the Camp library; says that the Chaplins’ School at William and Mary is closing. Writes about how Bill Maudlin is now satirizing service officialdom; the Navy is reclaiming all mattresses issued to men when they arrived.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23461">
            <head>Subseries 8: Folders 671-680: 25 October 1945-30 October 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 671-680: 25 October 1945-30 October 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">8</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Takes the petty officer’s test without reading the manual, which talks about nautical terms.  Calls in a reservation for Esther to come down November 21 to December 10; finds out that Virginia celebrates thanksgiving a week before the rest of the country; talks more about Esther’s pregnancy; hears that the current freeze on releasing yeomen will expire on January 1.  Gets ribbed by some of his friends for writing letters that are too impersonal; talks about some of Esther’s friends encouraged her to leave him when he did not want to have children.  Gets a “youngster” that is to begin training for his job, as his replacement.  Wonders if he is becoming unusually critical of the Navy of late, with regards mainly to demobilization.  Hears a man and his daughter talking about him and the fact that he works in an office, unlike the man’s daughter.  Gets a telegram that a man’s newborn and wife are not doing well, and so Recht gets some one to find Lt. Kennedy as he is leaving church to sign the man’s leave form; continues to wonder about what he will do after the Navy.  Talks the petty officer’s exam again, and says that it is for the last time, no matter what; talks about how a man got a “dependency discharge,” and how it annoyed the other men.  Wants to get some records of lullabies for the baby; sees that Kennedy has put through a request to advance Recht to Y2c; talks about a broken relationship between “Sarah and dad,” which stemmed from the depression years.  One of the librarians admits the Recht’s zeal for the library has gotten him excited about it.  Gets a package marked express and perishable 11 days after it was sent.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23462">
            <head>Subseries 9: Folders 681-690: 30 October 1945-22 November 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 681-690: 30 October 1945-22 November 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">9</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Sees the movie “The Lost Weekend.”  Talks with the recreation department sign painter, who had heard about him.  Talks about how the morning is not a good time to write to Esther, as all the routine matters must be taken care of first.  Changes Esther’s reservation to November 7 through November 24.  Goes to see the singer Niles with Lew, and decides that if he does not like it, he can just go to the College library.    Hears that the entire camp is scheduled to fold by June 1, although he should be out by then; finds out that his replacement-to-be does some sketching.  Brille, the head librarian, returns from how, and Recht says that he will be happy to eat with him and Esther; is still intent on get Planned Parenthood information in the library.  Hears that Brille has ordered the book Stork Bites Man, at Recht’s request.  Notices that the boot training program has reached its planned peak of receiving 2000 new recruits a week; feels a little under the weather and tries a few different cures for it; takes over Shelor’s job for Thanksgiving while Boilieu, his replacement, takes over his job.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23463">
            <head>Subseries 10: Folders 691-700: 25 November 1945-24 December 1945</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 691-700: 25 November 1945-24 December 1945,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">7</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">10</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Hears that Dr. Smit will stay on until March 1 and be promoted to Lt. Commander because they need him; talks about how men there are eager for only one thing, being discharged and sent home; hears that administrative heads might want to keep men there longer, to ease the transition.  An accident occurs with one of the buses taking recruits from camp to the football game in Williamsburg; reads an article in PM with comments by William Carlos Williams about Ezra Pound.  Has to tell men that they are being moved from the department, but leaves that for Lt. Kennedy to worry about.  Will come home from 28 December to 8 January.  Talks about his pending discharge, which is now definite in the near future, process beginning January 1.  Has a steak sandwich with pineapple, the best meat he has had while at the Camp.  Hears that the German PoWs are putting on a Sudermann play, Heimat.  Reads an article about the disorganization of the Allied occupation of Germany.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series" id="id23464">
        <head>Series 8: Folders 701-779: 25 December 1945-19 January 1946</head>
        <did>
          <unittitle>Folders 701-779: 25 December 1945-19 January 1946,
</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file" id="id23465">
          <did>
            <container label="Box">8</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23466">
            <head>Subseries 1: Folders 701-710: 25 December 1945-19 January 1946</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 701-710: 25 December 1945-19 January 1946,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">8</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">1</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Plans what he wants to do with all his Navy clothes after he is discharged.  Goes on leave for 10 days back up to Pittsburgh.  Is eager, even though his military service was not hard, to return to civilian life.  For the first time, when Recht returns to Camp, it is the Camp that now feels far away, instead of his home.  Notices that the camp store is slowly reducing its stock, in anticipation of the Camp closing; hears that the man who will be replacing him, Boulieu, has not been up to the task.  The child-parent exhibit, for which Recht helped to get information, closed.  Talks about a sardine carton lost from Esther’s father’s store.  Hears a theory that colds never leave the body, just lay in wait.  Thinks about painting their house, and discusses colors; is trying to buy as much as possible before leaving the Camp.  Hears about a steel strike, and discusses its impact; talks about the physical one gets when leaving the service.  Hears about Brille taking a vacation to Mexico on one of his leaves.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23467">
            <head>Subseries 2: Folders 711-720: 20 January 1946-26 January 1946</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folders 711-720: 20 January 1946-26 January 1946,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">8</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">2</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Asks about why one of his friends would not take her job back at the Social Work school.  Talks about how he believes slim people are healthier than “persons heavier.”  Talks about friends thinking about going to law school, and about how only 180 nylons were sent to the Camp, so he could not buy any.  The Camp gets another influx of recruits; talks about someone who is “quite a misfit”; sends some towels to friends back home.  Sees “Scarlett Street”; thinks that once he is moved to Induction, for preparation to go home, that he will not come to the office much, but let his replacement find his way.  Starts cleaning out his drawers in his office.  Needs to think out his positions on “the problem of white-Negro interrelationships.”  Arranges with Lt. Sorenson about coming into the office while in Induction, for part of the time; wants to take a vacation after out of the service, but not sure if to take one to New York City or just to rest at their home.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23468">
            <head>Subseries 3: Folder 721-729: 26 January 1946-2 February 1946</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folder 721-729: 26 January 1946-2 February 1946,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">8</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">3</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Finally gets information about where he is moving, and when.  Gets an interview to assign him to a specific separation center.  Sends a lot of things he wants at home through the mail to Esther, instead of packing them.  Finally gets the date and time that he will be leaving.  Starts trying to say goodbye to people from the camp.  Starts filling out all sorts of forms.  Sends his last letter from the Camp.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="subseries" id="id23469">
            <head>Subseries 4: Folder 730-779: Fragments</head>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Folder 730-779: Fragments,
</unittitle>
              <container label="Box">8</container>
              <container label="Sub-Series">4</container>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>Writes a letter detailing his morning routine at the Camp, probably from early in his stay there.  Talks about people in a stay at the Williamsburg Lodge.  Hears Lew talk about how Dorislee is immature; visits the Personnel Office and has fun pointing out two mistakes they made.  Camp has been receiving letters from men who have been transferred.  Talks about his feelings on his assignment to and at Peary and the way other men think of their assignments.  Talks about a Romanian, now a US citizen, working at Peary.  Talks about how the situation is in the office after Frankie has left, and how much work he does.  Talks to Phillips about libraries and their purpose.  Talks about plays at the Nixon Theater, which is in Pittsburgh.  Thinks that if the war were to go on for another year or so, he might try to work for the UNRRA[United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration].  Sees nothing but grave potential danger in the after-war period.  Talks about “books on and by Negroes.”  Talks about marks that Lt. Kennedy gave out to the men.  Thinks he might be able to get a GE electric iron.  Writes what someone, possibly Lt. Kennedy, wrote for his recommendation for commission.  Talks about race riots in Philadelphia.  Sees families at the pool; sees the movie “See My Lawyer;” hears that trains are being cancelled for troop movements.  Hears about men being moved and reassigned.  Hears a bit from men still in shock about Roosevelt’s death.  Talks about how the boot recruits and the chiefs are so eager to learn and get out of Peary, and Recht just calmly does his job.  Talks about how nice it was to hear Esther and Sid on the phone; discusses transportation to Williamsburg, and its difficulties.  Talks about sending food back to home.  Hears about more men leaving for Cleveland and elsewhere.  Does not see any of the men from his original barracks anymore; hears that most lawyers who come in believe they should be in administration or the legal department.  Hears about a sailor who was in the hospital for 74 days but is still in the service.  Talks about what he misses about Pittsburgh.  Talks about the wife of another family, whose husband is also in the military, moving in with Esther; hears about the possible closing of the Camp.  Hears some of the opinions the seamen have for yeomen.  Writes a letter on Recht’s Furniture letterhead.  Hears that the Captain of the Camp believes that the war is being fought to save Christianity.  Two letters from the summer of 1940, written to an Eleanor, and not written by Herman Recht; letters have holes cut out of them, indicating censorship.</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
    <!-- END SUBORDINATE COMPONENTS -->
  </archdesc>
</ead><!-- footer.inc.php -->
