<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/wm.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wm_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/wm_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY zknlva SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/lva/vivadoc.pl?file=vi01141.xml" NDATA html>
]><ead id="viw00122">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViW">PUBLIC "-//College of William and Mary::Earl Gregg Swem Library::Special Collections//TEXT (US::ViW::viw00122:: Abolitionist Papers Inventory, 1834-1888)//EN" "viw00122.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Inventory of the Abolitionist Papers Inventory, <date>1834-1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Abolitionist Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">95 Ab7
</num>
</subtitle>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By the College of William and Mary. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Ben Bromley, <date>02/20/07</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>Inventory of the Abolitionist Papers Inventory, <date>1834-1888</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Special Collections Research Center
<num type="Accession Number">95 Ab7
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Special Collections Staff
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Abolitionist Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1834-1888
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession Number" encodinganalog="099$a">Mss. 95 Ab7
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">9 items.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Letters, a speech, and a photograph relating to abolitionists Theodore Dwight Weld, Elizur Wright, Gerrit Smith, Henry Grew, William Lloyd Garrison, and Parker Pillsbury.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to all researchers.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Before publishing quotations or excerpts from any materials, permission must be obtained from the Manuscripts and Rare Books Librarian, and the holder of the copyright, if not Swem Library. 
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Abolitionist Papers (Mss. 95 Ab7), Special Collections Research Center, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gift, 1941
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Letters, a speech, and a photograph relating to abolition. Correspondents include: Theodore Dwight Weld (1803-1895) of Lane Seminary, Elizur Wright (1804-1885), Secretary of the American Anti-Slavery Society, Gerrit Smith (1797-1874), philanthropist and reformer, Henry Grew (1782-1862), Quaker abolitionist, William Lloyd Garrison (1805-1879), prominent abolitionist, and Parker Pillsbury (1809-1898), abolitionist author. Subjects include abolition tactics and organizations, expressions of sympathy to Garrison on the death of his wife and publication of Pillsbury's work. Also includes a photograph of Mary Grew (1813-1896), daughter of Henry Grew and abolitionist in her own right.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
	<c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">24 January 1834
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 pp. ALS.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Theodore D Wight Weld, Walnut Hills, [Ohio] to Elizur Wright Junior, Corresponding Secretary of the American anti-Slavery Society, New York City, New York. Received EW's letter; the decision that the letter requested was a heavy responsibility; has decided he serves the cause better where he is; has fought against slavery and colonization; colonization has able advocates; Brother Mehan and Professor Morgan have renounced colonization and come over to the abolitionist position; they are on the border of a slave state but within a year there will be 100 theological students at the institution. Lane Seminary in Walnut Hills, Ohio, - a strong abolitionist center that will influence the entire valley "more than a hundred societies in New York"; Beecher Stowe is dead set against their cause; believes the seminary would fold if he left; leads a bible class for colored adults; nominates Lewis Tappan as General Agent for the Society. JDW has secured EW's position of Corresponding Secretary in December of 1833.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c01>
	<c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">10 October 1839
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>1 pp. ALS.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Gerrit Smith, Peterborough, New Hampshire to "my dear Uncle", Daniel Cady Esquire, Johnstown, Fulton County, [New York],. Received DCs letter; hopes DC will be able to commerce proceedings in the Case of the Delaware Lot [?]. Hopes a speedy settlement with the representatives of R.M. Campbell and John E. Smith; business is poor and GS has not had a paying customer in 8 days.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c01>
	<c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">23 October 1861
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 pp. AD.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Henry Grew, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, "to the Friends of Righteousness and humanity to convene at West Chester on the 25th inst."   Regrets that he cannot attend the abolitionist meeting; hopes God will guide the convention; afraid that "the Tempter" will turn them from a "right end" and make them use "wrong means"; God may use the Civil War to bring about abolition, but he may allow wicked men to accomplish this; the faithful are obligated to not support the war if it is not a "right measure to accomplish a right end"; the war is not just because it seeks merely to restore the pre-war government that allowed slavery; support for a government that merely prevents the extension of slavery is not enough; even if the ends were right i.e. total abolition, war is still wrong; God's command of "Thou shalt not kill" applies to soldiers as well; ministers who leave the pulpit and accept commissions are hypocrites; God's weapons are sufficient to defeat slavery. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c01>
	<c01 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">March 1865
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	<physdesc>4 pp. ALS.
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>James Miller McKim. Pennsylvania a Freedmen's Relief Association, No. 424 Walnut Street, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to "my dear May (?). Relates establishment of the American Freedman Aid Commission; Judge Berd is president and Wendall Phillips Lawson is acting Secretary, a "grand" Anniversary will be marked by addresses by Phillip Brooks, Henry Ward Beecher, General Saxton (?) and Andrew; requests advice on choosing an editor. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive">4 February 1876
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 pp. ALS.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>H.G. Stone, Framingham, Middlesex County, Massachusetts to William Lloyd Garrison. Thanks WLG for his memorial card; expresses sympathy for the loss of his wife; hopes that he is recovering from his illness because his services to the country are still needed; Southern rebels are finding cause with power hungry Northern partisans
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive">20 February 1876.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>1 pp. ALS.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Elizabeth L. Miller, 7 Fifth Avenue, New York, [New York], to "my dear friend" William Lloyd Garrison. Sends sympathy for his great loss of Mrs. Garrison.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive">11 May 1876.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pp. ALS.
</physdesc>
</did>
<arrangement>
<p>. Mary S. Stetson for her father, Brooklyn County [New York], to "Dear Friend" William Lloyd Garrison. Written for her father, who expresses sympathy for Mrs. Garrison's death; he knew her as a child in 1825. Bears a short personal condolence from Mary herself. 
</p>
</arrangement>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive">2 July 1884.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>4 pp. ALS.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Parker Pillsbury, Concord, New Hampshire, to "My dear friend May". Mr. Phillips and the Wallcots have passed away and PP feels that there is nothing left that is dear to him; William Lloyd Garrison is hospitable; one thousand of his books have sold and he still has one thousand left that he cannot sell; he is in relatively good health. Stationary is an advertisement for PP's book, "Acts of the Anti-Slavery Apostles".
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive">n.d.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>2 1/4", 3 5/8". Ph.
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Black and white, head and shoulders view, of Mary Grew (1813-1896).
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>