<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vaffcr00006">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-VaFfCR">PUBLIC "-//Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vaffcr00006::A Guide to the Voting Records of Fairfax County, 1854-1936)//EN" "vaffcr00006.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Voting Records of Fairfax County, <date>1854-1936</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
</subtitle>
<author>Meg Wilder
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>  
<date type="publication">&#169; 2017 By Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Ashton Fonville, <date>09 September 2021</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Voting Records of Fairfax County, <date>1854-1936</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center <!-- Add your institution's name -->
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href=" http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/FairfaxCircuitCourt.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher> Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2017
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Voting Records of Fairfax County, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1854-1936
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physloc label="Shelf Location">Unit 33 and Map Drawer
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>Input Later</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
</origination>
</did>

<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>The Collection is open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Voting Records of Fairfax County, Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Permanent Record of the Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center.
</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Heavily creased and folded documents were treated with humidity and flattened. Post-1870 poll books with no identifying information on the covers were described using pencil. Oversized documents were placed in flat files and stored in map drawers.
</p>
</processinfo>

</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Commonwealth of Virginia ratified its first constitution in 1776, following the signing of the Declaration of Independence. Since its ratification, there have been regular amendments and six major revisions to the state's constitution: 1830, 1851, 1864, 1870, 1902, and 1971. The current constitution as of 2017 is an amended version of the 1971 constitution. These revisions to the Virginia Constitution are representative of the "political, social, regional, and racial climate of the times," according to the Virginia General Assembly.</p>
<p>The constitution of 1851 took significant steps in extending voting rights. In previous versions, only white male property holders could vote, but the 1851 revisions changed this law so that all white men were eligible to vote. Additionally, judges were to be elected rather than appointed and the position of Lieutenant Governor was created.</p>
<p>Article VII of the Constitution of Commonwealth of Virginia establishes the roles and duties of local government systems, with Section 4 of this article mandating, "There shall be elected by the qualified voters of each county and city a treasurer, a sheriff, an attorney for the Commonwealth, a clerk, who shall be clerk of the court in the office of which deeds are recorded, and a commissioner of revenue." The elections of which records are found in this collection fall under this section of the Virginia constitution.</p>
<p>Later significant extensions of voting rights in Virginia include granting the right to vote to African Americans under the 15th amendment to the United States Constitution in 1869, and to women under the 19th amendment in 1920. Our records of voter registration indicate that both African Americans and women in Fairfax County were eager to exercise their civic duties following the ratification of these amendments.</p>
<p>The voting records of Fairfax County are kept at the Fairfax Circuit Court under Title 17.1, Chapter 2 (Clerks, Clerks' Offices and Records) of the Virginia Code, which states, "The circuit court clerks shall have custody of and shall keep all court records, including books, evidence, records, maps, and papers, deposited in their offices or at such location otherwise designated by the clerk, as well as records stored in electronic format whether the storage media for such electronic records are on premises or elsewhere." The code also stipulates, "None of the records or papers of a circuit court shall be removed by the clerk nor allowed by him to be removed out of the county or city wherein the clerk's office is kept."</p>
</bioghist>


</archdesc>
</ead>


