<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vaffcr00003">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-VaFfCR">PUBLIC "-//Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vaffcr00003::A Guide to the Fairfax County School Records and Ledgers, 1870-1905)//EN" "vaffcr00003.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Fairfax County School Records and Ledgers, <date>1870-1905</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Emily Budd
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
</publisher>
<date type="publication">&#169; 2017 By Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Ashton Fonville, <date>22 July 2021</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Fairfax County School Records and Ledgers, <date>1870-1905</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the <lb/>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center <!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href=" http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/FairfaxCircuitCourt.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher> Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2017
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Fairfax County School Records and Ledgers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1870-1905
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">
</unitid>
<physloc label="Shelf Location">Unit 39, Shelf 3
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>6.55 linear foot</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>The Collection is open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Fairfax County School Records and Ledgers, Accession # , Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center<!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Permanent Records of the Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>This collection contains two sets of books from different sources- the first appears to be records related to the work of the Fairfax County School Board. Until the early 1900s, the Fairfax County School Board held their meetings at the Courthouse, as they had no official offices for themselves. These record books might have been brought to meetings and left- this could also explain why a few books contain minutes from meetings. Other books in this part of the collection may have been donated, but if so, the donors were anonymous.
</p>
<p>The second group of books in this collection relates to a court case involving John Chichester and the Commonwealth of Virginia (CFF# 1893-040: Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Sarah E. Chichester, et al). Chichester, who had served as county treasurer and School Board Clerk, was accused of not adequately carrying out his duties. The county sued for $100,000, which was the total cost of the error they claimed he made in the books and the $95,000 bond which he and six securities signed when he took the office of treasurer. Chichester passed away on June 27, 1889, so at the time of the trial, his wife and the six securities who signed the bond with him were responsible to defend him and pay the penalty if they lost the case. The court ruled in favor of the state, and in consequence, the defense had to pay the $100,000 that was then owed to the County. This money was paid over the course of several years.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Series 1:  Demographic records, 1873-1903. Eleven Ledgers. This series contains four School Censuses for 1890, and one for 1900; as well as three Teacher's Registers, two books containing the examinations of teachers, and one Virginia Public School Register. These documents contain teachers' and students' names, ages, education, and race. The censuses include the guardians of the students, the school they attended, what studies they pursued, and if the students could read and write. This series contains a wealth of information about the daily operations of the schools, such as attendance, textbooks used, and studies taught.
</p>
<p>Series 2: Financial records, 1870-1905. Six Ledgers. Includes salaries paid to teachers; expenses for each school district and schoolhouse (expenses included fire wood, paper, books, repairs to schoolhouses, and similar items); and funds received and spent by the county. Some documents contain minutes from school board meetings and expenses of the school treasurer while on official business. In this series, there are also receipts paid to teachers for their work.</p>
<p>Series 3:  Evidence from the John Chichester court case (CFF# 1893-040: Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Sarah E. Chichester et al), 1886-1890. Seven Ledgers. These books were used as evidence in the court case against John Chichester. They include reports of expenses for the schools (repairs, books, fire wood, teacher salaries, etc) and funds received and spent by the county. One book contains a record of official clerk business, as well as some meeting minutes.
</p>
<p>Series 4: Miscellaneous. 1880-1904, non-inclusive. Seven Folders. This series contains records that did not include financial or demographic information, or were removed from books in the other series. These include letters written to and from the school board and teachers, scratch paper, and receipts for items for the schools. One book in this series contains school laws for 1892, and another is entitled Nickerson's Manual of School Charts. </p>
</scopecontent>

<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Attendance of students, funding, demographics of students and teachers, costs of school districts, payment to teachers, items bought for schools, clerk's travel for work</subject>
<geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651$a">Fairfax County</geogname>
<function encodinganalog="657$a">Ledger books, receipts, letters, guidebooks for teaching</function>
<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655$a">Paper, ink, graphite, marbled book covers, leather</genreform>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="1">Demographic Records
<unitdate type="inclusive">
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 1: Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Lee District: White School Number 9
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 2: Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Lee District: Lorton Valley White School Number 6
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 3: Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Centreville District: School 6, White School
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 4: Virginia Public School Record - Dranesville District, Colored School Number 73
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 5: Providence school district, 1890 Census
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 6: Mt. Vernon school district, 1890 Census
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Box 1: Book 7: Falls church, 1890 Census">
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 8: Lee school district, 1890 Census
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="">Box 1: Book 9
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Falls church, 1900 Census
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

</c01>

</dsc></archdesc>
</ead>




	

	

	


	


	

	

	





	







	
		


	





