<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViFGM" url="http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/hamburg.html">http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/hamburg.html
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Guide to the John R. Hamburg Transportation Papers, <date>1956-1992</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">John R. Hamburg Transportation
<num type="collectionnumber">C0073
</num></subtitle>
        <author>FINDING AID AUTHOR
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>George Mason University Libraries
</publisher>
        <date type="publication">2006 By George Mason University Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by FINDING AID ENCODER, <date>FINDING AID ENCODED DATE</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2019-02-13">2019-02-13</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the TITLE, <date>DATES</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives
<num type="Accession Number">COLLECTION NUMBER
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Harold J. Barthold
</author>
      <publisher>George Mason University Libraries
</publisher>
      <date type="publication">2006
</date>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">
        <corpname>George Mason University. <subarea>Special Collections and Archives.
</subarea></corpname>
      </repository>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <persname>John R. Hamburg
</persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John R. Hamburg Transportation papers
</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1956-1992
</unitdate>
      <unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">C0073
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
        <extent>3.5 linear feet </extent>
        <extent>(7 boxes)
</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains papers from John Hamburg's career as a transportation planner. Hamburg specialized in urban transportation and worked on projects in Detroit, Chicago, Mexico City, Shanghai, and at the Baltimore-Washington International Airport.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no access restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions on personal use. Permission to publish material from the John R. Hamburg transportation papers must be obtained from the Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University Libraries.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>John R. Hamburg transportation papers, C0073, Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University Libraries.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by the John R. Hamburg estate, 2002.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>Processed by Special Collections and Archives staff. EAD markup completed by Eron Ackerman and Jordan Patty in August 2009. Additional processing and EAD markup completed by Hal Barthold in 2011.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>Born in 1928, John Robert Hamburg was a transportation planner specializing in urban transportation. Hamburg served in the United States Navy during World War II, then returned to his home town of Detroit to study urban sociology at Wayne State University. In the 1950s, after receiving his Master's degree, Hamburg worked on transportation studies in Detroit and Chicago. He served as acting director of the New York State Transportation Department in 1962-1965 and as a partner with Creighton-Hamburg Consultants in 1967-1974. During the 1960s Hamburg lectured and taught planning courses at Cornell University, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and Clemson University. In 1974 Hamburg co-founded John Hamburg and Associates, Inc., and from 1982 through the mid 1990s, he served as vice president of Barton-Aschman Associates in Washington, D.C. On April 22, 2000 Hamburg died at Presbyterian Hospital in Albuquerque after suffering a stroke.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains papers from John Hamburg's career as a transportation planner. Hamburg specialized in urban transportation and worked on projects in Detroit, Chicago, Mexico City, Shanghai, and at the Baltimore-Washington International Airport.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by subject and chronologically into one series.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Special Collections and Archives also holds many other <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:title="transportation collections" xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://sca.gmu.edu/collections-subject.php#TRANSPORTATION"/>.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Hamburg, John R.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Transportation--Planning.</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Urban transportation.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 1: The John R. Hamburg Transportation Papers,
</unittitle>
          <unitdate>April 1956-April 1992
</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p/>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Phoenix Conference TRBd, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May-October 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about a Transportation Research Board workshop titled "Transportation Requirements for Urban Activity Centers" held in Phoenix in September of 1984. Hamburg served on a panel about financing community infrastructure. Material contains "Introductory Comments" by J. Douglas Carroll, notes, a bibliography of participants, agendas, a newspaper articles and a bibliography.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Transp and Land Dev. TRBd A1D01, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>December 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A memorandum to the Transportation Research Board regarding committee membership.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>TRB Engelen Committee A1B01, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January 1984-January 1985</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from Rodney Engelen who was the chairman of the Transportation and Land Development committee. Material includes memos, meeting and workshop plans, committee activity reports, conference agendas, notes and a paper by Scott Oran and J. Douglas Carroll titled "Can Developers Be Equitably Charged For Off-Site Transportation Improvements: A Test Project in Princeton, NJ".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Port Authority 1, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January-April 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. Material includes, maps, notes, passenger volume information and information about computer mapping.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Cons. AGR 4-PU, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September-December 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A consultant's agreement between J. Douglas Carroll and Princeton University. Material also includes lists of dates, a letter concerning the agreement and a "statement of work".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>NJ DOT Network, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February-April 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the New Jersey Department of Transportation. Material includes maps, network data tape printout and code descriptions. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Data Sources - Tristate, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>July 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the New York Metropolitan Transportation Council. Material includes a New York Metropolitan Transportation Council pamphlet about data and information services, notes, maps and pricing information for maps from the New York Metropolitan Transportation Council. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Journey to Work NJ Census, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1983-June 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents about transit in New Jersey. Material includes a hand written memo, information about using the 1980 census data to evaluate transit routes, budget information, rough drafts and final copies of a research proposal and an Urban Transportation Planning Package.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Transit - 3 Sep. 84, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about transit in New Jersey. Material includes notes and budget information. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Port Authority - PLK, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Two Port Authority of NY and NJ business cards from John M. Ashe and Richard C. Roxberry.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Dep. Land Use Advisory, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June-December 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents from the Land Use Committee. Material includes a draft of "An Investigation into the Use of Dedicated Taxes for the Purchases of Critical Areas", meeting agendas and minutes, a pamphlet for the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, memos, a Hightstown Quadrangle Fact Sheet, a statement by the commissioner of NJ Department of Environmental Protection Robert E. Hughey, land use information and a Spring 1984 American Planning Association Newsletter.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>TRBb - 84-5, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A Transportation Research Board offer form for papers. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Transit Hudson-Bergen Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November-December 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the Hudson Bergen Project to create a bus line. Material includes a project proposal, project schedules, budget information, a D. S. Winokur Associates Inc. Brochure, subcontractor forms and completed survey forms for the bus service rationalization.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Census Files, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1982</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents about the 1980 Census. Material includes government census publications, a summary of major 1980 census series, Association of Public Data Users membership information, sex ratios based on standard census tabulation and census results.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>TRBb - 1984 Annual Meeting, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1983-January 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the 1984 Transportation Research Board. Material includes a publication manuscripts pamphlet, TRB program information form, notice about visual aids, information for authors pamphlet, AV equipment request form, paper preview form, agendas, meeting pamphlet and a general paper call. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">16</container>
            <unittitle>TRBb - 84/4, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1983-March 1985</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Material in this file includes a rolodex card, notes, a publication manuscripts pamphlet, information for the authors pamphlet, memos and a rough draft of "Using Census Data to Evaluate Transit Service".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Transit Agreement, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>August 1983-December 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about an agreement between the New Jersey Transit Corporation and Princeton University. Material includes maps of bus routes, Princeton University computer center usage information, blank New Jersey Transit Corporation agreement, notes, memos, completed agreement between NJ Transit Corporation and Trustees of Princeton University, budget information and census maps.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Transit - North Jersey Project 1, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1983-January 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about bus transit. Material includes census maps, notes, bus route maps, transportation program folders containing project services overviews and maps, "Using the 1980 Census to Evaluate the Equity of Transit Service in Northern New Jersey", budget information and a bus operator's daycard.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Tran-Bus South J Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>July 1981-February 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about a Southern New Jersey Bus Transit Project. Material includes a draft of Derivation of Performance Measures for Bus Route Evaluation System, NJ Transit Bus Operations information, an analysis of New Jersey Transit's South Jersey Lines, scope of services outline, a summary of cost for the New Jersey Transit Bus Study, notes, development and application of a bus route, Bus Route Evaluation Study for South Jersey, budget information, 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>TRBd Conference on Census User, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1984-February 1985</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the December 1984 National Conference on Decennial Census Data for Transportation Planning: 1980 Experience and 1990 Needs held in Orlando, FL. Material includes notes, a summary of findings and recommendations from the conference, National Academy of Science Travel Voucher, Pennsylvania State Data Center Newsletter, a Hertz rent-a-car map of Florida, a draft of "Prospectus for a Report on National Commuting Trends 1970-1980", an Epocot Center Guide Book, a conference pamphlet and a conference schedule and agenda. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>TNJ -1, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Two New Jersey Transit Bus Operations Inc. business cards, for Shirish Gupte and Joel Golub.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Bus Project Graphics, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1982-March 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about bus project graphics. Material includes large print outs of a bus operator's daycard, a report containing figures and graphs about the operator's daycard, presentation slides about NJ transit bus operations and a series of graphs about bus transit.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Bus Study Contracts, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January 1982</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the southern New Jersey bus evaluation study. Material includes a scope of services with six tasks and budget information. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>NJT - Bus Project - Datasheets, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>March-September 1982</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the bus transit program in New Jersey. Material includes print out of operator's daycard, "A Data Sampling Plan for the Southern Division of New Jersey Transit Bus Operations, Inc." by David T. Hunt, a table of bus garages, South Jersey bus service pamphlet, contact lists, meeting agendas, feasibility/technical studies program final evaluation, ridership information, preliminary system design presentation and performance monitoring program overall system design.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Bus Study Progress Reports, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1982-June 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about Material includes operations monitoring reports, an operator's daycard, meeting highlights, memos, daycard redesign drafts, "Review of Automated Passenger Counting Systems", two drafts of NJ Transit Bus Route Evaluation System Task II Develop System Design and Algorithms, maps, a data sampling plan, a preliminary report on optical scanners, schedule and fare module and a task list for Princeton.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>NJ Transit Info, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1981</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Information about New Jersey Transit. Material includes information about New Jersey Transit, budget information, transit news, fiscal year 1982 budget overview, executive director's report regarding fare increases, service economies, and three point program, notes from the Transaction Conference, conference program schedule and "Administration's Highway Legislation".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Communications/Meetings, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1981-January 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from NJ Transit meetings. Material includes meeting agendas, notes, a performance exception report from Turnerville Garage, memos, attendence sheets and meeting minutes.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>New Jersey State Rail Planning Phase I, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1981-July 1987</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about a proposal to New Jersey Department of Transportation for Rail Planning. Material includes notes, budget information and "Analytical Support for New Jersey State Rail Planning Phase I: Network Cleaning and Current Traffic Analysis and Display".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Southern New Jersey Bus Evaluation Study Scope of Service, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September-November 1981</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the Southern New Jersey Bus Evaluation Study. Material includes thirteen copies of Southern New Jersey Bus Evaluation Study Scope of Service, budget information, proposed changes, an outline of the scope of work, a contact list and a meeting agenda.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Personal - Vita, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>J. Douglas Carroll's resume.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Official Papers, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April-October 1982</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from J. Douglass Carroll's time in Indonesia. Material includes a boarding passes, personal correspondence, receipts, bills, notes, reimbursement forms, a United Nations Special Service Agreement, correspondence from National Urban Development Policy Project, Christina Adidjaja's resume and Bernard P. Markowicz's curriculum vitae. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Infrastructure Bank Legislation, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Official text of "An Act establishing the New Jersey Infrastructure Bank and making an appropriation" by the State of New Jersey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Rt 206 Corridor Study, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1982-March 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Material related to the Rt 206 Corridor Study including correspondence and a draft of the corridor study. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">3</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>New Jersey State Land Use Committee, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1981-February 1985</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the New Jersey state Land Use Committee. Materials include memos, meeting minutes, the rough draft of a pamphlet about Trenton area office locations of the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, a large brochure for the New Jersey state development guide, maps, an article from Scientific American "The Mechanization of Work", a Geographic Information System brochure, an opinion article about volunteers, a flyer for the application of environmental information to land use planning, a review of the New Jersey Geological Survey, notes, land use planning data tables, 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>New Jersey State Department of Environmental Protection Land Use Committee, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>December 1982-April 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the Land Use Committee. Material includes a committee list, a paper titled "The Acquisition of Land Cover Data", "A Land Use and Land Cover Classification System for Use with Remote Sensor Data", meeting agendas and minutes, State of New York Assembly act about village real estate tax, a trend chart, memos, Environmental Issues and Trends for the 1990's, committee reports, "Policy and Procedures for the Use and review of Population Forecasts for Water Resources Management Planning", an organizational chart of the New Jersey State Department of Environmental Protection, Department of Environmental Protection Planning Group Prospectus and Department of Environmental Protection Division of Water Resources Flood Hazard Area Regulations. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Dave Hunt's Work, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Handwritten notes and a print out of an abstract and an outline for expanding the role of interactive graphics in transit management.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>New Jersey Transit Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission - Bus Route Coding, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>August 1983-September 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission about Bus Route Coding. Material includes notes, a proposal for the route coding project and expense account information.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Estimating Free Speeds and Capacities For The Tri-State Transportation Planning Computer Models Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A report containing proposed methods for calculating capacities and free speeds for the Tri-State Transportation  Planning Computer Models Project.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal to Conduct a Study Entitled Support of the FHWA/UMTA Analysis System (UTAS) Computerized Planning Procedures, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal for a new multimodal transportation planning software and procedures. Material includes the proposal, a pricing proposal, cost estimates, machine configuration and technology requirements. FHWA= Federal Highway Administration, UMTA= Urban Mass Transportation Administration, UTAS= Urban Transportation Analysis System.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Study of the Feasibility of Demand Flexible Small Unit Transportation Services Freehold Borough-Freehold Township, New Jersey, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>December 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A technical proposal and cost and price proposal for the feasibility of transportation services in Freehold, New Jersey. Material also includes correspondence, qualifications of the firm Creighton Hamburg and Associates, a minority hiring and employment statement and a statement of incorporation.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal to Improve and Maintain UTAS Program HR, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1970</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal and cost proposal to improve and maintain the Urban Transportation Analysis System "Program HR".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Micro Assignment- -Final Report; Volume 1-Procedure and Theoretical Background Oct. 1969, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1969</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A large report on a model created to show traffic patterns. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Analysis of Trip Production by Household for Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>July 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>An analysis of travel by household in the Delaware Valley Region.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Access and Land Development Report, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January 1973</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A report presenting the findings of research on the development of a computer model capable of simulating the impact that alternative transportation and land development decisions have upon the development and performance of the activity and transport systems in the region.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>INTRANS Operation Manual, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>August 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Information on the peripheral operations for the Interactive Transportation Analysis System.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>Assessment of Options of Implementation of the INTRANS in the Tri-State Regional Planning Commission System, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A document exploring the issues and implementation of using the Interactive Transportation Analysis System in the Tri-State Regional Planning Commission offices.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>The Access and Land Development Prototype Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>An article by Morton Schneider aimed to show general and computable relationships among travel, land development, and the time and cost characteristics of transportation.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>John Hamburg Talk, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A summary of a talk given by John Hamburg at transportation conference in San Francisco on 10 October 1974.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>Modifications of Direct Traffic Estimation Method Model, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A document describing changes made to the Direct Traffic Estimation Model. The DTEM permitted traffic estimates to be made for single links in a highway network without the need for a complete zone-to-zone traffic assignment.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">16</container>
            <unittitle>Development of a Thoroughfare Plan and Inventory, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A qualifications statement of a development of a thoroughfare plan and inventory for the intensive study area of the north central Texas state planning region.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">4</container>
            <container type="Folder">17</container>
            <unittitle>Travel Behavior Report, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>An interim report on the initial review of the comparison of travel behavior in Washington, DC for the years 1955 and 1968. Also included is a letter from John Hamburg, president of Creighton, Hamburg and Associates.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Macro Analysis of the Operational Implications of a Major Shift from Auto to Transit Vehicles, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A technical proposal examining the implications of a shift from auto to transit vehicles. Also included is a cost estimate.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Technical Proposal for the Modification of Contract DOT-FH-11-8084 Development of Community Aggregate Planning Model, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A description of the work undertaken by Creighton, Hamburg and Associates to incorporate changes and additions into the Community Aggregate Planning Model. Also included a contract pricing proposal.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Number of Legs and Approach Mode of Transit Riders in the 1960 Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission Region, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A report on the 1960 transit riders organized by mode of travel and number of legs for travel.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Peak Hour Level of Service Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal calculating peak hour level of service for intersections in Montgomery County.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Prediction of Recreational Demand, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>March 1976</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal predicting the demand for urban recreation is strongly related to the problem of trip generation in the field of urban transportation planning.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal to Conduct a Survey and Analysis of Attitudes of Intercity Travelers Toward Intercity Transportation Alternatives, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal by Creighton, Hamburg and Associates to conduct a survey and analysis of attitudes of intercity travelers toward intercity transportation alternatives.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Statement of Qualifications, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A statement of qualifications, project experience, personnel assignments, biographical resumes, and schedule of survey operations from Creighton, Hamburg and Associates for the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Bus Passenger Survey, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposed survey design and procedures for the bus passenger survey conducted as part of a revenue allocation study.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>NCHRP 8-14 Transportation Research Board Proposal, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal for NCHRP Project 8-14 from John Hamburg and Associates about people traveling to activities and how they got from one place to another.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Development of Mode-Split Procedures Proposal, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>June 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal from John Hamburg and Associates to the Northeast Ohio Areawide Coordinating Agency describing how to produce revised mode-split procedures.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>Develop Zone-to-Zone Vehicle Distribution and Assignment Programs Incorporating DTEM Capability for Organizing Zone and Network Data, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A document describing a proposed procedure for giving the TSRPC zone-to-zone traffic assignment capabilities.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>Assessment of Options Regarding Task 2 - TSRPC Zone to Zone Vehicle Assignment Capabilities, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A document providing conclusions reached about zone to zone vehicle assignment capabilities.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>Technical Report Hypothetical Two City Tests, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September-December 1972</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A report presenting the results of a set of experiments which were run utilizing a prototype of a model at the University of Illinois.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Development of Manuals for Transportation Planning in Small Urban Areas, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>March 1976</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Technical and cost proposals for the development of manuals for transportation planning. Also included are notes and a disclosure statement.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>Capacity Restraint Observations, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>December 1973</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A memo listing observations related to capacity restraint alternatives for the Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">16</container>
            <unittitle>Travel Behavior Report, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1975</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>An interim report on the initial review of the comparison of travel behavior in Washington, DC for the years 1955 and 1968. Also included is a letter from John Hamburg, president of Creighton, Hamburg and Associates.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">17</container>
            <unittitle>Development of Procedures for Evaluating Urban Transportation System Alternatives, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1976</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal to develop a handbook for evaluation procedures for all types of transport actions, the proposal also includes resumes and a cot proposal.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">5</container>
            <container type="Folder">18</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal to Conduct a Travel Demand Study for the PIMA Association of Governments, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal describing a methodology by which reliable information for transportation planning purposes can be abstained for the Tuscon metropolitan area.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Determination of Origin-Destination Matrices from Link Volumes and Turning Movements, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Responses to questions about a proposal from John Hamburg and Associates called Determination of Origin-Destination Matrices from Link Volumes and Turning Movements.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1976-June 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Material in this file includes a cost proposal called Determination of Origin-Destination Matrices from Link-Volume and Turning Movement Data, correspondence, lists of previously completed contracts, budget information, a handwritten letter, graphs and notes.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>March 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A rough draft of a letter from John Hamburg,"The Use of Equilibrium Assignment Techniques", "Comments Regarding the Use of a Network Equilibrium Model When Determining OD Movements from Observed Link Flows and Turning Movements", pricing information and notes.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Theory of Transportation and Land Development, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1969-June 1970</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A rough draft and final copy of "Theory of Transportation and Land Development - Program Documentation".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Adaptation and Calibration of Micro Assignment to the Golden Triangle Area of Pittsburgh, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1973</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The final report on a contract between Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission and Creighton, Hamburg Incorporated.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Micro Assignment Final Report Volume II - Program Documentation, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>October 1969-December 1970</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The final report prepared for the US Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration on a model created to show traffic patterns. See folder 4.8 for volume 1.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Memo on Highway Capacity, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>January 1974</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A memo that discusses the impact of capacity in the simulation process, reviews some of the alternatives for obtaining capacity, and recommends how capacities should be inserted into the 1960 Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission network.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Final Report to North Central Texas Council of Governments, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February-July 1984</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The final report to the North Central Texas Council of Governments Regional Travel Survey Volume 1 Home Interview Surveys.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Preliminary Results of Trip Generation Analysis, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>August 1983</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A memo describing investigation and analysis of the trip generation model implemented in a computer program.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Thoroughfare Planning System, Thoroughfare Information System, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1980</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Technical specifications and user documentation of Program CAPSPD for a thoroughfare planning system and a thoroughfare information system.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>NCTCOG Model System Description, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>An overview description of the North Central Texas Council of Governments Multimodal Transportation Analysis Process.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal to Conduct a Travel Demand Study for the PIMA Association of Governments, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1977</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal describing a methodology by which reliable information for transportation planning purposes can be abstained for the Tuscon metropolitan area.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>Proposed Methodology for Drawing a Sample of Buses, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A paper describing the proposed methodology for drawing a sample of buses for the 1977 Revenue Allocation Project.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Sampling Variability and Recommended Procedures for Estimating Sample Precision, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1976</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A memo from John Hamburg addressing the issue of sampling variability and procedures for calculating the precision of the estimates of revenue by jurisdiction for the bus survey.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">6</container>
            <container type="Folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>Proposal for the Administration of a Transit Impact Monitoring Program Workplace Survey, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1980</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A proposal for a study which would obtain statistically valid information on the travel characteristics of the work or school trips of employees or students working or attending school in areas well-served by the Metropolitan Atlanta Rapid Transit Authority Phase A rail system.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Use of the Thoroughfare Planning System, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A large document about the use of the thoroughfare planning system.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Integrating Transportation Systems Management Into the Overall Transportation Planning Process, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>Undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A document by John Hamburg and George Lathrop titled "Integrating TSM into the Overall Transportation Planning Process".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Average Vehicle Ridership Calculation, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1991</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Correspondence and a copy of the AVR calculation worksheet.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Local Rail Freight Assistance Program, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>July 1990-March 1991</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Two documents about the Local Rail Freight Assistance Program, a benefit-cost methodology from the Federal Railroad Administration and the 1991 New Mexico State Rail Plan Update appendix on applying the benefit-cost methodology.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>New Mexico Project, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1990-March 1992</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about a proposed project in New Mexico. Material includes notes, "A Strategic Plan for Measuring and Forecasting Multimodal Transportation Activity" by Rolf R. Schmitt, "Highway Traffic Forecasting System Overview" by Rolf R. Schmitt, an introduction to Large Scale Simulation, cost estimates for taking household surveys of travel habits, evaluations of proposals, a scope of services for the project "Commodity Flows Within a Multimodal Transportation Forecast Model", "Initial reflections on Multimodal Large Scale Simulation Initiatives" by John Hamburg, budget information and comments on "Commodity Shipments Within a Multimodal Transportation Forecast Model" Proposal.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>AMTECH Corporation, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1992</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>A video tape from AMTECH Corporation titled "Welcome to the Future".
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Chicago Area Transportation Study, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1956</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Volume one of a coding manual for the Chicago Area Transportation Study.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">7</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous, </unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1991</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Miscellaneous files including an incomplete memo, a packet of maps, workshop minutes and attendance lists.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
