<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
  <eadheader findaidstatus="Completed" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-VGM" url="http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/mannmaps.html">http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/mannmaps.html</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Guide to the C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection, 
                    <date>1579-1961</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle>C. Harrison Mann, Jr.
		<num>C0213</num></subtitle>
        <author>Finding aid prepared by Processed by Special Collections and Archives. EAD markup completed by Greta Kuriger in July 2012.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections &amp; Archives</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/gmu_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date>2012</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the Archivists' Toolkit
                <date>2012-09-28T14:40-0400</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
                <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2019-02-13">2019-02-13</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
	</head>
      <unittitle label="Title">C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection</unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">C0213</unitid>
      <repository label="Repository">
        <corpname>George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections &amp; Archives</corpname>
      </repository>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
		</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent>5 linear feet</extent>
        <extent> (90 folders)</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <unitdate normal="1579/1961" type="inclusive" label="Date">1579-1961</unitdate>
      <abstract id="ref175" label="Abstract">Donated to George Mason University Libraries in September 1978 by the Mann family, the C. Harrison Mann Jr, Map Collection comprises ninety-six maps ranging from the sixteenth to nineteenth centuries and is housed in the Special Collections &amp; Archives department. Though the majority of the maps Mann collected are of Virginia, there are many pertaining to other parts of the United States and the world in the collection.</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <persname>Mann, Charles Harrison, Jr., 1908-1977 
		</persname>
      </origination>
    </did>
    <bioghist id="ref150">
      <head>Biographical note</head>
      <p>Charles Harrison Mann, Jr. was born in Alabama in 1908 and received his law degree from the University of Virginia in 1931. He subsequently became an attorney both in Washington, D.C. and in Arlington, Virginia where he and his wife Betty Hart Mann, maintained their home. In 1949, while serving as President of the Northern Virginia Chapter of the University of Virginia Alumni Association, Mann organized an exploratory committee of local citizens to develop support for higher education in Northern Virginia. Through these efforts, the Northern Virginia Center of the University opened in October 1, 1949.</p>
      <p>In 1953 Mann organized the Advisory Council to the Northern Virginia Center, which agreed that a two-year branch college should be established. Elected as a Democrat to the Virginia House of Delegates from 1954-1970, Mann sponsored a resolution calling for a study of educational needs for Virginia, and was instrumental in recommending the development of a college system in Virginia, particularly the establishment of a branch in Northern Virginia.</p>
      <p>Mann was responsible for creating an educational financial assistance program for Virginia college students, and was instrumental in sponsoring legislation allowing local governments to form regional boards to acquire and transfer land and buildings for educational use.</p>
      <p>He also served as the Chairman of George Mason College's first Board of Control. He sponsored bills constituting George Mason College as a branch of the University of Virginia and later elevating it to a four year division of the University with the right to grant degrees and offer graduate programs. He served on the GMU Board of Visitors from 1975 to 1977. He died in 1977.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <relatedmaterial id="ref152">
      <head>Related Material</head>
      <p>Special Collections and Archives also holds <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="C. Harrison Mann, Jr.'s personal papers" xlink:href=" http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/mann.html"/> and handwritten draft of his history of George Mason University. Papers pertain to his political career and include subject files, memoranda, campaign materials, speeches, newsclippings and other related materials. In addition, there is the C. Harrison Mann, Jr. collection of rare books and atlases that can be found searching the GMU Libraries catalog.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <arrangement id="ref176">
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>This collection is arranged by size of map.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <accessrestrict id="ref177">
      <head>Access Restrictions</head>
      <p>There are no access restrictions.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="ref178">
      <head>Use Restrictions</head>
      <p>There are no restrictions on personal use. Permission to publish material from the C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection must be obtained from Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University Libraries.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="ref180">
      <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection, C0213, Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University Libraries.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="ref181">
      <head>Acquisition Information</head>
      <p>Collection donated by Betty Hart Mann in 1979.</p>
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="ref182">
      <head>Processing Information</head>
      <p>Processed by Special Collections and Archives staff. EAD markup completed in July 2012 by Greta Kuriger.</p>
    </processinfo>
    <altformavail id="ref185">
      <head>Alternative Form Available</head>
      <p>Selections from the C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection are also available in the 
                <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Digitized Map Collection" xlink:href=" http://digilib.gmu.edu:8080/dspace/handle/1920/1935"/>.</p>
    </altformavail>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">America--Discovery and exploration-Maps.</geogname>
        <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Virginia--Maps.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Document Types:</head>
        <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="gmgpc">Maps.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc>
      <head>Contents List
	</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>C. Harrison Mann, Jr. Map Collection</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 id="ref2" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Virginiae Tabula</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323016" type="Folder" label="Maps">1</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1660</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref3">
            <p>New Virginia Map published ca. 1660 by Joan Blaeu (1597-1663) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 20.125 in. x 24.25 in. (51.12 cm x 62.23 cm). Map depicting seventeenth-century Virginia. Titlepiece in upper center. Vignettes of Chief Powhatan in upper left and Native American figure in upper right below explanatory note. This image is based upon the 1608 map by Captain John Smith.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Nova Virginiae Tabula" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1962">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Nova Virginiae Tabula, circa 1660 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref4" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginiae Partis Australis et Floridae Partis Orientalis, Interjacentiumq, Region Nova Descripto</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323017" type="Folder" label="Maps">2</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref5">
            <p>Map of Virginia and Florida published ca. 1640 by Willem Janszoon Blaeu (1571-1638) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 21.4 in. x 16.9 in. (54.35 cm x 42.93 cm). Map depicts seventeenth-century Virginia and parts of the southeast Atlantic coast. Large cartouche featuring Native American figures in upper center surrounding titlepiece. Smaller heraldic items in upper right and center of map. Cartouche featuring cherubs surrounds mileage chart in bottom center right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Virginiae Partis Australis et Floridae Partis Orientalis, Interjacentiumq, Region Nova Descripto" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1971">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Virginiae Partis Australis et Floridae Partis Orientalis, Interjacentiumq, Region Nova Descripto, circa 1640 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref6" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Map of Virginia and Maryland Sold by Thomas Basset in Fleetstreet and Richard Chiswell in St Paul's Churchyard (1)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323018" type="Folder" label="Maps">3</container>
            <unitdate>1676</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref7">
            <p>By Francis Lamb. Copper plate engraving, color. 20.7 in. x 17 in. (52.57 cm x 43.18 cm). Map depicting seventeenth-century Virginia, Maryland and part of New Jersey. Titlepiece in upper right with cartouche featuring angelic figures. Heraldic symbol with crown in upper left just above scale.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref8" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Virginiae Tabula</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323019" type="Folder" label="Maps">4</container>
            <unitdate>1671</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref10">
            <p>New Virginia Map by Arnoldis Montanus. Published in Amsterdam in 1671. Copper plate engraving, black and white. 19.3 in. x 16.28 in. (49 cm x 41.35 cm). Map depicts seventeenth-century Virginia. Titlepiece in upper right adorned with images of cherubs. Heraldic image in upper center and Explanatory Note in upper right adorned with figures of Native Americans and animals. Scale in bottom center is also surrounded by cherub figures.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Nova Virginiae Tabula" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1973">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Nova Virginiae Tabula, 1671 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref11" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Map of Virginia and Maryland Sold by Thomas Basset in Fleetstreet and Richard Chiswell in St Paul's Churchyard (2)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323020" type="Folder" label="Maps">5</container>
            <unitdate>1676</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref13">
            <p>By Francis Lamb. Copper plate engraving, color. 20.7 in. x 17 in. (52.57 cm x 43.18 cm). Map depicting seventeenth-century Virginia, Maryland, and part of New Jersey. Titlepiece in upper right with cartouche featuring angelic figures. Heraldic symbol with crown in upper left just above scale. This Map has slightly different coloration than Map 3.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A Map of Virginia and Maryland Sold by Thomas Basset in Fleetstreet and Richard Chiswell in St Paul's Churchyard (2)" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1974">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A Map of Virginia and Maryland Sold by Thomas Basset in Fleetstreet and Richard Chiswell in St Paul's Churchyard (2), 1676 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref14" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Belgica et Anglia Nova</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323021" type="Folder" label="Maps">6</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1662</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref15">
            <p>New Belgium and New England published ca. 1662 by Joan Blaeu (1597-1663) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 24.3 in. x 20.45 in. (61.72 cm x 51.94 cm). Map depicts seventeenth-century New Belgium, New England, and New Netherland. Titlepiece is middle right and decorated with images of Native Americans, heraldic symbol, and crown. Scale is in bottom left and decorated with images of children. Other artwork in the map include vignettes of stockade-fenced settlements, animals, and ships.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Nova Belgica et Anglia Nova" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1975">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Nova Belgica et Anglia Nova, circa 1662 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref16" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A New Map of Virginia, Maryland, and the Improved Parts of Pennsylvania and New Jersey</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323022" type="Folder" label="Maps">7</container>
            <unitdate>1719</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref17">
            <p>Map of Virginia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, and New Jersey by John Senex (1678-1740) published 1719 in London. Copper plate engraving, color. 24 in. x 20 in. (60.96 cm x 50.8 cm). Map depicts Virginia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, and New Jersey. Titlepiece in upper left. Scale in lower right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A New Map of Virginia, Maryland, and the Improved Parts of Pennsylvania and New Jersey" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1976">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A New Map of Virginia, Maryland, and the Improved Parts of Pennsylvania and New Jersey, 1719 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref18" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Northeast Coast - Pas Caert van Nieu Nederlandt en du Engelsche Virginies</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323023" type="Folder" label="Maps">8</container>
            <unitdate>1668</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref19">
            <p>Peter Goos. 17x21.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref20" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia Marylandia et Carolina in America Septentrionali</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323024" type="Folder" label="Maps">9</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1740</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref21">
            <p>Homann. 20x23.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref22" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia and Maryland</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323025" type="Folder" label="Maps">10</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1700</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref23">
            <p>Map of Virginia and Maryland by Herman Moll (1654-1732). Published in London ca. 1700. Copper plate Engraving, color. 9.5 in. x 13.85 in. (24.14 cm x 35.18 cm). Map depicts Virginia, Maryland and parts of southern New Jersey. Unadorned titlepiece in upper left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Virginia and Maryland" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1977">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Virginia and Maryland, circa 1700 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref24" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carte de la Virginie et du Maryland</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323026" type="Folder" label="Maps">11</container>
            <unitdate>1755</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref25">
            <p>Map of Virginia and Maryland by Gilles Robert de Vaugondy (1688-1766) published in 1755. Copper plate engraving, color. 31.75 in x 21.5 in (80.64 cm x 54.61 cm). Map depicting Virginia, Maryland, and parts of Pennsylvania and Delaware. Titlepiece and scale in bottom right has cartouche of flora.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Carte de la Virginie et du Maryland" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1978">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Carte de la Virginie et du Maryland, 1755 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref26" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The State of Virginia from the Best Authorities</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323027" type="Folder" label="Maps">12</container>
            <unitdate>1794</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref27">
            <p>State of Virginia Map by Samuel Lewis, Philadelphia. Copper plate engraving, black and white. 21.3 in. x 16.9 in. (54.1 cm x 42.9 cm). Map depicting Virginia, the Northwest Territory, and parts of Maryland. Titlepiece with scale in upper left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="The State of Virginia from the Best Authorities" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1979">
            <daodesc>
              <p>The State of Virginia from the Best Authorities, 1794 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref28" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map and Chart of parts of Bay of Chesapeake York and James River which are at Present the Seat of War</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323028" type="Folder" label="Maps">13</container>
            <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref29">
            <p>Unidentified. 10x15.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref30" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A New and Accurate Map of Virginia and Maryland</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323029" type="Folder" label="Maps">14</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1752</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref31">
            <p>Map of Virginia and Maryland by Emmanuel Bowen. Copper plate engraving, color. 9.75 in. x 16 in. (24.76 cm x 40.64 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century Virginia, Maryland, and part of New Jersey. Titlepiece and scale are in bottom right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A New and Accurate Map of Virginia and Maryland" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1980">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A New and Accurate Map of Virginia and Maryland, circa 1752 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref32" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Terrae-Marie Tabula</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323030" type="Folder" label="Maps">15</container>
            <unitdate>1671</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref33">
            <p>New Map of Maryland by John Ogilby (1600-1676). Copper plate engraving, color. 20.15 in. x 16.21 in. (51.18 cm x 41.17 cm). Map depicts seventeenth-century Maryland and parts of both Virginia, and New Jersey. Ornate Titlepiece is in top center of map. Dedication, adorned with the coat of arms of Lord Baltimore, is in the upper right, and scale in lower left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Nova Terrae-Marie Tabula" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1966">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Nova Terrae-Marie Tabula, 1671 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref34" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez Pierre Schenk sur le vygendam, al' Atlas de Sanson Avec Privilege 1708</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323031" type="Folder" label="Maps">16</container>
            <unitdate>1708</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref35">
            <p>Map of North America by Pierre Schenk (1660-1718) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 25 in. x 20.5 in. (63.5 cm x 52.07 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century North America. European territorial possessions are colored in. Ornately decorated titlepiece featuring mythological sea creatures is in upper right. Advertisement and scale are in upper left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez Pierre Schenk sur le vygendam, al' Atlas de Sanson Avec Privilege 1708" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1981">
            <daodesc>
              <p>L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez Pierre Schenk sur le vygendam, al' Atlas de Sanson Avec Privilege 1708, 1708 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref36" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Harbor at Cadiz</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323032" type="Folder" label="Maps">17</container>
            <unitdate>1585</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref37">
            <p>Ortelius. 19x23.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref38" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of the World (unidentified)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323033" type="Folder" label="Maps">18</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1680</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref39">
            <p>Copper plate engraving, color. 8 in. x 11 in (20.32 cm x 27.94 cm). Map depicting the world's continents as seen from the vantage point of the North Pole. No identification, though "1680" penciled-in on verso.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Map of the World (unidentified)" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1968">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Map of the World (unidentified), circa 1680 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref40" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Americae Sive Novi Orbis, Nova Descripto</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323034" type="Folder" label="Maps">19</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref41">
            <p>America or New World Newly Described by Abraham Ortelius (1528-1598). Copper plate engraving, black and white. 20.25 in x 15.6 in (51.43 cm x 39.62 cm). Map of North and South America. Ornately decorated titlepiece in lower left and sailing ships in center.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Americae Sive Novi Orbis, Nova Descripto" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1969">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Americae Sive Novi Orbis, Nova Descripto, circa 1640 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref42" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Insulae Americanae in Oceano Septentrionali cum Terris Adiacentibus</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323035" type="Folder" label="Maps">20</container>
            <unitdate>circa late 1500s - early 1600s</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref43">
            <p>Map of Caribbean islands and Gulf of Mexico by Willem Janszoon Blaeu (1571-1638) of Amsterdam. Copperplate engraving, color. 23 in. x 19.25 in. (58.42 cm x 48.89 cm). Map depicting Gulf of Mexico and Caribbean Islands and parts of North, South, and Central America. Titlepiece in upper left flanked by cherubs. Ornate dedication in lower left and scale in lower right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Insulae Americanae in Oceano Septentrionali cum Terris Adiacentibus" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1967">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Insulae Americanae in Oceano Septentrionali cum Terris Adiacentibus, circa late 1500s - early 1600s </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref1" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>America</unittitle>
            <container id="cid323036" type="Folder" label="Maps">21</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1710</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref44">
            <p>Map of North and South America by Herman Moll (1654-1732), London. Copper plate engraving, color. 9 in. x 14 in. (22.86 cm x 35.56 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century North and South America. Titlepiece in top left of map.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="America" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1983">
            <daodesc>
              <p>America, circa 1710 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref45" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez I. Covens et C. Mortimer. Avec Privilege</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324004" type="Folder" label="Maps">22</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1740</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref46">
            <p>Map of North and Central America by Guillame Delisle (1675-1726) of Paris. Copper plate engraving, color. 21 in x 25 in (53.34 cm x 63.5 cm). Map depicting the eastern part of North America and Central America. Ornately decorated titlepiece in upper left featuring mythical sea figures and scale in upper right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez I. Covens et C. Mortimer. Avec Privilege" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1984">
            <daodesc>
              <p>L'Amerique Septentrionale. Dressee sur les Observations de Mrs. de l'Academie Royale des Sciences &amp; quelques autres, &amp; sur les Memoires les plus recens. Par G. De L' Isle Geographie a Amsterdam chez I. Covens et C. Mortimer. Avec Privilege, circa 1740 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref47" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The United States of North America with the British Territories and those of Spain, according to the Treaty of 1784. Engraved by Wm Faden</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324005" type="Folder" label="Maps">23</container>
            <unitdate>1796</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref48">
            <p>Map of the United States by William Faden (1750-1836). Published 1796 in London. Copper plate engraving, color. 23 in. x 31 in. (58.42 cm x 78.74 cm). Map depicts the eighteenth-century United States of America and parts of Canada. Titlepiece in bottom right is decorated with images having to do with shipping and trade. Scale is in bottom left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="The United States of North America with the British Territories and those of Spain, according to the Treaty of 1784. Engraved by Wm Faden" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1985">
            <daodesc>
              <p>The United States of North America with the British Territories and those of Spain, according to the Treaty of 1784. Engraved by Wm Faden, 1796 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref49" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Draught of Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324006" type="Folder" label="Maps">24</container>
            <unitdate>1758</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref50">
            <p>Map of Chesapeake Bay Area of Virginia, Mark Tiddeman, London. Copper plate engraving, color. 19 in. x 23.5 in. (48.26 cm x 59.69 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century Tidewater and Chesapeake Bay area of Virginia. Titlepiece in bottom left. Scale is in bottom center.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A Draught of Virginia" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1986">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A Draught of Virginia, 1758 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref51" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A New Map of North America from the Latest Discoveries</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324008" type="Folder" label="Maps">25</container>
            <unitdate>1763</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref52">
            <p>Map of North America, J. Spillsbury, London. Copper plate engraving, color. 11 in. x 15 in. (27.94 cm x 38.1 cm). Eighteenth-century map depicting North America. Titlepiece is in bottom right. European territorial claims are delineated by colored outlining.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A New Map of North America fron the Latest Discoveries" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/1987">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A New Map of North America fron the Latest Discoveries, 1763 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref53" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Map of the British American Plantations Extending from Boston in New England to Georgia; Including all the Back Settlements in the Respective Provinces, as far as the Mississippi</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324009" type="Folder" label="Maps">26</container>
            <unitdate>July 1754</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref54">
            <p>Map of American Colonies by Thomas Bowen (1700-1763), London. Copper plate engraving, color. 9 in. x 12 in. (22.86 cm x 30.48 cm). Map depicting the eighteenth-century American colonies. Titlepiece in lower right flanked by images of Native Americans. Scale in middle right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="A Map of the British American Plantations Extending from Boston in New England to Georgia; Including all the Back Settlements in the Respective Provinces, as far as the Mississippi" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2012">
            <daodesc>
              <p>A Map of the British American Plantations Extending from Boston in New England to Georgia; Including all the Back Settlements in the Respective Provinces, as far as the Mississippi, July 1754 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref55" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>North America. Performed under the Patronage of Louis Duke of Orleans, First Prince of the Blood; by the Sieur D'Anville. Greatly Improved by Mr. Bolton. Engraved by R.W. Seale, MDCCLII</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324012" type="Folder" label="Maps">27</container>
            <unitdate>1752</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref56">
            <p>Map of North America by Simon Bolton and engraved by R.W. Seale. Copper plate engraving, color. 21 in. x 26 in. (53.34 cm x 66.04 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century British and French North America. Large decorated titlepiece in lower right adorned with images of cherubs, a Native American figure, animals, and plants.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="North America. Performed under the Patronage of Louis Duke of Orleans, First Prince of the Blood; by the Sieur D'Anville. Greatly Improved by Mr. Bolton. Engraved by R.W. Seale, MDCCLII" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2045">
            <daodesc>
              <p>North America. Performed under the Patronage of Louis Duke of Orleans, First Prince of the Blood; by the Sieur D'Anville. Greatly Improved by Mr. Bolton. Engraved by R.W. Seale, MDCCLII, 1752 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref57" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Orbis Tabula in Lucem Edita</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324014" type="Folder" label="Maps">28</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1670</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref58">
            <p>New Map of the World, by A. F. De wit. Copper plate engraving, color. 19 in. x 23 in. (48.26 cm x 58.42 cm). Seventeenth-century map of the world depicting the eastern and western hemispheres surrounded by images of the seasons, elements, and mythological figures.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Nova Orbis Tabula in Lucem Edita" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2029">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Nova Orbis Tabula in Lucem Edita, circa 1670 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref59" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mappe Monde qui Represente les deux Hemispheres Savoir celui de l'Orient et celui l'Occident tire'e des Quatre Cartes Generales de feu M. Le Professeur Hafius. Ir effe'e par G.M. Lowitz, et Publie'e par les Heritiers se Homann l'An 1746</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324016" type="Folder" label="Maps">29</container>
            <unitdate>1746</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref60">
            <p>World map showing eastern and western hemispheres, G.M. Lowitz. Copper plate engraving, color. 20 in. x 24 in. (49 cm x 41.35 cm). Eighteenth-century map depicting the eastern and western hemispheres of the world. Titlepieces in both upper left (Latin) and upper right (French) adorned with images of flora and fauna. Map has four insets, which depict the Arctic, Antarctic, Horizon of Nuremburg, and the Antipodes of Nuremburg.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Mappe Monde qui Represente les deux Hemispheres Savoir celui de l'Orient et celui l'Occident tire'e des Quatre Cartes Generales de feu M. Le Professeur Hafius. Ir effe'e par G.M. Lowitz, et Publie'e par les Heritiers se Homann l'An 1746" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2046">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Mappe Monde qui Represente les deux Hemispheres Savoir celui de l'Orient et celui l'Occident tire'e des Quatre Cartes Generales de feu M. Le Professeur Hafius. Ir effe'e par G.M. Lowitz, et Publie'e par les Heritiers se Homann l'An 1746, 1746 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref61" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Asiac Nova Descripto</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324017" type="Folder" label="Maps">30</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref62">
            <p>Blaeu. 17x21.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref63" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Englalond Anglia Anglosaonvm Heptarchia Terra Armis Animisqve Potens</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324019" type="Folder" label="Maps">31</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1607</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref64">
            <p>Map of England and part of Scotland by Guliel Hole (d. 1624). Copper plate engraving, color. 12 in. x 13 in. (30.48 cm x 33.02 cm). Seventeenth-century map of England and Scotland. Titlepiece in upper right adorned with ornate cartouche featuring a crown and colorful embellishments. Large compass rose in lower left.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Englalond Anglia Anglosaonvm Heptarchia Terra Armis Animisqve Potens" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2097">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Englalond Anglia Anglosaonvm Heptarchia Terra Armis Animisqve Potens, circa 1607 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref65" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Vectis Insula Anglice: The Isle of Wight</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324021" type="Folder" label="Maps">32</container>
            <unitdate>1648</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref66">
            <p>Map of the Isle of Wight, Joan Bleau (1597-1663) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 20 in. x 24 in. (50.8 cm x 60.96 cm). Seventeenth-century map of the Isle of Wight off the southern English coast. Title piece in lower left has cartouche featuring a coat of arms, and animals. Scale, adorned with globe, in lower right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Vectis Insula Anglice: The Isle of Wight" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2098">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Vectis Insula Anglice: The Isle of Wight, 1648 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref67" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hantshire</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324022" type="Folder" label="Maps">33</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref68">
            <p>Bleau. 20x24.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref69" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Dorset</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324023" type="Folder" label="Maps">34</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref70">
            <p>Blaeu. 20x24.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref71" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>England and Wales</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324024" type="Folder" label="Maps">35</container>
            <unitdate>1750</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref72">
            <p>John Rocque. 40x50. London. Two sheets.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref73" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Wigornmiensis Comitatus Cum Warwicensi, Nec Non Conventriae Libertas (Warwick, England)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324025" type="Folder" label="Maps">36</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1646</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref74">
            <p>Map of Warwickshire, England published ca. 1646 by Joan Blaeu (1597-1663) of Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 20 in. x 25 in. (50.8 cm x 63.5 cm). Map depicting seventeenth-century Warwickshire, England. Titlepiece in bottom left decorated with cartouche of fruits and flowers. Coats of arms in top left and bottom right, and scale in top right.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Wigornmiensis Comitatus Cum Warwicensi, Nec Non Conventriae Libertas (Warwick, England)" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2269">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Wigornmiensis Comitatus Cum Warwicensi, Nec Non Conventriae Libertas (Warwick, England), circa 1646 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref75" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carte Reduite de L'Ocean Occidental</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324026" type="Folder" label="Maps">37</container>
            <unitdate>1766</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref76">
            <p>Bellin. 23x36. Paris.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref77" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>From D'Anville (World)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324027" type="Folder" label="Maps">38</container>
            <unitdate>1788</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref78">
            <p>I. Harrison. 21x32. Two sheet map.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref79" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Hemisphere Occidental, Dressee en 1720 pour l'usage Particular du Roy sur les Observations Astronomiques et Geographiques Raportees la meme Annee vans l'Histoire et vans les Memoires de l'Acemie Rle. des Sciences Par Guillaume de l'Isle Premier Geographahe de sa Majeste' de la meme Academie</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324029" type="Folder" label="Maps">39</container>
            <unitdate>1720</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref80">
            <p>Map of the Western Hemisphere published by J. Covens and C. Mortimer in Amsterdam. Copper plate engraving, color. 20 in. x 20 in. (50.8 cm x 50.8 cm). Map depicting eighteenth-century Western Hemisphere (North and South America and Pacific islands). Title in upper part of map. European territorial holdings are outlined in color.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Hemisphere Occidental, Dressee en 1720 pour l'usage Particular du Roy sur les Observations Astronomiques et Geographiques Raportees la meme Annee vans l'Histoire et vans les Memoires de l'Acemie Rle. des Sciences Par Guillaume de l'Isle Premier Geographahe de sa Majeste' de la meme Academie" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2268">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Hemisphere Occidental, Dressee en 1720 pour l'usage Particular du Roy sur les Observations Astronomiques et Geographiques Raportees la meme Annee vans l'Histoire et vans les Memoires de l'Acemie Rle. des Sciences Par Guillaume de l'Isle Premier Geographahe de sa Majeste' de la meme Academie, 1720 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref81" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>St. Christopher's Island</unittitle>
            <container id="cid324030" type="Folder" label="Maps">40</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1800</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref82">
            <p>Unidentified. 19x24.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref83" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Granada</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325001" type="Folder" label="Maps">41</container>
            <unitdate>1778</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref84">
            <p>Unidentified. 21x24. Paris.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref85" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Isle of St. Vincent</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325002" type="Folder" label="Maps">42</container>
            <unitdate>1778</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref86">
            <p>LaRouge. 21x29. Paris.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref87" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>British Isles</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325003" type="Folder" label="Maps">43</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1850</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref88">
            <p>From Pinkerton's Atlas. 24x40. London.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref89" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Roads from Chelmsford in Essex to Maldon, Raleigh in Essex [and] Gravesend in Kent</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325004" type="Folder" label="Maps">44</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1675</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref90">
            <p>Map of roads between Chelmsford and Dover, England published by John Ogilby (1600-1676). Copper plate engraving, color. 15 in. x 18 in. (38.1 cm x 45.72 cm). Map depicts seventeenth-century road from Chelmsford to Dover, England. Titlepiece is in top center of map with a cartouche of mythological sea creatures and figures.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="The Roads from Chelmsford in Essex to Maldon, Raleigh in Essex [and] Gravesend in Kent" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2270">
            <daodesc>
              <p>The Roads from Chelmsford in Essex to Maldon, Raleigh in Essex [and] Gravesend in Kent, circa 1675 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref91" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Road from London to Cambridge, Ely, &amp; Kings Lynn, from Oxford to Cambridge, passing [through] Buckingham &amp; Bedford</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325009" type="Folder" label="Maps">45</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1720</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref92">
            <p>Map of road from London to Bury, England by J. Gibson and published circa 1720. Copper plate engraving, color. 7 in. x 12 in. (17.78 cm x 30.48 cm). Map depicts eighteenth-century road from London to Bury, England. Title runs entire length of map at top. Road is divided into ten numbered columns and towns and mileages are labeled.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="The Road from London to Cambridge, Ely, &amp; Kings Lynn, from Oxford to Cambridge, passing [through] Buckingham &amp; Bedford" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2271">
            <daodesc>
              <p>The Road from London to Cambridge, Ely, &amp; Kings Lynn, from Oxford to Cambridge, passing [through] Buckingham &amp; Bedford, circa 1720 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref93" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Vrbium Londoni et West Monasterii nec non Suburbii Southwark Accurata Ichnographia, in qua Vie Publicae Omnes et Fingulae, etc. (Map of London)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325010" type="Folder" label="Maps">46</container>
            <unitdate>1736</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref94">
            <p>2-sheet map of southern London by Christophe Homan (1703-30) and published 1736. Copper plate engraving, color. 25 in. x 31 in. (63.5 cm x 78.74 cm). 2-sheet map depicting eighteenth-century south London, England. Titlepiece in lower right with Lion and Unicorn Cartouche. Title of map is in Latin, while place and street names are in English. Other information is in German.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Vrbium Londoni et West Monasterii nec non Suburbii Southwark Accurata Ichnographia, in qua Vie Publicae Omnes et Fingulae, etc. (Map of London)" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2290">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Vrbium Londoni et West Monasterii nec non Suburbii Southwark Accurata Ichnographia, in qua Vie Publicae Omnes et Fingulae, etc. (Map of London), 1736 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Vrbium Londoni et West Monasterii nec non Suburbii Southwark Accurata Ichnographia, in qua Vie Publicae Omnes et Fingulae, etc. (Map of London)" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2291">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Vrbium Londoni et West Monasterii nec non Suburbii Southwark Accurata Ichnographia, in qua Vie Publicae Omnes et Fingulae, etc. (Map of London), 1736 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref95" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325011" type="Folder" label="Maps">47</container>
            <unitdate>1825</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref96">
            <p>Map of Virginia, Maryland and Delaware by Henry Schenck Tanner (1786 - 1858), Philadelphia. Engraving, color. 19 in. x 23 in. (48.26 cm x 58.42 cm). Nineteenth-century map depicting Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware. Titlepiece is in top center. Scale and Explanation are in bottom center. Counties within each state are colored, while bordering states are left white.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <dao xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="embed" xlink:title="Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware" xlink:role="jpg" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2030">
            <daodesc>
              <p>Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware, 1825 </p>
            </daodesc>
          </dao>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref97" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lot of 8 maps</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325008" type="Folder" label="Maps">48 a-h</container>
            <unitdate>1872</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref98">
            <p>Unidentified. 12x15. Includes: a) Virginia and Maryland, b) Texas, c) Arizona and New Mexica, d) Kentucky and Tennessee, e) Floriday, f) Georgia and Alabama, g) North and South Caroline, h) Baltimore, MD.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref99" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Map of the U.S. of A.</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325012" type="Folder" label="Maps">49</container>
            <unitdate>1794</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref100">
            <p>Wilkinson. 11x13. London.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref101" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>United States of America, Northern Part</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325013" type="Folder" label="Maps">50</container>
            <unitdate>1810</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref102">
            <p>Cadell and Davies. 23x30. London.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref103" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia and Maryland with latest improvements</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325014" type="Folder" label="Maps">51</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1838</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref104">
            <p>Unidentified. 9x11.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref105" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia, Delaware, Maryland, and West Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325015" type="Folder" label="Maps">52</container>
            <unitdate>1864</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref106">
            <p>A. J. Johnson. 18x26. New York.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref107" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia, Delaware, Maryland, and West Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331023" type="Folder" label="Maps">53</container>
            <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref108">
            <p>A. J. Johnson. 18x26. Same as item 52, but a different edition.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref109" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A New Map of Virginia with its Roads Canals and Distances</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325016" type="Folder" label="Maps">54</container>
            <unitdate>1853</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref110">
            <p>Cowperthwait. 14x17. Philadelphia.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref111" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Georgetown and the City of Washington</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325017" type="Folder" label="Maps">55</container>
            <unitdate>1855</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref112">
            <p>Cotton. 16x18. New York.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref113" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Georgetown and the City of Washington</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325018" type="Folder" label="Maps">56</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1865</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref114">
            <p>Johnson. 14x18. New York. Same as item 55.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref115" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325019" type="Folder" label="Maps">57</container>
            <unitdate>1855</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref116">
            <p>Colton. 16x18. New York.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref117" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Virginia and Maryland</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325020" type="Folder" label="Maps">58</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1830</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref118">
            <p>Seers &amp; Co. 11x16.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref119" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A Correct Map of Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325021" type="Folder" label="Maps">59</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1818</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref120">
            <p>Unidentified. 17x21.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref121" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>A New Map of Part of the U.S. of N. America</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325022" type="Folder" label="Maps">60</container>
            <unitdate>1828</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref122">
            <p>Cary. 21x24. London.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref123" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Geographical Statistical and Historical Map of Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325023" type="Folder" label="Maps">61</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1820</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref124">
            <p>Unidentified. 18x22.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref125" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Geographical Statistical and Historical Map of the District of Columbia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325024" type="Folder" label="Maps">62</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1820</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref126">
            <p>Unidentified. 18x22.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref127" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Johnson's Map of Vicinity of Richmond and the Peninsular Campaign</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325025" type="Folder" label="Maps">63</container>
            <unitdate>1862</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref128">
            <p>Unidentified. 18x27. New York.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref129" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Plan of the City of Washington</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325026" type="Folder" label="Maps">64</container>
            <unitdate>post 1800</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref130" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Tabula Geographica Principatus Anhaltini et Finitionaum Regionum</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325027" type="Folder" label="Maps">65</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1680</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref131">
            <p>Begin. 15x17.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref132" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lisbona</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325028" type="Folder" label="Maps">66</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1740</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref133">
            <p>Seutter. 221x25. Pictorial map with scene of burning of Lisbon.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref134" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Topographical Map of the District of Columbia with the Fortification around the City (Civil War)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325030" type="Folder" label="Maps">67</container>
            <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref135">
            <p>Unidentified. 16x32.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref155" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of the State of Virginia Reduced from the Nine Sheet Map of the State in Conformity to Law</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331002" type="Folder" label="Maps">68</container>
            <unitdate>1827</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref156">
            <p>Herman Boye. 31x50. Example of the first official map of Virginia backed with cloth in slip case.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref157" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Campaign Maps (Civil War)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331003" type="Folder" label="Maps">69</container>
            <unitdate>1867</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref158">
            <p>Major J.E. Wayes. 22x25. New York. Maps include 1) Petersburg and Five Forks, 2) Antietam, 3) Spotsylvania Courthouse, and 4) Richmond; folded maps each with a hard cover. In 2 folders.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref159" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of the Battlefield of Fredericksburgh (Civil War)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331004" type="Folder" label="Maps">70</container>
            <unitdate>1866</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref160">
            <p>Blackford. 20x24. Baltimore. Folded map with hard cover.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref136" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Tourist's Pocket Map of the State of Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325029" type="Folder" label="Maps">71</container>
            <unitdate>1835</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref137">
            <p>Young. 13x16. Philadelphia.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref161" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of the States of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331005" type="Folder" label="Maps">72</container>
            <unitdate>1834</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref162">
            <p>Mitchell (publisher). 22x18. Philadelphia. Folding traveler's map in red morocco folder (3x5); map torn in folds, folder chipped and rubbed. In the same folder as item 70.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref183" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Darien</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331024" type="Folder" label="Maps">73</container>
            <unitdate>1698</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref184">
            <p>By Richard Long. 21x25. Manuscript map on parchment showing the future site of the Scottish Colony near Panama which existed from 1698 to 1699, when it was captured by the Spanish Army. Darien was to be the Scottish Jamestown and was part of the British effort to expand southward into the Caribbean. The few survivors found refuge in Jamaica.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref138" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Norumbega et Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325031" type="Folder" label="Maps">74</container>
            <unitdate>1597</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref139">
            <p>Wytfliet. 9x12. Louvon.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref140" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Angliae Regni...(England)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325032" type="Folder" label="Maps">75</container>
            <unitdate>1573</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref141">
            <p>Ortelius. 17x21. Map from early atlas.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref142" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Nova Virginia Tabula</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325033" type="Folder" label="Maps">76</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1620</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref143">
            <p>Hondius. 19x23. Hondius edition of John Smith map of 1608.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref144" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Title page from Blaeu Atlas</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325034" type="Folder" label="Maps">77</container>
            <unitdate>1640</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref145">
            <p>12x19. Amsterdam.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref146" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Engraving of Ceremonies of Virginia and the King of Pegu</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325035" type="Folder" label="Maps">78</container>
            <unitdate>circa 1650</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref147">
            <p>Leide. 15x19.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref148" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of N. E. Virginia and vicinity of Washington</unittitle>
            <container id="cid325036" type="Folder" label="Maps">79</container>
            <unitdate>1862</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent id="ref149">
            <p>27x29. Washington D.C.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref163" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Delaware</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331006" type="Folder" label="Maps">84</container>
            <unitdate>1796</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref164" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Arlington and Vicinity (street indexed)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331007" type="Folder" label="Maps">85</container>
            <unitdate>1955</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref165" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of the City of Richmond, Virginia, 1861-1865</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331008" type="Folder" label="Maps">86</container>
            <unitdate>1961</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref166" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mineral Industries and Resources of Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331009" type="Folder" label="Maps">87</container>
            <unitdate>1959</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref167" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Present Richmond, Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331010" type="Folder" label="Maps">88</container>
            <unitdate>1961</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref168" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The New World</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331011" type="Folder" label="Maps">89</container>
            <unitdate>Reproduction of map from 1600</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref169" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>The Oldest Map of the New World</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331012" type="Folder" label="Maps">90</container>
            <unitdate>Reproduction of map from 1493-1496</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref170" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Alexandria Quadrangle, Virginia - District of Columbia - Maryland</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331013" type="Folder" label="Maps">91</container>
            <unitdate>1951</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref171" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Washington and Vicinity</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331014" type="Folder" label="Maps">92</container>
            <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref172" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>County of Arlington Virginia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331015" type="Folder" label="Maps">93</container>
            <unitdate>July 15, 1950</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref173" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lyon Park, 1,000 Lots and Acreage (of Clarendon, Virginia)</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331016" type="Folder" label="Maps">94</container>
            <unitdate>June 1, 1920</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 id="ref174" level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Map of Alexandria County, Virginia Formerly Part of the District of Columbia</unittitle>
            <container id="cid331017" type="Folder" label="Maps">95</container>
            <unitdate>July 1907</unitdate>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
