<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/gmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/gmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/gmu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vifgm00004">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//George Mason University::Fenwick Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViFGM::vifgm00004::A Guide to Porgy and Bess: A Contemporary Collection of Posters from the1950s)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vifgm00004.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViFGM">PUBLIC "-//George
             Mason University::Fenwick Library::Special Collections and
             Archives//TEXT (US::ViFGM::vifgm00004::A Guide to Porgy
             and Bess: A Contemporary Collection of Posters from the
             1950s)//EN" "vifgm00004.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to Porgy and Bess: A Contemporary
            Collection of Posters from the 1950s</titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Porgy and Bess: A Contemporary
            Collection of Posters from the 1950s 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Porgy and Bess
            001</num></subtitle>
            <author>Special Collections Staff</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Copyright George Mason University
            Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Special Collections &amp;
               Archives</addressline>
               <addressline>Fenwick Library (2FL)</addressline>
               <addressline>George Mason University</addressline>
               <addressline>Fairfax, Virginia 22030-4444</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (703) 993-2220</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (703) 993-2669</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: speccoll@gmu.edu</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2000 By Copyright
            George Mason University Libraries.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">22 Kb</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from ProCite
         database 
         <date>2000</date></creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-19">Feb 19, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//George Mason University::Fenwick
            Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT
            (US::ViFGM::vifgm00004::A Guide to Porgy and Bess: A
            Contemporary Collection of Posters from the 1950s)//EN"
            "vifgm00004.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to Porgy and Bess: A contemporary
         Collection of Posters from the 1950s 
         <date>2000</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections and Archives 
         <num type="Collection Number">Porgy and Bess
         001</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>George Mason University Libraries</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2000</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>Fenwick Library (2FL)</item>
            <item>George Mason University</item>
            <item>Fairfax, Virginia 22030-4444</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (703) 993-2220</item>
            <item>Fax: (703) 993-2669</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:speccoll@gmu.edu">
            speccoll@gmu.edu</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections">
            http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives,
      George Mason University Libraries</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Special Collections and Archives, George Mason
         University</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Porgy and Bess: A Collection of
         Posters from the 1950s</unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">Porgy and Bess 001</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">60
         posters</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Porgy and Bess: A Collection of Posters from the 1950s,
            Special Collections &amp; Archives, George Mason University
            Libraries</p>
         </prefercite>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Porgy and Bess was a three act "folk Opera" produced by The
         Theatre Guild at the Alvin Theatre, New York City, in 1927.
         The Opera was taken directly from a book by Dubose Heyward
         titled Porgy, with lyrics and music by Ira and George
         Gershwin. The opera revolves around Porgy, a
         physically-challenged African-American black beggar who lives
         and works in a Charleston tenement called Catfish Row and who
         loves the beautiful but weak-willed Bess. Bess is the mistress
         of the vicious Crown, but when Crown flees after murdering a
         man, she goes to live with Porgy. On Crown's return porgy
         fights with him and kills him. Porgy is taken to jail, and
         while there Bess is lured away by the drug peddler, Sportin'
         Life. When Porgy gets out of jail, he leaves Catfish Row to
         find Bess. This is where the play ends. The play remains one
         of the greatest of all American folk dramas.</p>
         <p>Robert Breen was the first Person to arrange postwar United
         States and Soviet cultural "changes. He also helped to bring
         federal financing to the performing arts. His greatest success
         was on the international stage in 1952. He directed and
         co-produced with Blevins Davis the critically acclaimed
         revival of Porgy and Bess. It toured twenty-nine countries in
         four years. The following is a brief account of the opera's
         successful tours through North and South America and
         Europe.</p>
         <p>The United States performances began in Chicago and had a
         slow start because of the summer heat and the preoccupation
         with the Republican National Convention. But, before long the
         tour became a huge success. Critics called the performances of
         Porgy and Bess, "the best sung version yet,"' and by the end
         of their stay in Chicago the cast was performing to standing
         room only crowds.</p>
         <p>From Chicago, the troupe traveled to Vienna, Austria for
         the opening of their European tour on September 7, 1952. In
         the past, Vienna had never been very receptive to American
         opera, but after Porgy and Bess, attitudes changed
         dramatically. The crowds went wild: they had never seen
         anything like it before in a theater. The next stop was Berlin
         and there, too, the audiences loved Porgy and Bess. It became
         the main event for a month-long festival. The reactions of the
         audiences were extraordinary, even though many could not
         understand what was being spoken or sung.</p>
         <p>Europeans were not the only ones to notice the amazing
         success of Porgy and Bess. In the United States people were
         also taking notice of Porgy and Bess, including President
         Dwight Eisenhower. He created an emergency fund with an annual
         appropriation of five million dollars. This fund was used to
         finance and promote "American" cultural activities, such as
         Porgy and Bess. Half the money went to theater productions.
         The economics of production demanded full houses, so when
         there was a period of empty seats in Europe, Billy Rose
         proposed bringing the tour home to the United States. But
         before going home, they traveled to Paris for one last
         performance. The reactions were the same as in Vienna and
         Berlin. Gendarmes were needed to keep those without tickets
         from crashing the gates. Critics called Porgy and Bess, "A
         masterpiece ... one doesn't have to say more. ,2 After Paris,
         the troupe returned to perform at the Ziegfeld Theatre in New
         York City. While there, the cast performed 305 shows and while
         still in New York, the popularity of Porgy and Bess picked up
         in Europe. The troupe was invited to revisit Paris, intending
         to stay only three weeks, but demand kept the opera performing
         for an additional seven weeks. From Paris, the opera moved to
         Zagreb, Yugoslavia. This was the first time American singers
         were invited behind the Iron Curtain.</p>
         <p>Their next stop was Egypt, first Alexandria and then Cairo.
         The first performance in Alexandria was on New Year's Eve, and
         critics were skeptical about the shows success, but the cast
         played to a packed house, while hundreds more were turned
         away. From Alexandria, they traveled to Cairo, where, once
         again, they were a huge success. Next, the troupe traveled to
         Tel Aviv, Israel, where they performed eight shows at the
         Habimah Theatre. People literally tackled the ticket takers so
         that they could get inside the theater.</p>
         <p>From Israel, the opera traveled to Barcelona, Spain. Here,
         they performed for ten days, and critics called Porgy and Bess
         "the best thing seen in Barcelona in twenty years."' From
         there they traveled to Italy, first to Milan and the
         world-renowned Teatro Alla Scala. For many in the cast it was
         a lifelong dream to perform in the Teatro Alla Scala. They did
         not let anyone down -- they performed as never before. It was
         the first time an American company had been invited to one of
         the world's premier opera houses. After Milan, the cast
         performed in Genoa and Florence, Lausanne, Marseilles, and
         back to Italy to perform in Turin and Rome. After Italy, they
         traveled to Zurich, and finished this leg of the European tour
         in Brussels and Antwerp.</p>
         <p>The troupe then changed direction, traveling south to Rio
         de Janeiro, and Lima. The audiences in South America thought
         Porgy and Bess was a revelation, and worthy of unrestricted
         applause.</p>
         <p>From South America, they went to the Soviet Union, first
         Leningrad and then Moscow. There were some misunderstandings
         on opening night in Leningrad because audiences had trouble
         understanding things such as the buzzard over Porgy's abode
         and the open attitudes about sexual passion. The Russians
         appeared to suffer from culture shock. By the end of the
         Leningrad tour, however, the cast was once again a huge
         success and played to full houses and enthusiastic audiences.
         Next, they appeared in Moscow where the cast felt more
         comfortable because the theater audiences were more accepting
         than the ones in Leningrad. On the second night the cast was
         honored by the attendance of the three most important Soviet
         politicians: Nikita Khrushchev, Nikolai Bulganin, and
         Vyacheslav Molotov. This was a rare occurrence because the
         leaders rarely attended public performances: when they did, it
         had always been on the last night.</p>
         <p>The next stops were again behind the Iron Curtain, Warsaw,
         and Prague. The performances were a huge success and once
         again tickets sold out before the performances began. After
         the troupe left Warsaw and Prague, they traveled to Germany,
         where they performed in Munich, Stuttgart, Dtisseldorf, and
         Hamburg. From Germany they traveled to Rotterdam, Netherlands,
         Aachus, Denmark and back to the Netherlands, this time in
         Amsterdam, where the tour ended on June 3, 1956.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Posters are arranged alphabetically according to the
         country where the performances were held.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <dsc type="combined">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Porgy and Bess Posters</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome
                  Theatre</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>June 23-30, 1955</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>22"x14"; Vertical; black background with
                  yellow lettering; white squares with black lettering;
                  white border</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome
                  Theater</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>June 23-30,1955</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>34"x24"; Large black background with bright
                  yellow lettering; white squares with black lettering;
                  white border</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Antwerp, Belgium: Hippodrome
                  Theater</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>June 23-30,1955</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>31"x96"; Black background with white
                  squares and black lettering; large bright yellow
                  lettering in the middle of "Porgy and
                  Bess".</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Brussels, Belgium: Theatre de la
                  Monnaie</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>June 23-30,1955</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>32"x24"; Black background with white
                  squares and black lettering; off white border; large
                  lemon yellow letters in middle; yellow square at top
                  with black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: Brazil Teatro
                  Municipal</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>July 7-13,1955</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>60"x92"; Four pieces; bright red background
                  with off white border and white lettering inside of
                  it</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Prague, Czechoslovakia: Kerlin
                  Theatre</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>February 11-19,1956</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>34"x24"; Washed out off-white background;
                  small black lettering, larger bold red lettering; on
                  the left side there is a square with the words "Porgy
                  and Bess".</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Prague, Czechoslovakia: Kerlin
                  Theatre</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>February 11-19,1956</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>42"x31"; Salmon colored fibrous paper with
                  black charted lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Arhus, Denmark: Aarhushallen</unittitle>
                  <unitdate>May 9-16,1956</unitdate>
                  <physdesc>33"x25"; White background in middle with
                  lime-green lettering and black writing;black and
                  white photographs taken from characters and scenes of
                  the play act as the boder.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Alexandria, Egypt: Theatre Mohamad Aly 
                  <unitdate>December 31,1954-January 2,
                  1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>69"x36"; White background; blue border with
                  white starts; blue and red lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Alexandria, Egypt: Theatre Mohamad Aly 
                  <unitdate>December 31,1954-January 2,
                  1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>12"x8"; Small washed out cream-color
                  background; black border with red and black
                  lettering; two star illustrations on either
                  side</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Cairo, Egypt: Theatre De'L Opera 
                  <unitdate>January 7-12,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>11"x8"; Washed out brown background; red
                  and black lettering; four different
                  versions</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Cairo, Egypt: Theatre De'L Opera 
                  <unitdate>January 7-12, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>69"x36"; White background; blue star
                  border; blue and red lettering; Egyptian lettering at
                  top.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Marseilles, France: Opera Municpal 
                  <unitdate>March 26-April
                  4,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>18"x12"; Off-white background;red and blue
                  lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Marseilles, France: Opera Municpal 
                  <unitdate>March 26-April
                  4,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>55"x36"; Large; bright purple with black
                  lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire 
                  <unitdate>February 16-March
                  1,1953</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x16"; Green backround with black and
                  white lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire 
                  <unitdate>September 30-December
                  4,1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>64"x94",48"x34"; Large;green background
                  with large black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire 
                  <unitdate>September 30-December
                  4,1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x16"; Vertical;dark green background
                  with white border;large bold black
                  lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Paris, France: Theatre De'L Empire 
                  <unitdate>September 30-December
                  4,1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>59"x40",59"x37"; Green background; large
                  black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Berlin,Germany: Titania Palast 
                  <unitdate>September 18-27,1952</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>23"x33"; Off-white background with blue
                  sketch-like illustration of village; magenta and
                  black lettering through the center</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Dusseldorf,Germany: Apolla Theatre 
                  <unitdate>November 18-22,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x34"; Lemon yellow background with
                  orenge border on the top and bottom; orange and black
                  lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Dusseldorf,Germany: Apolla Theatre 
                  <unitdate>November 18-22,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x34"; White background with black
                  lettering; blue patch with Porgy and Bess written in
                  yellow in the middle</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Frankfort,Germany: Stadtischen Buhnen 
                  <unitdate>November 25-27,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x33"; White background with black
                  lettering; blue patch of color in middle with "Porgy
                  and Bess" written in bright yellow</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Franfort,Germany: Stadtischen Buhnen 
                  <unitdate>November 25-27,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>24"x34"; Lemon yellow background; black
                  border on sides; orange border on top and bottom;
                  black and orange lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Hamburg,Germany: Opera House 
                  <unitdate>March 7-11,1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>23"x33"; Brick colored border surrounding
                  off-white background; brick colored
                  lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Munich,Germany: Deutsches Theatre 
                  <unitdate>December 1-6,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>48"x33"; Black and white background with
                  large yellow, black, and white lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Munich,Germany: Deutsches Theatre 
                  <unitdate>February 22-29,1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>48"x33"; Two pieces; bright red background
                  with bright yellow lettering reading "Porgy and Bess"
                  across the front</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Stuttgart,Germany: Staats Theatre 
                  <unitdate>March 1-4,1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>51"x34"; Two pieces; black background with
                  large yellow lettering in the middle</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Tel Aviv,Israel: Habimah Theatre 
                  <unitdate>January 26-30,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>37"x25"; White background with blue border;
                  red and blue lettering; bigger letters in the middle
                  than in the rest of poster</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Florence,Italy: Teatro Comunale 
                  <unitdate>March 9-13,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>27"x13"; Vertical; off-white background
                  with red and black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Florence, Italy: Teatro Comunale 
                  <unitdate>March 9-13,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>48"x33";Mustart-yellow background with
                  black lettering;red lettering in upper half; Two
                  purple stamp-like pictures on lower left part; tear
                  running through title. ("Porgy and Bess")</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Genoa, Italy: Teatro Carlo Felice 
                  <unitdate>March 1-6,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x14"; Vertical; beige background with
                  brown and red lettering;has a shield-like emblem
                  border at the top</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Milan, Italy: Teatro Alla Scala 
                  <unitdate>February 23-27,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>28"x40"; Bright yellow background; lists
                  names in black lettering with red lettering in the
                  upper half.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Milan, Italy: Teatro Allo Scala 
                  <unitdate>February 23-27,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>15"x11",40"x28",80"x40"; Light brown
                  background with dark brown lettering; red cross on
                  shield at top; decorative leafy-style
                  border</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo 
                  <unitdate>February 15-17,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>39"x28"; Bright blue background with a
                  yellow and green illustration of village; white
                  border; white lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo 
                  <unitdate>February 15-17,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>52"x38, 37"x26"; Bright yellow background;
                  balck lettering; red lettering at top; very
                  simple.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Naples, Italy: Teatro Di San Carlo 
                  <unitdate>February 15-17,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>22"x13"; Bright mustard yellow background;
                  brown border; red and brown lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane 
                  <unitdate>April 21-May 14,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>10"x7"; Small white playbills with red and
                  blue lettering; writing on front and back.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane 
                  <unitdate>April 21-May 14,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>55"x40",78"x54"; Bright mustard-yellow
                  background with black and red lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane 
                  <unitdate>April 21-May 14,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x14"; Vertical; blue background with
                  black and red lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane 
                  <unitdate>April 21-May 14,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x14"; Vertical; yellow background with
                  black and red lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Rome, Italy: Teatro Quattro Fontane 
                  <unitdate>April 21-May 14,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>80"x54"; Three pieces; green and bright
                  yellow background fading into one another; large red
                  lettering at top; black lettering at bottom; very
                  bright and colorful</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Turin, Italy: Teatro Alfieri 
                  <unitdate>April 9-17,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>27"x13"; Vertical; off-white pink
                  illustration of a lady in the background; large red
                  lettering towards top</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Turin, Italy: Teatro Alfieri 
                  <unitdate>April 9-17,1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>38"x26"; Pink and yellow illustration with
                  black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice 
                  <unitdate>September 22-25,
                  1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x28"; Vibrant red background with half
                  facial photo of Gershwin in upper right, illustration
                  of Porgy and Bess on left; black and whitw
                  lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice 
                  <unitdate>September 22-25,
                  1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x14"; A number of these in the
                  background colors of: yellow, blue-green, blue,
                  washed-out, white, and pink; black and red
                  lettering;vertical</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Venice, Italy: Teatro La Fenice 
                  <unitdate>September 22-25,
                  1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>55"x39"; Large; off-white; red and black
                  lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Amsterdam, Netherlands: Teatre Carre 
                  <unitdate>May 19-June3, 1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>49"x33"; White border; black lettering
                  within white squares; yellow squares with black
                  lettering; bright yellow lettering in very
                  middle</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Lima, Peru: Teatro Municipal 
                  <unitdate>September 3-7, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>52"x34"; Two pieces; washed-out white
                  background with black lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Warsaw, Poland: National Opera House 
                  <unitdate>January 24-February 1,
                  1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x28";White background; blue and red
                  lettering.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Barcelona, Spain: Gran Teatro Del Liceo 
                  <unitdate>February 3-13, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>50"x35"; Large; off-white with brown and
                  red lettering; branch style border with leaves on
                  it.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Lausanne, Switzerland: Theatre De Beaulieu
                  <unitdate>March 16-23, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>28"x14", 50"x36"; Washed-out yellow
                  background with black and red lettering; bold red
                  lettering in the middle.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Lausanne, Switzerland: Teatre De Beaulieu 
                  <unitdate>March 16-23, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>11"x8";Washed-out white with red and black
                  lettering; bold red lettering in the
                  middle.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Zurich, Switzerland: Hallenstadion 
                  <unitdate>June 3-12, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>50"x36";Light green background with painted
                  color figures of Porgy and Bess; black sketch of
                  village behind them; blue lettering at top; black
                  lettering throughhout the rest.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Zurich, Switzerland: Hallenstadion 
                  <unitdate>June 3-12, 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>20"x12"; Black border with lettering
                  surrounding light green background; painted color
                  figures of Porgy and Bess; black line sketch of
                  village behind them; blue lettering at
                  top.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Chicago, USA: Ciciv Opera House 
                  <unitdate>June 25, 1952</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>20"x14"; Two shades of orange background;
                  black and white lettering; illustration of Porgy and
                  Bess dancing in the middle</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>New York, USA: Ziegfeld Theatre 
                  <unitdate>March 10-November
                  28,1953</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>9"x6"; Small; off-white flyer with black
                  border; stars on sides; black writing; illustration
                  of village in black.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Leningrad, USSR: Palace of Culture 
                  <unitdate>December 26-January
                  5,1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>42"x28"; White background; blue and red
                  lettering in upper half.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Moscow, USSR: Stanilavsky Theatre 
                  <unitdate>January 10-17, 1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>40"x27"; White background; blue and red
                  lettering; blue lettering in bottom half</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Zagreb, Yugoslavia: Theatre De'L Opera 
                  <unitdate>December 11-14, 1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>39"x28"; White background; purple and white
                  lettering</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Zagreb, Yugoslavia: Theatre De'L Opera 
                  <unitdate>Dec 11-14, 1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physdesc>12"x8"; White background; red and black
                  lettering; writing on both sides.</physdesc>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
