<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/gmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/gmu_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/gmu_contact.xml">
]>
<ead id="vifgm00019">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//George Mason University::Fenwick Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViFGM::vifgm00019::Clarence A. Steele Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vifgm00019.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViFGM">PUBLIC "-//George
             Mason University::Fenwick Library::Special Collections and
             Archives//TEXT (US::ViFGM::vifgm00019::Clarence A. Steele
             Papers)//EN" "vifgm00019.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Guide to the Clarence A. Steele
            Papers</titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Steele, Clarence A. 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Steele 001</num></subtitle>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Copyright George Mason University
            Libraries</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Special Collections &amp;
               Archives</addressline>
               <addressline>Fenwick Library (2FL)</addressline>
               <addressline>George Mason University</addressline>
               <addressline>Fairfax, Virginia 22030-4444</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (703) 993-2220</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (703) 993-8911</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: speccoll@gmu.edu</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2001 By Copyright
            George Mason University Libraries.</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
            <p id="filesize">90K</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid created by James
         Safley</creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-19">Feb 19, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//George Mason University::Fenwick
            Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT
            (US::ViFGM::vifgm00019::Clarence A. Steele Papers)//EN"
            "vifgm00019.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by
            v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-25">Feb 25, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>Guide to the Clarence A. Steele
         Papers</titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections and Archives 
         <num type="Collection Number">Steele 001</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>George Mason University Libraries</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>Fenwick Library (2FL)</item>
            <item>George Mason University</item>
            <item>Fairfax, Virginia 22030-4444</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (703) 993-2220</item>
            <item>Fax: (703) 993-8911</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:speccoll@gmu.edu">
            speccoll@gmu.edu</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections">
            http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives,
      George Mason University</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Special Collections and Archives, George Mason
         University</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Clarence A. Steele Papers</unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">Steele 001</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">1/3 of one cubic
         foot (0.333)</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information</head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Clarence A. Steele Papers, Special Collections and
            Archives, George Mason University Libraries</p>
         </prefercite>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>Clarence A. Steele was the chairman of the Exploratory
         Committee and Advisory Council to the Northern Virginia
         University Center (NVUC). The Center was established in
         September 1949 as an adult education extension of the
         University of Virginia (UVa) at Charlottesville. A few years
         before, the idea for a center was set into motion. Seeing an
         opportunity for educational expansion and recognizing the
         needs of the growing Northern Virginia population, University
         of Virginia's Extension Division, headed by Professor George
         B. Zehmer, formed an Exploratory Committee to work out a
         feasibility plan for creating an extension in Northern
         Virginia. The upshot was the Northern Virginia University
         Center, which became fully operational in February 1950, with
         six classes enrolling about 50 students.</p>
         <p>The Extension Division named John Norville Gibson Finley as
         the Center's first director. The Center's administrative
         offices and "campus" were located on the campus of
         Washington-Lee High School in Arlington, Virginia. During the
         Center's early years, it offered college-level courses for
         adults. By the fall of 1953, the Center grew to 55 classes
         with 900 enrolled students. The Center, which had set out to
         serve only the immediate Washington metropolitan area in
         Virginia, expanded to serve an area that encompassed a radius
         of thirty miles around Arlington. This significant growth
         forced the Center to reevaluate its mission to the population
         it served. So in 1954, an Advisory Council formed to examine
         the challenges of expansion and to consider a "possible change
         of character" for the Center. Moreover, it was asked to
         "interpret the community and its desires to the University"
         and to "assist in creating a climate of demand for the
         educational services offered."</p>
         <p>The Advisory Council consisted of sixteen members, all of
         whom resided in Northern Virginia. The Council's first meeting
         was on January 4, 1954 in Washington-Lee High School, called
         and chaired by Clarence A. Steele, former chairman of the
         Center's Exploratory Committee, which the Council superseded.
         As chair, Steele presided over meetings and directed the
         activities of the Council. Together with Mr. Zehmer, head of
         the Extension Division, and President Colgate W. Darden of the
         University of Virginia, the Council explored ways to convert
         the Center into a formal branch of University of Virginia.
         Steele and the Council immediately began a dialogue with
         prominent members of the community, including Virginia
         senators Charles R. Fenwick and Harry F. Byrd, Jr., hoping to
         find support for a branch of the University of Virginia.</p>
         <p>In order to establish a branch, the Center had to comply
         with standards enacted by the Southern Association of Colleges
         and Secondary Schools, of which the University of Virginia was
         a member. Standards included: (1) a centrally located building
         sufficient for administration and instruction; (2) a sizable
         nucleus of full-time faculty members to ensure permanence and
         continuity; (3) adequate library and laboratory facilities;
         (4) a stable pattern of course offerings. Aware that the
         Center did not meet all of these conditions, the Advisory
         Council used the Southern Association standards as a
         foundation for their proposal. Steele thereby formed
         committees to focus on meeting the standards. The committees
         included: Building and Grounds, Ways and Means, Public
         Relations, Legal Council, and Research. This focus streamlined
         the Council, allowing members to use their expertise most
         productively. President Darden gave his full support to the
         endeavor, providing his own philosophy as an impetus: "bring
         the University of Virginia to the people" and "promote adult
         education formally and informally; culturally as well as
         technically."</p>
         <p>The most important task facing the Council was the search
         for a location for the new college. Throughout late 1954 and
         all of 1955 they searched for tracts of land suitable for a
         permanent location. In the meantime, the Northern Virginia
         Center (as the Center was now called) continued to grow,
         expanding to 110 classes with 2,100 enrolled students in the
         spring of 1956. More startling was the prediction that
         enrollment would reach 8,000 adult students within a decade.
         This, along with the area's growing number of high school
         graduates, necessitated a new emphasis: one which would make
         the branch an affordable two-year institution with day classes
         - serving all students, not just adults. At this time, a
         Virginia House Joint Resolution passed, "authorizing the
         establishment of a branch of the University of Virginia to be
         located in Northern Virginia" (passed by the House of
         Delegates and the Senate of Virginia in February 1956),
         thereby providing the legal underpinning to continue the
         expansion of the Center.</p>
         <p>By early 1956, many locations for the branch had been
         scouted out and researched. President Darden insisted that the
         college "have an appropriate campus, an ample campus, ample
         acres for spacing buildings, for parking, for playing fields
         of various kinds, for woods and vistas." Later in the year,
         three sites were seriously considered: the Ravensworth estate,
         between Annandale and Springfield, along Braddock Road; the
         Bowman or Herndon tracts, on the Sunset Hills farm land near
         Herndon; and seven Prince William County sites, including one
         along the border of Manassas Battlefield Park. In the summer
         of 1956, the Advisory Council unanimously endorsed the
         Ravensworth site. But not long after, a sub-committee assigned
         by the University of Virginia Board of Visitors was charged to
         survey the locations, and, to the Council's chagrin, it
         recommended the Bowman tract.</p>
         <p>The disagreement arose from an apparent conflict of
         interest between the Advisory Council and the Visitors
         sub-committee. A few years prior, the Virginia Advisory
         Legislative Council to the Governor and the General Assembly
         (VALC) drafted a report, recommending that new university
         branches should only be two-year institutions and be
         self-supportive. In other words, VALC "wanted to establish
         urban branches [without dormitories] where students could live
         at home," and thus raise the cost of tuition, saving the state
         from unnecessary expenses.</p>
         <p>Accordingly, in their search for branch locations, the
         Advisory Council looked for sites that would accommodate a
         "2-year, non-dormitory type of institution ONLY." They found
         the Ravensworth site ideal for those purposes. Conversely, the
         Visitors sub-committee's choice of the Bowman tract - a much
         larger and even more isolated area - clearly "envisioned a
         full scale dormitory type institution." The Council was
         unaware of the University of Virginia's plan to establish a
         large, four-year college with an extensive campus, and was
         unprepared for such a shift in focus.</p>
         <p>Gathering what support they could, the Council sent
         delegations from Arlington, Alexandria and Fairfax Counties to
         persuade the Board of Visitors to reconsider. Several members
         of the Visitors were openly antagonistic to the Ravensworth
         site, mainly because the Bowman tract offered a firmer
         political base to the region. Others felt that there was
         "little use for Northern Virginia" for the future of the
         University. After some debate the Visitors dryly agreed to
         "take the whole matter of establishing a branch under
         advisement." A few years later, in 1959, the Council and the
         Visitors settled their differences and decided on an entirely
         new site: the Farr tract, the site on which George Mason
         University now stands, located less than one mile south of
         Fairfax City.</p>
         <p>The Advisory Council to the Northern Virginia Center, with
         Clarence A. Steele at the helm, faced many challenges during
         the early years of its existence. The problems associated with
         growth, the evaluation of educational needs in Northern
         Virginia, and the search for a new location for the University
         branch occupied much time and required considerable
         investment.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>This collection contains papers and material owned by
         Clarence A. Steele relating to the Advisory Council to the
         Northern Virginia University Center. Included are minutes of
         meetings, letters, newspapers, and miscellaneous
         documents.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement>
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged by year, starting in 1954 and
         going until 1956/57.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <dsc type="analyticover">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Clarence A. Steele Papers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Northern Virginia Center: Correspondence
                  and Related Papers,Calendar Year 
                  <unitdate>1954</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 1</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Northern Virginia Center: Correspondence
                  and Related Papers,Calendar Year 
                  <unitdate>1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 2</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Northern Virginia Center: Correspondence
                  and Related Papers,Calendar Year [1 of 2] 
                  <unitdate>1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 3</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Northern Virginia Center: Correspondence
                  and Related Papers, Calendar Year [2 of 2] 
                  <unitdate>1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 4</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Northern Virginia Center: Miscellaneous 
                  <unitdate>1956</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 5</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Original Newspapers and
                  Commonwealth-Magazine of Virginia 
                  <unitdate>1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                  <physloc>Folder 6</physloc>
                  <container type="Box">Box 1</container>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
