<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://sca.gmu.edu/tools/ead.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/gmu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<ead id="vifgm00066">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViFGM" url="http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/">vifgm00066
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Guide to the Virtual Library of Virginia records, <date>1994-2004</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Virtual Library of Virginia
<num type="collectionnumber">C0148
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Harold J. Barthold
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>George Mason University Libraries
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006 By George Mason University Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date> 
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Eron Ackerman, <date>February 2009</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
   <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Virtual Library of Virginia records</titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Special Collections and Archives 
         <num type="Collection Number">C0148</num></subtitle>
	<p id="logostmt">
	<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
	</p>
         <publisher>George Mason University Libraries</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2011</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>Fenwick Library (2FL)</item>
            <item>George Mason University</item>
            <item>Fairfax, Virginia 22030-4444</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (703) 993-2220</item>
            <item>Fax: (703) 993-8911</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:speccoll@gmu.edu">
            speccoll@gmu.edu</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://sca.gmu.edu">
            sca.gmu.edu</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a"><corpname>George Mason University. <subarea>Special Collections and Archives.
</subarea>
</corpname>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a"><corpname>Virtual Library of Virginia
</corpname>
</origination>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virtual Library of Virginia records
</unittitle>
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1994-2004
</unitdate> 
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">C0148
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>10 linear feet </extent>
<extent>(20 boxes)
</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains documents and correspondence from the development and operations of the Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) consortium from its founding onward. Among the documents included are agendas, minutes, and supporting documents from Committee meetings, articles about VIVA, correspondence, contracts, listservs, meeting minutes, policies and procedures, proposals, publications, reports, and printouts of webpages.
</abstract>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Virtual Library of Virginia records, Collection #C0148, Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Collection donated by Katherine Perry in 1997-2010.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Special Collections and Archives staff. EAD markup completed by Eron Ackerman, Jordan Patty in 2009. Addtional processing and EAD markup by Harold J. Barthold in 2010.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) is a consortium organized in 1994 to provide, in an equitable, cooperative and cost effective manner, enhanced access to library and information resources for Commonwealth of Virginia institutes of higher education serving the higher education community. VIVA facilitates its member libraries cooperative purchase of electronic databases and sharing of other resources such as their valuable print collections.
</p>
<p>
The 39 State-assisted academic colleges and universities in Virginia are charter members of VIVA by legislative action. These include the 6 public doctoral institutions; 9 comprehensive institutions; and 24 community colleges and two-year branch campuses. In addition, the private non-profit institutions of higher education comprising the Virginia Independent College and University Library Association (VICULA) have participated as charter members from the inception of VIVA. The Library of Virginia, as a State library agency with educational and research mission, also participates as a member of VIVA. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains documents and correspondence from the development and operations of the Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) consortium from its founding onward as documented by Kathy Perry the Director of VIVA.
</p> 
<p>Series 1 contains documents generated by VIVA committees. Committees include the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the task force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access, the User Group, the Special Collections Committee and the Technical Issues Committee. Material includes meeting agendas, minutes and notes, committee assignment information, committee reports, committee lists, budget information, correspondence, journal subscription information, information about specific software and computer programs, cost savings and value added survey information, documents from regional meetings and workshops, lists of institutional participants, contact directories, VIVA information packets, travel reimbursement information, interlibrary loan information, press releases and information about the Virginia Heritage Project.
</p>  
<p>Series 2 contains material generated by the various meetings, forums, training sessions and workshops. Documents include correspondence, evaluation forms, meeting agendas, notes, and minutes, registration and attendance information, contact lists and directories, logistical information, information about software and computer programs, fact sheets, group lists, information about electronic resources, VIVA packets, VIVA publications, travel reimbursement information and ILL guidelines and lending reports. The series is divided into two subseries, Regional Meetings and Workshops.
</p>
<p>Series 3 contains information generated by VIVA contact directories. Material includes VIVA contact directories, committee lists, memos, correspondence, faxes, a personnel directory, notes, maps and lists of participating institutions, VIVA fact sheets,  recommendations for organization structure and VIVA publications.
</p>  
<p>Series 4 contains information generated by the cost saving and value added survey. The CSVA survey was sent to VIVA member institutions "to assess the impact of VIVA's shared purchase of electronic resources". Material includes rough drafts and final versions of the survey, blank and completed surveys, CSVA survey executive summaries, notes, budget information, narrative summaries, questionnaire responses, instructional letters, correspondence, documents on three and a half inch floppy disks, lists of journals available from Ideal (Academic Press), IAC, and Project Muse, survey distribution checklists, lists of VIVA participating institutions, survey results, financial benefit reports, information about the VIVA listserv and home page,  VIVA fact sheets, a rough draft of the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, VIVA electronic resources spreadsheets and subscription prices worksheets.
</p>
<p>Series 5 contains miscellaneous documents generated by the Virtual Library of Virginia. Material includes correspondence, travel reimbursement information, information from the Allied Health and Nursing Collaborative Collection Project, VIVA publications, newspaper articles, information about the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, VIVA website information, vendor client reviews, information about authentication, security, and access management issues for VIVA users, lists of VIVA institutional participants, budget information and lending information.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This collection is arranged according to subject.
</p>
<list>
<item>Series 1: VIVA Committees, April 1994-September 2004 (Boxes 1-13)
</item>
<item>Series 2: VIVA Events and Meetings, January 1995-August 2001 (Boxes 14-16)
</item>
<item>Series 3: VIVA Contacts Directories, January 1995-September 2000 (Boxes 17-18)
</item>
<item>Series 4: VIVA Cost Saving and Value Added Survey, July 1994-July 1999 (Boxes 19-20)
</item>
<item>Series 5: Miscellaneous VIVA Documents, November 1994-January 2003 (Box 20)
</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Special Collections and Archives also holds the George Mason University Libraries records.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Corporate Names:</head>
<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">VIVA, the Virtual Library of Virginia.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Library cooperation--Virginia.</subject>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 1: Committees, </unittitle>
<unitdate>April 1994-September 2004</unitdate>
<physdesc>(13 boxes)</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains documents generated by VIVA committees. Committees include the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the task force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access, the User Group, the Special Collections Committee and the Technical Issues Committee. The series is made up of six subseries each containing documents from the primary committees: the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Special Collections Committee, and the Technical Issues Committee.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
   		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.1: VIVA Steering Committee Meetings, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>July 1994-June 2002</unitdate>
    		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>Material generated before and after monthly VIVA Steering Committee meetings. The Steering Committee meeting files include meeting agendas, minutes and notes, committee assignment information, committee reports, committee lists, budget information, and correspondence in regards to the monthly meetings as well as annual retreats.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Minutes, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 29, 1994-September 21, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes of monthly Steering Committee meetings form July of 1994 to September of 1995.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Minutes, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 9, 1995-September 18, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes of monthly Steering Committee meetings from November of 1995 to September of 1997.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 29, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agenda, notes, correspondence and minutes from the July 1994 meeting.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 17, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes, correspondence and committee member list from the August 1994 meeting at the Institute of Textile Technology in Charlottesville.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 15, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Correspondence, notes, minutes and agendas from the September 1994 at Washington and Lee University in Lexington. Also included are a Washington and Lee University campus map and Electronics Collections Committee progress report. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October 13, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes, correspondence and agenda from the October meeting at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included is information about an upcoming vendor fair and a TRW Smart Search computer program.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Vendor Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 8, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Supporting informational publications from Data Research Associates.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">1</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Vendor Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 8, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p> Variety of documents related to vendor fair held at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Attendees lists, logistical information and directions to fair, correspondence, and registration forms.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 10, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes, agendas, notes and correspondence from the November meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is information about the OCLC SiteSearch System, the VIVA website design, vendor fair responses, and an article from The Richmond Times-Dispatch about college budget cuts.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 8, 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Attendance list, minutes and notes from December meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is budget information, VIVA stationary, correspondence about SOLINET, an article about VIVA from the Virginia Pilot, and meeting minutes from the User Services Committee.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 11, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, attendance sheets, notes, minutes and correspondence about the January meeting at J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College in Richmond. Also included is a VIVA information packet and meeting minutes from the User Services Committee.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>February 9, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Notes and agendas from the February meeting at Randolph-Macon College in Ashland. Also included is contact list requests, VIVA press release, Ariel literature, miscellaneous correspondence.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 8-10, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Notes, minutes and agendas from the March meeting at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included is budget information, committee member lists, and funding information from the Department of Commerce. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Retreat, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 8-9, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas for the retreat at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included are Electronic Collections Committee goals and accomplishments and funding information from the Department of Commerce.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 13, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Notes, agendas and minutes from the April meeting at the Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included are database factsheets, budget information, and regional meeting attendance lists
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 11, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and minutes from May meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is budget information, Electronics Collections Committee goals, and committee lists.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">2</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 8, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, committee lists and notes from the June meeting at Old Dominion University in Norfolk. Also included is an Interim Report of the Joint Subcommittee Studying the Reorganization of the State Library and Archives, correspondence from the Virginia council of higher learning, information about Ohio Library and Information Network, contact lists, 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 13, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Notes, committee lists and agendas from the July meeting at Sweet Briar College in Sweet Briar. Also included are VIVA contract samples and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Mtg., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 21-22, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Notes, agendas and action items from the September meeting at George Mason University in Fairfax. Also included are Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes, budget information, and committee lists.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting Information, </unittitle>
			<unitdate></unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents, articles, minutes, notes and other information for the steering committee meetings.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 9, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes, correspondence and minutes from the November meeting in Roanoke. Also included is information about UVA's Library website, Project Muse subscription information, and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 14, 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is budget information and Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>February 8, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the February meeting in Richmond. Also included is First Search budget information and a list of objectives for the CCM.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Minutes, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 14, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, Collection Committee reports, notes, minutes and correspondence from the March meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included are committee member lists, First Search usage information, budget information, faculty newsletters, Ariel survey, planning retreat agenda, VIVA logo edits, interlibrary loan information, and a report to the Council of Higher Education.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Minutes, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 9, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, minutes and notes from the May meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is Ariel information, interlibrary loan information, cost-savings and value-added survey, first search usage information and questionnaire, budget information, and collections committee recommendations. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Spring Retreat, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 13-14, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Outline, questionnaire and notes from the VIVA spring retreat at Radford University. Also included is information from the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee meeting. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">3</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Spring Retreat, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 13-14, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>VIVA Travel and Training costs summary and information, presentation slide notes, correspondence, keynote address notes, and minutes from the VIVA spring retreat at Radford University.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the August meeting at the Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is a recommendation to establish a cataloging committee, VIVA publicity plan and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 26, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and action items from the September meeting at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included is budget information, User Services committee meeting minutes, VIVA mission statement and vision information, contact lists, JMU ROCCO Forum publication, presentation slides about the cooperative collection development, 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 8, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, action items and notes from the November meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included are lists of participating institutions, presentation slides about VIVA, and CCM workshop planning correspondence. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 5-6, 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the December meeting at Virginia State University in Petersburg. Also included is State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes and information, VIVA fact sheets, budget information, organizational structure recommendations, a press release, restructuring information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 30, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the January meeting. Also included is information about the use of virtual meetings and organizational structure recommendations. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 6, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, action items and notes from the March meeting at the Library of Virginia in Richmond. Also included is a JSTOR proposal, organizational structure recommendations, budget information, committee lists and collections committee meeting minutes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 12, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, action items, notes, and minutes from the May meeting at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included is a First Search renewal and OVID proposition, interlibrary loan guidelines and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Spring Retreat, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 12-13, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, attendance sheets and notes from the Spring retreat at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included are presentation slides about VIVA's accomplishments, committee and contact lists, cost savings and value added survey executive summary, budget information and a VIVA pamphlet. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 5, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the June meeting at Christopher Newport University in Newport News. Also included is a First Search renewal and OVID proposition, institutional cost sharing options, budget information, cataloging guidelines, User Services committee meeting minutes, VIVA participating institutions, Senate resolution no. 218 regarding the demand for technologically skilled workers in Virginia industry, committee lists, Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes and a VIVA information packet.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 17, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, minutes and notes from the July meeting at the James Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included is a draft proposal to the State Council on Higher Education for Virginia and VIVA Publicity Committee information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">4</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 18-19, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the September meeting at the Virginia Military Institute in Lexington. Also included is a Library Materials Funding Study and budget information. 
 			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 6, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and correspondence from the November meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is information from the Consortium of Consortia meeting, listserv and home page information, cost savings and value added survey information, budget information, VIVA information packet and committee lists.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 4-5, 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at Blue Ridge Community College in Weyers Cave. Also included is collections budget information, committee information and State Council of Higher Education for Virginia executive summary.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 16, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and correspondence from the January meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is a 1997 House of Delegates standing committee list, a list of Virginia state legislators, Richmond Times-Dispatch articles and budget information.  
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 11, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and correspondence from the March meeting at the University of Richmond in Richmond. Also included is a steering committee list, funding information, journal information, Association of College and Research Libraries publication, VIVA electronic resources use statistics, Congressional Informational Service information, selection of electronic information  document from the International Coalition of Library Consortia and Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Retreat, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 5-6, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the May retreat at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is budget information and presentation transparencies about the biennial budget.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 4, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes and notes from the June meeting at Old Dominion University in Norfolk. Also included is a User Services Committee report, a Steering Committee report from the May 1998 retreat, budget information, cataloging guidelines and Library Advisory Committee meeting materials.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 14, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes, correspondence and notes from the August meeting conducted via conference call.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 24-25, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes and notes from the September meeting at Virginia Tech in Blacksburg. Also included is a Collections Committee report, archival repository survey, committee lists, electronic resource allocation spreadsheet, State Committee on Higher Education for Virginia Library Advisory Committee information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 2, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Minutes, notes and correspondence from the November meeting conducted via conference call. Also included is information about Mid-Atlantic Crossroads and Project Muse usage information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">5</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 3-4, 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, action items, minutes, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is budget information, VIVA presentation slides, definition of VIVA associate membership, committee lists, VIVA organizational charts, 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 11-12, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the March meeting at Longwood College in Farmville. Also included is a collections committee report, library services guidelines, electronic resources usage statistics and State Committee on Higher Education for Virginia Library Advisory Committee information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 3-4, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the June meeting at Clinch Valley College in Wise.  Also included is an information management, presentation slides and paper, collections committee meeting minutes and budget information. Large documents William B Allen remarks "The Library is the Center of Learning", 1999 Virginia Plan for Higher Education, Virginia Higher Education Performance Model and Inflation Measures for Schools Colleges and Libraries.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 9, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes, minutes and correspondence from the July meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is a list of committee assignments and committee lists. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 28, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Correspondence, votes, and minutes, from the September meeting which was an electronic vote.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October 8, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and correspondence from the October meeting at the James Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included are committee lists, participant lists and articles from the Chronicle of Higher Education Almanac.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 2-3, 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas and notes from the October meeting at University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is a Users Committee report, Interlibrary loan report, VIVA pamphlet rough draft, VIVA Preliminary Assessment Report and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 9-10, 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, action items, correspondence and notes from the March meeting at George Mason University in Fairfax. Also included is a definition of associate membership, Encoded Archival Description conversion guidelines, interlibrary loan guidelines and librarian lists.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 8-9, 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the June meeting at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included are member and committee lists, periodical access article, presentation slides about collection and access, budget information, and a users committee report.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">6</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 8, 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, retreat summary and notes from the August retreat at Virginia Tech in Blacksburg. Also included are member lists, VIVA preliminary assessment, budget information and lending information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA Assessment, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>1999-2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Preliminary assessment reports for VIVA. Reports include general initial observations about the overall effectiveness of VIVA. Assessment of the effectiveness of the administrative structure of VIVA; review of the documented financial benefits realized by the VIVA program; assessment of VIVA's effectiveness in meetings; recommendations provided. Also included are planning documents for the assessment.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 14-15, 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, minutes and notes from the September meeting at Old Dominion University in Norfolk. Also included is budget information, outreach committee report, budget information, and an Academic Libraries Survey.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 30-December 1, 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, minutes and notes from the November meeting at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included is budget information, a New York Times article and a users committee report.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 8-9, 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence, notes, action items and minutes from the March meeting at Washington and Lee University in Lexington. Also included is a committee list, budget information and consortia article, 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 7-8, 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and minutes from the June meeting at Richard Bland College in Petersburg. Also included is budget information, nelinet summary of electronic resources in Massachusetts, Virginia Libraries article, presentation slides and an outreach committee report. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 23-24, 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas and correspondence from the annual retreat at Randolph-Macon College in Ashland. Also included is organizational information, committee lists, participant institution lists, VIVA timeline, goals and objective lists and budget information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 6, 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, notes and correspondence from the September meeting at Mary Baldwin College in Staunton. Also included is the Virginia Virtual University Draft Proposal, VIVA fact sheet, committee lists, State Council of Higher Education for Virginia press release and a VIVA organizational chart.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 6, 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the Northern Virginia Community College in Manassas. Also included is an outreach committee report, budget information, committee list and subscription information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 7, 2002</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the March meeting at Virginia Military Institute in Lexington. Also included is budget information and resource sharing committee report.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">7</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Steering Committee Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 6, 2002</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Agendas, correspondence and notes from the June meeting at Christopher Newport University in Newport News. Also included is a Virginia Libraries article about the Virginia Heritage project, committee lists, presentation slides about committees, resources for users committee report and information about the Online Archive of California.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
   		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.2: VIVA Resource Users Committee, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>July 1994-September 2004</unitdate>
    		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by the Resources for Users committee and its predecessors. Around 1999, the number of committees in VIVA was reduced drastically and committees were folded into others. The Resources for Users Committee began as the Electronic Collections Committee, was renamed the Collections Committee, then finally became the Resources for Users Committee. Documents in the subseries include information about Legi-Slate, budget information, journal scription information, meeting agendas, notes, and minutes, correspondence, committee lists, "Selection and Presentation of Commercially Available Electronic Resources: Issues and Practices" by Timothy D. Jewell, Cost Savings and Value Added Survey information, documents from regional meetings, VIVA workshops, a cataloging workshop and a collections development workshop, FirstSearch information, lists of institutional participants, budget information, contact directories, information from training fairs, information about Project Confidence and VIVA information packets.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA: Collections Committee Communications. Etc., </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1994-June 2004</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Collections committee correspondence and information including a list of participating institutions, a contact directory, a VIVA meeting schedule, and member lists from the following committees: Collections, Interlibrary Loan Enhancements, Special Collections, Technical Issues, User Services, Electronic Collections, Steering Committee, Resource Sharing, Resources for Users, Outreach, State Council of Higher Education Library Advisory.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA-Collections Committee I, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 1995-January 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Collections Committee including an article from the Cyber Librarian, online dictionary directories, budget information, FirstSearch information, committee member lists, also included is meeting information such as minutes, agendas, correspondence and notes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA-Collections Committee II, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August-November 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Collections Committee including a list of participating institutions, pricing proposals, budget information, a cost savings and value added 1996/1997 executive summary and institutional comments, and cost savings value added surveys.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>User Services Regional Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Material generated by the User Services regional meeting held on April 4-7, 1995 at institutions throughout Virginia. Included are agendas, attendance lists, evaluation forms, brochure draft, and contact lists.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>User Services Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1994-June 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the User Services committee material includes workshop organization guide, meeting agendas, minutes and notes, user services survey, FirstSearch user institutions,  achievement list of user services committee, FirstSearch reference guide, Solinet information and an African American Poetry collection advertisement.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>User Services Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March-May 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Correspondence about the May 1997 VIVA workshop, also included is a registration confirmation.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>User Services-Users Group, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1997-November 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the User Services committee. Material includes the 1997 VLA/DCLA Conference agenda, VIVA list serve and FirstSearch information, meeting agendas and notes as well as User Group comments.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>User Services-Cataloging Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 1998-April 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence about the May 1999 VIVA Cataloging Workshop. Materials include agendas, electronic cataloging guidelines, meeting notes, workshop outlines and workshop logistics.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>User Services Collection Development Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 1997-March 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
 			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence about the March 1998 VIVA Users Services Collection Development Workshop. Materials include agendas, registration information, committee member lists, notes and report from the workshop.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee I, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 1994-July 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include budget information, committee member lists, FirstSearch subscription information, meeting agendas, minutes and notes, Legi-Slate comparisons to Lexis Nexis, a press release, and request for proposal drafts.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">8</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee II, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1994-December 1994</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include Internet Journal Services advertisements, meeting minutes and agendas, budget information, subscription information and requests for proposals. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee III, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 1994-November 1995</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include a list of goals for the committee, meeting notes, agendas and minutes, committee lists, subscription proposals, vendor lists, enrollment figures, electronic resource selection information and database information.  
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>"Selection and Presentation of Commercially Available Electronic Resources: Issues and Practices" by Timothy D. Jewell. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>RUC-Cost Savings and Value Added Survey Final Report, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>1995-1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Two copies of the Executive Summary of a Cost Savings and Value Added Survey from 1995-1996 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>RUC-Cost Savings and Value Added Survey, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>1996-1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents generated by the Cost Savings and Value Added Survey 1995-1996, including executive summaries, correspondence, blank surveys, lists of available journals from IAC, Ideal (Academic Press) and Project Muse.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 1997-October 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include meeting notes, agendas, and minutes, budget info, newspaper and journal subscription info, journal articles and information about electronic collections.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>RUC Training Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 2000-March 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the March 2000 VIVA training fair. Materials include training information, meeting plans/schedules, meeting notes and agendas, registration information, VIVA publications, attendees lists, VIVA information packet and FirstSearch information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>RUC InfoTrac Training, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence about VIVA InfoTrac training workshops. Materials include registration and attendance information, workshop agendas and evaluation forms. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>RUC Vendor Presentations, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Two VIVA information packets for vendor presentations. Packets include an agenda, evaluation, travel reimbursement information and VIVA fact sheet.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 1998-June 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include budget tables, meeting agendas, notes, and minutes, periodical information, cost surveys, budget information and Cost Saved and Value Added survey summary.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">9</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>RUC - OVID Training Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August-November 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the August-September 1999 Resources for Users committee OVID Training Fair. Materials include registration and attendance lists, meeting schedules, agendas, evaluation forms, travel reimbursement information and thank-you letters.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Resources for Users Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 1998-February 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Resources for Users committee. Materials include meeting agendas, minutes, and notes, budgets information, database/journal subscription information, VIVA Collection Development Principles and Selection Criteria, a press release and Cost Saved and Value Added survey summary.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>CIA net library -UVA, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>February-April 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Correspondence about the minutes from the February 2000 meeting of the VIVA Task Force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access . Material includes meeting minutes and an email.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>CIA Workshop, Electronic Journals, from Aggregator Sources, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October 1999-January 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the User Services Committee Subcommittee on Cataloging and Intellectual Access. Material includes meeting agendas notes, evaluation forms, presentation about creating web lists of electronic journals and a VIVA information packet including a VIVA pamphlet, fact sheet, communication information and presentation slides.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Cataloging, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1996-October 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the User Services Committee Subcommittee on Cataloging and Intellectual Access. Material includes information on electronic journals, a report on electronic resources, meeting agendas and minutes, a "Report and Recommendations for Providing Intellectual  Access to VIVA Resources" and cataloging guidelines. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Cataloging and Intellectual Access Task Force, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1996-November 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the User Services Committee Subcommittee on Cataloging and Intellectual Access. Material includes meeting agendas, notes and minutes, information about SerialsSolutions and cataloging guidelines.  
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Project Confidence, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January-April 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Collections Committee's "Project Confidence", which was designed to let VIVA member institutions see stability and to encourage them to cancel print subscriptions to journals. Material includes lists of available journals, project reports, Academic Search FullTEXT 1,000 Database coverage lists, lists of available journals, a report of an overview of OhioLink's comparison of general "full text" journal article databases, a Proquest directory, lists of "Core Titles" for Project Confidence, meeting minutes and agendas, ARIEL instructions, a news release about publishers offering journals electronically, VIVA participation spreadsheet and an EBSCO information packet. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">10</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>RFP Committee Vendor Presentations, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>A description of a vendor presentation meeting in March of 1998 at the University of Richmond. Material includes a schedule of presentations and an evaluation form. Also included is a VIVA information folder which contains help advice for electronic collection vendors, meeting agenda and notes, a list of restaurants in University of Richmond vicinity, a draft of VIVA principles and selection criteria, VIVA listserv and home page information, a VIVA pamphlet, travel reimbursement information and committee lists. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">11</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>RFP 1999 Vendor Presentation, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April-August 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Request for Proposal committee. The request was for a database provider for abstracting and indexing services. Material includes an agendas for the RPF vendor presentations, registrants for the vendor presentations, SilverPlatter publications, an OVID Technologies information packet and attendance and registration information. Also included are two VIVA information packets which contain VIVA pamphlets, VIVA fact sheets, agendas, evaluation forms and travel reimbursement information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">11</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>RFP Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>February-July 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents and correspondence from the Request for Proposal committee. RFP #M 0182 was a request for a database provider. Documents include schedules of meetings, an official Request for Proposal, attendance information for vendor presentation, journal subscription information, meeting notes and agendas, subscription prices, database provider selection criteria and evaluations, a rough draft of the request for proposal, large note pad pages with meeting notes and VIVA questions and answers.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">11</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Request for Proposal #M 0127, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 1996-August 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Request for Proposal #M 0127 for Interlibrary Loan Delivery Service from Federal Express. Also included is the contract between VIVA and FedEx, correspondence, a list of document delivery sites and service codes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">11</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Federal Express Response to RFP #M 0127 for Interlibrary Loan Delivery Service, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>The official response from FedEx to RFP #M 0127 for Interlibrary Loan delivery service. Material includes a spiral bound FedEx Service Guide, a table of contents, contract details, general information about Federal Express, "Electronic Data Interchange with FedEx", FedEx Datalink, shipping rates, an executive summary, a spiral bound FedEx EDI Invoice and FedEx EDI Remit Implementation Guide and a spiral bound group of "VIVA Topics to be Discussed".
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.3: VIVA Resource Sharing Committee, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>July 1994-July 2003</unitdate>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by the Resource Sharing Committee and its subcommittee the Interlibrary Loan Enhancement Committee, files include ILL Forum information, an article, meeting minutes and correspondence.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Resource Sharing Committee-ILL Forum, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May-August 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the Resources Sharing Committee for the Interlibrary Loan Forum held on July, 14 2000, documents include group information, agendas, comments, notes, registration information and attendance lists, presentation slides and evaluation forms. Also included is a list of ARIEL addresses and VIVA information packets.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Resource Sharing Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May-July 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Article from RLG Focus titled "Successful Borrow Direct Model for ILL to Expand in July", meeting minutes and correspondence.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Enhancement Committee I, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October 1994-March 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the ILL Enhancement Committee, documents include ARIEL document delivery protocol information, meeting minutes and agendas as well as presentation slides and information about OCLC Resource Sharing Strategy and FirstSearch.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Interlibrary Loan Enhancement Committee II, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 1994-April 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the ILL Enhancement Committee, documents include meeting minutes and notes, budget information, ARIEL Document Delivery Protocols and software information, ILL requests through FirstSearch, document delivery RFP Surveys, Virginia Tech Libraries acquisition of electronic information resources guidelines and a list of achievements of the VIVA ILL from 1994 to 1999.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Interlibrary Loan Enhancement Committee III, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 1999-June 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the ILL Enhancement Committee, documents include A Model for Library Support of Distance Education in the US, committee lists, a list of achievements of the VIVA ILL from 1994 to 1999, institutional borrowing and lending list from 1996 to 1997, meeting minutes, budget information, institutional allocation information, ILL conference information, Universal Resource Sharing Application prod cut description and information, and a proposal Statewide Courier Service.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>Interlibrary Loan Enhancement Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 1998 and March 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Two packets of correspondence about the cancelation of the Net Lender reimbursement program as well as an ARIEL software upgrade.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Letter, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March 1995-February 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents and correspondence generated by the Interlibrary Loan Committee. Material includes contact lists, VIVA listserv and home page information, Ariel guidelines and information, lending information and image processing system specifications.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Guidelines, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 1997-August 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Three versions of ILL guidelines from May of 1997, the proposed guidelines from July 2000, and the approved guidelines from August 2000.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Ariel, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1995-January 2003</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents and correspondence about Ariel including an Ariel survey, Ariel protocols and article about Ariel purchase by Infotrieve.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Guidelines, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Eight copies of the May 1997 ILL guidelines.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Guidelines, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1996-February 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence about allocation of various ILL resources including express mail, memorandums regarding allocations to member schools, delivery allocation memos and lending information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">12</container>
			<unittitle>ILL-OCLC Stats, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Statistics and lending information from the Interlibrary Loan and Online Computer Library Center. Two groups of information including VIVA Express Mail Allocations and an ILL summary report.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">12</container>
			<container type="Folder">13</container>
			<unittitle>ILL OCLC Stats, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Statistics, correspondence and lending information about Interlibrary Loan including an ILL summary report and a letter to the OCLC.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
   		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.4: VIVA Outreach Committee, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>October 1996-July 2001</unitdate>
    		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by the Outreach Committee. The files includes correspondence, information about the Across the Curriculum forum, meeting agendas, notes and evaluations, presentation slides and contact lists.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Outreach Committee-Across the Curriculum, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March-July 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents and correspondence generated before and after the VIVA Across the Curriculum Forum on July 27, 2001. The forum addressed the future of literacy efforts in Virginia. Documents include William and Mary promotional publications, travel information, Association of College and Research Libraries publication, registration and attendance information, VIVA information packets, agendas, evaluations and notes from the forum.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Outreach Committee-(Formerly Publicity Subcommittee of User Services), </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October 1996-July 2001</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence generated by the Outreach Committee and its predecessor the Publicity Committee, documents include contact lists, Publicity Committee 1998 plan, workshop information and presentation slides both hard copy and on a 3 1/2 inch floppy disk.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>User Group, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September-October 1998</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the User Group. Material includes meeting notes, conference invitations, VIVA pamphlet, group status reports, technical issues committee information and member lists, VIVA fact sheets and communication information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>User Group, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March-November 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the User Group. Material includes publications from the Virginia Libraries Association, meeting notes, a list of vendors attending the user group meeting and communication information. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>Committee Annual Reports, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 1999-June 2000</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>1999-2000 Annual reports from the Outreach Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee and the Resources for Users Committee.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.5: VIVA Special Collections Committee, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>June 1995-January 2003</unitdate>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by the Special Collections Committee. The Special Collections Committee files includes correspondence, exhibition programs, a press release, contact lists, information about the Virginia Heritage Project and EAD workshop participant lists and reimbursement information.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA-Special Collections Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 1995-June 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Special Collections Committee including contact lists, digital training workshop information package, meeting minutes, program for "'Twas The Night Before Christmas" exhibition, press release about the Electronic Archive of Early American Fiction, a draft proposal and description of the Virginia Heritage Collection Project, and a TechBooks publication.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA-Special Collections-Virginia Heritage Project, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 2000-January 2003</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Special Collections Committee about the Virginia Heritage Project. Documents include Virginia Heritage Project executive committee meeting minutes and agendas, budget information, grant proposals, a Virginia Heritage Project description and a committee list. 
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Special Collections Committee-Workshops, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January-February 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information regarding reimbursement information and participant list for the January 1999 EAD workshop.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 1.6: VIVA Technical Issues Committee, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>April 1994-January 1999</unitdate>
		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by the Technical Issues committee. Documents include correspondence, meeting notes, agendas, and minutes, VIVA institutional information, budget information, committee and member lists, as well as information about the User Authentication Workshop.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Technical Issues Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 1994-September 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Technical Issues committee. Materials include meeting notes, agendas and minutes, VIVA fact sheets, member lists, VIVA institutional IP addresses, budget information, equipment surveys and institutional subscription information.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Technical Issues Committee-User Authentication Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>December 1997</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the December 1997 User Authentication Workshop. Materials include workshop agendas, notes, registration workshop, logistical information, a VIVA information packet and workshop surveys.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">13</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>Technical Issues Committee, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 1998-January 1999</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Information and correspondence from the Technical Issues committee. Materials include meeting agendas and minutes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 2: VIVA Events and Meetings, </unittitle>
<unitdate>January 1995-August 2001</unitdate>
<physdesc>(3 boxes)</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains material generated by the various meetings, forums, training sessions and workshops held throughout Virginia and organized by and for VIVA. The series is made up of two subseries, the first contains documents from the official VIVA regional meetings, and the second contains material generated by VIVA training sessions, forums, and workshops.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="subseries">
   		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 2.1: Regional Meetings, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>January-July 1995</unitdate>
    		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by a series of regional VIVA meetings held throughout Virginia between April 4 and April 7, 1995. Material includes meeting agendas, minutes and notes, attendance lists, contact lists, logistical information, evaluations, information about software and computer programs and fact sheets.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>Regional Meeting at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 4, 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents produced for the April 4, 1995 regional meeting at Virginia Tech. Materials include meeting agendas and attendance lists.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Regional Meeting at Christopher Newport University, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 5, 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents produced for the April 5, 1995 regional meeting at Christopher Newport University. Materials include meeting agendas, individual attendance lists, and attendance lists by institution.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>Regional Meeting at The University of Richmond, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 6, 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents produced for the April 6, 1995 regional meeting at The University of Richmond. Materials include meeting agendas and attendance lists.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>Regional Meeting at George Mason University, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April 7, 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents produced for the April 7, 1995 regional meeting at George Mason University. Materials include meeting agendas, individual attendance lists, meeting logistical information, correspondence and user services training session evaluations.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Regional Meetings I, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January-April 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from interlibrary loan regional meetings throughout Virginia. Materials include meeting agendas and notes, contact lists, a draft VIVA brochure, presentation slides, Ariel information, workshop information and logistical paperwork, budget information and fact sheets. 
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
           	 	<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Regional Meetings II, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April-July 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from interlibrary loan regional meetings. Materials include VIVA fact sheets, presentation slides outline, overhead transparencies, attendance lists, Ariel information, contact lists, meeting agendas and minutes as well as workshop information.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>User Services and ILL Enhancement Regional Meeting Folders, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April-August 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Four VIVA folders from regional meetings, two from the User Services and two from the ILL Enhancement committees. Material included in the folders are draft brochures, meeting evaluations, attendance lists, meeting agendas, contact lists, information about the VIVA listserv and home page, VIVA fact sheets, ARIEL information, 
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
		</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
   		<did>
		<unittitle>Subseries 2.2: Trainings, Forums, and Workshops, </unittitle>
		<unitdate>April 1995-August 2001</unitdate>
    		</did>
		<scopecontent>
		<p>This subseries contains material generated by VIVA trainings, forums, and workshops held at institutions throughout Virginia. Material includes information about software and computer programs, registration and attendance information, group lists, information about electronic resources, contact lists and directories, meeting agendas, minutes and notes, fact sheets, VIVA packets, copyright information, VIVA Listserv and home page information, VIVA publications, fact sheets, travel reimbursement information, evaluations, ILL guidelines and lending reports.</p>
		</scopecontent>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Workshops, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>April-July 1995</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents from an interlibrary loan workshop at George Mason University. Material includes Ariel information, attendance lists, contact directories, meeting agendas and notes, fact sheets, VIVA listserv and home page information and registration information.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>August 1996 Workshops, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May-August 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from interlibrary loan workshops. Material includes shipping receipts, VIVA listserv and home page information and meeting agendas, minutes and notes.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Ariel Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March-April 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from Ariel workshop held on April 25 and 26, 1996. Material includes a training session proposal and tax information.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Workshops, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>February-April 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from Interlibrary Loan Workshops held on April 1 and 2, 1996 at VCU. Material includes evaluations, meeting agendas and minutes, participant lists, workshop descriptions.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">14</container>
			<container type="Folder">12</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Meeting, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January-February 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from an Interlibrary Loan Meeting held on February 7, 1997. Material includes meeting notes, ILL guidelines and lending reports and a list of loaning libraries.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Community Forum, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1995-July 2000</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from an Interlibrary Loan Community Forum held on January 11, 2000 at UVA. Material includes a list of issues and concerns, group lists, registration and participant lists, contact lists, meeting agendas, notes, Lending information, evaluation forms, forum report and recommendations, also included are agendas from the July 14, 2000 ILL Community Forum.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Community Forum, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1995-January 2000</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents from an Interlibrary Loan Community Forum held on January 11, 2000 at UVA. Material includes three VIVA packets which contain VIVA publications, fact sheets, communication and travel reimbursement information, forum agendas, evaluation forms, ILL guidelines and information, group information, Ariel memos and lending information. 
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>ILL Community Forum, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>July 2000-June 2001</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from an Interlibrary Loan Community Forum held on June 29, 2001 at UVA. Material includes ILL guidelines, copyright information, VIVA listserv and home page information, travel reimbursement information, evaluation forms, attendance lists, meeting notes and comment forms.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">4</container>
			<unittitle>IAC Training User Services, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May 3, 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>A summary of attendees to the IAC database training session with evaluations. The training sessions were held throughout Virginia between March 22 and 28, 1996.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">5</container>
			<unittitle>IAC Training Sessions, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 1997-February 1997</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Correspondence about an IAC database training session. Topics include registration, electronic resources and listserv and homepage information.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">6</container>
			<unittitle>CIA-TF Forum on Access to Electronic Journals, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>January 2000</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from Task Force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access Forum on Access to Electronic Journals. Materials include two VIVA packets which contain VIVA publications, fact sheets, communication information, forum agendas, evaluation forms, presentation slides and travel reimbursement information. Also included are completed evaluation forms.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">7</container>
			<unittitle>Training Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>March-April 2000</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from a VIVA training fair. Materials include a VIVA packet which contains a VIVA publication, fact sheet, travel reimbursement information, fair agenda and an evaluation. Also included is a number of thank you letters thanking people for their assistance at the training fairs.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">8</container>
			<unittitle>Training Fair, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>May-August 2001</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from a VIVA training fair. Materials include two VIVA packets which contains VIVA publications, listserv and home page information fact sheet, travel reimbursement information, fair agendas, evaluations, registration lists and electronic resource descriptions. Also included is directions to Blue Ridge Community College and registration information.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">9</container>
			<unittitle>Event Information Folders, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>June 2001</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Three VIVA information folders from the June 2001 ILL Community Forum. Material included in the folders is VIVA fact sheets, VIVA pamphlets, a forum schedule, ILL guidelines, copyright information, attendance lists, VIVA listserv and homepage information, travel reimbursement information and evaluation forms. 
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">10</container>
			<unittitle>Public Institutions, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>October-November 1998</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from and for VIVA participants in the Dow Jones Training session who belong to public institutions. Material includes, travel reimbursement information, notes, a training session announcement and a memo about supplies for VIVA workshops.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">15</container>
			<container type="Folder">11</container>
			<unittitle>Guide Folders, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>August 1999-March 2000</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Four VIVA information folders from training workshops. Material included in the folders are VIVA fact sheets, VIVA pamphlets, agendas for  "Train the Trainer" Workshop for OVID Technologies, evaluation forms, travel reimbursement information, agendas for a VIVA training fair, campus and building maps and lists of training links. 
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">16</container>
			<container type="Folder">1</container>
			<unittitle>VIVA Information Packets, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>September 1996-May 1997</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Two VIVA information folders from the "VIVA: Poised for the 21st Century" retreat. Material included in the folders are lists of VIVA committees and their members, travel reimbursement information, Kathy Perry's business card, retreat agendas, VIVA fact sheets, cost savings and value added survey executive summaries and executive summaries of the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee Biennial Budget Proposal.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
   			<did>
			<container type="box">16</container>
			<container type="Folder">2</container>
			<unittitle>Coordinated Collection Management Workshop, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 1995-November 1996</unitdate>
   			</did>	
		 	<scopecontent>
                        <p>Documents and correspondence from the Coordinated Collection Management workshop. Material includes two articles by George Soete, workshop objective lists, workshop agendas and notes, a hotel contract, presentation slides and a workshop information packet.
                        </p>
                        </scopecontent>
            		</c03>
			<c03 level="file">
			<did>
			<container type="box">16</container>
			<container type="Folder">3</container>
			<unittitle>George Soete Collaborative Collections Management Project, </unittitle>
			<unitdate>November 1995-January 1996</unitdate>
			</did>
			<scopecontent>
			<p>Documents and correspondence from and about George Soete who was hired as a consultant and facilitated a retreat of the Collaborative Collections Management Projects and the joint session with the VIVA Steering Committee on November 21-23, 1996. Material includes notes from the workshop, University of California Shared Collections and Access Program information, articles by George Soete, a problem assessment worksheet, attendance information and collaborative collections management retreat notes.
			</p>
			</scopecontent>
			</c03>
		</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 3: VIVA Contact Directories, </unittitle>
<unitdate>January 1995-September 2000</unitdate>
<physdesc>(2 boxes)</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains information generated by VIVA contact directories.</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">17</container>
	<container type="Folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>January and March 1995 Contacts Directories, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January-March 1995</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The January and March 1995 contacts directories. Material includes correspondence and the January and March 1995 contacts directories. Also included in the January directory is access information, personnel information, hours and borrowing information for some of the member institution libraries.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">17</container>
	<container type="Folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>January 1996 Contacts Directory, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January 1996</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The January 1996 contacts directory. Material includes VIVA committee lists and two copies of the January 1996 contacts directory.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">17</container>
	<container type="Folder">3</container>
	<unittitle>January 1996 Contacts Directory Rough Draft, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January 1996-January 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Rough drafts of the VIVA contacts directory, with corrections written on almost every page. Material includes correspondence, faxes sent into George Mason University from VIVA member institutions with corrections, 757 area code information, committee lists and a Virginia Community College System Learning Resources Personnel Directory.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">17</container>
	<container type="Folder">4</container>
	<unittitle>October 1996 Contacts Directory, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>May 1996-March 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from and about the October 1996 contacts directory. Material includes a map of participating VIVA institutions, committee lists, notes and the October 1996 VIVA contacts directory. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>March 1997 Contacts Directory, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June 1996-March 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from and about the March 1997 contacts directory. Material includes committee lists, a memo about maintaining contact directories, VIVA fact sheets, and an incomplete copy of the March 1997 contacts directory.  
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>March 1997 Contacts Directory II, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June 1996-March 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents from and about the March 1997 contacts directory. Material includes committee lists, two copies of the March 1997 contacts directory, recommendations for organization structure and VIVA publications.  
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">3</container>
	<unittitle>March 1998 Contacts Directory I, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January-March 1998</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>The March 1998 contacts directory. Material includes a memo about maintaining contact directories, VIVA committee lists and two copies of the March 1998 contacts directory.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">4</container>
	<unittitle>March 1998 Contacts Directory II, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>March 1998-July 1999</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents from and about the March 1998 contacts directory. Material includes correspondence, the March 1998 contacts directory and committee lists. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">5</container>
	<unittitle>September 2000 Contacts Directory, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June-September 2000</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents from and about the September 2000 contacts directory. Material includes correspondence, a response list, the September 2000 contacts directory and committee lists. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">6</container>
	<unittitle>Contact Lists, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January-April 1995</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the compilation of the VIVA contact directories. Material is primarily fax and email correspondence but also includes guidelines for required contact information, a list of school's .pub extensions and budget information.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">18</container>
	<container type="Folder">7</container>
	<unittitle>Committee Lists, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>September 1996-March 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Listing of committee members from the Steering Committee, Collections Committee, Coordinated Collection Management Allied Health and Nursing Subcommittee, Coordinated Collection Management Business Subcommittee, Coordinated Collection Management Science and Technology Materials Subcommittee, ILL Enhancements Committee, Publicity Committee, Special Collections Committee, Technical Issues Committee and User Services Committee.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 4: Cost Saving and Value Added Survey, </unittitle>
<unitdate>July 1994-July 1999</unitdate>
<physdesc>(1.5 boxes)</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains information generated by the cost saving and value added survey. The CSVA survey was sent to VIVA member institutions "to assess the impact of VIVA's shared purchase of electronic resources".</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">19</container>
	<container type="Folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Saving Survey 96-97, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>July 1994-March 1999</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes CSVA survey executive summaries from 95/96 and 96/97, rough drafts and corrections of CSVA information, financial benefit information, notes, budget information, questionnaire responses, narrative summaries and CSVA documents on 2 three and a half inch floppy disks.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">19</container>
	<container type="Folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Saving Survey Final Draft, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>September-October 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes the "final version" of the cost survey on 2 three and a half inch floppy disks, notes, rough drafts of the CSVA survey letter, a blank cost savings and value added survey, lists of journals available from Project Muse, lists of journals available from IAC, a list of journals available from Ideal (Academic Press), IAC Database subscription prices and Quattro Pro on a three and a half inch floppy disk and a three and a half inch floppy disk titled Cost Savings and Value Added Survey 1995-96 Original Documents.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">19</container>
	<container type="Folder">3</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Savings Survey, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June 1996</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes a rough draft of the CSVA survey, a sample of the letter of instruction for the survey, a blank survey, IAC Database subscription prices and Quattro Pro on a three and a half inch floppy disk, a list of journals available from IAC, four three and a half inch floppy disks titled: FT-IAC.WQ1, IAC Databases Subscription Prices Quattro Pro, Charts.VIV in WP 5.1 and IASTitle.1ST UVA (VIVA) ? 6/21/96 as well as draft correspondence about the CSVA survey with edits. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">19</container>
	<container type="Folder">4</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Savings and Value Added Survey Report, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>November 1996-April 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes a portion of the VIVA Contacts Directory, a list of VIVA Institutions, a Cost Survey Report on a three and a half inch floppy disk, the Cost Savings Value Added Survey Report, a rough draft of the survey report with edits, a financial benefits report and the results of the survey.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">19</container>
	<container type="Folder">5</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Savings and Value Added Survey, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>September 1996-July 1999</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes information about the VIVA listserv and home page, contact directory index, budget allocation information, VIVA fact sheet, VIVA electronic resources spreadsheets, a list of VIVA participating institutions, a financial benefits report, budget information, a rough draft of the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, survey results, a lists of participating institutions, a narrative for the survey and completed surveys from J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College, Averett College, Bridgewater College, Emory and Henry College and Ferrum College.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">1</container>
	<unittitle>Cost Savings and Value Added Survey, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>September 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the 1996-1997 cost savings and value added survey. Material includes instructions for filling out the CSVA survey, a blank survey and a list of journals available from project muse. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">2</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Cost Savings Value and Added Survey Documents, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Miscellaneous documents from the cost savings and value added survey. Material includes a CSVA survey narrative and rough drafts of the results of the CSVA survey and two three and a half inch floppy disks with subscription prices worksheets.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">3</container>
	<unittitle>Completed Cost Savings and Value Added Surveys, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June-October 1996</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Completed cost savings and value added surveys from the following institutions (organized alphabetically):  Blue Ridge Community College, Central Virginia Community College, Christopher Newport University, Clinch Valley College, Dabney S. Lancaster Community College, Danville Community College, Eastern Shore Community College, George Mason University, Hampden-Sydney College, Hollins College, J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College, James Madison University, John Tyler Community College, Liberty University, Longwood College, Lord Fairfax Community College, Lynchburg College, Mary Baldwin College, Mary Washington College, Marymount University, Mountain Empire Community College, Norfolk State University, Northern Virginia Community College Alexandria Campus, Northern Virginia Community College Manassas Campus, Old Dominion University, Piedmont Virginia Community College, Radford University, Randolph-Macon Women's College, Rapphannock Community College, Regent University, Richard Bland College, University of Richmond, Roanoke College, Southside Virginia Community College, Sweet Briar College, Thomas Nelson Community College, Tidewater Community College at Chesapeake Campus, Tidewater Community College at Portsmouth Campus, Tidewater Community College Virginia Beach Campus, University of Virginia, University of Virginia Business School, University of Virginia Law School, Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Highlands Community College, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Virginia Union University, Virginia Western Community College, Washington and Lee University, Washington and Lee University Law School, College of William and Mary, College of William and Mary Law School and Wytheville Community College. Also included is instructions for filling out the survey and a completed IAC Databases Full-Text Journals List Worksheet from Virginia Union.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">4</container>
	<unittitle>VIVA-Cost Savings and Value Added Survey, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>June 1996-November 1997</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence from the cost savings and value added survey. Material include instructional letters, a blank survey, a list of journals available from IAC Databases and Project Muse, survey distribution checklists, survey planning subcommittee correspondence, notes and financial benefit lists. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series 5: Miscellaneous Documents, </unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1994-January 2003</unitdate>
<physdesc>(0.5 box)</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains miscellaneous and unfiled documents generated by the Virtual Library of Virginia.
</p>
</scopecontent>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">5</container>
	<unittitle>Allied Health and Nursing Collaborative Collection Project, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>January-March 1999</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents from the Allied Health and Nursing Collaborative Collection Project including email correspondence and travel reimbursement information.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">6</container>
	<unittitle>Publications, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>February 1996-January 2003</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Publications from and about VIVA. Material includes VIVA bookmarks, VIVA informational pamphlets, a VIVA tenth anniversary booklet and a newspaper article from "The Chronicle of Higher Education".
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">7</container>
	<unittitle>1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>September 1997-March 1998</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents about the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal. Material includes four copies of the proposal itself and VIVA announcements.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">8</container>
	<unittitle>Website, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>December 1995-July 1996</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence about the VIVA website. Material includes resource registry information, VIVA logo design, meeting notes, style guidelines for the VIVA website, general VIVA information, a map of VIVA institutions, Britannica Online information, information about available electronic journals, contacts directory and lists of participating institutions.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">9</container>
	<unittitle>Vendor and Client Reviews, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>November 1994-April 1995</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Reviews of vendors and clients for VIVA. Material includes two client reviews, VIVA participation institution organizational charts, a draft of Massachusetts Public Higher Education Libraries Information Technology Recommendations and a program of the November 1994 Vendor Fair.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">10</container>
	<unittitle>Authentication, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>November 1995-April 1998</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Documents and correspondence about authentication, security, and access management issues for VIVA users. Material includes, guidelines for accessing library resources off-campus, network and security information, a list of VIVA member IP addresses, meeting notes, Infotrac information and two documents about user authentication and authorization issues. 
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<container type="box">20</container>
	<container type="Folder">11</container>
	<unittitle>Miscellaneous Documents, </unittitle>
	<unitdate>February 1997-April 1998</unitdate>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Miscellaneous, unsorted documents from VIVA Director Kathy Perry. Material includes a list of drawer contents, a list of VIVA institutional participants, budget information, lending information, "Technologically Delivered Instruction", survey questions and a memo about the VIVA contacts directory.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>
</c01>	
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
