<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViFGM" url="http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/wood.html">http://sca.gmu.edu/finding_aids/wood.html
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Guide to the John C. Wood papers, <date>1956-1974</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">John C. Wood
<num type="collectionnumber">C0115
</num></subtitle>
        <author>FINDING AID AUTHOR
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>George Mason University Libraries
</publisher>
        <date type="publication">2006 By George Mason University Libraries. All rights reserved.
</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by FINDING AID ENCODER, <date>FINDING AID ENCODED DATE</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2019-02-13">2019-02-13</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the TITLE, <date>DATES</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives
<num type="Accession Number">COLLECTION NUMBER
</num></subtitle>
      <author>FINDING AID AUTHOR
</author>
      <publisher>George Mason University Libraries
</publisher>
      <date type="publication">2006
</date>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Special Collections and Archives Staff
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">
        <subarea>George Mason University.</subarea>
        <subarea>Special Collections and Archives.</subarea>
      </repository>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
        <persname>John C. Wood
</persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">John C. Wood papers
</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1956-1974
</unitdate>
      <unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">C0115
</unitid>
      <physloc/>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a">
        <extent>1.5 linear ft.
</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains documents pertaining to Wood's career as mayor, including correspondence on the acquisition of land for George Mason College in the 1960s.
</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no access restrictions.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions on personal use. Permission to publish material from the John C. Wood papers must be obtained from Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University Libraries.


</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>John C. Wood papers, C0115, Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University Libraries.
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Donated by John C. Wood.
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>Processed by Special Collections and Archives staff. EAD markup completed by Eron Ackerman and Jordan Patty in August 2009. Additional processing and EAD markup completed by Hal Barthold in 2011.
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>John C. Wood was elected mayor of the City of Fairfax in 1952 and become the first rector of Mason's Board of Visitors in 1972. In both jobs Wood was a major force in the development of the university and pushed to acquire the land for both the Fairfax and Arlington Campuses.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection contains documents pertaining to Wood's career as mayor, including correspondence on the acquisition of land for George Mason College in the 1960s.
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <head>Arrangement
</head>
      <p>Organized by subject and date.
</p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Special Collections and Archives also holds the George Mason University Archives.
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcsh">Wood, John C.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">George Mason University.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Geographical Names:</head>
        <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Fairfax (Va.)</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Campus planning.</subject>
        <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Local government.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>The Files of John C. Wood, </unittitle>
          <unitdate>1956-1974</unitdate>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The files of John C. Wood, the mayor of Fairfax, Virginia, from 1953 to 1964.
</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Acquisition of Farr Property</unittitle>
            <unitdate>May 1956-June 1959</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence dealing with the acquisition of the Farr property in Fairfax. The Farr property, south of Fairfax, consisted of 150 acres on which to establish the Northern Virginia branch of the University of Virginia. Material includes resolutions, a list of distances from points in northern Virginia to Fairfax and Bowman, fundraising documents, notes and surveys and maps of the proposed sites of the Northern Virginia branch of the University of Virginia.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Advisory Committee I</unittitle>
            <unitdate>March-December 1971</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the George Mason College Advisory Committee of which John C. Wood was the chairman. Material includes a pamphlet announcing a master of education program at George Mason College, meeting agendas and minutes, memos, a report from Lorin A. Thompson, the Chancellor of George Mason College about admissions policies, extensive correspondence about an alleged violation of civil rights in the admissions policy, maps of the campus, a report on the progress of campus construction, by-laws of the advisory committee, committee lists, a report from the committee business manager, a report on the college, a report of academic highlights, a copy of the bill to separate George Mason College from the University of Virginia, a housing listing at George Mason College,  a report from the George Mason College School of Professional Studies to the Advisory Board, a newspaper article titled "Students' Rights Are Discussed", a chart displaying the organization of faculty at George Mason College, a list of duties and powers of the President of the University and an announcement of a graduate history program.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Advisory Committee II</unittitle>
            <unitdate>December 1970-April 1971</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the George Mason College Advisory Committee of which John C. Wood was the chairman. Material includes meeting minutes and agendas, budget information, board meeting logistics, "A Model Bill of Rights and Responsibilities" for higher education, George Mason College Bookstore agreement, a summary of interviews with high school guidance counselors, graduation rates, a map of George Mason Campus, committee lists, a bill of student rights and correspondence, reports, and articles about alleged civil rights violations in the admissions department.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>General File I</unittitle>
            <unitdate>November 1964-October 1966</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the papers of John C. Wood. Material includes meeting agendas and minutes, population figures, budget information, newspaper articles, a telegram, a program for the Association of Virginia Colleges Annual Meeting, committee meeting schedules, fine art loan and donation information, Arthur Arundel business card, admissions reports, a summary of advisory committee accomplishments, press releases and classroom attendance reports. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">1</container>
            <container type="Folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>General II</unittitle>
            <unitdate>April 1963-March 1965</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the papers of John C. Wood. Material includes written notes, newspaper articles, excerpts from addresses by President of UVA Edgar Shannon, a list of Advisory Committee members, speeches, budget information, journal articles and a report on George Mason College by the Planning Department.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Land Acquisition Appraisal File</unittitle>
            <unitdate>May-June 1967</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence about the acquisition of the land on which George Mason College was built. Material includes a table of projected cost of land acquisition and a map of the proposed site. Also included is a spiral bound Appraisal Report, the report contains budget figures, maps, photographs and descriptions of land for sale.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Land of Acquisition File or Board of Control I</unittitle>
            <unitdate>February 1967-August 1970</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the Board of Control for Land Acquisition. Material includes a list of land parcel value estimates, maps of land parcels, a contract for appraisal services, deeds, a receipt, meeting agendas, property accounting information, 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Land of Acquisition File or Board of Control II</unittitle>
            <unitdate>March 1967-May 1969</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the Board of Control for Land Acquisition. Material includes a deed, a description of part of the George Mason College property, maps of George Mason College and the proposed expansion land, property accounting tables, budget information, a list of members of the Board of Control, Board of Control fact sheet, financial summary of operations of Board of Control, a list of legal services with costs for those services and lists of land parcels for sale. 
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="Box">2</container>
            <container type="Folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Land of Acquisition File or Board of Control III</unittitle>
            <unitdate>September 1965-March 1967</unitdate>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents and correspondence from the Board of Control for Land Acquisition. Material includes meeting transcripts. memos, a notice of bond election, a list of questions and future space requirements for George Mason College.
	</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
