<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE 
ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vmi.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vmi_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vmi_contact.xml">
<!ENTITY johnson SYSTEM "http://www.vmi.edu/archives/Manuscripts/ms0341.html" NDATA html>
]>
<ead id="vilxv00024">
   <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b"
   findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924"
   dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1"
   repositoryencoding="iso15511">
      <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Military Institute::Preston Library::Archives//TEXT (US::ViLxV::vilxv00024::A Guide to the Johnson Family Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vilxv00024.xml&amp;#34;"
             countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLxV">PUBLIC
             "-//Virginia Military Institute::Preston
             Library::Archives//TEXT (US::ViLxV::vilxv00024::A Guide to
             the Johnson Family Papers)//EN" "vilxv00024.xml"</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>A Guide to the Johnson Family Papers, 
            <date>1858, 1862-1865</date></titleproper>
            <subtitle id="sort">Johnson Family, Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">mss 00341</num></subtitle>
            <author>Diane B. Jacob</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>Virginia Military Institute Archives</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Virginia Military Institute
               Archives</addressline>
               <addressline>Preston Library</addressline>
               <addressline>Virginia Military Institute</addressline>
               <addressline>Lexington, Virginia
               24450-0304</addressline>
               <addressline>USA</addressline>
               <addressline>Phone: (540) 464-7566</addressline>
               <addressline>Fax: (540) 464-7279</addressline>
               <addressline>Email: archives@vmi.edu</addressline>
               <addressline>URL:
               http://www.vmi.edu/archives/</addressline>
            </address>
            <date type="publication">&#169; 2002 Virginia
            Military Institute</date>
            <p id="usestatement">
               <extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
            </p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from HTML.
         Machine-readable finding aid created by Diane B. Jacob. Date
         of source: 
         <date>2002</date>.</creation>
         <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-16">Feb 16, 2004</date>
            <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Military Institute::Preston
            Library::Archives//TEXT (US::ViLxV::vilxv00024::A Guide to
            the Johnson Family Papers)//EN" "vilxv00024.xml" converted
            from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date normal="2004-02-26">Feb 26, 2004</date>
            <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter>
      <titlepage>
         <titleproper>A Guide to the Johnson Family Papers, 
         <date>1858, 1862-1865</date></titleproper>
         <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb />Virginia Military Institute Archives 
         <num type="Collection Number">mss 00341</num></subtitle>
         <p id="logostmt">
            <extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo" />
         </p>
         <publisher>Virginia Military Institute Archives</publisher>
         <date type="publication">2002</date>
         <list type="simple">
            <head>Contact Information:</head>
            <item>Preston Library</item>
            <item>Virginia Military Institute</item>
            <item>Lexington, Virginia 24450-0304</item>
            <item>USA</item>
            <item>Phone: (540) 464-7566</item>
            <item>Fax: (540) 464-7089</item>
            <item id="email">Email: 
            <extref href="mailto:archives@vmi.edu">
            archives@vmi.edu</extref></item>
            <item>URL: 
            <extref href="http://www.vmi.edu/archives/">
            http://www.vmi.edu/archives/</extref></item>
         </list>
         <list type="deflist">
            <defitem>
               <label>Processed by:</label>
               <item>Virginia Military Institute Archives Staff</item>
            </defitem>
            <defitem>
               <label>Funding:</label>
               <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
            </defitem>
         </list>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection">
      <runner placement="footer">Archives, Preston Library, Virginia
      Military Institute</runner>
      <did>
         <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
         <repository>Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military
         Institute</repository>
         <unittitle label="Title">Johnson Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1858;
         1862-1865</unitdate></unittitle>
         <unitid label="Collection number">mss 00341</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">The papers consist
         of 26 letters filed in one box.</physdesc>
         <langmaterial label="Language">
            <language langcode="eng">English</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
         <accessrestrict>
            <head>Access</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </accessrestrict>
         <userestrict>
            <head>Use Restrictions</head>
            <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
         </userestrict>
         <prefercite>
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Johnson Family Papers, mss 00342, Virginia Military
            Institute Archives, Lexington, VA 24450.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <altformavail>
            <head>Alternative Form</head>
            <p>The Johnson Family Papers are available in full-text
            format on the VMI Archives website at: 
            <extref entityref="johnson">
            http://www.vmi.edu/archives/manuscripts/ms0341.html</extref></p>
         </altformavail>
      </descgrp>
      <bioghist>
         <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Mortimer Howell Johnson,</emph>a lawyer
         was born at Bridgeport, Harrison Co. West Virginia in 1815. He
         married Eliza Dulaney Kemble, b. Kingwood, Preston Co., West
         Virginia. The Johnson Family resided in Brownsburg, Rockbridge
         County, Virginia at beginning of the Civil War, and Mortimer
         enlisted in April 1864 (at age 48)in the Rockbridge Senior
         Reserves. He was described as having a dark complexion, dark
         hair &amp; eyes, 5' 6". He died December 13, 1889, at
         Charleston, West Virginia and is buried at the High Bridge
         Presbyterian Church cemetery, Rockbridge Co., Virginia. He was
         the father of Porter Johnson, Virginia Military Institute
         Class of 1867.</p>
         <p>
         <emph render="bold">Porter Johnson</emph>was born in 1845 in
         Taylor County, West Virginia. He matriculated at the Virginia
         Military Institute on September 1, 1863 and was a cadet
         private at the Battle of New Market on May 15, 1864. Porter
         resigned from Corps of Cadets on March 6, 1865 and joined the
         8th Confederate Battalion commanded by Col. Garnett Andrews.
         He was captured at Salisbury, NC on April 12, 1865 and
         imprisoned, and was paroled June 13, 1865. He returned to
         Rockbridge County where he was a farmer. He died June 9,
         1917.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent>
         <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
         <p>The papers consist of 26 letters, bulk 1862-1865, from
         Mortimer Johnson and his son Porter to members of their
         immediate family. The Johnson family, originally from West
         Virginia, moved to Brownsburg in Rockbridge County, Virginia,
         although they maintained close ties to their former home.
         Topics in Mortimer's letters include civilian life during the
         war; the animosity between Union and Confederate sympathizers
         in West Virginia (the letter of April 28, 1863 discusses the
         Union loyalty of Stonewall Jackson's sister, Laura Jackson
         Arnold); the Battle of Fredericksburg and its aftermath (Dec
         1862); the Jones- Imboden Raid (West Virginia, April 1863).
         Porter's letters include a discussion of VMI cadet life at the
         Alms House in Richmond, Virginia, where the Corps was
         headquartered during the last months of the war.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <dsc type="in-depth">
         <head>Contents List</head>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <emph render="bold">Mortimer Johnson
                  Correspondence,</emph>
                  <unitdate type="inclusive">
                     <emph render="bold">1858; 1862-1865</emph>
                  </unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Leake Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1858 February 10</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Richmond, Virginia. Contains family
                  news; comments on work of the state legislature. 
                  <lb />"The legislature is working very slow and not
                  doing much good for the country. The House is not in
                  session yet this morning. At 8 o'clock I left my
                  boarding house came by the Post Office and barber
                  shop at half past 9 in the house and engaged in
                  writing this letter to you. The house meets at 11
                  o'clock and adjourns about 3 o'clock, so that we get
                  dinner at half past 3. Sometimes the house does not
                  adjourn until later. You set down in the house with a
                  comfortable cushioned chair to sit upon, a desk
                  before you to write upon and it frequently happens
                  that while a member thinks he is making a very fine
                  speech, one half the members are engaged in writing
                  letters or reading newspapers. I suppose you have
                  heard of the fight that happened in Congress last
                  Saturday. It was disgraceful to the Nation and the
                  men that were engaged in it are heartily ashamed of
                  it...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to C. W. Newlon, 
                  <unitdate>1862 February 2</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Brownsburg, Virginia. Regarding the
                  inflated prices of grain used to produce whiskey for
                  soldiers. 
                  <lb />"...The North expected to starve us out when
                  the war commenced. All that recognize a
                  superintending providence had cause to thank the
                  giver of daily bread last year for our unusually
                  heavy crop of all kinds of grain. It was every where
                  considered as an evidence that the Lord was on our
                  side. Grant that it was so will he continue to be if
                  we abuse his choicest favors-- if we convert
                  ourselves into a nation of extortioners and have for
                  our soldiers an army of drunkards. Grant as some
                  contend that liquor is necessary for the soldiers
                  should not a limit be placed upon the price of it .
                  Liquor for which 3 dollars per gal is paid after
                  running the blockade of the camp is frequently sold
                  to the soldier at the high price of from one to five
                  dollars per pint. If it is necessary for the soldier
                  it should be added to his rations and handed out
                  under proper rules and regulations and every other
                  person detected in smuggling liquor into the camp
                  should be summarily and severely punished...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1862 September 20</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Staunton, Virginia. Contains family
                  news; expresses concerns about high cost of food.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter fragment to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1862 late October</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Family news; mentions woman who is a Union
                  sympathizer; Porter is eager to join the army. 
                  <lb />"...His idea is that a man has but one time to
                  die and that a few years more or less will not make
                  any difference. He says that he is able to carry a
                  musket and that if he does not raise his arm in
                  defence of his country under existing circumstances
                  he shall never feel like asking a Southern woman to
                  marry him and that a northern woman he would not have
                  under any circumstances."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1862 December [ca.
                  15th]</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written shortly after the Battle of
                  Fredericksburg, Virginia. 
                  <lb />"...Our loss in the fighting that has taken
                  place is 1742 in killed and wounded. Our dead have
                  been buried. The Yankee dead remain unburied. The
                  field of battle is still in dispute. The Yankees have
                  not asked the privilege of burying their dead and we
                  cannot [venture] to do it. Ours were carried off
                  during the fight. We occupied the best position and
                  think the enemy loss 5 to our one. I have just been
                  to take a look at the Yankee Army. They are drawn up
                  in line of battle, but as it is now 4 o'clock we do
                  not think there will be a fight today. The principal
                  fight was on Friday--though in sight we feel
                  secure...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Porter, 
                  <unitdate>1862 December 18</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written after the Battle of Fredericksburg,
                  Virginia. 
                  <lb />"...The loss of the abolitionists in the last
                  battle near Fredericksburg was greater than we at
                  first supposed. They are again on the other side of
                  the River. I spent yesterday afternoon in going over
                  a portion of the battle field near or adjoining the
                  City. On the portion of the field I visited there
                  were at least 500 dead. Under a flag of truce they
                  were burying their dead but doing it in a very
                  careless manner. Unless they worked last night they
                  cannot get through before sometime today. After going
                  through Fredericksburg and seeing the results of
                  their vandalism I felt no sympathy for their justly
                  merited fate. Scattered books, broken [----],
                  furniture of all kinds and every description carried
                  into the streets and broken to pieces. Our own loss
                  is narrowed down to less than 400 killed and less
                  than a thousand wounded, while the loss of the enemy
                  cannot be less than 2000 killed and from 10 to 20
                  thousand wounded and missing. All who have visited
                  the ground concur in the opinion that the dead are
                  thicker upon the ground than any [field] they have
                  seen. One could have walked for 400 yds upon the
                  dead...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1862 December 25</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>References to the Battle of Fredericksburg;
                  personal news. 
                  <lb />"... Porter did not arrive here until the dead
                  were buried so that he missed a sight. I have very
                  much desired he should see under the hope it would
                  lessen his desire to join the army before he is
                  18...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1862 December 29</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Family and business news. 
                  <lb />"...I sold the wagon, harness and the two old
                  horses for 625 dollars including the horse I had when
                  you arrived. I thought it better to keep the two
                  young mares for the present. Porter was offered 300
                  dollars for the bay mare today but thinks she will
                  bring more money. I have heard nothing of the butter
                  and apples left at Staunton and Waynesboro and
                  probably never will. If so I shall lose by my
                  investment as I sold what arrived here for cost and
                  expenses. You had better have your apples opened and
                  see that they are not rotting. These that arrived
                  here had rotted considerably...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter 
                  <unitdate>1862 undated
                  fragment</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Regarding family friends who have been wounded;
                  refugee families; problem with currency. 
                  <lb />"...If you get any money either get gold or
                  valley money do not trust to N. W. Virginia money and
                  for this reason--If in the tide of War our armies
                  should ever win the N West your money will not be
                  good, as the men having charge of the banks will
                  leave and carry with them the specie...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 January 25</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Family news; mentions situation in West
                  Virginia.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 March 10</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from Lynchburg, Virginia. Remarks on
                  inflated prices. 
                  <lb />"...Here you see nothing and hear nothing but
                  tobacco--save when a soldier steps up to pay his bill
                  or asks what he will have to pay for a days board and
                  is answered 5, 6 or 7 dollars. I feel satisfied from
                  his look, that he wishes all these people in
                  Yankeedom and their town in ashes. I do not feel
                  hopeful at this time as to the result of the contest.
                  I do not fear that Yankees can whip us, but I do fear
                  that the desire of gain, the thirst for money will
                  yet overwhelm us. ..."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 March 14 and 15</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Misc. family and business news.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 March 29</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Misc. family and business news.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 April 25</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Beverly, West Virginia, regarding
                  situation there. 
                  <lb />"...Beverly was taken yesterday after about two
                  hours cannonading and some but not much skirmishing
                  of infantry. The abolitionists were about 1300 in
                  number. Latham succeeded in burning all his stores.
                  [He] succeeded in getting away in the direction of
                  Philippi with little or no loss of men. Our cavalry
                  pursued, but I fear without any success...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 April 28 and May
                  1</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at "Hillery's, 9 miles west of Beverley."
                  Regarding Jones-Imboden Raid, West Virginia; Union
                  sympathies of Laura Jackson Arnold. 
                  <lb />"...Had Jackson been in command we would have
                  been in Clarksburg today, The railroad would have
                  been destroyed. When we turned back almost every man
                  was dissatisfied--all wanted to fight the enemy
                  without regard to numbers. Mrs. J. Arnold 1 --sister
                  of Gen. Jackson--went off with the yankees. Arnold
                  stayed at home says he is a good southern man, that
                  his wife is crazy but Hell he says, could not govern
                  a Jackson...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1863 May 5</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Weston, West Virginia. References to
                  Jones-Imboden Raid and burning of bridge at Fairmont.
                  <lb />"...Gen. Jones arrived at Buckhannon Saturday
                  morning, having been at [ ], Morgantown, Fairmont,
                  [Skinnston], Bridgeport, Philippi. We immediately
                  marched to Weston arriving here on Sunday morning.
                  Beyond Evansville the Railroad was torn up for a
                  considerable distance. The fine bridge at Fairmont
                  was [blown] down. There was a fight at Fairmont,
                  several killed, 400 prisoners taken. 3 killed at
                  Bridgeport &amp; c. Gen Jones command brought in 1200
                  horses taken from Union and secession men without
                  pay...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1864 September 23</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from Camp Kemper, near Staunton. Regarding
                  the Battle of Winchester, Virginia. 
                  <lb />"...The enemy in far superior number attacked
                  Early about day light. We held our own until 3 oclock
                  driving the enemy some two miles--at which time our
                  Cavalry upon the left embracing Vaughan's, Imboden's,
                  McCausland's, and Wickham's brigade gave way. This
                  placed the enemy's cavalry in Winchester in the rear
                  of our infantry and close upon our wagon train. The
                  wagon train would have been destroyed but for the
                  large number of stragglers with the train--the Yankee
                  Cavalry mistaking them for a strong guard. Our
                  infantry retired fighting saving the train and all
                  the artillery but 3 pieces...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1864 October 11</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Richmond, Virginia. Contains general
                  family, business and war news.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson 
                  <unitdate>1864 December 4</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Lexington, Virginia. Contains family
                  and business news.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to Eliza Johnson, 
                  <unitdate>1865 March 7</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at Lexington, Virginia. General Sheridan
                  is in valley.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>
                  <emph render="bold">Porter Johnson
                  Correspondence,</emph>
                  <unitdate>
                     <emph render="bold">1865</emph>
                  </unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to his sister, 
                  <unitdate>1865 January 12</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from the Alms House in Richmond, Virginia,
                  where VMI was headquartered from December 1864 until
                  Richmond was evacuated in April 1865. 
                  <lb />"...We are very poorly fixed here for study,
                  twenty in a room, one small table, no chairs or
                  stools, but one gas burner, and attached to the side
                  of the wall instead of the center of the room where
                  it ought to be. There is but one little stove in the
                  room and the meanest coal that you can imagine. We
                  have but two meals a day which is quite often enough
                  of the kind, bread and beef for breakfast and beef
                  and bread for dinner...."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to his father, 
                  <unitdate>1865 February 5</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from the Alms House in Richmond, Virginia,
                  where VMI was headquartered from December 1864 until
                  Richmond was evacuated in April 1865. General
                  news.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter 
                  <unitdate>1865 February 23</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from the Alms House at Richmond, Virginia.
                  Porter has decided to join the army. 
                  <lb />"...I feel it due to myself as well as to you
                  to state to you some of the reasons I have for
                  leaving here and giving up the only opportunity which
                  I shall perhaps ever have of getting an education. In
                  the first place I am past nineteen years old and I
                  think that it is my duty to be in the army. All who
                  stay here after they become eighteen are generally
                  considered shirkers. Then I do not think that the
                  school will continue much longer than the first of
                  April, for is it reasonable to suppose or can it even
                  be expected that in this the death struggle of the
                  Confederacy when every man woman and child should be
                  at his or her post, when every nerve is to be
                  strained to attain the object which we have so long
                  fought for, that two or three hundred well drilled,
                  able bodied men will be allowed to remain idle and
                  inactive? I am sure the answer of any rational man
                  will be No!"</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to his father, 
                  <unitdate>1865 March 27 (#1)</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at New's Ferry. He has joined the army. 
                  <lb />"...I resigned about two weeks ago. I have been
                  in the trenches one week since, with the Corps. It
                  then took me a week or such a matter to make my
                  arrangements to leave the city. I have accepted the
                  place I wrote you about, and am now on my way to join
                  my command, it is at Charlotte, NC. I would like very
                  much to have come home before going into the army,
                  but the way not being open when I had the time at my
                  own disposal I did not attempt it."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to his mother, 
                  <unitdate>1865 March 27 (#2)</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written at New's Ferry. General news; sends
                  love.</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="item">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Letter to his mother, 
                  <unitdate>1865 June 16</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent>
                  <p>Written from Prison Hospital, Camp Chase, Ohio. 
                  <lb />"The order for release of prisoners has at last
                  arrived. I expect to be released in about a week. It
                  is a bitter pill but has to be swallowed. I do not
                  expect to be home immediately. J.W. McCorkle is sick,
                  he expects to go to his Uncles in Cabell county. I
                  must go with him. He would do the same for me and
                  more. Then I will go by West Va. I shall stop a few
                  days then hasten home as fast as possible. I am in
                  good health."</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
