<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vircuh00030">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViRCU-H">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::Tompkins-McCaw Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vircuh00030::Alton D. Brashear
Collection)//EN" "vircuh00030.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Alton D. Brashear Collection
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Brashear, Alton D. Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">ACC 136
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jody Romero
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Jody Romero, <date> 16 September, 2005 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Alton D. Brashear
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
<num type="Accession Number">ACC 136
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jody Romero
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Jody Romero
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Brashear, Alton D. Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1935-1955
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">ACC 136
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">2.5 linear feet.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Brashear, Alton D. Collection, Accession #ACC 136, Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donor Unknown. Part of the Tomkins-McCaw Library basement collection.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Originally processed 23 January, 1983
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>Alton Dean Brashear was born in Fort Smith, Arkansas on 17 March, 1906. He earned his DDS at Ohio State University in 1932 and interned at the University of Rochester where he earned a masters in anatomy.
Brashear taught anatomy at Louisiana State University from 1935 to 1938 when he left to accept a position at the Medical College of Virginia. At MCV, Brashear taught anatomy for over fifty years.
</p>
<p>Brashear was a member of the Army Reserve Medical Corps and taught anatomy courses for the Army. When World War II began, Brashear was assigned to the 45th General Hospital, a unit made up from staff of the
Medical College of Virginia where he served as Chief of Dental Services. After the war, Brashear wrote a history of the unit titled From Lee to Bari.
</p>
<p>Brashear was a member of several medical and dental societies including the American Association of Anatomists, American Dental Association and the Richmond Academy of Medicine. An accomplished photographer,
Brashear was a member of the Richmond Camera Club and served as a judge in several photograph competitions. He also took many of the photographs included in his book on the history of the 45th General Hospital.
</p>
<p>Brashear died in Richmond, Virginia on 30 June 1963 at the age of 57. A postgraduate course in the anatomy of the head and neck, initially taught by Brashear in 1954, was named in his honor by MCV after his
death.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Alton D. Brashear Collection is primarily the information, documents and materials gathered together to write the history of the 45th General Hospital. This Army medical unit was staffed by faculty from the
Medical College of Virginia during World War II. Brashear served as the Chief of Dental Services.
</p>
<p>The collection includes official papers, orders, personnel files and other documents relating to the initial training and operation of the hospital unit before and after its deployment to North Africa and
Italy. The collection also includes notes and material gathered by Brashear to write the unit's history From Lee to Bari, including page proofs and photographic layouts along with donations from Betty Brown and
Carrington Williams.
</p>
<p>The collection focuses on Brashear's activities encompassing his military service and his association with the 45th General Hospital. Information regarding his post war activities is rare and limited to his
academy endeavors.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection follows the original arrangement.
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>
