<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vircuh00051">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRCUH">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::Tompkins-McCaw Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vircuh00051::A Guide to the Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications, 1911-1958)//EN" "vircuh00051.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications, <date>1911-1958</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications
<num type="collectionnumber">2013/Feb/26
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Margaret T. Kidd
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 2014 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All rights reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Margaret T. Kidd, <date>19 March 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications, <date>1911-1958</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
<num type="Accession number">2013/Feb/26
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Margaret T. Kidd
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1911-1958
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">2013/Feb/26
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Shelved with the small collections.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>52 items, 1 folder</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Crippled Children's Hospital (Richmond, Va.)
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Crippled Children's Hospital photographs and publications, Accession # 2013/Feb/26, Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The donor for this collection is unknown.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Crippled Children's Hospital of Richmond, Virginia began as the result of an infantile paralysis epidemic in 1917 that left the affected children without a facility for treatment. Dr. William T. Graham, an orthopaedic surgeon, and Nancy Minor, superintendent of the Instructive Visiting Nurses' Association (INVA), recognized the need and began a free outpatient clinic in the basement of Graham's office located at 214 East Franklin Street. Within six months, the clinic treated more than 80 patients, yet proved inadequate to assist all in need. Outpatient treatment moved to the dispensary at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV). In 1918, the Virginia General Assembly passed a bill appropriating $20,000 over two years for the treatment of disabled children from the entire state. This money funded two wards at MCV for two years, but this was only temporary.
</p>
<p>A group of citizens, including Graham, Minor, and Dr. Ennion G. Williams the commissioner of the Virginia State Department of Health, met in June 1919 to discuss a hospital specifically for Virginia children disabled by birth defects, accidents, and diseases such as polio. From this meeting grew the Crippled Children's Hospital Association, dedicated to organizing and funding the hospital. Dooley Hospital on Marshall Street became the temporary location until they could finance and construct a new facility. The Woman's Auxiliary formed in 1920 to support the hospital and by 1924, they created a similar group to serve the disabled African American children cared for at St. Philip Hospital. Philanthropic groups such as Kappa Delta sorority and the Kiwanis Club also donated time and money to the hospital.</p>
<p>In 1923, the Crippled Children's Hospital Association purchased a house and one acre of land at Brook Road and Sherwood Avenue for use as a convalescent hospital. A bequest from Sally M. Dooley in 1925 allowed the purchase of additional property adjacent to the Book Road house for the construction of a 40-bed facility. Architect Henry Baskervill designed the new facility to resemble the Hospital of the Innocents (Ospedal degli Innocenti) in Florence, Italy complete with the della Robbia medallions, which became the symbol of the hospital. Construction began in 1927 and the hospital opened in 1928. </p>
<p>Services at the hospital grew and changed over the years. From a children's hospital for those with orthopaedic problems it developed into a multi-specialty hospital for all children. In 1982, the facility changed its name to Children's Hospital of Richmond, which reflected its broader mission. The hospital still operates today at its originial location on Brook Road with several thearpy centers in the area. In 2010, it joined with VCU Health Systems to form the Children's Hospital of Richmond at VCU. </p>
<p>for addional information on the history of the hospital please see <title render="italic">Crippled Children's Hospital : The First Sixty Years</title>, by Marjorie Branner Adams. This book is available in the TML Special Collections &amp; Archives Reading Room (RD705.5.V82 R522 1979)</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains photograhps, newspaper clippings, a magazine, and a promotional booklet for the hospital. The collection provides some insight into the early history and services of the hospital as well as the children who were patients.
</p>
<p>The photographs are undated with the exception of one labeled 1911, of a female adolescent with scoliosis. This photographs predates the clinc and hospital. The majority of the photographs are of patients and staff at the convalescent hospital located at Brook Road and Sherwood Avenue. This suggests that those photographs date from the mid 1920s as the house used for the convalescent hospital was purchased in 1923. Several were taken after the hospital was built in 1928. There is one 6.5" x 4.5" album and 32 loose pictures.</p>
<p>Also in this collection is a promotional booklet for the hospital from the late 1940 or early 1950s, which provides information on the history of the hospital, a listing of the staff and the board of trustees, and an overview of the services provided. There is a 1956 issue of <title render="italic">The Angelos of Kappa Delta</title>, which includes the history of Kappa Delta sorority's support of the hospital, a call for continued participation, a photo spread of the hospital, an article about Dr. William T. Graham, and a letter from Karaleen Ingersoll, the hospital administrator, thanking the sorority for it's generosity.</p>
<p>Found also in this collection are newspaper clippings mostly pertaining to the passing of Graham in 1953, and one clipping from 1917, regarding the appointment of Graham as an orthopaedist for the Medical College of Virginia War Unit.</p>
</scopecontent>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
  <corpname rules="dacs">Children's Hospital of Richmond at VCU (Richmond, Va.).</corpname>
            <corpname rules="dacs">Crippled Children's Hospital (Richmond, Va.).</corpname>
            <persname rules="dacs">Graham, William Tate, 1873 - 1953</persname>
            <persname rules="dacs">Ingersoll, Karleen</persname>
            <corpname rules="dacs" source="local">Medical College of Virginia.</corpname>
            <subject source="mesh">Hospitals--History--Virginia</subject>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
