<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vircuh00052">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRCUH">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::Tompkins-McCaw Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vircuh00052::A Guide to the Saul Kay papers, 1939-2000)//EN" "vircuh00052.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Saul Kay papers, <date>1939-2000</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Kay, Saul papers
<num type="collectionnumber">2014/Apr/3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Margaret T. Kidd
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 201 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All rights reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from being created directly into EAD, created by Margaret T. Kidd, <date>7 April 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Saul Kay papers, <date>1939-2000</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
<num type="Accession number">2014/Apr/3
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Margaret T. Kidd
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Saul Kay papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1939-2000
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">2014/Apr/3
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Shelved with the oversized, small collections.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Size" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>27 items</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Kay, Saul, 1914-2004
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p> Saul Kay papers, Accession # 2014/Apr/3, Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donor unknown.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
        <bioghist id="ref20">
            <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
            <p>Saul Kay was born February 13, 1914 in New York, New York. A violin player, Kay initially planned to become a professional musician. He studied with a private teacher and in a conservatory, but he wanted to attend college. At that time colleges did not offer degrees in music, so he decided to study medicine instead. Kay attended New York University and while pursing his pre-med studies he served as concertmaster of the university orchestra. He graduated from New York Medical College in 1939 and after completing his pathology residency in 1942, was drafted for service as part of the Army Medical Corps during World War II. Kay served for four years, rising to the rank of major and awarded the Bronze Star for his service.</p>
            <p>After the war, Kay completed residencies in pathology with the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Columbia Presbyterian Hospital in New York City. At Columbia he trained under noted pathologist Arthur Purdy Stout. Kay became a member of the Arthur Purdy Stout Club, which formed in Stout's honor in 1947. The group still exists today as the Arthur Purdy Stout Society of Surgical Pathologists.</p>
            <p>The Medical College of Virginia (MCV) recruited Kay in 1950, where he began the surgical pathology division. Kay was known for his "patient first" approach to medicine and was an early advocate of cervical cancer screenings. He served as department chair until 1979 at which time he was granted professor emeritus status. Kay continued to work at VCU Medical Center until 1996 and also consulted at McGuire Veterans Affairs Medical Center. The medical school recognized Kay's dedication to teaching by naming a faculty award in his honor in 1995. There is also a Saul Kay Chair in Diagnostic Pathology established at the school in 1997.</p>
            <p>Kay never gave up his love of music. He continued to play after being advised by his teacher, Louis Persinger, that he might enjoy music more if it was not his profession. He played while pursing his medical degree and during his military service he managed to borrow a violin wherever he was stationed. When Kay came to Richmond he helped form the Lakeside String Quartet. He also assisted in the creation of the Richmond Symphony which began in 1957. Kay served as first violinist in the symphony from 1957 to 2000.</p>
            <p>Kay passed away on January 7, 2004. He is interred at Arlington National Cemetery. He was married to Grace Calef Kay, also a physician, and they had a daughter, Deborah.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent id="ref1">
            <head>Scope and Contents note</head>
            <p>The collection is composed mostly of Kay's diplomas and certificates related to his medical education and career along with a prescription and treament notebook, photographs, official documents (medical licence), a letter from the MCV Pathology Department, and a resolution from the Richmond Symphony. It also includes some diplomas and certificates for his wife, Grace Calef Kay, who attended New York Medical College and completed a residency at Harlem Hospital in New York at the same time as her husband. The photographs are all group images taken while Kay was a resident at Columbia University Presbyterian Medical Center and at various annual Arthur Purdy Stout Club meetings. This is a very small collection, but it provides some information about the path of Kay's medical education, residencies, and career.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <controlaccess>
            <persname rules="aacr">Kay, Saul, 1914-2004</persname>
        </controlaccess>
        <dsc type="in-depth">
        <head>Contents List
        </head>
      <c01 level="file">
      <did>
      <unittitle>Certificates and diplomas
      <unitdate type="inclusive">1939-1985
      </unitdate>
      </unittitle>
      <container label="Folder" type="folder">1
      </container>
      <physdesc><extent>13 items </extent>
      </physdesc>
      </did>
      <scopecontent>
      <p>Includes New York Medical College diploma, 1939; Contin Society certificate, 1939; National Board of Medical Examiners, 1941; Harlem Hospital, intern-medical service 1941; Fordham Hospital, resident in pathology, 1942; New York Post Graduate Medical School and Hospital, resident in pathology, 1948; American Board of Pathology certificate for pathologic anatomy, 1949 and clinical pathology, 1951; Presbyterian Hospital, resident in surgical pathology, 1950 (signed by Arthur Purdy Stout); State Board of Medical Examiners of Virginia certificate, 1950; College of American Pathologist, fellow, 1955 and emeritus fellow, 1982; and American Society of Clinical Pathologists, fellow, 1956.
      </p>
      </scopecontent>
     </c01>
     
     <c01 level="file">
     <did>
     <unittitle>Certificates and diplomas, Grace Calef Kay
     <unitdate type="inclusive">1941
     </unitdate>
     </unittitle>
     <container label="Folder" type="folder">2
     </container>
     <physdesc><extent>3 items</extent>
     </physdesc>
     </did>
     <scopecontent>
     <p>Includes National Board of Medical Examiners, 1941; Harlem Hospital, intern-medical service, 1941; and University of the State of New York, medical license, 1941.
     </p>
     </scopecontent>
    </c01>
    
    <c01 level="file">
    <did>
    <unittitle>Letter, from MCV Dept. of Pathology
    <unitdate type="inclusive">1996
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
    <container label="Folder" type="folder">3
    </container>
    <physdesc><extent>1 item</extent>
    </physdesc>
    </did>
    <scopecontent>
    <p>A letter from the department recognizing Kay for his dedication and stating that a portrait has been commission of him to be displayed in the Division of Surgical and Cytopathology.
    </p>
    </scopecontent>
    </c01>
    <c01 level="file">
    <did>
    <unittitle>Notebook, prescription and treatment
    <unitdate type="inclusive">circa 1947
    </unitdate>
    </unittitle>
    <container label="Folder" type="folder">4
    </container>
    <physdesc><extent>1 item</extent>
    </physdesc>
    </did>
    <scopecontent>
    <p>Contains the handwritten notes by Kay on prescriptions and treatments for various conditions.
    </p>
    </scopecontent>
   </c01>
   <c01 level="file">
   <did>
   <unittitle>Official documents 
   <unitdate type="inclusive">1950
   </unitdate>
   </unittitle>
   <container label="Folder" type="folder">5
   </container>
   <physdesc><extent>2 items</extent>
   </physdesc>
   </did>
<scopecontent>
    <p>Medical license and document stating Kay has been added to the medical register by the clerk of the Hustings Court in the City of Richmond.
    </p>
    </scopecontent>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate type="inclusive">no date, 1953-1954, 1966
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">6
</container>
<physdesc><extent>6 items</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
</c01>
<c01 level="file">
<did>
<unittitle>Richmond Symphony resolution
<unitdate type="inclusive">2000
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Folder" type="folder">7
</container>
<physdesc><extent>1 item</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
    <p>A resolution passed by the board of directors recognizing Kay for his service to the symphony for 43 years.
    </p>
    </scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc> 
    </archdesc>
</ead>