<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vcu.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vcu-tm_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vircuh00024">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViRCU-H">PUBLIC "-//Virginia Commonwealth University::Tompkins-McCaw Library::Special Collections and Archives//TEXT (US::ViRCU-H::vircuh00024::Samuel C. Mitchell
Collection)//EN" "vircuh00024.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Samuel C. Mitchell Collection
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Mitchell, Samuel C. Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">84/Mar/10
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jody Romero
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By Virginia Commonwealth University. All Rights Reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from typescript, created by Jody Romero, <date>June 22, 2005 </date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Samuel C. Mitchell
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
<num type="Accession Number">84/Mar/10
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Jody Romero
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Jody Romero
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title">Samuel C. Mitchell Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date">1911-1913
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number">84/Mar/10
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">.25 Linear Feet
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Title], Accession #[ ], Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>This collection was donated by Dr. Benjamin Sheppard.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>Samuel Chiles Mitchell was born in Coffeeville, MS on 24 December 1864. A noted educator, Mitchell receives M.A. from Georgetown (TN) College in 1888. From 1889-1891, Mitchell teaches history and Greek at
Mississippi College, then returns to his alma mater in 1892 to teach Latin. He earns his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1899.
</p>
<p>Mitchell will become first associated with Richmond, VA after 1895 where he taught History at the University of Richmond. Mitchell becomes President of the University of South Carolina in 1908, but in 1913 he
was asked to return to Virginia
</p>
<p>The Medical College of Virginia and the University College of Medicine were two rival institutions ever since 1893, when faculty split from MCV, forming their own medical school. This rift had been widened due
to several incidents, like a fire that destroyed the main UCM building, and graffiti vandalism. After several months of talks the two college presidents, Dr. George Ben Johnston and Dr. Stuart McGuire, decided to
merge the two schools. Mitchell was asked to become the first president of the newly integrated Medical College of Virginia. While only in office a short time, Mitchell presidency was able to guide MCV back to
prominence. Mitchell then leaves to become President of what is now the University of Delaware in 1914.
</p>
<p>Mitchell would return to Richmond in 1920 to resume teaching History at the University of Richmond, a position he would keep until his retirement in 1945. He died 20 August, 1948.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Collection contains newspaper clippings from Richmond, Virginia area newspapers from 1911 to 1913. It chronicles the rivalry between the schools, Mitchell's appointment as President and the early
integration efforts. The Collection is limited to only what was in the newspapers during these years and is not a complete representation of Mitchell's career.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is arranged in chrological order.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="item">
<did>
<unittitle>Scrapbook; Newspaper clippings.
<unitdate type="inclusive">Jul. 1911 to Dec. 1913
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<container label="Box-folder" type="box-folder">1
</container>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains newspaper articles primarily by the Richmond Times-Dispatch, and Richmond News Leader. The Scrapbook focuses on the medical schools and the issues that surrounded them. Topics include the
sale of Memorial Hospital, graffiti attacks on the school, the merger of the Medical College of Virginia and the University College of Medicine, and the closing of the Old Dominion Hospital.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
