<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViAr00133">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViAr">PUBLIC "-//Arlington Public Library::Center for Local History//TEXT (US::ViAr::ViAr00133::A Guide to the Records Related to the September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, 2001-2008)//EN" "ViAr00133.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Records Related to the September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, <date>2001-2008</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, Records Related to the
<num type="collectionnumber">RG 133
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Heather Crocetto
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/arlington_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 2019 Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History<!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Gregory Pierce, <date>8 October 2020</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Records Related to the September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, <date>2001-2008</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History <lb/><!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Accession number">RG 133
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/APLlogo.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher> Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication" normal="2019-09">2019
</date> 
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer"> Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a"> Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History <!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Records Related to the September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">2001-2008
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RG 133
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>6 boxes</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p> The collection is open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Michael T. DeFina, Jr., retains copyright for all donated photographs.  Credit for photograph(s), regardless of the manner it/they is/are displayed, and the copyright holder must be contacted prior to display.  There are no copyright restrictions on the other material in this collection.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Records Related to the September 11, 2001 Terrorist Attacks on the Pentagon, Collection # RG 133, Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
</p>
<p>Contact Michael T. DeFina, Jr., for the preferred citation of his materials.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Michael T. DeFina, Jr., donated photographs in this collection in April 2002. Diane Kresh donated photographs in February 2018. Center for Local History staff received the correspondence from the Arlington County Fire Department in the spring of 2002 and received the County Manager materials in October 2018.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The September 11th terrorist attacks on the Twin Towers of the World Trade Center in New York and on the Pentagon in Washington, DC, left an indelible mark on this nation's history. For residents of the Washington-metro area and of Arlington County in particular, that day was especially difficult as the attack on the Pentagon happened "close to home."  
</p>
<p>Terrorists hijacked a west coast-bound plane taking off from nearby Dulles Airport and deliberately crashed it into the Pentagon. The Arlington County Fire Department responded quickly to the attack and over the course of three days brought the fire under control, searched for survivors, and then later recovered the dead. The County Manager, Ron Carlee, coordinated the response by fire, rescue, and police personnel from both Arlington and surrounding jurisdictions, and dealt with the media. Over time, Carlee sought analyses of the emergency response to prepare for the future and developed support systems for County employees involved in the Pentagon response. 
</p>
<p>People from the immediate area and around the country sent letters and thank you cards (most handwritten or homemade) to members of the Arlington County Fire Department in appreciation of their efforts to fight the fire and rescue survivors. Like many places around the country, Arlington County held ceremonies and observances commemorating those who perished and celebrating the heroic efforts by people inside the Pentagon and by the Arlington County Police and Fire Departments.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Record Group 133 is primarily made up of textual materials, but also contains photographs and some memorabilia and audio-visual materials. The entire collection consists of 2.5 linear feet and date between 2001-2008, with the bulk of the material dating 2001-2002. This collection has three very different subgroups. 
</p>
<p><title render="italic">Subgroup 1, Photographs</title>, contain photos of the Pentagon on September 11th and in the immediate days afterwards. Series in the subgroup are for each photographer. For Series 1, the photographs were taken by Michael DeFina on September 11th immediately after the attack and during the two days following. The photos depict scenes ranging from harrowing and heroic (fire crews fighting the enormous blaze) to quiet and eerie (the collapsed building facade or fire fighters resting between shifts). De Fina was a firefighter for the Washington Airport Authority that was called to the Pentagon. Series 2 contains images taken by Diane Kresh, who in 2001 was an Arlington resident and worked at the Library of Congress. At the time she donated these photographs, she was the Director of the Arlington Public Library.
</p>
<p><title render="italic">Subgroup 2, Correspondence</title>, consists of thank you cards or letters to the Arlington County Fire Department. Most of the correspondence comes from school children, but there are cards and letters from organizations and from other concerned individuals. The schools involved are from all over the United States, and some are from unidentified groups and individuals.
</p>
<p><title render="italic">Subgroup 3, County Remembrance and Response</title>, holds materials created by Arlington County in the days, months, and even years after the September 11th attacks. Series 1 in this subgroup has the County Manager's working files, which relay his day-to-day itineraries, talking points, and emails, and his reference files, which are reports on emergency response and preparedness in general and evaluating Arlington activities specifically. These documents are an excellent view on how Arlington County government responded to the attack on the Pentagon directly after the attack and how they put together long-term emergency preparedness plans and did outreach to the county's citizens and employees. Reports on the county's September 11th activities are in Series 2, After-Action Reports. Series 3 relates to Arlington's attempts to remember the attacks in ceremonies and memorials. The memorabilia in this series consists mainly of posters, flyers, and small artifacts from the two County-sponsored memorial services held in remembrance of the terrorist attacks. There are also VHS tapes recording memorial services and concerts.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Record Group 133 is divided into three subgroups: Photographs, Correspondence, and County Remembrance and Response. <title render="italic">Subgroup 1, Photographs</title>, is arranged by photographer, with each one getting a separate series. Series 1, Michael De Fina, is arranged according to a scheme devised by the photographer. There is a list created by Mr. DeFina in which he describes each of the photographs. This list is located in the front of the first folder for Subgroup 1, Series 1. 
</p>
<p><title render="italic">Subgroup 2, Correspondence</title>, is divided into three series: Identified Organizations, Identified Individuals, and Unidentified. Series 1, Identified Organizations, contains documents from schools, after-school groups, churches, and other religious organizations. It is filed alphabetically by organization. At the end of Series 1 is a folder entitled Miscellaneous Organizations which consists of identified organizations with a small number of correspondence (usually five items or less). It is arranged alphabetically by organization. Series 2, Identified Individuals, is arranged alphabetically by first name rather than last name because many individuals did not provide surnames. Series 3, Unidentified, contains all items that could not be identified by organization or individual name and is unarranged.
</p>
<p><title render="italic">Subgroup 3, County Remembrance and Response</title>, consists of three series. Series 1, County Manager's Files, are materials from County Manager Ron Carlee. Subseries 1 are Carlee's working papers. They are arranged in Carlee's original order and his folder titles are used in quotation marks [""]. Subseries 2 are reference materials used during the response and are arranged chronologically. Series 2, After-Action Reports, is also arranged chronologically. Any folder titles in quotes are titles retained from the original folders or are the official titles of the report in the folder. This is especially true of Series 2. Series 3, September 11th Remembrance, contains flyers and posters announcing memorial services organized by Arlington County. There are also two "grab bags" from those services containing ephemera, such as a copy of the program for the event, a miniature U.S. flag and a pin. Both series are arranged chronologically. All artifacts and oversized materials have been placed in appropriate housing. There are also several VHS tapes recording different memorial events.
</p>
<p>Folders with oversized materials have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added.
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>For more information on the Arlington County Fire Department, see <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=arlington/ViAr00170.xml"><title render="bold">RG 170, Personal Papers of James Fought</title></extref>. The Center for Local History conducted oral histories with Arlington County Fire Department staff and other 9/11 reminisces in Oral Histories, Series 5 (<title render="bold">VA 975.5295 A7243oh ser.5</title>). Of particular importance is the interview with James Schwartz, who was the Officer in Charge on that day.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess>
<head>Index Terms</head>
<controlaccess>
<head>Subjects:</head>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Pictoral works</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">Pentagon (Va.)</subject>
<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650$a">First responders.</subject>
<geogname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington (Va.)</geogname>
<geogname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="651$a">Arlington County (Va.)</geogname>
</controlaccess>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Subgroup 1">Photographs
<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 1">Michael DeFina Photographs
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Photographs, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 2">Photographs, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 2">Diane Kresh Photographs
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Photographs, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Subgroup 2">Correspondence
<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 1">Identified Organizations
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Blackburn Elementary, Ellenton, Florida
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 2">Brock Bridge Elementary School, Laurel, Maryland
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 3">Central Elementary School, Edgewater, Maryland**
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 4">Centre Ridge Elementary School, Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 5">Centre Ridge Elementary School, Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 6">Centre Ridge Elementary School, Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 7">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Mrs. Gilmore's 1st Grade Class), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 8">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Mrs. Leckley's 2nd Grade Class), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 9">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Mrs. Odom's 4th Grade Class), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">1
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 10">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Puzder), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 11">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Mrs. Tucker), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 12">Centre Ridge Elementary School (Whaley), Centreville, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 13">Christian Fellowship, Ashburn, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 14">Collegiate School, Richmond, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 15">Cornerstone Home School Group, Renton, Washington
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 16">Double Churches Middle School, Columbus, Georgia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 17">Ellettsville Elementary School
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 18">Gonzaga College High School, Washington, DC
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 19">Harvest Church, Toledo, Ohio
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 20">Kids Care Club (General), Washington, DC
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 21">Kids Care Club (Volunteer Center of Durham, North Carolina)
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 22">Kids Care Club (Louisville, Kentucky)
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 23">Rivendell School, Arlington, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 24">Robinson School
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 25">St. George's Episcopal Day School, Clarksdale, Mississippi
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">2
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 26">St. George's Episcopal Youth Group, Arlington, Virginia
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 27">Sidwell Friends School, Washington, DC
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 28">Tyee Middle School, Bellevue, Washington
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 29">Will Carleton Academy, Hillsdale, Michigan
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 30">Zion Lutheran School (Grade 8), Bethalto, Illinois
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 31">Miscellaneous Organizations**
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 2">Identified Individuals
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Identified Individuals**
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 2">Identified Individuals - Kim Fuller, et al
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 3">Unidentified
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Unidentified, ca.
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">3
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="Subgroup 3">County Remembrance and Response
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 1">County Manager Files
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Subseries 1">Working Papers
		</unittitle>
		</did>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 1">Carlee Working Papers, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001-09-11/2001-09-18">9-11-01 to 9-18-01
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 2">"Jurisdictional Support," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 3">"Security," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 4">"FEMA," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 5">"County Security," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 6">"Donations," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 7">"Economic Recovery," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>

			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 8">"EOC [Emergency Operations Center], 9/01," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 9">"National [Airport] 01," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 10">"9/11 Economical Impact," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 11">"Recognition of 9/11 Staff," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 12">"5/8/02 - DPP Bio Weapons Table Top Exchange," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 13">"Water System Risk Assessment," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>, n.d.
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 14">"Employee Assistance Programs," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 15">"EOC," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>, n.d.
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">3
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 16">"9-11 Speeches," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>, n.d.
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 17">"9-11 Anniversaries," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2003">2001-2003
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 18">"9-11 Memorial," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Subseries 2">Supporting Materials
		</unittitle>
		</did>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 1">Threat Assessments and Funding, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000/2001">2000-2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 2">County Board Statements, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 3">"Information Update 9/17/01, Public Affairs," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 4">"Federal Installations - Security," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 5">Opening and Closing of National Airport, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 6">"Pentagon Disaster Support by Arlington County and Mutual Aid Partners, 9/11-9/26/01," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 7">Remembrances and Lessons Learned, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2002">2001-2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 8">Arlington Civic Federation Preparedness Guide, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 9">Hazardous Materials and Supplies, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 10">"9-11 Articles," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2003">2001-2003
			</unitdate>**
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">4
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 11">"Preparedness - Citizen Corps," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001-10">October 2001
			</unitdate>(1)
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 12">"Preparedness - Citizen Corps," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001-10">October 2001
			</unitdate>(2)
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 13">"Preparedness - Citizen Corps," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2003
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 14">ELT Meeting Notes, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2002-11">November 2002
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 15">"Arlington County Office of Emergency Management Plan Summary, Fiscal year 2004," 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2004
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 16">Critical Incident Management Guide Sheet, n.d.
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
			<c04 level="item">
			<did>
			<unittitle label="File 17">Mental Health of Arlington Employees, 
			<unitdate type="inclusive">2001
			</unitdate>
			</unittitle>
			<container label="Box" type="box">5
                        </container>
			</did>
			</c04>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 2">After Action Reports
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">"Arlington County Conference Report: Local Response to Terrorism, Lessons Learned from the 9-11 Attack on the Pentagon," n.d.
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 2">"Arlington County After Action Report on the Response to the September 11th Attack on the Pentagon," 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
		</unitdate>(1)
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 3">"Arlington County After Action Report on the Response to the September 11th Attack on the Pentagon," 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
		</unitdate>(2)
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 4">Press Materials for After Action Report News Conference, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 5">"Arlington County September 11th Public Relations Campaign, Final Report," 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 6">"Your Guide to Emergency Preparedness," NVRC, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2003
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">5
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 7">"NFPA1710 Standards, Challenges for the Future," 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">2004
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">6
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Series 3">September 11th Remembrance
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="File 1">Announcements, Poster, and Other Ephemera, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2002">2001-2002
		</unitdate>**
		</unittitle>
		<container label="Box" type="box">6
                </container>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>AV Materials (Box 6)
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Arlington County - September 11 Highlights Reel" (VHS)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Arlington Remembers: 9/11 Commemorative Concert at the Netherlands Carillon" (VHS)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Arlington's Day of Remembrance and Appreciation, October 7, 2001" (VHS, three copies boxed separately)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Gateway Park Flay Drop Ceremony, Arlington Flags Unfurled, 9/11 Memorial 5K, September 11th, 2002" (VHS)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"The Pentagon: September 11th and the Aftermath" (VHS, two copies)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Arlington County After Action Report on the Response to the September 11th Attack on the Pentagon," 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2002
	</unitdate>(CDs, two copies)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>"Pentagon 9-11 Memorial Dedication, 9-11-2008" (CD)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
