<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viltblviletbl00240">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">

<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLTBL::viltblviletbl00240::A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 1831-1970; 1981)//EN" "viltblviletbl00240.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, <date>1831-1970; 1981</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Wilbur C. Hall Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Gabrielle Sanchez
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml" />

<date type="publication">2014 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Elizabeth E. Preston, <date>26 March 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, <date>1831-1970; 1981</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection number">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">

<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Laura Christiansen, Lisa DeZarn, Alexandra S. Gressitt, Mary Pender, and Gabrielle Sanchez
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1831-1970; 1981
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2 cu. ft. (5 boxes, 4 oversize folders; 9 VC folders)</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County.  There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Physical characteristics and conditions affect use of this material.  Photocopying not permitted. Visual materials may require special handling.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Wilbur C. Hall Papers (M 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2012.0025; 2012.0026
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Laura Christiansen, Lisa DeZarn, Alexandra S. Gressitt, Mary Pender, Gabrielle Sanchez, 2004, 2012, and 2014
</p>
<p>
NOTE: For ease of access, diaries (1811-1820) of Samuel B.T. Caldwell were processed separately as SC0004.</p> 
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Born in Leesburg, VA on February 7, 1892, Wilbur C. Hall is noted for his career as a lawyer, state legislator, orator, and public figure. Graduating from Washington and Lee School of Law in Lexington, VA in 1915, Hall served in the United States Navy during World War I.  In 1918, at the age of 24, he was elected to the Virginia General Assembly and served on the Assembly until 1935. He served as Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission from 1935-1939, and authored or sponsored important and influential legislation.
</p>
<p>Wilbur Hall also had a legendary career as a lawyer; he was called a "lawyer's lawyer" and "the best prepared lawyer before the bar of any court in Virginia." Hall contributed to the legal profession in numerous ways, being widely cited in case law and also serving as a supporter of Washington and Lee University's law program. He made several sizable gifts to the law school program during his lifetime, including a loan fund for deserving law students, and left the majority of his estate to Washington and Lee University. In 1967 Washington and Lee bestowed an honorary doctorate degree upon him. Hall noted this as being "the happiest moment of my life." Following his death in August 1972, the law school library, which he helped develop, was named Wilbur C. Hall Law Library.</p>
<p>Hall was a founding member of the Rotary Club of Leesburg and belonged to numerous civic and fraternal organizations. As a public figure and noted orator, he was in demand as a speaker and frequently spoke on historical topics.  An amateur historian, Hall also contributed to the preservation of historical landmarks and local historic sites. As Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission he helped to create a state historic marker program, establishing a number of markers for Loudoun county historic sites, including the site of Revolutionary war figure John Champe. Hall published articles about Champe and other historical topics of interest to him in a variety of journals. While Hall was a popular speaker and contributor to publications, it should be noted that he hired researchers to complete much of his writing and historical inquiries.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County.  There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life.  The collection is organized into two series.
</p>
<p>Series I consists of documents relating to his research into the history of Loudoun County and surrounding areas. The materials are organized alphabetically by subject.  The documents include transcripts of speeches he gave on various historical topics to organizations such as the American Legion, Lion's Club, Rotary Club, Ruritan Club, Loudoun County Chamber of Commerce, local historical societies and others. Also included are associated correspondence and research materials, including publications, maps, historical accounts, clippings and notes.  Correspondents include:  J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1898-1986); W. J. Barrow (1904-1967); Armistead L. Boothe (1907-1990); Mary Brackett (Mrs. Scott) Bowen (1887-1974); Omar N. Bradley (1893-1981); Benjamin H. Branch, Jr. (1919-1993); Wiley T. Buchanan, Jr. (1914-1986); Bryan Conrad (1870-1950); Elbert Cox (1906-1993); Cecil B. Dickson (ca. 1899-1986); E. Griffith Dodson (1923-1962); H. J. Eckenrode (1881-1952); Eugenia T. Fairfax (1873-1966); David E. Finley, Jr. (1890-1977); Marshall W Fishwick (1923-2006); Caroline B. Furness (1922-2007); R. K. Gheen (1914-1974); Stilson H. Hall (1893-1981); George P. Hammerly (1921-1984); Huntington Harris (1914-1993);  B. Powell Harrison (1911-2000); William J. Heffner (1909-1995); Laurence G. Hoes (1900-1978); George A. Horkan, Jr. (1926-2005);  Carlisle H. Humelsine (1915-1989); Eppa Hunton, IV; (1904-1976); Patrick J. Hurley (1883-1963); Asa Moore Janney (ca. 1908-2002); W. Pat Jennings (1919-1994);  Aurelia M. (Mrs. Walter T.) Jewell (1900-1992); Marven Jones (1882-1976); George Harrison Sanford King (1914-1985); George C. Marshall (1880-1959); Katherine Marshall (1882-1978); H(erbert) A. Martz (1898-1990); Frank P. Moncure (1889-1969); Benjamin Muse (1898-1986) Millard C. Myers (1883-1975); Lawrence F. O'Brien, Jr. (1917-1990); Carleton Penn (1922-2009); Lucas D. Phillips (1904-1994); Forrest C. Pogue, Jr. (1912-1996);  Joseph E. Profitt (1876-1958); W. Griffith Purcell (1912-1983); Jennings Randolph (1902-1998);  A. Willis Robertson (1887-1971); Clarence L. Robey (1884-1969); John W. H. Spencer (1919-2011); William B. Spong, Jr. (1920-1997); Stuart Symington (1901-1988); [Dorothy] Ullrich Troubetzkoy (1914-2003); William M. Tuck (1896-1983); Robert Whitehead (1897-1960); and Conrad L. Wirth (1899-1993). </p>
<p>Series II is made up of original nineteenth century documents collected by Wilbur Hall in the course of his historical research.  These documents include letters, public notices, legal documents, and advertisements originating from Loudoun County and surrounding areas.  They are organized chronologically.</p>
<p>The collection also contains a scrapbook of newspaper clippings chronicling Wilbur Hall's political activities, and two artifacts.  There is a United States flag with 46 stars which belonged to General George C. Marshall and an undated "Christmas card" (a photograph of Wilbur Hall pasted onto a wooden stand).</p>
<p>The visual materials consist of sixteen photographs of various sizes and formats dating from 1866-1968. Photographs feature Wilbur Hall or were collected by him in the course of his research into a variety of historical topics.  Organization of the photographs fall into two series: Series I consists of four folders containing photographs from research projects (speech or paper); Series II contains portrait images of Wilbur Hall.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Box: folder
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">

<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<p><bibref>Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Alumni, Biographies, Wilbur C. Hall, http://law.wlu.edu/alumni/bios/hall-wilbur.asp (accessed 2 February 2012).
</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Wilbur C. Hall Papers (M 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Out of the Attic, Volume 2, February Birthday, 25 February 1982.</bibref></p>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>Past Perfect catalogue records
</p>
</otherfindaid>
</descgrp>


</archdesc>
</ead>





