<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viletbl00191">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00191:: Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection  1973-2006)//EN" "viletbl00191.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection , <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-2006</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection 
<num type="collectionnumber">M 068
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Teckla H. Cox
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Elizabeth Preston, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">4 November 2011</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection , <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-2006</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">M 068
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Teckla H. Cox
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Teckla H. Cox
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-2006
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 068
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection consists of scrapbooks dating from 1974 to 2006, and material containing application forms (1986-1988) relating to the biannual preservation awards. The material also contains a letter from the society nominating Elizabeth Smith for the Loudoun County Commission on Women Award in 1999. Included in the collection are two video cassettes, one titled "Merit Winners Edit #3," and one "Preserving Our Heritage."
</abstract>
      <origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Loudoun County Preservation Society
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection open for research.
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection, 1973 - 2006 (M 068), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA..
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Loudoun County Preservation Society
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </altformavail>
      <accruals>
        <head>Accruals
</head>
        <p>2007.0007, 2008.0056, 2010.0162, 2011.0009X
</p>
      </accruals>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>Teckla H. Cox, 30 September 2011
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Historical Information
</head>
      <p>In 1973 two Loudoun County women, Evelyn Johnson and Mary Alice Wertz, were troubled by changes in the landscape of Loudoun County. Trees were being cut down in Leesburg, the Army Corps of Engineers planned to build a dam on the Potomac River at Seneca that would flood much of northern Loudoun County, and a developer wanted to build a regional shopping center at the intersection of Routes 7 and 28. By 14 February 1974 the women, joined by ten other concerned citizens, organized the Preservation Society of Loudoun County "to preserve the natural and cultural heritage of Loudoun County." They were soon joined by others and began their activity with a trip to Charleston, South Carolina. 
</p>
      <p>One of the society's first projects was to successfully lobby Loudoun County for the preservation of a row of houses on Edwards Ferry Road immediately east of the jail. It also worked to save the Valley Bank building, and gave contributions to such preservation projects as the Aldie Mill restoration and restoration of the Purcellville railroad station. In the1980s it monitored the possible mining of uranium in Virginia. It held workshops to educate Loudoun's citizens on preservation and worked for the preservation of wetlands and protection of mountainsides. The society tracked legislation on the local and state levels as it pertained to land use policy and preservation, including revisions to zoning ordinances of both Loudoun County and the Town of Leesburg. It monitored development in Loudoun County, particularly major land use changes such as the building of Ashburn Village and the development of the Shelburne Glebe property. </p>
      <p>In 1980 the society began a major project of presenting biannual preservation awards to encourage preservation and restoration by individuals and businesses. The society made the awards at its annual membership drive and party, held on a date near Valentine's Day, and at a summer gala. Both of these events were generally held in historic homes.</p>
      <p>Members made an annual trip to Richmond where they met with and made their wishes known to legislators. While in Richmond they visited at least one historic site in the city. Members also traveled to other historic cities and towns, studying preservation methods in each. </p>
      <p>In 2008 the society merged with the Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society, a group with similar interests but which had a narrower purpose, primarily to raise money to support restoration and preservation of historic buildings in Loudoun County. The new organization, called the Loudoun Preservation Society, will cover virtually all aspects of historic, cultural, and environmental preservation.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>The collection consists of scrapbooks dating from 1974 to 2006, and a folder of application forms (1986-1988) relating to the biannual preservation awards. The folder also contains a letter from the society nominating Elizabeth Smith for the Loudoun County Commission on Women Award in 1999. Included in the collection are two video cassettes, one titled "Merit Winners Edit #3," and one "Preserving Our Heritage."
</p>
      <p>The scrapbook dated 1983-1984 consists of newspaper articles about preservation related projects, such as adoption of a plan for the rural areas Loudoun County and articles regarding whether to demolish or to renovate the Valley Bank building in the court house square. There are a number of photographs, primarily of Edwards Ferry Road houses which the society was instrumental in saving. There are a few photographs taken on trips the group took to historic places. </p>
      <p>Scrapbook 1985-1987 contains further material on the Rural Plan and Valley Bank building as well as the society's consideration of new development projects. Preservation workshops sponsored by the society are noted. </p>
      <p>Scrapbook 1990-1992 contains material on the sale and preservation of Shelburne Glebe, the Cemetery Committee and preservation of wetlands. There are few photographs in this scrapbook except those in newspaper articles. The society's Public Process Workshop in 1990 is also noted.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook 1993-1997 has few photographs and primarily consists of printed items, notably articles on the Disney proposal for a theme park in neighboring Prince William County, and a history of the society. It contains material on a historic preservation and tourism program sponsored by the society entitled "An Afternoon of Discovery." This scrapbook also documents the inaugural Preservationist of the Year award, presented in 1995.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook 1995 is concerned only with the society's sponsoring of a show on "Arts and Letters in Loudoun County" featuring particularly Dagmar Wilson's (1916-2011) paintings of sites in rural Loudoun County as well as local writers.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook 1998-2001 contains a great many photographs of the 24th Valentine reception and the 25th anniversary of the society, the annual trip to Richmond, a trip to New Jersey and one to Savannah. There are a number of pamphlets and folded documents.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook 2003 contains very few photographs but has a number of articles about the County's program for the purchase of development rights.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook 2005-2006 contains copies of "En Garde," the Society's newsletter, newspaper articles, and brochures. It also contains emails to and from committee members, agendas, and minutes from several committees and the executive board.</p>
      <p>Also included in the collection are folders containing application forms for the Historic Preservation Awards Program for 1986 and 1988, and the nomination letter from the society proposing Elizabeth Smith for the Loudoun County Commission on Women Award in 1999 as well as two video cassettes: Merit Winners and "Preserving Our Heritage."</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <otherfindaid>
        <head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <phystech encodinganalog="538$a">
        <head>Technical Requirements
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </phystech>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Preservation Society of Loudoun County Cemetery Committee Records, 1990 (M 006), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Folder 1">Applications, Historic Preservation Awards Program,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986 and 1988
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Folder 2">Nomination, Loudoun County Commission on Women Award,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Video Cassettes
	</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985-1989
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1997
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook, Arts and Letters in Loudoun County,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1995
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998-2001
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983-1984
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1990-1992
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="item">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Scrapbook,
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2005-2006
	</unitdate></unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
