<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00066">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viltble00066:: Catoctin Dam Project Papers 1974-1975)//EN" "viltble00066.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Catoctin Dam Project Papers, <date>1974-1975</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Catoctin Dam Project Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">SC 0011
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca Ottinger
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date>26 February 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Catoctin Dam Project Papers, <date>1974-1975</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">SC 0011
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca Ottinger
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Rebecca Ottinger
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Catoctin Dam Project Papers
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1974-1975
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0011
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">3 folders
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">In mid-1974, announcements were made almost simultaneously by the Fairfax County Water Authority and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers that Catoctin Creek was a prime candidate for a dam and reservoir impounding water for a 7-day supply for the Washington, DC area during drought periods.  This plan would have flooded more than 3,000 acres of Loudoun County, including the hamlet of Taylorstown, VA and part of Waterford, VA.  Residents of this area organized the Catoctin Valley Defense Alliance to fight the project. Their strategies included 1) Achieving "scenic river" designation for Catoctin Creek  2) Having Taylorstown listed on the National Register of Historic Places   3) Getting an amendment to Virginia's eminent domain statute preventing one jurisdiction from obtaining water supply from a neighboring jurisdiction without permission of the affected jurisdiction  4) A public relations campaign to bring attention to this action.  The collection contains letters, articles, notes, and other information from 5 Jun 1974 until 28 Jan 1975.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect the use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Catoctin Dam Project Papers, 1974-1975 (SC 0011), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library, VA
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>1990.0002
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Rebecca Ottinger, 11 Sep 2006</p>
<p>Formerly filed as NUCMC 7</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>In mid-1974, announcements were made almost simultaneously by the Fairfax County Water Authority and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers that Catoctin Creek was a prime candidate for a dam and reservoir impounding water for a 7-day supply for the Washington, DC area during drought periods.  This plan would have flooded more than 3,000 acres of Loudoun County, including the hamlet of Taylorstown, VA and part of Waterford, VA.  Residents of this area organized the Catoctin Valley Defense Alliance to fight the project. Their strategies included 1) Achieving "scenic river" designation for Catoctin Creek  2) Having Taylorstown listed on the National Register of Historic Places   3) Getting an amendment to Virginia's eminent domain statute preventing one jurisdiction from obtaining water supply from a neighboring jurisdiction without permission of the affected jurisdiction  4) A public relations campaign to bring attention to this action.  </p>
<p>The first part of the plan was to get the Commonwealth of Virginia to name Catoctin Creek a scenic river; this action would provide protection by the state through the Commission on Outdoor Recreation.  The County of Loudoun decided to seek this status for both Goose Creek and Catoctin Creek and to concentrate on Goose Creek first.  The Catoctin Valley Defense Alliance, recognizing that, because of the amount of work necessary to obtain this status, it was highly unlikely that Loudoun County would get two creeks named in the same year, approached the Commission and offered to do much of the work necessary to achieve this designation for Catoctin Creek.  The Piedmont Environmental Council prepared the technical report and members of the Alliance obtained the necessary signatures of two-thirds of the affected landowners, and from the owners of two-thirds of the riparian land.  With this preparatory work done, a bill to declare Catoctin Creek a scenic river was introduced into the Virginia General Assembly by Senator Charles Waddell and was passed.  The effect of this action was twofold: 1) No obstruction can be built on this stream without legislative approval   2) It gave notice to the Army Corps of Engineers that the State of Virginia would not passively let them take whatever action they wished.</p>
<p>The second strategy involved gaining historic status for the small village of Taylorstown.  This effort involved approximately sixty four acres belonging to five landowners in the central part of the community which would have been the deepest part of the reservoir.  They were successful in obtaining listing on the National Register of Historic Places.  This designation would not prevent any action, such as building a dam; however, it would require that whatever federal agency proposed the action would be required to prepare an environmental impact statement, thus slowing the action.</p>
<p>The third plan of attack was to seek an amendment to Virginia's eminent domain statute, a proposal also being sought by a legislator in Tidewater Virginia.  House Bill No. 921, introduced into the House of Delegates of the Commonwealth of Virginia on February 11, 1974, contained the following wording, "No municipal corporation, after July one, nineteen hundred seventy-four shall construct, provide or operate without the boundaries of such municipal corporation any water supply system prior to obtaining the consent of the county or municipality in which system is to be located;...."  Representing the Alliance, Anna Hedrick and Philip Ehrenkranz (b 1939) testified at the legislative hearings in support of the bill, which was passed by the General Assembly of Virginia in 1975.</p> 
<p>Finally the Alliance launched a public relations and political campaign to gain attention by the media and elected officials for this struggle.  During the mid-1970s, newspapers including The Washington Post, The Richmond News-Leader, and all those in Loudoun, published editorials condemning the dam proposal.  Congressman Frank R. Wolf (b 30 Jan 1936), Senator Charles Waddell, and Delegates Earl E. Bell (b 10 May 1920) and Kenneth B. Rollins (b 16 Jan 1936) all came out against it.  The Loudoun County Board of Supervisors unanimously approved resolutions opposing the project, and members of the Fairfax Board opposed it as well.</p> 
<p>The successful strategies employed by the alliance served to put the would-be dam into governmental limbo.  Ehrenkranz, who had been appointed by the Board of Supervisors as Loudoun's representative to The Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments (COG) Water Committee, monitored all developments relevant to area water supply.  A highly significant development occurred in 1979, when the technical staff of the Interstate Commission on the Potomac River Basin released a study concluding that adequate water supplies could best be assured by interconnecting the area's existing reservoirs.  The Corps did not react to this alternative for over a year.  Then, at a meeting attended by Ehrenkranz at COG in 1981, a Corps representative announced that the Catoctin project would be abandoned.  Ehrenkranz was advised off-the-record that among the factors motivating the Corps decision were the interconnection proposal and public opposition to the dam and reservoir.</p> 
<p>Two years would pass before the Corps announcement was confirmed in its 1983 edition of "Water Forum Notes."  The headline reads, "Corps Study Concludes That Future Water Supply Needs Can Be Met With Existing Resources."  Importantly, the article states, "Development of Local Reservoir sites (including Catoctin Creek) undoubtedly would fact strong publish opposition which would likely represent a significant obstacle to implementation."</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains letters, articles, notes, and other information from 5 Jun 1974 until 28 Jan 1975.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Interview, Philip Ehrenkranz, 27 Nov 2006.</bibref>
<bibref>United States Congress, Biographical Directory of the United States Congress, http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=W000672</bibref>
<bibref>Commonwealth of Virginia, Virginia House of Delegates: http://dela.state.va.us/dela/Membios.nsf/94f6e9b9c9b5678f85256b1b00732227/5cd1606dcacb8ff985256c1b0058cac8?OpenDocument</bibref>
<bibref>Commonwealth of Virginia, Virginia House of Delegates: http://dela.state.va.us/dela/Membios.nsf/94f6e9b9c9b5678f85256b1b00732227/0e5ab4283068357a85256c0900517e0d?OpenDocument</bibref>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List</head>
<c01 level="item"><did><unittitle>Letters, Articles and Notes<unitdate type="inclusive">, 1974, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle><container label="Folder" type="folder">1</container></did>
     <scopecontent><list type="simple">
     <item>Letter dated 29 Aug 1974 from H.H. Douglas to Miss Anna Hedrick offering assistance in stopping construction of dam on. Catoctin Creek </item>
     <item>Letter dated 15 Oct 1974 to Phillip Ehrenkranz seeking information concerning houses on a tour</item>
     <item>Attached to previous letter but undated notes regarding: Taylorstown Mill, the John S. Hutchison House, Foxton Cottage, Clover Hill, Conrad Virts' House.  Blank sheets listing Footloose, Fancy Free, Hunting Hill, and Catoctin Mill Farm</item>
     <item>Letter, undated, but after tour to Raynold Cheronis about his house</item>
     <item>Letter dated 16 Oct 1974 to Raynold Cheronis regarding his house which would be flooded by the dam on the Catoctin Creek.</item>
     <item>Notes dated 10-28-74 </item>
     <item>Memo dated 4 Nov 1974 to members of Fairfax County Board of Supervisors from Supervisor Audrey Moore regarding control of water supply projects</item>
     <item>Letter of 7 Nov 1974 from Audrey Moore concerning control of water supply projects</item>
     <item>Memo dated 25 Nov 1974 from Audrey Moore to Fairfax County Board of Supervisors regarding responsibility for water projects</item>
     <item>Notes dated 12-12-74 listing names of people to contact regarding the dam project.</item>
     <item>Correspondence dated 18 Dec 1974 seeking help in stopping construction of Dam on Catoctin Creek.  Each letter mentions enclosure of current issue of <title render="italic">Echoes of History</title>.</item>
     <item>Letters to H.H. Douglas in response to letters of 18 Dec 1974</item>
     <item>Undated notes of names, addresses and phone numbers</item>
     <item>Article by Ray Cheronis regarding his house, Foxton  Cottage, Taylorstown, VA</item>
     <item>Miscellaneous undated notes</item>
     <item>Undated, unsigned notes regarding the proposed Catoctin Dam Project and its effect Taylorstown</item>
      </list></scopecontent></c01> 
<c01 level="item"><did><unittitle>Letters, Articles and Notes<unitdate type="inclusive">, 1974, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle><container label="Folder" type="folder">2</container></did>
     <scopecontent><list type="simple">
     <item>Article entitled "Millford," dated 26 Aug 1974 by John G. Lewis</item>
     <item>Ticket for Taylorstown House Tour, 12 Oct 1974</item>
     <item>Article by Raynold Cheronis entitled "Restoration Project"</item>
     <item>Undated article entitled "Catoctin Valley Threatened by Dam"</item>
     <item>Undated notes</item>
     <item>Copy of Code of Virginia 15.1-1239-15.1-1270, 15.1-1285-15.1-1310, 15.1-1056-15.1-1266</item>
     <item>Title Notes in Reference to Stone House and 1 plus acres, Ray and Ruth Cheronis</item>
     <item>Catoctin Valley Report, 30 Aug 1974, prepared by the staff of Piedmont Environmental Council, Warrenton, VA</item>
     <item>Article dated 9-15-74 from the Catoctin Valley Defense Alliance, P.O. Box 11, Waterford, Virginia 22190</item>
     </list></scopecontent></c01> 
<c01 level="item"><did><unittitle>Letters, Articles and Notes<unitdate type="inclusive">, 1974, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle><container label="Folder" type="folder">3</container></did>
     <scopecontent><list type="simple">
     <item>"New Metropolitan Water Study," <title render="italic">Piedmont Virginian</title>, 5 Jun 1974</item>
     <item>"Hamlet to Fight Watery Demise," <title render="italic">Washington Star-News</title>, 9 Jun 1974</item>
     <item>"Taylorstown residents ready to fight," <title render="italic">Piedmont Virginian</title>, 12 Jun 1974</item>
     <item>"Taylorstown organizes," <title render="italic">Piedmont Virginian</title>, 19 Jun 1974</item>
     <item>"Loudoun County Residents Mount Opposition to Dam," <title render="italic">Washington Post</title>, 20 Jun 1974</item>
     <item>"Anti-dam Taylorstown tour arranged," <title render="italic">Piedmont Virginian</title>, 2 Oct 1974</item>
     <item>"'Don't Dam Loudon' (sic) House Tour," (attributed to <title render="italic">Star</title>, 5 Oct 1974)</item>
     <item>"Taylorstown: A Lot to Lose," (identified only from Section R, Metro Virginia News)</item>
     </list></scopecontent></c01> 
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
