<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="viletbl00114">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00114:: Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A" 1904-1906)//EN" "viletbl00114.xml"
</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A", <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904-1906</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A"
<num type="collectionnumber">SC 0050
</num></subtitle>
        <author>Victoria Venne
</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
</extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">14 July 2010</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A", <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904-1906</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">SC 0050
</num></subtitle>
      <author>Victoria Venne
</author>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2006
</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:
</label>
          <item>Victoria Venne
</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Teachers Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A"
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904-1906
</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0050
</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"/>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English
</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">This collection consists of photo copies of pages from a teacher's register from Colored School "A" located in the Jefferson District of Virginia Public Schools. The register includes four pages of directions for daily and term records and twenty three pages to record the attendance of the students. 
</abstract>
      <origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Bronwen Souders
</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information
</head>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
        <head>Access Restrictions
</head>
        <p>Collection open for research .
</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
        <head>Use Restrictions
</head>
        <p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
        <head>Preferred Citation
</head>
        <p>Teacher's Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A" (SC0050), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA..
</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
        <head>Acquisition Information
</head>
        <p>Bronwen Souders, Waterford VA
</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail>
        <head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </altformavail>
      <accruals>
        <head>Accruals
</head>
        <p>2010.0171
</p>
      </accruals>
      <processinfo>
        <head>Processing Information
</head>
        <p>Processed by Victoria Venne, 11 May 2010
</p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
      <head>Biographical Information
</head>
      <p>The Religious Society of Friends of Waterford had an egalitarian view on life and believed African Americans should not be excluded from getting an education. It was because of this egalitarian view that one member, Reuben Schooley (ca. 1826-3 August 1900), agreed to sell a plot of land he owned "to the Colored people of Waterford and its vicinity."  This land was purchased in 1866 with the purpose of building a school for the African Americans of Waterford and surrounding areas. Although the land was purchased in 1866, it was not until 1868 that the land was officially deeded over to a board of five trustees that had been selected by the "colored people of Waterford and its vicinity." These trustees were Jonathan Cannady (n.d.), Alfred Craven (1831-n.d.), Matthew Harvey (1824-1895), Daniel Webster Minor (ca.1836-ca.1905), and Henson Young (1843-1930).
</p>
      <p>The Second Street School was erected in 1867, two years after the end of the Civil War. The building was built by the African Americans living in and around the town of Waterford. It is likely that Quaker residents of the area helped with financial aspects of building and maintaining the school before the Freedmen's Bureau became responsible for the school. When it was built, the Second Street School was one of eight schools for African Americans located in Loudoun County and one of three schools for African Americans in the Jefferson District. In around 1870, the Second Street School became part of Jefferson District's public-school system.</p>
      <p>The Second Street School has a few alternate names. It is referred to as the "Waterford School," the "Waterford Colored School," and "School A." The Second Street School was officially called "School A" by the Jefferson District. It was called "School A" because the African American schools in the area were given letters and the white schools were given numbers which made it easy to differentiate between them. When the school was first opened the teachers were white which was not uncommon in African American schools during the time period. In 1882 African Americans took over the teaching positions at the school. From that time on, it is presumed that only African Americans taught at the school.</p>
      <p>Starting in 1869 the Freedmen's Bureau started requiring schools to make monthly reports. There were specific questions that were to be answered by the teachers. Some of these questions include: how many students attended the school every month, what was the average attendance of students, what area of study were the students proficient in, and what was the public opinion of the school. Class sizes at the school were large because of the lack of African American schools in the area. There was a seasonal decrease in class sizes. Male students could not attend because they needed to help with planting and harvesting crops.</p>
      <p>
The Second Street School closed its doors to students in 1957. The Waterford Foundation acquired the school in 1977 because of its historical significance to the Waterford area. In 1984 the Waterford Foundation began a living history program at the school. The program is intended for third and fourth graders to come and learn about the history of the one room school house. Waterford Foundation volunteers portray the role of a teacher at the school and recreate a school day as it would have been when the school was still open.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
      <head>Scope and Content
</head>
      <p>This collection consists of photo copies of pages from a teacher's register from Colored School "A" located in the Jefferson District of Virginia Public Schools. The register includes four pages of directions for daily and term records and twenty three pages to record the attendance of the students. On these pages there are spaces for the names of pupils, age, attendance, and studies worked on monthly. The register was organized by month including four weeks of five days each. Two teachers used this register between 1904 and 1906. William B. Minor (ca. 1867-n.d.) used the register from 1904-1905 and was the son of Daniel Webster Minor, one of the five original trustees of the school. William B. Minor was also a student at the school before he became a teacher there. Letitia Burrell (n.d.) was a teacher at the school possibly until 1920. 
</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
      <bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
        <head>Bibliography
</head>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Ancestry Library Edition, United States census, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com.</bibref>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">1880 Census. ProQuest African American Heritage Database. ProQuest LLC. 2009-2010.</bibref>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">FamilySearch.org. Family History and Genealogy Records. Intellectual Reserve Inc., 2008. http://www.familysearch.org/eng/default.asp</bibref>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Loudoun Cemetery Database. Thomas Balch Library Databases.</bibref>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Scheel, Eugene M. "...to the Colored people of Waterford and vicinity, a Study of the Architecture and History of Their One-Room School, Waterford, Loudoun County, Virginia." Studies in Vernacular Architecture SVA-48. 1979.</bibref>
        <bibref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="">Teacher's Register for Virginia Public Schools, Jefferson District Colored School "A" (SC0050), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</bibref>
      </bibliography>
      <originalsloc encodinganalog="535$a">
        <head>Location of Originals
</head>
        <p>This collection is a copy of the original register which was lent to the Waterford Foundation in April 2001 by John Middleton.
</p>
      </originalsloc>
      <otherfindaid>
        <head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <phystech encodinganalog="538$a">
        <head>Technical Requirements
</head>
        <p>None
</p>
      </phystech>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
        <head>Related Material
</head>
        <p>Divine, John E. with Bronwen and John Souders. When Waterford and I Were Young. Waterford, Virginia. V Ref 975.582 DIV</p>
        <p>Scheel, Eugene M. "...to the Colored people of Waterford and vicinity, a Study of 
the Architecture and History of Their One-Room School, Waterford, Loudoun County, Virginia." Studies in Vernacular Architecture SVA-48. 1979. V Ref 975.528 SCH</p>
        <p>Scheel, Eugene M. The History of Middleburg and Vicinity. Warrenton, VA: Piedmont Press, 
1987. V Ref 975.528 SCH</p>
        <p>Souders, Bronwen C. and John M. Souders. A Rock in a Weary Land, a Shelter 
in a time of Storm: African American Experience in Waterford, Virginia. Waterford, VA: Waterford Foundation, Inc, 2003. V Ref 975.528 SOU</p>
        <p>Souders, Bronwen C. and John M. Souders. Share With Us, Waterford, Virginia's African-American Heritage: An Interpretive Guide to Your National Historic Landmark Village. Waterford, VA: Waterford Foundation, Inc, 2002. V Ref 975.528 WAT</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="in-depth">
      <head>Contents List
</head>
      <c01 level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Folder 1">Teacher's Register
<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1904-1906
</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
