<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00037">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00037:: Ball Family Genealogical Chart n.d.)//EN" "viletbl00037.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Ball Family Genealogical Chart, <date>n.d.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Ball Family Genealogical Chart
<num type="collectionnumber">OM 005
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Austin A. Backus
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date>19 January 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Ball Family Genealogical Chart, <date>n.d.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">OM 005
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Austin A. Backus
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Austin A. Backus
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Ball Family Genealogical Chart
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">n.d.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Accession number" encodinganalog="099$a">OM 005
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">3 items
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains three charts of various sizes depicting genealogies of several Ball families.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Gary Slaughter, Knoxville MD
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>See alternate formats.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Ball Family Genealogical Chart (OM 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Gary Slaughter, Knoxville MD
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>here is a use copy of the largest of the three manuscripts.
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>1993.0003
</p>
</accruals>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Several Ball lines existed in and around Virginia in America's early days. While it is nearly certain that the several lines all have English roots, they did not all come from the same colonist, or even the same family.</p>
<p>The most prominent line is that of Colonel William Ball I (1615-1680) of London, England who immigrated with his wife Hannah Atherold (d, 1695) and two of their three children, Joseph (b. 1649), and Hannah (b. 1650), in 1650 and settled in Lancaster County, VA as planters and eventually merchants. Colonel William II (1641-1694) was only nine when he and his parents left for the colonies. Colonel William I, Hannah, and their three children continued to live, work, and thrive in Northern, VA for several generations becoming one of the leading families in America's early years.</p>
<p>Confusion exists between the location of William I's home and that of his son, William II. They both died in Lancaster County, VA. It is believed William I had settled at the mouth of the Corotoman River in Lancaster County, VA by 1663. William II is usually associated with the Millenbeck estate on the Rappahannock River in Rappahannock County, VA.</p>
<p>Colonel Burgess Ball (1749-1800) was the great great grandson of Colonel William Ball I, and a resident of Leesburg VA. He was also an aide-de-camp to General Washington in the Revolutionary War. Washington's mother was a granddaughter of Colonel William I. Besides the Washingtons, the Balls intermarried with other families in and around Virginia. Hannah, the eldest daughter of Colonel William I, married Captain David Fox (1647-1669). The Foxes were a prominent family in 17th and 18th century Virginia. Other families include the Conways, Taylors, Taliaferros, and Chinns.</p>
<p>Captain Alling Ball of New Haven, CT and his wife Dorothy (d. 1690) whose name appears on the William Ball chart are hard to place in relation to William Ball I. Some sources decided they must be brothers though little or no evidence is given. The same mystery exists between Francis Ball (d. 1648) and William Ball I. Furthermore, conclusive evidence is yet to be found linking Alling and Francis Ball in any sort of kinship. Whether or not he had brothers in the colonies, the descendents of William Ball I were the most well-known and studied.</p>
<p>Another line is that of Edward (d. 1726) and Kezia Ball. Less is known about Edward and his family except for the names and some dates of their 13 children who appear on his family pedigree.</p>
<p>James Ball and his wife Ann (Nancy) (d.1822) were the founders of another Ball line. They resided in Fauquier County, VA where they leased land on which to build a home, and raise their ten children. James was an apple farmer by trade; his orchard stood on the same piece of property. Sheltial Ball (1780-1836), James and Nancy's fourth child and first son was the first of the family to settle in St. Louis County, MO in 1834. A year later, Sheltial's brother, James Jr. (1787-1852) followed him to Missouri as did their younger sister Nancy (1792-1855) with her husband, William Ellis. John Ball (1790-1838) with his wife Elizabeth Ellis (1790-1852) ended up in St. Louis County, MO probably around this same time though their date of arrival is uncertain. The rest of James and Nancy's children remained in or around Fauquier County, VA.</p>
<p>John (1670-1722) and Winifred Ball were of Stafford County, VA. Their son Moses Ball Sr. (1717-1792) settled in Fairfax County, VA. Moses Ball Sr.'s children and grandchildren eventually made their way to Southwest Virginia. His son, Moses Ball Jr., settled in Hawkins County, Tennessee, while others of the family established roots in Kentucky.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains three charts of various sizes depicting genealogies of several Ball families. All of them are fraying and yellowing around the edges. All three charts are hand printed, the smaller two on onion skin paper, while the largest is on card stock. There is also a copy of the William Ball chart in the collection.</p>
<p>The William Ball chart begins with Colonel William Ball I and traces his progeny down to 8 generations. Captain Alling Ball and Francis Ball appear at the top of the chart though the connection between any of the three is doubtful.</p>
<p>The Edward Ball chart records two distinct Ball lines with no apparent relation between the two. The first line begins with the family of Edward (d. 1726) and Kezia Ball and their thirteen children. Five more generations from the children are recorded.</p>
<p>The second line begins with James Ball and ends with his grandchildren. Confusion exists regarding his birth and death dates; some sources indicate 1744-1784, while others claim 1754-1794. This James Ball does appear, however, on the William Ball chart mentioned above. On that chart his father is not recorded but his uncles, William and James Ball, are. Additionally, James' descendents down to several generations are recorded on the William Ball chart.</p>
<p>The John Ball chart spans ten generations. The latest family member is Elizabeth Ball (b. 1932), in the line of George Ball of the third generation from John Ball.</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Ball Family Genealogical Chart (OM 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref>
<bibref><title render="italic">Ball: Genealogy and Family History</title>. Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref>
<bibref>Ball, Helen, compiler. <title render="italic">The Burgess Ball Family of Loudoun County, VA.</title> Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref>
<bibref>Ball, Palmer R., compiler. <title render="italic">The Ball Family of Southwest Virginia: Genealogy of Some of the Descendants of Moses Ball of Fairfax County.</title> Virginia: The Cumberlandcrafters, 1933.</bibref>
<bibref>Hayden, Rev. Horace Edwin. <title render="italic">Virginia Genealogies.</title> Pennsylvania: Wilkes-Barre, 1891. Reprint, Baltimore: Clearfield Company, 1992.</bibref>
<bibref><title render="italic">Genealogies of Virginia Families</title>. Vol. 1. "Taylor's Quarterly: Historical and Genealogical Magazine." Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Company, Inc., 1981.</bibref>
<bibref>Family Search: Family and Genealogy Research, www.familysearch.org.</bibref>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>


<c01 level="collection">
<did>
<container>Oversized Box 1
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Ball Family Genealogical Chart
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<list type="simple">
        	<item>Copy of the William Ball chart</item>
		<item>3 rolled charts</item>
        	</list>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>  

</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
