<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00206">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00206:: Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA 1938-1971)//EN" "viletbl00206.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA, <date>1938-1971</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA, 
<num type="collectionnumber">M 073, OMB 012
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Elizabeth Preston, <date>3 April 2012</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA, <date>1938-1971</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">M 073, OMB 012
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1938-1971
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 073, OMB 012
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"> </physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains extensive material about Frederick Douglass Elementary School in Leesburg, Virginia, but its scope goes far beyond this one school to questions of equality of educational opportunities in Loudoun County. The collection begins with correspondence concerning segregation and inequality in the public schools, proceeds to reactions to decisions requiring racial integration in the schools, and ends with five folders of materials concerning the construction of Douglass Elementary School.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Loudoun County Public Schools
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA 1938-1971 (M 073), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loudoun County Public Schools
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2010.0285, 2010.0307
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Rebecca K. Ottinger, 26 March 2012
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Frederick Douglass Elementary School (hereinafter Douglass Elementary) building in Leesburg, Virginia, was constructed in 1958 as a segregated school and continued to be used as an elementary school for African American students until 1968. Although the US Supreme Court ruled in 1958 that racial segregation in public schools was unconstitutional, Loudoun County's schools, operating on a "freedom of choice" plan, continued to be largely segregated.  In 1967 the US District Court ordered Loudoun County to use geographical attendance zones to determine pupil placement and required the county to integrate school faculty, staff, and buses by the 1968 school year. From 1968 to 1982 Douglass Elementary was a racially integrated elementary school, following which (1982-2001) the building was used for pre-school, Head Start, and special education classes as well as a warehouse facility and support staff location. After that time it was no longer used for classes, serving instead as space for various school board offices. When Loudoun County Public Schools began to explore the desirability of demolishing the Douglass Elementary building and constructing a new elementary school on that site, an archeological study and a study of the school's history and architectural significance were undertaken.  Loudoun County Public Schools engaged Thunderbird Archeology and History Matters, LLC to prepare a Phase I archaeological investigation and a historical review of the school for the purpose of preserving the history and commemorating the original school as a part of the new school.
</p>
<p>Two firms completed two reports, both of which are cataloged and available in Thomas Balch Library's general collection. <title render="italic">Phase I Archeological Investigations of the +/- 9.28 Acre Douglass Support Center Property, Leesburg,VA</title>, dated 2010, by Kimberly A. Snyder of Thunderbird Archeology concluded the building was not eligible for inclusion in the National Register of Historic Places and could be demolished and replaced.  The report by History Matters, LLC, dated April 30, 2010, titled <title render="italic">Desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools, 1954-1970</title>, documented the school's history in the context of state and national decisions regarding integration. This study expanded into an investigation of the issues and concerns of the African American community in Loudoun County beginning in the 1930s, not only in regard to Douglass Elementary School, but to equality of educational facilities and experiences of black students, racial segregation in the public school system, and concerns about the equal treatment of African American teachers in the system.</p>
<p>Upon completion of the research, Loudoun County Public Schools contacted the Black History Committee of the Friends of the Thomas Balch Library.  A number of concerned citizens opposed the demolition of the school, citing the building's historical significance to the African American community.  In response to this concern, Loudoun County Public Schools and the Black History Committee embarked on a joint project to preserve the history and establish a permanent exhibit of the former school in the new school.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains extensive material about Frederick Douglass Elementary School in Leesburg, Virginia, but its scope goes far beyond this one school to questions of equality of educational opportunities in Loudoun County. The collection retains the order in which it was received by the library. It begins with correspondence concerning segregation and inequality in the public schools, proceeds to reactions to decisions requiring racial integration in the schools, and ends with five folders of materials concerning the construction of Douglass Elementary School.
</p>
<p>The collection contains extensive copies of minutes of Loudoun County School Board as they relate to concerns of equality and racial segregation of students and teachers. These minutes cover numerous School Board meetings from 1938 to 1971. Also included are letters, petitions, and newspaper articles regarding conditions in African American schools, inequality of salaries between African American and white teachers, and other concerns of the African American community in regard to public education. Many items document reactions to the decision of the United States Supreme Court in Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka on May 17, 1954. </p>
<p>There is also an extensive file of information containing legal and construction specifications (1957-1958), beginning with the purchase of land and architectural renderings to furnishing and final inspection of the original Douglass Elementary.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Folder
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<p><bibref>Causey, Evelyn D. and Julia Claypool. <title render="italic">Desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools, 1954-1970</title>. Washington, DC: History Matters, 2010. 
</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Howard-O'Brien, Sara. Land Management Supervisor, Loudoun County Public Schools, Department of Planning and Legislative Services, personal communication, Rebecca Ottinger, 23 March 2012. </bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Research Materials Regarding Decision to Replace Frederick Douglass Elementary School, Leesburg, VA 1938-1971 (M 073), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Snyder, Kimberly A. <title render="italic">Phase I Archeological Investigations of the +/- 9.28 Acre Douglass Support Center Property, Leesburg, VA</title>. Gainesville, VA: Thunderbird Archeology, 2010.  </bibref></p>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<phystech encodinganalog="538$a">
<head>Technical Requirements
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</phystech>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Kimberly A. Snyder. <title render="italic">Phase I Archeological Investigations of the +/- 9.28 Acre Douglass Support Center Property, Leesburg, VA</title>. Gainesville, VA: Thunderbird Archeology, 2010. V REF 975.528 SNY; Evelyn D. Causey and Julia Claypool. <title render="italic">Desegregation in Loudoun County Public Schools, 1954-1970</title>. Washington, DC: History Matters, 2010. V REF 379.263 CAU 
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Separated Material
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</separatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>

<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Lists of teachers and students at Douglass Elementary School, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1957-1969
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Minutes of Loudoun County School Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1938-1944
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Minutes of Loudoun County School Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1944-1951
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Minutes of Loudoun County School Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1951-1956
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Minutes of Loudoun County School Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1956-1963
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Minutes of Loudoun County School Board, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1964-1971
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>

<container type="box">OMB 012
</container>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Architectural drawings for Douglass Elementary School and correspondence, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1957
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Architectural drawings and specifications concerning furniture and fixtures of Douglass Elementary School building, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1958
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Construction materials for Douglass Elementary School, correspondence and bills, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1957-1958
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Final inspections of Douglass Elementary School building, correspondence, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1959
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Letters, petitions, newspaper articles regarding inequality of segregated schools in Loudoun County; Deed for property on which to build Douglass High School in Leesburg, VA and correspondence regarding this gift, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1940-1953
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Loudoun County Institute for Colored Teachers, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1921; 1927-1932
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Reactions to the decision of the US Supreme Court in Brown vs. The Board of Education, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1955-1956
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Shared experiences of the faculty of Douglass High School, "A Brief History of Loudoun County Schools" from Annual Report of LCPS, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2001-2002
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 9">Topographical survey and correspondence concerning construction of Douglass Elementary School building, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1956-1957
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
