<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viltblviletble00290">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLTBL::viltblviletble00290::A Guide to the Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records, 1985-1994, n.d.)//EN" "viltblviletble00290.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records, <date>1985-1994, n.d.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">M 0214, VC 0083, ART 0012, OMB 029
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Gabrielle Sanchez
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher> Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169; 2017 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.<!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Database, created by Gabrielle Sanchez, <date>25 May 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records, <date>1985-1994, n.d.</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">M 0214, VC 0083, ART 0012, OMB 029
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2017
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Gabrielle Sanchez
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>

<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1985-1994, n.d.
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 0214, VC 0083, ART 0012, OMB 029
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>18 cubic feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The collection records Hanno Weber and Associates work as architect, designer, and construction project manager of the Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center.  Included are documents such as correspondence, contracts, invoices, and reports; architectural drawings and sketches; photographs; and material samples.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Hanno Weber and Associates </origination>

</did>

<descgrp type="admininfo"><head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records (M 0124), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Hanno Weber and Associates, Chicago, Illinois.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2016.0090
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Gabrielle Sanchez, 25 May 2017
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>

<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Hanno Weber (born 24 September 1937) is an American architect based in Chicago, Illinois.  A graduate of Princeton University, he founded Hanno Weber and Associates (HWA) in 1984.  The firm specializes in architecture, interior design, site planning, and urban design.  
</p>
<p>In 1986, after undertaking an analysis of existing government facilities and downtown parking demand, the Town of Leesburg issued a call for designs for a municipal government center and parking complex.  The new combined office building and parking complex would consolidate and expand town services as well as alleviate parking shortages, while blending with the historic scale and context of downtown Leesburg.  Over 200 architects submitted entries to the competition.  Hanno Weber and Associates' design was awarded the first prize of $10,000 and the design commission.  The firm also designed the interior of the building, including furnishings and accessories, and served as project manager for construction of the facility.  Construction on the municipal government center began in 1988 and was completed in 1991.</p>
<p>Hanno Weber and Associates' design for the municipal government center won several awards, including Architecture and Urban Design Competition, First Award (1987); AIA Urban Design Award of Excellence (1992); and AIA Chicago Chapter Interior Design Certificate of Merit (1992).</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection records Hanno Weber and Associates work as architect, designer, and construction project manager of the Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center.  Included are documents such as correspondence, contracts, invoices, and reports; architectural drawings and sketches; photographs; and material samples.
</p>
<p>The collection documents all phases of Hanno Weber and Associates work on the project including the initial design and contest submission; project management and programming; relationships with the Town of Leesburg, subcontractors and consultants; the bidding process; construction itself; dedication of the facility; and HWA's promotion of its work.  Whenever possible, materials have been arranged in the order outlined in HWA's Project Index (See M 0124, Box 1, Folder 7) as follows: Project Management and Programming; Client Records; Agencies Records; Consultant Records; Bidding; Contractors Records; Contract Accounting; and Construction Administration.  Materials relating to the design competition have been placed at the beginning of the collection, and materials relating to publicity subsequent to the completion of the project have been placed at the end of the collection.</p>
<p>Design competition materials include the design manual and guidelines, Leesburg town plan, HWA's winning entry, and the competition results.</p>
<p>The Project Management and Programming section contains materials documenting management of the construction process.  These include meetings of minutes with Town of Leesburg officials, design studies and reports, environmental reports, budgets, schedules, photographs of office interiors (see VC 0083), and product information.  This section also contains a large number of architectural drawings, including design sketches, working drawings, and alternate plans.  For storage reasons, the majority of these drawings are housed in OMB 029.  Please see the Drawings Index for a detailed list of drawings.</p>
<p>The Client Records section contains contracts, correspondence, telephone memoranda, and invoices related to HWA's client, the Town of Leesburg.</p>
<p>The Agencies Records section contains materials related to zoning and building permits.</p>
<p>The Consultant Records section contains contracts, correspondence, and invoices relating to various consultants, including mechanical, electrical, and civil engineers.</p>
<p>The Bidding section contains correspondence, evaluations, and other documents relating to the bidding process for the hiring of a construction general contractor.</p>
<p>The Contractor Records section contains correspondence between the general contractor and HWA, as well as Requests for Information (RFI).  In addition, this section contains a large number of architectural shop drawings, samples, and related correspondence.  The drawings and samples were submitted for HWA's approval by various subcontractors.  HWA assigned a number to each submittal, and HWA's index is available ("Submittals Checklist" M 0124, Box 8, Folder 13 and OMB 029, Box 1, Folder 18).  The shop drawings contain numerous notes, comments, and corrections.  They are stored folded.  The shop drawings and samples have been separated from the related correspondence due to their size and preservation storage needs (See M 0124, Box 20-22 and ART 012).</p>
<p>The Contract Accounting section contains Supplemental Instructions, Requests for Change Orders, Certificates of Payment, and other documents.</p>
<p>The Construction Administration section contains Construction Observation reports by HWA, Town of Leesburg, and an outside contractor, as well as minutes of construction meetings, reports, and punch lists.  In addition, this section contains photographs taken by both HWA and professional photographers documenting the construction progress (See VC 0083).</p>
<p>The collection also contains materials, including photographs, related to the municipal government center's dedication ceremony held in March 1991.  In addition, there are photographs and slides of the completed exterior and interior of the building and correspondence with vendors and architecture and design publications.</p>
</scopecontent>

<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>

<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>

<p><bibref>Hanno Weber and Associates, www.hannoweber.com, accessed 17 March 2017.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>
Town of Leesburg Municipal Government Center Hanno Weber and Associates Records (M 124), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref></p>
</bibliography>

<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Town of Leesburg, Virginia Records, 1813-present, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA 
</p>
<p>Leesburg Architectural Surveys 1971-2001 (M 016), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA. Town of Leesburg: Department of Planning, Zoning and Development: (RG 22), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA. Town of Leesburg: Department of Planning, Zoning and Development: Visual Records of Historic Sites (VC RG 22), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA</p>
<p>Historical Postcards, 1900-2008 (VC 0004), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA</p>
<p>Leesburg Opera House Handbill (SC 0012) Thomas Balch Library Leesburg, VA</p>
</relatedmaterial>

</descgrp>





</archdesc>
</ead>

