<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viltblviletbl00240">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletblviletbl00240::A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 1831-1970; 1981)//EN" "viltblviletbl00240.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, <date>1831-1970; 1981</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Wilbur C. Hall Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Gabrielle Sanchez
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml" />
<date type="publication">2014 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Elizabeth E. Preston, <date>26 March 2014</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, <date>1831-1970; 1981</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection number">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2014
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Laura Christiansen, Lisa DeZarn, Alexandra S. Gressitt, Mary Pender, and Gabrielle Sanchez
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1831-1970; 1981
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2 cu. ft. (5 boxes, 4 oversize folders; 9 VC folders)</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County.  There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>Physical characteristics and conditions affect use of this material.  Photocopying not permitted. Visual materials may require special handling.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Wilbur C. Hall Papers (M 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2012.0025; 2012.0026
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Laura Christiansen, Lisa DeZarn, Alexandra S. Gressitt, Mary Pender, Gabrielle Sanchez, 2004, 2012, and 2014
</p>
<p>
NOTE: For ease of access, diaries (1811-1820) of Samuel B.T. Caldwell were processed separately as SC0004.</p> 
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Born in Leesburg, VA on February 7, 1892, Wilbur C. Hall is noted for his career as a lawyer, state legislator, orator, and public figure. Graduating from Washington and Lee School of Law in Lexington, VA in 1915, Hall served in the United States Navy during World War I.  In 1918, at the age of 24, he was elected to the Virginia General Assembly and served on the Assembly until 1935. He served as Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission from 1935-1939, and authored or sponsored important and influential legislation.
</p>
<p>Wilbur Hall also had a legendary career as a lawyer; he was called a "lawyer's lawyer" and "the best prepared lawyer before the bar of any court in Virginia." Hall contributed to the legal profession in numerous ways, being widely cited in case law and also serving as a supporter of Washington and Lee University's law program. He made several sizable gifts to the law school program during his lifetime, including a loan fund for deserving law students, and left the majority of his estate to Washington and Lee University. In 1967 Washington and Lee bestowed an honorary doctorate degree upon him. Hall noted this as being "the happiest moment of my life." Following his death in August 1972, the law school library, which he helped develop, was named Wilbur C. Hall Law Library.</p>
<p>Hall was a founding member of the Rotary Club of Leesburg and belonged to numerous civic and fraternal organizations. As a public figure and noted orator, he was in demand as a speaker and frequently spoke on historical topics.  An amateur historian, Hall also contributed to the preservation of historical landmarks and local historic sites. As Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission he helped to create a state historic marker program, establishing a number of markers for Loudoun county historic sites, including the site of Revolutionary war figure John Champe. Hall published articles about Champe and other historical topics of interest to him in a variety of journals. While Hall was a popular speaker and contributor to publications, it should be noted that he hired researchers to complete much of his writing and historical inquiries.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County.  There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life.  The collection is organized into two series.
</p>
<p>Series I consists of documents relating to his research into the history of Loudoun County and surrounding areas. The materials are organized alphabetically by subject.  The documents include transcripts of speeches he gave on various historical topics to organizations such as the American Legion, Lion's Club, Rotary Club, Ruritan Club, Loudoun County Chamber of Commerce, local historical societies and others. Also included are associated correspondence and research materials, including publications, maps, historical accounts, clippings and notes.  Correspondents include:  J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1898-1986); W. J. Barrow (1904-1967); Armistead L. Boothe (1907-1990); Mary Brackett (Mrs. Scott) Bowen (1887-1974); Omar N. Bradley (1893-1981); Benjamin H. Branch, Jr. (1919-1993); Wiley T. Buchanan, Jr. (1914-1986); Bryan Conrad (1870-1950); Elbert Cox (1906-1993); Cecil B. Dickson (ca. 1899-1986); E. Griffith Dodson (1923-1962); H. J. Eckenrode (1881-1952); Eugenia T. Fairfax (1873-1966); David E. Finley, Jr. (1890-1977); Marshall W Fishwick (1923-2006); Caroline B. Furness (1922-2007); R. K. Gheen (1914-1974); Stilson H. Hall (1893-1981); George P. Hammerly (1921-1984); Huntington Harris (1914-1993);  B. Powell Harrison (1911-2000); William J. Heffner (1909-1995); Laurence G. Hoes (1900-1978); George A. Horkan, Jr. (1926-2005);  Carlisle H. Humelsine (1915-1989); Eppa Hunton, IV; (1904-1976); Patrick J. Hurley (1883-1963); Asa Moore Janney (ca. 1908-2002); W. Pat Jennings (1919-1994);  Aurelia M. (Mrs. Walter T.) Jewell (1900-1992); Marven Jones (1882-1976); George Harrison Sanford King (1914-1985); George C. Marshall (1880-1959); Katherine Marshall (1882-1978); H(erbert) A. Martz (1898-1990); Frank P. Moncure (1889-1969); Benjamin Muse (1898-1986) Millard C. Myers (1883-1975); Lawrence F. O'Brien, Jr. (1917-1990); Carleton Penn (1922-2009); Lucas D. Phillips (1904-1994); Forrest C. Pogue, Jr. (1912-1996);  Joseph E. Profitt (1876-1958); W. Griffith Purcell (1912-1983); Jennings Randolph (1902-1998);  A. Willis Robertson (1887-1971); Clarence L. Robey (1884-1969); John W. H. Spencer (1919-2011); William B. Spong, Jr. (1920-1997); Stuart Symington (1901-1988); [Dorothy] Ullrich Troubetzkoy (1914-2003); William M. Tuck (1896-1983); Robert Whitehead (1897-1960); and Conrad L. Wirth (1899-1993). </p>
<p>Series II is made up of original nineteenth century documents collected by Wilbur Hall in the course of his historical research.  These documents include letters, public notices, legal documents, and advertisements originating from Loudoun County and surrounding areas.  They are organized chronologically.</p>
<p>The collection also contains a scrapbook of newspaper clippings chronicling Wilbur Hall's political activities, and two artifacts.  There is a United States flag with 46 stars which belonged to General George C. Marshall and an undated "Christmas card" (a photograph of Wilbur Hall pasted onto a wooden stand).</p>
<p>The visual materials consist of sixteen photographs of various sizes and formats dating from 1866-1968. Photographs feature Wilbur Hall or were collected by him in the course of his research into a variety of historical topics.  Organization of the photographs fall into two series: Series I consists of four folders containing photographs from research projects (speech or paper); Series II contains portrait images of Wilbur Hall.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>Box: folder
</p>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<p><bibref>Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Alumni, Biographies, Wilbur C. Hall, http://law.wlu.edu/alumni/bios/hall-wilbur.asp (accessed 2 February 2012).
</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Wilbur C. Hall Papers (M 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Out of the Attic, Volume 2, February Birthday, 25 February 1982.</bibref></p>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>Past Perfect catalogue records
</p>
</otherfindaid>
</descgrp>

<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="M 005">Manuscripts
</unittitle>
<container>Series I: Wilbur C. Hall Speech, Research and Correspondence Files
</container>
</did>

        <c02 level="item">
        <did>
        <unittitle label="Box 1">A-Le
	</unittitle>
        </did>

		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 1">Alexander, Judge J. R. H.: Speech and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1966-1967
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 2">American Legion "Miss Loudoun County" Speeches,
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd (2)
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 3">Ball's Bluff Accounts: White, Col. E. V., History of the Battle of Ball's Bluff (nd); Notes on Ball's Bluff from Duyckinck, E.A., War for the Union, Vol. 2 (1861) 2pp, and "Remarks by J. D. Patch to The Leesburg Rotary Club," 14 May 1959, 7pp.
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 4">Ball's Bluff: Correspondence concerning a speech on Senator Edward Baker; the battle and battlefield, 1941, 1961 (14 letters)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 5">Ball's Bluff Cemetery newsclipping: "Herald History from the Files of the Fairfax Herald: Ball's Bluff Cemetery,"
		<unitdate type="inclusive">25 October 1968
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 6">Ball's Bluff Maps: Maps of the Battle of Ball's Bluff (nd, compiler or publisher), 2 copies
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 7">Bedinger: Burning of Homestead, Gosport, VA, 1864, by Mrs. E. J. Lee of Shepherdstown, W VA, typescript, nd, 7pp.
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 8">Bridger, James: Biography (2 copies) and correspondence
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1947-1948 
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 9">Chamber of Commerce, Loudoun County, speech, handwritten notes and typescript, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1969
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 10">Champe, John: Speeches (2), votes and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1954-1955; 1959-1967
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 11">Cooke, Philip St. George and the Mormon Battalion Memorial: Speeches, research, and correspondence, 1955-1956, 1967.  (See VC0043 Box 1, Folder 2 for images of the Mormon Battalion Monument)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 12">Democratic Committee and Loudoun County: Speeches (2), 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 13">Eaton, Mrs. John H. (Peggy O'Neal): Research notes and correspondence on birthplace, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1942 and 1955
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 14">Fauquier County: Speech, paper, and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1940
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 15">Fauquier County Railroads: Photocopy of article "Southern Railway Has Seen a Lot of History Since the 1850s" by Harry A. deButts in The Fauquier Democrat 50th Anniversary edition, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd (ca. 1955)
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 16">Fox, George and "Devils Kitchen": Speech, Research and Correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1954
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 17">Fredericksburg:  typescript of Civil War letter, 17 December 1862 and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1949
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 18">General Assembly: Editorials (2), 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1940 and nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 19">Greenup, Christopher: Speech and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1959-1960
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 20">Hall, Stillson Hutchins: Memorials, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1981
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 21">Hall, Wilbur C.: Correspondence, documents, and legal papers, 1931-1968; Hummel, Jr., Ray O. and W. J. Barrow, Library Trends "Lamination and Other Methods of Restoration," January 1956; Loudoun Camp Meeting Association, Inc. certificate for shares, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1908 
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 22">Hall, Wilbur C.: James Monroe Memorial Foundation Board appointment, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1960
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 23">Hall, Wilbur C.: Research notes on various topics, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 24">Hall, Wilbur C.: Tree of Life, 1960 and portrait photographs (2)  see VC0043, Folder 3 for portrait photographs of Wilbur C. Hall ca. 1934 and undated; see ART Box 1, item 1, Wilbur C. Hall "Christmas Card" (Photograph pasted onto wood cutout on wood stand), 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 25">Hunter, David (Major-General), typescript of 1864 Account of Burning Homes in Jefferson County, WVA, 4 pp.
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 26">Janney, John: Speech, research, and correspondence, 1938, 1961-1962; 1967-1968. See also VC0043, Folder 4: carte de visite John Janney, ca. 1866, inscribed and a group photograph of Lucas D. Phillips, Wilbur Hall (?) and Fred Howard
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 27">Jewell, William: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 1957-1961; see VC0043, Folder 5; images of William Jewell, Boone County Courthouse and Jewell Hall at William Jewell College, Liberty, Missouri
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder  28">Lee, Ludwell, Speech, 1938, 16pp
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder  29">Leesburg: Radio Talk (WJSV), speech, history, correspondence, research notes, and publication [The Town of Leesburg distributed by The Peoples National Bank of Leesburg, (2c)], 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1944, 1963, and nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder  30">Leesburg Business Directory, 1860, typed transcript and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1963 and nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>


        <c02 level="item">
        <did>
        <unittitle label="Box 2">Lo-R
	</unittitle>
        </did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 1">Loudoun County: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1942-1966
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 2">Tenth Annual Report of the Board of Directors of the Alexandria, Loudoun &amp; Hampshire Rail Road Company for the Year Ending September 30, 1869 Made to the Stockholders in General Meeting, Held November 3, 1869. (Alexandria: Robert Bell Stationers, 1869, 16 pp with cover pp)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 3">Loudoun National Bank: blank counter check, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 4">Loudoun Times Publishing Company Situation Report, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1963
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 5">Loveless Murder, news clippings
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1941
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 6">Lovettsville: research notes, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 7">Marshall, George C: Tribute, resolutions, correspondence, and pamphlets, 1959-1969 (See also ART003 and VC0043)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 8">Massey, "Parson" John E.: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1942
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 9">Memorial Day: Speeches, research, and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1967 and 1970
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 10">Mercer, Charles Fenton: Speeches, research notes, correspondence, Congressional Record Proceedings and debates of the 87th Congress, First Session, Vol 107 #22, February 6, 1961, and Abstract: Charles Fenton Mercer, 1778-1858 by Olliver O. Trumbo, 1937,1946, 1961, and nd
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 11">Monroe, James: Research materials in re Monroe's Congressional message of 2 December 1823 which became the Monroe Doctrine and Correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1940
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 12">Monroe, James: Speeches (4) and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1943, 1952, 1957, and nd
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 13">The Plan of a Memorial for President James Monroe at "Oak Hill" Loudoun County, Virginia by James Monroe Foreign Service Educational Foundation, Aldie, VA, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1946
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 14">Monroe, James: Speech, research notes, Fishwick, Marshall W., "James Monroe of Oak Hill," and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1960-1961
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 15">Mosby, John S.: Speech, research notes, photograph of Mosby, and certificate for John S. Mosby Sovereign Royal Council, 1877 and nd; see VC0043 Folder 7 for image of John S. Mosby and OM 019, folder 1 for Sovereign Royal Council certificate.
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 16">Neale, John Beckwith: Correspondence and research notes on birthplace, 1967; See VC0043 Folder 8 for image of Stonewall Jackson
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 17">Olive Branch Lodge (Masonic): History, remarks, correspondence, 1955-1968; see VC0043, Folder 9 group photograph (2) including Wilbur C. Hall
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 18">Public School System: Speech, research notes, publications: Hall, Wilbur C., The Future of Education in Virginia, Richmond, VA, 1930; Hall Wilbur C., "Representative Government At Its Worst in Virginia" reprinted from the Loudoun News, December 6, 1951; Remarks of Senator A. Willis Robertson Prepared for delivery at the Yorktown Victory Anniversary Celebration Sunday, October 19, 1958, Robertson, A. Willis, "Public Education in a Democracy," Congressional Records, 1961 (p. A323-4); Three Educational Address: Handicaps, Visions, and Talents, and Correspondence, 1930, 1951-1968
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 19">Rotary Club: Speeches, program, roster (1931), and correspondence, 1931-44, 1960, nd
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>


        <c02 level="item">
        <did>
        <unittitle label="Box 3">S-W
	<unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"/></unittitle>
        </did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 1">State Commission on Conservation and Development (VA): Speech, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1936
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 2">Union Cemetery (Leesburg, VA): Speech (3 copies), 1946 and Act of Incorporation and Revised By-Laws of Union Cemetery, Leesburg, Virginia Incorporated February 27th 1852 (no publisher or publication date)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 3">Washington, George: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1959
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 4">Wayne, Anthony (Maj. Gen.): Speech, Research Notes, and Correspondence, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1941
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container>Series II: Nineteenth Century Documents
</container>
</did>
        <c02 level="item">
        <did>
        <unittitle label="Box 3">
	</unittitle>
        </did>

		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 5">Broadside by SBT Caldwell to the Voters of Loudoun, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">5 August 1831 
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 6">Petition for appointment of George Mason as a midshipman, includes marginalia and 20 signatures, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">18 Jan 1832
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 7">Lawsuit (copy) Christian Lanbower v Asa Rogers filed 11 June 1833, 7 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 8">Indenture, Samuel M. Edwards for James L. Martin for the benefit of creditors and John Norris, for the period 1837-1938, 24 August 1837, 6pp
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 9">ALS, Clinton to Mr. Connolly, re: transcontinental railroad and trade with the Pacific, 1 January 1849, 4pp
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 10">PFFI, court summons for John Martin, in Ramey v Harpers Ferry Savings Institution, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1 January 1849
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 11">ALS, Alfred P. Warfield, Waterford, VA to Asa Jackson, Leesburg, re Sons of Temperance 4 January 1849, 1p. Waterford Division N0 95 S of T St of VA, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">15 February 1848
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 12">ALS, M. B. Perry, Gum Spring, VA to Thos. C. Connolly, Leesburg, re bid request for printing ballots for election of officers Gum Spring Sons of Temperance, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">8 January 1849
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 13">ANS, request for special elections, John B. Floyd, Governor of Virginia, 17 April 1849 and Notice of special election for the House of Delegates, Loudoun County, Thomas Saunders, Sheriff of Loudoun County, 19 April 1849 2 documents attached
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 14">ANS, Runaway Slave Ad 26 [May] 1849, Henry B Tyler, Washington DC [May 2] 8, 1849, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 15">ANS, Notice of Executors Sale of Negroes, Beverly Hutchinson, Executor for John Hutchins dec'd, 23 June 1849, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 16">Virginia State Lotteries for the benefit of Monongalia Academy, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">June and December 1849
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 17">ADS, Notice of Commissioners sale of house and lot of land pursuant to a decree of the County Court of Loudoun pronounced on the 15 day of August 1849 in the case of Chas. W. Burke an infant v Mary Burke and Virginia E. Burke, signed by A. M. Vandevanter deputy for T. Saunders, Sherriff, 7 Sept 1849, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 18">ANS, Notice for runaway slave ad, Thos. Foster and Wm Roach, Prince William County, 10 Sept 1849, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 19">ANS, Advertisement for fruit trees, Yardley Taylor, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">11 September 1849
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 20">ANS, Notice to collect debts owed to trustee, Robert L. T. White, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">19 September 1849
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 21">ANS, Notices (2) for the dedication of the Loudoun Lodge # 26, IOOF, 6 October 1846, Thomas Littleton and Chas B. Tebbs
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 22">ANS, Advertisement for missing mare, L. M. Watkins, 14 October 1849, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 23">ALS (3), Subscription renewal requests for the Chronicle, Leesburg, William Bradfield, P B Oden, and Emory &amp; Co., 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1849-1850
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 24">AN, Commissioner sale of Loudoun land, 22 January 1850, in the case of Solomon Crumbaker et al v Jacob Stoutsenberger surviving executor of John Stoutsenberger and executor Samuel Stoutsenberger, deceased, et al., 24 October 1849, 1p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 25">ADS, in a  Chancery Suit, Thomas Francis and Enoch Francis v Stephen McCarty and Elizabeth McCarty, his wife, John Francis, Edward Francis, William H Francis, and James Francis and William Francis, infant children of Lewis Francis dec'd and Fielding Littleton their guardian ad litem, Francis P. Knox, Clerk and F. W. Luckett, 24 October 1849, 1p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 26">ANS (2) Administrators sale, land, negroes, stock of the estate of George Cuthbert Powell, Middleburg, 16 October 1849, B. P. Noland, Administrator, and Public Sale of Negroes, 17 December 1849, estate of Cuthbert Powell, William H. Gray and Charles S. Powell, executors, 6 December 1849
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 27">PF, Broadside Advertisement for Drugstore, Waterford, 12 April 1851; see OM 019, Folder 1
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 28">Advertisement: Bazaar in Aid of the Southern Prisoners' Relief Fund, Liverpool, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">17 May 1864
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 29">The Centennial - balloon view of the grounds, Harpers Weekly 1876, see OM 019, folder 2
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 30">Johnstown, PA flood relief: Correspondence and Donor list, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1889
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 31">PFFI, Account of Mails received at the post office, undated and no place given, see OM 019, folder 3
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 32">ANS, advertisement for hiring out several valuable servant men, J. E. S. Hough; also for rent a dwelling on Cornwall St, JESH, Dec 31 ny, 1p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 33">Folder 33	ANS, Notice of land for sale in the German Settlement, T. W. Edwards, nd, 1 p
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>

        <c02 level="item">
        <did>
        <unittitle label="Box 4">S-W
	</unittitle>
        </did>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 1">Wilbur C. Hall Scrapbook, 
		<unitdate type="inclusive">1934-1935
		</unitdate>
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="file">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 2">Newspaper clippings on Hall's political activities
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="OM 019">Oversized Manuscripts
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Mosby, John S. Sovereign Royal Council Certificate, 1877 (see also box 2, folder 15)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Broadside Advertisement for Drugstore, Waterford, VA, 12 April 1851 (see also box 3, folder 27)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">The Centennial-balloon view of the grounds, Harpers Weekly, 1876 (see also box 3, folder 29)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Account of Mails received at the post office, undated and no place given (see also box 3, folder 31)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="ART 003">Artifacts
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">United States flag with 46 stars belonging to George C. Marshall,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Wilbur C. Hall "Christmas Card" (Photograph pasted onto wood cutout on wood stand),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">nd
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="VC 0043">Visual Collection
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">White, E. V
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0010">E. V. White, 35th Battalion, Virginia Calvary CSA., n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition, November 4, 1961" Copy
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Mormon Battalion Monument in Sandoval County, New Mexico c.1956
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0001">Inscribed Tablet, oblique view. Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0002">Inscribed Tablet, flat view Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0003">Monument, Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0004">Monument, Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0005">Monument, Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0006">View landscape near monument, highway. Sandoval County, New Mexico, Kodachrome print
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Wilbur C Hall, Portraits
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0013">Wilbur Hall n.d. portrait in oval
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0014">Wilbur Hall, n.d. signed
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Janney, John
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0007">John Janney, Carte de Visite c. 1866, inscribed
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0016">Group Photograph: Lucas Phillips, Wilbur Hall &amp; Fred Howard at the Laurel Brigade Inn, n.d. 3x 5
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Jewel, William (1789-1852)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0017">William Jewell
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0018">Jewell Hall, William Jewell College, Liberty, MO
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Marshall, George C.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0008">George Marshall, n.d.
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0009">George Marshall, standing meeting with nine seated men, n.d. q stamped "National Geographic Society."
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Mosby, John S.
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0011">Col. John S. Mosby, C.S.A. 43rd Battalion, VirginiaCalvary CSA n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition, November 4, 1961" Copy
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Jackson, Stonewall
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0012">General Stonewall Jackson n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition November 4, 1961" (2 copies)
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 9 ">Rotary Meeting (Group Photograph)
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0015-01 ">Wilbur Hall, George Hammerly, William Hefner, unidentified man, at meeting (Rotary Club speech memorializing Marshall?) n.d. 8x 10
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="VC_0043_0015-02">Wilbur Hall, George Hammerly, William Hefner, unidentified
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
	</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>


