<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00048">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00048:: St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection 1952-2006)//EN" "viletbl00048.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection, <date>1952-2006</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection
<num type="collectionnumber">M 033
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Austin A. Backus
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date>20 February 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection, <date>1952-2006</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">M 033
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Austin A. Backus
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Austin A. Backus
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1952-2006
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 033
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">.66 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection consists of two groups of records: the first regards the church proper including directories and annual reports, the second regards the Mt. Calvary Guild records -- a woman's auxiliary group of the church
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="110$a">Ann Thomas
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection (M 033), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Ann Thomas, Round Hill, VA
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2007.0081
</p>
</accruals>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The first St. Peter's Episcopal Church was not built in Purcellville, VA until 1911, yet its story begins in 1871 in Leesburg, VA when the 76th Council of the Diocese of Virginia granted parishioners of Western Loudoun County the right to plant a church in Hamilton, VA.  An already extant Catoctin Free Church separated from St. James Episcopal Church, Leesburg, and established themselves as St. Paul's Church, Hamilton in 1877.  Bishop Alfred Randolph (1836-1918) consecrated the church seven years later in 1884.  Their first rector was the Reverend Theodore Reid who held the position from 1874 to 1878.</p>
<p>From Hamilton, after only a few years of continuous growth, another church was ready to be planted and became Mt. Calvary, Round Hill in 1892.  Mt. Calvary was consecrated six years later by Bishop Robert Gibson (1846-1919) in September of 1898.</p>
<p>Leesburg, Hamilton, Round Hill, and Purcellville all fell within the Shelburne Parish, with Purcellville lying in the middle of the three surrounding communities.  Though a small town, Purcellville grew rapidly and soon the need for another church within the Shelburne parish was evident.  In 1911, the first St. Peter's, Purcellville was built on Main Street.</p>
<p>In 1930, further growth resulted in the formation of a whole new Parish in Western Loudoun County - Madison Parish - carved off of Shelburne.  Madison Parish consisted of the three Episcopal churches of Hamilton, Round Hill, and Purcellville.  Eventually the three churches of Madison Parish saw benefit to consolidation.  Purcellville was chosen for the central location and a new St. Peter's Episcopal Church was built at its present location on Glendale Street in 1964.  That same year, parishioners held the first service of the newly merged church.</p>
<p>The bell tower which currently sits atop St. Peter's was erected in December 2000.  It housed two bells, both with significance to Loudoun County history.  The newer of the bells, dubbed "Loudoun," was cast in a Baltimore foundry in 1922 and dedicated in the old St. Peter's then on Main Street in Purcellville.  With this bell parishioners commemorated the loss of 29 Loudoun County men who died in World War I.  Their names still ring the outside of the 500 pound bronze memorial.  The older bell first resided in St. Paul's, Hamilton.  In 1909 it was given in memoriam of Lt. Jesup Nicholson (1852-1893) by his parents Mr. and Mrs. A. S. Nicholson.  Lt. Nicholson served in the USMC from 1873 -1874.  He died of Kidney disease.</p>
<p>Mt. Calvary Guild is Madison Parish's chapter of Episcopal Church Women (ECW).  When Mt. Calvary Guild was first organized is unknown, but by the time the three churches of Madison Parish had consolidated into St. Peter's the women's group had already been meeting.  Mt. Calvary Guild operated consistently from the early 1950s through to the present in order to conduct business, socialize, and share Bible devotions together.  Their business included fundraising for different charities, keeping the church hospitable through decorating, managing the church kitchen, and many other tasks necessary for the maintenance and function of the church building and community.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The St. Peter's Episcopal Church Collection consists of two groups of records: the first regards the church proper including directories and annual reports, the second regards the Mt. Calvary Guild records - a woman's auxiliary group of the church.</p>
<p>The collection of church records contains two profiles of the Parish, one from 1987 and the other from 2001.  Also included is an informational brochure on the 1987 expansion project with a program for the dedication service, a welcome folder from some time after September 2002, a program for the service installing Thomas Simmons, as 21st rector of the church, a church bulletin from March 1974, a secretarial form from 1974 regarding dances held at the church, a February 1952 newspaper article about John Shinberger, rector of Madison Parish from 1949 to 1958, a 1994 ballot with all communicants listed, narrative budget for 2003, Vestry Nominee write-ups for 1998, marriage records from 1871-1887, program for the 1994 Christmas Eve Midnight Mass, "Ministries and Events" brochure for fall 2005 - winter 2006, a color photograph of the alter at Christmas, 1975, church directories from 1869 to 2006; 1973, 1980, 1982, and 1984, are missing, "Annual Reports" from 1968 - 2006; 1969 is missing, and a folder of information regarding the "Bell Tower Capital Improvement Campaign" of 1998 - 2000; it includes sketches of the proposed bell tower, newspaper clippings, and other miscellaneous information and forms regarding the project.  Scattered pieces of paper are slipped into several of the pages of the Annual Reports and Church Directories providing additional information on the church for the given year. </p>
<p>The Mt. Calvary Guild/Women's Auxiliary records contain a bound account book recording credits from fundraisers and offerings, and debits due mostly to donations.  The record begins on 27 September 1960, and ends on 16 July 1980.  All the entries are hand-written.  The collection also includes minutes of the Mt. Calvary Guild meetings from 1957 to 1977, with 1972 missing; 1965 is the largest of the group.  Minutes from the 2000 meetings include small devotional writings used at the meetings.  There is also a post card with a black and white picture of the Loudoun Bell on it, a newspaper clipping from December 2000 of the new bell tower, a November 2000 "Good News" publication of St. Peter's church, and other miscellaneous newspaper clippings of women involved with Mt. Calvary Guild.               </p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Cocke, Charles Francis.  <title render="italic">Parish Lines Diocese of Virginia</title>.  Richmond: Virginia </bibref>
<bibref>Frain, Elizabeth R. and Marty Hartt.  <title render="italic">Loudoun County, Virginia Death Register
1853-1896</title>.  Westminster, Maryland: Willow Bend Books, 1998. </bibref>
<bibref><title render="italic">Journal of the Diocese of Virginia</title> (May 1885): 42, 57.</bibref>
<bibref><title render="italic">Journal of the Diocese of Southern Virginia </title>(May 1885): 33.</bibref>
<bibref><title render="italic">Journal of the 26th Council... of the Diocese of Southern Virginia</title> (1918).</bibref>
<bibref>Scheel, Eugene, <title render="italic">Loudoun Discovered.  Vol. 4, Quaker Country and the Loudoun Valley</title>.  Leesburg: Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002.</bibref>
<bibref>St. Peter's Episcopal Church Records (M 033), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref>
<bibref>"US Navy and Marine Corps Officers: 1775-1900."  Naval Historical Center.  http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/NHC/Callahan/reg-usmc.htm</bibref>
<bibref>St. Peter's Episcopal Church, http://www.stpetes.net/history.html.</bibref>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Annual Reports (2004 Missing),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2002-2006
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Annual Reports,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1996-2001
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Annual Reports,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1991-1995
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Annual Reports,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1982-1990
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Annual Reports,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1975-1981
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Annual Reports (1969 Missing),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1968-1974
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Events and Special Services
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Building Projects
	<unitdate type="inclusive">	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
 	<unittitle label="Folder 9">Church Profiles,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1987, 2001
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Church Directories,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1993-2006
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Church Directories (1984 Missing),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1983-2002
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Church Directories (1980 Missing),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1970-1981
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Mt. Calvary Guild Minutes, Bell Tower information, "Loudoun" Bell Post Card,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">2000
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Mt. Calvary Guild/Women's Auxiliary Minutes (1972 Missing),
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1957-1977
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Mt. Calvary Guild Account Book,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1960-1980
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Lists of Names and Communicants,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1986, 1990, 1994
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Register of Marriages in Madison Parish,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1871-1887
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 9">Clippings,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1952, 1997
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 10">Building Use Policy - Dances,
	<unitdate type="inclusive">1974
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>


</c01>


</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
