<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00041">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00041:: Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County 1971-1983)//EN" "viletbl00041.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County, <date>1971-1983</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County
<num type="collectionnumber">M 022
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Teckla H. Cox
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date>19 February 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County, <date>1971-1983</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">M 022
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Teckla H. Cox
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Teckla H. Cox
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1971-1983
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 022
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">9 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection is composed of architectural surveys made by John G. Lewis, contracted as Northern Virginia Representative, and David Edwards, Architectural Historian, with Virginia Historic Landmarks Department (now Virginia Department of Historic Resources).
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Commonwealth of Virginia, Department of Historic Resources
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County 1972-1983 (M 022), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Commonwealth of Virginia, Department of Historic Resources
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>1995.0027
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>This is an artificially created collection; supporting information has been added and future survey forms may be added. Folders are filed by Virginia Department of Historic Resources numbers.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>Loudoun County was established in 1757 but some of the surveys are of sites that pre-date the founding of the County. Geologically the county is divided at almost the midpoint with the best agricultural land lying from Goose Creek to the Blue Ridge Mountains. Thus buildings in the west are generally more sophisticated and were surveyed first. There were only two important plantations east of Goose Creek, Belmont and Coton, properties of Lee cousins. Coton has been destroyed but Belmont remains. It is listed on the National Register of Historic Places and is currently used as a country club for the Belmont development.</p>
<p>There are over 60 National Register properties in the county and five National Historic Landmarks. Few of these buildings are elaborate plantation houses. Many are smaller farmhouses demonstrating the sophistication that Loudoun County's affluent farmers incorporated particularly in the interior woodwork. Others are log buildings and a number combine log, stone and brick demonstrating the progression of elegance as the farmers became successful.</p>
<p>Loudoun County, especially in its western half, had excellent farmland and was known throughout the state for its agricultural superiority until the 1970s when its proximity to Washington, D.C. began to draw developers. Less desirable farmland in the eastern half was developed first with large planned communities. In the west where no public sewer or water is available development began in the 1990s with very large houses on individual lots. Consequently, traditional agricultural has all but disappeared although small scale specialty farming is replacing it in some areas and the equine industry in the southwestern part of the county is still flourishing.</p>
<p>There are seven incorporated towns and numerous villages in the county. The early villages and towns grew up as market or commercial centers to serve the agricultural community. Later towns such as Hamilton, Purcellville and Round Hill developed in the 19th century as stops on the Washington and Old Dominion Railroad.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection is composed of architectural surveys made by John G. Lewis, contracted as Northern Virginia Representative, and David Edwards, Architectural Historian, with Virginia Historic Landmarks Department (now Virginia Department of Historic Resources). The bulk of the surveys are of sites in Loudoun County; however, there are survey files of Waterford that cover the entire village and a few surveys of Round Hill, Bluemont, Hillsboro, Middleburg, and Purcellville. The survey forms illustrate the many styles of architecture that became fashionable from the 18th century to the 20th century. There is also a set of USGS maps, with sites identified by their state assigned numbers.</p>
<p>The collection includes 969 folders covering information about sites in Loudoun County. The sites are numbered from 0001 to 1090. Missing numbers do not always indicate missing files. Some numbers or blocks of numbers were unassigned by the state. County sites are numbered with a prefix beginning with 053. Towns and major villages each have their own prefixes, e.g. Waterford: 401, Bluemont: 404, Hillsboro: 236, Middleburg: 259, Purcellville: 286. Files of National Register properties and National Historic Landmarks are marked on the folders with red stars.</p>
<p>The entire village of Waterford was surveyed by John G. Lewis. The files are numbered 1 through 138 although as is the case of the county files, some numbers were not utilized. Six folders contain surveys of two structures because the structures, while once separate, are now combined. A map of the Village of Waterford showing individual properties with state numbers is located with Waterford surveys.</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<bibref>Cox, Teckla H., retired Loudoun County Planner.
</bibref>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>Alphabetic and numeric lists of properties compiled by the Virginia Department of Historic Resources are available in the library, as well as a notebook listing sites by name of property and owners. Access to this information is also available through a database at the reference desk. A list of numbered properties in the towns and villages is located at the end of the Lewis/Edwards folders.
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p><title render="italic">"Notebooks of John G. Lewis on Areas of Loudoun County: Aldie, Catoctin &amp; Goose Creek, Hillsboro, Lincoln &amp; Loudoun Settlements &amp; Middleburg,</title>" VREF 975.528 LEW. <title render="italic">"Middleburg. Virginia - 1977, an Architectural Survey"</title> by John G. Lewis, VREF 975.528 LEW. <title render="italic">"Architectural Survey of the Older &amp; Historic Structures in the Town of Waterford, Virginia" </title>by John G. Lewis, VREF 975.528 LEW. <title render="italic">"The Minor Bartlow House 1744-1970"</title> by John G. and Elisabeth Lewis VREF 975.528 LEW. <title render="italic">"Photo Report of Various Structures Which Were Photographed but not Either Researched or Surveyed"</title> by John G. Lewis, VREF 975.528 LEW. Additional related information may be found in a vertical file labeled "Historic Properties."
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
<separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Separated Material
</head>
<p>OMB 006 -- USGS Quad Maps
</p>
</separatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="File Drawer" type="drawer">1
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folders">53-1 through 53-249
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>
	
</c01>


<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="File Drawer" type="drawer">2
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folders">53-250 through 53-669
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="File Drawer" type="drawer">3
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="file">
	<did>
	<unittitle>
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
	<p>Folders 53-670 through 53-1090 plus 5546. Numeric list of surveyed properties in towns and villages: Middleburg (prefix 259) 4 folders; Hillsboro (prefix 236) 2 folders; Purcellville (prefix 286) 1 folder; Waterford (prefix 401) 121 folders; Bluemont (prefix 404) 10 folders. The map of Waterford with sites numbered with the State designated numbers is also located at the beginning of the Waterford files.
	</p>
	</scopecontent>
	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">OM 006
</container>
</did>




	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Box 1">USGS maps, A-L
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Box 1">USGS maps, M-W
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did>
	</c02>

</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
