<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="viltbl00276">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00282::  Loudoun Agricultural Society Records )//EN" "viltbl00282.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>  Loudoun Agricultural Society Records
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort"> Loudoun Agricultural Society Records
<num type="collectionnumber">SC 0122
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Caroline Kessler
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher> Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169; 2016 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.<!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Laura Christiamsem, <date>20 December 2016</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper> Loudoun Agricultural Society Records
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">SC 0122
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2016
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Caroline Kessler
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a"> Loudoun Agricultural Society Records
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 0122
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>Less than .33 cubic ft.  </extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The collection contains 4 items related to the Loudoun Agricultural Society dating from 1852-1876.
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">Loudoun County Historical Society
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Loudoun Agricultural Society Records(SC 0122), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Loudoun County Historical Society
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2004.001
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Caroline Kessler, 9 August 2016
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>The Agricultural Society of Loudoun, Fauquier, Prince William, and Fairfax was founded during 1825 and 1826 in order to spread agricultural knowledge and innovation among the farmers of the respective counties. In March of 1842, a separate body was created in Loudoun County, called the Agricultural Society of Loudoun, also known as the Loudoun Agricultural Society and the Loudoun County Agricultural Society. The First Annual Meeting occurred in Leesburg on 19 October 1852, with Benjamin Hallowell (fl. 1800-1879) of Alexandria delivering the opening address.</p>
<p>In 1854, the Loudoun County Agricultural Academy and Chemical Institute was created with the aid of Benjamin Hyde Benton (fl. 1839-1857) to educate farmers in method and business skills, and to serve as a resource to catalogue ecological samples from the state of Virginia. The Institute offered the first vocational training in Loudoun but closed in 1861 as an effect of the Civil War, never to be reopened. In 1857, stock in the Society cost $20, with Robert L. Wright (1813-1865) signing as president and John W. Wildman (1822-1890) as treasurer.</p>
<p>The Agricultural Society sponsored an annual county fair in Leesburg during the 1850s and after the Civil War. The Eleventh Annual Fair and Cattle Show of the Agricultural Society was held in 1871. The fair awarded cash prizes ranging from $1-10, and after the Civil War, emphasis was placed on the Domestic Manufactures and Home Manufactures categories to encourage the production of local and homemade wares. Other competition categories included culinary classes and household fabrics. In November of 1873, President Ulysses S. Grant visited Leesburg and attended one such fair. </p>
<p>In the years after the Civil War, the Agricultural Society was assisted in their efforts by the formation of the Loudoun County Livestock Exhibition Association in the late 1800s. Farming associations were popular at this time, with the intention to revitalize local economies and restore stability to the area. Similar and concurrent organizations included the Catoctin Farmers' Club (est. 1863) and the Patrons of Husbandry, also known as the Grange (est. locally 1875), which later (1892) developed into the Populist Party. Club meetings were held over a meal served at a member's house and often comprised of a discussion of prices, a guest speaker or presentation, and an informal tour of the host's premises.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The collection contains 4 items, the earliest of which is a booklet published by the Agricultural Society in 1853 that replicates the address given by Benjamin Hallowell at their First Annual Meeting on 19 October 1852. The booklet was once secured by a stitched binding, and the spine is now covered by tape. Following the address is a stock certificate titled to Dr. A. R. Mott (1823-1894), dated 10 November 1857. The certificate is numbered 86 and quantifies one share in the Society, costing $20. The heading of the certificate is ornamented by two plough illustrations, a replication of which can be found on the third item, a blue silk prize ribbon. This ribbon is from the 1859 Loudoun Agricultural Fair, which was held in Leesburg in November. The ribbon has been sleeved, and in addition to the plough symbol, it also bears the image of a sheep.</p>
<p>The final item in the collection is a photocopy of a letter dated 1 May 1876 that was originally found in the Ledger of John Norris &amp; Sons, which covers 1858 to 1861. The letter contains an unfilled proxy form to designate alternative representation at the Annual Meeting of the Stockholders that was to be held on the second Monday in June 1876. The letter is closed by Henry Bronaugh (1844-1887), secretary of the Society. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<bibliography encodinganalog="581$a">
<head>Bibliography
</head>
<p><bibref>Ancestry Library Edition, United States census, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Loudoun Agricultural Society Records (SC 0122), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Poland, Charles P. Jr. From Frontier to Suburbia. Missouri: Walsworth Publishing, 1976.</bibref></p>
<p><bibref>Thomas Balch Library. Town of Leesburg. Loudoun County Cemetery Database, http://www.leesburgva.gov/services/library/cemetery/default.aspx.</bibref></p>
</bibliography>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<phystech encodinganalog="538$a">
<head>Technical Requirements
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</phystech>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Catoctin Farmers' Club Records (M 034), Mott-Bentley Family Correspondence (M 116), Norris and Sons Account Book (BV 005)
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<unittitle label="SC 0122">
</unittitle>
</did>
	<c02 level="subseries">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Box 1">
	</unittitle>
	</did>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 1">Address of Benjamin Hallowell, of Alexandria, at the First Annual Meeting of the Agricultural Society of Loudoun County, VA., Held at Leesburg, October 19, 1859 Booklet
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 2">1857 Loudoun Agricultural Society Stock Certificate
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 3">Photocopy of 1876 Letter and Proxy Form
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
<c03 level="item">
		<did>
		<unittitle label="Folder 4">1859 Loudoun Agricultural Fair Blue Ribbon
		</unittitle>
		</did>
		</c03>
		</c02>
</c01>
</dsc></archdesc>
</ead>
