<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/tbl.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/tbl_contact.xml">
]><ead id="viletbl00081">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViLeTBL">PUBLIC "-//Thomas Balch Library//TEXT (US::ViLeTBL::viletbl00081:: Catoctin Mountain Alliance 1985-1995)//EN" "viletbl00081.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Catoctin Mountain Alliance, <date>1985-1995</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Catoctin Mountain Alliance
<num type="collectionnumber">M 031
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2006 By Thomas Balch Library. All rights reserved.
</date> 
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MS Word, created by Beth Schuster, <date>9 September 2008</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Catoctin Mountain Alliance, <date>1985-1995</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Thomas Balch Library
<num type="Collection Number">M 031
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Thomas Balch Library
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2006
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Rebecca K. Ottinger
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Thomas Balch Library
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Thomas Balch Library
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Catoctin Mountain Alliance
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1985-1995
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">M 031
</unitid>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a">1.66 cu. ft.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">These records date from 1985 after the filing of the first request for a special exception by Beacon Hills Farm Associates and continue until 1995 with the announcement that marketing would begin on the Beacon Hill property under the plan of development which had been approved by the Loudoun County Planning Commission in 1992, a proposal approved by the Catoctin Mountain Alliance.  
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="110$a">B. Powell Harrison 
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection open for research .
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>No physical characteristics affect use of this material.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>Catoctin Mountain Alliance, 1985-1995 (M 031), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Sharon Kearns, Leesburg VA
</p>
</acqinfo>
<altformavail>
<head>Alternative Form Available
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>2006.0024
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Rebecca K. Ottinger, 2 June 2008</p>
<p>Research notes created in preparing the collection guide are available with the collection at the repository.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Historical Information
</head>
<p>On 27 June 1979 Beacon Hill, an estate composed of approximately 2,083 acres owned by Arthur (1903-1983) and Mary (1913-1997) Godfrey, was sold to Saudi Prince Talal bin Abdul Aziz (1935-) for just over five million dollars.  Godfrey was a nationally known radio personality in the 1950's who sometimes broadcast from his farm.  The prince made extensive changes and additions to the property, spending approximately 18 million dollars on these projects</p>
<p>On 16 November 1985 Beacon Hill was bought by a partnership called Beacon Hill Farm Associates (BHFA), later changed to Beacon Hill Farm Associates II, Limited Partnership. In September 1985, based on a conditional contract for the property BHFA applied to the Board of Zoning Appeals for a special exception to begin development of this property.  This action began a ten year long process of filings for various levels of development.  Neighbors of Beacon Hill organized Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association which closely monitored each step and fought the plans before the Loudoun County Planning Commission, with the Planning and Zoning Departments of the County, and in court.  B. Powell Harrison (25 Aug 1911-1 Nov 2000), was president of this association, and lawsuits were filed by him and his wife, Agnes Harrison.  The name of the organization changed to Catoctin Mountain Alliance in 1987, but the focus remained the same: to fight the high density development of the targeted property.  During the course of this fight Loudoun County Board of Supervisors passed the Mountainside Development Overlay District to regulate development on the mountainsides in Loudoun County; this law covered the Beacon Hill property.</p>
<p>The struggle between Beacon Hill Farm Associates II, Limited Partnership and Catoctin Mountain Alliance continued until 1992 when Loudoun County government approved plans to allow houses to be built on large tracts, an option which met with approval of Catoctin Mountain Alliance.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>These papers are files compiled by B. Powell Harrison who chaired this organization, originally named the Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association; in February 1987 the name was briefly changed to TBD Group (To Be Determined); on 1 June 1987 the group voted to change its name to Catoctin Mountain Alliance.   These records date from 1985 after the filing of the first request for a special exception by Beacon Hills Farm Associates and continue until 1995 with the announcement that marketing would begin on the Beacon Hill property under the plan of development which had been approved by the Loudoun County Planning Commission in 1992, a proposal approved by the Catoctin Mountain Alliance.  Records include news articles, speeches, letters, memos, zoning applications, lawsuits, financial records, and Harrison's notes regarding the proposed development of Beacon Hill. Records reflect order in which documents were arranged in Harrison's files; they are not always in chronological order. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<descgrp type="add">
<head>Adjunct Descriptive Data
</head>
<otherfindaid>
<head>Other Finding Aid
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</otherfindaid>
<phystech encodinganalog="538$a">
<head>Technical Requirements
</head>
<p>None
</p>
</phystech>
<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544$a">
<head>Related Material
</head>
<p>Vertical File, "Arthur Godfrey," Thomas Balch Library; Lewis Edwards Architectural Survey, "Beacon Hill," Thomas Balch Library
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List
</head>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">1
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Miscellaneous letters, news articles, and applications,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1986-1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Letters, news articles, petitions, and notices to the members of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> July 1979-November 1985 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Letters and public statements,
 	<unitdate type="inclusive"> January 1986-May 1986
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Letters, memos, and news articles,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> February-April 1986 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Financial records of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1985-1986 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Memos, letters, and reports,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> July 1986-June 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Membership list of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association, letters, and memos,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> November 1985-March 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Letters and memos,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> November 1985-May 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 9">News articles, press releases, memos, and advertisements,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> May-June 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 10">Public statements, memos, and letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> September-December 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 11">Statements, Letters, and memos,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> August-87 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 12">Statements, news articles, and letters,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> January-March 1988 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">2
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations most of which concern lawsuits regarding Beacon Hill,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> January-June 1988
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations most of which concern lawsuits regarding Beacon Hill,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> July-December 1988
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Miscellaneous articles, letters, reports, opinions, and presentations regarding "Episode 6" in which Beacon Hill Farm Associates II Limited Partnership sought to reverse the decision of the zoning administrator which said that the Mountainside Overlay District Ordinance applied to the their subdivision applications,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations regarding Beacon Hill. Also in opposition to Village Ordinance being considered as part of new Comprehensive) Plan,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> January 1989-October 1991 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Miscellaneous papers from 1989 mainly regarding Beacon Hill Farm Associates II's refiling of lawsuits,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 18-May-89 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Papers concerning lawsuits of Beacon Hill Farm Associates II and their applications to amend Rural Land Management Plan and application for subdivision of part of Beacon Hill Farm,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> January-April 1990 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Letters, articles, presentation regarding Beacon Hill Farm Associates II's application for special exception to allow subdivision of 1,092 acres of Beacon Hill into 70 building lots. Articles and reports relating Catoctin Mountain Associates' dropping its opposition to this proposal on conditions affecting road systems and mountain views. Letters and article reporting plans by Elm Street Development of McLean to begin marketing the approved lots. 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1992-1995 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">3
</container>
</did>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Letters requesting donations to support work of Catoctin Mountain Alliance, thank you letters to donors,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> October 1988-September 1990 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Thank you letters to donors to Catoctin Mountain Alliance,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1990-1992 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Catoctin Mountain Alliance members and donation information,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Miscellaneous correspondence regarding Catoctin Mountain Alliance,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Thank you letters to donors,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1988 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Information regarding Loudoun County's Mountainside Overlay Ordinance
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 7">Legal study commissioned by Piedmont Environmental Council and Catoctin Mountain Alliance of "Comprehensive Plan and its relation to the zoning ordinance" prepared by attorneys Robert E. Sevila and Tersh Boasberg; press releases; miscellaneous financial information
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 8">Letters, memos, reports; finances of Catoctin Mountain Alliance,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> June 1987-December 1989 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 9">Bills, letters, financial records of Catoctin Mountain Alliance,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1990-1995 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">4
</container>
</did>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Studies, letters, memos from Connie Krueger, Secretary of Catoctin Mountain Alliance (CMA), to B. Powell Harrison, President of CMA,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1989-1990 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Studies, memos, public statements regarding development proposed by Beacon Hill Associates II; news articles regarding plans for other developments,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987-1989 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Updated Beacon Hill Residential Development Traffic Impact Study prepared by Kellerco 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Studies and reports of Virginia Department of Transportation and Loudoun County agencies regarding proposed development of Beacon Hill. Statement of B. Powell Harrison to Board of Supervisors,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 14-Dec-89 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Statements, memos, reports regarding development of Beacon Hill; outline for Loudoun County, Virginia Zoning Ordinance,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1989-1990 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 6">Memos, reports letters, news articles,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1988-1990 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
<did>
<container label="Box" type="box">5
</container>
</did>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 1">Miscellaneous reports, articles, memos, lawsuits regarding development of Beacon Hill Estate. Chapter 36, Code of Virginia. 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987-1988 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 2">Beacon Hill Project Schedule, 1987 Cumulative Supplement, Code of Virginia, reports, lawsuits, memos regarding proposed Beacon Hill development,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 3">Reports, memos, lawsuits, zoning applications, magazine article,
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 1987-1988 	
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 4">Zoning application, memos, articles, Beacon Hill Site Access Plan prepared by Kellerco, 
	<unitdate type="inclusive"> 17-Jul-87 
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>

	<c02 level="item">
	<did>
	<unittitle label="Folder 5">Letters, memos, zoning application, news articles regarding development of Beacon Hill Estate; plan for development of Cheswick in western Loudoun. 
	<unitdate type="inclusive">
	</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
	</did> 
       	</c02>


</c01>

</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>

