<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00019">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00019::A Guide to the J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Papers, 1850-1987//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00019&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00019::A Guide to
             the J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Papers, 1850-1987//EN"
             "vih00019"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the J. Lindsay Almond Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1987</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Almond, J. Lindsay, Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 AL685 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 63 KB</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from paper by
         means of word processing program. Machine-readable finding aid
         created by Eileen Parris, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 June 2002.</date>]</creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00019::A Guide to the J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.,
            Papers, 1850-1987//EN" "vih00019" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1850-1987</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 AL685 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1850-1987</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 AL685 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">2,8000 (ca.) items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Correspondence, 1925-1983;
         speeches, 1927-1979; financial and legal papers, 1948-1978;
         scrapbooks, 1934-1963; newspaper clippings, 1931-1987;
         miscellaneous volumes; certificates and awards. Correspondence
         is non-official, but touches on Almond's term as Governor of
         Virginia and on his appointment to the U.S. Court of Customs
         and Patent Appeals. Scrapbooks and clippings document his
         campaigns and terms as attorney general and governor of
         Virginia, and contain a great deal of information on
         Virginia's resistance to school desegregation. Also included
         in the collection are correspondence, speeches, and
         miscellaneous papers of Almond's wife, Josephine Katherine
         (Minter) Almond (1901-1992), some of which concerns her
         service as First Lady of Virginia.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>J. Lindsay Almond Papers, 1850-1987 (Mss1 AL685 a FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of the estate of Josephine Katherine (Minter)
            Almond, through the courtesy of Lewis S. Minter, in
            1992.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>James Lindsay Almond, Jr., was born June 15, 1898, in
         Charlottesville, Va., the son of Lindsay and Eddie Nicholas
         (Burgess) Almond. At an early age his family moved to a farm
         in rural Orange County, Va. Almond entered the University of
         Virginia in 1917 as a member of the Student Army Training
         Corps but withdrew a year later and consequently served for a
         year as principal of the Zoar High School near Roanoke, Va.,
         1921- 1922. He then entered the University of Virginia School
         of Law and earned his law degree in 1923. He had been admitted
         to the Virginia Bar in 1921. He was in private practice as a
         lawyer in Roanoke, Va., 1923- 1932, and quickly became known
         for his handling of criminal cases.</p>
      <p>A Democrat, Almond's interest in politics began in his
         teens. His involvement with Democrat Harry Flood Byrd began in
         1925, when Almond made several speeches in support of Byrd's
         gubernatorial campaign. With Byrd's help, Almond was appointed
         assistant Commonwealth's attorney for the city of Roanoke,
         1930-1933, and a judge of the Roanoke Hustings court,
         1933-1945. He was later appointed to the 79th U.S. Congress
         and elected a member of the 80th U.S. Congress. The Virginia
         Democratic Party, led by Harry F. Byrd, asked Almond to step
         down from his Congressional seat and run for attorney general
         of Virginia, to which position he was elected in 1948. He
         served in this office until 1957, at which time he resigned to
         run for governor of Virginia.</p>
      <p>Both Almond's campaign for and service as governor were
         dominated by Virginia's response to the Supreme Court's school
         desegregation edict. As governor, he inherited a program of
         "massive resistance" designed to halt school integration by
         erecting a series of defensive obstacles. Realizing the
         movement was doomed and if continued would potentially destroy
         the Commonwealth's educational system, in January 1959 Almond
         admitted defeat and established a commission to develop a plan
         for the integration of Virginia's public schools. Almond's
         reversal on this issue cost him the support of the Harry F.
         Byrd and his many supporters.</p>
      <p>Following Almond's term as governor, he was appointed by
         President John F. Kennedy as an interim judge of the U.S.
         Court of Customs and Patent Appeals, Washington, D.C. With
         U.S. Senator Harry F. Byrd on the Senate Judicial Committee,
         it took much campaigning on the part of Almond's friends and
         supporters to secure his official appointment to this post in
         1963. He served as a member of this court until his retirement
         in 1986.</p>
      <p>J. Lindsay Almond married Josephine Katherine Minter
         (1901-1992) in 1925. A native of Roanoke, Va., Mrs. Almond
         attended Elizabeth College in Salem, Va., and received her
         bachelor's degree in 1923 from Wittenberg University in Ohio.
         The Almond's had no children, but raised Mrs. Almond's orphan
         nephew, Lewis S. Minter, from infancy. Mr. Almond died April
         14, 1986, and is buried in Evergreen Cemetery, Roanoke,
         Va.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Series 1 contains the non-official correspondence of J.
         Lindsay Almond, Jr., 1925-1983, chiefly as governor and while
         he was seeking a federal judgeship. Subjects mentioned include
         concerns of constituents; recommendations of persons for
         appointments by various state and local officials; the attempt
         on Almond's life in April 1959; Almond's stand on school
         desegregation (see the correspondence of Alburtis S. Harrison,
         Jr., Charles L. Lady, and Sydney F. Small); and the efforts of
         Almond's supporters to get him a position on the U.S. Court of
         Patent Appeals (see the correspondence of George Edward Allen
         (1885-1972), Miner Carl Andrews, Lester R. Bachner, Harry
         Flood Byrd (1887-1966), James O. Eastland, Charles Rogers
         Fenwick, Eppa Hunton IV, John Fitzgerald Kennedy, Robert
         Francis Kennedy, Marvin E. Nuckols, Jr., and A. Willis
         Robertson). This appointment was blocked for almost a year by
         U.S. Senator Harry F. Byrd, a member of the Senate Judicial
         Committee, who had broken with Almond over the latter's
         apparent reversal of his support of school desegregation and
         the policy of "massive resistance." Also included is scattered
         family correspondence, chiefly concerning the health of
         Almond's mother, Edmonia Nicholas (Burgess) Almond (d.
         1966).</p>
      <p>Series 2 contains speeches given on various occasions.
         Subseries 2.1, Speeches by J. Lindsay Almond, are arranged
         chronologically. See 1958-1960 for the bulk of speeches
         concerning school desegregation. Subseries 2.2, Speeches by
         Others, is arranged alphabetically by author.</p>
      <p>Series 3 includes scattered financial and legal records,
         1948-1978, of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., consisting of records of
         sale and purchase of residential real estate in Roanoke and
         Richmond, Va., loose accounts and papers including forms
         relating to his employment as a federal judge, canceled
         checks, an account book for his expenses relating to the last
         illness and death of his mother, Edmonia Nicholas (Burgess)
         Almond (d. 1966) of Locust Grove, Va., and miscellaneous items
         including an affidavit concerning the Virginia Senatorial
         campaign of 1946 and its connection with the C.I.O. Political
         Action Committee and a list of firearms owned by Mr.
         Almond.</p>
      <p>Series 4 includes scrapbooks, 1934-1963, containing chiefly
         newspaper clippings from Richmond and Roanoke, Va., newspapers
         documenting the various careers of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. The
         volumes are arranged in four subseries as follows: Subseries
         4.1 documents Almond's career as a judge of the Roanoke City
         Hustings Court and as a member of the U.S. House of
         Representatives. Series 4.2 documents Almond's return to
         Virginia to serve as Attorney General. Subseries 4.3 documents
         Almond's campaign for, election as, and service as governor of
         Virginia. Prominently mentioned is his fight against
         court-ordered desegregation of public schools. Subseries 4.4
         in many ways overlaps previous subseries but also includes a
         scrapbook concerning the Roanoke Racing Homer Club, Roanoke,
         Va., of which Almond was a member, and a 1963 barbecue given
         in Almond's honor.</p>
      <p>Series 5 consists of newspaper clippings, 1931-1987,
         arranged chronologically, chiefly from Roanoke and Richmond,
         Va., papers. Subjects include Almond's service as Attorney
         General of Virginia, campaign for and election as Governor of
         Virginia, the "massive resistance" movement, and the Almonds'
         life after leaving office. See also: Oversize.</p>
      <p>Series 6 contains brief biographical statements,
         occasionally in resolution form. Some items were evidently
         attached to letters of recommendation for various
         appointments. Persons represented include: J. Lindsay Almond,
         Josephine Katherine (Minter) Almond, Jerome M. Alper, Rufus
         Adolphus Ayers, Leroy S. Bendheim, Charles Newton Bordwine,
         Carter Lee Burgess, Mortimer Maxwell Caplin, Albert Edward
         Cox, John Alvin Crogan, Constantine N. Dombalis, John H. East,
         F. Howard Forsyth, Connie Barriot Gay, Edward Wren Hudgins,
         Thomas G. Massie, Joe G. Matthews, Josephine (Umberger)
         Minter, C. E. Myers, Andrew E. Newton, Gene A. Robens, Bradley
         Roberts, William L. Saunders, Erwin Seago, Robert N. W. Welch,
         and Elijah Brockenbrough White.</p>
      <p>Series 7 contains non-scrapbook volumes. Subseries 7.1
         consists of Almond's appointment registers, 1951-1961 (90 v.)
         kept while he was Attorney General and Governor of Virginia.
         Entries are short, often containing only the name of the
         person visiting. Occasionally mention is made of subject
         matter to be discussed. Almond's attendance at official
         functions (including receptions, luncheons, conferences) is
         also noted. Subseries 7.2 consists of miscellaneous volumes,
         including a letterbook, 1919 April 30-May 9, containing drafts
         of letters from J. Lindsay Almond to Josephine Katherine
         (Minter) Almond; student notebook, 1923 March 4-June 1, kept
         at the University of Virginia Law School; Roll book, 1957
         November 5, containing recollections of J. Lindsay Almond's
         gubernatorial victory, collected by the Almond Booster Club of
         Roanoke, Va.; and Guest register, 1958 April 22-1962 January
         4, of visitors to the Governor's Mansion.</p>
      <p>Series 8 includes diplomas, certificates of membership in
         various organizations, law licenses and certificates of
         qualification to appear before various courts, masonic
         materials, and miscellaneous items received during Almond's
         careers. Of special interest are his diploma from the
         University of Virginia, 1923; his law license, 1921; a
         certificate of appointment to the U.S. Court of Customs and
         Patent Appeals, 1962, signed by John F. Kennedy and Robert P.
         Kennedy; oath as Attorney General of Virginia, 1950;
         certificate of election as Democratic Party candidate for
         governor, 1957; and Virginia Senate Resolution No. 30 upon his
         death. (Many items are oversized.)</p>
      <p>Series 9 contains miscellaneous and other papers, including
         Almond family papers (will, 1956, of Edmonia Nicholas
         (Burgess) Almond; letter, 1891, of W. W. Scott to T. W.
         Almond); Almond family genealogical notes; funeral program for
         I. T. Minter (d. 1934), father of Josephine (Minter) Almond;
         writings about J. Lindsay Almond; original poetry and
         Christmas greetings from friends; and minutes of meetings,
         1974, of the Colon Club of Richmond, Va., a social club made
         up of members of the Richmond business and political
         elite.</p>
      <p>Series 10 contains the papers of Josephine Katherine
         (Minter) Almond. Subseries 10.1, Correspondence, 1942-1986,
         consists chiefly letters expressing support for J. Lindsay
         Almond's candidacy and election as governor, and of his
         actions as governor. Also, personal and family correspondence.
         Correspondents of note include Mildred Almond (concerning
         strained relations between J. Lindsay Almond and his brother
         over the care of their invalid mother), Jacqueline (Bouvier)
         Kennedy Onassis, Lewis S. and Ted A. Minter, Woodrow T. Scurry
         (of Roanoke, Va., a black man who spent time in prison and
         credited Gov. Almond with helping him to turn his life
         around), Wilbur Walker (concerning the Governor's schedule),
         and Edith Galt Bolling Wilson (of Washington, D.C., discussing
         Democratic politics and her relationship with the President
         and Mrs. Kennedy). Subseries 10.2, Speeches, 1940-1983,
         contains the text of speeches delivered by Mrs. Almond on
         various occasions. Arranged chronologically where possible,
         alphabetically by subject otherwise. Subseries 10.3., Other
         papers, 1923-1974, includes notes for speeches, commonplace
         containing poetry and prose, financial materials concerning
         household expenses at the Governor's Mansion, guest lists for
         planning events at the Governor's Mansion, notes for
         interviews, scrapbooks, and awards.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Organization</head>
      <p>Organized into ten series by material type. Correspondence
         is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Other materials
         are arranged chronologically wherever possible.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>Almond, J. Lindsay (James Lindsay),
         1898-1986.</subject>
      <subject>Almond, Josephine Katherine Minter, 1901-
         1992.</subject>
      <subject>Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.</subject>
      <subject>Democratic Party (Va.) -- History -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Eastland, James O. (James Oliver),
         1904-1986.</subject>
      <subject>Governors' spouses -- Virginia -- Social life and
         customs.</subject>
      <subject>Harrison, Albertis S. (Albertis Sydney),
         1907-1995.</subject>
      <subject>Judges -- Appointment, qualifications, tenure,
         etc.</subject>
      <subject>Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald),
         1917-1963.</subject>
      <subject>Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.</subject>
      <subject>Political campaign -- Virginia -- History -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Political oratory -- Virginia -- History -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>School integration -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Scrapbooks -- Virginia -- History -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Speeches, addresses, etc.</subject>
      <subject>United States. Court of Customs and Patent
         Appeals.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Politics and government --
         1865-1950.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Politics and government --
         1951-</subject>
      <subject>Virginia. Governor (1958-1962 : Almond)</subject>
      <subject>Virginia. Office of the Attorney
         General.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Virginia -- Political activity.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Virginia -- Social life and customs --
         20th century.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Correspondence, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1925-1983.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1-11</container>
        </did>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Alphabetical by correspondent.</p>
        </arrangement>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Speeches, undated and 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1946-1969.</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.1">Speeches by J.
                  Lindsay Almond, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1946-1969.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12-17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.2">Speeches by Others, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1927-1979.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Financial and legal
               materials, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1948-1979.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Real estate records, 1948-1964; loose accounts,
               1958-1978; cancelled checks, 1960-1966; account book,
               1962-1967; and miscellaneous, 1949 and n.d.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Scrapbooks.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.1">Scrapbooks, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1945-1948.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20-21</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Document Almond's career as a judge of the Roanoke
                  City Hustings Court and as a member of the U.S. House
                  of Representatives.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.2">Scrapbooks, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1946-1956.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22-23</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Document Almond's return to Virginia to serve as
                  Attorney General.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.3">Scrapbooks, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1956-1961.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">24-32</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Documents Almond's campaign for, election as, and
                  service as governor of Virginia. Prominently
                  mentioned is his fight against court-ordered
                  desegregation of public schools.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.4">Scrapbooks, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1934-1963.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">33-35</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>This subseries in many ways overlaps previous
                  subseries but also includes a scrapbook concerning
                  the Roanoke Racing Homer Club, Roanoke, Va., of which
                  Almond was a member, and a 1963 barbecue given in
                  Almond's honor.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Newspaper Clippings, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1931-1987.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">35
               (cont.)-37</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Biographies.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">38</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Miscellaneous
               volumes.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.1">Appointment
                  registers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1951-1961.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">39</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.2">Miscellaneous
                  volumes, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1919-1962.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">40</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Letterbook, 1919 April 30-May 9; student notebook,
                  1923 March 4-June 1, kept at UVA; roll book, 1957
                  November 5, Almond Booster Club, Roanoke Va.; guest
                  register, 1958 April 22-1962 January 4.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Certificates and awards, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1919-1982.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">41</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Diplomas, certificates of membership in various
               organizations, law licenses and certificates of
               qualification to appear before various courts, masonic
               materials, and miscellaneous items received during
               Almond's careers.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Miscellaneous and Other
               papers, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1857-1974.</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">41 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Papers of Josephine
               Katherine (Minter) Almond.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 10.1">Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1942-1986.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">42</container>
          </did>
          <arrangement>
            <p>Alphabetical by correspondent.</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 10.2">Speeches, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1940-1983.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">43</container>
          </did>
          <arrangement>
            <p>Arranged chronologically where possible,
                  alphabetically by subject otherwise.</p>
          </arrangement>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 10.3">Miscellaneous and
                  Other papers, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1923-1974.</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">44</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
