<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00004">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00004::Lupton Family Papers, 1745-1895)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00004.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00004::Lupton Family
             Papers, 1745-1895)//EN" "vih00004.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Lupton Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1745-1895</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Lupton Family Papers, 1745-1895 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 L9747 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">16 KB</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from
         Wordperfect. Machine-readable finding aid created by James
         Berwick, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">15 February 2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00004::Lupton Family Papers, 1745-1895)//EN"
            "vih00004.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
            (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Lupton Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1745-1895</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 L9747a FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Lupton Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1745-1895</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 L9747a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">1,400 (ca.) items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Correspondence, accounts, land
         records, Society of Friends (Hopewell Meeting) records,
         miscellany and estate materials of David Lupton (1757-1822) of
         Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va. Also include
         correspondence, accounts,mercantile records and estate
         materials of Nathan Lupton (of Winchester, Va.). Also, include
         correspondence, accounts, bonds, Civil War materials and
         miscellany of Jonah H. Lupton (of Frederick County, Va.).
         Also, include letters, account books, accounts, bonds,
         agricultural records, saw mill records, patent materials and
         miscellany of Joel Lupton (of Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick
         County, Va.). Also, include letters, accounts, student
         notebook, literary club records, fam materials of David P.
         Lupton (of Springdale," Frederick County, Va.). Also, include
         materials of Mary Walker (Lupton) Irish, David Lupton (1786-
         1814), Edward Walker Lupton, Hugh Sidwell Lupton, Isaac
         Lupton, Joseph Lupton (1718-1791), Joseph Lupton (1781-1825),
         and Lewis Lupton.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>No restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>No restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Cite as Lupton Family Papers, Mss1 L9747a FA2, Virginia
            Historical Society, Richmond, VA</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift/purchase of Thornton Tayloe Perry, III, Washington,
            D.C., and Mrs. Barclay K. Read, McLean, Virginia, in 1984.
            Accessioned 20 June 1986.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist>
        <head>Custodial History</head>
        <p>Formerly a part of the collections of Thornton Tayloe
            Perry II of Charles Town, West Virginia.</p>
      </custodhist>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Lupton family settled along Apple Pie Ridge near
         Winchester in Frederick County, Va., during the colonial
         period. Represented are farmer and landowner Joseph Lupton
         (1718-1791); his son, farmer, millwright and Quaker leader
         David Lupton (1757-1822); David's sons Joseph (1781-1825);
         David (1786-1814), a merchant in Alexandria, Va.; Nathan
         (1792?-1843), a merchant in Winchester, Va.; Jonah H.
         (1795-1870), farmer and horsebreeder; and Joel Lupton
         (1804-1883), farmer, millwright and manufacturer; and Jonah's
         son David P. Lupton (1846-1918) of "Springdale," Frederick
         County.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Joseph Lupton (1718-1791) settled a large tract near Bobb's
         March in Frederick County and became a major landowner. His
         land records in this collection, covering the period
         1759-1800, trace the title to a number of tracts in the county
         obtained from various parties. Joseph's son David Lupton
         (1757-1822) established the Quaker or Apple Pie Ridge branch
         of the family in Frederick County. He was a prominent farmer,
         millwright and Quaker leader. His correspondence, 1795-1822,
         largely focuses on family, fellow Quakers and on land dealings
         in Ohio. Among the more frequent or prominent correspondents
         are James Chenoweth (bearing a design for the internal
         mechanism of a grist mill); Philadelphia merchant and Quaker
         leader Samuel Rowland Fisher; Phineas Janney, an Alexandria
         merchant and Lupton's son-in-law; David Lupton (1786-1814),
         also a merchant in Alexandria; and Joseph Steer, a millwright
         and Quaker kinsman at Millgrove, Ohio.</p>
      <p>David Lupton's accounts, 1810-1822, include records of
         funds collected as agent for Samuel and Miers Fisher of
         Philadelphia, Pa. His land records (Box 2) trace title to
         tracts in Frederick and Hampshire counties and lots in
         Winchester, Va., and consist of deeds, plats, grants, etc. The
         Hampshire County (now W. Va.) materials primarily consist of
         records, 1789-1821, from the lawsuit of Lupton v. Azariah Pugh
         in the Virginia Superior Court of Law for the county,
         concerning lands of Jesse Pugh and containing articles of
         separation, 1808, of Jesse Pugh and Elizabeth (Gray) Pugh.</p>
      <p>As a member of Hopewell Meeting of the Society of Friends,
         David Lupton and his son Jonah H. Lupton recorded marriage
         certificates in the official record books. His papers contain
         a number of original marriage certificates, 1787-1833, signed
         by bridge and groom and witnessed by family members, guests,
         and members of the meeting. Included is a certificate for the
         marriage of David Lupton (1786-1814) and Ann McPherson at
         Hopewell in 1809.</p>
      <p>David Lupton collected materials, 1758-1815, concerning the
         estate of Isaac Hollingsworth, father of Lupton's first wife,
         Mary (1758-1814). The materials concern land in Winchester,
         Va., and include the will of Hollingsworth written in Loudoun
         County, Va., in 1758. Materials, 1813-1823, of the estate of
         Thomas McClun, father of Lutpon's second wife, Rachel (b.
         1773), include an inventory, will of Isaac Neil written in
         Frederick County, conditions for renting a plantation, a power
         of attorney to Nathan Lupton, an agreement and receipts. David
         Lupton served as an administrator of the estate of Henry
         Wells, a free black also known as "Black Harry" or "Free
         Harry." The materials contain an appraisal, account of the
         estate sale and general receipts.</p>
      <p>Miscellany of David Lupton illustrates his importance as a
         community leader. This includes an affidavit of John Mason of
         Anacostia Island, D.C., 1812; notes on a packing press; an
         agreement concerning Lupton's arbitration of a dispute; a
         subscription to the literary work of educator Aquila Massey
         Bolton; a will of Nicholas Scarff written in Frederick County,
         1815; and birth and death records of family members.</p>
      <p>David Lupton's sons, Joseph, Nathan and Joel, served as
         executors of his estate. Materials, 1823-1851, include
         correspondence, bonds and accounts (including accounts with
         tenants and agents); an inventory and appraisal; notice
         (broadside) and account of the estate sale; deeds and other
         real property records, including the rental of a mill; an
         agreement of the heirs; and records of litigation, especially
         the lawsuit of Asa H. Hoge (administrator of Rebecca (Lupton)
         Hoge) et al v. Nathan Lupton in the Virginia Circuit Superior
         Court for Law and Chancery for Frederick County, which
         includes the estates of Issac and Joseph Lupton.</p>
      <p>A few items exist in this collection for Joseph Lupton
         (1781-1825), David Lupton's eldest son. These include a trust
         agreement, 1817, miscellany, and an agreement and accounts of
         the estate, 1829. Lupton's son David (1786-1814) settled in
         Alexandria, Va., as a merchant. Records, 1814-1840, of his
         estate include a will written in 1814, materials in Ann
         (McPherson) Lupton v. Phinas Janney (including correspondence
         of lawyer Thomas Semmes with John McPherson Lupton), accounts
         and protested bonds of Abijah Janney &amp; Co. Of Alexandria
         (also concerning John McPherson &amp; Co. Of Alexandria); and
         letters and accounts, 1818- 1823, of Ann (McPherson)
         Lupton.</p>
      <p>Nathan Lupton (1792?-1843), fourth son of David Lupton,
         worked as a merchant in Winchester, Va. His correspondence
         (Box 4), 1815-1843, is especially heavy for the years
         1842-1843 and centers on the sale of flour, wheat and pig
         iron. There is much correspondence with Baltimore merchants
         and with George Franklin Hupp, proprietor of Columbia Furnace
         in Shenandoah County, and Joseph S. Machir, a Strasburg
         merchant. Nathan Lupton's account book, 1828, concerns farm
         labor, construction costs and the estates of David Lupton
         (1757-1822), Joseph Lupton (1781-1825) and Isaac Lupton. His
         accounts, 1829-1835, 1842-1843, detail a mixture of personal
         and business concerns.</p>
      <p>As a merchant, Lupton kept receipts for the sale and
         shipment of wheat and flour and store orders for merchandise,
         1842-1843. Receipts, 1842-1843, for the transportation of pig
         and bloom iron from Columbia Furnace by R. W. Ashton for
         George Franklin Hupp are largely directed to John Mason of
         Georgetown, D.C. Miscellany includes a trusteeship for John
         McPherson and Son of Alexandria in 1818. Estate materials
         consist of an inventory, appraisals, receipts and bonds.</p>
      <p>Nathan's brother Jonal H. Lupton (7195-1870) was a
         Frederick County farmer and horse-breeder. His few items of
         correspondence, 1823-1861, primarily consist of family
         letters, but there are some letters from Quaker educator and
         historian Samuel McPherson Janney at Springdale Boarding
         School in Loudoun County (see also accounts, 1855). Jonah
         Lupton's bonds include a number executed by Phineas Janney as
         president of the Bank of the Potomac in Alexandria, D.C. (now
         Va.), 1843-1846.</p>
      <p>A number of items relate to the family of Martha Ann
         Sidwell, Jonah Lupton's first wife. These include an epitaph
         for Martha Ann Sidwell (1792-1795); will of Richard Sidwell
         probated in Frederick County, 1805; unexecuted deed for land
         of Richard Sidwell; letters, 1818-1836, written to Martha Ann
         (Sidwell) Lupton and her commonplace book, 1813-1814,
         consisting primarily of lines of verse. Jonah H. Lupton's
         Civil Ware materials include a copy of a petition, 1863, of
         the loyal citizens of Winchester and Frederick County to
         Abraham Lincoln in behalf of General Robert Huston Milroy
         (signed by Jonah and Joel Lupton and 63 others); an account of
         property taken in 1861; passes; a certificate of loyalty,
         permit, order and requisition. Lupton's miscellany includes
         Society of Friends materials, 1829-1869, and two items of his
         second wife, Lydia (Walker) Lupton.</p>
      <p>Joel Lupton (1804-1883) also lived along Apple Pie Ridge,
         where he pursued a busy career as farmer, millwright and
         manufacturer. Lupton received letters, 1823-1878, from a
         number of different inventors and agents who were seeking to
         sell and distribute their versions of early threshing
         machines. Among these were Dr. Chester Clark of Philadelphia
         and Hazard Knowles of Washington, D.C. Lupton also took great
         interest in sawmill operation, as well as entering a business
         partnership with Henry Lowe of Baltimore in the paper
         manufacturing firm of Lavender, Lowe and Lupton.</p>
      <p>The account book, 1846-1866, of Joel Lupton concerns timber
         harvesting and sawmill operation with his brother Lewis. They
         had contracted to supply the Winchester and Potomac Railroad
         Company with their lumber needs. The book also bears accounts
         with Ridge Meeting of the Society of Friends in Frederick
         County (final page) and accounts of an unidentified Winchester
         merchant, 1815-1832 (the volume is filed oversize following
         Box 6).</p>
      <p>His accounts, 1823-1883, heaviest in the 1830s-1840s,
         indicate Joel Lupton invested significantly in the Winchester
         and Potomac Railroad, like his brothers. Agricultural records
         consist of railroad receipts for the shipment of hay, flour
         inspection certificates, receipts for the sale of wheat, and
         rates and regulations on the Winchester and Potmac Railroad.
         Agreements and deeds concerning land in Frederick and
         Hampshire counties, 1829-1847, largely concern mills.</p>
      <p>A number of items chronicle Joel Lupton's dealings with
         inventors or their agents (Box 7). These include Dr. Chester
         Clark and Pierson Reading (for improvements on threshing
         machines) and George C. Cochran (as an agent of manufacturers
         of a sausage meat cutter). Joel Lupton's miscellany contains
         records of sawmill operations, 1845-1851 (including an
         unexecuted agreement with the Winchester and Potomac Railroad
         Company); materials concerning the partnership of Lavender,
         Lowe, and Lupton; and records of a trusteeship by Henry Moore
         Brent.</p>
      <p>David P. Lupton (1846-1918), a son of Jonah H. Lupton,
         lived at "Springdale" in Frederick County. Letters, 1888-1895,
         written to this farmer are mostly from kinsmen. A student
         notebook, 1869, concerns the principles of surveying. Lupton
         and his younger sister, Rebecca Jane (Lupton) Broomell
         (1848-1924), belonged to a local literary club known as "The
         Sociable." Some records of this group that survive here are
         minutes (kept by their cousin Maria C. Lupton as secretary)
         and criticisms of meetings, 1873-1876, as well as copies of
         several handwritten numbers of a literary "magazine" edited by
         David and Rebecca Lupton, "The Social Evening," a work
         "Devoted to Literature, Humor, etc." (1874-1882). There is
         also one number of a similar volume edited by David P. Lupton
         called "The White Star: Devoted to Literary, Social and Moral
         Advancement" (1887).</p>
      <p>Farm materials of David P. Lupton consist of a deed for
         land, 1873; a certificate awarded by the Mutual Farmers' Club
         of Frederick County; notes and reports, 1874, to the Mutual
         Farmers' Club on dairy farming, animal husbandry and corn
         crops; an agreement, 1890; and broadsides.</p>
      <p>The last portion of the collection consists of a few items
         each for David Lupton'sa sons Isaac and Lewis Lupton; John M.
         Lupton and Co. Of Winchester, Va. (Operated by John McPherson
         Lupton, son of David Lupton (1786-1814)); and children of
         Jonah H. Lupton: Edward Walker Lupton, Hugh Sidwell Lupton and
         Mary Walker (Lupton) Irish.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <arrangement>
        <head>Arrangement</head>
        <p>Materials arranged into series according to primary
            creator.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <arrangement>
        <head>Organization</head>
        <p>The ten series are further subdivided by document type
            and organized chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>Agriculture -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Apple Pie Ridge (Frederick County, Va.) --
         History.</subject>
      <subject>Family -- Virginia -- Social life and
         customs.</subject>
      <subject>Farm life -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Frederick County (Va.) -- Economic conditions --
         19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Hopewell Monthly Meeting (Society of
         Friends)</subject>
      <subject>Irish, Mary Walker Lupton.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, David, 1757-1822.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, David, 1786-1814.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, David P., 1846-1918.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Edward Walker.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton family.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Hugh Sidwell.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Isaac.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Joel, 1804-1883.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Jonah H., 1795-1870.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Joseph, 1718-1791.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Joseph, 1781-1825.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Lewis.</subject>
      <subject>Lupton, Nathan, 1792?-1843.</subject>
      <subject>Merchants -- Virginia -- Frederick County --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Mills and mill-work -- Virginia -- Frederick
         County -- History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Saw-mills -- Virginia -- Frederick County --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Society of Friends -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- History -- Civil War,
         1861-1865.</subject>
      <subject>Winchester (Va.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Joseph Lupton (1718-1791),
               Frederick County, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1759-1800</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Land records.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">David Lupton (1757-1822),
               Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.1">Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1757-1822</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.2">Accounts, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1810-1822</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.3">Land records, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1745-1821</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.4">Quaker marriage
                  certificates,</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.5">Estates of Isaac
                  Hollingsworth, Thomas McClun, and Henry
                  Wells.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.6">
                  Miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 2.7">Estate, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1823-1851</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Joseph Lupton (1781-1825),
               Frederick County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Agreements, miscellany, estate accounts.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">David Lupton (1786-1814),
               Alexandria, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Estate materials; Ann (McPherson) Lupton
               materials.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Nathan Lupton (1792?-1843),
               Winchester, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1815-1843</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 5.1">Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1815-1843</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 5.2">Financial
                  papers.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Account books, loose accounts and bonds, wheat and
                  flour receipts, store orders, 1843; iron trade.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 5.3">Miscellany and
                  estate.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4
                  cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Jonah H. Lupton (1795-1870),
               Frederick County, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1823-1861</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 6.1">Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1823-1861</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 6.2">Financial
                  materials.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 6.3">Sidwell family
                  materials.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 6.4">Civil War
                  materials.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 6.5">
                  Miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Joel Lupton (1804-1883),
               Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1823-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.1">Letters, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1823-1878</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)-6</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.2">Account book, loose
                  accounts, and bonds. 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1823-1883</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.3">Agricultural
                  materials and land records, patent materials, and
                  miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">David P. Lupton (1846-1918),
               "Springdale," Frederick County, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1874-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Miscellaneous family
               materials.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>T</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 8.1">Letters, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1888-1895</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 8.2">Accounts and bonds, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1874-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 8.3">School and club
                  materials; miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">General Miscelleous family
               materials.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.1">Isaac
                  Lupton.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.2">Lewis
                  Lupton.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.3">John McPherson
                  Lupton.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.4">Edward Walker
                  Lupton.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.5">Hugh Sidwell
                  Lupton.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 9.6">Mary Walker (Lupton)
                  Irish.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">General
               miscellany.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">9 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Frederick County land records; unclassified
               miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
