<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00014">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00014::A Guide to the Wilson Family Papers, 1790-1944)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00014.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00014::A Guide to
             the Wilson Family Papers, 1790-1944)//EN"
             "vih00014.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Wilson Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790-1944</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Wilson Family Papers, 1790-1944 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 W6997 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">There are no
               restrictions</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">26 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         VHS staff, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">12 April 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00014::A Guide to the Wilson Family Papers,
            1790-1944)//EN" "vih00014.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Wilson Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1790-1944</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 W6997 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Wilson Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1790-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 W6997 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">3,050
         items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Chiefly papers of Rev. Lewis
         Feuilleteau Wilson of Gerrardstown and Hedgesville, Berkeley
         County, W. Va., including correspondence, 1831-1873, loose
         accounts, 1833-1872, Presbyterian church materials for
         Berkeley County and for Shenandoah County, Va., and post
         office records, 1836-1845, for Woodstock, Va. Also present are
         the papers of Mary Elizabeth (Chamberlin) Wilson of
         Gerrardstown and of Kabletown, Jefferson County, W. Va.,
         including correspondence, 1844-1894, and scrapbooks; papers of
         Hall Wilson of Gerrardstown and Kabletown, including
         correspondence, 1867-1910, loose accounts, 1859-1915, and
         other materials; and papers of Charles Lee Wilson of
         Kabletown, San Francisco, Calif., and Astoria, Ore., including
         correspondence, 1870-1889, describing his life and work in
         California and Oregon and his travels in the Washington
         Territory, 1885-1888, accounts, 1875-1889, Hampden-Sydney
         College materials, 1871-1874, and general miscellany. Also
         present in the collection are the diary, 1827-1828, of William
         McPherson (1748?-1831) and correspondence, 1836-1875, of Jane
         MacPherson (d. 1877) of Charles Town, W. Va., and Baltimore,
         Md., including many letters from family members in the North
         and Midwest giving a Union perspective on the Civil
         War.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Wilson Family Papers, 1790-1944 (Mss1 W6997 a FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift/purchase of Dr. Thornton Tayloe Perry, Washington,
            D.C., and Mrs. Barclay K. Read, McLean, Va., in 1984.
            Formerly a part of the collections of Thornton Tayloe Perry
            II of Charles Town, W. Va.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Wilson and related McPherson and Chamberlin families of
         Jefferson and Berkeley counties, W. Va. The McPhersons and
         Chamberlins were prominent in the Quaker community.
         Individuals represented in the collection include Lewis
         Feuilleteau Wilson (1804-1873), Presbyterian minister of
         Gerrardstown and Hedgesville, Berkeley County; Wilson's third
         wife, Mary Elizabeth (Chamberlin) Wilson (1815-1895) of
         Gerrardstown; and Hall Wilson (1847-1916) of Gerrardstown and
         Kabletown, Jefferson County, farmer and active member of the
         Democratic Party.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection opens with a few items each of several
         early members of two prominent Quaker families in what is now
         Jefferson County, W. Va. William McPherson (1748?-1831) kept a
         diary, 1827-1828, which contains cryptic notes on weather and
         family members. An 1825 letter from his son Jonas (b. 1773)
         discusses the latter's mercantile activities in Baltimore, Md.
         The papers of McPherson's contemporary, Jonas Chamberlain (d.
         1794), include accounts, a list of land warrants, and estate
         materials, all primarily from the 1790s. Also included are
         accounts of his wife, Mrs. Elizabeth Chamberlin.</p>
      <p>Chamberlin's son Elijah (d. 1818) married his first cousin
         Mary McPherson (1780?-1860), daughter of William McPherson and
         Jane Chamberlin. Elijah Chamberlin lived in Charles Town,
         Jefferson County. Among letters written to him, 1798-1817, is
         one interesting missive from William Cranch and William
         Thornton concerning sheep breeding. His financial records
         include accounts with Ferdinando Fairfax (1797, 1809).
         Chamberlin and John McPherson served as administrators of the
         estate of James Proctor (d. 1806) of Muse's Mill in Jefferson
         County. Their materials, 1804-1811, concerning the estate
         include letters to Proctor, loose accounts, (including
         accounts with Dr. John Dalrymple Orr and William Byrd Page)
         and receipts for wheat.</p>
      <p>Elijah Chamberlin's papers likewise include receipts from
         Alexandria merchants for the sale of flour, a commonplace
         book, 1790-1792, including accounts, and an order for lumber
         on the account of Ferdinando Fairfax, 1817. Daniel McPherson
         (b. 1775) served as his cousin's administrator. Estate
         materials include items concerning the guardianship of
         Chamberlin's children by his widow and litigation in courts in
         Jefferson and Loudoun counties.</p>
      <p>Mary (McPherson) Chamberlin's records consist of accounts,
         1819-1867 (especially receipts for tax payments in Jefferson
         County and Winchester, Va.), bonds, 1833-1837, and miscellany.
         Her estate materials include wills, 1849-1859, written in
         Berkeley County, Va. (now W. Va.), a note of lawyer John
         Hazlehurst Boneval Latrobe, receipts and an obituary
         notice.</p>
      <p>Mary (McPherson) Chamberlin's records consist of accounts,
         1819-1867 (especially receipts for tax payments in Jefferson
         County and Winchester, Va.), bonds, 1833-1837, and miscellany.
         Her estate materials include wills, 1849-1859, written in
         Berkeley County, Va. (now W. Va.), a note of lawyer John
         Hazlehurst Boneval Latrobe, receipts and an obituary
         notice.</p>
      <p>Lewis Feuilleteau Wilson (1804-1873), founder of this
         particular Wilson line in West Virginia, attended Princeton
         Theological Seminary and was ordained a Presbyterian minister
         in 1832. He was accepted into the Winchester Presbytery in
         that year and served as pastor at Woodstock and Strasburg
         churches in Shenandoah County until 1835. The latter year he
         moved to Berkeley County, where he remained the rest of his
         life as pastor of Presbyterian congregations at Falling
         Waters, Gerrardstown and Tuscarora.</p>
      <p>Wilson maintained correspondence, 1831-1873 (Box 3),
         primarily with fellow ministers in the Winchester Presbytery
         and as chairman of the Presbytery's Committee on Education,
         and with ministerial students at Jefferson College,
         Cannonsburg, Pa. (now Washington &amp; Jefferson College,
         Washington, Pa.) and at Union Theological Seminary in
         Virginia. Among the more frequent or prominent of these
         correspondents are ministers John Mayo Pleasants Atkinson,
         William Henry Foote (including minutes of the Presbytery
         concerning Wilson), James Robert Graham (of Winchester), John
         Lodor (of Montvue Collegiate Institute, Frederick County, Va.)
         and Samuel B. Wilson (of Fredericksburg, Va. ). Ministerial
         students include Jacob Doll, Stewart Robinson and William W.
         Stickley. There are also a number of letters from sisters of
         Wilson's first wife, Emeline (Forman) Wilson (1811-1837) of
         Freehold, N.J.</p>
      <p>Wilson's financial records, 1833-1872, include loose
         accounts of his second wife, Harriet Ann (Tabb) Wilson
         (1838-1839). Presbyterian Church materials concern Wilson's
         pastorates in Shenandoah and Berkeley counties (Box 5), as
         well as his work in the Winchester Presbytery. The Berkeley
         county materials consist of resolutions and reports; accounts;
         certificates of church membership; lists of subscribers to
         church buildings and a fund to defend "Old School"
         Presbyterians in a lawsuit in 1837; records, 1869-1871, of the
         education of Charles Scott Lingamfelter as a Presbyterian
         minister; and sermons preached by Wilson and William Thomas
         Leavell in Charles Town, 1858-1860. Wilson also retained
         marriage licences, 1833-1853, issued by court clerks in
         Berkeley, Jefferson, Morgan and Shenandoah counties,
         certificates issued for Negro slave marriages, and reports of
         marriages performed, 1847-1859.</p>
      <p>The records of Wilson's work on the Education Committee of
         the Winchester Presbytery are comprised of letters written to
         William Caldwell Matthews as chairman, 1834-1835 (including
         letters of Layton Y. Atkins [an elder in Fredericksburg],
         Jacob Doll, John Lodor and Stewart Robinson); accounts,
         1832-1860, mostly for educational expenses of ministerial
         students Jacob Doll, James J. Gardner, William C. Sheetz and
         Frederick Nicholas Whaley (including receipts from educators
         John Lodor and Samuel M. Whann); committee reports; and
         letters, 1833-1834, of John Lodor and Stewart Robinson to
         James Moore Brown of Martinsburg, Berkeley County, Va. (now W.
         Va.).</p>
      <p>Miscellaneous Presbytery materials include an affidavit and
         deed of William Henry Foote; official communications,
         1838-1869 (including a Charles Town broadside); letters,
         1832-1852; records of Wilson as moderator of the stated
         meeting in Front Royal, Va., in 1858; lists of pastors; and
         general miscellany.</p>
      <p>Box 6 contains records, 1836-1845, of the U.S. Post Office
         at Woodstock in Shenandoah County, kept by the postmaster,
         James Allen, a member of Wilson's congregation. The records
         consist of correspondence (including letters signed by Amos
         Kendall); quarterly accounts with the Post Office Department;
         receipts of payments to contractors; dead letter accounts;
         inventories of property and letters; and miscellany. Wilson's
         personal miscellany consists of bonds, materials concerning
         the guardianship of two of his sons, and receipts for wheat
         issued by millers at Spring Mills and Tuscarora Mills in
         Berkeley County. Lastly, there are some letters addressed to
         Emeline (Forman) Wilson, 1834-1836, primarily from family
         members in Freehold, N.J.</p>
      <p>Wilson's third wife, Mary Elizabeth (Chamberlin) Wilson
         (1815-1895), lived in Kabletown, Jefferson County,
         Gerrardstown and Hedgesville, Berkeley County, W. Va. Her
         correspondence, 1844-1894 (Boxes 7-12), is largely
         family-oriented, consisting of many letters from her children
         and stepchildren, as well as members of the Chamberlin family.
         Among the correspondents are William M. Chamberlin, James
         Robert Graham, John Henry Miller (a Lynchburg native who
         became a prominent attorney in San Francisco, Calif.) and
         Edwin Lindsley Wilson.</p>
      <p>Mrs. Wilson's youngest son, Charles Lee Wilson, attended
         Hampden-Sydney College in Virginia (1871-1874), taught school
         in Jefferson County, and then left for California in 1876. He
         wrote a letter home to his mother nearly every week for the
         next thirteen years. During that time his lengthy and
         interesting letters describe his activities as a clerk,
         stockbroker and customs officer in San Francisco (1876-1878,
         1881- 1884; including references to the Vigilance Committee in
         July 1877); a miner in Darwin, Calif. (1877-1878); a real
         estate broker in Oakland, Calif. (1878); a teacher at St.
         Matthers Hall, a military school in San Mateo, Calif.
         (1878-1881); a manager for the Alaska Commercial Co. on
         Ounalaska Island, Alaska Territory (1882); and a bookkeeper
         for salmon canneries in Astoria, Oregon, and Tacoma,
         Washington Territory (1885- 1888).</p>
      <p>Accounts, 1837-1891; scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and
         recipes, and general miscellany complete the papers of Mary
         Elizabeth (Chamberlin) Wilson (Box 12). The following box
         contains records of the Wilsons' eldest son, teacher Valerius
         Winchester Wilson (1839-1902), of Guinea Station and Woodford,
         1909; accounts, 1854-1887; and a lease, 1873, to a house in
         Kabletown, W. Va.</p>
      <p>Edwin Lindsley Wilson (1845-1915) was a Presbyterian
         minister in Gerrardstown, W. Va., and later in Waterford,
         Loudoun County, Va. His correspondence, 1866-1908, is
         primarily with brothers Hall Wilson and Charles Lee Wilson,
         while his accounts, 1865-1886, include records of his
         education at Winchester Classical School and Hampden-Sydney
         College (both 1866). There are also materials concerning his
         pastorate at Gerrardstown Presbyterian Church, 1874-1880. The
         correspondence, 1874-1909, of his wife, Nannie Elizabeth
         (Dupuy) Wilson (1849-1925), primarily concerns her husband and
         Charles Lee Wilson.</p>
      <p>Born Ashmun Hall Wilson (1847-1916), this Gerrardstown and
         Kabletown farmer soon dropped his first name. Hall Wilson was
         active in Democratic party politics in Berkeley County and was
         also a master of Mill Creek Grange. His correspondence,
         1867-1910 (Boxes 14-18), includes a large number of letters
         from Dr. Coketon, Durbin and Thomas, W. Va.) and Lewis
         Feuilleteau Wilson Edwin Graham Wilson and Frances Keightley
         (Timerlake) Wilson (concerning Edwin Lindsley Wilson); and his
         farm manager in Jefferson County, Benjamin F. Yates.</p>
      <p>Hall Wilson's loose accounts cover the period 1859-1915.
         Agricultural materials consist of agreements, notices,
         government reports and bulletins, tickets to local fairs, and
         miscellany. Democratic party materials, 1891-1908, include
         notices of meetings, campaign materials and broadsides, and a
         certificate as commissioner of elections in Berkeley County,
         1900. Records, 1873-1884, concerning Wilson as public school
         trustee in Jefferson County and materials, 1893-1899,
         regarding Gerrardstown Presbyterian Church also appear in the
         collection. A few items of miscellany (Box 20) conclude Hall
         Wilson's papers.</p>
      <p>Mary Emma (Seibert) Wilson (b. 1850), Hall Wilson's wife,
         maintained correspondence, 1864-1909, with many members of her
         family including brothers Fredericks N. Seibert (of
         Hedgesville, concerning local births, marriages and deaths)
         and Luther F. Seibert. Charles Scott Lingamfelter wrote a
         number of letters to her while a student at Hampden-Sydney
         College, as did her sister-in-law Ophelia Forman (Wilson)
         Harper. Emma Wilson's student essays and exercises, 1867-1869,
         have been preserved, along with a few items of miscellany (Box
         20).</p>
      <p>The youngest Wilson son, Charles Lee Wilson (1856-1889),
         has been mentioned above. Additional records of his in Box 21
         consist of correspondence, 1870-1889, while in Kabletown, W.
         Va., San Francisco, Calif., and Astoria, Oregon. Among the
         correspondents are John Henry miller and G. Edgar Walraven
         (while a student at Bethel Academy in Fauquier County, Va.).
         Accounts cover the period 1875-1889; Hampden-Sydney College
         records, 1871-1874, include reports, certificates and
         accounts. Letters of recommendation and introduction,
         1876-1888, have been preserved, as have a catalog, prospectus
         and history of St. Matthews Hall, San Mateo, Calif. News
         clippings, 1884, concern the history of vigilantes in San
         Francisco, Calif. Notes and an essay prepared by Wilson cover
         his trip from Martinsburg, W. Va., to Astoria, Oregon, in
         1887.</p>
      <p>The collection closes (Box 22) with a few items of
         correspondence of Lewis Feuilleteau Wilson (b. 1873), a fruit
         grower in Gerrardstown, W. Va., followed by miscellany of a
         number of other family members who also appear elsewhere in
         the collection, particularly within the correspondence of
         major figures discussed above. These family members include
         George E. Chamberlin, John Chamberlin, Jonas Chamberlin
         (1805?-1855), William M. Chamberlin, Jane M. (Chamberlin)
         Hamill, Charles Edwin Harper, Ophelia Forman (Wilson) Harper,
         Catherine Virginia (Hedges) Seibert, James Hall Wilson, and
         other members of the Chamberlin, Seibert, and Wilson
         families.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The collection is arranged in sixteen series by individual
         and further subdivided by document type or subject where
         necessary.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>California -- Description and travel --
         1869-1950.</subject>
      <subject>Chamberlin family.</subject>
      <subject>Gerrardstown (W. Va.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Hedgesville (W. Va.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Kabletown (W. Va.) -- History.</subject>
      <subject>McPherson family.</subject>
      <subject>McPherson, Jane, d. 1877.</subject>
      <subject>McPherson, William, 1748?-1831.</subject>
      <subject>Oregon -- Description and travel -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Presbyterian Church -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Presbyterian Church -- West Virginia -- History --
         19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Shenandoah County (Va.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
         -- Public opinion.</subject>
      <subject>Washington (State) -- Description and travel --
         19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Wilson, Charles Lee, 1856-1889.</subject>
      <subject>Wilson family.</subject>
      <subject>Wilson, Hall, 1847-1916.</subject>
      <subject>Wilson, Lewis Feuilleteau, 1804-1873.</subject>
      <subject>Wilson, Mary Elizabeth Chamberlin,
         1815-1895.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">William McPherson
               (1748?-1831), Jefferson County, Va. (now W.
               Va.)</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Diary, 1827-1828; letter, 1826.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Jonas Chamberlin (d. 1794),
               Berkeley County, Va. (now W. Va.) 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1790-1817</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Accounts, 1790-1796; list of land warrants; estate
               materials, 1795-1801; Mrs. Elizabeth Chamberlin's
               accounts, 1802-1817</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Elijah Chamberlin (d. 1818),
               Charles Town, Jefferson County, Va. (now W. Va.) 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1790-1858</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters, 1798-1817; accounts, 1795-1817; wheat and
               flour milling (James Proctor estate, receipts);
               commonplace book, 1790-1792; miscellany; estate
               materials, 1826-1858</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Mary (McPherson) Chamberlin
               (1780?-1860), Charles Town, Jefferson County, Va. (now
               W. Va.)</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Accounts, 1819-1867; miscellany; estate materials,
               1849-1869</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Samuel MacPherson
               (1798-1873), Charles Town, Va. and Baltimore,
               Md.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1820-1868; accounts, 1828-1838;
               miscellany, 1821-1828</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Jane MacPherson (d. 1877),
               Charles Town, Va. (now W. Va.) and Baltimore, Md. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1833-1875</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1836-1875; accounts, 1833-1836,
               1858-1867; miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Lewis Feuilleteau Wilson
               (1804-1873), Gerrardstown and Hedgesville, Berkeley
               County, Va. (W. Va.)</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.1">Correspondence,
                  1831-1873</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.2">Loose accounts,
                  1833-1872</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.3">Presbyterian Church
                  materials, 1832-1872</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Berkeley County, Va. (now W. Va.) and Shenandoah
                  County, Va., churches, marriage licences, Winchester
                  Presbytery.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.4">Post Office records
                  and miscellany 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1836-1845</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Woodstock, Va., Post Office records, 1836-1845;
                  personal miscellany; Emeline (Forman) Wilson
                  letters.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Mary Elizabeth (Chamberlin)
               Wilson (1815-1895), Gerrardstown and Hedgesville,
               Berkeley County, Kabletown, Jefferson County, W.
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 8.1">Correspondence,
                  1844-1894</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7-12</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Arranged alphabetically by correspondent</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 8.2">Accounts, scrapbooks
                  and miscellany 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1837-1891</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Accounts, 1837-1891; scrapbooks (second volume
                  filed oversize after this box); miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Valerius Winchester Wilson
               (1839-1902), Guinea Station, Woodford, Va., and
               Hedgesville, W. Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1871-1896; accounts, 1854-1887;
               lease, 1873</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Edwin Lindsley Wilson
               (1845-1915), Gerrardstown, W. Va., and Waterford,
               Loudoun County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1866-1908; accounts, 1865-1886;
               Gerrardstown Presbyterian Church.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">Nannie Elizabeth (Dupuy)
               Wilson (1849-1925), Gerrardstown, W. Va., and Waterford,
               Loudoun County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1874-1909</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">Hall Wilson (1847-1916),
               Gerrardstown and Kabletown, W. Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 12.1">Correspondence,
                  1867-1910</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">14-18</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 12.2">Accounts, Political
                  materials, and miscellany, 1859-1915</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Loose accounts, 1859-1915; agricultural materials,
                  1868-1908; Democratic party activities; 1891-1908;
                  Jefferson County school trustee, 1873-1884;
                  Gerrardstown Presbyterian Church, 1893-1899; personal
                  miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 13">Mary Emma (Seibert) Wilson
               (b. 1850), Gerrardstown and Hedgesville, W.
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">20</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1864-1909; student essays and
               exercises, 1867-1869; miscellany</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 14">Charles Lee Wilson
               (1856-1889), Kabletown, W. Va., San Francisco, Calif.,
               and Astoria, Oregon.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1870-1889; accounts, 1875-1889;
               Hampden-Sydney College, 1871-1874; letters of
               recommendation, 1876-1888; St. Matthews Hall; newspaper
               clippings; notes and essay, 1887; general
               miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 15">Lewis Feuilleteau Wilson
               (b. 1873), Gerrardstown, W. Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1883-1908</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 16">Family miscellany 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1796-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">22 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Chamberlin, Seibert and Wilson family members,
               1796-1944.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
