<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00015">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00015::A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 1819-1976)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00015.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00015::A Guide to
             the Page Family Papers, 1819-1976)//EN"
             "vih00015.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819-1976</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Page Family Papers, 1819-1976 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 P1456 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">73 kb.</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         VHS staff, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">April 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00015::A Guide to the Page Family Papers,
            1819-1976)//EN" "vih00015.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1819-1976</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 P1456 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1819-1876</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 P1456 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">2,050 (ca.)items (18 manuscipt
         boxes)</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Page Family Papers, 1819-1976 (Mss1 P1465 a FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Mrs. William Maury Hill, Richmond, Va., in 1989.
            Accessioned June 26, 1996.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Records of four generations of the Page family of Hanover
         County and Richmond, Va., and related families. Represented
         are Francis Page (1780-1849); his son John Page (1821-1901) of
         "Oakland," Hanover County, a graduate of the University of
         Virginia, lawyer, and for four years an attorney for the
         Commonwealth in Hanover County; Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson)
         Page (1821-1912), wife of John Page and mother of Francis
         Page, Thomas Nelson Page, and Rosewell Page; Robert Nelson
         (1819-1886), Episcopal missionary to China and brother of
         Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page; Robert's wife, Rose (Points)
         Nelson (1827-1885); Francis Page (1849- 1918), better known as
         "Frank," an Episcopal priest who served parishes in Virginia,
         Texas, and Brooklyn, N.Y.; Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) of
         Richmond, Va., Washington, D.C., and York Harbor, Me., lawyer,
         lecturer and writer, and U.S. Ambassador to Italy from
         1912-1918; Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page (1867-1888), first wife of
         Thomas Nelson Page and originally from "Staunton Hill,"
         Charlotte County, Va.; Florence (Lathrop) Field Page
         (1858-1921), first married to Henry Field (brother of Marshall
         Field) and then married in 1893 to Thomas Nelson Page;
         Rosewell Page (1858-1939) of "Oakland," Hanover County, lawyer
         in Richmond, writer, member of the General Assembly of
         Virginia, and second auditor of Virginia from 1912-1928; Ruth
         (Nelson) Page (1871-1975?), second wife of Rosewell Page; Anne
         (Page) Johns (b. 1899) of Richmond, daughter of Rosewell and
         Ruth (Nelson) Page; Frank Stoddert Johns (1884-1971), Anne
         (Page) Johns' husband; and Julien Harrison Hill (1877-1943),
         banker in Richmond and father-in-law of Ruth Nelson (Johns)
         Hill, daughter of Anne (Page) Johns and Frank Stoddert Johns;
         and Lucy Colder De Lancey (Kearny) Hill (b. 1881), wife of
         Julien Harrison Hill. Also included are scattered
         correspondence of the Bruce, Field, Johns, Lathrop, Nelson,
         and Points families, and Page cousins.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Series 1 of the collection begins with the papers of
         Francis Page (1780-1849), consisting of two receipts, one for
         the digging of a well (1819) and one for his subscription to
         the National Vaccine Institution (1825).</p>
      <p>Series 2 contains the papers of John Page (1821-1901) of
         "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., and consist of correspondence,
         1877-1898. Principal correspondents are his wife, Elizabeth
         Burwell (Nelson) Page, and his sons, Rosewell Page and Thomas
         Nelson Page. One of the few letters in the collection written
         by Rosewell as he practiced law in Danville, Va., is in this
         series. Letters by John Page to his son Thomas discuss family
         activity, political and business tasks that the father wants
         the son to handle in Richmond, Va., business and personal
         advice, and news of the crops at "Oakland."</p>
      <p>Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page (1821-1912) materials
         follow in Series 3. Page, of "Oakland," Hanover County, Va.,
         kept a diary, 1905, recording activities for each day. Entries
         describe the farm activities at "Oakland," the servants and
         their roles, local epidemics of smallpox, and the lives of her
         son, Rosewell Page, and his wife, Ruth (Nelson) Page, who
         lived at "Oakland," including frequent reference to Rosewell's
         role as a layman in the Episcopal Church, news of her other
         two sons, Francis (better known as Frank) Page, an Episcopal
         priest, and Thomas Nelson Page who occasionally visits
         "Oakland" and checks on his land holdings and mill operations
         in Hanover County, Va. Two pages of accounts are at the end of
         the diary and include references to servants' wages and farm
         expenses. Scattered accounts appear throughout the diary.</p>
      <p>Also present are letters of Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson)
         Page, chiefly written to her middle son, Thomas Nelson Page,
         from 1876 to 1912. Elizabeth wrote primarily from "Oakland,"
         Hanover County, Va., but also while visiting her sister,
         Virginia Lafayette (Nelson) Nelson, in Charlottesville. Her
         letters to Thomas are addressed to numerous locations around
         the United States, especially New York and York, Maine, and in
         Europe. In them, Elizabeth discusses her daily activities on
         the farm at "Oakland" and the activities of other family
         members such as her brother, William Nelson, who ran the
         farming operations at "Oakland." With the help of servants,
         she tended chickens, hogs, ducks, and turkeys, preserves food,
         and handled other household tasks. Some of Elizabeth's letters
         to Thomas include attached letters from other relatives to
         Elizabeth such as Frank Page, her oldest son.</p>
      <p>In addition to her correspondence with Thomas Nelson Page,
         Elizabeth's papers include letters from her school days at
         Long Branch written to her father, Thomas Nelson; letters from
         her son, Frank Page and his wife, Letitia Rives (Morris) Page,
         writing from Waco, Texas, where he served as an Episcopal
         priest in 1890 and in 1911 as a priest in Brooklyn, N. Y.; a
         1877 letter from her brother, Robert Nelson, while serving as
         a missionary in China; an 1865 letter from Anne Wickham, a
         niece of Elizabeth, concerning the Civil War and her feeling
         that Jefferson Davis had no role in the assassination of
         Abraham Lincoln; and several letters to Elizabeth in 1888
         expressing sympathy over the death of Anne Seddon (Bruce)
         Page, Thomas Nelson Page's first wife.</p>
      <p>Series 4 begins with the diary of Robert Nelson (1819-1886)
         kept initially while serving as an Episcopal missionary in
         Shanghai, China, in 1878, as an account book for a children's
         school; then kept in Woodbury, Conn., during the last years of
         his life and that of his wife, Rose (Points) Nelson, whose
         picture and obituary appear on p. 108 of the volume. Robert
         Nelson was a brother of Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page.</p>
      <p>Diary entries from 1885 to 1886 note Robert's
         church-related activities, including the number of baptisms,
         illnesses of church members, attendance at Episcopal
         conferences, and descriptions of his sermons. On page 90,
         Robert talks about his participation as a minister in Ulysses
         Simpson Grant's funeral, and on page 59, Robert laments the
         low nature of his annual salary of $600.00 in 1885. He gives
         much information about his family's daily life, travels,
         illnesses, and birthdays. His children's attendance at school
         and careers are also mentioned. A trip to Virginia, including
         to "Oakland," and Charlottesville, are discussed on pages
         109-111.</p>
      <p>Robert Nelson's correspondence, 1851-1886, was mostly
         written from or addressed to Shanghai, China, where Nelson
         served as a missionary. Included are interesting and detailed
         descriptions of Chinese customs, his family's activities, the
         burning of his chapel and people stealing all the chapel
         furnishings, baptism of Chinese people, and the children's
         school Nelson ran. One letter from Nelson to his sister,
         Virginia Lafayette (Nelson) Nelson of Charlottesville,
         concerns a female student whose family threatens to break her
         legs because she is a Christian.</p>
      <p>Robert Nelson's miscellaneous papers include a resolution,
         1881, by the Committee for the Shanghai Temperance Society. It
         honors Nelson for his service on the eve of his departure from
         China to live the remainder of his life in Connecticut.</p>
      <p>Series 5 contains the papers of Rose (Points) Nelson
         (1827-1885), including correspondence, undated-1870,
         containing a partial letter (n.d.) from Rose's daughter, Mary
         C. Nelson, while Mary was traveling by ship towards Yokohama,
         Japan; and a letter (1870) of Rose's to Mary C. Nelson giving
         general advice on life as Mary left their home in Shanghai,
         China, to go to the United States.</p>
      <p>Rose Nelson's papers also include parts of a diary written
         probably in 1865 while she was at "Oakland," Hanover County,
         Va. In the diary she discusses her children and family
         activities, the death of Mr. Lincoln, whom she compared to
         Herod, her glowing opinion of the slaves, and how people are
         avoiding taking the oath of allegiance; and a narrative, 1865,
         concerning the death of her son, William Nelson.</p>
      <p>Series 6 includes papers of Francis Page (1848-1918). His
         correspondence, 1877-1910, includes a 1903(?) letter to his
         brother, Rosewell Page, concerning the beginning of his
         ministry at St. John's Church, Brooklyn, N.Y., and letters to
         his other brother, Thomas Nelson Page, congratulating Tom and
         Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, Tom's first wife, on their first
         anniversary and congratulating Tom in 1893 on his second
         marriage to Florence (Lathrop) Field Page, telling Tom of his
         call to St. John's Church, asking Tom if he knows anything
         about the church, and discussing family news, including in
         1911 how Frank is coping with the loss of his first wife,
         Letitia Rives (Morris) Page (better known as Lettie).</p>
      <p>Francis Page's legal papers, 1961, include incomplete
         affidavits related to Frank Page and J. Packard Laird, Jr.,
         concerning property in Hanover County, Va. Frank's heirs are
         listed.</p>
      <p>Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) materials appear in Series
         7. Correspondence, 1861-1922 (1,305 items) is arranged in
         chronological order, with undated materials appearing first.
         Fans of Page's works wrote letters commenting on his writing
         and his lectures and asking for autographs, biographical
         sketches of Page, new articles to print in their magazines, or
         permission to reprint portions of his work. Friends wrote to
         arrange meetings and trips, and some wrote their condolences
         at the death of his first wife, Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, in
         1888. For charitable causes people ask Page to donate money or
         to autograph copies of his books. Notable correspondents
         include William Gillette, an actor and playwright, Joseph
         Forney Johnston, a governor of Alabama and a U.S. Senator,
         Herbert Putnam, Librarian of Congress from 1899-1939, and his
         second wife, Florence (Lathrop) Field Page.</p>
      <p>Most letters from 1861-1887 are written to Tom in Hanover
         County, Va., Richmond, or Charlottesville. From 1861-1877 most
         of the correspondence is business-related as Tom was a
         practicing lawyer in his early adult years, but there is
         scattered correspondence from family and friends, including
         his first wife, Annie. One business letter concerns Tom's
         efforts to buy a farm in Hanover County, Va. In the 1880s his
         correspondence becomes more numerous as he continues to reside
         in Hanover County and Richmond practicing law and beginning to
         receive fan letters for "Marse Chan," one of his early stories
         first appearing in 1884 in the Century Magazine and published
         in a collection in 1887. In 1886 Tom and Annie are married and
         some letters to Tom are written to him aboard ship headed for
         England where they spent their honeymoon. Also, in 1886,
         Rosewell Page, Tom's younger brother, writes to him about his
         law practice in Danville, Va. Thomas Nelson Carter, Tom's law
         partner in the firm of Page and Carter, Richmond, Va., writes
         Tom in 1887 while Tom is on a trip to Brussels. Carter
         congratulates him on his writing and discusses a Richmond
         group of writers called The Skaerl. Tom writes Carter from St.
         Paul, Minn., talking about his travel and investments. Over
         the years that Tom travels or lives away from Virginia, Carter
         helps to keep the law practice going in Richmond and helps Tom
         with his financial concerns. (After Tom marries the second
         time to Florence (Lathrop) Field Page, the partnership is
         dissolved and Tom devotes the rest of his life to writing,
         donating time and money to charitable causes, and serving as
         U.S. Ambassador to Italy during World War I.)</p>
      <p>Also, in 1887, most of the correspondence comes from fans
         wanting Tom to lecture in their towns, thanking him for
         assisting them in critiquing their writing, asking for help in
         getting their works published, wanting copies of his work,
         wanting articles written by Tom to publish in university
         publications, newspapers, and magazines, and asking for
         autographs. One publisher expresses his disappointment that
         Tom goes to another publisher. Unrelated to his writing there
         are occasional business letters, including a telegram in which
         a gentleman wants to invest in Page's iron works.</p>
      <p>Beginning in 1888, Tom and Annie write frequently while she
         spends time with her parents at "Staunton Hill," Charlotte
         County, Va., or while Tom travels frequently on speaking
         tours. Tom shares some news of his legal schedule, Richmond
         news, and how he misses her. On September 4, 1888, Tom writes
         "Law is dull. Indeed, I do not know what I should do without
         my Literary side-shows from time to time." While traveling in
         Georgia on August 2, 1888, Tom talks about his meeting and
         impressions of Joel Chandler Harris. On August 31, 1888, Tom
         writes Annie that he is trying to get Two Little Confederates
         ready to return to Charles Scribner. Fans continue to
         correspond with Tom praising In Ole Virginia in which appears
         "Marse Chan," and asking him to lecture in locations such as
         Charlottesville, Staunton, and Richmond, all in Va.,
         Louisville, Ky., Washington, D. C., Baltimore, Md., New York,
         N.Y., and Tennessee. Henry Woodfin Grady, a friend of Tom's,
         requests that Tom come to do readings in Atlanta, and Charles
         Scribner communicates with Tom about publishing his
         writings.</p>
      <p>Annie died in December 1888, and thus much of the extant
         correspondence for this year includes sympathy letters to Tom.
         Family and friends extend their sympathies at his loss, but
         also, complete strangers write from around the United
         States.</p>
      <p>From January through March, 1889, numerous people continue
         to send their sympathies from the United States and abroad.
         Richard Malcolm Johnston, a Georgia lawyer, author, and
         educator who idealized the South as Tom did, offers his
         condolences and talks about his readings on the lecture
         circuit with Mark Twain. In this January 23rd letter, Richard
         writes, "We had an excellent audience. I never saw Mark so
         fine. It was most generous in [sic] him to volunteer to come
         to my help." Tom was to have been Richard's lecture partner
         but Clemens filled in for Tom who canceled due to the death of
         Annie. James Burton Pond, in February and March, corresponds
         with Tom during this sad time. He served as a general agent
         and manager for numerous writers and musicians. In February,
         an artist from Washington, D.C., A. G. Keaton, is arranging
         the details for a portrait he is doing of Annie. (In July and
         August, F. R. Pustet and Co., New York, N.Y., converses with
         Tom about a stained glass window being made as a memorial for
         Annie.)</p>
      <p>By April, 1889, Tom began to receive more business-related
         correspondence. Johnston wrote more often, encouraging Tom to
         enter a new lecture arrangement with Pond. Hilgard Tyndale of
         Charles Scribner's Sons discussed the play he was writing
         based on "Marse Chan" (3/10/89 and 4/4/89). Several colleges
         invited him to visit. J. M. Stoddart with Lippincott's Monthly
         Magazine notified Tom on April 2nd that he would receive
         $400.00 for two articles he had written, while D. Lothrop
         Company of Boston wanted Tom to write a short serial. Molly
         Elliott Seawell, a fellow author, seemed to see Tom as a
         mentor and asked for advice on her writing.</p>
      <p>To help assuage Tom's sorrow, Rosewell and Tom traveled in
         Europe in July and August of 1889. Thomas Nelson Carter, Tom's
         law partner, kept them abreast of Richmond news and mentioned
         possible investments (7/24/89 and 8/19/89). Fans continued to
         write asking questions about his writings, requesting copies
         of his works, and asking for writing advice. In August, Sally
         Page (Nelson) Hughes, daughter of William Nelson of "Midway,"
         Mecklenburg County, Va., gave Tom her personal reminiscences
         of Michel Ney, also known as Peter Stuart Ney.</p>
      <p>Tom lived with Rosewell in Richmond during 1890-1891 except
         for when he has away on business, especially in Kentucky. He
         traveled briefly in England during this time also. Family
         letters include letters from Annie's mother, Sarah Alexander
         (Seddon) Bruce (5/7/91 and 11/4/91), Thomas Jefferson Page, a
         Southern expatriate living in Florence, Italy, (1/12/90 and
         2/26/90), his aunt, Anne Rose Page, who lived much of her life
         at "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., and his uncle, William
         Nelson, who was the manager of "Oakland," asking for financial
         assistance (3/18/91). (There is much correspondence between
         Tom and his mother, Elizabeth; it appears in Series 3.
         Likewise, correspondence with his father, John, appears in
         Series 2; there is much less of this
         correspondence.)Publishers continued to write Tom, including
         Warwick House, an English publisher writing about royalties;
         Ward, Lock, Boyden and Co., London, trying to defend their
         handling of the sales of In Ole Virginia; and The Christian
         Union, New York, concerning revising a paper Tom has written.
         Much of the correspondence in these years, however, came from
         fans and friends who praised Tom and his works asking again
         for biographical sketches of him, thanking him for speaking to
         their group, encouraging Tom to write a history of the South,
         wanting autographs, and inviting him to visit their homes
         while he is on the lecture circuit. Almost all of Tom's fan
         mail is positive except for two negative letters (one dated
         10/31/91) from a fundamentalist concerning how Tom rendered a
         verse from the Bible. William G. Eggleston of The Chicago
         Herald wanted help with using black dialect (5/31/90). A few
         letters illustrate Tom's philanthropic nature, as in November
         1890, someone wrote to ask him to become a member of the Maury
         Memorial Commission. He raised money for the Richmond Public
         Library; Joseph Reid Anderson sent Tom a contribution for the
         library on March 2, 1891.</p>
      <p>A baroness in France and Tom began corresponding in 1891.
         There are six letters starting on March 11 concerning
         Alexandre Marie Quesnay de Beaurepaire, who wanted to
         establish an academy of arts and sciences in Richmond after
         the American Revolution. Baroness Yetta Blaze de Bury asked
         for Tom's assistance in finding more information about Quesnay
         de Beaurepaire. She also commented on another of Tom's works,
         On Newfound River.</p>
      <p>In 1892 Tom continued to live in Richmond, Va., as a
         bachelor in-between frequent travels for speaking engagements.
         Friends invited Tom to visit with them when he spoke in places
         such as New York, Alabama, and Texas, while fans wrote to ask
         him to speak at schools in Louisville, Ky., Winchester, Ky.,
         and Roanoke, Va. or to speak at clubs like the Southern Club
         of Harvard, to provide complimentary passes at clubs like the
         Union League Club of Chicago when he visited in that city, to
         help them with their writing aspirations, and to praise On
         Newfound River and The Old South.</p>
      <p>Tom's life changed when he married Florence (Lathrop) Field
         Page on June 6, 1893. After that time, his visits Washington,
         D.C., New York City, and York Harbor, Maine, but throughout
         his marriage Florence and Tom traveled every year overseas.
         Frequent letters from Rosewell kept Tom abreast of matters at
         "Oakland," including comments on how Tom's works were in
         demand in Richmond bookstores, news of neighbors and friends,
         and family activity such as their mother's giving Christmas
         presents to white and black workers at "Oakland" or their
         father's discussion about where he was on Christmas Eve during
         each year of the Civil War (12/24/94). Rosewell discussed
         investments, selling family land in Hanover County, Va., Tom's
         tenant, Edmund T. Taylor, at "Mont Air," Hanover County, Va.,
         the status of crops, horses, and livestock, and Tom's opinion
         of Uncle Tom's Cabin as discussed in The Atlanta Evening News
         (1/16/01). Edmund T. Taylor, Tom's tenant farmer in Bandana,
         Va., wrote Tom in August and September of 1901 about the corn,
         potato, and wheat crop and the livestock, sent a drawing of a
         barn that he wanted Tom to approve, and discussed rebuilding
         bridges in Hanover County, Va., washed out by high water.
         Tom's letters to his family in Virginia are rarely found in
         Mss1P1465aFA2 but his letter of May 17, 1893 to Rosewell was
         written prior to going on his honeymoon aboard a steamer to
         London. Tom enclosed a check to provide for contingencies at
         "Oakland" and urged Rosewell, if necessary, to contact Thomas
         Nelson Carter, Tom's power-of-attorney and law partner, for
         stocks to be sold to provide emergency monies for the
         homestead.</p>
      <p>Business letters came from a lawyer in Charlottesville,
         Va., concerning land Tom wished to buy (7/28/93), Ward, Lock
         and Bowden, a publisher in London, with an attached agreement
         concerning publishing of Tom's works in England (7/14/94),
         Charles Scribner discussing publishing schedules, royalties,
         and a contract for Polly (10/31/94 and 2/11/95) actually
         published earlier in In Ole Virginia in 1887, J. Cabell
         Brockenbrough concerning translating Tom's work into French
         (8/23/95), Sol Smith Russell concerning critiquing Tom's plays
         (7/17/96), and Elizabeth Marbury of New York who was trying to
         submit Red Rock to playwrights and managers but is not having
         any luck (1/29/01). Tom received correspondence from the
         various clubs he was a member of in Washington, D.C., such as
         the Chevy Chase Club (9/13/00). Over the years he served as an
         officer in these clubs and helped with renovations and
         fund-raising. John Stewart Bryan, writing for his father
         Joseph Bryan who was ill, wrote several letters in 1900
         concerning stock in the Lake Superior Co. Occasionally Tom
         received mundane letters about his Washington, D.C., home at
         No. 1759 R Street. Some refer to repairs needed on his
         property. In October 1900, his insurance agent sent a list
         with evaluations of the contents of this home. Like most folks
         with ample financial means, Tom frequently received
         fund-raising letters. For example, a feeder school to the
         University of Virginia located at Morrisville, Va., requested
         money in December 1902.</p>
      <p>Friends and fans continued to write with high praises for
         one of Tom's latest works, Red Rock, wanting to know if his
         fiction was based on actual events, or writing to share
         similar stories of black slaves. Ellen Shields of Natchez,
         Miss., inspired by Tom's viewpoint, discussed a sketch of a
         black carpenter who worked for her father on their plantations
         and who liked to preach (7/2/00). The editor of The
         Philadelphia Item asked Tom's opinion about British and
         American reviewers (8/18/00).</p>
      <p>Distant family members and sometimes unrelated folks wrote
         Tom for political influence and financial assistance. B. M.
         Fontaine did not want to become further indebted to Tom, and
         Joseph Reid Anderson Bruce, a nephew by marriage, wanted some
         help in getting a job (9/17/00). In June 1900, A. L. Nelson
         wished Tom could help finance a distant relative's education
         at the University of Virginia. A cousin in Naples, Florida,
         requested Tom's aid in getting someone into the U.S. Naval
         Academy (2/12/03), while Frank Nelson, Jr., thanked Tom for
         money loaned to him at Virginia Polytechnic Institute.</p>
      <p>From 1904-1908, Tom's correspondence again was an even mix
         of fan letters and business letters. Fund-raising letters
         abound with several requests for complete sets of his printed
         works to be donated to various libraries in Virginia, for
         money to renovate an Episcopal church, or for money to pay for
         medical treatment of indigent persons. Marie von Unschuld at
         the University of Music and Dramatic Art in D.C. wrote for
         Tom's financial assistance in establishing scholarships for
         her students (7/18/04). Tom received mail from agricultural
         researchers about alfalfa experiments and inoculating
         leguminous plants and from the U.S. Department of Agriculture
         concerning the building of a road near Beaverdam in Hanover
         County, Va.</p>
      <p>Letters from friends and family are scattered through
         1904-1908; most family letters are from Rosewell, especially
         in 1905, sharing news from the mill and news of the corn,
         wheat, millet, and pea crops, cutting of timber, installing of
         a phone line, selling of lambs and wool, building of a dam on
         one of the Hanover County properties, and changes in tenants.
         Rosewell sent a six-month statement concerning all farm costs
         and asked Tom to pay various debts. Other family letters to
         Tom discuss his financing of schooling for Rosewell's
         daughter, Anne, and for a distant relative, Randolph Rosewell
         Page, at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. A cousin from Clifton
         Forge, Va., Lizzie R. Taylor, asked Tom for money to build a
         rectory. Strangers as well as friends wanted Tom to help them
         get jobs such as J. L. Hall, a professor at William and Mary
         College, who wanted a job at the University of North Carolina
         (7/7/04), or a law professor at Wake Forest College wanting
         Tom to go to the White House and ask the President to appoint
         him to a district court judgeship (12/16/08). Several letters
         in 1904 indicate that Tom was trying to influence the Library
         of Congress to hire Alexander Welbourne Weddell.</p>
      <p>Notable letters to Tom in this time period came from Samuel
         Langhorne Clemens, thanking Florence and Tom for their
         kindness to his wife, who died in June 1904; from Thomas
         Nelson Carter about a land auction; and Teddy Roosevelt, who
         Carter would not vote for "on account of his putting forward
         the Negroes in the platform..." (6/24/04); from John Singleton
         Mosby concerning the Gettysburg campaign (10/26/08); from
         Ernest Thompson Seton, an animal painter, lecturer, and
         adventurer (12/8/08); and from Victor Howard Metcalf, lawyer
         and Secretary of the Navy, thanking Tom for a copy of his work
         on Robert E. Lee.</p>
      <p>The last box of Thomas Nelson Page correspondence dates
         from 1909 to 1922. The usual pattern of letters prevails here
         but noteworthy letters follow. Leonard Gunnell, a cousin by
         marriage, worked at the Smithsonian Institution and sent Tom a
         picture of the old home at Oakland (1/09). (Oakland burned in
         1899 and was rebuilt in six months.) Also, in January 1909,
         Tom received letters about horses he can buy in Vermont and
         Virginia. Cyrus Hall McCormick, son of the inventor, sends Tom
         a book about the Southern black; "...I send it herewith,
         knowing that you, who understand so thoroly [sic] the old-time
         life of the Southern negro...(2/3/09)." From Lexington, Ky.,
         Foxhall A. Daingerfield writes Tom his impressions of Robert
         E. Lee, who he knew personally during the Civil War (2/8/09).
         In September 1909, Charles Scribner's Sons enclosed a contract
         for publication of John Marvel, Assistant.</p>
      <p>In 1912 there were many letters from Ruth (Nelson) Page to
         Tom. It appears Ruth was helping Rosewell with the management
         of Oakland and other properties owned or subsidized by Tom.
         Rosewell campaigned and won the election to become the second
         auditor of Virginia. He served in that post until 1928; thus,
         much of his time was spent in Richmond. Ruth's letters
         describe family and farm news, especially the health and death
         of her mother-in-law, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page.
         Rosewell still wrote Tom on a few occasions, but the remainder
         of the 1912 letters are sympathy letters from strangers,
         friends, and family concerning Elizabeth's death. A few
         thank-you notes from distant cousins discuss Tom's kindness in
         paying their school tuition.</p>
      <p>From 1913 to 1917 there are only twenty items, mainly
         letters from Ruth and Rosewell. Ruth praised Tom upon becoming
         the U.S. Ambassador to Italy. Ruth and Rosewell's daughter,
         Anne (Page) Johns, wrote her uncle from Stuart Hall School,
         Staunton, Va.; Tom financed this niece's education. For a
         number of years, there was a school run at "Oakland," and Ruth
         mentioned "our academy" in her February 20, 1916 letter. Also,
         in 1916, Jonathan Daniels, Secretary of the Navy, wrote Tom
         about the Federal Reserve Act (5/12/16). Walter Hines Page, a
         cousin and an editor at Doubleday, Page and Co., Long Island,
         N.Y., informed Tom of changes in their personnel, resulting in
         delays dealing with his book (unidentified) (1/19/13). From
         1918 until Tom's death in 1922, correspondence is slim,
         numbering thirty-two items. The effects of World War I are
         quite evident in letters to Tom in 1918. H. Rozier Dulany, a
         real estate agent in Washington, D.C., wrote Tom about a
         tenant's rent, travels to Tom's farms in Virginia, selling
         Tom's cattle, and the "scarcity of farm labor in Virginia"
         (1/1/18). Several of Ruth's letters discussed the effects of
         the war, especially her letter of June 23, 1918. Her April
         1918 letters dwell on the death of Frank Page, Tom's older
         brother. In September, Ruth explained her move to Richmond
         where her daughter Anne is working for the war effort,
         postponing her education until after the war. In October, Ruth
         discussed the Spanish flu epidemic in Richmond, and in
         November, Ruth described the impact on Richmond of returning
         soldiers. Anne wrote her uncle on October 20 explaining the
         nature of her war job at the bag-loading plant, mentioning
         measuring black powder for ammunition. Rosewell wrote Tom in
         Italy in February 1919, "You have filled one of the most
         difficult posts in the world with dignity and honor...." In
         one of Tom's last letters, he wrote to "Lil Gals," probably
         his step-daughters, mentioning he had to borrow money to carry
         on at York Harbor, Maine (9/18/21).</p>
      <p>Thomas Nelson Page materials also include financial records
         consisting of receipts or bills for office supplies, crops
         such as oats and hay, farm equipment, lumber, hardware,
         freight charges from Europe, but mainly, royalty payments from
         Charles Scribner's Sons.</p>
      <p>Among Page's miscellaneous materials are three
         certificates, 1874-1877, from the University of Virginia for
         Tom's having passed courses in law, and there is a commission
         for Page having attained the rank of 1st Lieutenant of the
         Richmond Light Infantry Blues.</p>
      <p>Scattered papers refer to cases Tom handled when he
         practiced law in Richmond, Va. Other notable papers give
         Rosewell the power-of-attorney (1913) for Tom and include a
         copy of Tom's will (1922).</p>
      <p>Among the last items in this series are newspaper articles
         about Tom, including a description of his funeral service in
         1922. Also present are pictures, 1919-1921, including one that
         is undated but identified a dress that belonged to Elizabeth
         (Burwell) Nelson. The caption on this picture says the dress
         was kept at "Oakland" and, thus, was lost when the house
         burned in 1899. Photographs taken in 1919 document Italian
         troops guarding the American Embassy and concern Italian
         Premier Vittorio Orlando's return from the Paris peace
         conference. Another photograph shows Tom and Rosewell in
         Denver, Colo. Finishing the series are two undated addresses
         concerning the history of the settlement of Jamestown and the
         commemoration of the Virginia Convention of 1776. A speech,
         probably written by Tom, dated 1906, was given in Lisbon for
         the American Legation, and concerns the medical profession.
         Miscellaneous papers include the wedding announcement (1886)
         for Tom's first marriage to Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, a sonnet
         (undated) to Amelie Louise (Rives) Chandler Troubetzkoy
         written on reading her "Grief and Faith", recent news (1919)
         about Yugoslavia as reported in the Italian press, an essay
         (undated) about Page and "Marse Chan," an invitation list
         (undated) for a dinner, probably given in honor of Jonathan
         Daniels at the American Embassy in Italy, and notes (undated)
         about On Newfound River, written in memory of Annie.</p>
      <p>Series Eight contains the papers of Anne Seddon (Bruce)
         Page (1867-1888), known as "Annie," Thomas Nelson Page's first
         wife. Her correspondence is mainly from family and friends,
         including her parents, brothers, and sisters, who share family
         happenings and alwayed praise Tom and his writing. William
         Cabell Bruce, a brother, described his life as a lawyer in
         Baltimore, Md., in November 1882, while Charles Bruce, her
         father, wrote about his daily routine at "Staunton Hill,
         Charlotte County, Va., in March 1887. From 1885 to 1888, James
         Douglas Bruce, another of her brothers, wrote Annie while he
         lived abroad in Germany and France. Family included Thomas
         Nelson Carter, who was a cousin of Annie's and the law partner
         of her husband, and Tom's aunt, Anne Rose Page. In December
         1886, she wrote Annie a story about a black child brought up
         by a white woman in Goochland County, Va. He murdered the
         woman when he turned eighteen because she would not buy him a
         certain pair of shoes. Anne Rose also commented on Tom's
         writings. Friends such as Lelia Augusta (Myers) Morgan wrote
         in August 1886, about the earthquake in Richmond, Va., while
         Annie and Tom are on their European honeymoon. In February
         1887, an unidentified correspondent wrote from England
         mentioning a dinner she attended where several artists were
         present including James Abbott McNeill Whistler.</p>
      <p>Series Nine includes correspondence exists between Florence
         (Lathrop) Field Page (1858-1921), Thomas Nelson Page's second
         wife, and Rosewell Page, Ruth (Nelson) Page, Anne (Page)
         Johns, all relatives of Tom, and Florence's grandson by her
         daughter Minna (Field) Gibson Burnaby, Henry Field (originally
         named Henry Gibson). Henry wrote from England and described
         the Christmas activities around him in 1908. A few letters to
         Florence relate to financial transactions or obtaining a tutor
         for one of Flo's daughters. Also included are accounts,
         1897-1900, in part pertaining to paying a tutor and to a
         purchase at a home furnishings store in Washington, D.C.</p>
      <p>Series 10 begins with the correspondence, 1888-1938, of
         Rosewell Page (1858-1939). Half of Rosewell's correspondence
         comes from family or friends and half from business
         acquaintances. Aunt Anne Rose Page, along with Rosewell's
         mother, write him about the death in 1893 of Frank's baby,
         Rose, and affairs at Oakland. Ruth, his wife, gives him news
         of their children and Rosewell's parents and requests various
         things for Rosewell to bring from Richmond. Elizabeth Hope
         Stewart of "Brook Hill" sends him congratulations for his
         marriage to Ruth in 1898. Other folks compliment him on
         becoming a member of the Virginia House of Delegates and
         express sympathy in the loss of Tom's two wives. While Anne
         (Page) Johns attends Stuart Hall School, Staunton, Va.,
         Rosewell writes his daughter about family news.</p>
      <p>As a member of the law firm of Rutherfoord and Page,
         Richmond, Va., Rosewell received legal letters related to
         cases he handled, but much of his business correspondence
         related to either his biography of his brother Tom or Tom's
         publications. From 1922-1937, Charles Scribner's Sons
         corresponded with Rosewell about publishing his biography of
         Tom, royalty payments for at least 28 of Tom's publications,
         renewing copyright on one of Tom's stories, asking Rosewell's
         permission to publish a new edition of Two Little
         Confederates, arranging a special educational edition of Red
         Rock, and concerning movie rights for Tom's works. In 1934,
         Lola D. Moore, a representative for authors and artists in
         Hollywood and Beverly Hills, Calif., corresponded with
         Rosewell wanting to market Red Rock in the movie industry.
         Another agent, Grace Morse of New York, also wrote Rosewell
         about trying to sell movie rights. Other business letters
         refer to "Oakland" and the surrounding area in Hanover County,
         Va., including building of a bridge across the South Anna
         River and placement of telephone lines through Page
         property.</p>
      <p>The remainder of the series includes accounts, 1897-1927,
         including five notes (1905) on the school account for Hall's
         Free School run by Miss Orr and, probably, sponsored by the
         Page family; notes on logging expenses (no date); accounts
         between Tom and Rosewell concerning farm expenses in
         1907-1908; and a royalty report for Tom's publication for
         1927. Also included are undated manuscripts, including a draft
         of Rosewell's Hanover County: Its History and Legends and
         Thomas Nelson Page: A Memoir of a Virginia Gentleman. A draft
         of a speech about Jamestown filed in Series 7.7 possibly was
         by Rosewell also. Lastly, miscellaneous materials, 1868-1916,
         include an undated newspaper picture of Rosewell, his wife and
         daughter, and others attending a memorial observance of Edgar
         Allan Poe's birthday, and a biographical sketch and picture of
         Rosewell.</p>
      <p>Ruth (Nelson) Page's papers make up Series 11. Most of
         Ruth's correspondence is found in earlier series of her
         mother-in-law, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page, her
         brother-in-law, Thomas Nelson Page, and her husband, Rosewell
         Page. Other family letters found here include those from Minna
         (Field) Gibson Burnaby, Thomas Nelson Page's step-daughter,
         about a visit to "Rock Ledge," York Harbor, Maine, and of
         Ruth's son, Robert Nelson Page. One letter by this son was
         written in August 1921, from "Rock Ledge." In October 1918,
         Mary C. Nelson, Ruth's sister who served as a Red Cross nurse
         during World War I, wrote from Paris. John Cook Wyllie,
         Director of Libraries at the University of Virginia, addressed
         Ruth in July 1967, discussing the acquisition of Thomas Nelson
         Page papers.</p>
      <p>Series 12 contains materials of Anne Page. In 1914, Anne
         Page, daughter of Rosewell and Ruth Page, attended Stuart Hall
         School in Staunton, Va., and she wrote her brother, Robert
         Nelson Page. During World War I, Anne was back in the Richmond
         area working for the war effort at DuPont Engineering Co.;
         this company sent congratulations to its workers, including
         Anne, on November 14, 1918. Anne wrote Karl E. Johnson at the
         Red Cross headquarters in Petersburg, also in 1918, asking if
         she and the Hall's Free School, probably run under the
         auspices of the Page family at "Oakland," could open a canteen
         on the Richmond-Washington Highway to serve soldiers. (Then,
         during World War II, Anne received a letter from Richmond
         Filter Center thanking its workers for their help in wartime.)
         From 1929-1941, Anne received letters from the national Junior
         League Magazine concerning articles that she wrote for this
         publication. William B. Thalhimer, Jr., wrote in April 1951,
         about wanting to honor her as one of Richmond's noted authors.
         From 1967-1969, Anne received letters from various persons
         associated with the University of Virginia concerning the sale
         of Thomas Nelson Page manuscripts to the college.</p>
      <p>Anne (Page) Johns's materials also include an annual report
         for 1930-1931, an undated constitution, copies of The Leaguer
         from May 1929-June 1931, and drafts of historical articles on
         the Junior League of Richmond; and war ration books from World
         War II.</p>
      <p>One of two letters to Frank Stoddert Johns (1884-1971),
         husband of Anne (Page) Johns, arrived in April 1953, from an
         assistant to the Ambassador of Italy, thanking Dr. Johns for
         his courtesies when the assistant visited Virginia at the
         centennial celebration of the birth of Thomas Nelson Page.
         Other Frank Johns materials include a war ration book from
         World War II, an undated news article concerning the receipt
         of a portrait of Dr. Johns at Hampden-Sydney College, and a
         1950 article about the college naming an auditorium for him.
         Johns had served as chairman of the Board of Trustees since
         1938.</p>
      <p>Section 14 concerns Julien Harrison Hill (1877-1943),
         father-in-law of Ruth Nelson (Johns) Hill, daughter of Anne
         (Page) Johns and Frank Stoddert Johns. Four scrapbooks trace
         Hill's life, beginning as a student in Petersburg, and
         following him throughout his career. The first volume, dated
         1896-1942, includes a catalogue for the 1895-1896 session of
         the University School in Richmond, Va., the school first
         started in Petersburg, Va., by William Gordon McCabe. Hill is
         listed as a student. Hill participated in sports activities at
         the University School, as well as in college at the University
         of Virginia, which he entered in 1897. The baseball team
         schedule for 1898 includes a picture of the team. After Hill's
         college years, he continued to enjoy sports as noted in this
         scrapbook. One article dated April 11, 1942, concerns Hill's
         son, William M. Hill, captain of the University of Virginia
         football team.</p>
      <p>The second volume of Hill's scrapbooks, dated 1904-1943,
         focuses on Hill's adult civic and social activities such as
         his membership in the Commonwealth Club and the Richmond
         German, efforts to get more playgrounds across Virginia,
         service as a member of the Civilian Examining Committee for
         the U.S. War Department in 1918 and a member of the Board of
         Managers of the Richmond Male Orphan Society in 1919. In the
         nineteen twenties he served on the Medical College of Virginia
         Board of Visitors, and in 1936, he was a director of the
         Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Co. On December 17, 1940,
         Lady Nancy Witcher (Langhorne) Shaw Astor wrote Hill after he
         sent a group contribution to relieve the Air Raid distress.
         Personal asides include information about the death of his
         mother, Frances Cadwallader (Harrison) Hill, in 1916, and the
         death of his father, William Maury Hill, in 1918, about the
         wedding of his daughter, Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson, in
         1940, and about the death of Hill, himself, in 1943.</p>
      <p>In the scrapbook for 1904-1943 Hill documented the progress
         of his adult career. In his young adult years, he served as
         assistant cashier at the National State Bank in Richmond and
         then, in 1915, he became a director of the National State and
         City Bank, later known as the State-Planters Bank and Trust
         Company. In 1917 he was still cashier but was elected to be a
         vice-president, and in 1920, he became president of the bank.
         A 1920 article by Hill appeared in the Journal of Accountancy.
         Hill became president of Old Dominion Trust Co. in 1922. Other
         news articles highlight his membership in professional groups
         such as the American Bankers Association, his service on the
         Advisory Committee of the Richmond Loan Agency of the
         Reconstruction Finance Corporation in 1932, and his
         appointment by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to his Advisory
         Committee on Works Allotment in 1935. Enclosures are dated
         1939 and concern Hill's wife, Lucy, and the birth of their
         seventh child, Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson. There are
         photographs and negatives of Diana and other siblings.</p>
      <p>The last volume of the scrapbooks, dated 1914-1917,
         concerns Hill's appointment and service as the chief of staff
         of the Governor of Virginia, Henry Carter Stuart. The letter
         from Stuart offering the position to Hill is in the scrapbook
         as well as articles about Stuart. Also included are other
         newspaper articles about Hill's professional and civic
         activities.</p>
      <p>Among Hill's miscellany are the certificate signed by
         Governor Stuart, making Hill his chief of staff, along with a
         memorial editorial of December 2, 1943, celebrating the life
         of Hill.</p>
      <p>Lucy Colder De Lancey (Kearny) Hill materials include
         letters congratulating Lucy, wife of Julien Harrison Hill, on
         the birth of Diana Kearny (Hill) Patterson.</p>
      <p>Series Sixteen includes correspondence of extended family
         members in the Bruce, Field, Johns, Lathrop, Nelson, Points,
         and Page families. Notable letters include an undated Civil
         War letter from a hospital at Warm Springs, Va. from a
         preacher who writes about how hard it is to console the sick
         soldiers and a January 3, 1864 letter from Stevenson Points to
         Lizzie Stevenson when he was a prisoner at Fort Delaware, Del.
         At the death of Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page in December 1888,
         members of the Bruce family receive sympathy letters. In
         January 1891, George Washington Points corresponded with Mary
         C. Nelson about the genealogy of the Points (also known as
         Poyntz) family. Bryan Lathrop, brother of Florence (Lathrop)
         Field Page, admonished Minna (Field) Gibson Burnaby about the
         status of her finances in 1912. Mary C. Nelson, sister of Ruth
         (Nelson) Page and Red Cross nurse during World War I, wrote an
         interesting letter in November 1918, about the ending of the
         war and the reactions in Paris. A last notable letter
         (undated) was written from Scotland to Miss Bessie (otherwise
         unidentified) and is from Johannes Wolf, a musicologist
         specializing in medieval music.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Collection is arranged in sixteen sections by main entry
         and further subdivided by subject or record type where
         necessary.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>Authors, American -- Virginia --
         History.</subject>
      <subject>China -- Social life and customs -- 1644-
         1912.</subject>
      <subject>Diaries -- China -- Shanghai -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Diaries -- Connecticut -- Woodbury -- History --
         19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Diaries -- Virginia -- Hanover County -- History
         -- 20th century.</subject>
      <subject>Education -- China -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Episcopal Church -- Connecticut -- Clergy --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Episcopal Church -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
      <subject>Family -- Virginia -- Social life and
         customs.</subject>
      <subject>Farm management -- Virginia -- History..</subject>
      <subject>Hanover County (Va.) - - Social life and
         customs.</subject>
      <subject>Laity -- Eipscopal Church -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Missionaries -- China -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Mothers and sons -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
      <subject>Nelson, Robert, 1819-1886.</subject>
      <subject>Oakland (Hanover County, Va.)</subject>
      <subject>Page, Elizabeth Burwell Nelson,
         1821-1912.</subject>
      <subject>Page family.</subject>
      <subject>Page, Rosewell, 1858-1939.</subject>
      <subject>Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Social life and customs.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Virginia -- Family
         relationships.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Virginia -- Social life and
         customs.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Francis Page (1780-1849)
               loose accounts</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Francis Page (1780-1849)
               loose accounts</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">John Page (1821-1901)
               correspondence</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson)
               Page (1821-1912) papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 3.1">Diary</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 3.2">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2-3</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Robert Nelson (1819-1886)
               papers</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Rose (Points) Nelson
               (1827-1885) papers</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">4 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Francis Page (1849-1918)
               papers</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="Box">4
               (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Thomas Nelson Page
               (1853-1922) papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 7.1">Correspondence
                  (undated, 1861-1887)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5-11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.2">Accounts</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.3">
                  Certificates</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.4">Legal
                  papers</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.5">Newspaper
                  articles</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.6">Pictures</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.7">Speeches</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.8">Miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page
               (1867-1888) correspondence</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Florence (Lathrop) Field
               Page (1858-1921) papers</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 9.1">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">13
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 9.2">Accounts</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">13
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Rosewell Page (1858-1939)
               papers</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.1">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">13
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.2">Accounts</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.3">
                  Manuscripts</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">14
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.4">Miscellany</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">Ruth (Nelson) Page
               (1871-1975?) correspondence</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">14 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">Anne (Page) Johns (b. 1899)
               papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.1">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.2">Junior League
                  papers</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.3">Miscellany</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 13">Frank Stoddert Johns
               (1884-1971) papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 13.1">
                  Correspondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 13.2">Miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 14">Julien Harrison Hill
               (1877-1943) papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 14.1">
                  Corresopondence</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">16
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 14.2">Scrapbook</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">16
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 14.3">Scrapbook</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 14.4">Scrapbook</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 15">Lucy Colder De Lancey
               (Kearny) Hill (b. 1881) portions of
               scrapbook</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">18 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 16">Miscellaneous
               correspondence</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">18 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
