<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="vihi00023">
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="completed" scriptencoding="iso15924"
    dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virgnia Historical Society//TEXT
      (US::ViH:: vih00023::Alexander Wilbourne Weddell papers, 1888-1947)//EN"
      "vih00023.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Alexander Wilbourne Weddell papers, <date era="ce"
            calendar="gregorian">1888-1947</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Weddell, Alexander Wilbourne papers <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1
            W4126 b FA2 </num></subtitle>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2020 (<emph><extref
              xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/" xlink:type="simple"
              >CC0 1.0</extref></emph>)</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
            xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of Use
          </extref>
        </p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using a form and manually entry <date era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">2020-08-17</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in <language langcode="eng">English </language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>Alexander Wilbourne Weddell papers, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian"
          >1888-1947</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>Virginia Historical Society<num type="Collection Number"> Mss1
          W4126 b FA2 </num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
          xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed"
          xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2020</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by: </label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary </head>
      <repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">Virginia Historical Society, Richmond,
        Va.</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Alexander Wilbourne Weddell papers, <unitdate era="ce"
          calendar="gregorian">1888-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection Number">Mss1 W4126 b FA2 </unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">
        <extent>6 linear feet (ca. 800 items)</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">Materials in this collection are in
          <language>English</language>. </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Mainly materials related to Weddell’s career as a diplomat and
        ambassador of the United States in Argentina and Spain. The papers include
        diaries/calendars, correspondence, financial records, scrapbooks, diplomatic files,
        organizational records, speeches, Virginia House, publications, miscellaneous, and Virginia
        Chase Steedman Weddell papers. The bulk of papers are correspondence which starts in 1883,
        but is especially heavy after 1927. The correspondence is both personal and professional and
        concern his diplomatic career and missions along with civic and philanthropic organizations.
        There is also documentation of the construction and maintenance of the Weddell’s Richmond
        home, Virginia House. </abstract>
      <origination label="Creator">Weddell, Alexander Wilbourne, 1876-1948</origination>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information</head>
      <accessrestrict id="ref2">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>The collection is open for research use.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <acqinfo id="ref4">
        <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head>
        <p>Gift of the estate of Alexander Wilbourne Weddell in 1948. Accessioned 13 April 1985.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Alexander Wilbourne Weddell Papers, 1858-1955, (Mss1 W4126 b FA2), Virginia Historical
          Society, Richmond, Va. </p>
      </prefercite>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
      <p> Born in Richmond, Virginia, on April 6, 1876, Alexander Wilbourne Weddell was the son of
        Episcopal minister Alexander Watson Weddell and his wife, Penelope Margaret Wright. With the
        early death of his father and a large family of six siblings, Alex Weddell struggled to
        secure a rudimentary education and find a profession. A chance meeting while working as a
        clerk at the U. S. Copyright Office led to his first diplomatic post as secretary to the
        minister of Denmark. Stationed in Zanzibar, Catania, Athens, Beirut, Calcutta, and Mexico
        City, Weddell moved slowly up the foreign service professional ladder. His career in foreign
        service as a consul or ambassador would last for almost forty years, culminating in
        ambassadorships in Argentina and Spain. Virginia Atkinson Chase Steedman was born in
        Missouri in 1874 to Edwin E. Chase and Virginia Atkinson Chase. She was educated at Miss
        Brown's School for Girls in New York City. In 1900 She married James Harrison Steedman from
        a wealthy family, but he unfortunately he died in 1921 after serving in World War I.
        Steedman, was a wealthy widow from St. Louis, Missouri when she and Weddell were introduced
        by mutual friends in Calcutta during a around-the-world trip in 1922. Mr. Weddell
        accompanied Steedman and her companions back to the United States by cruise ship. The
        courtship on the ship resulted in the couple marrying four months later in New York. Virgina
        Weddell was an integral part of Alexander Weddell's success in the foreign service. Weddell
        retired, due to health, from foreign service in 1942. The Weddell's returned to Richmond and
        their historically rebuilt English priory home, Virginia House. The couple and their maid
        tragically died a train collision accident in rural Missouri on January 1, 1948. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content</head>
      <p>Papers concerning Alexander W. Weddell’s diplomatic and consular service. Papers were
        organized by Weddell for publication of a memoir of his life and career. Papers include
        correspondence with family, friends, foreign service officers, and politicians and
        miscellany from the various posts of service. Researchers should consult the other Weddell
        collections in conduction with research in this collection. Note that some subjects and
        correspondents may appear several locations, so this description and the guide which follows
        should be examined thoroughly.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The papers of Ambassador Weddell and his wife thoroughly cover their lives in the
        diplomatic community and as active civic-minded Richmonders. In the paragraphs which follow,
        attention is drawn to their various activities by describing important record groups within
        the collection and explaining the methods of processing these materials. An attempt has been
        made to maintain the ambassador’s own arrangement of his personal records, as nearly as
        possible, which occasionally means that papers covering a single subject, event, or
        organization may be filled in several locations. Such occurrences are cross-referenced
        fully. Also, since the Weddell’s were both interested in many of the same projects and
        organizations, some materials of Mrs. Weddell and those addressed to both are filed with Mr.
        Weddell’s records. Researchers should read this entire description and guide before actually
        examining the collection. </p>
      <p>The collection has 4 series: Series 1. Weddell family papers 1858-1925; Series 1.1. James
        Weddell, 1865; Series 1.2. Alexander Watson Weddell; Series 1.3. Penelope Margaret Wright
        Weddell, 1895-1925; Series 2. Alexander and Virginia Weddell papers, 1907-1948; Series 2.1.
        Diaries/Calendars,1907-1947; Series 2.2. Correspondence, 1883-1947 (arranged alphabetically
        by year); Series 2.3. Correspondence, 1923-1946, with Virginia (Chase) Steedman Weddell;
        Series 2.4. Financial Records, 1897-1947; Series 2.5. Miscellaneous, 1899-1946; Series 2.6.
        Diplomatic Service files, 1908-1942 (arranged chronological by post); Series 2.7.
        Organization and Association files, 1923-1948, (arranged alphabetically by organization);
        Series 2.8. Speeches, Addresses, and publications,1930-1947,(speeches, and publications
        [arranged alphabetically]); Series 2.9. Virginia House; Series 2.10. Miscellaneous; Series
        3. Virginia (Chase) Steedman Weddell papers, Series 3.1. Diaries, Series 3.2.
        Correspondence, Series 3.3. Financial and Philanthropy, Series 3.4. James Harrison Steedman;
        Series 3.5. Miscellaneous; Series 4. Family Miscellaneous. </p>
      <p>Series 1. concerns Alexander W. Weddell’s grandfather, James Weddell (1807-1865); father,
        Alexander Watson Weddell (1841-1883); and his mother, Penelope Margaret Wright Weddell
        (1840-1901). The collection beings with a few items from the estate of Weddell’s
        grandfather, James Weddell of Petersburg. Then follow materials of or concerning his father,
        Rev. Alexander Watson Weddell. Most of these papers relate to pastorates in Harrisonburg and
        Richmond, Va., and include copies of summons, notes, and a scrapbook. Rev. Weddell took a
        particular interest in the Protestant Episcopal Home for Ladies in Richmond. His wife left
        an interesting reminiscence of the Fall of Richmond in 1865, as well as a few miscellaneous
        items. Also included are letters of condolence at her death, as well as records of Alex
        Weddell as administrator of his mother’s estate.</p>
      <p>Series 2. Alexander W. Weddell's papers, 1883-1948 </p>
      <p>Series 2.1. includes his diaries/appointment books which start in 1907. The early books are
        written in French, and document his diplomatic post or place of residence for that year.
        Weddell's personal and professional correspondence </p>
      <p>Series 2.2, starts in 1883, but bulk starts in 1927. It is organized alphabetically by year
        with separate folders for select correspondents within each year, as well as for other
        correspondents or subjects for which extensive material exists. Notable correspondents
        include: Viscountess Astor; Virginia senators Harry Flood Byrd; Carter Glass, and Claude
        Augustus Swanson; Virginia Governors Colgate W. Darden, Andrew Jackson Montague, and John
        Garland Pollard; Richmond author Ellen Glasgow; U.S. secretaries of state Cordell Hull, and
        Sumner Welles; and Eleanor Roosevelt. There is also a group of thirteen letters from
        President Franklin Delano Roosevelt. Specialized correspondence relating to these various
        interests and activities in many cases has been segregated unit separate files.
        Organizations that can be found in general correspondence are Richmond Community Council,
        Officers Club of Richmond (World War II), and the Young Men’s Christian Association. During
        Weddell’s absences as ambassador to Argentina and Spain, his secretary, Mrs. Elizabeth
        Cabell Dugdale, maintained his correspondence and took charge of Virginia House. Her files
        begin in 1931. </p>
      <p>Series 2.3. is correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Weddell, which is heaviest between
        1923-1927. </p>
      <p>Series 2.4. is Financial Records, 1897-1947, which are extensive. Series includes personal
        account and expense records, but detailed banking and investment records organized
        alphabetically by financial institution. These materials concern both Mr. and Mrs. Weddell’s
        account holdings. </p>
      <p>Series 2.5. Miscellaneous, 1899-1946, is educational records, scrapbooks, which document
        the Weddell’s lives and careers throughly and serve as an important introduction to the
        succeeding diplomatic and organization files. Also documented is the Weddell’s marriage in
        1923. Virginia Chase Steedman Weddell was a substantial heiress in her own right, and the
        financial security that occurred as a result of the marriage allowed Weddell to pursue many
        important interests, which the couple often shared. </p>
      <p>Series 2.6. Diplomatic Service files, 1908-1942, supplement general correspondence and
        cover all of Weddell’s diplomatic and consular posts. The heaviest documentation is for his
        years as ambassador to Argentina and to Spain. These files include dispatches, speeches,
        programs, dinner invitations and menus, magazine articles and news clippings and a wide
        variety of interesting miscellany (see guide and also U. .S. State Department folders in
        general correspondence.) The Argentina files contain Weddell’s records of the Inter-American
        Conference for the Maintenance of Peace in Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1936, which saw Franklin
        D. Roosevelt’s first visit to South America (file includes letter of Sumner Welles); the
        Seventh International Conference of American States in Montevideo, Uruguay, 1933 (files
        includes Cordell Hull letter); and a folder on the Chaco Peace Conference of 1935, for which
        Weddell won great honors as a key figure in negotiating a settlement between Bolivia and
        Paraguay (includes letter of John Garland Pollard to Mrs. Weddell). These files also contain
        several scrapbooks and journals kept by Weddell of his trips into the interior of Argentina.
        (Photographic materials and similar items have been transferred the museum photograph
        collection). Weddell’s most difficult post was Madrid, following the end of the Spanish
        Civil War and in the early days of World War II. His files are complete and informative and
        also include scrapbooks covering the entire mission. </p>
      <p>Series 2.7. Ambassador Weddell kept extensive files for the organizations in which he took
        an active part. These files include correspondence, minutes, reports, news clippings, and
        support materials. </p>
      <p>Weddell served as chairman of the Richmond-Henrico Branch of the American Red Cross. The
        files include letters of Harry F. Byrd (13 Jan. 1943) and Colgate W. Darden (19 March 1943).
        He also served as a director of the Children’s Homes Society of Virginia, seeking homes for
        orphaned or abandoned children in the dark years of the Depression and World War II. He was
        a longtime finance committee member and later vice president (note letter of John Garland
        Pollard, 18 April 1931). </p>
      <p>As president of the Richmond Branch of the English-Speaking Union and a director of the
        national organization, Weddell worked for mutual understanding among all people who share
        our common language. His files include letters from Colgate W. Darden (25 Feb. 1943), George
        Catlett Marshall (six letters between Dec. 1942-April 1943), John Garland Pollard (29
        December 1932) and Lewis F. Powell, Jr. (seven letters between Oct. 1946-June 1947). </p>
      <p>During World War II Mrs. Weddell was state chairman of the Women’s Council of the Navy
        League of the U. S., with headquarters at the Navy League Club in Richmond. Weddell himself
        served as a regional vice president of the League and a chairman of the local Navy Day
        Celebrations in October 1943. His files contain three letters of Colgate W. Darden between 7
        Sept. 1943 and 15 Sept. 1944. Weddelll also chaired the Democracy Programs of the Richmond
        Office of Civilian Defense during the war. Note Letters of Harry F. Byrd (2 Oct. 1942) and
        Colgate W. Darden (17 Oct. 1942). </p>
      <p>One of Weddell’s most important local activities involved his role as chairman of the board
        of trustees of the Richmond Academy of Arts. Intentionally modeled after Quesnay’s Academy
        of Richmond in the 1780s and 1790s (for which several research files exist), the Richmond
        Academy sought to establish a key center for the arts in Virginia. The movement eventually
        led to the founding of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, of which Weddell served a term as
        president. In 1936 a spilt developed between the two organizations, and very few Academy
        items appear in Weddell’s files after that date. Correspondence includes letters of Colgate
        W. Darden (eight letters between 12 Nov. 1942 and 11 July 1945), Cordell Hull (24 April
        1944) and John Garland Pollard (twelve letters between 24 Dec. 1931 and 7 July 1935). Mr.
        Weddell was active in the Richmond Community Fund by 1929 and served as president 1932-1933.
        During the latter period he was also chairman of the Richmond Mayor’s Committee on
        Unemployment Relief. In 1942 the organization became the Richmond War and Community Fund and
        several postwar folders concern foreign relief during that period. See also letter of Nancy
        Astor (14 Nov. 1932) and John Garland Pollard (14 Sept. 1932, 18 March 1933). As president
        of the St. John’s Episcopal Church Foundation in Richmond, Weddell endeavored to secure
        gifts for an endowment fund and for restoration and preservation of the historic structure
        (note letter of Colgate W. Darden, 9 Oct. 1945), Cordell Hull (24 April 1944), and John
        Garland Pollard (twelve letters between 24 Dec. 1931 and 7 July 1935). </p>
      <p>Mr. Weddell was active in the Richmond Community Fund by 1929 and served as president
        1932-1933. During the latter period he was also chairman of the Richmond Mayor’s Committee
        on Unemployment Relief. In 1942 the organization became the Richmond War and Community Fund
        and several postwar folders concern foreign relief during that period. See also letter of
        Nancy Astor (14 Nov. 1932) and John Garland Pollard (14 Sept. 1932, 18 March 1933). </p>
      <p>As president of the St. John’s Episcopal Church Foundation in Richmond, Weddell endeavored
        to secure gifts for an endowment fund and for restoration and preservation of the historic
        structure (note letter of Colgate W. Darden, 9 October 1945). Most of his records concerning
        St. Paul’s church involve his sponsorship of the Weddell Memorial Church located first in
        the Fulton area of East Richmond and later on Montrose Heights. The files also concern the
        acquisition of the painting “Conversion of St. Paul” by Benjamin West in 1943 and a memorial
        to Penelope (Weddell) Anderson in 1927. Files for St. Stephen’s Church in the Westhampton
        section of Richmond relate to furnishings for the Weddell Memorial Chapel in honor of
        Penelope (Weddell) Anderson. </p>
      <p>Weddell was a longtime member of the Society of the Cincinnati in Virginia after his
        election in 1927. See letter of Harry F. Byrd (10 October 1928) and Colgate W. Darden (24
        April 1947). His greatest interest, however, lay ini the Virginia Historical Society, on
        whose executive committee he served for many years. He confessed to a friend that his
        election as president of the Society “realized the ambition of my life.” Among these folders
        are letters from Nancy Astor (30 July 1945 portraits files; 10 June 1946 Charles Bridges
        file); Harry F. Byrd (26 Nov. 1945); Colgate W. Darden (23 July 1945 E. R. Williams portrait
        file); and John Garland Pollard (17 June 1932). </p>
      <p>Series 2.8. Speeches, addresses, publications, 1930-1947, includes a general file of
        Weddell’s speeches, addresses, toasts, etc. The following box begins files of his various
        publications in alphabetical order. He wrote several books, most under the auspices or
        authority of theVirginia Historical Society, but with heavy personal investment. </p>
      <p>A Description of Virginia House (Richmond, 1947) was paid for by the Weddells, but all
        revenue was to go to the Virginia Historical Society. The files include drafts, notes,
        proof, a list of prospective subscribers, and some correspondence, especially with architect
        William Lawrence Bottomley (9 Sept. 1946, 2 Dec. 1947)</p>
      <p>Weddell’s Introduction to Argentina (New York, 1939), grew from his great love of that
        nation. The volume was originally entitled “Argentina: A Good Neighbor.” Correspondence
        includes letters of Ellen Glasgow (29 Dec. 1938), Cordell Hull (28 April 1939) and Sumner
        Wells (11 June 1938). </p>
      <p>The Memorial Volume of Virginia of Virginia Historical Portraiture (Richmond, 1930),
        developed out of the “Exhibition of Virginia Portraits” held to commemorate the opening of
        Virginia House in the Spring of 1929. Early materials include correspondence of the Virginia
        Historical Society’s Committee on the Exhibition of Historical Portraits (George Cole Scott,
        chairman, Preston Davie, Earl Gregg Swem, and Weddell). Katherine Lyon Scott, Weddell’s
        personal secretary at the time, also figures prominently, and numerous letters are directed
        to Harry F. Byrd as honorary chairman of the exhibition. The files contain financial and
        subscription records, insurance materials, private viewing records, returned portraits, and
        portrait files (including correspondence, notes, biographical information, loan agreements,
        and some reproductions). A scrapbook is filed oversize following box 43. Correspondents
        include Lady Astor (21 Feb., 15 Oct., 13 Nov. 1928, files 33, 94, 135); William Lawrence
        Bottomley (file 142); Harry F. Byrd (28 March, 21 May, 6 June 1928; 11 May 1929; 4 Jan.
        1930; files 15a-e, 15f-g, 33, 108, 127); Andrew J. Montague (file 72, three letters); and
        Claude A. Swanson (30 March 1929). Another important and frequent correspondent throughout
        these files in New York collector Thomas Benedict Clarke (1848-1931), who prepared a review
        of American portraiture for the Memorial Volume. </p>
      <p>Files for Portraiture in the Virginia Historical Society (Richmond, 1945) contain
        correspondence, notes on artists and subjects, news clippings, drafts and miscellany.
        Richmond, Virginia, in Old Prints, 1737-1887 (Richmond, 1932) developed from an exhibit at
        the Richmond Public Library in 1931. The general files include a mixture of correspondence
        and accounts (see especially letters of Claude A. Swanson, 9-15 April 1931), while a
        separate prints file and news clippings file are maintained. </p>
      <p>Lastly, Weddell became involved in a project to provide an adequate survey history of
        Virginia. The Virginia History Fund that he administered for the Virginia History Foundation
        financed Matthew Page Andrews’s The Soul of A Nation: The Founding of Virginia and Project
        of New England (New York, 1943). The general files contain lengthy correspondence with
        Andrews and letters from Harry F. Byrd (24 June 1942) and Colgate W. Darden (16 Aug.
        1942).</p>
      <p> Series 2.9. Virginia House, In 1925, the Weddell’s purchased an old English manor house,
        Warwick Priory, which was being demolished in England. In the midst of public outcry, they
        had the structure shipped to America and reassembled in the Windsor Farms area of Richmond.
        An addition, designed by architect Henry Grant Morse, intentionally coped the format of
        Sulgrave Manor, the Washington ancestral home in England. The Weddell’s deeded the structure
        to the Virginia Historical Society, retaining only a life interest in the building. Virginia
        House files include original construction and title folders, repair and maintenance records,
        servants and household employees files, garden plans and care. The “loggia” file contains
        extensive correspondence with and plans by New York architect William Lawrence Bottomley.
        The files marked “Household Employees, 1930-1933” contains two letters of Andrew J.
        Montague. (See also the photograph collection of the museum department, especially for
        photographs and additional Bottomley materials.)</p>
      <p>Series 2.10. Miscellaneous. Note specifically the files on “Stardust,” an unpublished
        volume of poetry gathered by Mr. and Mrs. Weddell as an “anthology of things read and
        loved.” Correspondence includes a letter of Ellen Glasgow (27 May 1940). The estate files
        include numerous news clippings and letters concerning the deaths and funeral of the
        Weddells and of Mrs. Weddell’s personal maid, Violet Mary Andrews (Box 51). Series includes
        various Diplomatic Commissions which are notably signed by William H. Taft, Woodrow Wilson,
        Warren G. Harding, Calvin Coolidge, Franklin Roosevelt and John Garland Pollard. </p>
      <p>Series 3. Virginia Chase Steedman Weddell, Some files of Mrs. Weddell are maintained
        separately. </p>
      <p>Series 3.1. These include two diaries, 1922-1923, kept during the period when she first met
        and then married Alex Weddell. Her personal correspondence contains some early letters of
        the Chase and Atkinson families, including her father Edwin Elisha Chase (1850-1900), and
        her mother, Virginia (Atkinson) Chase (1854-1900), as well as letters from Harry F. Byrd
        (1932), Ellen Glasgow (1938-1939), Cordell Hull (1936), John Garland Pollard (1933), and
        Eleanor Roosevelt (1929, 1935-1936, 1941). </p>
      <p>Virginia Weddell worked tirelessly among the victims of Civil War during her husband’s
        mission to Spain. She administered funds for the American Committee for Relief in Spain and
        helped to organize in New York City the Committee to Send Anesthetics and Medicines to
        Spain. Mrs. Weddell established her own private relief fund and also distributed monies for
        the American Red Cross and Quaker Relief Fund. Records Among her papers includes
        correspondence, accounts and account books (2 volumes), reports, a radio address and
        miscellany (box 53).</p>
      <p>Box 54 contains complete files on the estate of industrialist James Harrison Steedman,
        (1867-1921) of St. Louis, Mrs. Weddell’s first husband. Beginning in 1898, the materials
        include records of Steedman’s naval reserve service during World War I, his subsequent
        illness and death, and the settlement of his estate. A trust fun was established for his
        widow, who was also his executrix and sole beneficiary. That trust also funded the Steedman
        fellowship in the School of Architecture at Washington University in St. Louis. The estate
        files contain Mrs. Weddell’s correspondence with attorneys, trust officers, and Steedman
        relatives; inheritance and income tax records; and materials concerning the Steedman’s
        California home, “Glen Arden,” in Santa Barbara. </p>
      <p>Following Mrs. Weddell’s files are a very few items for each of Mr. Weddell’s sisters. The
        collection closes with information in the Weddell’s memberships in various hereditary
        patriotic organizations and the supporting genealogical research on the Atkinson, Chase,
        Cunningham, and Washington families (for Mrs. Weddell) and the Creecy, Gale, Ward, Weddell
        and Wright families (for Mr. Weddell). The Wright family folders include much information on
        Weddell’s grandfather, Dr. David Minton Wright (1807-1863), who was executed in Norfolk by
        Federal authorities during the Civil War. Primarily, these materials were collected to
        refute a 1907 article appearing in the Century Magazine. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <head>Adjunct Descriptive Data</head>
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Archival Materials</head>
        <p>Virginia Historical Society: Mss1 W4126 a-e, Mss1 W4126 b FA2, </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Persons:</head>
        <persname>Anderson, Henry W. (Henry Watkins), 1870-1954</persname>
        <persname>Astor, Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor, Viscountess, 1879-1964 </persname>
        <persname>Bottomley, William Lawrence, 1883-1951</persname>
        <persname>Bruce, William Cabell, 1860-1946</persname>
        <persname>Bryan, John Stewart, 1871-1944</persname>
        <persname>Bryan, Jonathan</persname>
        <persname>Byrd, Harry F. (Harry Flood), 1887-1966</persname>
        <persname>Carr, Wilbur John, 1870-1942</persname>
        <persname>Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933</persname>
        <persname>Darden, Colgate W. (Colgate Whitehead), 1897-1981 </persname>
        <persname>Dugdale, Elizabeth Cabell, 1902-1990</persname>
        <persname>Ellyson, Lora Effie Hotchkiss, 1848-1935</persname>
        <persname>Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945</persname>
        <persname>Glass, Carter, 1858-1946</persname>
        <persname>Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923 </persname>
        <persname>Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955 </persname>
        <persname>Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1894–1956</persname>
        <persname>Montague, Andrew Jackson, 1862-1937 </persname>
        <persname>Morrow, Dwight W. (Dwight Whitney), 1873-1931</persname>
        <persname>Morse, Henry Grant, 1884-1934</persname>
        <persname>Olds, Robert Edwin, 1875-1932</persname>
        <persname>Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922</persname>
        <persname>Pollard, John Garland, 1871-1937</persname>
        <persname>Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962</persname>
        <persname>Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945</persname>
        <persname>Sheffield, James Rockwell, 1864–1938</persname>
        <persname>Swanson, Claude Augustus, 1862-1939</persname>
        <persname>Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930</persname>
        <persname>Templewood, Samuel John Gurney Hoare, Viscount, 1880-1959</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Alexander Watson, 1841-1883</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Alexander Wilbourne, 1876-1948</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Elizabeth Wright, 1878-1955</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, James, 1807-1865</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Margaret Ward, 1869-1935</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Penelope Margaret Wright, 1840-1901</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, Virginia Chase Steedman, 1874-1948</persname>
        <persname>Weddell, William Sparrow, 1874-1944</persname>
        <persname>Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961</persname>
        <persname>Williams, John L. (John Langbourne), 1831-1915</persname>
        <persname>Williams, John Skelton, 1865-1926</persname>
        <persname>Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Family Names:</head>
        <famname>Weddell family Genealogy</famname>
        <famname>Wright family Genealogy</famname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Corporate Names:</head>
        <corpname>Protestant Episcopal Church Home for Ladies (Richmond, Va.)</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject>American Red Cross</subject>
        <subject>Argentina Diplomats United States</subject>
        <subject>Argentina Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>Autobiography</subject>
        <subject>Catania (Italy)</subject>
        <subject>Charities Virginia Richmond History 20th century</subject>
        <subject>Copenhagen (Denmark)</subject>
        <subject>Denmark Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>Diplomatic and consular service, American</subject>
        <subject>Diplomatic and consular service United States History 20th century</subject>
        <subject>Greece Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>India Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>Italy Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>Mexico Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>Richmond Community Fund (Richmond, Va.)</subject>
        <subject>Southern Churchman</subject>
        <subject>Spain Foreign relations United States</subject>
        <subject>United States. Consulate (Athens, Greece)</subject>
        <subject>United States. Consulate (Calcutta, India)</subject>
        <subject>United States. Consulate (Catania, Italy)</subject>
        <subject>United States. Consulate (Mexico City, Mexico)</subject>
        <subject>United States. Consulate (Zanzibar, Zanzibar)</subject>
        <subject>United States. Department of State</subject>
        <subject>United States Diplomatic and consular service History 20th century</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Argentina</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Denmark</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Greece</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations India</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Italy</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Mexico</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Spain</subject>
        <subject>United States Foreign relations Zanzibar</subject>
        <subject>United States. General and Special Claims Commissions</subject>
        <subject>Virginia House (Richmond, Va.)</subject>
        <subject>Virginia Museum of Fine Arts</subject>
        <subject>Virginians Argentina</subject>
        <subject>Virginians Mexico</subject>
        <subject>Women's Council of the Navy League of the United States</subject>
        <subject>Zanzibar</subject>
        <subject>Zanzibar Foreign relations United States</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>

    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 1. Weddell family papers, <unitdate type="inclusive"
              >1858-1925</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 1.1. James Weddell (1807-1865) </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Estate accounts, <unitdate>1865</unitdate></unittitle> 
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 1.2. Rev. Alexander Watson Weddell (1841-1883)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Honorary degree, sermons, notes, news clippings; scrapbook; obituary
                notices </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02>
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 1.3. Penelope Margaret Wright Weddell (1840-1901)</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Reminiscence, 1895, of the Fall of Richmond in 1865; letters of condolence,
                1901; administrator’s records, 1901; miscellany, 1858-1925</unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 2. Alexander Wilbourne and Virginia Weddell, <unitdate type="inclusive">1876-1948</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.1. Diaries/calendars, 
              <unitdate>1907-1947</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">1-3</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Diaries, 1907-1913; 1915-1916; 1919-1947 (36 vols.); desk calendars, 1947 </unittitle> 
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.2. Correspondence,
              <unitdate>1883-1947</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">4-15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
          <c02 level="subseries">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Subseries 2.3. Correspondence, 1923-1946, with Virginia (Chase) Steedman Weddell 
              </unittitle>
              <container label="Box" type="box">15</container>
            </did>
          </c02>
            <c02 level="subseries">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Subseries 2.4. Financial Records, 
                  <unitdate>1897-1947 </unitdate>
                </unittitle>
                <container label="Box" type="box">16-29</container>
              </did>
              <c03>
                <did>
                  <unittitle>Personal account book, Loose accounts, book/manuscript orders, monthly expense sheets/petty cash, investment/ banking records, and income tax records </unittitle> 
                </did>
              </c03>
            </c02>
              <c02 level="subseries">
                <did>
                  <unittitle>Subseries 2.5. Miscellaneous, 
                    <unitdate>1899-1946</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <container label="Box" type="box">30</container>
                </did>
                <c03>
                  <did>
                    <unittitle>Educational records, scrapbooks, marriage to Virginia (Chase) Steedman </unittitle> 
                  </did>
                </c03>
              </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.6. Diplomatic Service Files,  
              <unitdate>1908-1942</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">30-34a</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>American legation, Copenhagen, Denmark; American Consul, Zanzibar; American Consul, Catania, Italy; American Consul general, Athens, Greece; American Consulate, Calcutta, India; American Consulate, Mexico City, Mexico; Ambassador to Argentina; Ambassador to Spain; and calling cards. </unittitle> 
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.7. Organization and Association files, <unitdate>1923-1948</unitdate> 
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">35-41</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.8. Speeches, Addresses, and publications, <unitdate>1930-1947</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">41-48</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.9. Virginia House, <unitdate>1925-1947</unitdate> 
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">49-50</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 2.10. Miscellaneous, <unitdate>1929-1948</unitdate> 
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">50-51</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 3. Virginia (Chase) Steedman Weddell, <unitdate type="inclusive">1866-1947</unitdate>
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 3.1. Diaries,
              <unitdate>1922-1923</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">52</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 3.2. Correspondence, 
              <unitdate>1866-1947</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">52-53</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 3.3. Financial and Philanthropy,
              <unitdate>1923-1955</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">53</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Loose accounts, Commonplace books, address books, land records, presentation at Court of St. James, passport, relief work </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 3.4. James Harrison Steedman estate files, 
              <unitdate>1895-1945</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">54</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 3.5. Miscellaneous 
            </unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="box">55</container>
          </did>
          <c03>
            <did>
              <unittitle>Speeches, memberships, Christmas cards, news clippings, recipe book, personal miscellany </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Series 4. Family Miscellaneous
          </unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellany of Weddell sisters, genealogical materials, hereditary patriotic societies</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="box">55</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
