<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00009">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00009::A Guide to the Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00009.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00009::A Guide to
             the Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers)//EN"
             "vih00009.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1995</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Brown, Aubrey Neblett, Papers of 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 B8122 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">17 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         James Berwick. 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">25 March 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00009::A Guide to the Aubrey Neblett Brown
            Papers)//EN" "vih00009.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002
            by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1944-1995</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 B8122 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1944-1995</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 B8122 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">730 (ca.)
         items.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The Aubrey N. Brown papers include
         a wide variety of documents related to race relations and the
         civil rights movement dating from 1944. The collection
         includes newspaper clippings, pamphlets, correspondence from a
         variety of sources, and some of the organizational records
         from the Richmond Area Council on Human Relations and the
         Virginia Council on Human Relations (organized by the Southern
         Regional Council). Also included in the collection are
         materials related to the Presbyterian Outlook, such as papers
         pertaining to the history of the magazine and articles related
         to race that appeared in the publication. Part of the
         collection also includes annual family newsletters generated
         by Brown.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Aubrey Neblett Brown Papers, 1944-1995 (Mss1 B8122 a
            FA2), Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Aubrey N. Brown, Jr., Richmond, Va., in 1990.
            Accessioned 17 May 1996.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Aubrey Neblett Brown was born May 6, 1908, in Hillsboro,
         Texas. He attended Davidson College in North Carolina and
         earned a graduate degree in Union Theological Seminary in
         Richmond, Virginia. He married Sarah Dumond Hill (1910-1995)
         of Richmond and they had eight children. Brown returned to
         Richmond in 1943 and served as editor of the Presbyterian
         Outlook until his retirement in 1978. Throughout his career,
         Brown participated in several organizations that fostered
         improved race relations.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Series 1 concerns the Richmond Area Council on Human
         Relations (RACHR) from 1960 through 1967. The RACHR was an
         interracial council that was established during the mid-1950s.
         This council was one of many local councils in Virginia that
         functioned under the wing of the Virginia Council of Human
         Relations (a subsidiary of the Southern Regional Council). The
         purpose of the RACHR was to facilitate cooperation between the
         races through meetings and events. They also supported the
         efforts of activists who were agitating for racial
         equality.</p>
      <p>The portion of organizational records in this collection
         includes membership and solicitations lists; meeting minutes,
         which include attendees, progress notes, and future goals;
         correspondence; newspaper clippings about the RACHR; program
         announcements (1962-1964); newsletters about the activities of
         the RACHR; council brochures; financial records; and
         miscellany. Items are arranged chronologically (ca. 90
         items).</p>
      <p>Series 2 includes a variety of documents concerning the
         sit-ins in Richmond which occurred during March 1960. It
         includes letters from some of the participants to Aubrey
         Brown, as well as a letter by Brown to the administration at
         Union Theological Seminary in which he voices his support for
         the students' protest; magazine articles about the sit-ins in
         Richmond, as well as local newspaper clippings; and a brief
         report about the establishment of the Richmond Citizens
         Advisory Committee which was established during the sit-ins
         (ca. 15 items).</p>
      <p>Series 3 contains 4 items, 1960, which include
         correspondence about Christian students involved with the
         Civil Rights Movement and documents about the protest
         resignation of Dr. J. Robert Nelson, Dean of the Vanderbilt
         University Divinity School</p>
      <p>Series 4 concerns the Virginia Council on Human relations,
         1960-1968. The Virginia Council on Human Relations was one of
         several state councils established in the South by the
         Southern Regional Council. The purpose of the organization was
         to help to establish local councils and to provide them with
         support activities and news of events held by other councils.
         The VCHR and the local councils worked toward easing racial
         tensions by providing interracial gatherings, sponsoring
         speakers, and disseminating information about race
         relations</p>
      <p>This is one of the larger sections in the collection and is
         arranged chronologically. It contains some of the
         organizational records that include minutes from the board of
         directors meetings, membership solicitations, financial
         records, correspondence, newsletters, newspaper clippings
         about activities of and appointments to the VCHR,
         organizational brochures, and miscellany (ca. 140 items).</p>
      <p>Series 5 concerns the Southern Regional Council, 1952-1968.
         Established in 1944, the Southern Regional Council was an
         outgrowth of the Commission on Interracial Cooperation. One of
         the goals of the SRC was to collect and disseminate data bout
         issues related to race, particularly civil rights agitation
         and discriminatory policies.</p>
      <p>This section includes documents generated by the Southern
         Regional Council to disseminate information about race
         relations and civil rights agitation. This section is arranged
         topically: miscellaneous documents, news releases disseminated
         by the SRC, some issues of New South magazine (the official
         organ of the SRC), publications and pamphlets, reports and
         special reports that focus on specific struggles within the
         Civil Rights Movement. Within each folder, the documents are
         arranged chronologically (ca. 50 items). Series 6 dates from
         1943-1990 and contains articles about race that were published
         in the Presbyterian Outlook; documents pertaining to the
         history of the Presbyterian Outlook, edited by Brown; and two
         memos from Brown soliciting information about the Civil Rights
         Movement to be used for publication (ca. 40 items).</p>
      <p>Series 7 contains a collection of speeches, 1957-1963 and
         undated, made by Brown, arranged chronologically. The speeches
         reflect his thoughts about race relations. Some include the
         place and date at which the speech was given (ca. 15
         items).</p>
      <p>Series 8 contains correspondence, 1958-1963 and undated.
         Most of the letters in this section are addressed to Brown.
         The correspondence reflects the wide variety of sources from
         which Brown received information. A particular letter of
         interest is from Newman Hamblet, Vice President of Thalhimer
         Bros., Inc., and member of the RACHR, updating Brown on the
         status of an employee in 1963 (this employee was an
         African-American who was given a job at Thalhimers at the
         request of Brown) (ca. 15 items).</p>
      <p>Series 9 contains two news releases, 1960 and 1961. One
         concerns segregation at public schools in Georgia; the other
         concerns resistance to desegregation at the University of the
         South at Sewanee, Tennessee (2 items).</p>
      <p>Series 10 concern the Religious News Service, 1959-1963,
         and contains news excerpts about activities and events in the
         religious community (ca. 10 items).</p>
      <p>Series 11 contains organization newsletters, 1960-1989, and
         includes three newsletters from the Student Non-Violent
         Coordinating Committee (SNCC), which was established during
         1960 to help organize student protesters. The additional
         newsletters are from a wide variety of religious and civil
         rights organizations, 1960-1989 (ca. 15 items).</p>
      <p>Series 12 includes documents relating to the Conference on
         Integration of a Segregated Society, 1962, held at Vanderbilt
         University. Included are correspondence and planning notes for
         the conference, a press release, and a speech given at the
         conference. The folder with correspondence includes a letter
         from author Lillian Smith (1897-1966) to Brown about race
         relations and her book Killers of the Dream (ca. 30
         items).</p>
      <p>Series 13 concerns Brown's service as chairman of the
         Virginia State Advisory Committee to the United States
         Commission on Civil Rights.. The two documents in this section
         consist of a conference program and a list of organizations
         that met with the committee in March 1966 (2 items).</p>
      <p>Series 14 concerns Brown's service as the chairman of the
         planning committee for the Conference on People, Religion, and
         a Changing Virginia. The conference was held at the John
         Marshall Hotel in Richmond in November 1966; its purpose was
         to bring together Virginia' religious community to discuss the
         role of churches in social change. The documents in this
         section include conference information, such as announcements
         and a program guide; correspondence; a discussion guide used
         for groups during the conference, and several pages of
         handwritten discussion notes that summarize what each group
         concluded about race relations; expenditures; participants; a
         press release and newspaper clippings; and speeches (ca. 30
         items).</p>
      <p>Included in Series 15 are pamphlets and publications,
         1944-1967 and undated, about segregation and racial issues.
         Publications about Virginia include "When a City Closes Its
         Schools," which is about public schools in Norfolk (1960);
         "Events in Virginia," a pamphlet distributed by the Virginia
         State Chamber of Commerce in Richmond (1962); and "Danville,
         Virginia," a booklet about the violent civil rights
         demonstrations there (1963). This section is arranged
         chronologically according to the dates given on each
         publication (ca. 60 items).</p>
      <p>Series 16 is the largest section of the collection and
         contains a variety of newspaper clippings, 1951-1966 and
         undated, from several different papers, which include the
         Richmond Times Dispatch, the Richmond News Leader, the
         Christian Science Monitor, and the New York Times. The
         articles focus on racial issues and the Civil Rights Movement
         and are arranged chronologically (ca. 150 items).</p>
      <p>Series 17 is made up of miscellaneous documents, 1945-1980
         and undated, chiefly articles about race relations. Many were
         generated by religious organizations that were concerned with
         social action or made resolutions about race relations. This
         section contains three folders: the first contains dated
         documents; the second contains documents without dates; and
         the third includes handwritten notes (ca. 20 items).</p>
      <p>Series 18 includes two types of Brown family
         newsletters--"Brown's Bugle" (1956-1970) and "Anno Domini"
         (1971-1972, 1974-1977, and 1979-1995); excerpts from letters
         written by Aubrey Brown III (b. 1937) while serving in the
         Peace Corps in Nigeria from 1961-1964; the resumes of Aubrey
         N. Brown, Jr. (1990 and 1995); a brief biography of Brown
         written by Patricia Cornwell; and biographical sketches
         (written by Brown) about some of the founding members of the
         Ginter Park Presbyterian Church (ca. 40 items).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The papers of Aubrey N. Brown are arranged into eighteen
         series by subject and document type.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms:</head>
      <subject>African Americans -- Virginia -- Civil
         rights.</subject>
      <subject>Brown, Aubrey N. (Aubrey Neblett), 1908-</subject>
      <subject>Civil rights movements.</subject>
      <subject>Clergy -- Political activity.</subject>
      <subject>Segregation in education.</subject>
      <subject>Southern States -- Race relations.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Social conditions -- 20th
         century.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Richmond Area Council on
               Human Relations 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1960-1967</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1960, 1961, 1962, 1963, 1967, and misc. documents
               (n.d.)</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Richmond Sit-Ins,
               1960</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, magazine articles, newspaper
               clippings, Richmond Citizens Advisory Committee.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">National Student Christian
               Federation.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Virginia Council on Human
               Relations 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1960-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1960, 1961, 1962, 1963, 1964, 1965, 1966, 1967, 1968,
               misc. documents (n.d.).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Souther Regional Council, 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1960-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2
               (cont.)-3</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Misc. documents (1960-1968), news releases, New
               South, publications, reports; Southern Regional Council
               special reports.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Presbyterian
               Outlook</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Articles, history, memos.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Speeches by Aubrey
               Brown</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Corresondence 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1958-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1958-1960, 1962-1963 and n.d.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">News Releases</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Religious News
               Service</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">Organizational Newsletters,
               1960-1989</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">Conference on Integration
               of a Segregated Society</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, planning notes, press release,
               speech.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 13">Virginia Advisory committee
               to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights</unittitle>
          <container label="Folder" type="Box">3
               (cont.)</container>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 14">Conference on People,
               Religion, and a Changing Virginia</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Conference information, announcements and programs;
               correspondence; discussion guide; discussion guide notes
               (3 folders); expenditures; participants; press releases
               and newspaper clippings; speech (3 folders).</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 15">Miscellaneous Publications,
               1940s-1967</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">4
               (cont.)-5</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1940's, 1950-1954, 1955-1957, 1958-1959, 1960,1961,
               1962, 1963 (2 folders), 1964-1965 and 1967, n.d.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 16">Newspaper Clippings,
               1951-1966.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">5 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1951, 1954, 1955, 1956, 1957, 1960, 1961, 1962, 1963,
               1964, 1966, n.d.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 17">Miscellaneous
               Documents</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">5 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>1945-1968, n.d., handwritten notes.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 18">Brown Family</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">5 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Brown's Bugle, Anno Domini, Aubrey Brown III, Aubrey
               Brown Resume</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
