<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00011">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00011::A Guide to the Keith Family Papers, 1830-1979)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00011.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00011::A Guide to
             the Keith Family Papers, 1830-1979)//EN"
             "vih00011.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Keith Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830-1979</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Keith Family Papers, 1830-1979 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 K2694 c
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">ca. 22 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         Virginia Historical Society staff, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">29 March 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00011::A Guide to the Keith Family Papers,
            1830-1979)//EN" "vih00011.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Keith Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1830-1879</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 K2694 c
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Keith Family Papers, 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1830-1979</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 K2694 c FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">1,025 (ca.) items in 14 manuscript
         boxes.</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Chiefly correspondence and other
         materials of Robert Taylor Scott (1834-1897) and his wife
         Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott (1838-1923). R. T. Scott was a
         lawyer in Warrenton and Prince William and Fairfax counties, a
         member of the constitutional convention of 1867 and the
         Virginia General Assembly of 1881-1882, and served as
         attorney-general of Virginia from 1889 to 1897. At the
         beginning of the Civil War he organized a company of infantry
         and served as captain of Company K, Eighth Virginia Regiment,
         C.S.A., until he was appointed to the staff of General George
         Edward Pickett. His materials include extensive
         correspondence, chiefly with his wife, both before and during
         the Civil War, discussing family and personal matters, legal
         education, admittance to the bar and practice of law, and the
         impending conflict. War-time correspondence describes the
         secession convention of 1861, general camp life, duties as
         quartermaster, and Union activities in Fauquier County and
         near Leesburg, Va. Also included are legal records and some
         records for Company K, Eighth Virginia Regiment. Records of
         Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott include general correspondence,
         accounts, land records, miscellany, and materials from her
         term as president of the Black Horse Chapter, United Daughters
         of the Confederacy, at Warrenton, Va.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Keith Family Papers, 1830-1979 (Mss1 K2694 c FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Mrs. Fanny K. Day, Edison, N.J., Judge James
            Keith, Fairfax, Va., John A. C. Keith, Fairfax, Va., and
            Vice-Admiral R. Taylor Scott Keith, Coronado, Calif., 15
            May 1985.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>This collection of Keith family papers consists of
         materials from five generations of Keith, Scott and Carter
         family members from Warrenton and surrounding Fauquier County.
         Robert Taylor Scott (1834-1897) was a lawyer in Warrenton and
         Prince William and Fairfax counties, a member of the
         constitutional convention of 1867 and the Virginia General
         Assembly of 1881-1882, and served as attorney-general of
         Virginia from 1889 to 1897. His wife, Fanny Scott (Carter)
         Scott (1838-1923), served as president of the Black Horse
         Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, at Warrenton,
         Va.</p>
      <p>Also represented in the collection are Robert I. Taylor
         (1777?-1840), Mary Elizabeth (Berry) Taylor (d. 1863?),
         Elizabeth Blackwell (Pickett) Scott (1788-1862), Isham Keith
         (1801-1863), Juliet (Chilton) Keith (1800-1887), Anne Smith
         (Chilton) Johnston (1810-1893), Robert Eden Scott (1808-1862),
         Heningham Watkins (Lyons) Scott (1827-1886), Margaret Gordon
         (Scott) Lee (1817-1866), Richard Henry Carter (1817-1880),
         Mary Welby (DeButts) Carter (1819-1885), Isham Keith
         (1833-1902), Sarah Agnes (Blackwell) Keith (1837-1912), James
         Keith (1839-1918), John Scott (1845-1882), Sophia DeButts
         (Carter) Carter (1841-1928), Richard Carter Scott (1859-1928),
         Mary Welby (Scott) Keith (1870-1958), Alice Dixon (Payne) Carr
         (1870-1966), Katherine Isham Keith (1865-1944), Thomas
         Randolph Keith (b. 1872), and John Augustine Chilton Keith (b.
         1907).</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>Robert I. Taylor (1777?-1840) was a prominent Alexandria
         lawyer and president of the town's common council. His papers
         contain several items of correspondence, estate materials and
         materials concerning the guardianship of Richmond Marshall
         Scott (b. 1829) by William Haywood Foote (1781?-1846),
         executor of Richard Marshall Scott (d. 1833). The latter
         includes a commonplace book kept by Foote. Taylor's wife, Mary
         Elizabeth (Berry) Taylor (d. 1863?) also has several letters
         in the collection, as does Elizabeth Blackwell (Pickett) Scott
         (1788-1862), wife of Judge John Scott (1781-1850).</p>
      <p>Correspondence of Isham Keith (1801-1863), his wife, Juliet
         (Chilton) Keith (1800-1887), and her sister, Ann Smith
         (Chilton) Johnston (1810-1893), is included herein. Isham
         Keith was an influential Warrenton business man. Among his
         correspondence is a letter to Judge John Scott and several
         letters from a brother in Georgia, John Marshall Keith
         (1788-1841), discussing the sale of a slave and state and
         national politics.</p>
      <p>Robert Eden Scott (1808-1862), son of Judge John Scott and
         Elizabeth Blackwell (Pickett) Scott, was recognized as one of
         the state's leading Whigs in the years immediately prior to
         the Civil War. His papers consist of correspondence, mostly
         with his son, Robert Taylor Scott, and materials concerning
         Sarah Scott (Ashton) Glassell. Robert Eden Scott's third wife,
         Heningham Watkins (Lyons) Scott (1827-1886) has several items
         of correspondence in the collection, as does his sister,
         Margaret Gordon (Scott) Lee (1817-1866). There is also a box
         of estate materials for Margaret Gordon (Scott) Lee (box 2),
         which contains accounts, vouchers, correspondence and reports
         to the Fauquier County Court.</p>
      <p>Richard Henry Carter (1817-1880) was a major in the 8th
         Virginia Infantry during the Civil War. In 1879 he received an
         appointment to the U. S. custom house in Panama and his
         correspondence is largely with his son-in-law, Robert Taylor
         Scott, during this period. One letter, dated 10 March 1880,
         discusses national politics and American policies toward
         Panama; however, much of his correspondence concerns a large
         debt which was administered by RTS (see below). Carter's wife,
         Mary Welby (DeButts) Carter (1819-1885), also has several
         letters in the collection.</p>
      <p>The Keith papers contain some correspondence of Isham Keith
         (1833-1902), son of Isham Keith and Juliet (Chilton) Keith,
         and his wife Sarah Agnes (Blackwell) Keith (1837-1912), as
         sell as a scrapbook belonging to her. A letter to Mrs. Keith
         from Armistead Churchill Gordon (1855-1931) discusses family
         history. James Keith, circuit judge and president of the
         Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals from 1895 to 1916, was
         another son of Isham Keith and Juliet (Chilton) Keith. His
         letters are largely with family members and deal with family
         history. There is also an autograph album belonging to Judge
         Keith from the 1859-1860 session as the University of
         Virginia.</p>
      <p>The major figure in the Keith family papers is Robert
         Taylor Scott (1834-1897), attorney-general of Virginia from
         1889 to 1897. Sone of Robert Eden Scott and Elizabeth (Taylor)
         Scott, he was born on 10 March 1834 at Warrenton, Va. He
         graduated from the University of Virginia in 1854 and was
         admitted to the Warrenton bar in 1857. At the outbreak if the
         Civil War, Scott organized a company of infantry which was
         mustered into service as Company K, Eighth Virginia Regiment,
         under Colonel Eppa Hunton. RTS served as its captain until the
         fall of 8162, when was appointed to the staff of General
         George Edward Pickett as division quartermaster. He remained
         on Pickett's staff until the end of the war.</p>
      <p>Robert Taylor Scott was a member of the constitutional
         convention of 1867 and the Virginia General Assembly of
         1881-1882, representing Fauquier and Loudoun counties. He was
         elected attorney-general in 1889 and re-elected four years
         later.</p>
      <p>Materials pertaining to Robert Taylor Scott include
         correspondence, CSA materials, legal files, financial records,
         a few items pertaining to his political career, copies of
         speeches, clippings, miscellany and obituaries. Most of the
         correspondence is between Scott and his wife, Fanny Scott
         (Carter) Scott, during the Civil War and the years immediately
         before. These letters deal primarily with personal and family
         matters, yet many contain information valuable to the
         historical researcher as well. Much of the pre-war
         correspondence concerns Scott's law activities; his education
         and apprenticeship under his father, admittance to the bar,
         and practice in Warrenton and Prince William and Fairfax
         counties. Of particular interest are the letter of 31 December
         1856, discussing a slave insurrection in Prince William
         County; letter of 12 July 1860, concerning a runaway slave;
         and letter of 3 January 1861, concerning the purchase or hire
         of slaves. Other letters during this period deal with politics
         and the impending conflict. The Civil War correspondence, from
         1861 through November 1864, describes the secession convention
         of 1861 (at which RTS was an observer and his father, RES, a
         delegate), general camp life, Scott's duties as quartermaster,
         Union activities in Fauquier and campaigns in which Scott was
         involved. Scott's letters from Camp Johnston, near Leesburg,
         dated 20 September 1861 to 1 October 1861 and from camp near
         Centreville, dated 1 January 1862 to 5 March 1862, provide an
         especially good picture of such facets of camp life as:
         quarters and provisions, leaves and furloughs, religious
         activities, health, morale and discipline. Other selected
         letters are indexed following this description.</p>
      <p>Scott's legal records include several miscellaneous files,
         a copy of a partnership agreement with James Vass Brooke
         (1824-1898) and records concerning his role as fiduciary for
         Maria Louisa (Nelson) Carter, William Wesley Phillips,
         Lawrence Ashton and John Quincy Marr. Marr was the first
         Confederate soldier to be killed during the Civil War and
         Robert Taylor Scott was administrator for his estate. Scott's
         CSA service file contains orders, muster roles and
         quartermaster's pay records for Company K, 8th Virginia
         Regiment. Among Scott's financial records are materials
         concerning the debt of Richard Henry Carter.</p>
      <p>Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott (1838-1923) was the wife of
         Robert Taylor Scott and the daughter of Richard Henry Carter
         and Mary Welby (DeButts) Carter. Her papers include general
         correspondence, accounts, land records, miscellany and
         materials from her term as president of the Black Horse
         Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, Warrenton, Va.
         Her correspondence with John Augustine Chilton Keith
         (1870-1915) relates primarily to the estate of Robert Taylor
         Scott and includes two letters from John Singleton Mosby
         (1833-1916) concerning restitution due RTS for tobacco
         confiscated by the Union army in 1865. Land records mainly
         concern tracts in Warrenton. Materials concerning Fanny Scott
         (Carter) Scott's presidency of the UDC chapter include
         correspondence, copies of applications containing service
         records and several biographical sketches of Robert Randolph,
         one of the captains of the Black Horse Cavalry during the
         Civil War.</p>
      <p>John Scott (1845-1882), son of Robert Eden Scott and Ann
         (Morson) Scott, was a lawyer in Baltimore, Maryland, and
         California and items pertaining to him include diplomas,
         certificates, a catalog of his law library and materials
         concerning his death in California. There are also
         miscellaneous materials for Sophia DeButts (Carter) Carter
         (1841-1928), sister of Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott.</p>
      <p>Robert Taylor Scott and Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott had
         three children who lived to adulthood and two are represented
         herein. Richard Carter Scott (1859-1928) was a lawyer and
         judge in Richmond, VA. A University of Virginia graduate, he
         worked in Norfolk for the Virginia, Tennessee and Georgia Air
         Lines and the Exchange Bank of Virginia before coming to
         Richmond in 1885 as Deputy Collector of Internal Revenue. He
         entered the attorney-general's office in 1889 when his father
         was elected to that post. He was appointed attorney-general in
         1897 to serve out the remainder of his father's term and in
         1904 was appointed by the General Assembly judge of the 10th
         judicial circuit.</p>
      <p>Most of the correspondence of Richard Carter Scott was
         written to his father during his days in Norfolk and these
         letters are arranged with his father's correspondence. Another
         correspondent of RCS is William Wallace Scott (1845-1929),
         author, state law librarian and secretary to the State
         Democratic Committee from 1883-1892. Included in the
         miscellaneous material is Richard Carter Scott's account of
         the 1910 Episcopal Church Convention in Cincinnati.</p>
      <p>Mary Welby (Scott) Keith's (1870-1958) materials include
         correspondence primarily with her husband, John Augustine
         Chilton Keith, certificates from the Virginia Female Institute
         (Staunton, Va.), signed by Mrs. J. E. B. Stuart, and a
         scrapbook. There are also two scrapbooks belonging to Alice
         Dixon (Payne) Carr (1870-19676), kept in Warrenton.</p>
      <p>Two children of Isham Keith and Sarah Agnes (Blackwell)
         Keith, Katherine Isham Keith (1865-1944) and Thomas Randolph
         Keith (1872- ), are prominent in the collection. Materials
         pertaining to Katherine Isham Keith include correspondence, a
         scrapbook containing two letters from John Singleton Mosby and
         one from James Keith, and genealogical materials. Harry Flood
         Byrd (1887-1966), George Campbell Peery (1873-1952) and Robert
         Walton Moore (1859-1941) are all correspondents. Thomas
         Randolph Keith's correspondence primarily concerns
         genealogy.</p>
      <p>John Augustine Chilton Keith (b. 1907), sone of John
         Augustine Chilton Keith and Mary Welby (Scott) Keith has
         several items of correspondence in the collection. Among these
         materials is a lengthy study of "Gordonsdale," Fauquier
         County, written by Reginald J. Vickers. The last box (14)
         contains miscellaneous family materials, clippings,
         genealogical notes on the Keith and Scott families and
         information on Stuyvesant School, Warrenton, Va. Included in
         the materials on Stuyvesant School is an essay written by John
         Augustine Chilton Keith (1907- ), about the school and its
         founder, Edwin Burrus King (1876-1950).</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The papers of the Keith family is arranged into 25 series
         by individual and further subdivided by material type where
         necessary.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms:</head>
      <subject>Confederate States of America. Army -- Military
         life.</subject>
      <subject>Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia
         Infantry Regiment, 8th. Company K.</subject>
      <subject>Keith family..</subject>
      <subject>Lawyers -- Virginia -- Warrenton -- History --
         19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Scott family.</subject>
      <subject>Scott, Fanny Scott Carter, 1838-1923.</subject>
      <subject>Scott, Robert Taylor, 1834-1897.</subject>
      <subject>Taylor family.</subject>
      <subject>United Daughters of the Confederacy. Black Horse
         Chapter (Warrenton, Va.).</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- History -- Civil War,
         1861-1865.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Politics and government -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Warrenton (Va.) -- History.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Societies and clubs.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Robert I. Taylor (ca.
               1777?-1840)</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1834-1840; guardianship of Richard M.
               Scott by William Haywood Foote, 1833-1846; estate,
               1854-1867.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Mary Elizabeth (Berry)
               Taylor (d. 1863?), Alexandria, D.C. (now
               Va.)</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1833-1834; recipe.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Elizabeth Blackwell
               (Pickett) Scott (1788-1862), "Gordonsdale," Fauquier
               County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, undated.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
          <p>Correspondence, undated.</p>
        </arrangement>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Isham Keith (1801-1863),
               "Woodbourne," Fauquier County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1837-1844.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Juliet (Chilton) Keith
               (1800-1887), "Woodbourne," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1858-1871.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Ann Smith (Chilton) Johnston
               (1810-1893), "Woodbourne," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1857-1858; account.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Robert Eden Scott
               (1808-1862), "Oakwood," Fauquier County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1838-1862; miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Heningham Watkins (Lyons)
               Scott (1827-1886), "Oakwood," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correpondence, 1860-1886.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Margaret Gordon (Scott) Lee
               (1817-1866), "Oakwood," Fauquier County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1
               (cont.)-2</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>General correspondence, 1858-1864; book of verse,
               1830; estate, 1866-1874.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Richard Henry Carter
               (1817-1880), "Glen Welby," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1830-1880.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">Mary Welby (DeButts) Carter
               (1819-1885), "Glen Welby," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1843-1885.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">Isham Keith (1833-1902),
               "Woodbourne," Fauquier County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1857-1905; miscellany; scrapbook.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 14">James Keith (1839-1918),
               Fauquier County and Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1902-1915; obituaries; autograph
               album.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 15">Robert Taylor Scott
               (1834-1897), Warrenton, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 15.1</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3
                  (cont.)-7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>General correspondence, 1843-1897 unidentified,
                  B-M.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 15.2</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>CSA materials; legal files.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Subseries 15.3</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Financial materials; state debt; General Assembly;
                  speeches; clippings; miscellany; obituaries.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 16">Fanny Scott (Carter) Scott
               (1838-1923), Warrenton, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 16.1">General
                  Correspondence, 1857-1922.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 16.2">Accounts, 1897-1922;
                  land records; UDC materials.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">10</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 17">John Scott (1845-1882),
               Baltimore, Md., and California.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">11</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Miscellany; materials concerning his death.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 18">Sophia DeButts (Carter)
               Carter (1841-1928), Loudoun County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">11 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 19">Richard Carter Scott
               (1859-1928), Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">11 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence with individuals, 1885-1914;
               correspondence with institutions, 1889-1902;
               miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 20">Mary Welby (Scott) Keith
               (1870-1958), "Woodbourne," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">11
               (cont.)-12</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1895-1949; miscellany; scrapbook.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 21">Alice Dixon (Payne) Carr
               (1870-1966), Warrenton, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">12 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Scrapbooks.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 22">Katherine Isham Keith
               (1865-1944), "Woodbourne," Fauquier County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1894-1933; scrapbook; genealogical
               materials.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 23">Thomas Randolph Keith (b.
               1872), Fairfax, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1911-1929.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 24">John Augustine Chilton
               Keith (b. 1907), Warrenton, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1934-1979.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 25">Family and General
               Miscellany</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">14</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Notes on Keith and Scott families; materials on
               Stuyvesant School.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
