<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00010">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00010::A Guide to the Adele Clark Papers, 1855-1976)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00010.xml&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00010::A Guide to
             the Adele Clark Papers, 1855-1976)//EN"
             "vih00010.xml"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Adele Clark Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1976</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Clark, Adele, Papers 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 C5472 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">19 Kilobytes</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         James Berwick. 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">28 March 2002</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00010::A Guide to the Adele Clark Papers,
            1855-1976)//EN" "vih00010.xml" converted from EAD 1.0 to
            2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Adele Clark Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1855-1976</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 C5472 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">Adele Clark Papers 
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1855-1976</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 C5472 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">900 (ca.) items. (2 archival and 1
         oversize box).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Include scattered business and
         personal correspondence, ca. 1916-1950, as well as newspaper
         clippings, organizational minutes, notes and other published
         and manuscript materials pertaining to a wide array of Clark's
         political and artistic interests. Among the organizations with
         which Miss Clark worked were the Equal Suffrage League of
         Virginia, the League of Women Voters of Virginia, and the
         Federal Art Project in Virginia. Correspondence, 1916-1940 and
         1926-1939, with Nora Houston (1883-1942) and Willoughby Ions
         (1881-1977) illuminates the relationship between women's
         personal and professional networks and their political
         activities. The correspondence, 1906-1929, of Clark's mother,
         Estelle (Goodman) Clark (1847-1893) with her three daughters
         offers insights into relationships between mothers and their
         adult children. The collection also contains information on
         teaching art history in a variety of contexts, on women's
         suffrage and women's rights, and on other civic and political
         activities.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Adele Clark Papers, 1855-1976 (Mss1 C5472 a FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Adele Clark in 1979. Accessioned 7 July
            1986.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>Adele Clark was a major figure in Richmond's art scene and
         political life for nearly three-quarters of a century. Born in
         Montgomery, Ala., she spent her childhood in New Orleans, La.,
         before moving to Richmond in 1894. Seven years later she
         graduated from the Miss Virginia Randolph Ellen School (now
         St. Catherine's). While working as a stenographer for the
         chamber of commerce, Miss Clark studied art with Lily Logan at
         the Art Club of Richmond. In 1906, Miss Clark received a
         scholarship to the Chase School of Art in New York, where she
         studied under Robert Henri and Kenneth Hays Miller. Shortly
         after her return to Richmond to teach at the Art Club, she
         became involved in the women's suffrage movement.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>This collection begins with the papers of Robert Clark
         (1832?-1906) and his wife, Estelle (Goodman) Clark
         (1847-1937). His papers consist of three letters written by a
         brother Tom Clark and miscellany; hers include correspondence,
         accounts, and miscellany. A folder of her general
         correspondence precedes individual folders of letters with her
         three daughters, Adele Clark, Edith (Clark) Cowles, and
         Gertrude (Clark) Dew, as well as one containing two letters
         from President Franklin Delano Roosevelt. Accounts and letters
         concerning the deaths of two family members follow.</p>
      <p>Correspondence of Edith (Clark) Cowles includes letters
         with her sister, Adele Clark, and illustrator Dugald Stewart
         Walker. Adele Clark (1882-1983) was a major figure in
         Richmond's art society and political life for nearly
         three-quarters of a century. Born Adele Goodman Clark in
         Montgomery, Ala., she spent most of her childhood in New
         Orleans, La., before moving to Richmond in 1894. Seven years
         later Clark graduated from the Miss Virginia Randolph Ellett
         School (now St. Catherine's). While working as a stenographer
         for the chamber of commerce she studied art with Lily Logan at
         the Art Club of Richmond. In 1906, Adele Clark received a
         scholarship to the Chase School of Art in New York where she
         studied under Robert Henri and Kenneth Hays Miller. Shortly
         after her return to Richmond to teach at the Art Club, she
         became involved in the women's suffrage movement</p>
      <p>Adele Clark's papers reflect her varied careers and
         avocations, yet mostly pertain to her personal life and art
         activities. Major collections of her papers documenting her
         work with the Equal Suffrage League, the Virginia League of
         Women Voters, and the U.S. Work Projects Administration have
         been given to the Virginia State Library, the University of
         Virginia, Virginia Commonwealth University, and other
         institutions.</p>
      <p>Adele Clark's papers begin with a section of general
         correspondence, which consists of letters with family members,
         artists, politicians, and suffragists. Among the more
         prominent are: Ella Graham Agnew, Edmund Minor Archer, Harry
         Flood Byrd (1887-1966), Colgate Whitehead Darden, Marion
         Montague Junkin, Elizabeth Dabney (Langhorne) Lewis, Theresa
         Pollak, and Roberta Wellford. Separate folders contain
         correspondence with Richmond artist Nora Houston and artist
         and designer Willoughby Ions, Adele Clark's first cousin.</p>
      <p>Accounts precede financial records, which include materials
         concerning "Swannanoa," the summer home of James Henry Dooley,
         uncle of Nora Houston. Adele Clark was helping the Dooley
         family dispose of this property after the death of Sallie
         (May) Dooley in 1925. A few items documenting Adele Clark's
         brief tenure as acting dean of women at the College of William
         and Mary precede materials concerning her uncle, Edward Samuel
         Goodman, who died in 1931. These include inquiries concerning
         his health, sympathy letters and trust information. Sympathy
         letters concerning the death of Nora Houston, recipes,
         miscellaneous newspaper clippings and personal miscellany
         conclude this section.</p>
      <p>Materials pertaining to Adele Clark's art career and
         political activities are located in box 2. These begin with a
         folder of general art correspondence, arranged alphabetically,
         which mostly consists of portrait requests, commissions,
         inquiries, and letters with miscellaneous art institutions.
         Clark was treasurer and member of the board of directors of
         the Richmond Art Club as well as a student and instructor
         there. A minute book, loose minutes, correspondence, loose
         clippings and a scrapbook of clippings, located with oversized
         materials in box 3, document her affiliation with the club. An
         unsigned appeal from James H. Dooley, the club's president, is
         found among the loose minutes.</p>
      <p>In 1919, Adele Clark and Nora Houston, with whom she shared
         a studio, founded the Virginia League of Fine Arts and
         Handicrafts in an attempt to revive the Chevalier Quesnay de
         Beaurepaire's Academy of Sciences and Fine Arts. This soon
         became the Virginia League of Fine Arts, which merged with the
         Richmond Academy of Arts in 1931. This collection contains a
         copy of the league's constitution, amendments and reports as
         well as a few items of correspondence. Minutes of the board of
         trustees of the Richmond Academy of Arts document the merger
         and the two years following. Lecture notes and student papers
         from the College of William and Mary extension in Richmond
         (Richmond Professional Institute) precede WPA materials. The
         latter mainly consists of letters with Campbell Bascom Slemp
         about the Southwest Virginia Museum at Big Stone Gap, but also
         include a scrapbook, located in box 3, and the transcript of a
         1963 interview.</p>
      <p>From 1941 to 1964, Adele Clark served on the State Art
         Commission, an organization she helped establish in 1916.
         Materials, primarily reports and minutes, span her entire
         affiliation with the commission, but mostly pertain to her
         last three years of service. Materials of the Virginia Society
         for Crippled Children and Adults include correspondence,
         reports and notes on patients and demonstrate Clark's interest
         in using art in rehabilitation. In 1947, a portrait gallery of
         state police officers who died in the line of duty was
         established at state police headquarters in Chesterfield
         County. Adele Clark was commissioned to paint one of these
         portraits. Materials concerning the dedication include
         clippings and a program that contains biographical sketches of
         artists and subjects.</p>
      <p>In 1956, the Richmond Artists Association was founded to
         encourage local appreciation and patronage of contemporary
         art. Among these materials are copies of the constitution,
         by-laws, rosters, and a directory. Materials concerning the
         dedication of the Nora Houston Gallery at St. Paul's School in
         1972 follow. A copy of the dedication address by Edmund Minor
         Archer recounts Nora Houston's contributions to Richmond art.
         Notes and articles, invitations, announcements and exhibition
         information, a visitor's roster to a 1946 exhibition, two
         sketchbooks and loose sketches, and miscellany conclude this
         section.</p>
      <p>The rest of Adele Clark's papers concern her role as a
         political activist. These materials are relatively few in
         number and often individual folders contain only several items
         that span a large date range. For example, the first folder in
         this section contains materials concerning women's rights
         (excluding the League of Women Voters) from 1912 to 1976. This
         material includes correspondence, clippings, notes, and
         miscellany concerning various women's issues from suffrage to
         the Equal Rights Amendment. As previously mentioned Adele
         Clark's Equal Suffrage League and Virginia League of Women
         Voters papers were given to another institution. An index to
         those papers donated to the James Branch Cabell Library at
         Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond follows folders
         on the Richmond and Virginia Leagues. In 1923, the Virginia
         League of Women Voters established the Virginia Women's
         Council of Legislative Chairmen of State Organizations to
         coordinate lobbying efforts among like-minded organizations.
         In the mid-1950's this became the Virginia Council on State
         Legislation. Materials concerning these organizations mainly
         include bulletins and reports. In 1921, Governor E. Lee
         Trinkle appointed Adele Clark to the Commission on
         Simplification of state Government. A few items of
         correspondence, reports and bulletins, mostly from budget
         director LeRoy Hodges, document the commission's work.</p>
      <p>Materials that pertain to Prohibition and the National
         recovery Administration consist almost entirely of newspaper
         clippings. Minutes and resolutions from a meeting on economic
         security held in Richmond on March 7, 1935, with Secretary of
         Labor Frances Perkins precede miscellaneous information
         concerning a variety of labor and racial issues. A transcript
         of an interview (ca. 1920) with an ex-slave from Maryland is
         found with this material. A folder of political miscellany and
         one concerning Adele Clark's activities on behalf of the
         Diocesan Council of Catholic Women conclude Adele Clark's
         papers.</p>
      <p>The papers of Adeline Harmon (Cowles) Cox (1907- ) and
         miscellaneous family items are located at the end of box
         2.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>The papers of Adele Clark are arranged into seven series by
         individual and further subdivided by subject or material
         type.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms:</head>
      <subject>Art and state -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Art -- Study and teaching.</subject>
      <subject>Clark,Adele, 1882-1983.</subject>
      <subject>Clark, Estelle Goodman, 1847-1937.</subject>
      <subject>Equal Suffrage League of Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Federal art Project (Va.)</subject>
      <subject>Houston, Nora, 1883-1942.</subject>
      <subject>Ions, Willoughby, 1881-1977.</subject>
      <subject>League of Women Voters of Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Mothers and daughters.</subject>
      <subject>Richmond(Va.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Suffrage.</subject>
      <subject>Women artists -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Family relationships.</subject>
      <subject>Women in politics -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Women -- Suffrage.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Robert Clark (1832?-1906),
               Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1855; miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Estelle (Goodman) Clark
               (1847-1937), Richmond, Va. 
               <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
               1903-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>General correspondence, 1903-1936; correspondence
               with daughters, 1906-1929; correspondence with Franklin
               Delano Roosevelt, 1933, 1937; accounts, 1928-1930,
               1935-1937;</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Edith (Clark) Cowles
               (1874-1954?), Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1917-1938</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Adele Clark (1882-1983),
               Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.1">General and
                  Financial Materials 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1916-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>General Correspondence, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1918-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence with Nora Houston, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1916-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence with Willoughby Ions, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1926-1939</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Accounts, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1927-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Checking Accounts, 
                     <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1933-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
              <p>1933-1941, 1960-1961</p>
            </scopecontent>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Swannanoa, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1926-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Financial miscellany</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>William and Mary, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Edward Samuel Goodwin, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1927-1941</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Death of Nora Houston, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1942</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Recipes; miscellaneous clippings;
                     personal miscellany,</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.2">Art related
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>General art correspondence, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1922-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Art Club, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1901-1918</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia League of Fine Arts/Richmond
                     Academy, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1920-1935</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia Museum of Fine Arts 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1939-1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Richmond Professional Institute, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>WPA, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1936-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Art Commission, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1942-1964</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia Society for Crippled Children
                     and Adults, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1946-1954</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia Police Gallery, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Richmond Artists Association, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958, 1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Nora Houston Gallery, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1970-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Art notes and articles; art
                     invitations, announcements and exhibit
                     information; register, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Sketchbook and sketches; art clippings
                     and miscellany</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 4.3">Political
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Women's suffrage and women's issues, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1912-1976</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Richmond League of Women Voters, 
                     <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1938-1938,1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia League of Women Voters 
                     <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1923-1942,
                     1963</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Index to league papers at Virginia
                     Commonwealth University.</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Virginia Women's Council of Legislative
                     Chairmen of State</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Organizations?Virginia Council on State
                     Legislation, 
                     <unitdate type="bulk" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1924-1942,
                     1953-1963</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Prohibition 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1929-1932</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>NRA, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1933</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Conference on economic security, 
                     <unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1935</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Labor, racial and political
                     miscellany</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Catholic Church, 
                     <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                     1932-1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Adeline Harmon (Cowles) Cox (1907-),
               Richmond, Va.,</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Family Miscellany</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">2 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence and miscellany</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Oversized materials</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Adele Clark: Art Club scrapbook, 1907-1917; WPA
               scrapbook, 1940; certificates and posters.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
