<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00017">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-partial-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00017::A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00017&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00017::A Guide to
             the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977)//EN"
             "vih00017"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1977</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 W6376 c
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">91 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         VHS staff, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">3 May 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00017::A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers,
            1754-1977)//EN" "vih00017" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002
            by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1754-1977</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 W6326 c
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers,
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1754-1977</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 W6326 c FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">11,500 (ca.) items (51 manuscript
         boxes).</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">The collection includes
         correspondence (some copies), 1778-1799, of attorney John
         Wickham (1763-1839) of Richmond, Va., and extensive materials
         concerning the settlement of his estate (including wills,
         correspondence, financial, land and legal records, and trust
         materials, some involving Robert E. Lee and William Henry
         Fitzhugh Lee). Also contains papers of William Fanning Wickham
         (1793-1880) of "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va., including
         diaries (17 v.), 1828-1880, concerning agricultural
         operations, slave families and runaway slaves, and local
         events during the Civil War and Reconstruction; family
         correspondence, 1817-1878; accounts; land records; and
         materials concerning the emancipation and resettlement in Ohio
         of slaves belonging to the estate of Samuel Gist. Also
         contains letterbooks, 1877-1881, of Williams Carter Wickham
         (1820-1888) as a Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company official
         and Republican Party State Executive Committee chairman;
         correspondence, 1862-1888; financial records; "Hickory Hill"
         farm records; and materials concerning the management of
         "North Wales," Caroline County, Va., for Dr. Charles Carter of
         Philadelphia, Pa. Alsoincludes correspondence, 1848-1913,
         financial records, and estate materials of Lucy Penn (Taylor)
         Wickham (1830-1913); letterbooks, 1931-1940, scrapbooks,
         correspondence, 1874-1941, farm records, and Virginia Senate
         and Democratic Party materials of Henry Taylor Wickham
         (1849-1943) of "Hickory Hill"; correspondence, accounts, farm
         records, and Richmond, Va., rental property records of Elise
         Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham; and miscellaneous records of
         other members of the Wickham and Fanning families.</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977 (Mss1 W6326 c FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Mrs. Credilla B. W. Bordley, Ashland, Va., and
            Lawrence V. M. Wickham, Hanover, Va., in 1987. Accessioned
            22 July 1988.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Wickham family of Richmond and Hanover County, known as
         the "Hickory Hill Wickhams," was founded by the celebrated
         post-Revolutionary attorney John Wickham (1763-1839). This
         collection traces the descendants of Wickham and his first
         wife, Mary Smith Fanning, through the line of his eldest son,
         William Fanning Wickham.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The collection opens with materials of William Fanning
         (1728-1782) of Brunswick and Greensville counties, Va., an
         Anglican clergyman who was both an uncle of John Wickham and
         father of Wickham's first wife. Included are a certificate of
         ordination, 1754, issued to Fanning as a deacon in the Church
         of England (signed by the Bishop of Gloucester and bearing a
         seal of the Bishop of London); a 1781 letter of Fanning to
         Virginia Governor Thomas Nelson (a copy made in 1857)
         concerning John Wickham; and a will probated in Greensville
         County. Early folders also contain notes on the Fanning, Gray,
         Tazewell, and Wickham families (apparently taken from the
         family Bible of Mary (Gray) Tazewell Fanning); and
         correspondence, 1930, of Henry Taylor Wickham with George
         MacLaren Brydon concerning William and Edmund Fanning.</p>
      <p>Series 2 contains papers of Edmund Fanning (1739-1818),
         another of Wickham's uncles who took a particular interest in
         the younger man's education and career. Edmund Fanning pursued
         his own colorful career in colonial administration and
         eventually served as governor of Nova Scotia. His records in
         this collection include correspondence, 1738-ca. 1812, with
         Sir Robert Pigot, John Wickham (concerning Wickham's service
         in the King's American Regiment and as a lawyer in Richmond,
         Va.), and Mary Smith (Fanning) Wickham; letters, 1777-1778
         (copies made in 1873) of Fanning (while serving in the King's
         American Regiment) to James Fanning and Hannah Smith (Fanning)
         Wickham (concerning John Wickham); a prayer, ca. 1788, for the
         governor, council, and assembly of Prince Edward Island,
         Canada; and biographical sketches, ca. 1800-1829.</p>
      <p>Series 3 contains a limited number of John Wickham's own
         personal records survive in Box 1 of this collection. Letters,
         1806, written to Philadelphia merchant David Parish concern
         the personal and financial affairs of entrepreneur David Ross;
         while letters, 1778-1799 (copies of which were made in
         1873-1874) written to John Wickham (1734-1808) and Harriet
         Smith (Fanning) Wickham, John Wickham's parents, describe his
         travels in Europe and practice of law in Richmond, Va.</p>
      <p>John Wickham's land records, 1801-1842, primarily concern
         plantations in Henrico and Goochland counties known as "Middle
         Quarter," "Lower Quarter," and "Ellerslie" and are related to
         his acquisition of the "East Tuckahoe" plantation. These
         papers consist of proceedings, exhibits, decrees, and other
         records from the lawsuit of Wakelyn Welch, surviving partner
         of Robert Cary and Company of London v. the executors of
         Thomas Mann Randolph (a British debt case that concerns in
         part the sale of "Middle Quarter Plantation" and its Negro
         slaves to Wickham in 1800) signed by George Wythe and bearing
         a seal of the Virginia High Court of Chancery; a deed of
         trust, 1838, of Wickham to BenjaminWatkins Leigh and William
         Fanning Wickham for the benefit of John Wickham's children
         (deed covers slaves, cattle, horses, and personal property on
         the plantation); and a newspaper notice, 1842, of the public
         auction of these lands.</p>
      <p>Wickham's miscellany contains a commission, 1782, in the
         King's American Regiment of Foot (signed by George III and
         Thomas Townshend, Viscount Sydney, and bears seal); an
         argument, 1795, of John Wickham (through not in his hand) as
         counsel for the U.S. in the U.S. Circuit Court at Richmond in
         U.S. v. Daniel Lawrence Hylton (concerning the
         constitutionality of the federal carriage tax); a deed of
         trust (copy), 1800 to shares in the Bank of Baltimore for the
         benefit of Mary (Gray) Tazewell Fanning; a statement, ca.
         1820, of the case of John Ponsonby Martin concerning the
         confiscation of the Virginia estate of John Martin by the
         Commonwealth of Virginia in 1779; a student notebook, n.d.,
         used (probably by one of Wickham's children) to practice
         handwriting; lines of verse, 1835, copied from the Southern
         Literary Messenger concerning Wickham's speech before the
         Virginia House of Delegates; and drafts of a biographical
         sketch, 1887, by Williams Carter Wickham.</p>
      <p>The next three boxes (Boxes 2-4) cover the very extensive
         and complicated proceedings over the estate of John Wickham.
         Due to a number of technicalities, Wickham's estate matters
         eventually absorbed the estates of Richmond physician James
         McClurg, his father-in-law, and of several of his children who
         died young, and gave rise to an enormous amount of
         litigation.</p>
      <p>The estate records begin with two copies of Wickham's
         lengthy will, 1839, probated in Richmond. Correspondence,
         1852-1875, of William Fanning Wickham (as surviving executor
         with Benjamin Watkins Leigh) including numerous letters from
         Julia (Wickham) Leigh (concerning family affairs and the U.S.
         Customs House in Richmond), John Wickham (1825-1892) of St.
         Louis, Mo., and John Wickham (1825-1902) of "East Tuckahoe,"
         Henrico County , Va. An account book, 1856-1880, kept by
         William Fanning Wickham bears frequent notes on transactions
         and financial affairs of the estate and on his trusteeship for
         a younger Wickham daughter, Frances (Wickham) Graham. Loose
         accounts cover the period 1848-1863; bonds, 1853-1869.
         Materials concerning land of John Wickham in Kentucky and
         Missouri and of Doctor McClurg in Randolph County [W.Va.] and
         in Kentucky (Folder 5) include correspondence with Joseph
         Rogers Underwood and others and notes of William Fanning
         Wickham. Estate miscellany consists of a petition to and order
         of the Richmond Circuit Court in 1864; materials, 1858,
         concerning Amy (a Negro slave) at Eastern Lunatic Asylum
         (later Eastern State Hospital) in Williamsburg, Va., and notes
         of William Fanning Wickham.Box 4 contains records of a trust
         established by the estate for a granddaughter of John Wickham,
         Charlotte Georgiana Wickham, upon her marriage in 1859 to
         William Henry Fitzhugh Lee. William Fanning Wickham and Robert
         E. Lee served as trustees. Materials include the deed of trust
         (marriage settlement) establishing the trust, signed by all
         the above parties plus Williams Carter (grandfather of the
         bride and her guardian); notes and memoranda of William
         Fanning Wickham, 1858-1868; and an order and receipt,
         1866-1868, of William Henry Fitzhugh Lee concerning shares of
         Virginia 6% state stock (also signed by Robert E. Lee).</p>
      <p>Correspondence of William Fanning Wickham as trustee
         includes numerous communications with Doctor Charles Carter,
         Robert E. Lee, and William Henry Fitzhugh Lee (of "Arlington,"
         "Ravensworth," Fairfax County, and "White House," New Kent
         County). Two bank books and some loose accounts cover the
         period 1854-1867. Materials, 1856-1879, concern lot #502 at
         Grace and Sixth streets in Richmond and #533 at Broad and
         Sixth streets, owned respectively by Maclurg Wickham and W. H.
         F. Lee in the division of the estate of Doctor James McClurg.
         Another group of records, 1861, concern the lot and tenanment
         on Cary Street adjoining the Bank of Richmond, A deed of
         release (copy), 1867, of W. H. F. Lee conveys land in Warwick
         County, Va., received from the estate of Doctor William
         Foushee. Lastly, materials, 1880-1882, concern a lawsuit in
         Richmond Chancery Court of William Henry Fitzhugh Lee v.
         William Carter Wickham (executor of William Fanning Wickham)
         etal. (including correspondence of Wickham and Lee, an answer
         of Wickham, exhibits, receipts, and notes).</p>
      <p>Series 4, containing the personal records of William
         Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) commences with Box 5. A prominent
         attorney of early Richmond like his father, William Fanning
         Wickham retired early to his plantation in Hanover County,
         "Hickory Hill," and devoted the rest of his life to his family
         and to agriculture. He kept a long series of diaries (17
         volumes) beginning in 1828, in which he recorded little of a
         personal nature but much on agricultural operations. weather,
         the sale of produce, plantation life, horse breeding, and
         local affairs. Many of the diaries include lists of Negro
         slaves (with their ages) at"Hickory Hill" and adjoining
         plantations, as well as records of slave births and deaths.
         Some volumes include plats of fields (beginning with volume
         5). Volume 8 covers the Hanover County homefront during the
         Civil War, describing the treatment of slaves and noting
         runaways to the Union Army. It mentions a battle near "Hickory
         Hill" on 27 May 1862 (entry for 31 May), news of campaigns and
         Union raids during the summers of 1862 and 1863, and reports
         on the Spotsylvania Campaign, 14-31 May 1864. Volume XIV
         reports the devastating fire at "Hickory Hill" on 13 February
         1875.Wickham's general correspondence covers the period
         1817-1878 and is generally maintained with family members.
         Letters to Anne Butler (Carter) Wickham and William Carter
         Wickham mostly concern the elder Wickham's trip to Europe in
         1852 (visiting Geneva, London, Paris, and Rome). Other
         correspondents include Doctor Charles Carter of Philadelphia
         (largely concerning the estate of Williams Carter, and "North
         Wales," in Caroline County, letters dated 1865 concern the
         postwar crisis in Virginia), Edmund Fontaine (concerning train
         stops on the Virginia Central Railroad in Hanover County),
         William Cabell Rives, Judith Page (Walker) Rives (concerning
         the death of William Cabell Rives), Littleton Waller Tazewell
         (imperfect), James Maclurg Wikcham (concerning the death of
         George Wickham) and Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham. Letters of
         condolence, sent to William Fanning Wickham upon the death of
         Anne Butler (Carter) Wickham in 1868, also include
         acknowledgements by Wickham (especially to Robert E. Lee) and
         other members of the Carter and Wickham families, and a prayer
         by Wickham.</p>
      <p>Wickham's financial records in Box 7 include accounts,
         1828-1841, 1854-1863, and 1872-1878; a memoranda book of
         stocks, 1853-1861; bonds, 1878, of Wickham to John Henry
         Wickham and Mrs. Maria F. Wickham; and bonds, 1879, with E.
         and S. Wortham, Richmond commission merchants.</p>
      <p>"Hickory Hill" land records cover the acquisition of the
         plantation and adjoining acreage between 1828 and 1878 which
         totaled nearly 3500 acres by the latter date. An 1878 survey
         report, title history, and map give an overview of the gradual
         evolution of the plantation. Folder 1 contains deeds,
         1820-1828, of the heirs of George William Smith to William
         Fanning Wickham and include an agreement, power of attorney,
         and plat. A deed, plat, and survey cover the lands of Doctor
         Josiah Holt. Other records consist of deeds, agreements, and
         plants, 1836-1837, of adjacent lands acquired from the heirs
         of John D. Thilman; plats, notes, and a deed covering the John
         H. Taliaferro lands, 1837-1858; a deed and plats, 1867-1873,
         of land exchanged with Edmund Winston; plats and surveys of
         "Hickory Hill," ca. 1852-1861; miscellaneous adjacent tracts,
         1833-1867; notes of William Fanning Wickham; and a deed, 1880,
         of Wickham to Williams Carter Wickham.</p>
      <p>Folder 2 consists of a report, 1844, concerning a petition
         to build a mill dam t power grist and saw mills; estimated
         values and lists of taxable real and personal property, 1823,
         1852-1864, 1873; records, 1842-1857, concerning the purchase
         of slaves; accounts of expenses of farm operations, 1866-1876;
         and records of the division of the farm into a field system
         for crop rotation, 1871-1878. The next folder concerns "South
         Wales," the largest trace of the "Hickory Hill" plantation.
         Materialsinclude a letter, 1769, of Harry Terrill concerning
         farming operations; a plat, n.d., of a portion of the tract
         between the railroad and the county road; agreements, 1859,
         with the Virginia Central Railroad Company; and a survey and
         plat, n.d., of the Hanover Courthouse Road. Lastly, Folder 4
         concerns "The Lane" (a tract also known as "Lanefield" or
         "Long Lane"). Items include a deed, 1825, of Thomas Nelson
         Carter, deed of trust, agreement, and bond; a bond, 1841, of
         Elizabeth Jacquelin (Ambler) Brent Carrington (with deeds of
         trust and release); a bond, 1843, of Wickham to Littleton
         Waller Tazewell (with deeds of trust and release); and undated
         plats.</p>
      <p>One of the most interesting matters handled by William
         Fanning Wickham as an attorney concerned the estate of Samuel
         Gist (d. 1815), a London merchant. Gist lived in Virginia for
         a number of years but returned to England before the American
         Revolution. During that conflict, the Commonwealth of Virginia
         sought to confiscate his lands and goods but the General
         Assembly was prevailed upon to enact legislation in 1782
         vesting his property in the hands of a daughter Mary (Gist)
         Anderson Pearkes and her first husband, William Anderson. Gist
         continued to receive the profits from his estates after the
         war through his manager in Hanover County, Benjamin Toler, and
         by his will sought to emancipate his slaves and provide for
         their welfare through the sale of property in Goochland
         County. An act of Assembly in 1816 created a trust supervised
         by the Superior Court of Chancery in Richmond to be
         administered until all creditors of the estate were satisfied,
         when funds could be generated from the sale of land and other
         property to benefit the freed slaves, who in turn had to leave
         the Commonwealth. William Fanning Wickham acted as one of the
         trustees from 1817 until 1847 and in 1858-1859 heard from
         members of the Quaker committee devoted to the care of free
         blacks in Ohio, where Gist's slaves finally settled. The whole
         issue was raised again in 1877-1880 by E. Cumberland, one of
         the original freedmen who moved to Ohio and settled on lands
         purchased through funds from the estate but which the blacks
         had no right to alienate themselves.</p>
      <p>Materials from the Gist estate include correspondence of
         William Fanning Wickham as surviving trustee with agents,
         attorneys, former slaves, and Quakers in Ohio (especially
         David Bailey, a former resident of Petersburg, and George
         Carter) during three periods: 1845-1849 (closing the Virginia
         affairs of the trust), 1850-1858 (reports from Ohio Friends),
         and 1870-1880 (the re-establishment of extended claims by
         former Gist slaves and their descendants). General materials
         include loose accounts, 1826-1853; bonds, 1819; records,
         1832-1847, concerning the acquisition of lands in Brown and
         Highland counties, Ohio, and the maintenance of former slaves;
         and a letter (copy) of John Wickham (1763-1839) to John
         Hampden Pleasants concerning his role as one of the original
         trustees.</p>
      <p>Records from supervision of the Gist estate by the Virginia
         Superior Court of Chancery in Richmond (later the Circuit
         Superior Court of Chancery) include memorials to the court,
         decrees, orders, etc., 1845- 1847, and a long series of
         commissioner's reports, 1818-1847. Records of the case
         Archibald Anderson etal. v. Samuel Gist's executors etal.,
         heard by Chief Justice John Marshall in the Fifth U.S. Circuit
         Court for the Virginia District in Richmond (concerning claims
         under the will of William Anderson) consist of an 1824 decree
         of the court, a statement of accounts, notes of argument of
         the opposing counsel (Robert Stanard and Benjamin Watkins
         Leigh), and agreement and bond with Richard Anderson, and
         miscellany (copy of an amended bill of complaint and letter of
         William Fanning Wickham to Chancellor Creed Taylor).</p>
      <p>William Fanning Wickham also served for many years as agent
         or trustee for his younger sister Frances (Wickham) Graham
         after the death of her husband. Records include an account
         book, 1867=1880; loose accounts, 1871-1882; bonds, 1875-1879,
         of John Wickham (1825-1902), Littleton Waller Tazewell
         Wickham, and Maclurg Wickham; agreements, 1874-1878,
         concerning cash advances for her above-named brothers; a
         lease, 1868, to Grubbs and Williams of Richmond to a lot on
         Eleventh Street between Main and Bank streets; and a receipt,
         1881, for payment for buildings erected on that lot. Specific
         materials concerning the indebtedness of John and Littleton
         Waller Tazewell Wickham to Maclurg Wickham are comprised of
         deeds of trust, 1858-1877, to "East Tuckahoe" and "Woodside,"
         Henrico County; a deed of trust (copy) concerning mineral
         rights, 1874, granted to the James River Coal Company; a plat
         of "East Tuckahoe," ca. 1858; and materials of William Fanning
         Wickham concerning John Wickham's bankruptcy proceedings.</p>
      <p>Additional personal records of William Fanning Wickham
         (Boxes 9-10) include pardon materials, 1865 (provost marshal's
         certificate, petition to President Andrew Johnston,
         certificate of the Secretary of State (William Henry Seward),
         and pardon document); notes, charts, and materials collected
         by Wickham concerning the Carter, Fanning, Nelson, Randolph
         and Wickham families (see also general correspondence); and a
         commonplace book, n.d. (early nineteenth century), consisting
         primarily of descriptive and historical notes on England and
         English counties.</p>
      <p>Wickham's miscellany includes a sketch of Benjamin Watkins
         Leigh prepared by William Hamilton Macfarland; a personal
         reminiscence of John Marshall; a commonplace bok, n.d.
         consisting of notes on the U.S. Constitution and
         constitutional history; essay speech, n.d., probably made at
         Hanover Court House concerning reconstruction in Virginia; an
         inventory of personal papers; a letter, 1843, of Thomas Tabb
         Giles to William Daniel (concerning a book in the library at
         "Hickory Hill"); lines of verse; and miscellaneous notes.
         Estate materials consist of a will probated in Hanover County,
         accounts, a letter to the executor (Williams Carter Wickham),
         and bonds.</p>
      <p>Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), a son of William
         Fanning Wickham, trained as a lawyer but abandoned the law
         early to become a planter at "Hickory Hill." He served as a
         local militia officer prior to the Civil War and became a
         cavalry general in the army of Northern Virginia. After the
         war, he surprised neighbors and fellow veterans by joining the
         Republican party, a political organization in which he became
         very influential. For many years a second vice-president of
         the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company, Wickham also served
         in the Virginia Senate, where he opposed the Readjusters. His
         materials are represented in Series 5.</p>
      <p>An important group of three postwar letterbooks
         (letter-press) kept by Williams Carter Wickham survives in
         this collection. Volume I covers the years 1877 to 1880 and is
         largely devoted to personal and business affairs and
         Republican party politics. (Indexes to each of the letterbooks
         have been prepared by VHS staff members and are filed with the
         appropriate volumes.) Among the individuals to whom Wickham
         addresses letters in this volume are Robert Rufus Bridgers,
         Doctor Charles Carter (of Philadelphia, concerning the estate
         of Williams Carter and "North Wales," Caroline County, VA),
         John Echols, Charles Meriwether Fry (concerning the Chesapeake
         Coal Company of New York), President Rutherford B. Hayes,
         Virginia Governor Frederick William Mackey Holliday, Collis
         Potter Huntington, Hugh McCullock, William Snead Oakey (of
         Salem, Va.), Doctor Thomas Pollard (concerning the use of marl
         at "Hickory Hill"), John Warren Porter (of the Charlottesville
         Republican), George William Richardson (concerning the sale of
         "Oakland," Hanover County, Va.), William Lawrence Royall,
         James Beverley Sener, U. S. Treasury secretary John Sherman,
         Samuel M. Yost (a Republican party associate), Haxall-Crenshaw
         Company of Richmond, and the Richmond Whig.</p>
      <p>Letterbook II (1880-1881) also concerns Wickham's personal
         and business affairs, some relating to the C. and O. Railroad,
         plantation operations and agricultural production, Republican
         party activities, and St. Paul's Church in Hanover County (see
         especially letters to Bickerton Lyle Winston). Among the
         addressees are Chester A. Arthur, James G. Blaine, Doctor
         Charles Carter, Robert Randolph Carter, John Callaghan (of
         Norfolk), Charles Meriwether Fry, Philip Haxall (as president
         of Haxall-Crenshaw Company, Richmond), Collis Potter
         Huntington (concerning William Lawrence Royall [p. 7] and
         artist John Adams Elder [p.2651], William Henry Fitzhugh Lee,
         Conway Robinson (concerning the trial of Aaron Burr, a dinner
         for Burr hosted by John Wickham and attended by Chief Justice
         John Marshall, and Benjamin Watkins Leigh), George William
         Richardson, James Beverley Sener, Henry Taylor, and Samuel M.
         Yost.</p>
      <p>Finally, Volume III (also 1880-1881) was kept as chairman
         of the Republican State Executive Committee, concerns
         activities of the Central Committee and the Republican State
         Convention in Lynchburg in August 1881, and includes letters
         written to Republican leaders throughout Virginia, especially
         concerning the presidential election of 1880 and state
         elections in 1881. Among the addressees are John Callaghan,
         President James A. Garfield, Doctor Joseph Jorgenson, John
         Singleton Mosby, Arthur Alexander Spitzer, J. B. Work, and
         Samuel M. Yost.</p>
      <p>General Wickham's correspondence, 1862-1888, covers any of
         the same subjects as do his letterbooks, with the addition of
         letters concerning the offer of the post of Secretary of the
         Navy to Wickham in the administration of James A. Garfield in
         1880 and Wickham's own efforts to acquire information on his
         ancestors. Prominent correspondents include Cornelius Clarke
         Baldwin (concerning Joseph Glover Baldwin and Benjamin Watkins
         Leigh), Doctor Charles Carter, Judge Robert William Hughes,
         Collis Potter Huntington, Henry Brainered McClellan
         (concerning James Breathed, Wickham's service as colonel of
         the 4th Virginia Cavalry Regiment, and Jeb Stuart's raid into
         Pennsylvania in 1862), George William Richardson, Thomas
         Lafayette Rosser (concerning cavalry in the Confederate State
         Army), David Watson Taylor, and Doctor Thomas Fanning Wood (of
         Wilmington, N.C., enclosing a manuscript history of the Wood,
         Fanning, and Coffin families).</p>
      <p>Box 12 contains eleven volumes of Wickham's personal
         account books, 1875-1885, and an account book covering
         "household expenses at Hickory Hill." Loose accounts are
         scattered, but cover 1861, 1868-1888, and are heaviest in the
         years 1873-1879. Many of these accounts relate to farming,
         shipping of goods, construction of the mansion at "Hickory
         Hill," and furnishing the house.</p>
      <p>The "Hickory Hill" farm materials begin with 15 volumes of
         "farm books," 1866-1888, which bear records of expenditures
         and receipts, as well as accounts with individual laborers,
         managers, and timbermen. Loose materials, 1871-1888, include 2
         folders of records concerning the purchase of adjacent lands
         added to the "Hickory Hill" tract; a lease to "Knapp's" in
         Hanover County for conducting an egg and poultry business; an
         agreement concerning the care of sheep; materials concerning
         the construction of a stable and barn; insurance policies; a
         written plan for farm operations; measurements for carpeting
         several rooms in the mansion house; notes on the division of
         fields for crop rotation; notes and accounts concerning farm
         laborers; and miscellany.</p>
      <p>Box 16 is wholly devoted to materials, 1867-1887,
         concerning "North Wales," a plantation across the Pamunkey
         river in Caroline County that Williams Carter Wickham managed
         for his cousin, Doctor Charles Carter of Philadelphia. Initial
         materials include a deed of William Carter, William Fanning
         Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham (all as executors and
         trustees of the estate of Williams Carter [d. 1864]) to
         Charles Carter; a lease to John H. Allen, an agreement
         concerning a debt owed by Allen's estate, and a letter of Mrs.
         N. V. Allen to William Fanning Wickham; a letter of E. and S.
         Wortham of Richmond to doctor Carter; an agreement of Williams
         Carter Wickham with John C. Allen as overseer; an appraisal of
         livestock; a map of 1878; and a lease to Williams Carter
         Wickham in 1882. Farm books (3 volumes) cover the period
         1878-1886, while loose accounts date from the years 1877-1879.
         Miscellaneous items include shipping records (corn); notes on
         plantation operations and field divisions for crop rotation;
         and inventories of stock and equipment.</p>
      <p>The next box (17) of Wickham's papers concerns the estate
         of Margaret William Tryon (Fanning) Cumberland of Enham Lodge,
         Leamington, Eng., a sister of Wickham's grandmother Mary Smith
         (Fanning) Wickham. These materials, 1880-1888, concern Mrs.
         Cumberland's bequest of personal items to Wickham. Documents
         that survive include correspondence of Wickham with Mrs.
         Cumberland, Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, and London
         attorney William Ford, executor of Mrs. Cumberland's estate. A
         folder contains notes on the Fanning family; a copy of an
         autobiographical "statement" of Edmund Fanning; and
         biographical notes made by Maria Fanning. Another folder
         contains a sketch of a window of Lillington Church,
         Warwickshire, Eng., memorializing Lt. Col. Bentinck Harry
         Cumberland; materials concerning Fanning Grammar School,
         Malpeque, Prince Edward Island, Canada; notes on silver plate
         and jewelry; and a memorandum of assets of the estate.</p>
      <p>Wickham followed his father as a trustee for Frances
         (Wickham) Graham, who came to live at "Hickory Hill." Acting
         with Maclurg Wickham over the years 1880-1888, Wickham
         maintained a few items of correspondence, accounts (including
         contributions to the salary of Sewall Stavely Hepbron as a
         rector of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hanover County), and
         records of financial advances to John Wickham (1825- 1902) and
         Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham.</p>
      <p>Williams Carter Wickham also served as a trustee under a
         marriage agreement between George Harrison Byrd of Baltimore
         and Lucy Carter Wickham, one of Wickham's nieces. The records
         of this trusteeship, 1857- 1892, include correspondence with
         Byrd, accounts, and a release issued to the estate of Williams
         Carter Wickham. Materials, 1876-1889, cover Wickham's
         activities as trustee for Reverend Edmund Wilcox Hubard and
         his wife Julia Leiper Taylor (a sister of Wickham's wife,
         Lucy). These consist of correspondence with the Hubards (of
         Bedford an Rappahannock counties, Va.), Henry Taylor, and
         William Penn Taylor; accounts and receipts; a memoranda
         concerning title to land in Richmond, Va.; orders of the
         Westmoreland County Court; and letters to Henry Taylor Wickham
         as executor of Williams Carter Wickham.</p>
      <p>There follow materials concerning Wickham's years of
         service with the C. and O. Railway, 1872-1888. Items
         concerning the Central Land Company of West Virginia include
         an agreement of John and Daniel Kerr Stewart regarding lands
         in Virginia, West Virginia, and Ohio purchased by Collis
         Potter Huntington and his associates under contract with the
         C. and O.; a letter of Daniel Kerr Stewart; and accounts. Some
         records cover Wickham's post as receiver and consist largely
         of newspaper clippings, a letter to the committee for
         reorganization, and an agreement. Another agreement concerns
         fences along Wickham's property in Hanover County. Lastly,
         miscellany includes accounts and complimentary tickets from
         the Richmond City Railway Company.</p>
      <p>Some loose Republican party materials, 1881-1887, include
         newspaper clippings concerning Virginia Senator William
         Mahone; an invitation issued to Wickham by the U.S. State
         Department; a petition from Hanover County voters encouraging
         Wickham to retain his seat in the Virginia Senate; and a
         letter of William Fanning Wickham [1860-1900] to Ann Carter
         (Wickham) Rensaw Byerly concerning General Wickham's political
         career. Miscellaneous land records, 1876-1878, consist of a
         deed to land in Hanover County owed by E. F. Baker; insurance
         policies on a lot and house on Cedar Street in Richmond,
         "Oakland," Hanover County, and the Episcopal parsonage of St.
         Paul's Parish, Hanover County, Va.</p>
      <p>General Wickham's personal miscellany is comprised of a
         broadside, 1861, as a Virginia state senator for Hanover and
         Henrico counties concerning the Virginia Secession Convention;
         a certificate of election, 1863, to the Confederate States
         Congress (signed by George Wythe Munford); a code book, n.d.,
         used for messages between Wickham and C. T. Dabney; a stock
         certificate, 1886, for 100 shares in Spring Valley Gold Mining
         Company of California; a contract, 1887, for enclosing the
         Wickham family section in Shockoe Hill Cemetery in Richmond;
         and a letter, 1882, of Henry Hall of the New York Tribune to
         John Page. Wickham's estate materials include a copy of his
         will probated in Hanover County; telegrams of condolence sent
         to Lucy Penn (Taylor ) Wickham and Henry Taylor Wickham (many
         from his railroad associates and fellow veterans like Collis
         Potter Huntington andFitzhugh Lee); a letter from Virginia L.
         Nelson; a biographical sketch of Wickham and memoranda of his
         Civil War service; resolutions of respect and tribute; and
         obituary notices and newspaper editorials.</p>
      <p>Williams Carter Wickham married Lucy Penn Taylor in 1848
         and they lived at "Hickory Hill." Mrs. Wickham's papers, in
         Series 6, include several dozen early letters, 1848-1866, she
         wrote to Elizabeth (Kane) Shields, daughter of Judge John
         Kintzing Kane of Philadelphia and sister of Arctic explorer
         Elisha Kent Kane and Thomas Leiper Kane (all of whom are
         mentioned in the letters, along with notes of William Fanning
         Wickham). Mrs. Wickham's correspondence, 1888-1913, is
         primarily with Henry Taylor and Henry Taylor Wickham, in part
         concerning "Hickory Hill." Her accounts sporadically cover the
         period 1875-1913, along with personal property tax returns,
         1893-1909. Correspondence, 1902, of Henry Taylor Wickham
         concerns his mother's purchase of shares in the Chesapeake
         Land and Improvement Company of Richmond. Her collected
         genealogical notes concern the Hubard, Leiper, Pendleton, and
         Taylor families.</p>
      <p>Two folders of Mrs. Wickham's personal papers concern the
         estate of her father, Henry Taylor of "Belvidera,"
         Spotsylvania County, Va. These materials, 1853-1921, are made
         up of a letter of Taylor to Mrs. Wickham; copies of Taylor's
         will; a memorandum and notes of Henry Taylor Wickham;
         materials concerning Julia Leiper (Taylor Hubard v. Henry
         Taylor's administrator in the Westmoreland County Court
         (1864-1866) and Julia Leiper (Taylor) Hubard v. Henry Taylor
         etal. in the Westmoreland County Circuit Court. Materials
         regarding a trust created for the benefit of Lucy Penn
         (Taylor) Wickham consist of the appointment by Julia Dunlap
         (Leiper) Taylor and William Penn Taylor of William Fanning
         Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham as trustees; decrees and a
         report to the Westmoreland County Circuit Court in William
         Carter Wickham etal. v. Henry Taylor's executors etal.; a deed
         of trust and release of Henry Taylor to "Leeds Farm,"
         Westmoreland County; extracts from the records of the Circuit
         Court for Spotsylvania County; and proceedings in Rosa V.
         Taylor v. Henry Taylor etal. in Spotsylvania Circuit
         Court.</p>
      <p>Five folders of documents concern the estate of Lucy Penn
         (Taylor) Wickham, 1913-1915. These include copies of her
         numerous wills; a legal opinion of Hill Carter; inventories;
         correspondence and accounts of the executors. One folder
         contains records from Henry Taylor Wickham etal. v. Stuart Lee
         Dance, as guardian of the children of William Fanning Wickham
         (1860-1900) in the Hanover County Circuit Court (bill of
         complaint and exhibits; motions and decrees; depositions;
         accounts; notes; petitions for appeal to the Virginia Supreme
         Court of Appeals). "Hickory Hill" materials are comprised of a
         lease to Henry Taylor Wickham, 1892; financial records of
         William Fanning Wickham's (1860-1900) management of the farm;
         deeds of the heirs of Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham (Ann Carter
         (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, Williams Carter Wickham Renshaw, and
         Williams Carter Wickham [1887-1985]); and a deed and agreement
         concerning sale of a portion of "Prospect Hill," adjoining
         "The Lane," to C. P. Cardwell, and access to a road called
         "The Boulevard" in Hanover County. Estate miscellany consists
         of materials concerning a debt of Sol L. Bloomberg, a
         memorandum and notes of Henry Taylor Wickham, and obituary
         notices.</p>
      <p>Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), eldest child of Williams
         Carter Wickham and Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham, also trained as
         an attorney and practiced for many years in Hanover County and
         Richmond. He was long- time general counsel for the Chesapeake
         and Ohio Railway Company. Henry Wickham's papers begin with a
         series of six letterbooks, 1931-1940, kept at his office in
         the First National Bank Building in Richmond. They cover
         personal business and family affairs, Democratic party
         politics, Wickham's lengthy career in the Virginia Senate, his
         law practice, and his activities as a member of the
         Westmoreland Club and supporter of the Richmond Community
         Fund. Reminiscences of the Civil War service of Williams
         Carter Wickham are sprinkled throughout these volumes. His
         papers make up Series 7.</p>
      <p>Along with numerous family members, addressees (indexed in
         each letterbook by Wickham himself) include Matthew Page
         Andrews (beginning in vol. IV), Leon Maurice Nelson Bazile
         (begin vol. V), Harry Flood Byrd, William Duval Cardwell,
         Herbert Fitzpatrick McCall Frazier, Carter Glass, Newton Lewis
         Hall (as farm manger of "Hickory Hill"), George P. Lyon,
         Andrew Jackson Montague, Rosewell Page, George C. Peery, John
         Garland Pollard, Absalom Willis Robertson, William H. Shelton,
         Cornelius T. Smith, Claude Augustus Swanson, and William
         Munford Tuck (beginning vol. V), and the Richmond real estate
         management firms of Elam and Funsten, Charles A. Rose Co., and
         Morton G. Thalhimer, Inc.</p>
      <p>Henry Taylor Wickham's loose correspondence, 1874-1941, is
         largely personal, directed mostly to family members, although
         some items concern his business affairs. A good number are
         letters of condolence on the death of Williams Carter Wickham
         (1820-1888). Among the more frequent or significant
         correspondents are Alice (Carter) Bransford (of "Shirley,"
         Charles City County, Va.), Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw
         Byerly, William Anderson Glasgow (enclosing a typescript copy
         of a memoir by Frederick Johnston and letters, 1814-1815, of
         John Randolph of Roanoke and Custis Lee, Mildred Childe Lee,
         Robert Henry Renshaw, George Barksdale Wickham (while
         attending Virginia Military Institute,, Lexington), Williams
         Carter Wickham (1887-1985), and Eleanor Landis (Porcher)
         Windle (enclosing a typescript copy of a letter of Anne Butler
         (Carter) Wickham concerning the capture of William Henry
         Fitzhugh Lee at "Hickory Hill" by Union forces in 1863).</p>
      <p>An account book, 1867-1870, of Henry Taylor Wickham covers
         his student days at Washington College (now Washington and Lee
         University) in Lexington and at the University of Virginia,
         and includes lists of law books and lines of verse written by
         Wickham. Along with an account book, 1942, two passbooks,
         1915-1926, and a check stub book, 1922-1926, financial records
         also include loose accounts, 1920-1939 (mostly consisting of
         canceled checks before 1931).</p>
      <p>Box 26 contains materials relating to several real estate
         properties managed for Wickham in the 1930s by Elam and
         Funsten and by Charles A. Rose Co. (1309 East Cary Street, 13
         North Governor Street, and 1333 West Broad Street).</p>
      <p>"Hickory Hill" materials fill more than three boxes
         (17-30). Beginning with four volumes of farm books, 1893-1913,
         that record wages paid to laborers, general farm accounts, and
         records of agricultural operations, these materials likewise
         include loose farm records and accounts, 1929-1943, consisting
         in part of time sheets, payrolls and produce statements. A few
         additional loose items cover agricultural operations in
         1894-1898; records collected by Wickham of the southern
         boundary of "Hickory Hill," "South Wales," the "Lane Island"
         (formed from a portion of "The Lane" by the changing course of
         the Pamunkey river), and land belonging to the estate of
         Christopher Wingfield, consisting primarily of plats, surveys
         correspondence, and notes (most dated between 1908-1915); and
         contracts, 1927-1942, with Newton Lewis Hall as farm
         manager.</p>
      <p>Some loose items concerning Wickham's college days include
         certificates and diplomas, 1867-1868, issued by Washington
         College (all signed by Robert E. Lee and various faculty
         members); a membership certificate in the alumni association
         signed by John Echols, Samuel H. Letcher, and others); a
         diploma issued by the University of Virginia, 1870, as
         Bachelor of Law (signed by Socrates Maupin, John Barbee Minor,
         and others); and an honorary doctor of laws degree conferred
         by Washington and Lee University, 1935.</p>
      <p>Records concerning Wickham's lengthy career in the Virginia
         Senate range widely. They include vote totals in Hanover and
         Caroline counties for elections held in 1899 and 1907;
         certificates of election, 1923- 1939; a transcript of a
         newspaper clipping, 1906, concerning Thomas Staples Martin;
         clippings concerning members of the Bryan family, the Richmond
         Times-Dispatch, and alleged legislative corruption, 1913;
         certificates concerning election expenditures, 1935; materials
         concerning the primary and general elections of 1939;
         materials, 1934, concerning a proposal to alter Hanover
         County's form of government to a "county executive" system
         (newspaper clippings, notes and a letter of Dr. Early Lee Fox
         of Randolph-Macon College, Ashland); and a joint resolution,
         1942, of the Virginia General Assembly concerning Henry Taylor
         Wickham.</p>
      <p>Many of Mr. Wickham's speeches over the year survive in his
         personal papers. Some loose items, 1935-1942, primarily
         concern Democratic party politics and historical subjects in
         Virginia (such as Patrick Henry's political career and college
         life at Washington and Lee University under Robert E. Lee).
         Many more items are bound together in three volumes of
         speeches and addresses (Box 31), including a number of items
         written by or about Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888). For
         examply, in Volume I (1860-1926) there are remarks made by
         Williams Carter Wickham at a meeting of citizens at Henrico
         courthouse, 3 December 1860, concerning instructions from
         electors on his course in the Virginia Senate (no. 1); an
         address of Williams Carter Wickham, ca. 1860, concerning a
         call to the U.S. Congress for a convention to amend the U.S.
         Constitution (no. 2); a speech of Andrew Jackson Montague,
         1926, concerning Williams Carter Wickham (no. 16); numerous
         addresses of Henry Taylor Wickham to literary societies,
         veterans' groups, and local celebrations and commemorations
         (such as the unveiling of portraits at Hanover Court House in
         1926, with biographical sketches of Henry Rose Carter, George
         Pitman Haw, John Enoch Mason, John Robert Taylor, and others).
         The remaining two volumes include the following: Volume II
         (1901-1937): addresses of Henry Taylor Wickham to the League
         of Women Voters and local woman's clubs, and as president of
         the Patrick Henry Centennial Association; an 1858 manuscript
         roll of the Hanover Dragoons (later Company G of the 4th
         Virginia Cavalry Regiment, C.S.A., commanded by Williams
         Carter Wickham); and biographical sketches of James Churchill
         Cooke, William Brockenbrough Newton, Samuel Cornelius Redd,
         and Thomas White Sydnor; and Volume III (1888-1938): primarily
         political campaign speeches of Henry Taylor Wickham;
         recollections of Robert E. Lee; and addresses to local
         Confederate veterans' associations.</p>
      <p>Boxes 32 through 37 contain 12 volumes of scrapbooks
         assembled and indexed by Henry Taylor Wickham, 1867-1943. Each
         is listed separately below, with a brief reference to general
         and/or outstanding contents:</p>
      <p>Scrapbook I (1867-1932): mostly newspaper clippings
         concerning Republican party politics; orations and speeches of
         Henry Taylor Wickham; Funders-Readjusters in Virginia; John
         Sergeant Wise (pp. 6-10); Williams Carter Wickham (pp. 12-30,
         40-76); obituary notice of Williams Carter Wickham (p. 39);
         and broadsides, 1867-1886, of Williams Carter Wickham issued
         to voters of Hanover and Henrico counties (pp. 17, 70,
         72).</p>
      <p>Scrapbook II (1888-1936): largely concerns the death of
         Williams Carter Wickham and the monument erected in Monroe
         Park, by Edmund Virginius Valentine; Hanover Troop Association
         reunions.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook III (1888-1905): election campaigns and service
         of Henry Taylor Wickham in the Virginia Senate, especially as
         chairman of the senate finance committee and president pro
         tem; broadside to voters (pp. 5- 6); Democratic party
         politics; the Virginia Debt Commission (concerning West
         Virginia's portion of the Virginia state debt).</p>
      <p>Scrapbook IV (1905-1923): Henry Taylor Wickham's Virginia
         senate career and elections; letter of Thomas Staples Martin
         to Wickham, 1906 (p. 5); newspaper clippings and magazine
         articles concerning historical subjects and railroad
         business.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook V (1923-1930): Virginia Senate career; historical
         celebrations in Hanover County; obituary notices of Admiral
         James Harrison Oliver of "Shirley," Charles City County, Va.
         (pp. 75-77); letter of Harry Flood Byrd to Wickham, 1929 (p.
         92).</p>
      <p>Scrapbook VI (1930-1934): Wickham's memoir of Judge Edmund
         Waddill (pp. 39-41); reports and speech of Wickham concerning
         the bust of Patrick Henry placed in the hall of the Virginia
         House of Delegates, 1932 (pp. 52ff); letter of Douglas
         Southall Freeman to Wickham, 1934 (p. 90).</p>
      <p>Scrapbook VII (1934-1937): local legislative issues;
         letters of Francis Pendleton Gaines of Washington and Lee
         University (pp. 12, 24), and William Thomas Reed (pp. 20-21,
         concerning "Rocky Mills," Hanover County); two letters of
         Harry Flood Byrd (p. 94); activities as president of the
         Patrick Henry Bicentennial Association; texts of some speeches
         included.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook VIII (1883-1937): Henry Taylor Wickham's career
         and speeches; broadside of Williams Carter Wickham, 1883; many
         clippings about Virginia Chesterman Wickham, Richmond
         socialite.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook IX (1937-1938): Virginia Senate service and
         Democratic politics.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook X (1939-1940): Virginia Senate career; some
         speeches; correspondence tipped in: R. Walton Moore (15
         September 1939), Robert Kincaid Brock (1 June 1939), Harry
         Flood Byrd (28 February 1940), Carter Class (March 1940).</p>
      <p>Scrapbook XI (1940-1942): Virginia Senate career.</p>
      <p>Scrapbook XII (1942-1943): letter of Harry Floor Byrd (30
         November 1942); death of Henry Taylor Wickham in March
         1943.</p>
      <p>Records from the law practice of Henry Taylor Wickham date
         mostly from the later years of his career. These include
         materials concerning Wickham's association with the C. and O.
         Railway Company, 1889-1935; license applications and fees,
         1931-1933; updated law notes; records from Henrico County
         Board of Supervisors v. J. B. Bourne etal., 1934, in the
         Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals; and a certificate of
         incorporation (typescript copy), 1919, of the Richmond Gas and
         Electric Appliance Company (including George Barksdale Wickham
         as an officer).</p>
      <p>Wickham's land and tax records consist of a deed
         (typescript), 1890, to lot 590 on Grace Street in Richmond; a
         deed (unexecuted), 1916, to land in Hanover County; personal
         property tax forms, 1899-1909; a title insurance policy, 1938,
         covering the Boulevard Apartments, 225 North Boulevard, in
         Richmond; and a petition (typescript copy), ca. 1920 in Henry
         Taylor Wickham v. Commonwealth of Virginia in the Hanover
         County Circuit Court (concerning personal property and income
         taxes).</p>
      <p>Wickham saved a large number of newspaper clippings that
         cover his legal and political career, Confederate military
         history, and local history in Caroline and Hanover counties
         and the City of Richmond. He also collected notes and records
         on the following families: Barksdale, Carter, Fanning, Leiper,
         Penn, Taylor, and Wickham. His general miscellany, finally,
         includes cards, notes, telegrams, etc., concerning the
         Wickhams' 50th wedding anniversary in 1935; a power of
         attorney, 1938, concerning the Social security Act; newspaper
         clippings and an eulogy by Wickham at the funeral of Rosewell
         Page; historical notes on the Blair family of Virginia; notes
         concerning visitors to the While Sulphur Springs, W.Va., in
         1875 (identified in an accompanying photograph); a letter
         (copy), 1926, of Judge Jake Fisher of Braxton County, W.Va.,
         to Herbert Fitzpatrick concerning a Michael Miley photograph
         of Robert E. Lee; lists of books; and miscellaneous notes and
         lines of verse.</p>
      <p>Wickham's estate records fill seven folders in Boxes 38-39/
         They begin with obituary notices, resolutions, and memorial
         tributes, and certificates of death and probate. Much of the
         correspondence of the estate, handled by the widow, Elise
         Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham, and Richmond attorney R. Grayson
         Dashiell, is directed to Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985).
         Financial records include loose accounts, 1943-1944, an
         account book and account statements rom the Savings Bank and
         Trust Company in Richmond, and a check stub book. Tax forms
         and receipts for the years 1940-1944 follow.</p>
      <p>Records of rental properties in Richmond managed by Charles
         A. Rose Co. (225 North Boulevard, 721 West Broad Street, 1333
         West Broad Street, and 2711 Hanover Avenue) and by Elam and
         Funsten (1309 East Cary Street, 13 North Governor Street)
         appear in folders 5-6. Lastly, estate miscellany is comprised
         of correspondence and an application for widow's benefits
         filed with the Railroad Retirement Board, 1947; and an
         agreement with Hill Carter concerning timber on "Loblolly
         Hill," in Hanover County, a portion of the Wickham farm.</p>
      <p>Series 8 concerns Elise Warwick Barksdale (1861-1952), who
         married Herny Taylor Wickham in 1885 and lived at "Hickory
         Hill." Her correspondence includes one letter to her father
         dated 1869, and numerous items of communication with family
         members, 1896-1948. Some are written or received as a member
         of the Board of Managers or as president of the Exchange for
         Woman's Work in Richmond, Va. Many letters are written by
         George Barksdale Wickham (while attending Virginia Military
         Institute, Lexington) and Williams Carter Wickham ([1887-1985]
         while serving in the U.S. Navy), while a letter from Doctor
         George Ainsley Barksdale itself bears a letter of Margaret
         (Branch) Glasgow written at Summer Rest resort in Greenwood,
         VA.</p>
      <p>Financial records (boxes 41-42) consist of loose accounts
         (including numerous canceled checks), 1902-1936, three
         passbooks on Richmond banks, 1891-1919, and seven check stub
         books, 1896-1923. Bank statements and canceled checks from
         1948-1950 are filed separately. State and federal income and
         personal property tax forms and returns, 1941-1951,
         follow.</p>
      <p>Farm records at "Hickory Hill" are quite similar to those
         kept by Henry Taylor Wickham and consist of time sheets,
         payrolls, produce statements, records of expenditures, and
         loose accounts arranged by year. Records (including some lease
         agreements) of investment properties in Richmond managed for
         Mrs. Wickham by Charles A. Rose Co. in the years 1932,
         1942-1945, and 1947-1950, cover income and disbursements for
         rental properties at 1517-21 West Broad Street, 613-15 North
         Lombardy Street, 721-23 West Broad Street, 225 North
         Boulevard, 1319-23 West Broad Street, 1333 West Broad Street,
         and 2711 Hanover Avenue. Those managed by Elam and Funsten
         were located at 1309 East Cary Street, 13 North Governor
         Street, 1417-23 East Cary street, 1301 East Main Street, and
         124-30 Virginia Street. Morton G. Thalhimer, Inc., managed the
         properties at 1319 West Broad Street in 1932 and in
         1947-1950.Box 47 contains some miscellaneous items of members
         of the Barksdale and Warwick families. Mrs. Wickham's
         ancestors. An account, 1859, of Abraham Warwick with Hunt and
         Roskell of London bears a draft of a letter of Warwick to that
         firm, dated 19 November 1860, concerning the unsettled
         political situation in the American South. A letter of Robert
         E. Lee, dated 1 June 1866, to Elise Florence (Warwick)
         Barksdale has been indexed elsewhere. These miscellaneous
         items also include passports, 1810 and 1854, issued to William
         Jones Barksdale by William Pinkney (as American minister to
         great Britain) and William Learned Marcy (as U.S. secretary of
         state). Newspaper clippings collected by Doctor George Ainsley
         Barksdale primarily concern Virginia and Confederate military
         history, while the doctor's scrapbook, 1889-1892, includes a
         pardon signed by Andrew Johnson and William Henry Seward (p.
         15), as well as autograph notes (taken from official C.S.A.
         documents) of Fitzhugh Lee, John Letcher, James Alexander
         Seddon, Walter Herron Taylor, and John Withers (p. 92). The
         scrapbook if filed oversize after Box 47.</p>
      <p>Box 48 contains records of the distribution of land at
         "Brookfield," Henrico County, VA., to the heirs of Abraham (or
         Abram) Warwick, including a portion of adjoining land that was
         developed in 1925 as "Lakeside Terrace." Materials include
         bills of complaint, answers, proceedings, decrees, memoranda,
         plats, leases, deeds, and notes and correspondence of Henry
         Taylor Wickham in the related cases of Eliza Agnes (Hayes)
         Warwick (widow of Abram Warwick v. Peter C. Warwick etal. and
         Caroline Warwick v. Elise Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham
         etal.</p>
      <p>Mrs. Wickham kept records as an officer of the Ladies' Aid
         Society of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hanover County from
         1893 to 1916. The organization raised funds for building
         projects, mission activities, and to supplement the salary of
         their rector. These records are a few items of correspondence;
         an account book, 1893, which includes lists of members; a bank
         pass book, 1893-1894; loose accounts; resolutions of the
         vestry; and notes.</p>
      <p>A visitors'' register, 1930-1961, records the sojourn of
         guests at "Hickory Hill" and includes the signatures of
         Admiral William Fredericks Halsey (25 Sept. 1938, 29 July
         1942, 14 Nov. 1946, 27 Jan. 1950, and 22 April 1950) and
         William Munford Tuck (15 April 1939). Mrs. Wickham made many
         diary-like entries in this volume through these years. Another
         visitors' register, 1949, was kept on behalf of the Ashland
         Branch of the Garden Club of Virginia. Miscellany includes a
         membership certificate, 1896, in the Virginia Society of the
         Colonial Dames of America; a life membership certificate
         issued in 1909 by the Association for the Preservation of
         Virginia Antiquities; newspaper clippings concerning the
         Wickham and Barksdale families and "Hickory Hill"; and notes,
         recipes and lines of verse. Letters, cards and telegrams of
         condolence sent to Williams Carter Wickham on his mother's
         death in 1952 complete Box 48.</p>
      <p>Series 9 contains materials relating to Henry Taylor
         Wickham's brother, William Fanning Wickham (1860-1900), who
         trained to be an attorney and lived for many years at "Hickory
         Hill." His records surviving in this collection include
         materials concerning the Hanover Troop (Troop D of the 1st
         Cavalry Battalion of Virginia Volunteers) consisting of
         letters (including one from Governor Fitzhugh Lee, 19 July)
         written to Wickham in 1889, many enclosing bills of lading for
         military supplies; and oaths of allegiance subscribed to by
         officers and men of the unit. Wickham's personal miscellany
         includes two items of correspondence, 1874; loose accounts,
         1877 and 1889; notes and records concerning "Hickory Hill"
         farm, 1886-1888; and materials, 1900, concerning his
         estate.</p>
      <p>Henry and William Wickham's sister, Ann Carter (Wickham)
         Renshaw Byerly appears throughout the collection, but in
         Series 10 are gathered only a small number of letters,
         1869-1888, written to her by Eleanor Agnes Lee, Mary Anna
         Randolph (Custis) Lee, and William Henry Fitzhugh Lee.</p>
      <p>Series 11 contains the papers of Williams Carter Wickham
         (1887-1985), son of Henry Taylor and Elise Wickham and the
         last major character to appear in this collection. He attended
         the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Md., and served for many
         years in the U.S. Navy. During the Second World War he was
         hospitalized in Denver, Colo., and later Bethesda, Md., and
         retired on disability in 1945 after reaching the rank of
         captain.</p>
      <p>Captain Wickham's correspondence, 1897-1967, includes
         communications from Harry Flood Byrd, Richmond attorney
         Randolph Grayson Dashiell, Admiral William Frederick Halsey,
         and Wickham's wife, Credilla (Miller) Wickham. Records of his
         naval service consist of a letter (copy), 1940, of Doctor
         George Ben Johnston concerning Wickham's physical condition;
         grade records, 1907, and certificates of graduation, 1909,
         1911, from the U.S. Naval Academy; commissions (some signed by
         Claude Augustus Swanson, William Howard Taft and Woodrow
         Wilson); a Bachelor of Science degree awarded as a graduate of
         the Naval Academy in 1938; orders and reports concerning
         Wickham's naval service, 1941-1943; correspondence and records
         concerning his disability and retirement, 1944-1949 (including
         orders signed by James Forrestal); correspondence and records
         concerning military insurance with the Veterans
         Administration; commendation for services, 1942-1944, as
         Convoy Control Officer of the U.S. Tenth Fleet; and an
         address, n.d., of Wickham to the Hanover County Woman's Club
         concerning his early years of naval service.Miscellany is
         comprised of an undated teacher's recommendation signed by E.
         R. Whitlocke; correspondence and exams of Wickham in the
         LaSalle Extension University course in law, Chicago, Ill.,
         1945; lineage charts showing the descent of Williams Carter
         Wickham for the Virginia Society of Colonial Dames; wedding
         invitations; a membership certificate, 1912, in the A.P.V.A.;
         and collected newspaper clippings.</p>
      <p>Captain Wickham's younger brother, George Barksdale Wickham
         (1888-1928), attended Virginia Military Institute and later
         became a Richmond businessman. His records, in Series 12 of
         this collection, include school materials, n.d.-1903; grade
         reports while a student at V.M.I., 1904-1905, 1907; a wedding
         invitation, 1916; A.P.V.A. certificate, 1912; and obituary
         notices.</p>
      <p>In Series 13, the collection closes with family miscellany
         (materials of Lawrence Vernon Miller Wickham while service in
         the U.S. Marine Corps; and a commonplace book, 1973-1977, of
         Lois (Wingfield) Wickham, widow of Williams Carter Wickham
         [1917-1982]) and a few items of general miscellany (autograph
         album, 1877-1889, kept by Carrie Lee Colton in Annapolis and
         Jessup's Cut, Md.; and correspondence, 1877-1886, of Reverend
         Pike Powers of Richmond, Va.)</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Arranged in thirteen series by main entry and further
         subdivided by date or subject as necessary.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>Agriculture -- Virginia -- History.</subject>
      <subject>Carter, Charles, 1818-</subject>
      <subject>Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company.</subject>
      <subject>Democratic Party (Va.) -- History -- 20th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Diaries -- Virginia -- Hanover County -- History
         -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Fanning family.</subject>
      <subject>Fugitive slaves -- Virginia -- Hanover County --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Gist, Samuel, d. 1815.</subject>
      <subject>Hanover County (Va.) -- History.</subject>
      <subject>Hickory Hill (Hanover County, Va.)</subject>
      <subject>Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward),
         1807-1870.</subject>
      <subject>Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh, 1837-1891.</subject>
      <subject>North Wales (Caroline County, Va.)</subject>
      <subject>Plantations -- Virginia -- Hanover
         County.</subject>
      <subject>Real estate management -- Virginia -- Richmond --
         History -- 20th century.</subject>
      <subject>Reconstruction -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Republican Party (Va.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Slaves -- Emancipation -- Virginia.</subject>
      <subject>Trusts and trustees -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- History -- Civil War,
         1861-1865.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Politics and government --
         1865-1950.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Elise Warwick Barksdale,
         1861-1952.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham family.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Henry Taylor, 1849-1943.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, John, 1763-1839.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Lucy Penn Taylor, 1830-1913.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, William Carter, 1820-1888.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, William Fanning, 1793-1880.</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">Series 1. William Fanning
               (1728-1782), Greensville County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Certificate of ordination; letter, 1781; will, 1782;
               genealogical notes; Henry Taylor Wickham correspondence,
               1930</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">William Fanning (1728-1782),
               Greensville County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Certificate of ordination; letter, 1781; will, 1782;
               genealogical notes; Henry Taylor Wickham correspondence,
               1930</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Edmund Fanning (1739-1818),
               Nova Scotia, Canada</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">1 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1783-1812; letters, 1777-1778;
               prayer; biographical sketches</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">John Wickham (1763-1839),
               Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 3.1">Correspondence,
                  1778-1799</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes letters to David Parish</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 3.2">Land records and
                  miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 3.3">Estate
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">2-4</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Wills; correspondence; financial and land records;
                  Wickham et al. v. Leigh et al.; W.H.F. Lee trust</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">William Fanning Wickham
               (1793-1880), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.1">Diaries,
                  1828-1880</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.2">Correspondence,
                  1817-1878</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">6</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Includes letters of condolence, 1868</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.3">Financial and legal
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">7</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Accounts; memorandum of stocks; bonds; land
                  records ("Hickory Hill," "South Wales," "The
                  Lane").</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.4">Samuel Gist
                  estate</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.5">Miscellaneous
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">9-10</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Frances (Wickham) Graham trust; pardon materials;
                  genealogical notes; commonplace book, miscellany;
                  estate</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Williams Carter Wickham
               (1820-1888), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.1">Letterbooks,
                  1877-1881</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">10
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.2">Correspondence,
                  1862-1888</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.3">Financial materials,
                  1861-1888</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">12-13</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Personal account books, 1875-1885 (11 v.); account
                  book, 1880-1888, "household expenses"; accounts,
                  1861, 1868-1888; bonds, 1877-1888</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.4">Hickory Hill materials,
                  1866-1888</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">13
                  (cont.)-15</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Farm books, 1866-1888 (15 v.); loose materials,
                  1871-1888</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.5">North Wales materials,
                  1867-1887</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">16</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.6">Margaret William Tryon
                  (Fanning) Cumberland estate materials,
                  1880-1888.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">17</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.7">Frances (Wickham)
                  Graham trust, 1880-1888</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">18</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 5.8">Miscellaneous and Other
                  legal papers, 1872-1888</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">19</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>George Harrison Byrd trust; Julia Leiper (Taylor)
                  Hubard trust; C. and O. Railway materials, 1872-1888;
                  Republican party materials, ca. 1881-1887;
                  miscellaneous land records; general miscellany,
                  estate.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 6">Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham
               (1830-1913), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 6.1">Correspondence,
                  1848-1913.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 6.2">Financial materials,
                  1875-1913</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Accounts, 1875-1913; tax returns; Chesapeake Land
                  and Improvement Co..</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 6.3">
                  Miscellaneous</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Genealogical notes; estate of Henry Taylor</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 6.4">Estate materials,
                  1913-1915</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">20
                  (cont.)-21</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">Henry Taylor Wickham
               (1849-1943), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.1">Letterbooks,
                  1931-1940</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22-23</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.2">Correspondence,
                  1874-1940</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">24-25</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.3">Financial materials,
                  1867-1942</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">25</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Account book, 1867-1870; account book, 1942;
                  passbooks, 1915-1926 (2 v.); check stub book,
                  1922-1926; and accounts, 1920-1925, 1931-1933,
                  1938-1939.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.4">Richmond, Va., rental
                  properties.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">26</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.5">Hickory Hill
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">27-30</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Farm books, 1893-1913 [4 v.]; time sheets,
                  payrolls, produce statements; and land records.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.6">Student records, etc.,
                  1867-1935.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">30
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.7">Virginia State
                  materials</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">30
                  (cont.)-31</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Speeches, addresses, etc.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.8">Scrapbooks,
                  1874-1943</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">32-37</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.9">Legal
                  papers</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">37
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Law practice; land and tax records</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.10">Miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">37
                  (cont.)-38</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Newspaper clippings; genealogical notes and
                  records; general miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 7.11">Estate materials,
                  1943-1945</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">38
                  (cont.)-39</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Elise Warwick (Barksdale)
               Wickham (1861-1952), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.1">Correspondence, 1869,
                  1896-1948</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">40</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.2">Financial materials,
                  1891-1951</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">41-42</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Accounts, 1902-1936; passbooks (3 v.), 1891-1919;
                  check stub books (7 v.,) 1896-1923; bank statements
                  and canceled checks, 1948-1950; tax forms and
                  returns, 1941-1951.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.3">Hickory Hill materials.
                  Farm records (time sheets, payrolls, produce
                  statements, accounts, etc.)</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">43-45</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.4">Richmond, Va., rental
                  properties, 1931-1951.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">45
                  (cont.)-47</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.5">Barksdale and Warwick
                  family miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">47
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 8.6">Miscellaneous
                  materials.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">48</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Brookfield," Henrico County, Va., materials,
                  1891-1925; Ladies' Aid Society, St. Paul's Episcopal
                  Church, Hanover County, Va.; visitor's registers (2
                  v.), 1930-1961; miscellany</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">William Fanning Wickham
               (1860-1900), "Hickory Hill," Hanover County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">49</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Hanover Troop materials, 1889; personal
               miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Ann Carter (Wickham)
               Renshaw Byerly (1851-1939), "Hickory Hill," Hanover
               County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">49 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters, 1869-1888.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">Williams Carter Wickham
               (1887-1985), Washington, D. C. and "Hickory Hill,"
               Hanover County, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 11.1">Correspondence,
                  1897-1967.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">49
                  (cont.)-50</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 11.2">U.S. Navy Service and
                  miscellany, 1904-1949.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">51</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">George Barksdale Wickham
               (1888-1928), Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">51 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>School materials and miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 13">Miscellany.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">51 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Family and general miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
