<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Converted with dtd2schema.vh.xsl -->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng"
		type="application/xml" 
		schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
		title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" id="vih00016">
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" repositoryencoding="iso15511">
    <eadid publicid="PUBLIC &amp;#34;-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00016::A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1766-1945)//EN&amp;#34; &amp;#34;vih00016&amp;#34;" countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViHi">PUBLIC "-//Virginia
             Historical Society//TEXT (US::ViH::vih00016::A Guide to
             the Wickham Family Papers, 1766-1945)//EN"
             "vih00016"</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 
            <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1766-1945</date></titleproper>
        <subtitle id="sort">Wickham Family Papers, 1766-1945 
            <num type="collectionnumber">Mss1 W6326 a
            FA2</num></subtitle>
        <sponsor>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</sponsor>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_address.xi.xml"/>
        <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">© 2002 By Virginia
            Historical Society. All rights reserved.</date>
        <p id="usestatement">
          <extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html">Conditions of
               Use</extref>
        </p>
        <p id="filesize">53 kb</p>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from word
         processing program. Machine-readable finding aid created by
         VHS Staff, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2 May 2002.</date></creation>
      <langusage>Description is in 
         <language>English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-17" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 17, 2004</date>
        <item>PUBLIC "-//Virginia Historical Society//TEXT
            (US::ViH::vih00016::A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers,
            1766-1945)//EN" "vih00016" converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002
            by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2004-02-25" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">Feb 25, 2004</date>
        <item>converted to conform to eadVIVA.dtd by
            vivastrict.xsl</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date normal="2013-11-21">2013-11-21</date>
        <item>Converted to schema conforming EAD by dtd2schema.vh.xsl.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <titleproper>A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 
         <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1766-1945</date></titleproper>
      <subtitle>A Collection in 
         <lb/>the Virginia Historical Society 
         <num type="Collection Number">Mss1 W6326 a
         FA2</num></subtitle>
      <p id="logostmt">
        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/vhs.jpg"/>
      </p>
      <publisher>Virginia Historical Society</publisher>
      <date type="publication" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</date>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu:/vivaead/add_con/vhs_contact.xi.xml"/>
      <list type="deflist">
        <defitem>
          <label>Processed by:</label>
          <item>Virginia Historical Society Staff</item>
        </defitem>
        <defitem>
          <label>Funding:</label>
          <item>Web version of the finding aid funded in part by a
               grant from the National Endowment for the
               Humanities.</item>
        </defitem>
      </list>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <runner placement="footer">Virginia Historical Society</runner>
    <did>
      <head>Descriptive Summary</head>
      <repository>Virginia Historical Society</repository>
      <unittitle label="Title">A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers,
         <unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
         1766-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid label="Collection number">Mss1 W6326 a FA2</unitid>
      <physdesc label="Size">5,500 (ca.) items (37 mss.
         boxes)</physdesc>
      <langmaterial label="Language">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langmaterial>
      <abstract label="Abstract">Abstract: The collection includes
         correspondence, 1798-1839, of Richmond, Va., attorney John
         Wickham, primarily concerning business and legal affairs and
         politics (correspondents include Stephen Decatur, Edmund
         Ruffin, and U.S. senator Littleton Waller Tazewell); legal
         records (including materials concerning the treason trial of
         Aaron Burr in 1807); records concerning "East Tuckahoe"
         plantation, Henrico County, Va.; and records concerning the
         settlement of Wickham's estate. Also, includes correspondence,
         1836-1897, of Wickham's son Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham
         (1821-1909), New Orleans, La., attorney and planter at
         "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (including letters of Thomas
         Ashby concerning the "Bunker Hill" plantation, Darlington
         County, S.C., and of Elizabeth Selden Maclurg Wickham of
         Richmond and while visiting the Virginia springs); accounts;
         and materials concerning his law practice. Also, includes
         correspondence, 1864-1895, of Francis Peyre Porcher
         (1825-1895), physician of Charleston, S.C., with family
         members, prominent medical practitioners, and business
         associates; and family and personal correspondence, 1870-1929,
         of his daughter, Julia Wickham (Porcher) Wickham (1860-1933),
         especially with French soldiers and widows World War I, along
         with two autograph albums compiled by Mrs. Wickham featuring
         signatures and letters of prominent American and English
         literary, political and scientific figures. Also, includes
         diaries (36 v.), 1900-1939, correspondence, 1872-1935, and
         miscellaneous records of Thomas Ashby Wickham (1857-1939),
         attorney of Sprague, Wash., and Richmond, Va., judge of the
         Henrico County Court, and while serving in the Virginia
         Senate; correspondence, 1891-1897, and miscellaneous records
         of his cousin and law partner, William Fanning Wickham
         (1860-1900) of Richmond, Va., concerning his law practice,
         local civic activities, and service with the 1st Cavalry
         Regiment of Virginia Volunteers; and miscellaneous records of
         other Wickham family members</abstract>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admininfo">
      <head>Administrative Information 
         </head>
      <accessrestrict>
        <head>Access</head>
        <p>Collection is open for research.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict>
        <head>Use Restrictions</head>
        <p>There are no restrictions.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite>
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
        <p>Wickham Family Papers, 1766-1945 (Mss1 W6326 a FA2),
            Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <acqinfo>
        <head>Acquisition Information</head>
        <p>Gift of Dr. Charles W. Porter and Mrs. Julia Wickham
            Porter, Richmond, Va., in 1986. Accessioned 1 October
            1987.</p>
      </acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Information</head>
      <p>The Wickham family of Richmond and Henrico County, known as
         the "Woodside Wickhams," was founded by the celebrated
         post-Revolutionary War attorney John Wickham (1763-1839). A
         skilled advocate and friend to many of the prominent legal and
         political figures of his day, Wickham married twice and had
         numerous off-springs. This collection primarily traces his
         descendants by his second wife, Elizabeth Selden McClurg.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent>
      <head>Scope and Content Information</head>
      <p>The collection opens with attorney John Wickham's personal
         correspondence, largely with his second wife, Elizabeth Selden
         (McClurg) Wickham, and his children. Letters from a number of
         prominent correspondents appear as well, including: James
         Breckinridge (concerning the Virginia Constitutional
         Convention of 1829-1830), Joseph Carrington Cabell (enclosing
         lengthy letters of Isaac A. Coles concerning his travels in
         western Virginia, Kentucky, Indiana, Illinois, the Missouri
         Territory, and the Missouri Compromise), Stephen Decatur,
         Maria M. Fanning (of Prince Edward Island, Canada; in part
         concerning Governor Edmund Fanning), Robert Gamble (enclosing
         an extract from a letter of George Mathews, governor of
         Georgia), John Church Hamilton (concerning a biography of
         Alexander Hamilton), William Gaston, Edmund Ruffin, Benjamin
         Silliman (of Yale College), Littleton Waller Tazewell (about
         35 letters written while a U.S. senator from Virginia, a
         Norfolk attorney, and a planter on the Eastern Shore;
         enclosing a copy of a letter from Chief Justice John Marshall
         [18 January 1827] and notes on admiralty law; and describing a
         cholera epidemic [17 September 1832]), George Wickham (while
         serving as an officer in the U.S. Navy aboard the U.S.S.
         Constellation in the Mediterranean Sea [see also Josiah
         Colston]), and Walter Maclurg Wickham (as a medical student
         and physician in Baltimore, Md.).</p>
      <p>Box three commences with materials from John Wickham's law
         practice. These include his 1787 licence to practice in
         Virginia; a commonplace book, ca. 1766-1780, kept by an
         unidentified person (no doubt a Wickham relative), with notes
         on procedural law in the inferior and superior courts of the
         Colony of New York and accounts (p. 130ff) of an unidentified
         individual; proceedings and orders of the Board of British
         Debt Commissioners in Philadelphia, Pa., 1798-1808; records of
         actions in the U.S. Circuit Court for the District of Virginia
         in the so-called British Debt Cases, 1795-1808; and a will of
         Nicholas M. Vaughan of Goochland County 1833.</p>
      <p>Materials concerning the famous trial of Aaron Burr in the
         federal court in Richmond on treason charges in 1806-1807
         primarily revolve around Wickham's questioning of the
         integrity of evidence provided by General James Wilkinson and
         Wilkinson's attempt to secure satisfaction on the field of
         honor. The records include copies of Wilkinson's letters to
         President Thomas Jefferson; correspondence of Wickham with
         George Hay, Dr. William Upshaw and James Wilkinson; and
         affidavits and a memorial of Miles Selden and John Wickham.
         (Wickham's writings are letter-press copies in very poor
         condition and barely legible.)</p>
      <p>While a resident of Richmond, John Wickham purchased a
         large tract of land in western Henrico County known as "East
         Tuckahoe." His records of that estate include lists of slaves
         at "Middle Quarter" and "Lower Quarter," 1821-1837 (the 1825
         list includes Wickham's notes on various workers); test
         borings for coal, 1809-1834; and notes on the wheat crop,
         1836.</p>
      <p>John Wickham's commonplace book, 1804-1807, records notes
         on climate, weather, agriculture and population, and
         undoubtedly served as a source for the pamphlet on climate
         that he wrote. Miscellaneous materials include a lengthy essay
         on slavery and abolition(undated but probably written by
         Wickham in the 1830s); a biographical sketch of Chief Justice
         John Marshall (see letter of Bushrod Washington, Box 2);
         physician's instructions for the care of Elizabeth Selden
         (McClurg) Wickham, 1823; epitaphs of certain of the Wickham
         children; notes concerning a tour through Europe, ca. 1784;
         and lines of verse.</p>
      <p>Materials concerning the estate of John Wickham include his
         will, 1839, probated in Richmond (bearing extensive notes of
         Benjamin Watkins Leigh); letters of condolence addressed to
         Mrs. and Henry Hiort; Richmond City tax receipts, 1854-1863;
         and litigation among the heirs, 1854 (also concerns the estate
         of Dr. James McClurg). Division of the "East Tuckahoe" estate,
         1847-1871, includes agreements, litters of John Wickham
         (1825-1902) And William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) to
         Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham; an abstract of title; notes
         and a bond.</p>
      <p>John Wickham married first Mary Smith Fanning, who bore him
         two sons and died young in 1799. His second wife, Elizabeth
         Selden McClurg, was a celebrated belle of her day. The papers
         of this second Mrs. Wickham, in Series 2, consist of
         correspondence, 1794-1850, including letters of Edwin Burwell,
         Stephen Decatur, Dr. James McClurg, Eliza (Kinloch) Nelson (at
         "Shirley" Charles City county), Littleton Waller Tazewell,
         Eliza Carter (Randolph) Turner (of "Shirley," Charles City
         County), George Wickham, and John Wickham ([1825-1902] at
         Harvard College). Copies of wills of benefactors include those
         of Edwin Burwell (an early admirer, written in Richmond,
         1798), Dr. James McClug (probated in Richmond, 1823), and
         Walter McClurg (probated in Elizabeth City County in 1784).
         Miscellany is comprised of a receipt, 1850; autograph of Henry
         Clay; recipes; and lines of verse.</p>
      <p>The eldest of the children of John and Elizabeth Wickham
         featured prominently in this collection is Maclurg Wickham
         (note that the children began to spell "McClurg" as
         "maclurg"). Maclurg Wickham (1814-1900) lived at "East
         Tuckahoe." His papers are contained in Series 3, and consist
         of a diary, 1851-1882, with many gaps, that deals primarily
         with plantation operations, the management of slaves
         (including lists of slaves with records of the distribution of
         clothing and supplies), and notes from 1890 concerning the
         recent death of family members and friends. Some of the
         records in this diary were entered by John Wickham
         (1825-1902). A few items of correspondence, 1848-1876, include
         letters from his brother William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880).
         Additional materials are made up of loose accounts, 1860-1897;
         bonds of Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham and receipts of
         Maclurg Wickham, 1859-1865; and materials, 1893-1897, from the
         lawsuit of Maclurg Wickham trustee etal. v. the heirs of
         Frances (Wickham) Graham etal. in an unidentified Virginia
         court (including correspondence and notes of William Fanning
         Wickham [1860-1900] as counsel and receipts of the
         legatees).</p>
      <p>Maclurg Wickham's miscellany consists of diplomas from the
         University of Virginia, 1831-1832; a pardon, 1865, signed by
         President Andrew Johnson and William Henry Seward; a lease of
         Thomas E. Clarke to the "Woodside" plantation in Henrico
         County (including trust deeds concerning horses and cattle at
         "Woodlawn," Henrico County); personal property tax return,
         1896; and an insurance policy, 1897. Wickham's estate records
         are comprised of notes of Henry Taylor Wickham concerning the
         draft of a will and the response; a certificate of the
         executor's qualification; an inventory; and an unexecuted
         deed, 1909, to real property in Richmond, Va.</p>
      <p>Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham was named for one of his
         father's closest personal friends. Educated at the University
         of Virginia, he practiced law in New Orleans for a time before
         returning to Virginia in the 1850s. His papers comprise Series
         4. His correspondence (Boxes 5-8), 1836-1897, largely concerns
         his life as a student at the University, the estates of his
         two deceased wives, and plantation a portion of the old "East
         Tuckahoe" estate. Among the more important of frequent
         correspondents are: Thomas Ashby (of Charleston, S.C.,
         concerning the "Bunker Hill" plantation in Darlington County,
         S.C.), Parke Farley Berkeley, John Minor Botts, Alfred T.
         Conrad, Francis Buckner Conrad, William W. Harllee (of Mars
         Bluff, S.C., concerning the purchase and sale of the "Bunker
         Hill" plantation), William F. Harrison (of Powhatan County),
         Gabriella Brockenbrough (Wickham) Leigh, Robert Nash Ogden
         (New Orleans judge, concerning the estate of John Nicholson),
         John Scott (of "Oakwood," Fauquier County, concerning the
         abolition of slavery), Philip Montague Thompson (at the
         University of Virginia), Elizabeth Seldon Maclurg Wickham
         (with comments on everyday life and society in Richmond; some
         letters written from New Orleans, La., Salt Sulphur Springs
         and Sweet Springs, W. Va., and Hot Springs, Bath County, Va.),
         George Wickham, John Wickham ([1825-1902] at the White Sulphur
         Springs and Sweet Springs, W.Va., in1844 and bearing
         references to John Minor Botts and Robert Edward Lee),
         Littleton Tazewell Wickham, Thomas Ashby Wickham (practicing
         law at Sprague, Washington and visiting White Sulphur Springs,
         W.Va., in 1895), William Fanning Wickham ([1793-1880] of
         "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, concerning the lawsuit Wickham
         etal. v. Leigh etal. in Richmond Circuit Court), and H. B.
         Taliaferro &amp; Co., Richmond (postwar produce and commission
         merchants).</p>
      <p>L. W. T. Wickham's financial records are found in Boxes
         8-9. These include two account books, 1851-1874 (record of
         checks) and 1874-1878; a passbook, 1855-1857; and loose
         accounts, 1849-1882 and 1890-1891. Materials, 1837-1839,
         concerning Wickham's education at the University of Virginia
         include essays (bear notes of Professor George Tucker), a
         speech on slavery, scheme of study, invitations, accounts,
         eximinations, and diplomas. Records of invitatins, accounts,
         examinations, and diplomas. Records of Wickham's law practice,
         1848-1852, consist of licenses, a commonplace book bearing
         abstracts of Virginia and British case reports and notes of
         John Wickham (1763-1839), notes on law, materials concerning
         lawsuits in Louisiana, and materials concerning his law
         partner in New Orleans, Francis Buckner Conrad.</p>
      <p>Bell &amp; Gibson of Richmond constructed Wickham's home at
         "Woodside" about 1857. Records in Box 10 include agreements,
         accounts, an insurance policy, and letters to William Fanning
         Wickham (1793-1880) from Baltimore craftsmen concerning a
         mantle. William F. Harrison of Powhatan County built a barn
         and "machine shelter" on the estate and his records are
         comprised of agreements, accounts, notes and miscellany. Then
         follow records of agricultural operations, 1857-1875: deeds to
         portions of the estate; inventories of personal property;
         lists of slaves; a petition to the Virginia General Assembly
         concerning fence laws; agreements with overseers; notes and
         miscellany.</p>
      <p>In the later 1850s Wickham purchased the land and slaves at
         "Bunker Hill" in Darlington County, S.C., from his
         father-in-law, Thomas Ashby. After Wickham's wife died, the
         transaction became a point of conflict between the two men.
         Records consist of bonds, receipts of Ashby, accounts,
         proceedings concerning the dower right of Elizabeth Peyre
         (Ashby) Laurens Wickham, accounts of sales of property, lists
         of slaves, a letter of William W. Harllee to Dr. Edward
         Porcher, and miscellany.</p>
      <p>A few of Littleton Wickham's records from the period of the
         Civil War survive. These include certificates; assessors'
         receipts for produce; a petition of George A. Mathews to
         Confederate Secretary of War James Alexander Seddon (draft in
         the hand of Wickham); a pass; petition of Henrico County
         residents to General Edward R. S. Canby concerning the fencing
         of farms (signed by L.W.T. Wickham, Maclurg Wickham, and about
         two dozen others); and notes. Materials relating to Wickham's
         postwar filing for bankruptcy in the U.S. District Court for
         Eastern Virginia consist of a petition, schedules of property
         (broadsides), a deposition, power of attorney, notes and
         letters of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) and William
         Fanning Wickham (1860-1900) as a counsel, a copy of the
         marriage settlement of Charlotte Georgiana (Wickham) Lee and
         William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, receipts, and certificates.</p>
      <p>Miscellaneous documents relating to Littleton Waller
         Tazewell Wickham are comprised of a letter of Daniel Webster
         to Benjamin Watkins Leigh in 1840; plans for the gradual
         abolition of slavery written by Wickham in 1847; a lease,
         1862, to a house in Richmond; litigation involving Wickham,
         1867-1870; a will written in Henrico County, 1861; lines of
         verse composed by Wickham (including odes to Richmond and to
         Virginia); a commonplace book, 1886 (two entries); letters
         written to Wickham &amp; Co., Lorraine, Va., 1893-1897; and
         newspaper clippings.</p>
      <p>Littleton Wickham married his first wife, Eliza Wyckoff
         Nicholson, in New Orleans, but she died young in 1850. She is
         represented in Series 5. Her correspondence, 1846-1850, is
         primarily with relatives and largely concerns the estate of
         her father, John Nicholson. Among her correspondents are
         Alfred T. Conrad, Louisiana congressman Charles Magill Conrad,
         Francis Buckner Conrad, Frances S. D. Ogden, Judge Robert Nash
         Ogden and Elizabeth Selden Maclurg Wickham. Box 12 also
         contains a few accounts, 1849-1850, and materials concerning
         the estate of John Nicholson ([d. 1848] including
         correspondence of L.W.T. Wickham and William T. Hepp
         [administrator]; accounts; power of attorney; petition to the
         Louisiana District Court in New Orleans; a printed message of
         the governor of Pennsylvania concerning the estate of John
         Nicholson [d. 1800]; a document of partition and compromise;
         inventories of estate property; court proceedings; and notes
         of L.W.T. Wickham and others). Miscellany and a few items from
         her estate round out the records of the first Mrs. Wickham
         (will [three copies], memorial by L.W.T. Wickham and funeral
         notice, certificate from the Louisiana district Court for
         Jefferson Parish, accounts, court proceedings [drafts of
         petitions and motions], and notes).</p>
      <p>The second Mrs. Wickham, the widow Elizabeth Peyre (Ashby)
         Laurens of Charleston, S.C., likewise died young in 1859 after
         bearing four children. Her papers, in Series 6, include
         letters written to her, 1852- 1859, including one from South
         Carolina attorney general James Louis Petigru. The collection
         also includes letters, 1821-1831, written by her mother,
         Elizabeth (Peyre) Sinkler Ashby, to a handful of
         correspondents, and a letter of E. Thomas concerning the death
         of Mrs. Ashby. Series 7 contains the papers of John Wickham
         (1825-1902), the youngest of the Wickham sons, who also lived
         at "Woodside" in Henrico County. His correspondence,
         1837-1902, includes letters from Benjamin Watkins Leigh,
         Winfield Scott (concerning an appointment to the military
         academy at West Point) and Littleton Waller Tazewell (bears an
         extract from a letter of President John Tyler to Tazewell, 24
         October 1842). Along with sporadic accounts, Box 13 contains
         John Wickham's records of "East Tuckahoe," particularly
         concerning mineral rights and mining proposals and including
         plats and notes of John J. Pleasants, deeds, and an
         agreement.</p>
      <p>John Wickham likewise filed for bankruptcy following the
         Civil War. Records of these proceedings in the U. S. District
         Court for Easter Virginia consist of a memorandum of
         proceedings; petition; reports; reply and exceptions of
         Maclurg Wickham (drafts in the hand of William Fanning Wickham
         [1860-1900]); letters addressed to William Fanning Wickham of
         T.A. &amp; W.F. Wickham of Richmond; notes and miscellany.
         Some general miscellany and a few items from his estate
         (including diplomas from the University of Virginia, 1841, and
         a will written in Henrico County in 1901) complete John
         Wickham's records.</p>
      <p>Series 8 contains materials relating to this generation of
         Wickhams. Included are a number of items of correspondence of
         Dr. James McClurg, Littleton Waller Tazewell, Elizabeth Selden
         Maclurg Wickham, George Wickham, James Maclurg Wickham and
         others.</p>
      <p>Series 9 contains the papers of Dr. Francis Peyre Porcher,
         whose daughter married a son of L.W.T. Wickham. Porcher was an
         eminent South Carolina physician and medical writer who had
         married a granddaughter of John Wickham (1763-1839). His
         correspondence in this collection, 1864-1895, is directed
         largely to family members, prominent American and European
         practitioners, and some financial and business associates
         (especially concerning railroad bonds). Some letters concern
         the collection of autographs for his daughter, discussed
         below. Correspondents include Dr. Abel Seymour Baldwin,
         Florida congreeman Silas Leslie Niblack, Dr. George Frederick
         Shrady, Julia Wickham (Porcher) Wickham, William Fanning
         Wickham (1793-1880) and a number of Porcher family members.
         Lectures, 1849 and 1870) on Cicero and the Roman Forum, an
         1879 lecture before the Young Men's Christian Association of
         Charleston, S.C., and an undated essay concerning South
         Carolina local history also survive.</p>
      <p>Dr. Porcher's miscellany includes a number of interesting
         items. Along with a few accounts, 1865-1869 and 1895, are
         orders of the Confederate States Surgeon General Samuel
         Preston Moore, 1862; notes on the Confederate service of the
         7th South Carolina Infantry Regiment; Confederate States
         Bonds, 1863; Florida Central Railroad stock certificates,
         1868; a published articles on Yellow Fever, 1894; and a
         commission, 1881, as South Carolina representative to the
         American Public Health Association, signed by Governor Johnson
         Hagood. These are followed by a few miscellaneous Porcher
         family materials: letters to or from Isabella Sarah (Peyre)
         Porcher, Virginia (Leigh) Porcher and Dr. Walter Peyre
         Porcher; and essays on freedmen in South carolina by Alexander
         Mazyck Porcher.</p>
      <p>Series 10, the papers of Thomas Ashby Wickham (1857-1939),
         include thirty-six volumes of Judge Wickham's diaries, for the
         years 1900, 1902-1925, and 1929-1939. The entries are cryptic
         notations on local weather, farming activities, travel,
         personal finances, and the like. Judge Wickham's
         correspondence, 1872-1938 (beginning in Box 19), is primarily
         with members of his family, concerning his law practice in the
         Washington Territory, his service in the Virginia Senate
         (especially regarding confirmation proceedings for the
         appointment of Judge William Francis Rhea to the State
         Corporation Commission), and the estate of Frances (Wickham)
         Graham. This includes a large number of letters from his law
         partner and later Washington State Supreme Court justice
         Wallace Mount.</p>
      <p>Following a group of loose accounts and check stub books
         (two volumes), the collection contains records of Judge
         Wickham's residence at "Woodside." These include an insurance
         policy, proposal for rental of farm land, agreements,
         materials concerning bridge construction over Tuckahoe Creek
         and miscellany. Other land records of Wickham concern the
         acquisition of lots and improvements in Richmond and Henrico
         County, 1909- 1912.</p>
      <p>Records concerning Judge Wickham's law practice, 1843-1921,
         consist of licences and licence fees; law notes; a tribute to
         James Robertson Vivian Daniel; notes concerning the
         professional conduct of John Anthony Lamb; accounts of the law
         firm of T.A. &amp; W.F. Wickham in Richmond, 1893-1896; cases
         in the Richmond Chancery Court, Richmond Law and Equity Court,
         and Henrico Circuit Court (including the estate of Frances
         (Wickham) Graham in Graham's trustee v. Graham's heirs);
         materials concerning lands in Richmond belonging to Lucy
         Wickham (Fitzhugh) Faison and R. H. Sinton (in the lawsuit of
         Joseph A. Johnston v. Rebecca Johnston etal.); and materials
         concerning executorships and trusteeships handled by Wickham
         during his judicial career.</p>
      <p>Judge Wickham's political materials concern his service in
         the Virginia Senate in 1908 (petition of citizens of York
         County for a portion of their district to be added to James
         City County; materials concerning the confirmation proceedings
         in the case of Judge Rhea on the State Corporation Commission)
         and his unsuccessful bid to win the 1910 Democratic
         Congressional Primary against Congreeman John Lamb (notes;
         form letter; labor union materials, newspaper clippings). The
         judge's miscellany includes the diary of an 1895 visit to
         White Sulphur Springs, W.Va.; stock certificates, 1907-1910;
         tax forms for various years; and a will (revoked).</p>
      <p>Following Judge Wickham's papers are the surviving records
         of his cousins and law partner William Fanning Wickham
         (1860-1900). They practiced together in Richmond in the 1890s
         as T.A. &amp; W.F. Wickham. Contained in Series 11, William F.
         Wickham's correspondence largely concerns his law practice,
         St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hanover County (letters from
         architects, manufacturers, contractors, etc.), the Virginia
         State Agricultural and Mechanical Society (especially
         concerning the Virginia State Fair of 1893), the First Cavalry
         Regiment of Virginia Volunteers, Wickham's purchase of a farm
         in Powhatan County, and local alumni of the University of
         Virginia. Prominent correspondents include Anne Carter
         (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, horsebreeder H. Clay Chamblin,
         Stuart Lee Dance, Alexander Barclay Guigon, Maryland horseman
         Robert Hough, Fenton Noland (of Offley, Va.), Thomas Nelson
         Page, clergy Clevius Orlando Pruden, Hanover County attorney
         Hill Carter Redd, federal judge Edmund Waddill, Henry Taylor
         Wickham, Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham, John Sergeant Wise, and
         the Re. E. Lee Camp of Sons of Confederate Veterans in
         Richmond.</p>
      <p>Additional records of William Fanning Wickham consist of
         accounts, 1893-1897; materials as colonel commanding the First
         Cavalry Regiment of Virginia Volunteers (general and special
         orders, invitations to participate in special events, expenses
         of a court-martial, and subscribers to the Albemarle Light
         Horse Troop of Virginia Volunteers); invitations and notices
         of meetings of such secret societies, clubs, and fraternal
         orders as the Scottish Rite Freemasons, Shriners, Knights
         Templar, Tuckahoe Farmers' Club, and Wednesday Club of
         Richmond. General miscellany includes records of his law
         practice; assorted materials concerning the construction of
         St. Paul's Church in Hanover County; materials concerning the
         Seay Farm in Powhatan County; Republican Party materials;
         records of the University of Virginia alumni banquet in
         Richmond, 1894; bonds; and materials concerning Hanover County
         courthouse.</p>
      <p>Series 12 contains materials relating to Julia Wickham
         Porcher (1860-1933), who married her cousin Thomas Ashby
         Wickham in 1897 and lived at "Woodside." She kept a diary (Box
         28) in 1896 during a trip to England and France that contains
         numerous clippings and photographs along with daily notations.
         Her correspondence, 1870-1929, is primarily with Porcher
         family members and with friends, but also includes letters
         from a number of French soldiers and widows during and just
         after World War I. Among the significant correspondents:
         Hobart Asquith (concerning his Confederate serve in the
         Maryland Line under generals Lunsford Lindsay Lomax and
         Williams Carter Wickham), Episcopal clergyman Ambler Mason
         Blackford, French clergyman C. Boyer (written in French at the
         close of World War I), New York banker Charles Meriwether Fry,
         Elizabeth (Leigh) Fry, Hamilton Wright Mable, Virginia Carter
         Minor, Alexander Mazyck Porcher, Isabella Sarah (Peyre)
         Porcher, Virginia Leigh Porcher, Dr. Walter Peyre Porcher,
         Helen Willis (Minor) Poyntz, Conway Robinson (concerning
         President Rutherford B. Hayes), Mary Susan Selden (Leigh)
         Robinson, Irish actress Patricia (Collinge) Smith, Littleton
         Maclurg Wickham, and Bishop Richard Hooker Wilmer (enclosing a
         copy of his pamphlet entitled Some Thoughts on Robert Elsmere,
         in a Letter to a Friend [1889?]).Mrs. Wickham's account books
         include a volume covering expenses on a trip to Europe in 1891
         and a passbook apparently on a New York bank, 1895-1896. Then
         follow in Boxes 33-34 her very extensive collection of
         autographs of famous persons. Mrs. Wickham apparently began
         collecting as a young woman with her father's encouragement
         and aid, and amassed a fine group of letters, autographs, and
         clipped signatures from her father's friends and medical
         associates, as well as from other Porcher and Wickham family
         members. The first volume remains intact and an index to it
         follows this collection description. Loose items have been
         filed in the same box with the album, as the index will show.
         The second volume was in very poor condition, the highly
         acidic paper on which many items were pasted threatened their
         very existence. The volume thus was disassembled and the loose
         items filed alphabetically according to type of document. A
         separate index of the documents removed from this second
         volume is also available.</p>
      <p>The remaining materials of Mrs. Wickham in this collection
         include a scrapbook dating from 1904 containing numerous
         newspaper clippings, and a large file of clippings grouped
         around certain subjects (obituary notices, Virginia and South
         Carolina local history, Huguenots in America, general
         information). Miscellany consists of a few accounts,
         1920-1926; an essay on women; a student notebook (primarily
         concerns literature and language); materials concerning the
         "Half-Hour Reading Club," 1889-1895, presumably in South
         Carolina; genealogical and historical notes; and lines of
         verse by Edmund Pendleton.</p>
      <p>Series 13 is made up of a few surviving papers of Judge
         Thomas Ashby Wickham's brother Littleton Tazewell Wickham
         survive in this collection. They consist of correspondence,
         1880-1889; accounts, 1886-1888; account books (two volumes),
         1878-1883, 1882-1883; and a check stub book, 1882-1884. Series
         14 contains papers of their sister Elizabeth (Wickham)
         Fitzhugh, including letters, 1866-1881, from Thomas Ashby,
         Mary Louise Brooks, Isabella Sarah (Peyre) Porcher, William
         Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) and others; accounts, 1882-1884;
         and miscellany. A number of items of correspondence,
         1882-1939, of Mrs. Wickham's sister Virginia Leigh Porcher,
         make up Series 15. These may be found in Box 36 as well.</p>
      <p>Littleton Maclurg Wickham (1898-1973), son of Judge Thomas
         Ashby Wickham, represents the last generation of "Woodside
         Wickhams" in this collection. His papers are contained in
         Series 16. His correspondence, 1909-1945, is primarily with
         family and friends from the University of Virginia and
         concerns in part Zeta Psi Fraternity of North America and
         Wickham's service in World War I. Correspondents include John
         Herbert Claiborne, Richard Hartwell Cocke (of "Lower Bremo,"
         Fluvanna County, and as an attorney in Alabama), Richard
         Davenport Gilliam, Congreeman Andrew Jackson Montague, Amelia
         Louise (Rives) Chanler Troubetzkoy and Dr. Frederick Henry
         Wilke.</p>
      <p>Records of Littleton Wickham's days at the Episcopal High
         School in Alexandria, both as student and teacher, may be
         found in Box 37. Examination reports, exam questions, a list
         of students, invitations and programs illustrate his career as
         a student, 1911-1915, while teach contracts (signed by
         Archibald Robinson Hoxton) and accounts cover his teaching
         career, 1917-1921 (see also his correspondence with his
         mother, Julia Wickham (Porcher) Wickham). Wickham attended the
         University of Virginia, graduating from the college in 1917
         and attending the School of Law from 1922 to 1924. Examination
         reports, a recommendation from Professor Richard Henry Wilson,
         and miscellany cover his years in Charlottesville. Miscellany
         concerns his World War I service (1917) and personal accounts,
         1923-1938.</p>
      <p>The collection closes with Series 17, which contains
         miscellaneous family and non-family materials including
         letters written to or by Anne Alston Porcher, Margaret Ward
         Porcher and Ashby Porcher Wickham; a commonplace book of Mary
         Charlotte Porcher, 1850; and accounts of Julia Porcher
         (Wickham) Porter, 1931-1937.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement>
      <head>Arrangement</head>
      <p>Arranged into seventeen series by main entry and further
         subdivided by document type or subject as necessary.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <controlaccess>
      <head>Index Terms</head>
      <subject>Ashby, Thomas, 1783-1872.</subject>
      <subject>Autograph albums -- Virginia --
         Richmond.</subject>
      <subject>Bunker Hill (Darlington County, S.C.)</subject>
      <subject>Diaries -- Virginia -- Henrico County -- History
         -- 20th century.</subject>
      <subject>East Tuckahoe (Henrico County, Va.)</subject>
      <subject>Lawyers -- Virginia -- Richmond --
         History.</subject>
      <subject>New Orleans (La.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Physicians -- South Carolina -- Charleston --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Porcher, Francis Peyre, 1825-1895.</subject>
      <subject>Practice of law -- Louisiana -- New Orleans --
         History -- 19th century.</subject>
      <subject>Practice of law -- Virginia - - Richmond --
         History.</subject>
      <subject>Sprague (Wash.) -- History -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Tazewell, Littleton Waller, 1774-1860.</subject>
      <subject>United States -- Politics and government --
         1783-1865.</subject>
      <subject>Veterans -- France -- History -- World War,
         1914-1918.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia -- Description and travel -- 19th
         century.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia. General Assembly. Senate -- Members --
         History -- 20th century.</subject>
      <subject>Virginia. Militia. Cavalry Regiment, 1st
         (1891-1897)</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Elizabeth Selden Maclurg,
         1815-1853.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham family.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, John, 1763-1839.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Julia Wickham Porcher,
         1860-1933.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Littleton Waller Tazewell, 1821-
         1909.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, Thomas Ashby, 1857-1939.</subject>
      <subject>Wickham, William Fanning, 1860- 1900.</subject>
      <subject>Woodside (Henrico County, Va.)</subject>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <head>Contents List</head>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 1">John Wickham (1763-1839),
               Richmond and "East Tuckahoe," Henrico County,
               Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 1.1">Correspondence, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1798-1839</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">1-2</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 1.2">Law materials and
                  miscellany, 
                  <unitdate type="inclusive" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">
                  1766-1833</unitdate></unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">3</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Law practice, 1766-1833; Burr trial, 1806-1807;
                  "East Tuckahoe" materials; commonplace book;
                  miscellany; estate.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 2">Elizabeth Selden (McClurg)
               Wickham (1781-1853), Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">4</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1794-1850; wills of benefactors;
               miscellany.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 3">Maclurg Wickham (1814-1900),
               "East Tuckahoe," Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">5</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Diary, 1851-1882; correspondence, 1848-1876;
               accounts, 1860-1897; bonds; Wickham v. Graham materials;
               miscellany; estate.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 4">Littleton Waller Tazewell
               Wickham (1821-1909), New Orleans, La., and "Woodside,"
               Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.1.">Correspondence,
                  1836-1897.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">5
                  (cont.)-8</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.2">Financial materials,
                  1849-1891.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">8
                  (cont.)-10</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Account books, bank books, loose accounts, bonds
                  and notes.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.3">University of Virginia
                  records, 1837-1839.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">10
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.4">Law practice,
                  1848-1852.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">10
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="series 4.5">Plantation records,
                  "Woodside" and "Bunker Hill," 1858-1861.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">10
                  (cont.)-11</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 4.6">Miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">11
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Civil War materials, 1862-1865; bankruptcy
                  materials, 1859-1880; miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 5">Eliza Wyckoff (Nicholson)
               Wickham (d. 1850), New Orleans, La.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">12</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1846-1850; accounts, 1849-1850;
               estate of John Nicholson, 1842-1851; miscellany;
               estate.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="series 6">Elizabeth Peyre (Ashby)
               Laurens Wickham (1824-1859), Charleston, S.C. and
               Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">12 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters to, 1852-1859; letters of her mother,
               Elizabeth (Peyre) Sinkler Ashby, 1821-1831.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 7">John Wickham (1825-1902),
               "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1837-1902; accounts, 1876-1877,
               1893-1902; "East Tuckahoe" materials, 1840-1868;
               bankruptcy materials, 1878-1896; miscellany and
               estate.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 8">Remaining children of John
               Wickham (1763-1839).</unittitle>
        </did>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 9">Doctor Francis Peyre Porcher
               (1824-1895), Charleston, S.C.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 9.1">Correspondence and
                  lectures, 1864-1895.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">14</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 9.2">Porcher family
                  materials, 1864-1883, and miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 10">Thomas Ashby Wickham
               (1857-1939), Sprague, Washington, Richmond, and
               "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">13</container>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.1">Diaries, 1900,
                  1902-1925, 1929-1939</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">15
                  (cont.)-19</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.2">Correspondence,
                  1872-1938</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">Box 19
                  (cont.)-20</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.3">Financial materials,
                  1882-1939</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">21</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Accounts, 1882-1885, 1895-1922 (sporadic),
                  1930-1939; check stub books (2 v.), 1910-1912,
                  1912-1914.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.4">Plantation materials,
                  1894-1935</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>"Woodside" materials, 1894-1935; land records,
                  1900-1912</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 10.5">Legal and political
                  materials, 1843-1921, and miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">22
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Law practice, 1843-1921; Virginia Senate, 1908;
                  Democratic Congressional primary, 1910;
                  miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 11">William Fanning Wickham
               (1860-1900), Richmond, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 11.1">Correspondence,
                  1891-1897.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">23-26</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 11.2.">Financial
                  materials, 1893-1897.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">27</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Subseries 11.3">Military,
                  1893-1894, personal, and general
                  miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">27
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>First Cavalry Regiment material, 1893-1894; secret
                  societies, clubs, fraternal orders; general
                  miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 12">Julia Wickham (Porcher)
               Wickham (1860-1933), Charleston, S.C., and "Woodside,"
               Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.1">Julia Wickham Diary,
                  1896</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">28</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.2">Correspondence,
                  1870-1929.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">28
                  (cont.)-32</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.3">Account books, 1891,
                  1895-1896</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">33</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.4">Autograph albums,
                  1769-1887</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">33
                  (cont.)-34</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Autograph album I, 1769-1887; Aautograph album II,
                  1825-1884</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 12.5">Scrapbook and
                  miscellany.</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">35</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Scrapbook, 1904; newspaper clippings;
                  miscellany.</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 13">Littleton Tazewell Wickham
               (1858-1890), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">36</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1880-1889; accounts, 1886-1888;
               account books (2 vols.), 1878-1883, 1882-1883; check
               stub book, 1882-1884.</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 14">Elizabeth (Wickham)
               Fitzhugh (1854-1889), "Woodside," Henrico County,
               Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">36 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters to, 1866-1881; accounts, 1882-1884;
               miscellany</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 15">Virginia Leigh Porcher
               (1866-1940), Charleston, S.C., and "Woodside," Henrico
               County, Va.</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">36 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Correspondence, 1882-1939</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 16">Littleton Maclurg Wickham
               (1898-1973), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 16.1">Correspondence,
                  1909-1945</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">36
                  (cont.)-37</container>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle label="Series 16.2">Educational materials
                  and miscellany</unittitle>
            <container label="Box" type="Box">37
                  (cont.)</container>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Episcopal High School records; University of
                  Virginia; miscellany</p>
          </scopecontent>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle label="Series 17">Miscellaneous family and
               non-family materials</unittitle>
          <container label="Box" type="Box">37 (cont.)</container>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>Letters, commonplace book, accounts</p>
        </scopecontent>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
