<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/document.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/eadVIVA/eadVIVA.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xmlchar "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY logo SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/rmc.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY conditions SYSTEM "http://www.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/vhp/conditions.html" NDATA html>
<!ENTITY address SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/rmc_address.xml">
<!ENTITY contact SYSTEM "http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/rmc_contact.xml">
]><ead id="vias00003">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="unverified-partial-draft">
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="ViAsR">PUBLIC "-//Randolph-Macon College::McGraw-Page Library::Special Collections Dept.//TEXT (US::ViAsR::eadid::A Guide to the Paul Neff Garber Papers)//EN" "vias00003"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Papers of Paul Neff Garber 1899-1972
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">Garber, Paul Neff Papers
<num type="collectionnumber">Special Collections 4B, 5, 1-5
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Processed by Special Collections Staff
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
</publisher> &address;
<date type="publication">&copy; 2005 By Randolph-Macon College. All rights reserved.
</date>
<p id="usestatement">
<extref entityref="conditions">Conditions of Use
</extref>
</p>
<p id="filesize">[ca. ## Kilobytes]
</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from Index to Papers of Bishop Garber, created by Elmore Brown, 1974
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Paul Neff Garber Papers 1899-1972
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in the<lb/>Archives and Special Collections Department of<lb/>the McGraw-Page Library
</subtitle>
<author>Special Collections Staff
</author>
<p id="logostmt">
<extptr actuate="onload" show="embed" entityref="logo"/>
</p>
<publisher>Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
</publisher>
<date type="publication">2005
</date> &contact;
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>John Robertson IV
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository">Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
</repository>
<unittitle label="A Collection of the Professional and Personal Papers of Paul Neff Garber">The Garber Collection
<unitdate type="inclusive">1899-1972
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics">57 archival boxes along with 15 scrapbooks
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict>
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>Collection is open to research.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict>
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite>
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>The Paul Neff Garber Papers, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College, Ashland, Va.
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo>
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>The majority of the collection was a gift from Bishop Garber to the college in August of 1964, when he left Virginia, having been appointed Bishop of the North Carolina Conference. The remainder of the
collection was donated by Mrs. May.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist>
<head>Biographical/Historical Information
</head>
<p>Bishop Paul Neff Garber 1899-1972 Paul Neff Garber was born in New Market, VA, the son of Samuel and Ida Garber. He was raised there and began his religious life attending The Church of the Brethren. He was an
undergraduate at Bridgewater College and later received his Masters and Doctorate degrees from the University of Pennsylvania. He went on to teach history at the University of Pennsylvania, Brown University, and
Duke University. In 1926, he became the first professor of church history at the newly opened Duke School of Religion. His career at Duke continued for 18 years, becoming the school's registrar in 1928 and dean in
1941. He was elected Bishop in 1944. At this point, he was assigned to the Geneva Area Episcopacy, which consisted of nine European countries and part of North Africa. Bishop Garber returned to the U.S. when he
was assigned to the Richmond Area Conference in 1951, which consisted of Virginia and North Carolina. When the Raleigh Area Conference was created in 1964, Garber became its first bishop. He served there until his
retirement in 1968, at which time he went back to Switzerland, having been commissioned by the Methodist World Council to write a history of the Methodist Church. His retirement here was pleasant, doing research
among old friends and colleagues. He was nearly finished with this work when he suddenly passed away on December 18, 1972. History of Methodism in Europe was completed by Roy Short, a noted Methodist Historian,
and was published in 1980. Garber wrote several other books, mainly on the history of the United Methodist Church.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent>
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Garber Papers include a plethora of materials ranging from Garber's birth to his death. These materials include personal items such as diaries and correspondences, professional items from his work as bishop
in both Europe and the United States, lecture notes, research notes and typed scripts of sermons and lectures.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The collection is divided into nine topical divisions and each topical division is divided either topically or chronologically.
</p>
</arrangement>
<dsc type="combined">
<head>Contents List
</head>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 1-7
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>His personal life from birth to his election as bishop. This will also include some data on personal items throughout his lifetime; also addenda concerning his death.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 8-15
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Garber's Episcopacy in Europe. These documents shed light upon the overall situation in Europe and the work that the Methodist Church was doing there. Included are Garber's correspondences, reports, and
articles on his travels and work in the Geneva Episcopacy.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical by nation or region
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 8
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Austria Conference: includes correspondences with European officials, European churches, and colleagues. Along with the correspondences are essays written by Garber and others about Christianity's movements
in Austria.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Chronological
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 8
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Belgium Conference: includes information on Belgium Methodism from Garber and others, correspondences concerning relief projects for Belgium, personal correspondence, and correspondence with European
preachers.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 8
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Bulgaria Conference: Correspondences concerning the struggle of the Bulgarian Church, correspondences, and reports concerning the persecution of the Methodists in Bulgaria. The files document the arrests
and trials of Protestant Ministers.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 9
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Czechoslovakian Conference: Includes articles and reports by Garber and others concerning the post-war state of Czechoslovakia along with correspondences between Garber and Czechoslovakian churchmen. Much
of the material deals with Czechoslovakian reconstruction and other post-war aid.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 9
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The German Conference: Includes German Methodist Church records, correspondences, and articles concerning the state of the German Methodist Church.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 9
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Hungarian Conference: Includes Documentation of Garber's travels through Hungary, accounts of the work done in Hungary through the Church, appeals for aid, and correspondences.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 10
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Italian and Spanish Conferences: The vast majority of these documents deals with the Methodist Church in Italy. These documents include correspondences concerning financial aid for churches, reports on the
Methodist Church in Italy and Spain, and documents in Italian and Spanish.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 10
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Yugoslavian Conference: Correspondence from Yugoslavian leaders, reports and letters from the Yugoslavian Methodist Church and its leaders.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 10-11
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The North African Conference: Includes correspondences indicating an effort by Garber and others to bring more focus to North Africa. Other documents highlight the Methodist mission efforts in North Africa and
the state of Methodism there.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 11-12
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Polish Conference: Correspondences with leaders of the Polish Methodist Church along with reports on the church and the leaders.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 12
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Includes correspondences and reports from Methodist leaders in Scandinavia; A few letters concerning the church in Latvia.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 12
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Swiss Conference: Some correspondences from Garber's acquaintances, along with newspaper articles and his own reports concerning the Methodist Church in Switzerland.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 35
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Addresses given by Garber placing Methodism in the cultural contexts of various nations, including: North Africa, Belgium, Italy, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria, Hungary, Spain, and Eastern Orthodox countries. The
addresses highlight the historical and modern challenges that Methodism faces.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 12
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Newspaper articles and manuscripts. Garber's account of travel to Geneva by ship and his initial experiences in Europe. Other articles on North Africa, Poland, and Germany.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 12
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences, Official Documents, and Passports which show the physical conditions and purposes of his travels in North Africa and Europe.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 13
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>A wide array of Garber's correspondences with colleagues throughout Europe and in America.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 13
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Documents show the creation of the Crusade for Christ Scholarship and give examples of those who benefited from it.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 13
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>A Telegram asking about Garber's arrest and indictment, letters to Garber expressing fear that the church may have to go under ground. These spark advance specials to Garber's episcopacy. Included is a outline
of aid given to Poland, North Africa, and Belgium from the Charlotte District.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 13
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Documents concerning aid to Europe from the World Council of Churches. Several essays on the church in Europe, newspaper clippings about Garber's work, and correspondences.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 13-14
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Includes various correspondences noting the giving and receipt of aid for Europe along with newspaper clippings concerning European aid. Includes many documents on the Methodist Committee for Overseas Relief.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 14
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This includes correspondences, articles, and reports relevant to Garber's time in Geneva.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 14 and 15
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Mostly correspondence between Garber and his co-workers, includes a list of prominent Methodist workers in Europe and North Africa.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 15-16
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences, reports, and newspaper articles showing the direction Garber took the Virginia and North Carolina Methodist conferences during his time as Bishop.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 15
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences, reports, and articles concerning the work done during Garber's time as bishop of the Virginia conference. Much of the material documents Garber's campaign for Methodist educational
institutions, from which Virginia Wesleyan College sprung.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 16
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences and several newspaper articles featuring Garber and his work in the North Carolina Conference. Several reports document the state and future of the Church in North Carolina.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 16
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Garber's correspondences with individuals and institutions concerning his role as a bishop and friend. Includes correspondences with Randolph-Macon College, other bishops, and churches both inside and outside
of his conference.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>16-18
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Miscellaneous Documents From Garber's time as Bishop.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 16
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences and reports concerning church issues at the time (race, education, organization) and their roles at General Conference.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 17-18
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Material on the Jurisdictional system and the struggle to integrate the system through the elimination of the Central Jurisdiction. Also contains more general administrative material.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 19-21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Methodist Churches role in the social context of the time, along with Administrative concerns.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 19
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences, reports, and newspaper articles showing the bitter conflict over integration in the Virginia Conference of the Methodist Church.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 20
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Material concerning interdenominational cooperation in the church. National Council, World Council, Methodist World Council, American Council of Churhes, and Catholicism are all part of the file.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 20
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Various documents on Methodist Pastors and their relationships with their churches.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The Church's role in securing health care facilities for the residents of Tangier Island.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> A few documents on the Methodist Church's opposition to the escalation of the conflict in Vietnam along with other cold-war issues.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Material that show the Methodist Church's specific role in Social issues of the time.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p> Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c03 level="item">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Materials demonstrating the fear the Methodist Church held of communism as a "subversive influence in Methodism."
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Correspondences demonstrating the fear that communist ideas might be printed throughout the Methodist press.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c03>
<c03 level="item">
<did>
<physloc>Box 21
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Wide ranging materials including The Vatican, Red China, and Prayer in Public schools. Most material is correspondence pressuring Garber to act on the various issues.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc> Boxes 22 and 35
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Personal items.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 22
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Wide ranging personal correspondences.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc> Box 22
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Professional and Personal Correspondences along with official papers and reports.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 22 and 35
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Various Personal correspondences expressing Garber's views on the actions of his colleagues as well as outside correspondences and reports.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Box 22
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Appraisals, evaluations, and letters of appreciation from those in Garber's episcopacy, as well as his colleagues.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 22
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Letters expressing gratitude for all that the Garbers have done. Contains letters of kindness from all of the places Garber's work reached.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 22
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Evaluations, both good and bad, of Garber's work as a Bishop.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 22-26; 34-44
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>A wide range of personal and professional items: diaries, bank papers, reports, scrapbooks, etc.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 36-39
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Twenty One Volumes of Diaries dating from the years between 1945 and 1950. Also contains many very small date books Garber accumulated over the years.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Chronological
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc> Boxes 40-43
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The typed pages of the volumes of diaries from 1945-1950 with some editing.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Chronological
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 24
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Bulk Correspondence with Episcopal Colleagues: Flint, Leete, etc.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 22, 23, 24
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Materials on the Wesleyan Tradition.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 25
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Materials dealing with the prospect of a union of Methodists and Episcopalians, and more broadly a greater movement toward Church unity.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 25
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Correspondences, proposals, and pamphlets chronicle the steps toward the Unification of the E.U.B and Methodist churches.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 26, 34
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Receipts, Bank Statements, and Ledger all showing how money was spent to rebuild the Methodist Church in Post-War Europe.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 22, 23
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Various Cards, Gift Lists, and acknowledgements.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p> Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 22, 23
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Many personal letters and cards; including wedding congratulations, appointments, holidays, and elections.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 22, 23
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Various bank papers from America and Europe; a few of Garber's old checkbooks.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 25
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Information from many colleges in the South during Garber's time. Including Duke, Drew, Emory and Henry, and Randolph-Macon.
</p>
</scopecontent>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Archival Boxes
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Garber's Scrapbooks containing photos correspondences, and personal cards.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 27, 29-33, 47-56
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Historical and Cultural Studies by Garber, Classroom Notes, and Speeches and Sermons used throughout his professional life.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 45, 46
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Notes Garber used for preparing Sermons. Mostly verse explications and outlines.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 27
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Hand-written notes on the church, religions, and cultures.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Box 29
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Papers in Criminology, Religion, Race, and Sociology.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 47-56
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p> Notes used by Garber teaching Church History at Duke Divinity School.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
<c02 level="subseries">
<did>
<physloc>Boxes 29-33
</physloc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>Seventy-Five Typed Speeches by Garber: including sermons and addresses for many occasions.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement>
<p>Topical
</p>
</arrangement>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
