<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa1994">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa1994::A Guide to the Academic Affairs - Accreditation Materials, 1962-1985)//EN" "ViRa1994.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Academic Affairs - Accreditation Materials, <date>1962-1985</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">RU 3.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Chelsey Slemp, July, 2010 and  Gene Hyde, Summer and Fall, 2010.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>13 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Academic Affairs - Accreditation Materials, <date>1962-1985</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">RU 3.2
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Aaron Spelbring,  Chelsey Slemp, and Gene Hyde
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Academic Affairs - Accreditation Materials, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1962-1985
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RU 3.2
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Located in locked compact shelving, level 1.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>3.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Official documents, papers, and reports related to the accreditation in/of the following areas: National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (NCATE), Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS), Computing Services, Dance, Nursing, Music Therapy, Recreation and Leisure Service, and Social Work. For the full collection details see the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/academic-affairs-accreditation.html">finding aid.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Radford University Academic Affairs Office
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Academic Affairs, RU 3.2, Radford University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Academic Affairs - Accreditation Materials, Accession # RU 3.2, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Radford University Academic Affairs Office.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>More materials are expected. Some materials are unprocessed.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>Given by Radford University Academic Affairs Office.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Aaron Spelbring. Finding aid and additional processing by Chelsey Slemp, July, 2010. Additional finding aids and processing by Gene Hyde, Summer and Fall, 2010.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>The Mission of the Academic Affairs Division at Radford University is to create a challenging, supportive and engaging educational culture that is anchored in the liberal arts tradition and is ethically responsive to the needs of the 21st century global society. The Academic Affairs Office includes academic advising needs for the students of Radford University as well as the office of the Provost Staff and handles Community College and Transfer affairs. 
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Academic Affairs-- Accreditation Collection houses official documents, papers and reports related to the Accreditation of Radford University. These records include reports and other documents related to the National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (NCATE) from the Vice President of Academic Affairs (VPAA) for the years 1969- 1970. Further NCATE materials cover the years 1965-1981 such as correspondence, preliminary reports, visiting team reports and newspaper clippings. Papers from the Dean of Instruction/VPAA pertaining to NCATE from 1962 include surveys of Radford College Graduates, information on textbooks, faculty and guidance, as well as various academic matters for the 1920's-40's.</p>
<p> This collection also holds records pertaining to the Accreditation of Radford University from the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) from the VPAA office. These records include, but are not limited to, a Self Study of Student and Faculty Questionaires from 1971, an Inventory of Programs and Resources, a Fifth Year report and First Year Follow Up reports. These items have a date range of 1967- 1977.</p>
<p> Other departments seeking Accreditation are also present in these papers. Computing Services, Dance and Nursing have records contained in this collection such as a Self Education Study for the National League of Nursing. These documents have a date range of 1970's-1980's. The Music and Music Therapy programs have accreditation information contained herein that feature items from the National Association of Schools of Music from the 1980's. Finally these records feature items related to the Accreditation of the Recreation and Leisure Service and Social Work Departments from the 1980's. Various Self Study Reports are also present from the years 1962, 1971, 1992, and 1993. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 1. Academic Affairs - VPAA (Vice President of Academic Affairs). NCATE 1969-1970</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 2. Academic Affairs - Dean of Instruction/VPAA. Papers, NCATE - 1962. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p> Box 3. Academic Affairs - VPAA. NCATE - 1965-1981 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 4. Academic Affairs - VPAA. Southern Association of Colleges and Schools(SACS).</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 5. Academic Affairs - VPAA. Southern Association of Colleges and Schools Accreditation - 1971. </p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 6. Academic Affairs - VPAA. Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1972-1973 (Box 1 of 2)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 7. Academic Affairs - VPAA. Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1972-1973 (Box  2 of 2)  </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 8. Academic Affairs. Accreditations: Computing Services, Dance, and Nursing. 1970s and 1980s. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 9. Academic Affairs. Accreditations: Music - Music Therapy </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 10. Academic Affairs. Accreditations: Recreation and Leisure Service, and Social Work, 1980s. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 11. Academic Affairs. Accreditations: Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Self Study Reports</p></blockquote> 
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>
