<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa9624">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa9624::A Guide to the Hazel Grove Winesett Collection , 1931-1994)//EN" "ViRa9624.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hazel Grove Winesett Collection , <date>1931-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">SC 201.9
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Theibert and Gene Hyde, Spring 2013.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>19 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Hazel Grove Winesett Collection , <date>1931-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">SC 201.9
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Theibert
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Hazel Grove Winesett Collection , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1931-1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">SC 201.9
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">    Located in locked compact shelving, Level 1, Row 23
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>3.5 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains class notes from Hazel Winestt's high school and college years, her last will and testament, and scrapbooks.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Hazel Grove Winesett
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Hazel Grove Winesett Collection, Special Collections, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Hazel Grove Winesett Collection , Accession # SC 201.9, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No additional accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processing and finding aid by Sarah Theibert with finding aid assistance by Gene Hyde, Spring 2013.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Hazel Winesett, the child of Lawrence and Laura Frost Winesett, was born April 17, 1913 and raised in Carroll and Wythe counties. Her father owned a country grocery store in Austinville and lived above it until he built a house next door. Her father was a successful businessman, investing in property and municipal bonds, as well as a hotel in downtown Wytheville. house was built next door. Hazel attended Woodlawn schools and graduated from Woodlawn High School in 1932. She matriculated at Radford State Teacher's College and graduated in 1938 and took her first job teaching home economics at West Jefferson High School in Ashe County, NC. After a year, she moved to Okaloosa County, Florida, to take a teaching position at Fort Walton Beach High School. 
She moved back to Austinville after three years of teaching.She relocated to Pulaski when her father built a small ranch house and made this her home for the next 50 years. </p>
<p>Hazel remained active in Pulaski by becoming involved with local clubs and traveling. In the early 1950's Hazel became a dedicated member of a local variety show sponsored by the Lions Club and the Business and Professional Women's Club. She sang in the choir at First Christian Church, and was a leader and officer in the Christian Women's Fellowship. She was active in the Pulaski Business and Professional Women's Club. Hazel's modest living and careful spending in Pulaski disguised her financial worth. Many were surprised after her death she when she left large endowments not only Radford University, but also to Lynchburg College, her old school districts, and her church. In 2002 Hazel Grove Winesett endowed a gift of $820,000 to McConnell Library, the largest gift the Library has received to date. Each year the Library uses interest from the endowment to fund a number of projects that serve the Radford University community, including prizes for the Winesett Library Research Award and the Winesett Book Collecting Contest. Funds from the endowment's annual interest are also used to purchase resources, equipment, and furnishings. </p>
<p> -Sarah Theibert, Spring 2013, based on information in the Hazel Grove Winesett Collection.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>This collection contains class notes from Hazel Winestt's high school and college years, her last will and testament, and scrapbooks.</p></blockquote></p>
<p> In Box 3, the  Tan Scrapbook includes material from church and clubs she was involved with. She was a member of the First Christian Church, sang in the choir, and formed the Christian Women Fellowship. She also joined the Young Men's Christian Organization. She joined the Business and Professional Women in Pulaski, who nominated her to be Miss Progress.</p>
<p> The Brown scrapbook contains news about local disasters, marriages and betrothals, anniversaries, poems, recipes, and photos of Pulaski and Winesett's childhood. Winesett kept her graduation program, Radford graduation announcements, and birthday cards from her loved ones. The scrapbook provides Business and Professional Women club news about their events and the talks Winesett hosted about her travel to the Middle East. It also documents her travels to New York City, Cuba, Hawaii, and Germany with pictures and postcards.
</p>
<p> The Burgundy Scrapbook  contains cards (birthday, Christmas, get well, and postcards), local news and recipes, letters, travel logs and photos of travel destinations (Las Vegas, NV; Grand Canyon, AZ; Myrtle Beach, SC; and Europe), poems, Radford graduation invitations, and photos of friends. The scrapbook also holds a history of her teaching career, Radford State Teachers College registration and news of Radford employees, a photo of the Radford campus, handkerchiefs, and religious sayings or pictures.</p>
<p> In Box 4,  the Unbound Scrapbook contains local tragedies, memorials, recipes, ads, poems, cards (Christmas and thank you), marriage and anniversary announcements, and photos of Hazel Winesett and the Winesett store. Her religious life is documented through articles about church duties, Winesett's enrollment in church's school in 1969, photos and bible passages, her Holy Land itinerary, and her last will and testament to the First Christian Church Choir. The scrapbook includes her Europe tour schedule and her travels to Hawaii; St. Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands; Florida; Bermuda; Athens, Australia; and China. She collected stamps and placemats from her destinations. The scrapbook also holds more information about the Business and Professional Women club and a Delta Kappa Gamma bulletin.</p>
<p> The Bound Scrapbook  features cards (postcards, good wishes, and Thanksgiving), letters (from her travels, friends, and Christmas), poems, local articles about funerals, and wedding invitations. It also has photos of Winesett growing up, her birthday parties, friends, cruises she took, and the family gravesite. She saved articles about the Holy Land and religious passages and photos found by her and her loved ones. Winesett had received a choir award for her service to the First Christian Church. The scrapbook holds some of Radford University history with articles about the centennial, Jehan Sadat's visit, M'Ledge Moffet's activities, alumni events, and a contributor donor acknowledgement of 1981-82. There are also more photos and stamps of when she traveled to Florida and New Zealand.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p><emph render="bold">Box 1</emph></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 1: Last Will and Testament</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Folder 2: Biology </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 3: Conference </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 4: Education 11</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Folder 5: Education 12</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Folder 6: Education 26 and 27 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 7: English I</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 8: English II </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 9: English III </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 10: English 22 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><emph render="bold">Box 2</emph> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 1: Government 25 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 2: U.S. History 1609-1931</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 3: History 12 and 42, magazine articles </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 4: Science II </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 5: Vocational Guidance </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Folder 6: Miscellaneous</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p><emph render="bold">Box 3</emph> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Item 1: Tan Scrapbook</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Item 2: Brown Scrapbook</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Item 3: Burgundy Scrapbook</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p><emph render="bold">Box 4</emph></p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Item 1: Unbound Scrapbook</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Item 2: Bound Scrapbook</p></blockquote> 
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>
