<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa9635">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa9635::A Guide to the McConnell Library Records: Academic Affairs , 1930-1991)//EN" "ViRa9635.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the McConnell Library Records: Academic Affairs , <date>1930-1991</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">RU 3.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Gene Hyde, Caitlin Johns, and Amanda Altice, 2010-11.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>13 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the McConnell Library Records: Academic Affairs , <date>1930-1991</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">RU 3.3
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Gene Hyde, Caitlin Johns, Amanda Altice, Sarah Theibert, and Andy Bristol 
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">McConnell Library Records: Academic Affairs , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1930-1991
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RU 3.3
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Located in locked compact shelving, level 1.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>19.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">McConnell Library Records contains documents and papers related to the adminstration, collections, and other matters related to McConnell Library. More <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/mcconnell-library.html">information</extref> is available through the online finding aid.
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">McConnell Library
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], McConnell Library Records, Radford University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. McConnell Library Records: Academic Affairs , Accession # RU 3.3, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Office of Academic Affairs
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>Additional accruals are expected and ongoing.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>Given by Office of Academic Affairs
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processing and finding aid by Gene Hyde, Caitlin Johns, and Amanda Altice, 2010-11. Additional processing by Sarah Theibert, February 2013, and Andy Bristol Summer 2013.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>The library at Radford was first located in the Administration Building, once standing where Muse Hall is located. When the college opened in 1914, the library housed 1,500 volumes. The library gets its name from former President of the University, John Preston McConnell. Groundbreaking for McConnell Library began in 1931, with a budget of $43,000. The library was completed during the 1931-32 session. Students helped move the books into the new two-story library.
In the mid-1990s, a second addition towards Main Street brought the library to its present size, with five floors that hold over a half a million physical materials, various spaces for student study and collaboration, special events, a vibrant University Archives, and Information Literacy Centers to ensure Radford University students graduate with the research, information-seeking, and source evaluation skills they need to navigate their chosen fields.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>McConnell Library Records contains documents and papers related to the adminstration, collections, and other matters related to McConnell Library. These records feature library memorandums: created by individuals such as David Moore, Ed Huber, Thomas Mullis and Charles Owens. Also present are assorted library papers and Library Committee Minutes such as the Library Annual Report for 1985 and 1986 and the Materials Selection Policy from 1984-85. A bound register named John Preston McConnell library spanning the years 1932-1968 is also included. The next section of information pertains to Public Relation Files and Printed Columns spanning the years 1960-2004. Materials contained in that category include, but are not limited to, Radford Pamphlets from various years, Student Library Guidelines and Theatre Bills from 1976-2004, Photographs of Library workers from May of 1992 and Pierrett Catier-Huber's Scrapbook Clippings 1972-1988.</p>
<p> Box 2 of this collection includes lists of holdings. policies and plans from 1978-2000. Items that can be found are collection size information from the years 1978-1985, periodical holdings for 1989 and 1997, and a vistior register from 1999. Academic Affairs Annual Reports make up Box 3 covering the years 1931-1959. Annual Reports of Academic Affairs from 1970 to 2001 and memorandums from 1974-1983. Correspondence is also held in this collection with years 1925-1972 represented. 16 boxes of this collection are made up of Libary Operation Files covering various topics such as Telephones, Travel, Furniture, Personnel and Publicity. Three ledgers for material purchases dating to 1970-1971 and 1971-1972 are also present with one unknown year.</p>
<p> Box 23 consists of McConnell Library photographs circa 2000. Archvist files are retained in this collection and range from the 1970's to the 1990's  with information on donor relations, the Goldberg Collection and the strategic plan of the library are present. Along with various other miscellaneous items such as Library Annual Reports, surveys, policies, maps, workbooks and newspaper clippings. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 0.McConnell Library Memorandums, Assorted Library Papers, Library Committee Minutes</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 1. Public Relation Files and Printed Columns 1960 - 2004</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 2. Lists of Holdings, Policies and Plans - 1978 - 2000</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p> Box 3. Annual Reports - 1931 - 1959 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p> Box 4. Annual Reports 1970 - 2001 and Memorandums 1974 - 1983</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p> Box 5. Correspondence -1936 - 1972 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 6 -  Box 21. Operation Files </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 22.  Materials Accounts </p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 23. McConnell Library Photos, circa 2000</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 24. McConnell Library Slides </p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 25 - Box 27. Miscellaneous</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p> Box 28. Archivist Files 1970s - 1990s</p></blockquote> 
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>
