<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa0818">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa0818::A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, 1915-2009)//EN" "ViRa0818.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, <date>1915-2009</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">RU 4.1.6
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Theibert and  Gene Hyde.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->
<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>17 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, <date>1915-2009</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">RU 4.1.6
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Theibert
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1915-2009
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RU 4.1.6
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Locked in compact shelving, level 1, shelf 19E.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1915-2009</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents pertain to business of the Virginia Home Economics Association. In this collection, articles include documents associated with membership to the organization, documents that detail the founding of the association, and activities and budget information for the Virginia Home Economics Association. To see the full inventory of items see the Radford University Archive website at <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/moffett-VHEA.html">Radford Archives: VHEA</extref>  
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a"> Virginia Home Economics Association
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Home Economic Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, M'Ledge Moffet Collection, Radford University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Home Economics Papers and Virginia Home Economics Association Documents, Accession # RU 4.1.6, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No additional accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processing and finding aid by Sarah Theibert with finding aid assistance by Gene Hyde.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>Mrs. Mary E. Dillard and Miss Frances Sale, from the State Normal and Industrial School, started the Virginia Home Economics Association (VHEA) in 1909. Mrs. Dillard was named President and Miss Sale was Vice President of the home economics section created form the Virginia Teachers Association, later known as the Virginia Educational Association. The first section meeting of the VHEA was November 29, 1911 and there were 29 members.The organization had its first regional meeting in March 1915 at Radford and established a constitution and purpose. 
The VHEA's purpose was to promote interest in home economics in Southwest Virginia, to study current home economics pedagogy, and to identify VHEA with the state and national Home Economics Association and to cooperate with Women's Clubs. In 1930, the Virginia Home Economics Association separated from the Virginia Educational Association. The annual meeting topics are listed in the Resume document from 1931 to 1954 and emphasize what was important for the Home Economic Association to create a program for. Based on the Resume of the History of the Virginia Home Economics Association 1909 - 1954 found in the collection.</p>
<p> M'Ledge Moffett (1892-1969)was the youngest and only member of faculty for the department of Household Arts at what is now Radford University at its founding in 1913. In 1920, she was appointed the first Dean Of Women, a position she held until her retirement in 1962. M'Ledge was a founding member of the VHEA . She was president of that organization for the year 1915-1916 and again for the year 1925-1926. In 1925, M'Ledge Moffett changed the fiscal year and the constitution to conform to the National Association. To see Moffett's full biography consult the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/moffett-VHEA.html">biographical/historical note</extref> of the finding aid of this collection.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Box 1 contains memberships forms, correspondence, a paper on the affiliations of the Virginia Economic Association, list of duties to create the association, membership lists, newspaper clippings, programs, and newsletters from 1926 to 1955. </p>
<p>Box 2 contains a large Black and Red Book, which is Item 1, and Folders 1-15 were the documents found within the book. The box contains a note on this collection, the Resume of the History of the Virginia Home Economics Association 1909 - 1954, home economic section and regional meeting reports, documents on temporary committees, the association's constitution and preamble, membership applications and fees, correspondence, newsletter, and a report on the associations status and the achievements they had met.</p> 
<p>Also in Box 2 are a list of home economic teachers, lists on possible members of the association and graduates and students of the home economic program, Home Economic education report, a completion certificate from 2009, and a black notebook. The black notebook in Folder 8 contained treasurer reports from 1922 to 1925, a copy of the Resume, 1922 budget report, list of affiliated clubs, newsletters, meeting report, and membership lists of 1924 to 1925.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 1. Virginia Home Ec. Association, 1924-1955</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 2 The Black and Red Book</p></blockquote>
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>
