<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa1789">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa1789::A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents , 1938-1946)//EN" "ViRa1789.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents , <date>1938-1946</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">RU 4.1.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Amanda Altice, Molly Chamblin, and  Gene Hyde.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>13 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents , <date>1938-1946</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">RU 4.1.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Amanda Altice, Molly Chamblin, and  Gene Hyde.
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1938-1946
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RU 4.1.5
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Locked in compact shelving, level 1, shelf 20E.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>4.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents contains correspondence, government publications, local organizational publications, newspaper clippings, gas rationing documents, and official local records related to M'Ledge Moffett's membership and leadership in local organizations during World War II. The collection reflects the original order of Moffett's files, and whenever possible, notes the specific contents of folders and envelopes saved by Moffett.<extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/moffett-wwii.html">M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">M'Ledge Moffett
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], World War II Era Community and College Documents, M'Ledge Moffet Collection, Radford University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents , Accession # RU 4.1.5, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No additional accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Amanda Altice, Spring 2011, with additional materials added in Summer 2012 by Molly Chamblin. Finding aid by Amanda Altice, Molly Chamblin, and Gene Hyde.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>M'Ledge Moffett was born in 1892, the only child of William Ledgerwood Moffett and Mary Stoops Moffett. The name M'Ledge was formed from shortened versions of her parents names, Mary and Ledgerwood. She was hired at what is now Radford University in 1913 by President J.P McConnell as the youngest faculty member and the only member of the Household Arts Department. For the first several years after the college opened, Moffett taught all of the Household Arts courses (Elementary Sewing, Elementary Cooking and Household Management) which met five times a week. </p>
<p> In 1920, the Radford Normal School was reorganized and McConnell appointed Moffett as the new Dean of Women, a year before she received her Master of Arts degree. She was the first person to hold that post at any of the Virginia institutions of higher education.  During the World War II years (1941-45) she was active in community and college defense planning and preparation. She was a leader in the community Civilian Mobilization program and was active in planning and educating the community about Victory Gardens. This collection contains official publications, correspondence, memoranda, and documents related to Victory Gardens, the Red Cross, Civilian Mobilization, Child Care, Nutrition, and other topics related to the domestic front at Radford College and the city of Radford during World War II. She held the Dean's post until her retirement in 1962. She died in 1969.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The M'Ledge Moffett Collection: World War II Era Community and College Documents contains correspondence, government publications, local organizational publications, newspaper clippings, gas rationing documents, and official local records related to M'Ledge Moffett's membership and leadership in local organizations during World War II.The collection reflects the original order of Moffett's files, and whenever possible, notes the specific contents of folders and envelopes saved by Moffett. This is a 7 Box collection.
<lb/>
<blockquote><p><emph render="bold">Related Matierals</emph></p></blockquote>
<lb/>
<blockquote><p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/moffett-dean.html">M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Dean's Office Records</extref></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/moffett-scrapbooks.html">M'Ledge Moffett Collection: Newspaper Clippings Scrapbooks</extref></p></blockquote>
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>This is a seven box collection that reflects the original order of Moffett's files, and whenever possible, notes the specific contents of folders and envelopes saved by Moffett.
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>


