<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa1969">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa1969::A Guide to the Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection , 1941-1966)//EN" "ViRa1969.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection , <date>1941-1966</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">AC 012
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Brandon Edwards and Gene Hyde
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>7 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection , <date>1941-1966</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">AC 012
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Brandon Edwards, Wess Hess and Andy Bristol
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1941-1966
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">AC 012
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Locked in compact shelving, level 1.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>3.5 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">Construction on the Radford Army Ammunition Plant (a.k.a, Radford Arsenal) was started in September 1940, and the plant began producing powder in April 1941. Box 1 contains official publications, news clippings, and other materials related to the history of the Ammunition Plant from 1941 through the 1960s. Box 2 contains 71 issues of the plant's newsletter, The Radford Plant Weekly - "The Official Publication of the Radford Ordinance Works," dating from November 13, 1940 to May 14, 1942. The full collection finding aid can be found <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/RAAP.html">here.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Collector" encodinganalog="100$a">Radford Army Ammunition Plant
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection, Appalachian Collection, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection , Accession # AC 012, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>McConnell Library regional history vertical files and Mary Lalone.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No further accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>Materials were originally collected in regional history vertical files in McConnell Library from the 1940s-1970s, and moved to this collection in 2011. Additional materials were donated by Radford professor Mary LaLone in 2013.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by Brandon Edwards and Wes Hess, Winter 2012, and Andy Bristol, Summer 2013, Finding aid by Brandon Edwards and Gene Hyde.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>The Radford Army Ammunition Plant was founded in 1941 to support America's efforts in World War II as the Radford Ordance Works and New River Plant. In 1945, The works were renamed Radford Arsenal. The Arsenal covers more than 7,000 acres, on two seperate sites, in Southwest Virginia. In 1961, the plants name was changed to the Radford Ordance Plant and in 1963 changed again to the Radford Army Ammunition Plant. As of 2011, BAE Systems took over contract (ownership) of the Plant and is the sole supplier of TNT to the Department of Defense. The Radford Ammunition Plant is currently the primary supplier of solventless propellents and is the only North American manufacturer and supplier of nitrocellulose. 
</p>
</bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Radford Army Ammunition Plant Collection contain booklets such as Highlight of Radford Arsenal from 1955  and Information on Radford Arsenal. Newspaper articles are split into two categories in this collection. The first category are newspapers that show happenings at the Arsenal and major milestones in the early days of operation between 1941 and 1978, whereas the second category are editions of the Roanoke Times created between 1998 and 2000. Other related material found in this collection are a performance review, two safety calenders and a program commemorating 25 years of operation in 1966. 71 issues of the Radford Plant Weekly, the Official Publication of the Radford Ordinance Works, reside in this collection and cover a two year span from 1940-1942. The third grouping of material are deemed to be of research value in the form of books written on the Plant such as The Power Plant by Jeff Schneider and the Millstone Manufacture in Virginia edited by Charles D. Hockensmith. The fourth and final grouping of this collection hold magazines  and research catalogs such as Life Magazine from March of 1941 and catalog searches - Farm Security Administration, Radford, Virginia.   
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 1: Booklets, newspaper articles, and other materials related to the Radford Army Ammunition Plant (RAAP)</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 2: The Radford Plant Weekly - "The Official Publication of the Radford Ordinance Works." A total of 71 copies, from Vol. 1, No. 1 (November 13, 1940) to Vol. 3, No. 45 (May 14, 1942) </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 3: Books, Newspaper Articles, and research materials regarding RAAP</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 4: Magazines, Research catalogs, and other papers regarding RAAP </p></blockquote>
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>




