<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa0818">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa0818::A Guide to the Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection , 1985-1988)//EN" "ViRa0818.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection , <date>1985-1988</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">RU 3.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Sarah Theibert and Gene Hyde.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>13 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection , <date>1985-1988</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">RU 3.5
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Sarah Theibert 
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1985-1988
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">RU 3.5
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Located in locked compact shelving, level 1, Shelf 19D.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Extent" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Jehan el Sadat Collection contains correspondence, class lecture notes, newspaper articles, and other materials related to her tenure as a Visiting Professor at Radford University in 1985-86. For the full collection details, <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/visiting-scholars-sadat.html">click here.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Jehan el Sadat
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection, Radford University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Visiting Scholars - Jehan el Sadat Collection , Accession # RU 3.5, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Jehan el Sadat
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No additional accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>Donated by Jehan el Sadat.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processing and finding aid by Sarah Theibert with finding aid assistance by Gene Hyde.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Jehan el Sadat was born in Cairo, Egypt, and met her future husband, Anwar Sadat when she was 15. Anwar Sadat, 16 years her senior, was a political activist who had recently been released from prison at the time. Jehan Sadat's parents initially objected to her marriage to Anwar but eventually allowed the couple to wed. Mrs. Sadat began her own activism in her village of Talla, promoting women's independence through a program that trained train girls and women of all ages to make handicrafts. 
She expanded her work to include boys and men, training them in skills such as carpentry, electric works, and carpet weaving. Mrs. Sadat also helped establish family services such as a kindergarten, family guidance, and a clinic.</p>
<p> Anwar Sadat became President of Egypt in 1970, and is best known for signing the Camp David Accords in 1978 that led to the first peace treaty between Israel and Egypt in 1979. Islamic fundamentalists felt Sadat had betrayed the Egyptian people and assassinated him during a parade in 1981. His death left Jehan el Sadat alone with their four children: Lobna, Noha, Jehan, and Gamal. Mrs. Sadat decided to continue her activism after her husband's death by promoting women's rights and peace in Egypt.</p>
<p> Mrs. Sadat advocated for more rights and security for Egyptian women, and pushed a new Civil Rights law through the Egyptian parliament in 1976. She also fought to help Egyptian orphans by initiating the S.O.S. Children's Villages. Mrs. Sadat founded and/or headed the following organizations: The Egyptian Red Crescent Society, The Egyptian Blood Bank Society, The Egyptian Society for The Scientific Association for Egyptian Women, The Egyptian Society for Biomedical Engineering, The Higher Committee for Children, The Egyptian Society for the Welfare of University and Higher Institute Students, and The Egyptian Society for the Preservation of Antiquities.</p>
<p> Mrs. Sadat received a BA in Arabic Literature from Cairo University's Faculty of Arts. She earned a Master's degree from Cairo University in 1980, writing a thesis on The influence of Shelley on Arabic Literature. In 1986 she earned her Ph.D. from Cairo University, writing her dissertation on The Influence of English Criticism on Romantic Critics in Egypt Between the Two Wars. She came to the US and held positions at Radford University and University of South Carolina. At Radford she was an Honorary Visiting Professor in 1985-86, teaching the courses Women in the Third World and Egypt: Its History and Culture.</p>
<p> Mrs. Sadat won various international awards for her efforts to help women and promote the message of peace. In 1975, she was named Volunteer of the Year from the Rehabilitation International U.S.A., named a Paul Harris Fellow from The Rotary Foundation of Rotary International, as well as being the recipient of the Commissioner's Award from the Rehabilitation Services Administration in December. She has been awarded a number of honors, including Cross of Merit from the Italian Red Cross, a Distinguished Public Service award from the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, the Margret Sanger Award from the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, the Women's International Center Living Legacy Award, the Crittenton Center International Humanitarian Award, the Eleanor Roosevelt United Nations Award, the Community of Christ International Peace Award, and the Pearl S. Buck Award.</p>
<p> Mrs. Sadat published her autobiography, A Woman of Egypt, in 1987. In 2009 she published My Hope For Peace, a call for peace in the Middle East. Both volumes are available at McConnell Library.</p>
<p>Sarah Theibert, based on an autobiographical sketch by Jehan el Sadat.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The Jehan el Sadat Collection contains correspondence, class lecture notes, newspaper articles, and other materials related to her tenure as a Visiting Professor at Radford University in 1985-86. This collection houses items such as Mrs. Sadat's lectures from various classes throughout the Fall and Spring of 1985 and 1986. Sadat's correspondence is also featured here ranging from 12/9/85 to 2/12/88. Also there are various items such as Mrs. Sadat's stationary and brief biography, newspaper articles involving Mrs. Sadat and information on the Conference of Status of Women. 
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 1. Miscellaneous Items</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 2. Sadat's Lectures</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 3. Sadat Correspondence</p></blockquote>
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>

