<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa5027">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa5027::A Guide to the Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection , 1872-2008)//EN" "ViRa5027.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection , <date>1872-2008</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">AC 022
</num>
</subtitle>
<author> David Atkins, Spring 2013.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>7 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection , <date>1872-2008</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">AC 022
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item> David Atkins, Spring 2013.
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1872-2008
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">AC 022
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">Located in locked compact shelving, Level 1, Row 31, Shelves G-H.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>27.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection contains materials from the personal collections of Riner, VA resident Virginia Deal Lawrence. Materials in the collection include scrapbooks filled with newspaper and magazine clippings, letters, receipts, photographs, and personal notes. The bulk of the material is from the 1940's to the 1990's, but the collection contains material from the 1880's to 2008. All the material was gathered and preserved by Miss Lawrence and her mother, Fannie Deal Smith Lawrence, through their love of scrapbook collecting. The collection primarily contains articles about the Roanoke and New River Valleys, with specific attention given to the Riner community. Newspaper articles about local history, people, places, and events are found throughout the collection. Several newspapers and magazines are identified in the collection, these include: The Roanoke Times and World News, The Lexington Gazette, Southern Agriculturalist, The Radford News Journal, The Montgomery News Messenger, The Richmond Times-Dispatch, Esso Farm News, Virginia Intermont College Alumnae Magazine, Radford College Alumnae News, Mountainside Magazine, The New River Current, and The Christiansburg Herald. See the full details in the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/lawrence-scrapbook.html">finding aid.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">Virginia Deal Lawrence and Fannie Deal Smith Lawrence
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. All materials in the collection are available for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection, Appalachian Collection, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection , Accession # AC 022, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Donated by the estate of Virginia Deal Lawrence.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No further accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>Donated by the estate of Virginia Deal Lawrence. Materials in boxes 36 and 37 are on loan from the Auburn United Methodist Church and are not a permanent part of the collection.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Processed by David Atkins, Spring 2013.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>Miss Virginia Deal Lawrence was born on February 28, 1909, in Riner, Virginia. She was the daughter of James Lewis Lawrence and Fannie Deal Smith Lawrence. She had one sibling, Mary Eileen Houston. Her father operated the C. Lawrence store in Riner, a general merchandise store. After finishing secondary school Miss Lawrence attended Virginia Intermont College, in Bristol, Virginia. She would then transfer to Radford College to pursue a teaching career. She received her degree from Radford College on June 9, 1930. During her time at Radford she became the charter member of Sigma Sigma Sigma, the first sorority established at the school. After graduating Miss Lawrence taught one year fifth grade at New port Elementary, located just outside of Blacksburg, VA. From there she went on to teach at Riner Elementary for the next 42 years, teaching second grade. For 35 years she was the treasurer of the Alpha Lambda Chapter of Delta Kappa Gamma Society, the International Honorary Society for Teachers in Giles and Montgomery Counties. In 1970 she appeared in the September edition of Outstanding Educators of America and received Montgomery County's Outstanding Teacher Award. Throughout her life Miss Lawrence was a loyal member of the Auburn United Methodist Church in Riner. She taught the Kindergarten Sunday school class, served as the church historian, the Communion Steward, and the Treasurer of the Lord's Acre. She was also a member of the Auburn United Methodist Women and was the group's treasurer for many years. She published a booklet about the 100-year history of her church entitled, Auburn United Methodist Church, Riner, VA, 1885-1895. During her lifetime she remained active in many of the above listed groups. She considered herself a local historian and was an avid scrapbook collector. Virginia Deal Lawrence passed away on July 9, 2012, at the age of 103.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>The first boxes of the Virginia Deal Lawrence Scrapbook Collection, boxes 1-18, contain scrapbooks 1-73. Scrapbook 1 has receipts and invoices from the C. Lawrence and Sons general store, which was located in Riner, VA. Scrapbooks 2-73 consist of newspaper and magazine clippings about the Roanoke and New River valleys, with an emphasis on Montgomery County. The material in this part of the collection dates from 1872 to 2009. Boxes 19-26 contain scrapbooks 74-104. These scrapbooks include newspaper and magazine clippings concerning national and world news, although some local stories are represented as well. The material in this part of the collection dates from 1926 to 2006. Box 27 houses scrapbooks 105-109. These scrapbooks are filled with poems, anecdotes, stories, recipes, and other miscellaneous items. The material dates from 1910 to 1980. Boxes 28-30 are composed of miscellaneous items related to Montgomery County and the surrounding area. The items include tourist guides, church pamphlets, history journals, etc. Box 31 contains a family photo album and miscellaneous letters and documents. Box 32 holds two Tri Sigma scrapbooks and the C. Lawrence Store Ledger. Box 33 and 34 has several scrapbooks and other materials about Auburn Schools, Riner, and the Montgomery County area. Box 35 is Map draw D5 located in room 534 in the McConnell Library and contains the Lawrence family Genealogical chart. Box 36 and 37 house ten scrapbooks from the Auburn United Methodist Church. these books are on loan from Kathy Smith, the executor of the Virginia Lawrence estate. The archive will temporarily hold these books until digital copies of the books are made and added to the collection. The scrapbooks will be housed permanently in the Auburn United Methodist Church Library upon construction.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p><blockquote><p>Box 1: Scrapbooks 1-4</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 2: Scrapbooks 5-9 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 3: Scrapbooks 10-12 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 4: Scrapbooks 13-17</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 5: Scrapbooks 18-22 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 6: Scrapbooks 23-26 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 7: Scrapbooks 27-31</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 8: Scrapbooks 32-36 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 9: Scrapbooks 37-41</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 10: Scrapbooks 42-45 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 11: scrapbooks 46-49 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 12: Scrapbooks 50-53</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 13: Scrapbooks 54-57</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 14: Scrapbooks 58-60 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 15: Scrapbooks 61-63</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 16: Scrapbooks 64-66 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 17: Scrapbooks 67-69 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 18: Scrapbooks 70-73 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 19: Scrapbooks 74-78 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 20: Scrapbooks 79-82 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 21: Scrapbooks 83-86 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 22: Scrapbooks 87-90 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 23: Scrapbooks 91-94 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 24: Scrapbooks 95-97 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 25: Scrapbooks 98-100 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 26: Scrapbooks 101-104 </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 27: Scrapbooks 105-109</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 28: Journal of the New River Historical Society- Issues, Newsletters, and Tour Guides.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 29: Assorted items related to Montgomery County History</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 30: Miscellaneous items, including accession papers, pamphlets, news clippings photocopies, lesson plans, and many other various items. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 31: Photograph album and miscellaneous papers. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 32: Three Sigma Sigma Sigma scrapbooks, a C. Lawrence store ledger, and an issue of The Triangle. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 33: Scrapbooks and other miscellaneous materials related to Auburn Schools.</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 34: Several miscellaneous items related to Auburn United Methodist Church, Riner history, Llyod Sumner, and Montgomery County.</p></blockquote> 
<blockquote><p>Box 35: Assorted books, yearbooks, and other items relating to area schools. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 36: Miscellaneous photographs, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and more. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Box 37: Lawrence family genealogical charts dating back to 1720</p></blockquote>
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>

