<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa1994">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa1994::A Guide to the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Records , 1899-1965)//EN" "ViRa1994.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Records , <date>1899-1965</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">AC 001
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Caitlin Johns,  Dave Atkins and Dave Horn
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>7 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Records , <date>1899-1965</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">AC 001
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Dave Atkins, Dave Horn and Caitlin Johns
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Records , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1899-1965
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">AC 001
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>53.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">The Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Collection contains deeds, plats, maps, ledger books, correspondence, and annual reports of the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company relating to its activities in Bedford County, Botetourt County, Radford City, Bristol City, Wythe County, eastern Tennessee, and Roanoke County. The materials deal primarily with events from 1900 through the middle 1960's, even though there are some materials referring to the 1800's. For full collection <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/VICC-records.html">click here.</extref> Parts of this collection have been <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://monk.radford.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/VICC">digitized.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. The collection is open for research. No interlibrary loan.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], Virginia Iron, Coal, and Coke Company Records, Appalachian Collection, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Records , Accession # AC 001, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>Additonal accruals are not expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Finding Aid by Caitlin Johns, updated from original finding aid created in 1986. Reprocessed with finding aid additions by Dave Atkins and Dave Horn during 2012.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical/Historical Information 
</head>
<p>The Virginia Iron, Coal, and Coke Company was created in 1899 and operated coal mines, iron mines, furnaces, and related businesses in Southwest Virginia throughout the early 20th Century.VICC went through several owners after the Second World War, and in 1984 then-owner ANR Coal Company of Roanoke, Virginia, donated the iron and land records to Radford University. A <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://monk.radford.edu/cdm/singleitem/collection/VICC/id/5">history</extref> of the VICC by retired Radford History Professor Harold W. Mann is available on the RU Digital Collections website.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>Thye Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Collection contains deeds, plats, maps, ledger books, correspondence, and annual reports of the Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company relating to its activities in Bedford County, Botetourt County, Radford City, Bristol City, Wythe County, eastern Tennessee, and Roanoke County. The materials deal primarily with events from 1900 through the middle 1960's, even though there are some materials referring to the 1800's.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>NOTE: The VICC Collection is being reprocessed to better preserve, protect, and describe the materials in the collection. As of January 2013, the collection has been reprocessed through box 15.As the materials were reprocessed and placed in new folders, they have been expanded and relaxed, and consequently now take up more room. Some overlap has occurred, and this is now labeled old and new boxes when the box numbers from the new and old box labelling overlap.</p>
<p>The VICC Collection was originally housed in expanding legal manilla folders that were labeled Folder 1, Folder 2, etc. These folders typically contain documents relating to a specific topic, location, set of legal documents, etc. The materials in these folders have been removed and placed in archival file folders. The labels reflect the original manilla folders (Folder 1) while the individual items in them are in the original order and are in files. Consequently Box 1, Folder 1, File 3 contains the third item originally found in the first folder in the collection,which is now housed in Box 1.
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>


