<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--Change Vircuh to match your repository-->
<?xml-model href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/eadVIVA/ead-ext.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" title="extended EAD relaxng schema" ?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="ViRa5207">
<eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft">
<!-- Change below to match your institution's ead information -->
<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-ViRa">PUBLIC "-//Radford University::University Archives::McConnell Library//TEXT (US::ViRa::ViRa5207::A Guide to the William C. Blizzard Photography Collection , 1967-1994)//EN" "ViRa5207.xml"
</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William C. Blizzard Photography Collection , <date>1967-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle id="sort">
<num type="collectionnumber">AC 015
</num>
</subtitle>
<author>Ashley Tussey, Gene Hyde and Wes Hess, 2012.
</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>

<publisher>Radford University, University Archives, McConnell Library<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher> <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/add_con/ru_address.xi.xml" /><!-- Change to match your institution -->

<date type="publication">&#169;  By Radford University. All rights reserved. <!-- Add your institution's name and copyright statement -->
</date>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Machine-readable finding aid derived from MARC record, created by Kaitlin Scott, <date>7 July 2017</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Description is in
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<titleproper>A Guide to the William C. Blizzard Photography Collection , <date>1967-1994</date>
</titleproper>
<subtitle>A Collection in <lb/>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
<num type="Collection number">AC 015
</num>
</subtitle>
<p id="logostmt">
<!-- Change for your institutions logo -->
<extptr xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/logos/ru.jpg"/>
</p>
<publisher>University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</publisher>
<date type="publication">
</date> 
<list type="deflist">
<defitem>
<label>Processed by:
</label>
<item>Ashley Tussey, Gene Hyde and Wes Hess, 2012.
</item>
</defitem>
</list>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="collection">
<runner placement="footer">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</runner>
<did>
<head>Descriptive Summary
</head>
<repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="852$a">University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University<!-- Add your institution's name -->
</repository>
<unittitle label="Title" encodinganalog="245$a">William C. Blizzard Photography Collection , 
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Date" encodinganalog="245$f">1967-1994
</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<unitid label="Collection number" encodinganalog="099$a">AC 015
</unitid>
<physloc label="Location">The collection is stored in a file cabinet in Room 534, McConnell Library.
</physloc>
<physdesc label="Physical Characteristics" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>6.0 Linear feet</extent>.
</physdesc>
<langmaterial label="Language">
<language langcode="eng">English
</language>
</langmaterial>
<abstract label="Abstract">This collection contains approximately 10,000 photographic slides taken by William C. Blizzard. Blizzard was a photojournalist who documented many aspects of life in West Virginia and surrounding region. His subjects range from news photography depicting coal miners and the coal industry, to scenic nature photos, to regional arts and crafts. The full collection inventory can be seen <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://mozart.radford.edu/archives/findingaids/blizzard-photography.html">here.</extref> Portions of this collection have been <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://monk.radford.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/USSRphotos">digitized.</extref>
</abstract>
<origination label="Creator" encodinganalog="100$a">William C. Blizzard
</origination>
</did>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Administrative Information
</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506$a">
<head>Access Restrictions
</head>
<p>An appointment for research is required. All materials in the collection are available for research. No interlibrary loan. A related collection is the <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://monk.radford.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/blizzard">William C. and Bill Blizzard When Miners March Collection</extref> which has been digitized.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540$a">
<head>Use Restrictions
</head>
<p>There are no restrictions.
</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite encodinganalog="524$a">
<head>Preferred Citation
</head>
<p>[Identification of item], William C. Blizzard Photography Collection, Appalachian Collection, McConnell Library, Radford University, Radford, VA. William C. Blizzard Photography Collection , Accession # AC 015, University Archives, McConnell Library, Radford University <!-- Add your institution's citation information -->
</p>
</prefercite>
<acqinfo encodinganalog="541$a">
<head>Acquisition Information
</head>
<p>Purchased from Wess Harris in 2011.
</p>
</acqinfo>
<accruals>
<head>Accruals
</head>
<p>No additional accruals are expected.
</p>
</accruals>
<custodhist>
<head>Custodial History
</head>
<p>The collection was purchased from Wess Harris in 2011 at the same time as the William C. and Bill Blizzard When Miners March Coal and Labor Collection.
</p>
</custodhist>
<processinfo>
<head>Processing Information
</head>
<p>Files were initially organized by Ashley Tussey, with additional processing by Gene Hyde and Wes Hess, 2012.
</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
<bioghist encodinganalog="545$a">
<head>Biographical Information
</head>
<p>William C. Blizzard (December 22, 1916- December 29, 2008) was a journalist, historian, and photographer. Over the course of his career he worked as a photographer and features writer for the Charleston Gazette, as well as publications such as The Nation and Labor's Daily. He also published articles and photographs in many magazines and newspapers. The narrative that would become When Miners March was originally published as a series of articles in Labor's Daily in the 1950s. Wess Harris worked with William C. Blizzard to publish When Miners March as a book in 2004.Blizzard was educated at West Virginia University and the Columbia School of Journalism. He served in the United States Army Air Corps during World War II where he was a photographer. He had a long career as a journalist and photographer, working for many papers and as a free lance writer.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a">
<head>Scope and Content
</head>
<p>This collection contains approximately 10,000 photographic slides taken by William C. Blizzard. Blizzard was a photojournalist who documented many aspects of life in West Virginia and surrounding region. His subjects range from news photography depicting coal miners and the coal industry, to scenic nature photos, to regional arts and crafts. 
Blizzard used the following categories to arrange his slides: Animals, Auto, B.A.S.S., Birds, Children, Cities, Disaster Wrecks, Education, England, Fairfest, Family, Farm, Florida, Holidays, Industrial Business, Ireland, Kentucky, Medical, Miscellaneous, Mudrun, Ohio, Outdoor Recreation, Old File, People (odd folk), Plants, Plants and Animals - Zoobot, 
Poverty, Russia, Russia Winter, Scenic, Science, Senior Citizens, Social, Society SCA, Sports, Teenagers, Tennessee, U.S. History, Virginia, Workmen, West Virginia Arts and Crafts, West Virginia Historic, WV Homes, West Virginia, West Virginia Parks-Forests, West Virginia Schools, and Young People.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
<head>Arrangement
</head>
<p>The William C. Blizzard Photography Collection consists of 512 hanging sleeves containing up to 20 slides each. This is the collection of a working freelance photographer who organized and labeled his slides by category, and the file numbers reflect Billizard's original file labels. Individual slides are typically labeled with Blizzard's name and contact information.
</p>
</arrangement>
</archdesc>
</ead>

